<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03535922</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RES0034066</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03535922</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Routinely Measured Patient-reported Outcomes in Hemodialysis Care</brief_title>
  <acronym>EMPATHY</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Routinely Measured PATtient Reported Outcomes in HemodialYsis Care (EMPATHY) Trial: A Cluster Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alberta Health Services</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alberta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patient-reported outcome measures (PROMs) are reports coming directly from patients about how
      they function or feel in relation to a health condition and its therapy, without
      interpretation of the patient's responses by a clinician or anyone else. PROMs capture
      patients' experiences of symptoms and impact of disease on functioning and can support
      clinicians to monitor disease progression and facilitate patient-centered care.

      The EMPATHY trial will determine the effects of routinely measuring PROMs on the experiences
      of patients undergoing hemodialysis in Alberta and Ontario. In this study, two kinds of PROMs
      will be used: a disease-specific PROM and a generic PROM. The disease-specific PROM focuses
      on health symptoms related to chronic kidney disease and the generic PROM focuses on general
      health.

      In the trial, patients will be invited to complete the PROMs, and results of the measures
      will be linked to treatment aids for clinicians, providing specific information on how
      symptoms can best be managed. These care pathways will also be available to patients not
      receiving PROMs. The main outcome of this study will be patient-clinician communication,
      which will be assessed using a questionnaire called the &quot;Communication Assessment Tool&quot;. In
      addition to assessing the effect of using these questionnaires on patient-provider
      communication, this study will allow us to explore whether their use affects patient
      management and symptoms, use of healthcare services, and the overall cost of implementing
      these questionnaires in clinical practice.

      Each dialysis unit (including all patients) will be randomized to one of four study groups:
      1) Patients will complete the disease-specific PROM; 2) Patients will complete the generic
      PROM; 3) Patients will complete both the disease-specific and generic PROM; 4) Patients will
      receive usual care.

      Clinicians (in dialysis units randomized to PROMs, groups 1-3) will receive the results of
      the questionnaires completed by the patients. This is intended to trigger the clinician to
      ask the patient about certain symptoms if any exist. All clinicians in all study groups will
      have access to the clinical &quot;treatment aids&quot;, which are tools that help identify and manage
      certain symptoms that patients might have. For example, people with severe itching will be
      cared for based on a step-wise treatment algorithm. Patients will also receive a report of
      their questionnaire(s) results, with an explanation of what it means.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The overall aim of this study is to explore the usefulness of integrating PROMs assessment,
      implemented through an e-health application, in the clinical management of hemodialysis
      patients. The specific objectives are as follows:

      Primary objective: to determine the effects of routine measurement and reporting to care
      providers of PROMs specifically a chronic kidney disease-specific PROM and/or a generic PROM,
      on patient-reported experience, particularly patient-clinician communication, for patients
      with CKD undergoing hemodialysis.

      Secondary objectives:

        -  To determine if there is a difference in patient-reported experience and management
           induced by a condition-specific versus a generic PROM;

        -  To determine the effects of routinely measuring and reporting the PROMs on the clinical
           management of symptoms;

        -  To determine the effects of routinely measuring and reporting the PROMs on health
           outcomes and healthcare utilization;

        -  To determine the cost-effectiveness of routinely measuring the PROMs for patients with
           CKD undergoing hemodialysis;

        -  To explore the perspectives and experience of patients and clinicians with routine
           measurement and reporting of PROMs in clinical practice.

      Study Design:

      The investigators propose the use of a cluster RCT design to avoid any potential
      contamination between the study groups. This study is a pragmatic RCT that will involve the
      random allocation of clusters (i.e., dialysis units) into four groups:

        -  Group 1: Completes disease-specific PROM

        -  Group 2: Completes generic PROM

        -  Group 3: Completes both PROMs

        -  Group 4: Usual care; does not complete any of the PROMs (control)

      Treatment aids for symptoms assessed by the PROMs will be made available for all clinicians
      in all study groups. Details about intervention and treatment aids are provided below.

      Hypotheses:

      The investigators hypothesize that the routine measurement and reporting of PROMs will lead
      to improvement in communication between CKD patients and clinicians in dialysis units in
      Canada compared to usual care. The investigators also hypothesized that this will lead to
      better symptom and disease management, and improvement in mental health and quality of life.
      Furthermore, the investigators anticipate that this intervention will be cost-effective and
      will be acceptable and feasible in the dialysis units' environment.

      Setting and Population:

      All available dialysis units from Alberta (Northern and Southern Alberta Renal Programs -
      NARP/SARP) and selected units in Ontario (Ontario Renal Network - ORN) will be invited to
      participate in this study. The unit of randomization will be the dialysis units within
      NARP/SARP/ORN, not dialysis programs or individual patients. Randomization will be done
      within each renal program (NARP/SARP/ORN) to ensure that units from all programs are
      represented in all study groups.

      Dialysis Unit Eligibility Criteria:

      Inclusion criteria:

        -  Hemodialysis unit providing chronic in-center hemodialysis;

        -  Hemodialysis care providers willing to review an individual patient's routinely
           collected PROMs as part of patient assessment.

      Exclusion criteria:

        -  Hemodialysis unit unable or unwilling to administer the PROMs to in-centre hemodialysis
           patients as part of clinical workflow to all possible patients;

        -  Hemodialysis unit already implementing PROMs measurements, and unable to withhold it
           during the trial period.

      Inclusion/exclusion criteria for individual patients: All patients undergoing hemodialysis
      who are 18 years or older at the start of the study, and are willing and able to complete the
      PROMs as part of the trial will be eligible to participate in this study.

      Interventions:

      Since blinding is not feasible in this trial, it will be conducted as an open trial.
      Consequently, research staff, clinicians, and all patients will be aware of group allocation;
      cluster randomization is intended to minimize potential biases associated with an open trial
      design. Eligible dialysis units will be randomly allocated to one of 4 study groups:

        1. The disease-specific PROM group: The disease-specific PROM will be administered every 2
           months to all patients able to complete the instrument for a period of 12 months. The
           PROMs results will be reported back to the patient, and patients will be prompted to
           follow-up with their care providers if they provide a positive response to any of the
           symptoms assessed by the PROM. The PROMs results will also be printed in a report form
           and added to the patient's medical chart for review by clinicians. The report will
           display each patient's most recent results in comparison with their previous results,
           and in comparison with the general dialysis population. The PROMs report will be
           accompanied by treatment aids for all symptoms. The proposed disease-specific PROM is
           the Edmonton Symptom Assessment Scale modified for renal patients (mESASr).

        2. The generic PROM group: The generic PROM will be administered every 2 months to all
           patients able to complete the instrument for a period of 12 months. The PROMs results
           will be reported back to the patient, and patients will be prompted to follow-up with
           their care providers if they provide a positive response to any of the symptoms assessed
           by the PROM. The PROMs results will also be printed in a report form and added to the
           patient's medical chart for review by clinicians. The report will display each patient's
           most recent results in comparison with their previous results, and in comparison with
           the general dialysis population. The PROMs report will be accompanied by treatment aids
           for all symptoms. The proposed generic PROM is the EQ-5D-5L.

        3. The disease-specific and generic PROM group: The disease-specific and generic PROMs will
           be administered every 2 months to all patients able to complete the instrument for a
           period of 12 months. The PROMs results will be reported back to the patient, and
           patients will be prompted to follow-up with their care providers if they provide a
           positive response to any of the symptoms assessed by the PROM. The PROMs results will
           also be printed in a report form and added to the patient's medical chart for review by
           clinicians. The report will display each patient's most recent results in comparison
           with their previous results, and in comparison with the general dialysis population. The
           PROMs report will be accompanied by treatment aids for all symptoms.

        4. The control or 'usual care' group: Patient in this group will follow usual care as
           provided in the dialysis unit and will not complete any PROM; however, all the treatment
           aids will be made available for clinicians in this study group during the trial period.

      Treatment aids:

      Treatment aids are clinical protocols developed by expert clinicians for the management of
      certain symptoms and disorders. Treatment aids specific to symptoms assessed by the
      disease-specific PROM (e.g., itchiness, restless leg syndrome) and the generic PROM (e.g.,
      pain, anxiety/depression) will be developed and made available for all clinicians at all
      study sites. These treatment aids are intended to support clinicians in the management of
      symptoms identified by these PROMs. Treatment aids have been developed in the NARP, and are
      currently being piloted in an ORN PROMs pilot.

      For each symptom/problem area, a patient information sheet will also be developed and
      provided to patients, to better understand the reason why the symptom/problem may have
      developed, treatment options that might be considered, as well as self-care activities they
      can undertake to alleviate the symptom or problem.

      Study Period:

      The study will be implemented over 36 months. The first 6 months will involve the
      administrative approvals, completing ethics requirements, training of clinicians on the use
      of PROMs; the following 18 months will involve trial implementation including assessments and
      interventions. The last 12 months will involve compiling the data from all study sites, data
      analysis and reporting of results.

      REAIM Evaluation:

      The investigators will use the REAIM (Reach, Effectiveness, Adoption, Implementation,
      Maintenance) framework to comprehensively evaluate the different components of the
      implementation of the EMPATHY trial. This will be done by using a combination of quantitative
      and qualitative research methods. The main results (E-effectiveness) will be based on the
      traditional quantitative analysis of the cluster randomized trial for the primary outcome and
      selected secondary outcomes. Elements of Reach, Adoption, and Implementation will be assessed
      through qualitative methods, including reviewing documents, charts, meeting minutes, and
      semi-structured individual interviews with samples of patients and clinicians who will be
      involved in the trial at different sites. These interviews will be conducted at baseline,
      6-months and at the completion of the trial.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Communication Assessment Tool (CAT) scores over 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline, 6 months, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The CAT assesses patient perceptions of clinicians' interpersonal and communication skills. 'Communication' refers to the interactions between members of the healthcare team (i.e., nurses, nephrologists) and the patient.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in EQ-5D-5L scores over 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline, 6 months, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The EQ-5D-5L is a standardized generic measurement of health-related quality of life. This measure provides a simple descriptive profile and single index value for health status. The intended purpose of this measure for this survey is for clinical and economic evaluation of healthcare.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Disease-specific PROM (ESAS or IPOS) scores over 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline, 6 months, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of symptom burden (choice of instrument depends on regional dialysis program). The purpose of this outcome measure is to enable tracking of the effectiveness of targeted symptom management strategies at the patient and program levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom treatments initiated</measure>
    <time_frame>12 month study period</time_frame>
    <description>Chart review for action taken as result of PROMs measurement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in GAD-2 scores over 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline, 6 months, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the Generalized Anxiety Disorder 2 item questionnaire (GAD-2). The GAD-2 is a screening tool for anxiety.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PHQ-2 scores over 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline, 6 months, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured by the Patient Health Questionnaire- 2 items (PHQ-2). The PHQ-2 is a screening tool for depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in PACIC-11 scores over 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline, 6 months, and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The 'Patient Assessment of Chronic Illness Care-11 item questionnaire' measures a number of aspects of care, including patient activation; delivery system design and decision support; goal setting and tailoring; problem-solving and contextual counselling; follow-up and coordination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare utilization over 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>One year prior and one year after the study intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Survey and clinical data will be linked to administrative data on healthcare utilization of participants</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-effectiveness/cost-utility analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>12 month study period</time_frame>
    <description>A cost-effectiveness analysis of the different study groups, compared to the usual care arm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4160</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Kidney Disease Requiring Chronic Dialysis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>The disease-specific PROM group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hemodialysis (HD) units randomized to this PROMs assessment group will administer a disease-specific PROM every 2 months to all patients able to complete the instrument independently or with assistance for a period of 12 months. Patients will receive a copy of their PROM results in report form and patients will be prompted to follow-up with their care providers if they provide a positive response to any of the symptoms assessed by the PROM. The disease-specific PROM report will also be added to the patient's medical chart for review by clinicians. The report will display each patient's most recent results in comparison with their previous results, and in comparison with the general dialysis population. The PROM report will be accompanied by treatment aids for all symptoms. The proposed disease-specific PROM is the Edmonton Symptom Assessment Scale modified for renal patients (mESASr)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>The generic PROM group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HD units randomized to this PROMs assessment group will administer a generic PROM every 2 months to all patients able to complete the instrument independently or with assistance for a period of 12 months. Patients will receive a copy of their PROM results in report form and patients will be prompted to follow-up with their care providers if they provide a positive response to any of the symptoms assessed by the PROM. The generic PROM report will also be added to the patient's medical chart for review by clinicians. The report will display each patient's most recent results in comparison with their previous results, and in comparison with the general dialysis population. The PROM report will be accompanied by treatment aids for all symptoms. The proposed generic PROM is the EQ-5D-5L.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Disease-specific and generic PROMs group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HD units randomized to this PROMs assessment group will administer a disease-specific and generic PROM every 2 months to all patients able to complete the instrument for a period of 12 months. Patients will receive a copy of both their PROMs results in report form and patients will be prompted to follow-up with their care providers if they provide a positive response to any of the symptoms assessed by the two PROMs. The disease-specific and generic PROMs reports will also be added to the patient's medical chart for review by clinicians. The report will display each patient's most recent results in comparison with their previous results, and in comparison with the general dialysis population. The PROMs reports will be accompanied by treatment aids for all symptoms.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>The control or 'usual care' group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>HD units randomized to this group will follow usual care and patients will not have any PROMs assessment; however, all the treatment aids will be made available for clinicians in this study group during the 12 months trial period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PROMs Assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Routine measurement and reporting of disease-specific PROMs, generic PROMs, or combination of both</description>
    <arm_group_label>The disease-specific PROM group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>The generic PROM group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Disease-specific and generic PROMs group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Undergoing hemodialysis within an eligible in-centre dialysis unit in Alberta or
             Ontario

          -  18 years or older at the start of the study

          -  Willing and able to complete the PROMs as part of the trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Johnson, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hilary Short, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>780-492-5233</phone>
    <email>heshort@ualberta.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boyce MB, Browne JP. Does providing feedback on patient-reported outcomes to healthcare professionals result in better outcomes for patients? A systematic review. Qual Life Res. 2013 Nov;22(9):2265-78. doi: 10.1007/s11136-013-0390-0. Epub 2013 Mar 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23504544</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marshall S, Haywood K, Fitzpatrick R. Impact of patient-reported outcome measures on routine practice: a structured review. J Eval Clin Pract. 2006 Oct;12(5):559-68. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16987118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Valderas JM, Kotzeva A, Espallargues M, Guyatt G, Ferrans CE, Halyard MY, Revicki DA, Symonds T, Parada A, Alonso J. The impact of measuring patient-reported outcomes in clinical practice: a systematic review of the literature. Qual Life Res. 2008 Mar;17(2):179-93. doi: 10.1007/s11136-007-9295-0. Epub 2008 Jan 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18175207</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boyce MB, Browne JP, Greenhalgh J. The experiences of professionals with using information from patient-reported outcome measures to improve the quality of healthcare: a systematic review of qualitative research. BMJ Qual Saf. 2014 Jun;23(6):508-18. doi: 10.1136/bmjqs-2013-002524. Epub 2014 Feb 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24505110</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Antunes B, Harding R, Higginson IJ; EUROIMPACT. Implementing patient-reported outcome measures in palliative care clinical practice: a systematic review of facilitators and barriers. Palliat Med. 2014 Feb;28(2):158-75. doi: 10.1177/0269216313491619. Epub 2013 Jun 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23801463</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Patrick DL, Deyo RA. Generic and disease-specific measures in assessing health status and quality of life. Med Care. 1989 Mar;27(3 Suppl):S217-32. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2646490</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laupacis A, Wong C, Churchill D. The use of generic and specific quality-of-life measures in hemodialysis patients treated with erythropoietin. The Canadian Erythropoietin Study Group. Control Clin Trials. 1991 Aug;12(4 Suppl):168S-179S.</citation>
    <PMID>1663853</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perrone RD, Coons SJ, Cavanaugh K, Finkelstein F, Meyer KB. Patient-reported outcomes in clinical trials of CKD-related therapies: report of a symposium sponsored by the national kidney foundation and the U.S. Food and Drug Administration. Am J Kidney Dis. 2013 Dec;62(6):1046-57. doi: 10.1053/j.ajkd.2013.07.004. Epub 2013 Aug 26.</citation>
    <PMID>23988757</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davison SN, Jhangri GS, Johnson JA. Longitudinal validation of a modified Edmonton symptom assessment system (ESAS) in haemodialysis patients. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2006 Nov;21(11):3189-95. Epub 2006 Sep 6.</citation>
    <PMID>16957010</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fayers PM. Evaluating the effectiveness of using PROs in clinical practice: a role for cluster-randomised trials. Qual Life Res. 2008 Dec;17(10):1315-21. doi: 10.1007/s11136-008-9391-9. Epub 2008 Sep 27.</citation>
    <PMID>18821031</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 13, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alberta</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jeffrey Johnson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD, Professor, Chair, and Associate Dean</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hemodialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Kidney Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

