<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03530254</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IGX1-P&amp;E-DV-17-08</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03530254</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Study PGT-A vs PGT-A+ERA</brief_title>
  <acronym>PGT-A&amp;ERA</acronym>
  <official_title>International Multi-center, Randomized and Controlled Clinical Study, to Evaluate the Clinical Benefit of the ERA Test in Infertile Patients Undergoing Assisted Reproduction Treatment and Medical Indication of PGT-A.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Igenomix</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Igenomix</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients who have shown previous implantation failures, despite transferring good quality and
      chromosomally normal embryos (diagnosed by PGT-A), could have a displaced Window of
      Implantation (WOI) and consequently, alterations in their endometrial receptivity. The
      correction of this displacement can improve the results of the Assisted Reproduction
      Treatments (ART).

      The ERA test (Endometrial Receptivity Analysis) evaluates the transcriptomic endometrial
      profile to determine if the patient's uterus is receptive when the embryo is transferred
      during an In Vitro Fertilization (IVF) process, and identifies the personalized WOI of the
      patient. This process is called Personalized Embryo Transfer (pET).

      The Preimplantation Genetic Test of Aneuploidies or PGT-A (Preimplantation Genetic Testing
      for Aneuploidy), is currently carried out using Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) and serves
      to identify chromosomally normal embryos prior to their transfer in an IVF treatment.
      Aneuploidies are rarely compatible with life or can cause congenital diseases. So, the
      identification of chromosomally normal embryos, improves the success of reproduction in cases
      in which infertility is caused by such aneuploidies.

      Therefore, the aim of this study is to determine, in a randomized and prospective way, the
      clinical benefit of adding the ERA test to the embryonic aneuploidies test for patients with
      a PGT-A indication.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The lack of receptivity of the uterus and chromosomal abnormalities in the embryo are the two
      main causes of implantation failure. Patients with implantation failure, should consider the
      PGT-A test to identify and select euploid embryos. In addition, it should be evaluated the
      endometrium receptivity state at the time of Embryo Transfer (ET).

      The PGT-A is an important genetic test that was developed to select embryos during IVF
      treatment and avoid embryonic chromosomal abnormalities that lead to miscarriage or life born
      with chromosomal diseases. Embryonic aneuploidy is linked to maternal age. The most common
      consequences are implantation failure, miscarriage or life born with multiple congenital
      anomalies. The transfer of euploid embryos (chromosomally normal) diagnosed by PGT-A has
      shown an increase in implantation rates.

      Morphology is the most traditional and routine method of embryo selection being used.
      However, it is difficult to distinguish normal and abnormal embryos by observing their
      morphology under a microscope. Therefore, morphological analysis should not be the only
      technique used to decide which embryo should be transferred. Application of NGS in PGT-A
      cycles demonstrates that this methodology is reliable, allowing identification and transfer
      of euploid embryos resulting in ongoing pregnancies. However, despite the transfer of
      morphologically normal euploid embryos, it is not always possible to acquire optimal results
      in Assisted Reproductive Techniques (ART).

      On the other hand, the endometrial gene expression profile allows the diagnosis of the
      endometrium receptivity status. This is carried out by a molecular tool developed and
      patented by Igenomix (PCT/ES2009/00386). The ERA test is a customized expression microarray
      that identifies the transcriptomic expression profile signature of the personalized Window of
      Implantation (pWOI). A bioinformatic predictor determines the moment of maximum receptivity,
      indicating the best time to perform a pET.

      If the result of the ERA test is &quot;Receptive&quot;, the WOI and the moment of taking the biopsy
      overlap. Nevertheless, if the result is &quot;Pre-Receptive&quot;, the optimal implantation window is
      expected to be after the moment in which the biopsy is taken, and if the diagnosis is
      &quot;Post-Receptive&quot;, the optimal window of implantation is prior to the biopsy. In a subsequent
      cycle, a pET will be performed according to the ERA test results.

      Recently, it has been conducted a pilot study in patients with previous implantation failures
      with PGT-A and euploid embryo transfer (ET). The results of the ERA test have shown that a
      high percentage of these patients have been diagnosed as Non-receptive (90%). This percentage
      is higher than the expected in the normal population (12-20%) or in the Repeated Implantation
      Failure (RIF) patients without PGT-A (25-30%). Once the pET was performed according to the
      results of the ERA test, the gestation rate was 55.55%.

      So, the objective of the present study is to validate these preliminary results in a
      prospective, multi-center, randomized and controlled study to demonstrate the value of the
      endometrial factor and the improvement of the results obtained in patients with PGT-A
      indication. If confirmed, it would be recommended the ERA test for all ART patients, not only
      for those with PGT-A, demonstrating the significance in searching for the pWOI to improve
      reproductive outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Live birth rate</measure>
    <time_frame>40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of babies born per embryo transfer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Implantation rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of implanted embryos per total number of embryos transferred</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical pregnancy</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of clinical pregnancies per total number of pregnancies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Biochemical pregnancy</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of biochemical pregnancies per total number of pregnancies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical miscarriages</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of clinical miscarriages per total number of pregnancies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ectopic pregnancies</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of ectopic pregnancies per total number of pregnancies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Obstetric complications</measure>
    <time_frame>40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Type and number of obstetric complications during pregnancy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">740</enrollment>
  <condition>Infertility of Uterine Origin</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PGT-A without ERA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with PGT-A indication and ET in a Hormone Replacement Therapy (HRT cycle) according to the usual clinical practice (day 5 of progesterone supplementation: P+5/120h).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PGT-A and test ERA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with PGT-A indication and pET in HRT cycle following the ERA test indication (when the WOI is confirmed as &quot;Receptive&quot;).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PGT-A</intervention_name>
    <description>PGT-A will be carried out following the usual clinical practice. Trophectoderm biopsy samples from blastocysts are analyzed by NGS to screen for numerical chromosomal abnormalities.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PGT-A without ERA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PGT-A and test ERA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ERA Test</intervention_name>
    <description>The ERA test requires an endometrial biopsy and will determine if the endometrium is receptive or not by analysing the expression levels of 236 genes involved in endometrial receptivity, to assess the optimal time to place an embryo into the uterus and promote a successful implantation and pregnancy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PGT-A and test ERA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Majority of age patients whose written informed consent approved by the Ethics
             Committee (EC) has been obtained, after having been duly informed of the nature of the
             study and voluntarily accepted to participate after being fully aware of the potential
             risks, benefits and any discomfort involved.

          -  Patients who already have frozen euploid blastocysts (day 5/6 development) analysed by
             PGT-A.

          -  Patients with embryos obtained from their own oocytes fertilized by Intracytoplasmic
             Sperm Injection (ICSI).

          -  Patients with an expected embryo transfer of one or two embryos (Single ET or Double
             ET) in a HRT cycle.

          -  Body Mass Index: 18,5-30 Kg/m2.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of pathologies or malformations that affect the uterine cavity such as
             polyps, intramural myomas ≥ 4cm or submucosal, septum or hydrosalpinx during the
             patient's participation in the study. Patients suffering these pathologies before or
             after their inclusion in the study are allowed to participate if the pathology is
             corrected before performing any study procedure.

          -  Any illness or medical condition that is unstable or which, according to medical
             criteria, may put at risk the patient's safety and her compliance in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Majority of age infertile patients who already have frozen euploids blastocysts (day 5/6 development) obtained from their own oocytes, fertilized by ICSI and analysed by PGT-A, with an expected embryo transfer of one or two embryos in a Hormone Replacement Therapy cycle (HRT cycle).</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carlos Simón, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Igenomix</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carlos Gomez, BSc MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+34963905310</phone>
    <phone_ext>18543</phone_ext>
    <email>carlos.gomez@igenomix.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Diana Valbuena, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+34963905310</phone>
    <phone_ext>18544</phone_ext>
    <email>diana.valbuena@igenomix.es</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>RMA CT</name>
      <address>
        <city>Norwalk</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06851</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christina Portela-Dias, BSN RN</last_name>
      <phone>203-750-7400</phone>
      <email>Cdias@rmact.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mark Leondires, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(+1) 203-956-2265</phone>
      <email>mleondires@rmact.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Leondires, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IVF Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Margate</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33063</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan Sciandra, BSN RN</last_name>
      <phone>954-247-6258</phone>
      <email>Susan.Sciandra@integramed.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Marcelo Barrionuevo, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(+1) 954-247-6200</phone>
      <email>barrionue@aol.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marcelo Barrionuevo, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fertility Centers of New England</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reading</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01867</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joseph Hill, MD</last_name>
      <phone>781-942-7000</phone>
      <email>hillj@FertilityCenter.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Peter Wieckowski, pHD</last_name>
      <phone>781-942-7000</phone>
      <email>wieckowskip@FertilityCenter.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pregna Medicina Reproductiva</name>
      <address>
        <city>Caba</city>
        <zip>C1425</zip>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Laura Kopcow, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+54 1148341600</phone>
      <email>lkopcow@pregna.com.ar</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mariana Degani, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+54 1148341600</phone>
      <email>mdegani@pregna.com.ar</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Geare Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Recife</city>
        <state>Pernambuco</state>
        <zip>52011-040</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Madalena Caldas, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(+81) 30341147</phone>
      <email>ppmatheus@uol.com.br</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Madalena Caldas, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Olive Fertility Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <zip>BC V5Z 3X7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gary Nakhuda, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(+1) 604-559-9950</phone>
      <email>GNakhuda@olivefertility.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gary Nakhuda, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shady Grove Fertility Chile</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vitacura</city>
        <zip>6800</zip>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Freudenthal, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(+56) 232638900</phone>
      <email>michael.freudenthal@sgfertility.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Freudenthal, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Georgian- American Center for Reproductive Medicine ReproART</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tbilisi</city>
        <zip>0179</zip>
        <country>Georgia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mother And Child Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Defence Colony</city>
        <state>Delhi</state>
        <zip>110024</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nalini Mahajan, MBBS, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(+91) 1141030715</phone>
      <email>drnalinimahajan@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nalini Mahajan, MBBS, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>OASIS centre for reproductive medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Banjara Hills</city>
        <state>Hyderabad</state>
        <zip>500034</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Durga Rao, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(+91) 9490624638</phone>
      <email>durga@oasisindia.in</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Durga Rao, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Humanitas Fertility Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rozzano</city>
        <state>Milano</state>
        <zip>20089</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Levi Setti, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(+39) 282244500</phone>
      <email>paolo.levi_setti@humanitas.it</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Levi Setti, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NASCERE</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mexico City</city>
        <state>Cdmx</state>
        <zip>05120</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lucia Daniela Garcia Montes, BS PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(+52) 15554521311</phone>
      <email>lucia.daniela.garcia.montes@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Gerardo Barroso, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(+52) 15554521311</phone>
      <email>barrosog@me.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gerardo Barroso, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Reproducción Bilbao</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bilbao</city>
        <state>Bizkaia</state>
        <zip>48014</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gorka Barrenetxea, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(+34) 946111213</phone>
      <email>gbarrenetxea@reproduccionbilbao.es</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gorka Barrenetxea, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Milenium Centro Médico y de Bienestar de Alcobendas - Sanitas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Alcobendas</city>
        <state>Madrid</state>
        <zip>28108</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ana Gaitero, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(+34) 917165820</phone>
      <email>agaitero@sanitas.es</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ana Gaitero, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center of Reproductive Medicine and Sciences - Taipei Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <zip>110</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chii Ruey Tzeng, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(+886) 227372181</phone>
      <phone_ext>8540</phone_ext>
      <email>tzengcr@tmu.edu.tw</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chii Ruey Tzeng, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Taiwan IVF Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zhubei</city>
        <zip>302</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nelson Chen, BSc PhD</last_name>
      <email>icryoegg@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jack Y.J. Huang, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(+886) 36589090</phone>
      <email>jyjhuang@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jack Y.J. Huang, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Acıbadem Maslak</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sarıyer</city>
        <state>İstanbul</state>
        <zip>34457</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Bülent Tiraş, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+90 5324282898</phone>
      <email>bulent.tiras@acibadem.com.tr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bahceci Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <zip>07720</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Necati Findikli, BS MSc PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(+90) 2123103100</phone>
      <email>nfindikli@bahceci.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mustafa Bahceci, MD PhD</last_name>
      <phone>(+90) 2123103166</phone>
      <email>mbahceci@bahceci.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mustafa Bahceci, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Argentina</country>
    <country>Brazil</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Chile</country>
    <country>Georgia</country>
    <country>India</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Mexico</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
    <country>Turkey</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 8, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Endometrial receptivity</keyword>
  <keyword>Preimplantation Genetic Diagnosis (PGD)</keyword>
  <keyword>Preimplantation Genetic Testing for Aneuploidy (PGT-A)</keyword>
  <keyword>Embryo Transfer (ET)</keyword>
  <keyword>Endometrial Receptivity Analysis (ERA)</keyword>
  <keyword>Endometrial Diagnosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Live Newborn Rate (LBR)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infertility, Female</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

