<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03533556</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB2017-767</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03533556</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of L-theanine and Caffeine on Attention and Attention-related Brain Activity of Children With Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of L-theanine and Caffeine on Attention and Attention-related Brain Activity of Male Children and Adolescents With Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder: a proof-of- Concept fMRI Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Texas Tech University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Texas Tech University Health Sciences Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Texas Tech University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      L-theanine and caffeine are two natural constituents of tea. Both of these compounds are
      among the U.S. Food and Drug Administration's list of Generally Recognized as Safe (GRAS)
      substances. Results of several clinical trials the PI and his team has conducted are
      consistent with results of many others to indicate that oral intake of each of 2.5 mg/kg body
      weight of L-theanine and 2.0 mg/kg body weight of caffeine is associated with improved
      attention in adults. Furthermore, there is evidence to suggest that, when taken in
      combination, L-theanine and caffeine seem to have additive effects in improving attention in
      adults. However, the specific actions of these substances have not been examined in children
      and adolescents with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), who are characterized
      by impaired attention, hyperkinesia and impulsivity.

      Therefore, the investigators plan to study the functional activity of brains (both at rest
      and when performing standard tasks designed to measure attention) in children diagnosed with
      ADHD using functional magnetic resonance imaging, after they consume either 2.5 mg/kg of
      L-theanine, 2.0 mg/kg of caffeine and their combination as compared to a placebo (water).
      Based on our previous findings, the investigators expect to observe improvements (speed of
      responding and accuracy) in standard tests of attention with intake of L-theanine, caffeine
      and their combination as compared to the placebo. The investigators also expect to observe
      decreased functional activity in brain regions that typically show increased activity during
      mind wandering with intake of L-theanine, caffeine and their combination.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 14, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>2.5 mg/kg body weight of L-theanine, 2.0 mg/kg body weight of caffeine and their combination each dissolved in 100 ml of water (solvent) or the solvent alone (i.e. placebo) will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of fMRI blood oxygen level dependent (BOLD) responses of the brain in response to Stop Signals of an SSRT recorded following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>45 minutes after the administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of functional magnetic resonance imaging reactivity of the whole brain, anterior and posterior nodes of the default mode network, bilateral dorsolateral prefrontal cortex and anterior cingulate cortex in response to stop signals of a stop signal reaction time task following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of fMRI blood oxygen level dependent (BOLD) responses of the brain in a Go-NoGo CPT recorded following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes after the administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of functional magnetic resonance imaging reactivity of the whole brain, anterior and posterior nodes of the default mode network, bilateral dorsolateral prefrontal cortex and anterior cingulate cortex in Go-NoGo continuous performance task following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of resting state fMRI functional connectivity recorded following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>75 minutes after the administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of functional magnetic resonance imaging resting state functional connectivity of the anterior and posterior nodes of the default mode network, bilateral dorsolateral prefrontal cortex and anterior cingulate cortex and the remaining regions of the brain following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of cerebral blood flow measured following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>80 minutes following administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of cerebral blood flow estimated using arterial spin labeled echo following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of delay discounting following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>140 minutes following administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of delay discounting as measured using a delay discounting task presented on a laptop computer following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of stop signal delay following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>45 minutes following administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of stop signal delay of a stop signal reaction time task performed in the magnetic resonance imaging scanner following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of reaction times of correct Go responses in a Go-NoGo CPT following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes following administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of reaction times of correct Go responses in a Go-NoGo continuous performance task performed in the magnetic resonance imaging scanner following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of commission errors in the Go-NoGo CPT following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes following administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of commission errors in the Go-NoGo continuous performance task performed in the magnetic resonance imaging scanner following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of performance in Flanker Inhibitory Control and Attention Test following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>100 minutes following administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of performance in Flanker Inhibitory Control and Attention Test of the NIH Toolbox Cognition Battery following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of performance in Dimensional Change Card Sort Test following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>100 minutes following administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of performance in Dimensional Change Card Sort Test of the NIH Toolbox Cognition Battery following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of performance in Pattern Comparison Processing Speed Test following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>100 minutes following administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of performance in Pattern Comparison Processing Speed Test of the NIH Toolbox Cognition Battery following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of post- vs. pre-treatment change of STAI-CH State Scale following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately before and 90 minutes after administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of State Trait Anxiety Inventory for Children (State Questionnaire) immediately prior to and following administration of each treatment will be compared with the corresponding post- vs. pre-treatment change of placebo.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of commission errors in SSRT following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>45 minutes following administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of commission errors of the stop signal reaction time task performed in the magnetic resonance imaging scanner following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of omission errors in SSRT following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>45 minutes following administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of omission errors of the stop signal reaction time task performed in the magnetic resonance imaging scanner following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of omission errors in Go-NoGo CPT following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes following administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of omission errors of the Go-NoGo continuous performance task performed in the magnetic resonance imaging scanner following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of performance in Picture Sequence Memory Test following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>100 minutes following administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of performance in Picture Sequence Memory Test of the NIH Toolbox Cognition Battery following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Differences of performance in List Sorting Working Memory Test following administration of each treatment and the placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>100 minutes following administration of each treatment / placebo</time_frame>
    <description>L-theanine, caffeine, L-theanine-caffeine combination and placebo will be administered on 4 separate days (at least 5 days apart) in a random counter-balanced order. Differences of performance in List Sorting Working Memory Test of the NIH Toolbox Cognition Battery following administration of each treatment will be compared with the placebo.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>L-theanine</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral administration of 2.5 mg/kg body weight of L-theanine dissolved in 100 ml of water</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Caffeine</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral administration of 2.0 mg/kg body weight of caffeine dissolved in 100 ml of water</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>L-theanine-Caffeine Combination</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral administration of a combination of 2.5 mg/kg body weight of L-theanine and 2.0 mg/kg body weight of caffeine dissolved in 100 ml of water</description>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral administration of 100 ml of water</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Children and adolescents (age 8-17 years)

          2. Male

          3. Diagnosed with ADHD by a clinician (e.g. a psychiatrist or a pediatrician)

          4. Responded to stimulants (i.e. the symptoms of ADHD have improved in the past with a
             prescription of stimulants)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Gross impairment of vision or hearing that would prevent the participants from
             performing neuropsychological tasks

          2. Inability to read and follow written instructions

          3. WISC-V IQ score of &amp;lt; 80

          4. Physical, neurological or concurrent psychiatric impairments (except ADHD) that could
             affect cognitive and motor functions

          5. Regular intake of medication that could alter visual, auditory, cognitive or motor
             functions (except stimulants)

          6. History of head injury that resulted in loss of consciousness / history of brain
             surgery

          7. Intake of drugs containing caffeine, other phosphodiesterase inhibitors or adenosine
             receptor blockers within the past 3 months

          8. Intake of medications which are known to have pharmacological interactions with
             caffeine within the past 3 months

          9. Current / past diagnosis of tics or other forms of dyskinesia

         10. History of development of headache, drowsiness, anxiety, insomnia or nausea following
             intake of caffeine or caffeine containing beverages

         11. Current / past history of smoking and / or alcohol or drug abuse

         12. Absolute contraindications to undergo MRI

         13. Unwillingness or inability to entirely refrain from use of electronic devices during
             study visits

         14. Unwillingness or inability to refrain from intake of L-theanine and caffeine
             containing food or beverages within the 24 hours prior to each study visit

         15. Unwillingness or inability to follow written, on-screen and verbal instructions given
             by the study team
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Participant eligibility is based on self-representation of gender identity</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chanaka Kahathuduwa, MBBS PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Texas Tech University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chanaka Kahathuduwa, MBBS PhD</last_name>
    <phone>8068342451</phone>
    <email>chanaka.kahathuduwa@ttu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ann Mastergeorge, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>8068347162</phone>
    <email>ann.mastergeorge@ttu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Tech University - Department of Human Development and Family Studies</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lubbock</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>79409</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chanaka N Kahathuduwa, MBBS PhD</last_name>
      <phone>806-834-2451</phone>
      <email>chanaka.kahathuduwa@ttu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ann Mastergeorge, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>806-834-7162</phone>
      <email>ann.mastergeorge@ttu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chanaka Kahathuduwa, MBBS PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ann Mastergeorge, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sarah Wakefield, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 10, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 10, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperkinesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Caffeine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

