<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03536559</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CNMAu8.201</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03536559</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nanocrystalline Gold to Treat Remyelination Failure in Chronic Optic Neuropathy In Multiple Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>VISIONARY-MS</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 2, Randomized, DB-PC, Parallel Group Study for the Treatment of Visual Pathway Deficits In Chronic Optic Neuropathy to Assess the Efficacy, Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of CNM-Au8 For Remyelination In Multiple Sclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Clene Nanomedicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Clene Australia Pty Ltd</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Clene Nanomedicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this trial is to assess the efficacy and safety of CNM-Au8 as a
      remyelinating treatment for vision-impairing MS lesions in participants who have chronic
      vision impairment as a result of Relapsing Remitting Multiple Sclerosis. The primary endpoint
      is the improvement in remyelination as measured by visual evoked potentials after 24 weeks of
      treatment. The secondary endpoint is the improvement in low contrast vision as measured by
      low contrast letter acuity after 24 weeks of treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double-blind, parallel group, placebo-controlled study of the efficacy,
      safety, and pharmacokinetics of CNM-Au8 in stable RRMS patients who have Chronic Optic
      Neuropathy (residual deficits of conduction velocity in the visual pathway) as evidenced by
      prolonged latency of visual evoked potentials (VEP) at Baseline.

      Patients will be screened over a 4-week period. Patients who meet the inclusion criteria and
      none of the exclusionary criteria will be enrolled into the clinical study.

      All enrolled patients will have their visual baseline established in both eyes by
      electrophysiological, functional, and morphological tests.

      For each patient, the eye with the worst mf-VEP latency delay will be considered as the
      affected eye. The other eye will be considered as the fellow eye. In patients with bilateral
      VEP latency abnormalities, the worst eye (highest latency) will be selected as the affected
      eye. If both eyes have the similar VEP latency abnormalities (± 2 ms), then one eye will be
      randomly selected by the statistician to assess as the designated affected eye. Efficacy
      endpoints will be assessed in the affected and the fellow eye. Randomization will be
      stratified to ensure proportional representation of patients with unilateral vs. bilateral
      mf-VEP abnormality across treatment groups.

      Patients will be randomized to one of three groups: placebo, or one of two doses of CNM-Au8.
      All patients will receive their randomized oral treatment daily over at least 24 consecutive
      weeks during the Fixed Duration Treatment Period. The study will also have a blinded Variable
      Duration Treatment Period for up to an additional 24-weeks (48-week maximum blinded duration)
      until the last-patient enrolled completes his/her Week 24 study visit. The first enrolled
      patients will remain in the study until either a maximum of 48-weeks or until the
      last-enrolled patient reaches their 24-week visit, whichever comes first. When the last
      enrolled patient completes his or her 24-Week visit, treatment will end for the patients
      enrolled in the Variable Duration Treatment Period with their next scheduled study visit.

      The primary efficacy outcome measure will be assessed based upon each patient's Week 24 study
      visit. The study will remain blinded until the study database is locked.

      All patients who are discontinued from treatment will complete the End-of-Study (EOS)
      assessment.

      At the end of the Variable Duration Treatment Period, patients will complete an EOS
      assessment and then may choose either to exit the study, or receive open-label CNM-Au8 in a
      separate Open-Label Safety Extension Study.

      An independent DSMB will be responsible for monitoring the safety of the study on a quarterly
      basis and ad hoc at the request of the DSMB or the Sponsor (e.g., in the event of unexpected
      SAEs) to review data throughout the Fixed Duration Treatment Period and the Variable Duration
      Treatment Period. The DSMB may make recommendations on the conduct of the study, including
      study termination. Appropriate procedures will be detailed in a DSMB Charter that will define
      disclosure of any findings along with patient- and study-stopping criteria.

      There will be four study periods followed by a separate Open-Label Safety Extension Study:

        1. A four-week screening period (Screening Period);

        2. A fixed 24-week blinded, randomized treatment period (Fixed Duration Treatment Period);

        3. A variable-duration, blinded treatment period (Variable Duration Treatment Period) where
           patients continue the previously randomized treatment for up to an additional 24-weeks
           (total blinded duration of 48-weeks). This period will end for all patients when the
           last-enrolled patient reaches his or her 24-week visit (LP-24Wk) at which time patients
           in the Variable Duration Treatment Period will complete their next scheduled study
           visit;

        4. A four-week follow-up period (End-Of-Study Assessment) for patients not continuing in
           the separate Open-Label Safety Extension Study.

      Following the end of the blinded treatment period, patients will be given the option to enter
      a separate Open-Label Safety Extension Study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 23, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>randomized, double-blind, parallel group, placebo controlled study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The drug formulations will be identical in appearance (size, shape, volume, color) and smell. The packaging and labeling will be designed to maintain blinding to the Investigator's team and to patients. There are no visible differences between the active drug, and placebo dosing units</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Multifocal Visual Evoked Potential (mfVEP) Latency</measure>
    <time_frame>At six month (24-weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>mfVEP latency is an electrophysiologic measure of remyelination that assesses the speed of conduction of electrical signals in neurons of the visual system.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Low Contrast Letter Acuity (LCLA)</measure>
    <time_frame>At six months and then every 12 weeks thereafter, up to 48-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>LCLA is a functional measure of contrast vision</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Multifocal Visual Evoked Potential (mfVEP) Latency</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 12 weeks following the 6-month primary endpoint, up to 48-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>mfVEP latency is an electrophysiologic measure of remyelination that assesses the speed of conduction of electrical signals in neurons of the visual system.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Multifocal Visual Evoked Potential (mfVEP) Amplitude</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 12 weeks following the 6-month primary endpoint, up to 48-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>mfVEP amplitude is an electrophysiologic measure of axonal protection that assesses the magnitude of electrical signals in neurons of the visual system.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Full field Visual Evoked Potentials (ff-VEP) latency</measure>
    <time_frame>At three month intervals beginning at 12-weeks, up to 48-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>ffVEP latency is an electrophysiologic measure of remyelination that assesses the latency of electrical signals conduction in neurons of the visual system.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Full field Visual Evoked Potentials (ff-VEP) amplitude</measure>
    <time_frame>At three month intervals beginning at 12-weeks, up to 48-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>ffVEP amplitude is an electrophysiologic measure of axonal protection that assesses the magnitude of electrical signals in neurons of the visual system.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT)</measure>
    <time_frame>At three month intervals beginning at 24-weeks, up to 48-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measure of optic nerve morphology and retinal layers</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)</measure>
    <time_frame>At three month intervals beginning at 24-weeks, up to 48-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Structural imaging of MS lesions</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>High Contrast Visual Acuity Testing (HCVA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6-weeks, up to 48-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Standard visual acuity testing</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Expanded Disability Status Scale (EDSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>At three month intervals beginning at 12-weeks, up to 48-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Standardized MS functional scales</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Multiple Sclerosis Functional Composite Scale (MSFC)</measure>
    <time_frame>At three month intervals beginning at 12-weeks, up to 48-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Standardized MS functional scales</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Symbol Digit Modality Test (SDMT)</measure>
    <time_frame>At three month intervals beginning at 12-weeks, up to 48-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Pattern matching functional scale</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>National Eye Institute Visual Function Questionnaire (NEI-VFQ-25)</measure>
    <time_frame>At three month intervals beginning at 12-weeks, up to 48-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Visual Function Quality of Life Scales</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Ten-item Neuro-Ophthalmic Supplement (10-item NOS)</measure>
    <time_frame>At three month intervals beginning at 12-weeks, up to 48-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Visual Function Quality of Life Scales</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Six-Minute Walk Test (6MWT)</measure>
    <time_frame>At three month intervals beginning at 12-weeks, up to 48-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Standardized Measure of Mobility and Exercise Tolerance</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Relapsing Remitting Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Optic Neuropathy</condition>
  <condition>Optic; Neuritis, With Demyelination</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>15mg CNM-Au8</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>15mg suspension of clean-surfaced, faceted, gold nanocrystals in 60ml of sodium bicarbonate buffered water</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>30mg CNM-Au8</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>30mg suspension of clean-surfaced, faceted, gold nanocrystals in 60ml of sodium bicarbonate buffered water</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The matched placebo to be used in this study will consist of water, sodium bicarbonate, and food coloring to match volume and color of the experimental treatments.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CNM-Au8</intervention_name>
    <description>CNM-Au8 is a dark red/purple-colored liquid formulation consisting of a stable suspension of faceted clean surfaced elemental gold nanocrystals in buffered deionized water with a concentration of up to 0.5 mg/mL of gold. The formulation is buffered by sodium bicarbonate present at a concentration of 0.545 mg/mL. There are no other excipients. The drug product is formulated to be taken orally and will be provided in single dose HDPE containers. The study doses vary by the concentration of gold nanocrystals per milliliter in a volume of 60 mL.</description>
    <arm_group_label>15mg CNM-Au8</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>30mg CNM-Au8</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo is liquid with identical color and taste</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. At least 18 years of age and up to 50 years of age (inclusive).

          2. Clinical diagnosis of MS (meeting McDonald criteria, 2010) who have had RRMS no longer
             than 10 years from diagnosis.

          3. Presence of chronic optic neuropathy defined by clinical and/or multifocal visual
             evoked potential (mf-VEP) criteria.

          4. Retinal Nerve Fiber Layer (RNFL) thickness &gt; 70 μm.

          5. Stable disease activity based on the Investigator's judgment over the prior 12 months.

          6. Able to understand and give written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. An acute optic neuritis episode or systemic steroid treatment within the prior 6
             months.

          2. MS-related clinical relapse requiring systemic steroid treatment within the prior 12
             months.

          3. Unstable treatment with a disease modifying therapy (DMT) defined as a treatment
             change within prior 3-months unless due to intolerability.

          4. Any immunosuppression therapy other than those approved for the treatment of MS.

          5. Any drug known or suspected of producing retinal or optic nerve toxicity including
             hydroxychloroquine, chloroquine, clofazimine, vigabatrin, or ethambutol.

          6. Any active ophthalmological causes for retinal damage other than MS.

          7. Diabetes with retinopathy or a previous diagnosis of Diabetes Mellitus or history of
             prior impaired fasting glucose ≥126 mg/dL (or ≥ 200 mg/dL after oral glucose tolerance
             test).

          8. History of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis C (HepC) virus antibody, or
             hepatitis B (HepB) virus antibody.

          9. History of gold allergy.

         10. Patients taking stimulant medications (including: amphetamine, dextroamphetamine,
             lisdexamfetamine, methylphenidate, or modafinil).

         11. Patients taking clemastine fumarate or 4-aminopyridine (fampridine).

         12. Females who have a positive pregnancy test result, or who are pregnant, breastfeeding,
             or planning to conceive during the study.

         13. History or evidence of substance abuse or alcohol abuse within 5 years prior to
             Screening, including alcoholism; or severe tobacco use (&gt;1 pack/day).

         14. Clinical history of toxic neuropathy (e.g., secondary to treatment with ethambutol,
             isoniazid, linezolid, gentamycin, chloramphenicol, vincristine, or penicillamine).

         15. Current enrollment in any other drug or device treatment study within 3 months prior
             to Baseline. Participation in an observational non-interventional study (i.e., no drug
             or device therapy) is not an exclusion criterion.

         16. Inability to undergo any planned study procedures such as VEP or MRI, including
             reduced renal clearance (screening: GFR &lt; 45 mL/min), history of severe
             hypersensitivity to gadolinium-DTPA, claustrophobia; or inability to comply with study
             requirements based on Investigator judgment.

         17. Based on the investigator's judgment, concurrent chronic or acute illness or unstable
             medical condition that may deteriorate that could confound the results of safety
             assessments.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Heidi Beadnall, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Sydney</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Glen Frick, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>801-676-9695</phone>
    <email>info@clene.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Austin Rynders</last_name>
    <phone>801-676-9695</phone>
    <email>info@clene.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 2, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 14, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 14, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 14, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>gold</keyword>
  <keyword>nanocrystal</keyword>
  <keyword>multifocal visual evoked potential</keyword>
  <keyword>full field visual evoked potential</keyword>
  <keyword>low contrast vision</keyword>
  <keyword>low contrast letter acuity</keyword>
  <keyword>remyelination</keyword>
  <keyword>demyelination</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis, Relapsing-Remitting</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Optic Nerve Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Demyelinating Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Optic Neuritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

