<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03534609</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>L18000</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03534609</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genius System for Neck Treatment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Exploratory Evaluation of the Lutronic Genius System for Treatment of the Neck</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>LUTRONIC Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>LUTRONIC Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Genius system is substantially equivalent to the Infini device (K121481). The study is a
      prospective, multi-site, non-randomized study of up to 30 treated subjects presenting for
      treatment of mild to moderate lines, wrinkles, textural concerns, and/or skin laxity of the
      neck.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      At enrollment, standardized baseline/pretreatment 2D and 3D images will be obtained from each
      subject. Study subjects will receive three neck treatments completed 30 days apart. Subjects
      will be contacted via a phone call 3 days following each treatment to assess for adverse
      events and expected treatment effects. Effectiveness assessments will occur prior to
      Treatments #2 and #3, and a follow-up visit will be completed at 90 days following Treatment
      #3. Each assessment visit will include efficacy, adverse events, and expected treatment
      effects assessments, and post-treatment 2D and 3D digital images will be captured.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 27, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Prospective, non-randomized, open label</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Masked qualitative assessment of improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 90 days following the last treatment</time_frame>
    <description>An assessment of paired pre- and post-treatment photographs will be conducted by blinded assessors evaluating for improvement in neck appearance from pre- to post-treatment. The assessors choose the photo they believe to be the post-treatment photo, i.e., Left photo or Right photo.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinician aesthetic improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to Days 90 following the last study treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>Overall aesthetic improvement based on completion of the Clinician Global Aesthetic Improvement Scale, a 5-point scale (0-4) that rates global aesthetic improvement from the pre-treatment appearance with 4 being 'Very Much Improved' and 0 being 'Worse'. The scale will be administered based on a live assessment of the subject while referring to the subject's pre-treatment photographs, and based on a comparison of the subject's pre-treatment photographs to the Day 90 follow-up photographs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject aesthetic improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to Days 90 following the last study treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>Overall aesthetic improvement based on completion of the Subject Global Aesthetic Improvement Scale, a 5-point scale (0-4) that rates global aesthetic improvement from the pre-treatment appearance with 4 being 'Very Much Improved' and 0 being 'Worse'. Subjects will complete the scale based on a live assessment while referring to a hand mirror and their pre-treatment photographs, and based on a comparison of their pre-treatment photographs to their Day 90 follow-up photographs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline to 90 days following the last study treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction will be evaluated based on subjects' completion of a patient satisfaction questionnaire while referring to a hand mirror and their pre-treatment and their Day 90 follow-up photographs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment-related pain</measure>
    <time_frame>For the duration of each study treatment which typically can last up to approximately 90 minutes.</time_frame>
    <description>During each study treatment, subjects' pain levels will be monitored using a validated Numeric Rating Scale (0-10), with 0 being 'No Pain' and 10 being 'Worse Possible Pain'.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Wrinkles, Skin Laxity, Skin Texture</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Genius System Neck Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lutronic Genius System treatment of lines, wrinkles, and texture concerns on the neck.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lutronic Genius System</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment of the neck using the Lutronic Genius System</description>
    <arm_group_label>Genius System Neck Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female, age 18 years and older.

          2. Subject in good health.

          3. Fitzpatrick Skin Type I to VI.

          4. Mild to moderate lines, wrinkles, textural concerns, and/or skin laxity of the neck.

          5. Understands and accepts the obligation not to undergo any other procedures in the
             areas to be treated through the follow-up period.

          6. Willingness and ability to comply with protocol requirements, including returning for
             follow-up visits and abstaining from exclusionary procedures for the duration of the
             study.

          7. Post-menopausal, surgically sterilized, or using a medically acceptable form of birth
             control at least 3 months prior to enrollment and during the entire course of the
             study.

          8. Absence of physical or psychological conditions unacceptable to the investigator.

          9. Willingness and ability to provide written consent for study-required photography and
             adherence to photography procedures (i.e., removal of jewelry and makeup).

         10. Willingness and ability to provide written informed consent and HIPAA authorization
             prior to performance of any study-related procedure.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Presence of an active skin condition or infection in the treatment area such as sores,
             Psoriasis, eczema, rash, severe active inflammatory acne or oral herpes simplex
             breakout.

          2. History of skin disorders, keloid scarring, and/or abnormal wound healing.

          3. Open wounds or lesions in the area(s) to be treated.

          4. Inability to understand the protocol or to give informed consent.

          5. History of chronic drug or alcohol abuse.

          6. History of vascular disease.

          7. History of bleeding disorders.

          8. BMI equal to or greater than 30.

          9. Subjects who are pregnant, nursing, or anticipate a pregnancy during the length of the
             trial.

         10. Subjects with current skin cancer or other malignant disease including pre-malignant
             moles.

         11. Poorly controlled medical condition that could compromise wound healing or increase
             risk of infection such as an impaired immune system due to immunosuppressive diseases
             such as AIDS and HIV, or use of immunosuppressive medications, radiation therapy, or
             chemotherapy.

         12. Subjects with implanted medical devices: pacemaker, cardioverts, superficial metal
             within the treatment area, and other implantable devices or synthetic fillers.

         13. Subjects with sensitivity or allergy to gold.

         14. Subjects with sensitivity or allergy to local anesthetics such as lidocaine or
             tetracaine.

         15. Concurrent enrollment in any study involving the use of investigational devices or
             drugs.

         16. History of surgical or cosmetic treatments in the area(s) to be treated within the
             past six months.

         17. History or current use of the following prescription medications:

               1. Daily anticoagulants, aspirin, iron supplements, herbal supplements such as
                  ginkgo, ginseng or garlic within the past two weeks;

               2. Topical retinoid within the past one week; and

               3. Psychiatric drugs that in the investigators opinion would impair the subject from
                  understanding the protocol requirements or understanding and signing the informed
                  consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kari Larson, MBA</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Sponsor GmbH</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kari Larson, MBA</last_name>
    <phone>801.244.0058</phone>
    <email>klarson@lutronic.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Laser and Skin Surgery Center of New York</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jennifer Moreno</last_name>
      <phone>212-686-7306</phone>
      <email>jmoreno@laserskinsurgery.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Brittney Schmidt</last_name>
      <phone>212-686-7306</phone>
      <email>bschmidt@laserskinsurgery.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Roy Geronemus, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 16, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 11, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cutis Laxa</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

