<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02463331</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0571/04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02463331</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Possible Role of Chloroquine to Induce a Complete Remission in the Treatment of Autoimmune Hepatitis: a Randomized Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Possible Role of Chloroquine in Conjunction to Prednisone to Induce a Complete Remission in the Treatment of Autoimmune Hepatitis: a Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sao Paulo General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The gold-standard treatment of Autoimmune hepatitis (AIH), with prednisone alone or in
      conjunction with azathioprine can reach resolution of the disease in 70-80% of the cases in
      US. However, in Brazil the response to these treatments seems to be worse, approximately 35%
      in five years. Because of the side effects of the gold-standard treatment and the need for an
      alternative option for the no responsive patients, news drugs must be evaluated for this
      proposal. Chloroquine diphosphate is an antimalarial drug that has been used for the
      treatment of rheumatological diseases for at the least five decades. Chloroquine was used as
      a single drug for up to two years for the maintenance of AIH remission in an open study.
      There was a 6.49 greater chance of relapse in the historical controls when compared with
      patients treated with chloroquine (72.2% x 23.5%; p = 0.031). The aim of this study was to
      investigate whether chloroquine in conjunction with prednisone can be used as an alternative
      treatment of AIH in a randomized study, and to evaluate its side effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Autoimmune hepatitis (AIH) is a chronic disease with a progressive destruction of hepatic
      parenchyma, leading to cirrhosis and high mortality in the absence of specific treatment. It
      has been demonstrated that the treatment with corticosteroids and azathioprine provides
      clinical and laboratory improvement, reduction of histological inflammatory activity on liver
      biopsy and an increased survival.

      Because of the side effects of the gold-standard treatment and the need for an alternative
      option for the no responsive patients, news drugs must be evaluated for this proposal.

      Chloroquine is a drug of the group of 4-aminoquinolines, synthetic derivatives of quinine and
      constituent of the bark of the Cinchona tree. Chloroquine accumulates in tissues in
      considerable amounts. In animals, from 200 to 700 times the plasma concentration can be found
      in liver, spleen, kidneys and lungs. As a weak base, it accumulates intracellularly,
      particularly in lysosomes with a consequent increase in pH within these organelles, which
      could contribute to its toxicity. Lysosomal lamellar bodies are observed in tissues affected
      by chloroquine, such as retina and neuromuscular system. Chloroquine inhibits the absorption
      and the binding of mitochondrial calcium, alters the membrane permeability and the transport
      of enzymes to the lysosomes. Apparently there are other mechanisms to explain its
      anti-inflammatory action; such as the interference with the release of TNF from mononuclear
      phagocytes by inhibiting gene expression and the down-regulation of TNF receptors, by
      delaying their transport to the cellular surface. Due to these mechanisms of action,
      chloroquine has anti-inflammatory activities and therefore is used in diseases such as
      rheumatoid arthritis and systemic lupus erythematosus. In liver diseases, chloroquine was
      used in patients with hepatitis B with normalization of the levels of aminotransferases and
      of the prothrombin time during treatment and relapse after drug discontinuation. Chloroquine
      was also evaluated in patients with porphyria cutanea tarda and despite the clinical and
      biochemical improvement, liver biopsies remained unchanged after one year of treatment.

      A previous pilot study was performed in our institution, and published in 2005, with
      chloroquine diphosphate for the maintenance treatment of AIH. In this study, 14 patients with
      a biochemical and histological remission were treated with chloroquine diphosphate 250 mg/day
      for at least 12 months or until disease recurrence, and compared with 18 historical controls,
      which was held in discontinuation of treatment after remission. The chance of relapse was
      6.49 times higher in the historical controls when compared with patients in the group treated
      with chloroquine (72.2% versus 23.5%, p = 0.031). The use of chloroquine was safe in patients
      with liver cirrhosis without decompensation, and there were no serious adverse events within
      two years of use.

      The most common adverse effects of chloroquine are mild and transient such as
      gastrointestinal symptoms, headache, dizziness, blurry vision and fatigue. The more severe
      reactions described are itching, cardiovascular manifestations, dyskinesias, eye injuries,
      neuromuscular disorders and hearing loss. Among the most feared adverse effects of
      chloroquine, are the eye injuries, usually associated with chronic treatment. They may
      consist of changes in the retina, lens, cornea and optic nerve. Usually they remain stable
      after drug withdrawal, if the drug is discontinued in early stages. However, the retinal
      damage can increase when found in advanced stages, and may progress even years after
      cessation of chloroquine. It is believed that the chloroquine retinopathy can be prevented or
      recognized in an early reversible stage with judicious use, appropriate doses and regular
      ophthalmologic follow-up. It is recommended that the daily dose does not exceed 250 mg of
      chloroquine diphosphate or 400 mg of hydroxychloroquine, and ophthalmologic evaluations are
      carried out every 4 to 6 months. Despite the adverse effects and toxic reactions described
      above, there is a consensus in most studies with chloroquine that it is a well tolerated
      drug, provided that the appropriate dosage guidelines and regular eye examinations are
      followed. With these cautions in mind, its use rarely causes serious side or irreversible
      effects.

      The aim of this study was to investigate whether chloroquine in conjunction with prednisone
      can be used as an alternative treatment of AIH in a randomized study, and to evaluate its
      side effects.

      To be included patients had to satisfy the following criteria simultaneously: a diagnosis of
      probable / definite AIH and the indication of treatment (according to the International AIH
      Group), normal liver function and absence of clinical signs of decompensated liver disease
      (ascites, hepatic encephalopathy, gastrointestinal bleeding and hepatocellular carcinoma).
      For their enrollment, it is necessary that the patients are in accordance with the proposed
      study, following the precepts of the Declaration of Helsinki. If patients refuse to
      participate in the study, they will be treated following the traditional guidelines of our
      service. Treatment will be discontinued in case of pregnancy, patient's desire, side-effects
      or relapse of AIH.

      Patients were randomized to receive azathioprine and prednisone or chloroquine and
      prednisone. The alternative treatment, with chloroquine, was maintained unless it caused
      major side-effects, no biochemical response or treatment failure. In this case, azathioprine
      was introduced in association with prednisone. All patients had visits every 30 days during
      the first six months with routine blood tests performed. After then, consultations were every
      two months. All complaints were recorded. Every patient were treated by the doctors
      responsible for the study, laboratory tests were performed in the Central Laboratory of the
      hospital. All patients underwent to initial ophthalmologic evaluation followed by six-monthly
      evaluations. The drug was withdrawal, if changes suggestive of retinopathy were observed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Biochemical Response to Therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>six months</time_frame>
    <description>The biochemical response is defined when there is normalization of hepatic enzymes, mainly AST and ALT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Histopathological Response to Therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>liver biopsy was was performed to evaluate histopathological response after 18 months of biochemical response</time_frame>
    <description>Histopathological response is achieved when there is minimal or no inflammation in hepatic tissue, as assessed by liver biopsy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">57</enrollment>
  <condition>Autoimmune Hepatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>chloroquine plus prednisone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Chloroquine diphosphate 250mg/day associated to prednisone in variable doses</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>azathioprine plus prednisone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>azathioprine in variable doses (50-150mg/day) associated to prednisone in variable doses</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chloroquine diphosphate</intervention_name>
    <description>One pill of chloroquine diphosphate per day until the end of the study</description>
    <arm_group_label>chloroquine plus prednisone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Chloroquine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>prednisone</intervention_name>
    <description>Prednisone 5-15 mg/day until the end of the study</description>
    <arm_group_label>chloroquine plus prednisone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>azathioprine plus prednisone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>azathioprine</intervention_name>
    <description>azathioprine 1-2mg/Kg/day until the end of the study</description>
    <arm_group_label>azathioprine plus prednisone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of autoimmune hepatitis according to Autoimmune Hepatitis International
             Group with indication for treatment

          -  No evidence of decompensated liver cirrhosis

          -  Non-pregnant women and women with no intention to become pregnant

          -  Willing to participate in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Discrete biochemical changes and histological inflammatory activity absent / minimal
             (periportal / peri-septal: 0/1 +) or decompensated cirrhosis

          -  Cases of loss of follow up
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eduardo LR Cançado</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Sao Paulo General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 18, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 1, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 4, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>November 2, 2016</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>November 2, 2016</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">December 30, 2016</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 29, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 29, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Sao Paulo General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lydia Teófilo de Moraes Falcão</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Association of Chloroquine and Prednisone as an Alternative Treatment for Autoimmune Hepatitis: a Randomized Trial</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>autoimmune hepatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>chloroquine</keyword>
  <keyword>treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis, Autoimmune</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chloroquine diphosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prednisone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Azathioprine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chloroquine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Chloroquine Plus Prednisone</title>
          <description>Chloroquine diphosphate 250mg/day associated to prednisone in variable doses
Chloroquine diphosphate: One pill of chloroquine diphosphate per day until the end of the study
prednisone: Prednisone 5-15 mg/day until the end of the study</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Azathioprine Plus Prednisone</title>
          <description>azathioprine in variable doses (1-2mg/Kg/day) associated to prednisone in variable doses
prednisone: Prednisone 5-15 mg/day until the end of the study
azathioprine: azathioprine 1-2mg/Kg/day until the end of the study</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="26"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="31"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="10"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="25"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="16"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="6"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Adverse Event</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="4"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Lost to Follow-up</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Pregnancy</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="3"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Lack of Efficacy</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="6"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Physician Decision</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="3"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Chloroquine Plus Prednisone</title>
          <description>Chloroquine diphosphate 250mg/day associated to prednisone in variable doses
Chloroquine diphosphate: One pill of chloroquine diphosphate per day until the end of the study
prednisone: Prednisone 5-15 mg/day until the end of the study</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Azathioprine Plus Prednisone</title>
          <description>azathioprine in variable doses (50-150mg/day) associated to prednisone in variable doses
prednisone: Prednisone 5-15 mg/day until the end of the study
azathioprine: azathioprine 1-2mg/Kg/day until the end of the study</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="26"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="31"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="57"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="37.54" spread="15.99"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="37.23" spread="17.63"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="37.28" spread="16.84"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="24"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="45"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="12"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Biochemical Response to Therapy</title>
        <description>The biochemical response is defined when there is normalization of hepatic enzymes, mainly AST and ALT.</description>
        <time_frame>six months</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Chloroquine Plus Prednisone</title>
            <description>Chloroquine diphosphate 250mg/day associated to prednisone in variable doses
Chloroquine diphosphate: One pill of chloroquine diphosphate per day until the end of the study
prednisone: Prednisone 5-15 mg/day until the end of the study</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Azathioprine Plus Prednisone</title>
            <description>azathioprine in variable doses (1-2mg/Kg/day) associated to prednisone in variable doses
prednisone: Prednisone 5-15 mg/day until the end of the study
azathioprine: azathioprine 1-2mg/Kg/day until the end of the study</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Biochemical Response to Therapy</title>
          <description>The biochemical response is defined when there is normalization of hepatic enzymes, mainly AST and ALT.</description>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="26"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="31"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="14"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="21"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Histopathological Response to Therapy</title>
        <description>Histopathological response is achieved when there is minimal or no inflammation in hepatic tissue, as assessed by liver biopsy.</description>
        <time_frame>liver biopsy was was performed to evaluate histopathological response after 18 months of biochemical response</time_frame>
        <population>The histological response was only evaluated in the patients with biochemical remission, since in the patients without biochemical response it was already known that there would be activity in the liver tissue.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Chloroquine Plus Prednisone</title>
            <description>Chloroquine diphosphate 250mg/day associated to prednisone in variable doses
Chloroquine diphosphate: One pill of chloroquine diphosphate per day until the end of the study
prednisone: Prednisone 5-15 mg/day until the end of the study</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Azathioprine Plus Prednisone</title>
            <description>azathioprine in variable doses (1-2mg/Kg/day) associated to prednisone in variable doses
prednisone: Prednisone 5-15 mg/day until the end of the study
azathioprine: azathioprine 1-2mg/Kg/day until the end of the study</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Histopathological Response to Therapy</title>
          <description>Histopathological response is achieved when there is minimal or no inflammation in hepatic tissue, as assessed by liver biopsy.</description>
          <population>The histological response was only evaluated in the patients with biochemical remission, since in the patients without biochemical response it was already known that there would be activity in the liver tissue.</population>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="14"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="21"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="10"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Chloroquine Plus Prednisone</title>
          <description>Chloroquine diphosphate 250mg/day associated to prednisone in variable doses
Chloroquine diphosphate: One pill of chloroquine diphosphate per day until the end of the study
prednisone: Prednisone 5-15 mg/day until the end of the study</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Azathioprine Plus Prednisone</title>
          <description>azathioprine in variable doses (1-2mg/Kg/day) associated to prednisone in variable doses
prednisone: Prednisone 5-15 mg/day until the end of the study
azathioprine: azathioprine 1-2mg/Kg/day until the end of the study</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="26"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="31"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Eye disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>machulopatia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="26"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="31"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <default_assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="26"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="31"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>gastric intolerance</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="26"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="31"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Nervous system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>neuropathy</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="26"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="31"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>hyperpigmentation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="26"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="31"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Lydia Teófilo de Moraes Falcão</name_or_title>
      <organization>Clinic Hospital of University of Sao Paulo</organization>
      <phone>55-81-996486935 ext 81</phone>
      <email>lydiatmf@yahoo.com.br</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

