<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02467504</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>hrIL-2 RA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02467504</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Low-dose Recombinant Human IL-2 for the Treatment of Rheumatoid Arthritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double Blind, Placebo-controlled Pilot-study to Evaluate Efficacy and Safety of Low-dose hrIL-2 in the Treatment of Disease Modifying Antirheumatic Drugs (DMARD)-Naive Patients With Rheumatoid Arthritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Peking University People's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Monash University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Beijing ShuangLu Pharmaceutical Co., Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Peking University People's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is an immune-mediated inflammatory disease, characterized by
      symmetric poly-arthritis usually involving the small joints of the hands and feet. In
      addition, various extra-joint manifestations may develop. Several immunomodulating agents
      have been attempted in the treatment of RA without achieving satisfactory results.
      Dysfunction of regulatory T (Treg) cells has been detected in diverse autoimmune diseases,
      which can be promoted by interleukin-2 (IL-2). The investigators hypothesized that low-dose
      IL-2 could be a novel therapy in active RA patients. This clinical study will test the
      efficacy and safety of low dose IL-2 treatment in RA. The investigators perform a
      single-centre, double-blind pilot trial with hrIL-2 in RA. The investigators evaluate the
      effectiveness and safeness of low-dose hrIL-2 for RA by randomized controlled study (hrIL-2
      (N = 30) + Methotrexate (MTX)+ Loxoprofen versus placebo+MTX + Loxoprofen group (N = 30)).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Each RA patients (n=60) with DAS&gt;3.2 received low-dose IL-2+MTX+ Loxoprofen or placebo+MTX +
      Loxoprofen (active group: placebo group =1:1, 1 million units every other day subcutaneously
      (hrIL-2 1×106, ip, Qod) for a period of 14 days. After a 14-day rest, another cycle started)
      for 3 cycles. The end points were safety and clinical and immunologic response.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants Achieving DAS28 remission.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 24</time_frame>
    <description>DAS 28 remission is defined by a disease activity score (28 joint) calculated using the C-reactive protein formula (DAS28-CRP) of less than 2.6</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of Clinical safety ( type and number of adverse events and serious adverse events)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to week 24</time_frame>
    <description>adverse events includes injection site reactions, influenza-like symptoms, infection, fever, tumor, cardiovascular event, drug-induced liver and kidney damage.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of immunological responses with percentage of Treg cells, Th17 cells and Tfh cells</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>analysis regulatory CD4+ T(Treg) cells, interleukin 17 (IL-17)-producing helper T (Th17) cells and follicular helper T (Tfh) cells before and during IL-2 treatment. P values&lt;0.05 are considered statistically significant.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants Achieving DAS28 Low Disease Activity.</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Low disease activity is defined by a disease activity score (28 joint) calculated using the C-reactive protein formula (DAS28-CRP) of less than 3.2</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants achieving a good or moderate European League Against Rheumatism (EULAR) response</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Good response is defined as: DAS28-CRP ≤ 3.2 and decrease from Baseline by &gt; 1.2.
moderate response is defined as achievement of one of the following: DAS28-CRP ≤ 3.2 and decrease from Baseline &gt; 0.6 and ≤ 1.2 DAS28-CRP &gt; 3.2 and ≤ 5.1 and decrease from Baseline &gt; 0.6 DAS28-CRP &gt; 5.1 and decrease from Baseline &gt;1.2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants meeting the American College of Rheumatology 20% response criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>The assessments are based on a 20% or greater improvement from Baseline in the number of tender joints, a 20%, or more improvement in the number of swollen joints, and a 20% or greater improvement in 3 of the 5 remaining core set measures: Patient's Global Assessment of Disease Activity (PtGADA), Physician's Global Assessment of Disease Activity (PhGADA), Patient's Assessment of Arthritis Pain (PtAAP), physical function as assessed by the Health Assessment Questionnaire - Disability Index (HAQ-DI) and C-Reactive Protein (CRP).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants meeting the American College of Rheumatology 50% response criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>The assessments are based on a 50% or greater improvement from Baseline in the number of tender joints, a 50%, or more improvement in the number of swollen joints, and a 50% or greater improvement in 3 of the 5 remaining core set measures: Patient's Global Assessment of Disease Activity (PtGADA), Physician's Global Assessment of Disease Activity (PhGADA), Patient's Assessment of Arthritis Pain (PtAAP), physical function as assessed by the Health Assessment Questionnaire - Disability Index (HAQ-DI) and C-Reactive Protein (CRP).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants meeting the American College of Rheumatology 70% response criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>The assessments are based on a 70% or greater improvement from Baseline in the number of tender joints, a 70%, or more improvement in the number of swollen joints, and a 70% or greater improvement in 3 of the 5 remaining core set measures: Patient's Global Assessment of Disease Activity (PtGADA), Physician's Global Assessment of Disease Activity (PhGADA), Patient's Assessment of Arthritis Pain (PtAAP), physical function as assessed by the Health Assessment Questionnaire - Disability Index (HAQ-DI) and C-Reactive Protein (CRP).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants meeting the 2011 American College of Rheumatology/ European League Against Rheumatism (ACR/EULAR) remission criteria simplified for clinical practice</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>The 2011 ACR/EULAR remission criteria simplified for clinical practice is defined as:Tender Joint Count (TJC) ≤ 1, Swollen Joint Count (SJC) ≤ 1 and Patient's Global Assessment of Disease Activity (PtGADA) ≤ 1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Clinical Disease Activity Index (CDAI) ≤ 2.8</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, week 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Simplified Disease Activity Index (SDAI) ≤ 3.3</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, week 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects with a Health Assessment Questionnaire- Disability Index (HAQ-DI) ≤ 0.5</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, week 2</time_frame>
    <description>The domains of the HAQ-DI are dressing and grooming, arising, eating, walking, hygiene, reach, grip and common daily activities. The total score ranges from 0 to 3 with lower scores meaning lower disability.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self reported quality of life as measured by the SF-36 quetionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>Score ranging from 0 to 100 with higher scores indicating less bodily pain, better health status, better mental health, better physical functioning, less limitations due to emotional problems, less limitations due to physical problems, better social functioning, better vitality, better health</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Work Productivity Survey - Rheumatoid Arthritis [WPS-RA]</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>In the last month, number of work days missed, number of work days with reduced productivity. The Arthritis interference in the last month with work productivity is measured on a scale that ranges from 0 (no interference) to 10 (complete interference). In the last month, number of days with no household work, number of days with reduced household work productivity, number of days with hired outside help, number of days missed of family/social/leisure activities in the last month. The Arthritis interference in the last month with household work productivity is measured on a scale that ranges from 0 (no interference) to 10 (complete interference).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of Erythrocyte Sedimentation Ratio (ESR)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 4, week 8, week 12, week 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure of C Reactive Protein (CRP)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 4, week 8, week 12, week 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's Global Assessment of Disease Activity (PtGADA)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>VAS score from 0 to 10 for Patient's Global Assessment of Disease Activity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician's Global Assessment of Disease Activity (PhGADA)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>VAS score from 0 to 10 for Physician's Global Assessment of Disease Activity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's Assessment of Arthritis Pain (PtAAP)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 12, week 24</time_frame>
    <description>VAS score from 0 to 10 for Patient's Assessment of Arthritis Pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Rheumatoid Arthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>hrIL-2 active (1 million U doses of hrIL-2s.c.injection) MTX Folic acid Loxoprofen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>hrIL-2 placebo (1 million U doses of placebo s.c.injection) MTX Folic acid Loxoprofen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>hrIL-2 active</intervention_name>
    <description>hrIL-2 active (1 million U doses of hrIL-2s.c.injection)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Human recombinant IL-2</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>hrIL-2 placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>hrIL-2 placebo (1 million U doses of hrIL-2 placebo s.c.injection)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MTX</intervention_name>
    <description>Methotrexate (oral administration)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Folic Acid</intervention_name>
    <description>Folic Acid (oral administration)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Loxoprofen</intervention_name>
    <description>Loxoprofen (oral administration)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female ≥18 and ≤70 years of age at time of screening

          -  Diagnosed with rheumatoid arthritis

          -  Must have active disease to be initiated by DMARDs (Disease Modifying Anti-Rheumatic
             Drugs)

          -  Moderate or severe rheumatoid arthritis during screening, as defined by a disease
             activity score (28 joint) calculated using the C-reactive protein formula (DAS28-CRP)
             &gt; 3.2

          -  Have given written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient presenting or having a history of other inflammatory joint disease

          -  Patient with ongoing or previous Stevens-Johnson syndrome, toxic epidermal necrolysis
             or erythema multiforme

          -  Patient with significantly impaired bone marrow function or significant anaemia,
             leucopenia or thrombocytopenia due to causes or other than active rheumatoid arthritis

          -  Persistent infection or severe infection within 3 months before enrollment,

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension, uncontrolled diabetes, unstable ischemic heart disease,
             active inflammatory bowel disease, active peptic ulcer disease, terminal illness or
             other medical condition which, in the opinion of the investigator, would put the
             patient at risk to participate in the study,

          -  Clinically relevant cardiovascular, hepatic, neurological, endocrine, or other major
             systemic disease making implementation of the protocol or interpretation of the study
             results difficult

          -  Severe hypoproteinemia (e.g., in case of severe liver disease or nephrotic syndrome)
             with serum albumin &lt; 30 g/L

          -  Moderate or severe impairment of renal function, as known by serum creatinine &gt;
             133μmol/L (or 1.5 mg/dl)

          -  Patient with history of recent and clinically significant drug or alcohol abuse

          -  Impairment of liver function or persisting ALT (SGPT) elevations of more than 2-fold
             the upper limit of normal

          -  Known HIV positive status

          -  Known positive serology for hepatitis B or C

          -  Patient with hypersensitivity to any of the excipients in the tablets of methotrexate

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Breastfeeding

          -  Women of childbearing potential, except if they fulfill specific conditions,

          -  Men wishing to father children during the course of the study or within the 24 months
             thereafter (or 3 month with the washout procedure)

          -  Patient with a congenital or acquired severe immuno-deficiency, a history of cancer or
             lymphoproliferative disease, or any patient who has received total lymphoid
             irradiation

          -  Previous therapy at any time with:

        any DMARD including methotrexate, oral or injectable gold salts, chloroquine,
        hydroxychloroquine, ciclosporin, azathioprine, methotrexate, sulfasalazine any alkylating
        agents, e.g., cyclophosphamide, chlorambucil, biological agents, e.g., interferon,
        monoclonal antibodies, growth factor, cytokines any investigational drug any
        antimetabolites

        • Therapy within the previous 4 weeks with: oral corticosteroids exceeding a prednisolone
        equivalent of 10 mg/day parenteral or intra-articular corticoid injection

          -  Enrollment in any other clinical trial involving off-label use of an investigational
             drug or device, or enrollment in any other type of medical research

          -  Any active infection (including chronic or localized infections) for which
             anti-infectives were indicated within 28 days prior to first investigational product
             dose

          -  BMI(body mass index) under 18.5 kg/m2 or more than 30 kg/m2

          -  The above information is not intended to contain all considerations relevant to a
             patient's potential participation in a clinical trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Zhanguo Li, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Peking University Institute of Rheuamotology and Immunology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Xiaoying Zhang, MD</last_name>
    <phone>8613810001444</phone>
    <email>xiaoying19880307@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jing He, MD</last_name>
    <phone>8618611707347</phone>
    <email>hejing1105@126.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Rheumatology and Immunology, Peking University People's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100044</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Xiaoying Zhang, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+8613810001444</phone>
      <email>xiaoying19880307@163.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 4, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 10, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 10, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 10, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 11, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Peking University People's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zhanguo Li</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dept. Rheumatology and immunology,Peking University People's Hospital</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Folic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin B Complex</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Loxoprofen</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antirheumatic Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

