<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02465294</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB201400484</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02465294</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Influence of Probiotics on Body Weight and Composition</brief_title>
  <acronym>WLP</acronym>
  <official_title>The Influence of Probiotics With a Behavioral Life Style Intervention on Body Weight and Composition in Overweight Participants: A Randomized, Double-blinded, Placebo-controlled Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the addition of two different probiotic
      interventions to a comprehensive behavioral lifestyle intervention on body weight loss and
      overall health in overweight adults.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled study. After obtaining informed
      consent, healthy overweight adults aged 18 to 75 years (n=76/intervention group with n=228
      total/study) will be randomized to one of three groups: Lactobacillus, a blend of
      Bifidobacterium and Lactobacillus, or placebo. Participants will consume 1 capsule per day of
      probiotic or placebo for 12 weeks. Participants will attend weekly behavioral lifestyle
      intervention meetings, which will address dietary and physical activity contributions to
      weight loss, in groups of approximately 20 subjects during the 12 intervention weeks.

      Participants will complete daily questionnaires throughout the week before and during the
      intervention period which address subject compliance and bowel habits. A dual X-ray
      absorptivity scan will be done to measure body composition during the week before the
      intervention and during the 12th week of the intervention period (± 1 week). Blood samples
      will be collected via a finger prick at the baseline and final time points. Blood samples
      will be used to measure cardiovascular and metabolic markers of health. Stool samples will be
      collected from 25 subjects per intervention group during the week before the intervention
      period and the 12th week of the intervention period. Dietary intake will be assessed during
      the week before the intervention period and during the week of the final appointment (± 1
      week). Gastrointestinal symptoms and physical activity questionnaires will be completed upon
      providing consent to the study, being randomized to an intervention, and during the last week
      of the intervention period. Questionnaires regarding income, weight control strategies, and
      quality of life will be completed during randomization and during the last week of the
      intervention period. Stool samples will be collected from a subgroup of participants during
      the week before the intervention period and during the 12th week of the intervention period.
      These samples will be used to detect the presence and/or abundance and/or survival of the
      probiotic microorganisms at the end of the digestive tract.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    study withdrawn due to funding
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>February 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in baseline to week 12 in the percentage of body weight lost between the probiotic groups and the placebo group</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline (start of week 1) to Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Body weight (kg)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in body composition (Fat mass) between the probiotic groups and the placebo group</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from Pre-baseline to Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Fat mass (kg)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in body composition (Waist circumference) between the probiotic groups and the placebo group</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from Pre-baseline to Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Waist circumference (cm)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in body composition (Sagittal abdominal diameter) between the probiotic groups and the placebo group</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from Pre-baseline to Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Sagittal abdominal diameter (cm)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in bowel habits between the probiotic groups and the placebo group</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from Pre-baseline (Week -1) to Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Bowel movement frequency (average number per week)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in gastrointestinal symptoms between the probiotic groups and the placebo group</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from Pre-baseline (Week -1) to Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Symptoms measured using the Gastrointestinal Symptom Rating Score questionnaire provide a score for the follow five syndromes: abdominal pain, reflux, constipation, diarrhea, and indigestion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in markers of cardiovascular health between the probiotic groups and the placebo group</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from Pre-baseline to Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Serum cholesterol (mg/dl)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in nutritional intake between the probiotic groups and the placebo group</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from Pre-baseline (Week -1) to Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Total energy intake (kcal) will be assessed using the automated self-administered 24 hour dietary recall.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in weight control strategies between the probiotic groups and the placebo group</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from Pre-baseline (Week -1) to Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Differences in weight control strategies questionnaire scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in intestinal microbiota community composition between the probiotic groups and the placebo group</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from Pre-baseline (Week -1) to Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>Stool samples will be collected from a subgroup of participants to analyze intestinal microbiota community composition.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Overweight</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Potato starch and magnesium stearate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will be used as a control to asses the efficacy of the other probiotic arms. The placebo will contain encapsulated potato starch and magnesium stearate which is used the matrix in the probiotic supplements. The placebo refers only to the intervention supplement, not the behavioral lifestyle intervention. All subjects will participate in the same behavioral lifestyle intervention. In addition, blood tests will be performed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lactobacillus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lactobacillus will be taken as a capsule once daily for 12 weeks by subjects in the group receiving this supplement (group is unknown, double-blinded). All subjects will participate in the same behavioral lifestyle intervention. In addition, blood tests will be performed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mix of Bifidobacterium and Lactobacillus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A blend of Bifidobacterium and Lactobacillus will be taken as a capsule once daily for 12 weeks by subjects in the group receiving this supplement (group is unknown, double-blinded). All subjects will participate in the same behavioral lifestyle intervention. In addition, blood tests will be performed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Probiotic</intervention_name>
    <description>This group will receive the Lactobacillus probiotic, which will be taken as a capsule once daily for 12 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lactobacillus</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lactobacillus</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Behavioral lifestyle intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>All participants will participate in weekly group meetings of 15 to 20 participants for a facilitated discussion of specific nutritional, behavioral, and physical activity topics chosen to promote weight loss.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Potato starch and magnesium stearate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Lactobacillus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Mix of Bifidobacterium and Lactobacillus</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>This group will receive the placebo and will be taken as a capsule once daily for 12 weeks. The placebo will contain encapsulated potato starch which is used the matrix in the probiotic supplements.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Potato starch and magnesium stearate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Potato starch and magnesium stearate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood Test</intervention_name>
    <description>All subjects will have blood tests performed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Potato starch and magnesium stearate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Lactobacillus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Mix of Bifidobacterium and Lactobacillus</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Probiotic</intervention_name>
    <description>This group will receive the blend of Bifidobacterium and Lactobacillus probiotic, which will be taken as a capsule once daily for 12 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mix of Bifidobacterium and Lactobacillus</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>A blend of Bifidobacterium and Lactobacillus</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        To participate in the study you must:

          -  Be age 18 to 75 years

          -  Have a BMI ≥ 25

          -  Be willing to receive random assignment to probiotic or placebo supplementation

          -  Be willing to and able to complete the Informed Consent Form in English

          -  Be willing to complete questionnaires, records, and diaries associated with the study
             and to complete all study visits

          -  Be committed to losing weight over the 12-week study period

          -  Be willing to discontinue consumption of fermented foods or probiotics (e.g., yogurts
             with live, active cultures or supplements).

          -  Be willing to provide a social security number (SS#) to receive study payment? Note:
             the subject can still participate if unwilling to provide SS#, but no financial
             reimbursement can be provided.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        To participate in the study you must NOT:

          -  Have used another investigational product within 3 months of enrolling in the study

          -  Be pregnant or breast-feeding or planning on becoming pregnant in the next 18 months

          -  Be allergic to milk, soy, or yeast

          -  Have gained or lost at least 10 lbs in the previous 3 months

          -  Have had uncontrolled angina (severe chest pain) within the past 6 months

          -  Have insulin-dependent diabetes (oral medications are not exclusionary)

          -  Use weight-loss medications

          -  Have had cancer treatment (radiation, chemotherapy, or surgery) within the past 6
             months or any other treatment or condition known to weaken the immune system (e.g.,
             systemic corticosteroids or HIV/AIDS)

          -  Be currently being treated for or have any of the following physician-diagnosed
             diseases or conditions: inflammatory bowel disease, celiac disease, short bowel
             syndrome, or any other malabsorptive syndrome?

          -  Have any physical condition deemed likely to significantly interfere with your ability
             to participate in a lifestyle intervention involving eating and physical activity
             changes

          -  Be currently participating in Weight Watcher's or another weight loss program
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bobbi Langkamp-Henken, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 1, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 8, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 8, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 8, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 9, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Probiotics</keyword>
  <keyword>Weight loss</keyword>
  <keyword>Body composition</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Body Weight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

