<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02464098</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EPIGUT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02464098</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Epidemiology of Diarrheal Diseases in Pediatric Oncology Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Epidemiology of Diarrheal Diseases in Pediatric Oncology Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Diarrhea is a common problem in the pediatric population. Children with cancer are especially
      at increased risk for gastrointestinal infection-related morbidity and mortality due to their
      ongoing immunosuppression. However, the epidemiology of diarrheal illnesses in
      immunocompromised children is poorly understood. In the past, many or most cases of
      gastroenteritis have gone undiagnosed, largely due to a lack of sensitive diagnostic tests
      and a presumption that a large proportion of cases are due to treatment, rather than
      infections. The availability of new diagnostic tests that detect many gastrointestinal
      pathogens simultaneously offers the first opportunity to gain a comprehensive picture of the
      causes of infectious diarrhea in children with cancer.

      Researchers at St. Jude Children's Research Hospital want to learn about the epidemiology of
      diarrheal diseases in pediatric oncology patients utilizing broadly multiplexed, automated
      PCR.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study plans to enroll participants in two groups:

        -  GROUP 1: Participants with hematologic malignancies or solid tumors.

             -  Participants who agree to take part in this research study will have stool samples
                collected at diagnosis (baseline sample) and each month thereafter for 12 months
                from the time of enrollment. Stool samples will be screened for different types of
                microbes that may be present. For participants who develop diarrhea during these 12
                months, three additional stool samples will be collected on Day 0, Day 7 and Day
                14; two blood samples and mid-turbinate nasal swab will be collected as well on Day
                0 and Day 7 of the first observed diarrheal episode to screen for additional
                microbes that may be the cause of the diarrhea.

        -  GROUP 2: Participants who are hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT) patients.

             -  Participants who agree to take part in this research study will have stool samples
                collected within one week prior to conditional chemotherapy (baseline sample) and
                weekly thereafter for a total of 16 weeks (pre- and early post-engraftment
                periods), followed by monthly for 8 months. Stool samples will be screened for
                different types of microbes that may be present. For participants who develop
                diarrhea, three additional stool samples will be collected on Day 0, Day 7 and Day
                14; two blood samples and mid-turbinate nasal swab will be collected as well on Day
                0 and Day 7 of the first observed diarrheal episode to screen for additional
                microbes that may be the cause of the diarrhea. For GROUP 2 participants, two
                diarrheal episodes will be studied per patient: the first diarrheal episode during
                the pre-engraftment period, and the first diarrheal episode during the
                post-engraftment period.

      Participants with a change in cancer treatment plan enrolled on study: Group 1 participants
      who experience a change in their cancer treatment plan necessitating an allogeneic stem cell
      transplant will be taken off study for group 1 and offered the opportunity to consent to
      group 2 Participants who chooses to then enroll on group 2 will complete the 12-month study
      requirements as defined in the protocol for group 2 participants.

      General health information from participant medical records and other health-related
      information about symptoms will also be obtained at the time of collection of the samples.

      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE:

        -  To assess the prevalence of microbial pathogens in the stool of pediatric oncology
           patients with diarrheal illness.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

        -  To describe the clinical course, symptomatology, morbidity and mortality associated with
           diarrheal diseases in pediatric oncology patients at St. Jude Children's Research
           Hospital.

        -  Evaluate the performance of the multiplex polymerase chain reaction (PCR) assay for the
           diagnosis of infectious diarrhea in comparison to the standard of care methods.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 19, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency by pathogen type of infectious pathogens</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistics of infectious pathogens identified in diarrheal stools from PCR testing will be summarized.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion by pathogen type of infectious pathogens</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistics of infectious pathogens identified in diarrheal stools from PCR testing will be summarized.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistics of symptoms, clinical course, morbidity and mortality in patients with diarrhea will be summarized.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Descriptive statistics of symptoms, clinical course, morbidity and mortality in patients with diarrhea will be summarized.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of infectious pathogens identified by multiplex PCR assay versus standard tests</measure>
    <time_frame>at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Infectious pathogens of diarrheal stools identified by the multiplex PCR assay will be compared descriptively against those identified by standard testing, and McNemar's test will be applied.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Diarrhea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants with diagnosis of hematological malignancy or solid tumor.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      All stool, blood and respiratory samples will be saved frozen for future testing.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Participants will be pediatric oncology patients including patients with recent diagnoses
        of solid tumor or hematologic malignancy, or patients undergoing hematopoietic stem cell
        transplant.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Equal to or less than 18 years of age.

          -  GROUP 1: Patients diagnosed in the preceding 14 days with confirmed diagnosis at St.
             Jude of a new hematological malignancy or solid tumor in the preceding 14 days, OR
             patients diagnosed with a new hematological malignancy or solid tumor and has
             initiated chemotherapy within the previous 72 hours from enrollment.

          -  GROUP 2: Patients scheduled to receive conditioning for hematopoietic stem cell
             transplant (HSCT) in the subsequent 7 days.

          -  Parent or legal guardian willing and able to give informed consent and comply with
             study requirements.

          -  Anticipated to be available for all study visits.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients from GROUP 1 (diagnosed in the preceding 14 days with a new hematological
             malignancy or solid tumor) who underwent HSCT in the previous 12 months.

          -  Has any condition that would, in the opinion of the investigator, place the subject at
             an unacceptable risk of injury or render the subject unable to meet the requirements
             of the protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Randall T. Hayden, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Randall T. Hayden, MD</last_name>
    <phone>866-278-5833</phone>
    <email>referralinfo@stjude.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Randall T. Hayden, MD</last_name>
      <phone>866-278-5833</phone>
      <email>referralinfo@stjude.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Randall T. Hayden, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stjude.org</url>
    <description>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stjude.org/protocols</url>
    <description>Clinical Trials Open at St. Jude</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 3, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 3, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 8, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Hematological Malignancies</keyword>
  <keyword>Solid Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation (HSCT)</keyword>
  <keyword>Childhood Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diarrhea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

