<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02466022</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>U of S BIO 15-76</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02466022</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dexmedetomidine for Sedation in Total Knee Replacements</brief_title>
  <official_title>Does Single Dose Dexmedetomidine for Procedural Sedation Reduce Post-operative Pain in Total Knee Arthroplasty? A Randomized Control Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Saskatchewan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Saskatchewan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Dexmedetomidine has demonstrated benefits both in sedation, and post-operative pain control,
      with less respiratory depression than other common sedatives. Traditionally, dexmedetomidine
      has been used with a large loading dose and infusion, which has been known to cause
      dose-dependent negative side-effects (Abdallah et al., 2013). Single dose dexmedetomidine
      produces less negative side-effects, but still effective sedation and reduced post-operative
      pain (Jung et al., 2013). There is evidence for its benefits with general anesthesia but only
      a few studies exist investigating its benefits when administered for sedation purposes with
      spinal anesthesia, and no studies primarily examine post-operative opioid consumption. The
      investigators hypothesize that single dose dexmedetomidine for procedural sedation will
      reduce opioid consumption after total knee arthroplasty (TKA).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators plan a randomized control trial.

      Sample. Based on a literature and a previous study by the investigators team (RQHR
      #13-80/USask Bio #13-232), average reduction in opioid consumption for dexmedetomidine bolus
      and infusion is 50%. Less data exists for single dose. However two randomized control trials
      (Kaya et al., 2010; Hong et al., 2012) reduced consumption frequency by 55% and 45%, using
      0.5ug/kg and 1.0ug/kg respectively. A meta-analysis demonstrated a mean difference of -10mg
      vs -21mg in opioid consumption for bolus studies vs bolus and infusion studies at 24 hours
      (Schnabel et. al 2013). A reduction of 50% was recently seen in a study conducted earlier by
      the investigators center at 24hours with a bolus and infusion (RQHR #13-80/USask Bio
      #13-232). An expected Patient Controlled Analgesia (PCA) consumption at 24hours for total
      knee arthroplasty is 27mg with a standard deviation of 19mg (Paul et. al, 2013). Using this
      information, it was decided 40% reduction in opioid consumption at 24hours could be expected
      and represent a clinically significant result. Subsequent power calculation required a sample
      size of 50 (25 per arm) to demonstrate a 40% reduction in opioid consumption at 24 hours,
      with a study power of 80% and P-value under 0.05.

      Ethics. Ethics approval was obtained from the University of Saskatchewan Biomedical Research
      Ethics Board, and from the Regina Qu'Appelle Health Region Research Ethics Board.

      Patients will be identified by one of the investigators through the daily surgical slate to
      which they already have access for patient care.

      Informed written consent will be obtained from 50 patients on the Same-Day Admission Unit by
      one of the investigators not involved in the patient's care.

      Randomization and Allocation. Following informed consent by one of the investigators,
      patients will be randomized into one of two groups based on a 1:1 ratio. Sealed envelopes
      will be prepared by the Department of Anesthesia's Research Coordinator using a web-based
      random number generator, and opened by a researcher (Dr. Maslany or Dr. Vipulananthan)
      independent of the clinical team. The drug will be prepared by a resident or nurse not
      involved in the patient's case; this staff member will vary depending on who is available
      when the need arises. Surgeons, anesthetists, ancillary staff and patients will be blinded to
      patient allocation.

      Study Drug. The study drug (which does not require refrigeration) will be kept locked in the
      Anesthesia office at the Regina General Hospital. It has been arranged that Pharmacy will
      deliver the study drug in a batch, and the investigators will use a tracking sheet to account
      for the 25 vials that are required for the study. Both Dexmedetomidine and Normal saline are
      colorless and thus unrecognizable by either the patient or the anesthetist. There is no risk
      to the patient of delay in receiving midazolam at an appropriate time once the case is
      started. If the patient asks for more sedation at any time, it will be provided.

      Procedure. Prior to entering the operating room, all patients will be familiarized with the
      Numerical Rating Scale (NRS) and instructed how to use patient controlled analgesia and
      instructions to press the PCA demand button if their NRS pain is 4 or greater. All patients
      will receive a 500cc bolus of lactated ringer's solution intravascular volume loading during
      spinal anesthetic delivery. Monitors include electrocardiography, non-invasive blood pressure
      measurement, pulse oximetry, and end-tidal carbon dioxide concentration with nasal prongs for
      monitoring respiration. Oxygen will be delivered at 3 litres per min.

      Using a computer-generated randomization table by blinded staff, patients will be randomly
      allocated 1:1 to receive 0.5ug/kg of dexmedetomidine (experimental group) or same volume of
      normal saline (control group) over 10 min. The current standard of care, though variable,
      entails patients receiving a midazolam bolus for sedation during the operation, if the
      patient requests sedation. For patients who request sedation, a syringe of dexmedetomidine or
      saline will be run as a single dose infused over 10 minutes. However, a midazolam bolus (0-4
      mg IV) will be available at the anesthetist's discretion to achieve a moderate sedation score
      as defined by the American Society of Anesthesiology.

      Bupivicaine 0.75% 1.7cc (12.75mg) and fentanyl 10 micrograms will be administered
      intrathecally for analgesia 5 min after infusion has been completed.

      The level of sensory block will be assessed, as per standard care, with pinpricks and ice
      cubes. Motor block will be assessed with a modified Bromage scale (0=no paralysis; 1=unable
      to raise extended leg; 2=unable to flex knee; 3=unable to flex ankle) (Bromage et al. 1964).

      Rescue phenylephrine and ephedrine will be available to the anesthesiologist to use at their
      discretion for hypotension.

      Patients will be discharged from post-anesthetic care unit, as per standard practice, once
      discharge criteria met as per modified Aldrete scoring system. For Total Knee Arthroplasty,
      the average PACU stay would be 45-60min. Patients will be kept until they meet the
      requirements of the modified Aldrete score and no longer, as per standard care.

      Data collection. Baseline characteristics will be collected by Dr. Vipulananthan from the
      patients' charts, including: age, weight, height, sex, duration of surgery, baseline heart
      rate and blood pressure. Primary and secondary outcome measures will be collected, including:
      total morphine consumption at 6, 12, and 24hours, time to first morphine request, pain scores
      (Numerical Rating Scale) at 6, 12, and 24 hours at rest, intraoperative midazolam use, time
      of readiness of discharge from the post-anesthetic care unit, intraoperative and
      post-anesthetic care unit hemodynamics, duration of sensory and motor blockade by
      two-dermatome sensory regression, recovery of L2 dermatome sensation and knee flexion,
      adverse opioid effects of nausea, vomiting, pruritis, urinary retention, post-operative
      shivering, and patient satisfaction.

      Analysis. Statistical methods will include multivariate analysis of variance and Mann-Whitney
      U-test to compare groups. There will be no crossover between groups and results will be
      analysed on an intention to treat basis. Sub-group analyses of Type II diabetic patients will
      be analyzed for insulin resistance. Statistical significance will be accepted at a
      probability level of under 0.05.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total Morphine Consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Hours</time_frame>
    <description>mg of IV morphine administered via Patient Controlled Analgesia. Patient will be told to deliver morphine dose for pain =&gt;4 from a numerical rating scale for pain from 0 to 10</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Morphine Consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12 and 24 hours, and time to first morphine request</time_frame>
    <description>mg of IV morphine administered via Patient Controlled Analgesia. Patient will be told to deliver morphine dose for pain =&gt;4 from a numerical rating scale for pain from 0 to 10</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>6, 12 and 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>rated on a numerical rating scale for pain from 0 to 10</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative Midazolam</measure>
    <time_frame>During the operation</time_frame>
    <description>mg usage of IV midazolam for rescue sedation if patient requests more</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of readiness of discharge from the post-anesthetic care unit</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately post-operation, average 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>minutes spent in PACU until criteria met by modified Aldrete Score</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative heartrate</measure>
    <time_frame>During the operation</time_frame>
    <description>Lowest heart rate recorded in beats per minute</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of sensory blockade two-dermatome sensory regression</measure>
    <time_frame>During the operation, and immediately post-operation, average 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Time in Minutes for recovery of 2 dermatomes of sensation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse opioid effects of nausea</measure>
    <time_frame>First 24 hours post-operation</time_frame>
    <description>Binary yes/no if patient experienced nausea</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>First 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>rated 0-4</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first morphine request</measure>
    <time_frame>first 24 hours post-operation</time_frame>
    <description>Time in minutes to first morphine request by patient</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>During the operation</time_frame>
    <description>Lowest systolic blood pressure recorded in mmHg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative heartrate</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after operation in PACU recovery, average 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Lowest heartrate in PACU recorded in beats per minute</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after operation in PACU recovery, average 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Lowest systolic blood pressure recorded in mmHg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Motor blockade</measure>
    <time_frame>During the operation, and immediately post-operation, average 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Time in minutes until patient regains knee flexion</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse opioid effect of vomiting</measure>
    <time_frame>First 24 hours post-operation</time_frame>
    <description>Binary yes/no if patient experienced vomiting</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse opioid effect of constipation</measure>
    <time_frame>First 24 hours post-operation</time_frame>
    <description>Binary yes/no if patient experienced constipation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse anesthetic effect of shivering</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after operation in PACU recovery, average 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>Binary yes/no if patient experienced shivering</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse opioid effect of pruritus</measure>
    <time_frame>First 24 hours post-operation</time_frame>
    <description>Binary yes/no if patient experienced pruritus</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse opioid effect of urinary retention</measure>
    <time_frame>First 24 hours post-operation</time_frame>
    <description>Binary yes/no if patient experienced urinary retention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Post-operative Pain for Total Knee Arthroplasty</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dexmedetomidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive one 0.5ug/kg bolus of Dexmedetomidine over 10 minutes for sedation prior to spinal anesthetic (12.75mg of heavy Bupivicaine and 10ug of Fentanyl) and 0-4mg of Midazolam for rescue sedation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive 0.1cc/kg Normal Saline bolus delivered over 10 minutes for control arm prior to spinal anesthetic (12.75mg of heavy Bupivicaine and 10ug of Fentanyl) and 0-4mg of Midazolam for rescue sedation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexmedetomidine</intervention_name>
    <description>Bolus dose prior to spinal anesthetic</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dexmedetomidine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Precedex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bupivicaine</intervention_name>
    <description>Intrathecal hyperbaric bupivicaine 12.75mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dexmedetomidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Marcaine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Normal Saline</intervention_name>
    <description>Bolus 0.1cc/kg Normal Saline over 10 min</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dexmedetomidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Normosol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fentanyl</intervention_name>
    <description>Intrathecal Fentanyl 10ug</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dexmedetomidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Midazolam</intervention_name>
    <description>0-4mg of IV Midazolam prn for rescue sedation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dexmedetomidine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Versed</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  adults over 18 years undergoing elective unilateral primary total knee arthroplasty
             under spinal anesthesia with an American Society of Anesthesiologists physical status
             class I to III.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  will include contraindication to:

               -  Dexmedetomidine,

               -  morphine, or

               -  Spinal Anesthesia,

          -  as well as anybody with chronic pain being treated by opioids prior to the operation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jurgen Maslany, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Regina</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Regina Qu'Appelle Health Region</name>
      <address>
        <city>Regina</city>
        <state>Saskatchewan</state>
        <zip>S4S 0A5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abdallah FW, Abrishami A, Brull R. The facilitatory effects of intravenous dexmedetomidine on the duration of spinal anesthesia: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Anesth Analg. 2013 Jul;117(1):271-8. doi: 10.1213/ANE.0b013e318290c566. Epub 2013 Apr 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23632057</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jung SH, Lee SK, Lim KJ, Park EY, Kang MH, Lee JM, Lee JJ, Hwang SM, Hong SJ. The effects of single-dose intravenous dexmedetomidine on hyperbaric bupivacaine spinal anesthesia. J Anesth. 2013 Jun;27(3):380-4. doi: 10.1007/s00540-012-1541-0. Epub 2013 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>23307164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaya FN, Yavascaoglu B, Turker G, Yildirim A, Gurbet A, Mogol EB, Ozcan B. Intravenous dexmedetomidine, but not midazolam, prolongs bupivacaine spinal anesthesia. Can J Anaesth. 2010 Jan;57(1):39-45. doi: 10.1007/s12630-009-9231-6. Epub 2009 Dec 29.</citation>
    <PMID>20039221</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hong JY, Kim WO, Yoon Y, Choi Y, Kim SH, Kil HK. Effects of intravenous dexmedetomidine on low-dose bupivacaine spinal anaesthesia in elderly patients. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2012 Mar;56(3):382-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1399-6576.2011.02614.x. Epub 2012 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22220945</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schnabel A, Meyer-Frießem CH, Reichl SU, Zahn PK, Pogatzki-Zahn EM. Is intraoperative dexmedetomidine a new option for postoperative pain treatment? A meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Pain. 2013 Jul;154(7):1140-9. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2013.03.029. Epub 2013 Mar 27.</citation>
    <PMID>23706726</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paul JE, Nantha-Aree M, Buckley N, Cheng J, Thabane L, Tidy A, DeBeer J, Winemaker M, Wismer D, Punthakee D, Avram V. Gabapentin does not improve multimodal analgesia outcomes for total knee arthroplasty: a randomized controlled trial. Can J Anaesth. 2013 May;60(5):423-31. doi: 10.1007/s12630-013-9902-1. Epub 2013 Mar 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23479393</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 1, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 8, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 9, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 14, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 14, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 15, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Saskatchewan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nirupan Vipulanathan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Anesthesiology Resident</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bupivacaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fentanyl</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Midazolam</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexmedetomidine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

