<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02467114</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>036/15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02467114</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Interactions Between Attentional Networks and Their Influence on Perception</brief_title>
  <acronym>AtNet</acronym>
  <official_title>Interactions Between Attentional Networks and Their Influence on Perception: a Project in Healthy Subjects and Hemispatial Neglect Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Inselspital, Berne</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Bern</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Luzerner Kantonsspital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Inselspital, Berne</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Attention can be defined as the preparedness to rapidly and accurately respond to stimuli
      coming from the investigators environment and to effectively select between relevant and
      irrelevant information. According to a current model, visual attentional control is based on
      two separate groups of brain regions, so called brain networks. These networks control
      different attentional aspects (e.g., spatial/non-spatial attention) and they interact with
      each other. A disruption of these interactions can lead to attentional disorders such as
      hemispatial neglect. Patients with hemispatial neglect have difficulties directing their
      attention to the left visual field and they act as though the latter does not exist.

      To date, the interactions between the two attentional networks are poorly understood. The aim
      of this study consists in further clarifying different aspects of these interactions and
      their influence on visual perception in healthy participants and in patients with hemispatial
      neglect. Transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) will be the principal method applied in this
      study. TMS is a painless and non-invasive method, with which the activity of brain areas can
      be influenced temporarily. This allows us to draw conclusions regarding the functions and
      interactions of these brain areas.

      This study is designed to have a significant impact on the basic understanding of attentional
      control in the human brain and it can benefit the comprehension and treatment of attentional
      disorders, such as hemispatial neglect.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background

      Attention can be defined as the preparedness to rapidly and accurately respond to stimuli
      coming from the investigators environment and to effectively select between relevant and
      irrelevant information. Attention is a complex cognitive function based on multiple
      components. A recent model postulates that attentional control in the brain is based on two
      discrete neural networks. The ventral (temporo-parietal - ventral frontal) network controls
      non-spatial aspects of attention, such as alertness and vigilance, and stimulus detection and
      reorientation in both hemifields. This network is lateralized towards the right hemisphere
      and plays a role as a 'circuit-breaker'. The dorsal (superior parietal - dorsal frontal)
      network controls spatial attentional shifts, is largely top-down driven, and substantially
      overlaps with eye movement control. This network is not functionally lateralized, each
      hemisphere containing dynamic topographical maps of the contralateral space. Moreover, the
      dorsal networks of the two hemispheres compete to direct attention to the contralateral
      hemispace, thereby exerting reciprocal inhibition.

      Hemispatial neglect - the failure to detect, orient, or respond to stimuli located in the
      contralesional side of space - has been interpreted in terms of pathological changes in the
      interaction between the two attentional networks. Neglect is very common after cerebral
      lesions of the right hemisphere, usually affecting the ventral attentional network. The
      structurally intact right dorsal network would thus receive a weakened input from the right
      ventral network. The ensuing imbalance in the inhibition between the dorsal networks of the
      two hemispheres would then result in the rightward bias in attentional allocation, typically
      observed in hemispatial neglect.

      However, little is known regarding the interactions between ventral and dorsal attentional
      networks and their influence on perception, and the greatest part of the evidence has been
      acquired through correlational approaches. The aim of this study is to further elucidate
      different aspects of these interactions and to investigate their influence on spatial and
      non-spatial attentional performance and on visual perception.

      Objective

      A first objective consists in further elucidating how and through which anatomical structures
      the ventral and the dorsal attentional networks interact. A second objective concerns how the
      interplay of dorsal and ventral attentional networks influences visual perception, in
      particular in cases in which visual stimuli are ambiguous.

      Methods

      Transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS) is the principal method applied in this study. TMS is
      a non-invasive, painless method which is able to influence cortical areas directing attention
      in an interference approach and to thus establish causal relationships. Furthermore, TMS, in
      combination with the measurement of motor evoked potentials (MEP), allows for the assessment
      of the excitability of cortico-cortical circuits.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cortical excitability, as measured by motor evoked potentials (MEPs)</measure>
    <time_frame>During or within 1 hour after application</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Spatial attentional performance, as measured by cognitive testing</measure>
    <time_frame>During or within 1 hour after application</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of perceptual switches</measure>
    <time_frame>During or within 1 hour after application</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of dominance phases of perceptual switches</measure>
    <time_frame>During or within 1 hour after application</time_frame>
    <description>Measured in seconds</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alertness level, as measured subjectively by a visual analogue scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>During or 1 hour after application</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alertness level, as measured objectively by cognitive testing</measure>
    <time_frame>During or 1 hour after application</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spatial bias of attentional allocation, as measured by standardised paper-pencil neuropsychological tests</measure>
    <time_frame>During or 1 hour after application</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spatial bias of attentional allocation, as measured by free visual exploration with eye movement measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>During or 1 hour after application</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">214</enrollment>
  <condition>Hemispatial Neglect</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All study participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Stimulation with TMS, a sham coil &amp; no intervention</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS)</intervention_name>
    <description>This method will be applied to measure cortical excitability and as an interference approach; real TMS stimulation will be compared with sham stimulation and no stimulation</description>
    <arm_group_label>All study participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham coil stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Stimulation with a sham coil as a comparison</description>
    <arm_group_label>All study participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control without stimulation</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>All study participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent

          -  Healthy participants:

          -  Age 18-80 years

          -  Neurologically healthy, i.e., with no documented or present neurological disease or
             brain injury

          -  normal or corrected-to-normal visual acuity

          -  Patients:

          -  Age 18-80 years

          -  Showing signs of left hemispatial neglect after a right-hemispheric brain lesion, as
             assessed by previous neuropsychological testing and clinical judgment

          -  Normal or corrected-to-normal visual acuity

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Healthy participants:

          -  Any instable medical condition, in particular epilepsy (past or present, including
             seizures or febrile convulsions)

          -  Any surgical intervention to the brain

          -  Implanted medical devices (e.g., cochlear implants, infusion pumps, neurostimulators,
             pacemakers)

          -  Presence of metal in the region of the head (excluding fixed dental implants such as
             tooth fillings or fixed dental braces)

          -  Drug or alcohol abuse

          -  Intake of any medication that is likely to lower seizure threshold

          -  For female participants: pregnancy or breast feeding or intention to become pregnant
             during the course of the experiment. All participants of childbearing potential will
             be asked to take a pregnancy test.

          -  Patients:

          -  Any instable medical condition, in particular epilepsy (past or present, including
             seizures or febrile convulsions)

          -  Implanted medical devices (e.g., cochlear implants, infusion pumps, neurostimulators,
             pacemakers)

          -  Presence of metal in the region of the head (excluding fixed dental implants such as
             tooth fillings or fixed dental braces)

          -  Drug or alcohol abuse

          -  Intake of any medication that is likely to lower seizure threshold

          -  For female participants: pregnancy or breast feeding or intention to become pregnant
             during the course of the experiment. All participants of childbearing potential will
             be asked to take a pregnancy test
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>René M. Müri, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Neurology, Inselspital, Bern University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas Nyffeler, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Center for Neurology and Neurorehabilitation, Luzerner Kantonsspital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>René M. Müri, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
    <phone>+41 31 632 30 81</phone>
    <email>rene.mueri@insel.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Dario Cazzoli, Dr. phil.</last_name>
    <phone>+41 31 632 46 97</phone>
    <email>dario.cazzoli@artorg.unibe.ch</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Division of Cognitive and Restorative Neurology, Department of Neurology, Inselspital, Bern University Hospital; Gerontechnology and Rehabilitation Group, ARTORG Center for Biomedical Engineering Research, University of Bern</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bern</city>
        <zip>3010</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>René M Müri, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
      <phone>+41 31 632 30 81</phone>
      <email>rene.mueri@insel.ch</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Dario Cazzoli, Dr. phil.</last_name>
      <phone>+41 31 632 46 97</phone>
      <email>dario.cazzoli@artorg.unibe.ch</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>René M Müri, Prof. Dr. med.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corbetta M, Patel G, Shulman GL. The reorienting system of the human brain: from environment to theory of mind. Neuron. 2008 May 8;58(3):306-24. doi: 10.1016/j.neuron.2008.04.017. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18466742</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corbetta M, Shulman GL. Control of goal-directed and stimulus-driven attention in the brain. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2002 Mar;3(3):201-15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11994752</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corbetta M, Shulman GL. Spatial neglect and attention networks. Annu Rev Neurosci. 2011;34:569-99. doi: 10.1146/annurev-neuro-061010-113731. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21692662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koch G, Oliveri M, Cheeran B, Ruge D, Lo Gerfo E, Salerno S, Torriero S, Marconi B, Mori F, Driver J, Rothwell JC, Caltagirone C. Hyperexcitability of parietal-motor functional connections in the intact left-hemisphere of patients with neglect. Brain. 2008 Dec;131(Pt 12):3147-55. doi: 10.1093/brain/awn273. Epub 2008 Oct 22.</citation>
    <PMID>18948300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sack AT. Using non-invasive brain interference as a tool for mimicking spatial neglect in healthy volunteers. Restor Neurol Neurosci. 2010;28(4):485-97. doi: 10.3233/RNN-2010-0568. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20714073</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 27, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 9, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Perceptual Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

