<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02464748</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17165</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>26675465</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>17022</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02464748</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Telehealth in Motor Neurone Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>TiM</acronym>
  <official_title>Telehealth in Motor Neurone Disease: A Single Centre, Randomised Controlled Feasibility and Pilot Study of the Use of the TiM Telehealth System to Deliver Highly Specialised Care in Motor Neurone Disease at a Distance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Sheffield</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Motor neurone disease (MND) is a rare but debilitating neurological condition that causes
      paralysis of the body's muscles leading to severe disability and eventually death. Patients
      often struggle to travel the long distances to specialist clinics to receive the care they
      require whilst this expert care is often unavailable in the community. Telehealth has the
      potential to enable a specialist team to monitor the health and wellbeing of patients and
      their carers whilst they are at home. This could improve the patient's health, improve the
      quality of life of both patients and their carers, and lead to more effective use of health
      resources.

      This is a randomised controlled pilot study that will involve 40 patients who are cared for
      by the Sheffield Motor Neurone Disease care centre and their main informal carer (a total of
      80 participants). Half of the participants will use the telehealth system for a minimum of
      six months and maximum of eighteen months and information will be collected from patients,
      carers and their care team. This will include collecting clinical outcome measures, health
      resource use and the opinions and experience of using the system. All participants will
      continue to receive their usual care.

      This is a pilot study. It aims to determine the feasibility and acceptability of the
      telehealth system to patients, carers and their health care providers. It also aims to
      determine how a larger trial could successfully evaluate the clinical and cost-effectiveness
      of the system.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      MND is often referred to as amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) or Lou Gehrig's disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility and acceptability of using the telehealth system from interviews</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Recruitment rate, retention rate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">77</enrollment>
  <condition>Motor Neuron Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients and their primary carer will use a weekly telehealth system. This involves a series of questions on a tablet computer that is transmitted to their regional MND care centre for review and action.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TiM telehealth arm</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patient Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients aged 18 years or over who have attended the MND clinic at the Royal
             Hallamshire Hospital, Sheffield.

          -  Patients with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis diagnosed by a consultant neurologist with
             symptom onset within the last three years.

             o Or

          -  Patients with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, primary muscular atrophy or progressive
             lateral sclerosis diagnosed by a consultant neurologist with a deterioration in their
             condition as evidenced by a deterioration in the ALS functional rating score
             (ALSFRS-R) by at least two points during the previous 18 months.

          -  Live within 120 minute drive from Sheffield

        Patient Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients attend another MND care centre in the UK.

          -  Significant impairment in decision making capacity preventing informed consent by the
             subject due to a major mental disorder including fronto-temporal dementia.

          -  Patient unable to use the TiM system due to physical, intellectual or language
             difficulties and unwilling to permit carer to operate it on their behalf. Patients
             will be asked to complete two questions used within the TiM system, with, or without
             the help to their carer to verify their ability to use the system.

          -  The patient has no eligible informal carer willing to participate in the trial

          -  Insufficient mobile telephone reception in the patients' home to use the TiM system.

          -  Any other major impairment that may affect their ability to participate in the study

        Carer inclusion criteria

          -  Age 18 years or older

          -  Person identified by the patient as the major provider of informal care (emotional
             and/or practical support) to the patient and provides more than one hour per week of
             unpaid care

          -  Carer willing to allow data they provide during the trial to be shared by the research
             team with their own doctor in the event of serious clinical need.

        Carer exclusion criteria

          -  Significant decision making capacity preventing informed consent due to a major mental
             disorder.

          -  Carer unable to use the TiM system due to physical, intellectual or language
             difficulties. Carers will be asked to complete two questions used within the TiM
             system to verify their ability to use the system.

          -  Inability to participate in the study due to other major physical or mental illness or
             language difficulties.

          -  Professional carers receiving direct payment for their services.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sheffield Institute for Translational Neurosciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sheffield</city>
        <zip>S10 2HQ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 13, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 3, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 8, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 26, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 26, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 28, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Motor Neuron Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

