<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02465853</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CMRPG8C0771</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02465853</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hemiplegic Shoulder Pain and Rotator Cuff Injuries</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Outcome in Subacute Stroke Patients With Hemiplegic Shoulder Pain and Rotator Cuff Injuries After Hyaluronic Acid Injection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hemiplegic shoulder pain (HSP) is one of most complications after stroke. HSP would impede
      rehabilitation programs and the motor recovery of affected upper extremity. HSP was
      associated with impaired daily life activities and prolong hospital stay after stroke.
      Therefore, effective managements is important in stroke patients with HSP. Rotator cuffs
      injuries are related to HSP. Clinically, hyaluronic acid (HA) is used for rotator cuff
      injuries. Previous researchers reported that HA could provide pain relief, improved motion,
      and increased daily activities. In this study, fifty subacute stoke patients will be
      enrolled. These patients will be allocated into group A and B randomly. The patients in group
      A received HA injection while patients in group B received normal saline injection. Patients
      from both groups received injection for 3 times each on the 1st, 2nd, 3rd week. All the
      patients will still receive rehabilitation programs of physical therapy and occupational
      therapy. Each patient will receive physical, sonographic examinations, and stroke Specific
      Quality of Life Scale (SSQOL). The aims of this study are to investigate the benefits of HA
      injection on pain relief, motor function recovery, and life quality in subacute stroke
      patients with HSP before and after HA injection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In this study, a two-year program is expected to receive a total cases of 50 subacute stroke
      patients with hemiplegic shoulder pain. The patients are randomly divided into two groups. In
      experimental group, the patients (25 people) will accept the shoulder hyaluronic acid
      injections for pain management. In control group, the patients (25 people) will receive 0.9%
      physiological saline injections. All participants will receive total 3 times shoulder
      injections at the 1st, 2nd, 3rd week. Except shoulder injections, stroke patients may receive
      regular rehabilitation program including physical therapy and occupational therapy. All
      measurements including shoulder sonography, physical examinations, and the questionnaire for
      life quality (SSQOL) will be conducted before the first injection, after completing shoulder
      injection, and 3/6 months after shoulder injection. Shoulder sonography is used to
      investigate shoulder soft tissue condition of hemiplegic shoulder including biceps tendon,
      infraspinatus tendon, supraspinatus tendon, subscapularis tendon, and subdeltoid bursa in
      this study. The physical examination includes all shoulder motion plane, shoulder sensory
      (light touch, pinprick, and position sense) and motor function (Fual Meyer scale and
      brunnstrom motor recovery stage), shoulder spasticity measured by modified Ashworth scale,
      and hemiplegic shoulder pain by visual analog scale. The investigators use Stroke Specific
      Quality of Life Scale to evaluate the quality of life in stroke patients with HSP. In this
      study, the investigators want to explore the short and long term effects of HA injection on
      pain relief, motor function recovery, and life quality in stroke patients with HSP.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>the change from baseline on hemiplegic shoulder sonography</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week , 4th week, 3 month and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>use sonographic to investigate the soft tissues surrounding the hemiplegic shoulder</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>shoulder range of motion</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week , 4th week, 3 month and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>goniometer Shoulder abduction 0-180, flex 0-180, ext 0-60, internal rotation 0-90, external rotation 0-90</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week , 4th week, 3 month and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Stroke Specific Quality of Life Scale questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>shoulder sensory</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week , 4th week, 3 month and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>light touch, pin prick, position sense</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>shoulder pain</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week , 4th week, 3 month and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>visual analog scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>shoulder spasticity</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week , 4th week, 3 month and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>modified Ashworth scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>motor function</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week , 4th week, 3 month and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Fual Meyer scale, brunnstrom motor recovery stage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Shoulder Pain</condition>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Rotator Cuff Injuries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Injection 0.9% Physiological saline solution&lt;2.5 ml and physical therapy and occupational therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hyaluronic Acid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>injection Hyaluronic Acid 2.5ml and physical therapy and occupational therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hyaluronic Acid</intervention_name>
    <description>Injection Hyaluronic Acid in the experimental group</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hyaluronic Acid</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>sodium hyaluronate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physiological saline solution</intervention_name>
    <description>Injection 0.9% Physiological saline solution&lt;1.0 ml</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>saline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>physical therapy and occupational therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>rehabilitation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Hyaluronic Acid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The subacute stroke patients with hemiplegic shoulder pain

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  previous shoulder pain or injury in recent 6 months

          -  local infection near the injection area

          -  shoulder arthropathy

          -  systemic neuromuscular disease;

          -  severe cardiovascular or pulmoanry disease

          -  impaired cognition function leading to poor communication
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Huang Yu Chi, Bachelor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ChangGungMH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kaohsiung</city>
        <zip>833</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Najenson T, Yacubovich E, Pikielni SS. Rotator cuff injury in shoulder joints of hemiplegic patients. Scand J Rehabil Med. 1971;3(3):131-7.</citation>
    <PMID>5156175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Griffin J, Reddin G. Shoulder pain in patients with hemiplegia. A literature review. Phys Ther. 1981 Jul;61(7):1041-5.</citation>
    <PMID>6166017</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bohannon RW, Larkin PA, Smith MB, Horton MG. Shoulder pain in hemiplegia: statistical relationship with five variables. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1986 Aug;67(8):514-6.</citation>
    <PMID>3741075</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Turner-Stokes L, Jackson D. Shoulder pain after stroke: a review of the evidence base to inform the development of an integrated care pathway. Clin Rehabil. 2002 May;16(3):276-98. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12017515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Snels IA, Dekker JH, van der Lee JH, Lankhorst GJ, Beckerman H, Bouter LM. Treating patients with hemiplegic shoulder pain. Am J Phys Med Rehabil. 2002 Feb;81(2):150-60. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11807352</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van Ouwenaller C, Laplace PM, Chantraine A. Painful shoulder in hemiplegia. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1986 Jan;67(1):23-6.</citation>
    <PMID>3942479</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gilmore PE, Spaulding SJ, Vandervoort AA. Hemiplegic shoulder pain: implications for occupational therapy treatment. Can J Occup Ther. 2004 Feb;71(1):36-46. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15015899</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Snels IA, Beckerman H, Twisk JW, Dekker JH, Peter De Koning, Koppe PA, Lankhorst GJ, Bouter LM. Effect of triamcinolone acetonide injections on hemiplegic shoulder pain : A randomized clinical trial. Stroke. 2000 Oct;31(10):2396-401.</citation>
    <PMID>11022070</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parker VM, Wade DT, Langton Hewer R. Loss of arm function after stroke: measurement, frequency, and recovery. Int Rehabil Med. 1986;8(2):69-73.</citation>
    <PMID>3804600</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wanklyn P, Forster A, Young J. Hemiplegic shoulder pain (HSP): natural history and investigation of associated features. Disabil Rehabil. 1996 Oct;18(10):497-501.</citation>
    <PMID>8902421</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roy C SM, Hill L. Shoulder pain in acutely admitted hemiplegics. Clinical Rehabilitation. 1994;8:334-340</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lo SF, Chen SY, Lin HC, Jim YF, Meng NH, Kao MJ. Arthrographic and clinical findings in patients with hemiplegic shoulder pain. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2003 Dec;84(12):1786-91.</citation>
    <PMID>14669184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ikai T, Tei K, Yoshida K, Miyano S, Yonemoto K. Evaluation and treatment of shoulder subluxation in hemiplegia: relationship between subluxation and pain. Am J Phys Med Rehabil. 1998 Sep-Oct;77(5):421-6.</citation>
    <PMID>9798835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Poulin de Courval L, Barsauskas A, Berenbaum B, Dehaut F, Dussault R, Fontaine FS, Labrecque R, Leclerc C, Giroux F. Painful shoulder in the hemiplegic and unilateral neglect. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1990 Aug;71(9):673-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2375673</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ada L, Goddard E, McCully J, Stavrinos T, Bampton J. Thirty minutes of positioning reduces the development of shoulder external rotation contracture after stroke: a randomized controlled trial. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2005 Feb;86(2):230-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15706548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Griffin A, Bernhardt J. Strapping the hemiplegic shoulder prevents development of pain during rehabilitation: a randomized controlled trial. Clin Rehabil. 2006 Apr;20(4):287-95.</citation>
    <PMID>16719027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ada L, Foongchomcheay A, Canning C. Supportive devices for preventing and treating subluxation of the shoulder after stroke. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2005 Jan 25;(1):CD003863. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15674917</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chae J, Yu DT, Walker ME, Kirsteins A, Elovic EP, Flanagan SR, Harvey RL, Zorowitz RD, Frost FS, Grill JH, Fang ZP. Intramuscular electrical stimulation for hemiplegic shoulder pain: a 12-month follow-up of a multiple-center, randomized clinical trial. Am J Phys Med Rehabil. 2005 Nov;84(11):832-42.</citation>
    <PMID>16244520</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chantraine A, Baribeault A, Uebelhart D, Gremion G. Shoulder pain and dysfunction in hemiplegia: effects of functional electrical stimulation. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1999 Mar;80(3):328-31.</citation>
    <PMID>10084443</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shibata Y, Midorikawa K, Emoto G, Naito M. Clinical evaluation of sodium hyaluronate for the treatment of patients with rotator cuff tear. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2001 May-Jun;10(3):209-16.</citation>
    <PMID>11408900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blair B, Rokito AS, Cuomo F, Jarolem K, Zuckerman JD. Efficacy of injections of corticosteroids for subacromial impingement syndrome. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 1996 Nov;78(11):1685-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8934482</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vecchio PC, Hazleman BL, King RH. A double-blind trial comparing subacromial methylprednisolone and lignocaine in acute rotator cuff tendinitis. Br J Rheumatol. 1993 Aug;32(8):743-5.</citation>
    <PMID>8348279</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Plafki C, Steffen R, Willburger RE, Wittenberg RH. Local anaesthetic injection with and without corticosteroids for subacromial impingement syndrome. Int Orthop. 2000;24(1):40-2.</citation>
    <PMID>10774861</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akgün K, Birtane M, Akarirmak U. Is local subacromial corticosteroid injection beneficial in subacromial impingement syndrome? Clin Rheumatol. 2004 Dec;23(6):496-500.</citation>
    <PMID>15278758</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Penning LI, de Bie RA, Walenkamp GH. The effectiveness of injections of hyaluronic acid or corticosteroid in patients with subacromial impingement: a three-arm randomised controlled trial. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2012 Sep;94(9):1246-52. doi: 10.1302/0301-620X.94B9.28750.</citation>
    <PMID>22933498</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iwata H. Pharmacologic and clinical aspects of intraarticular injection of hyaluronate. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 1993 Apr;(289):285-91. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8472428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meloni F, Milia F, Cavazzuti M, Doria C, Lisai P, Profili S, Meloni GB. Clinical evaluation of sodium hyaluronate in the treatment of patients with sopraspinatus tendinosis under echographic guide: experimental study of periarticular injections. Eur J Radiol. 2008 Oct;68(1):170-3. Epub 2007 Dec 21.</citation>
    <PMID>18096343</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chou WY, Ko JY, Wang FS, Huang CC, Wong T, Wang CJ, Chang HE. Effect of sodium hyaluronate treatment on rotator cuff lesions without complete tears: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. J Shoulder Elbow Surg. 2010 Jun;19(4):557-63. doi: 10.1016/j.jse.2009.08.006. Epub 2009 Dec 5.</citation>
    <PMID>19963403</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Byun SD, Park DH, Choi WD, Lee ZI. Subacromial Bursa Injection of Hyaluronate with Steroid in Patients with Peri-articular Shoulder Disorders. Ann Rehabil Med. 2011 Oct;35(5):664-72. doi: 10.5535/arm.2011.35.5.664. Epub 2011 Oct 31.</citation>
    <PMID>22506189</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blaine T, Moskowitz R, Udell J, Skyhar M, Levin R, Friedlander J, Daley M, Altman R. Treatment of persistent shoulder pain with sodium hyaluronate: a randomized, controlled trial. A multicenter study. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2008 May;90(5):970-9. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.F.01116.</citation>
    <PMID>18451387</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Itokazu M, Matsunaga T. Clinical evaluation of high-molecular-weight sodium hyaluronate for the treatment of patients with periarthritis of the shoulder. Clin Ther. 1995 Sep-Oct;17(5):946-55.</citation>
    <PMID>8595646</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ko JY, Wang FS, Huang HY, Wang CJ, Tseng SL, Hsu C. Increased IL-1beta expression and myofibroblast recruitment in subacromial bursa is associated with rotator cuff lesions with shoulder stiffness. J Orthop Res. 2008 Aug;26(8):1090-7. doi: 10.1002/jor.20631.</citation>
    <PMID>18327798</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 16, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 9, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hemiplegic shoulder pain</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of Life</keyword>
  <keyword>stroke</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shoulder Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rotator Cuff Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pharmaceutical Solutions</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyaluronic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>no available now</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

