<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02463695</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STH18541</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02463695</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Characterisation of Cortical Vestibular Evoked Potentials (C-VEPs)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Characterisation of Cortical Vestibular Evoked Potentials (C-VEPs): A Comparative Study of Normal Ears Versus Those With Vestibular Deficits</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The pathophysiology of vertigo is complex and usually requires specialist involvement. During
      the diagnostic process, patients commonly undergo tests which assess the integrity of the
      gaze and posture stabilisation mechanisms involving the inner ear (vestibular system), the
      visual systems and the subconscious neural pathways that interconnect them. Whilst these
      tests are useful they fail to provide information concerning the neural connections to the
      cortex and therefore neglect the perceptual aspects of disequilibrium.

      At present the possibility of routine examination of these higher projections remains elusive
      as no practical alternatives to the expensive functional magnetic resonance imaging systems
      exist. However, recently a novel method of recording cortical vestibular evoked potentials
      (CVEPs) has been described.

      CVEPs utilise an existing method used to interrogate cortical projections from the auditory
      system in which sound waves stimulate the inner ear and the resulting electrical responses
      from the brain are recorded. The recent breakthrough is in the realisation that these
      responses also contain information from the balance organs and therefore are a direct measure
      of cortical processing of the vestibular inputs.

      Current evidence shows that CVEPs are present in the normal population and absent in patients
      with no vestibular function. The primary aim for this study is to extend the patient cohort
      to include those who have a vestibular injury but retain residual function. Patients going
      through standard testing will have also have CVEPs on both ears providing seminal information
      into the effect of injury to the peripheral vestibular system on the cortical pathways.
      Furthermore, by following the cohort through their complete management pathway it will be
      possible to ascertain if the CVEP can be used to predict rehabilitation outcome success.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Ears with a vestibular deficit:

      Patients referred to the tertiary ear nose and throat clinics as well otoneurological clinics
      at the Royal Hallamshire will be eligible for enrolment. The investigators aim to record data
      from 36 ears with vestibular dysfunction.

      A) Patients will receive a consultation with an ENT Consultant or Registrar as per standard
      practice.

      B) If the patient is deemed by the doctor to have an otoneurological cause for their symptoms
      then further audiovestibular testing and imaging will be arranged as per standard practice.
      The patients will then be made aware of this study and if interested will be given the
      opportunity to discuss it further with the chief investigator (CI) or the principal
      investigator (PI).

      C) If agreeable the patients will be given information packs by the PI/CI and taken through
      the study.

      D) The patients will leave the consultation with the information pack and be asked to
      consider participation in the study. They will have no obligation to take part and they can
      contact the any member of the research team to ask for further information or to have any
      questions answered.

      E) Upon their return for audiovestibular testing the patients will inform the CI/PI if they
      wish to participate in the study and if so will have an additional test at the end of test
      sequence. This will add approximately 30 minutes to their appointment time.

      F) Patients who are suitable for rehabilitation (as per standard care pathway) will go ahead
      and have the course of treatment at subsequent visit(s). The outcomes following the treatment
      will be logged and correlated with the CVEP to check for any correlation that may or may not
      be present.

      Otologically normal ears:

      Normative data will be collected from 36 normal ears from subjects that have no history of
      audiovestibular symptoms and are not being investigated for any balance disorders. Healthy
      controls will be recruited via poster advertisements and potential participants asked to
      contact the research team if they are considering taking part.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>October 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The degree of change of cortical vestibular evoked potential measured by amplitude (in microvolts)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The time interval between the stimulation and response (latency) of cortical vestibular evoked potential</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Vestibular Neuronitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>vestibular deficit</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Initial clinical assessment including otoneurological examination, pure tone audiometry, tympanometry vestibular screening tests and Magnetic Resonance Imaging as clinically indicated.
The cortical vestibular evoked potentials will add approximately add an extra 30 minutes to the test sequence but is minimally invasive and will not cause any pain or discomfort. It will be conducted on both the affected and non-affected ears.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>otologically normal controll</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Normative data will be collected from 36 normal ears from subjects that have no history of audiovestibular symptoms and are not being investigated for any balance disorders. The cortical vestibular evoked potentials will be recorded from both ears</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>cortical vestibular evoked potentials (CVEPs)</intervention_name>
    <description>CVEPs utilise an existing method used to interrogate cortical projections from the auditory system in which sound waves stimulate the inner ear and the resulting electrical responses from the brain are recorded (known as Cortical Auditory Evoked Potentials CAEPs)</description>
    <arm_group_label>vestibular deficit</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>otologically normal controll</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cortical auditory evoked potential</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Vestibular deficit Group:

               1. Over 18 years of age

               2. Can provide informed consent

               3. Deemed to have an otoneurological cause for their symptoms (true vertigo, room
                  spinning even when head is still)

               4. No middle ear pathology

        NORMATIVE GROUP:

          1. Over 18 years of age

          2. Can provide informed consent

          3. No previous otoneurological history

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  VESTIBULAR DEFICIT GROUP PATIENTS

               1. Participants under the age of 18

               2. Participants unable to provide informed consent

               3. Patients not deemed to have an otoneurological cause for their symptoms

               4. Patients with middle ear pathology

        NORMATIVE GROUP:

          1. Previous history of problems with hearing and or balance

          2. Participants under the age of 18

          3. Participants unable to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jaswinder S Sandhu, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jemima Clarke</last_name>
    <phone>+44114 226 5938</phone>
    <email>Jemima.calrke@sth.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sheffield</city>
        <state>South Yorkshire</state>
        <zip>S10 2JF</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jemima Clarke</last_name>
      <phone>+441142265938</phone>
      <email>jemima.clarke@sth.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jaswinder S Sandhu, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 28, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 2, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 4, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 2, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 2, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 4, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>partial vestibular deficit</keyword>
  <keyword>cortical vestibular evoked potential</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vestibular Neuronitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

