<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02467660</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11847</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02467660</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Meditation or Health &amp; Wellness Education Via Internet for Adults 50-80 Years Old</brief_title>
  <official_title>Meditation or Health &amp; Wellness Education Via Internet for Adults 50-80 Years Old</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oregon Health and Science University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oregon Health and Science University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      1. Telephone Eligibility Screening

        2. Baseline Visit, includes online questionnaires, physical measures, cognitive tasks,
           voice recordings, physical recordings of brain waves, heart rate, breathing rate, and
           sweat during computer tasks, collect saliva samples and respond to handheld device that
           rings randomly for the two days following the visit

        3. Randomized to receive (a) an internet-based Mindfulness Meditation program, (b) an
           internet-based Health &amp; Wellness Education program, or (c) no training. IF assigned to
           receive a training program, participants complete weekly one-hour online trainings and
           daily home practice for 6 weeks

        4. Endpoint Visit (same as Baseline), scheduled 8 weeks after Baseline

        5. All participants receive Meditation and Education programs after the Endpoint Visit

        6. Online questionnaire follow-up 6 months after the Endpoint
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim of this research project is to evaluate whether an internet-based mindfulness
      meditation training improves cognition and resilience in stressed older adults. Dr. Oken
      specializes in evaluating the effects of stress on the human body, and he plans to use
      advanced statistical analyses to create a &quot;multi-domain physiologic measure.&quot; This means
      study staff will collect biological data, including electroencephalogram (EEG, brainwaves),
      blood pressure, heart rate, breathing rate, and saliva samples. The investigator hypothesizes
      that when he statistically combines all of these together, he will have a measure that
      correlates with self-rated (survey) measures of resilience and stress.

      Participants will undergo a telephone screening to determine eligibility, and then they will
      fill out online questionnaires before their Baseline Visit at the lab. Study staff will take
      physical measurements (i.e. height, weight, vision), administer short cognitive tasks that
      measure attention and memory, and collect biological data (listed above) during several
      different tasks. Some of the tasks are very simple, such as breath counting and listening to
      an audio recording of a podcast. And some of the tasks are intended to be more stressful,
      such as one that presents difficult math problems. The investigator hopes to induce stress so
      that study staff can measure resilience by evaluating how long it takes participants to
      return to a biological baseline, such as their usual blood pressure. In total, the visit is
      approximately 3 ½ hours long.

      After the Baseline, participants are sent home with a handheld device that administers random
      5-minute assessments, as well as tubes to collect saliva, for the two days following the
      in-lab visit. Once data collection is complete, participant will come into the lab to return
      the device and samples and learn whether they have been randomized to receive the
      internet-based mindfulness meditation training (40% chance), an internet-based health &amp;
      wellness education program (40% chance), or a non-active waitlist (20% chance). All
      participants will be informed before the study begins that they will have access to the
      meditation and education materials once their participation is complete. Participants
      receiving the meditation and education will complete a one-hour online training each week for
      six weeks, and they will use an iPod to listen to guided meditations or educational podcasts
      (depending on group assignment) for 30-45 minutes per day. The iPod tracks their home
      practice, and they will return it at the end of the study. All participants will receive a
      weekly call from study staff to check in about whether they have experienced any health
      changes and, if applicable, how the meditation or education program is going.

      Eight weeks after the Baseline Visit, participants will again fill out online questionnaires
      and come back to the lab for an Endpoint Visit, which is very similar to the Baseline. They
      will again collect saliva samples and complete assessments on a handheld device for two days
      following the visit. They will mail the samples and device back to the lab and then receive
      access to both internet-based training programs and associated audio recordings. Participants
      will then be asked to fill out online questionnaires one last time 6 months after the
      Endpoint Visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Golden Stroop Cognitive Task Total Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in Stroop score at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measures selective attention, cognitive flexibility, and processing speed</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Heart Rate Variability</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in Heart Rate Variability at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Used as a measure of resiliency to determine how quickly a participant returns to baseline following an experimental stressor</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite multi-domain physiologic measure</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in multiple measures from Baseline at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>ECG, EEG, Respiration, self-report questionnaires</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Task Total Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in AVLT scores at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluates short-term auditory-verbal memory, rate of learning, learning strategies, retroactive and proactive interference, presence of confabulation of confusion in memory processes, retention of information, and differences between learning and retrieval</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Verbal Fluency Total Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in Verbal Fluency score at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measures executive function</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Letter Number Sequencing Total Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in Leter Number Sequencing score at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measures executive function</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systolic and Diastolic Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in Systolic and Diastolic Blood Pressure at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Used as a measure of resiliency to determine how quickly a participant returns to baseline following an experimental stressor</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Respiration Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in Respiration Rate at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Used as a measure of resiliency to determine how quickly a participant returns to baseline following an experimental stressor</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Salivary Cortisol Levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in Cortisol Levels at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measures general stress from baseline to endpoint and it's also used as a measure of resiliency to determine how quickly a participant returns to baseline following an experimental stressor; Several samples are taken during Baseline and Endpoint Assessments (8 weeks apart), and four samples are collected each day for two days following the Baseline and two days following the Endpoint</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Stress, Physiological</condition>
  <condition>Stress, Psychological</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Online Mindfulness Meditation Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Weekly 1-hr online training and daily meditation for 30-45 min for 6 wks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Online Health &amp; Wellness Education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>6-week training entails completing weekly 1-hour online training and listening to educational podcasts for 30-45 minutes per day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wait List Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No training</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mindfulness Meditation</intervention_name>
    <description>Using study-provided iPod device to listen to guided meditations daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Online Mindfulness Meditation Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health &amp; Wellness Education</intervention_name>
    <description>Using study-provided iPod device to listen to educational podcasts daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Online Health &amp; Wellness Education</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Between the ages of 50 and 80 years old

          -  Be stable on all medications for at least 2 months and willing to NOT change
             medications for the duration of the study

          -  Have access to a computer with internet in order to complete online questionnaires
             three separate times and complete 1-hour trainings once per week for six weeks

          -  Willing to travel to OHSU for a total of three times

          -  Willing to follow the study protocol, including completely weekly internet-based
             trainings and doing 30-45 minutes of home practice daily for 6 weeks IF randomly
             assigned to receive the meditation or education trainings

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have any significant medical or neurological diseases, such as major organ failure,
             insulin-dependent diabetes, or active cancer

          -  Have significant untreated depression

          -  Have significant visual or hearing impairment

          -  Take certain medications in the last 2 months, such as neuroleptics or steroids

          -  Have prior experience with mediation classes or other mind-body classes (e.g. yoga or
             tai chi) within the past 2 years

          -  Have had a regular meditation practice in the past 30 days

          -  Be gone for more than one full week during study participation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Barry S Oken, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Oregon Health and Science University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dan Klee, BS</last_name>
    <phone>5034945650</phone>
    <email>klee@ohsu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tabatha Memmott, BS, BA</last_name>
    <phone>5034945650</phone>
    <email>memmott@ohsu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hatfield Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dan Klee, BS</last_name>
      <phone>503-494-5650</phone>
      <email>klee@ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 20, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 10, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 12, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oregon Health and Science University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Barry S. Oken</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, MS</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stress, Psychological</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

