<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02460965</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UH-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02460965</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Understanding Hallucinations (Part II)</brief_title>
  <acronym>UH-2</acronym>
  <official_title>Understanding Hallucinations (Part II) - fMRI and EEG</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Iris Sommer</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UMC Utrecht</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Hallucinations occur in many patients with different kinds of diseases, including
      psychiatric, neurological and perceptual impairment. The origin of these hallucinations is
      only partly understood. This prevents correct prediction of treatment response and hampers
      the development of new, more effective treatment strategies.

      Different subtypes of hallucinations resulting from different neuropathology may exist across
      diagnostic entities, and be responsive to different treatment strategies. Understanding the
      origin of these subtypes with use of fMRI and EEG can help to make rational treatment
      decisions on an individual basis and enhance the development of innovative treatment
      paradigms.

      Objective: The primary objective is to find specific abnormalities on resting state fMRI
      related to the pathophysiology of different subtypes of hallucinations. Secondary objectives
      are to find EEG connectivity measures that are related to the pathophysiology of different
      subtypes of hallucinations, reveal correlating patterns of EEG and fMRI that underlie the
      experience of hallucinations across different disorders, and to examine the frequency of
      spontaneous synchronized burst activations in auditory and visual cortices using fMRI.

      Study design: The investigators intend to examine neural correlates of hallucinations over
      different disorders using resting state EEG, fMRI and sMRI in an observational study.

      Study population: A total of 140 hallucinating patients will be included, 20 of each of the 7
      different diagnostic groups. As a control group, 140 non-hallucinating patients with the same
      disorder of similar severity will be included.

      Main study parameters/endpoints: The main study endpoint is the difference in resting state
      correlates as measured with fMRI between hallucinating and non-hallucinating participants and
      between hallucinating individuals of different subtypes, namely: connectivity within the DMN
      and connectivity of the DMN to sensory cortices and the hippocampal-amygdala complex.

      Nature and extent of the burden and risks associated with participation, benefit and group
      relatedness: Participation in the study will entail an MRI scan of 40 minutes and an EEG
      measurement of 5 minutes. Total visit time, including preparations, will be approximately 2,5
      hours. The risks associated with participation and the benefits to the individuals are
      negligible. The potential benefit to society in the future is considerable if the findings
      lead to optimization of treatment strategies and treatment response.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in fMRI resting state correlates between hallucinating and non-hallucinating participants and between hallucinating individuals of different subtypes.</measure>
    <time_frame>Three years</time_frame>
    <description>The main study endpoint is the difference in resting state correlates as measured with fMRI between hallucinating and non-hallucinating participants and between hallucinating individuals of different subtypes, namely: connectivity within the DMN and connectivity of the DMN to sensory cortices and the hippocampal-amygdala complex.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The difference in EEG correlates between hallucinating and non-hallucinating participants and between hallucinating individuals of different subtypes.</measure>
    <time_frame>Three years</time_frame>
    <description>The differences in EEG spectral analysis, synchronization likelihood, clustering index, path lengths and assortativity between hallucinating and non-hallucinating participants and between hallucinating individuals of different subtypes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The auditory and visual cortex responsiveness patterns between hallucinating individuals of different subtypes.</measure>
    <time_frame>Three years</time_frame>
    <description>The frequency of spontaneous synchronized burst activations in auditory and visual cortices</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cardio-respiratory rhythms to correct for cardio-respiratory processes in the fMRI signal.</measure>
    <time_frame>Three years</time_frame>
    <description>In order to remove cardiac and respiratory pulsality effects that contaminate BOLD fMRI time series, cardiac signals and respiration will be measured</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>8</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Hallucinations</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with schizophrenia</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with borderline personality disorder</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with hearing impairment</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with visual loss</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with Parkinson's Disease</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with Alzheimer's Disease</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with dementia with Lewy Bodies</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy participants</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The participants will consist of 7 different diagnostic categories. Individuals with
        hallucinations will have to experience at least one episode of hallucinations over the last
        month. The control group will consist of non-hallucinating individuals who have the same
        disorder as the hallucinating individuals and are matched group-wise for severity of the
        disease, medication, age, sex, handedness and education.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous participation in the phenomenology/cognition study 13-059.

          -  Belong to one of the diagnostic groups as described above in 4.1.

          -  Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  &lt; 18 years of age

          -  Any contraindication for a 3Tesla MRI scan
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Iris Sommer, Prof, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UMC Utrecht</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sanne Koops, Msc.</last_name>
    <phone>+31887558672</phone>
    <email>S.Koops@umcutrecht.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UMC Utrecht</name>
      <address>
        <city>Utrecht</city>
        <zip>3584 CX</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sanne Koops, Msc.</last_name>
      <phone>+31 8858672</phone>
      <email>S.koops@umcutrecht.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Iris EC Sommer, Prof.Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sanne Koops, Msc.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Remko van Lutterveld, Dr.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 24, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 2, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 3, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 25, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 25, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 26, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>UMC Utrecht</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Iris Sommer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof.Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hallucinations</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

