<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02468453</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IH149901</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02468453</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>VELOS for the Treatment of Vascular Lesions and Skin Rejuvenation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multi-center, Multi-cohort, Prospective, Open-label Study of VELOS for Treatment of Vascular Skin Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Syneron Medical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Syneron Medical</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center, multi-cohort, prospective, open-label study of VELOS for treatment of
      vascular skin disorders. The plan is to enroll up to 60 subjects from up to 3 centers in the
      US and worldwide. The purpose is to collect data from the use of VELOS.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this trial is to collect data from the use of VELOS in clinical
      practice under a wide range of treatment parameters variability including RF energy, laser
      fluence, and laser pulse duration for treating each of the vascular disorders. This will be
      conducted by documenting the physician selected treatment parameters, as well as the
      subjects' clinical clearing response, perception of improvement and sensations, through the
      study treatments and post-treatment(s) follow-up visits.

      Optional exploratory objectives: Collection of safety and efficacy data of the Velos with DCD
      cooling and Velos with contact cooling. The investigator may opt to include in this study
      noninvasive measurements of erythema, melanin and texture (which may be performed by eg.
      Chromameter, Mexameter or 3D imaging), and measurements of linear vessel diameters and lesion
      size.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evidence of leg vein and skin improvement by validated vascular assessment scale and wrinkle assessment scale</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 months after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Evidence of leg vein and skin improvement by validated vascular assessment scale and wrinkle assessment scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number and severity of all complications caused by the laser will be recorded and descriptively tabulated</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject Improvement Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject assessment of comfort level associated with treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>day 0, afer 4 weeks, 8 weeks and 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Numerical Response Scale for Rating Pain (NRS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Vascular Lesions</condition>
  <condition>Photoaging</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 -facial skin disorders</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pulsed dye laser/bipolar radiofrequency (Velos) treatment of facial skin disorders including photo-damage, age spots, lentigos, solar telangiectasia and general facial telangiectasia</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 - leg veins</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pulsed dye laser/bipolar radiofrequency (Velos) treatment of leg veins of diameter of at least 1mm, i.e., venulectasia and reticular leg veins.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3-general skin rejuvenation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pulsed dye laser/bipolar radiofrequency (Velos) treatment treatment of general skin rejuvenation including Rosacea, erythematous scars (including acne), and erythematous striae (subjects enrolled in this group must have at least two of the above mentioned treatment indications.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4-improving skin laxity</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Velos (Bipolar radiofrequency only) treatment for improving skin laxity or skin tightness/firmness</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>velos</intervention_name>
    <description>VELOS combines 595nm pulsed dye laser energy with bipolar RF energy. The study device can deliver 0.45 to 40 ms laser pulses at a maximum of 25 J/cm2</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1 -facial skin disorders</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2 - leg veins</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3-general skin rejuvenation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4-improving skin laxity</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject is a healthy Male or Female at least 18 years of age

          2. Subject has a vascular (blood vessels) and skin disorders or erythematous scars or
             erythematous striae or wishes to improve skin laxity or skin firmness. In special
             cases non-erythematous scars or non-erythematous striae may be allowed as well.

          3. Fitzpatrick Skin Type I - VI

          4. Subject must be able to read, understand and sign the Informed Consent Form

          5. Subject must be willing and able to adhere to the treatment and follow-up schedule and
             post-treatment care instructions

          6. Subject must be willing to have limited sun exposure for the duration of the study,
             including the follow-up period

          7. Subject is willing to have photographs and/or videos taken of the treated area which
             will be used, de-identified, in evaluations and may be used, de-identified, in
             presentations and/or publications

          8. For female candidates - subject must be post-menopausal, or surgically sterilized, or
             using a medically acceptable form of birth control during the entire course of the
             study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject is pregnant or planning to become pregnant during the study duration.
             Pregnancy will be assessed by question at screening.

          2. Subject has an active electrical implant anywhere in the body, such as a pacemaker or
             an internal defibrillator.

          3. Subject has an implant in the treated area (such as metal plates or screws) or an
             injected chemical substance, including Botox and collagen injections (if the face area
             is treated).

          4. Subject has a known collagen (connective tissue) disorder, vascular disease,
             scleroderma or other autoimmune disease (i.e. rheumatoid arthritis, lupus).

          5. Subject has a history of diseases stimulated by heat or sun exposure, such as
             recurrent Herpes Simplex in the treated area, unless treatment is conducted following
             a prophylactic regimen.

          6. Subject has a history of immunosuppression/immune deficiency disorders (including HIV
             infection or AIDS) or currently using immunosuppressive medications.

          7. Having or undergoing any form of treatment for active cancer, or having a history of
             skin cancer or any other cancer in the areas to be treated, including actinic
             keratosis, presence of malignant or pre-malignant pigmented lesions.

          8. Subject is suffering from significant concurrent illness, such as such as cardiac
             disorders, diabetes (type I or II), or pertinent neurological disorders.

          9. Subject has an infection or is suffering from current or has a history of significant
             skin conditions in the treated area or inflammatory skin conditions, including, but
             not limited to: photodermatoses, active acne, excessive skin dryness, psoriasis,
             eczema, rash, rosacea (particularly severe open wound stage), varicella scars, open
             lacerations or abrasions and active cold sores or herpes sores prior to treatment
             (duration of resolution as per the Investigator's discretion) or during the treatment
             course.

         10. Having a known anticoagulative or thromboembolic condition or taking anticoagulation
             medications one week prior to and during the treatment course (to allow inclusion,
             temporary cessation of use as per the subject's physician discretion).

         11. Use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDS, e.g., ibuprofen-containing
             agents) one week before and after each treatment session.

         12. Subject has a history of pigmentary disorders, particularly tendency for hyper- or
             hypo-pigmentation.

         13. Subject has a history of keloid scarring or of abnormal wound healing.

         14. Subject has a known photosensitivity to the study laser wavelength, history of
             ingesting medications known to induce photosensitivity, or history of seizure
             disorders due to light.

         15. Subject has undergone any surgical, light-based therapy or RF procedures in the
             treatment area within 3 months of treatment or during the study.

         16. Having undergone any other surgery in the treated area within 3 months of treatment
             (or more if skin has not healed completely) or during the study.

         17. Subject has undergone a facial dermabrasion or chemical peel treatment within 3 months
             of treatment or during the study (if face is treated).

         18. Having received Botox/collagen/fat injections or other methods of augmentation with
             injected or implanted material in the treated area within 9 months of treatment or
             during the study (if face is treated).

         19. Subject has undergone a resurfacing procedure, face lift or eyelid surgery within a
             year of treatment or during the study (if face is treated).

         20. Subject has a tattoo or permanent make-up in the treated area.

         21. Subject has systemically used retinoids, antioxidants or medical grade of skin
             nourishing supplements within 2 months of treatment or during the study.

         22. Excessively tanned in areas to be treated or unable/unlikely to refrain from tanning
             during the study.

         23. Participation in a study of another device or drug within three months prior to
             enrollment or during the study.

         24. As per the Investigator's discretion, any physical or mental condition which might
             make it unsafe for the subject to participate in this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian Zelickson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Zel Skin &amp; Laser Specialists 4100 W. 50th Street, Edina, MN 5542</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roy Geronemus, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>New York 317 East 34th Street 6th and 11th Floors New York, NY 10016</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Roy Geronemus, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(212) 686-7306</phone>
    <email>mail@laserskinsurgery.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Brian Zelickson, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(952) 929-8888</phone>
    <email>info@zelskin.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Scripps Clinic - Carmel Valley</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92130</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nancy Giovanetty</last_name>
      <phone>858-764-9040</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Edward Victor Ross, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Syneron Candela Institute for Education Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wayland</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01778</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Meghan Murphy, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>508-358-0359</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Konika Schallen, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zel Skin &amp; Laser Specialists</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edina</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55424</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Laser and Skin Surgery Center of New York</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sadick NS, Makino Y. Selective electro-thermolysis in aesthetic medicine: a review. Lasers Surg Med. 2004;34(2):91-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15004818</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sadick NS. Combination radiofrequency and light energies: electro-optical synergy technology in esthetic medicine. Dermatol Surg. 2005 Sep;31(9 Pt 2):1211-7; discussion 1217.</citation>
    <PMID>16176773</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 31, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 10, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>velos</keyword>
  <keyword>Vascular</keyword>
  <keyword>Rejuvenation</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

