<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00362362</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>060224</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>06-N-0224</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00362362</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Collection of Blood Samples for DNA in Motor Neuron Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Collection of Blood Samples for DNA Analysis in Motor Neuron Diseases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will collect blood samples from patients with primary lateral sclerosis (PLS) and
      amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) to be used for research on genetic causes of motor neuron
      diseases and other neurological disorders.

      Patients 18 years of age and older with PLS or ALS may be eligible for this study. Candidates
      are screened with a medical history, physical examination and diagnostic tests.

      Participants provide a blood sample. The sample, along with masked (anonymous) medical and
      family history information are sent to the NINDS Respository at the Coriell Cell Repositories
      in Camden, NJ. This facility collects, stores and distributes medical research information
      and cell cultures and DNA samples to researchers at hospitals, universities and commercial
      organizations. The blood sample has an identification number that is unrelated to any
      identifying information for the patient and cannot be tracked back to the patient.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVE:

      The causes of sporadic motor neuron diseases, primary lateral sclerosis (PLS) and amyotrophic
      lateral sclerosis (ALS) are unknown. Genes have been identified for some forms of familial
      motor neuron diseases. We don't know whether genes also play a role in sporadic motor neuron
      disease, for example through risk-factor genes or by the interaction of multiple genes as a
      complex genetic disorder. Identification of genetic contributions to sporadic motor neuron
      diseases requires analysis of DNA from patients.

      The goal of this protocol is to collect blood samples from patients with motor neuron disease
      for creation of cell lines to bank in a repository created through an NINDS initiative. The
      cell lines will be used for DNA extraction. The repository provides anonymized samples of
      patient DNA or cell lines to investigators who are seeking to define genetic causes,
      contributions, and susceptibilities to neurological disorders. DNA and cell lines created
      from the blood sample are stripped of patient identifiers and stored indefinitely. A limited
      amount of clinical data, termed the clinical data elements, will be available for each coded
      sample. The samples will only be available for research. The results of testing will not be
      communicated to the patient.

      STUDY POPULATION:

      All patients will be enrolled in a primary protocol for the study of motor neuron diseases at
      NIH. This protocol will serve as a secondary protocol for sample collection and reporting of
      clinical data elements. Patients with Primary lateral sclerosis must meet the diagnostic
      criteria for PLS proposed by Pringle and patients with ALS must fulfill the revised El
      Escorial criteria for probable or definite ALS.

      DESIGN:

      Determination of diagnosis and eligibility will be carried out as part of the primary
      protocol. Patients will be informed of the DNA sample repository and its purpose. After
      informed consent is obtained, 2 tubes of blood will be drawn and assigned a unique identifier
      code. The coded samples, and a clinical data element form will then be sent to the
      repository, which will extract DNA and prepare cell lines. The identities of the subjects
      will not be stored. An aliquot of the sample will be forwarded to the associate investigator
      to look for disease associations with genetic markers.

      OUTCOME MEASURES:

      There is no specific outcome measure for this protocol. The samples will be made accessible
      to a wide variety of researchers seeking to determine the causes of motor neuron diseases and
      other neurological disorders through the repository's contract with NINDS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 7, 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date>September 9, 2013</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment type="Actual">23</enrollment>
  <condition>Motor Neuron Diseases</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  PRIMARY LATERAL SCLEROSIS INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients with PLS, aged 18 and older, must meet the diagnostic criteria proposed by Pringle
        (1992), incorporating Santa Clara (2004) consensus for pure PLS.

        Clinical:

          -  Insidious onset in adulthood, progressive course

          -  No family history

          -  Disease duration greater than 3 years without lower motor neuron clinical signs

          -  Clinical signs restricted to corticospinal/corticobulbar tract dysfunction

        Imaging:

          -  Brain MRI normal (except cortical atrophy)

          -  Normal cervical spine

          -  Negative chest X-ray, negative mammograms in women

        EMG after 3 years, but within last 3 years, showing no active denervation.

        Normal serological studies for serum chemistry, Vitamin B12, Vitamin E levels, very
        long-chain fatty acids.

        Negative serology for syphilis, Lyme disease, HTLV 1 and 2.

        AMYOTROPHIC LATERAL SCLEROSIS INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients with ALS, aged 18 and older, must fulfill the revised El Escorial criteria for
        probable or definite ALS.

          -  Probable ALS: Upper and Lower motor neuron signs are present in more than two regions,
             but some UMN signs must be rostral to LMN signs.

          -  Definite ALS: Upper and Lower motor neuron signs are present in more than three
             regions.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mary Kay Floeter, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pringle CE, Hudson AJ, Munoz DG, Kiernan JA, Brown WF, Ebers GC. Primary lateral sclerosis. Clinical features, neuropathology and diagnostic criteria. Brain. 1992 Apr;115 ( Pt 2):495-520.</citation>
    <PMID>1606479</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brooks BR, Miller RG, Swash M, Munsat TL; World Federation of Neurology Research Group on Motor Neuron Diseases. El Escorial revisited: revised criteria for the diagnosis of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis. Amyotroph Lateral Scler Other Motor Neuron Disord. 2000 Dec;1(5):293-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11464847</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Younger DS, Chou S, Hays AP, Lange DJ, Emerson R, Brin M, Thompson H Jr, Rowland LP. Primary lateral sclerosis. A clinical diagnosis reemerges. Arch Neurol. 1988 Dec;45(12):1304-7.</citation>
    <PMID>3196189</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 9, 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 9, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 9, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 10, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary Lateral Sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood Sample</keyword>
  <keyword>PLS</keyword>
  <keyword>ALS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Motor Neuron Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

