<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00364585</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0604008494</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>0000022806</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00364585</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Prospective Evaluation of the GreenLight Model 120 Laser</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Evaluation of the GreenLight Model 120 Laser System for the Treatment of Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the performance of the GreenLight™ model 120
      delivering higher average power to allow for more flexibility in the working distance of the
      delivery device with the same power density to tissue as that of the current GreenLight
      model. In addition this study will examine the Laserscope GDD (guided delivery device) that
      has been designed exclusively for use with the GreenLight™ model 120.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia (BPH) refers to a medical condition which occurs in aging men
      where the prostate gland is enlarged preventing the free flow of urine. This causes symptoms
      of frequent urination, constant feeling of urgency to go to the bathroom, and difficulty
      passing urine due to the obstruction caused by the enlarged gland. The incidence (number of
      new cases) of BPH increases from 40% among males between the ages of 50 and 60 years to 90%
      among males older than 80 years of age. Treatment of BPH is currently undergoing intense
      scrutiny due to the cost and morbidity (complications and disability due to the procedure)
      associated with the &quot;gold standard&quot; treatment, Transurethral Resection of the Prostate
      (TURP). The TURP procedure has established its place as a standard of care for BPH due to its
      exceptional clinical efficacy and established long-term durability. Despite the clinical
      prowess of TURP, there remain significant concerns regarding the relatively high incidence of
      postoperative morbidity and the significant economic burden on world healthcare systems.
      Laser vaporization prostatectomy, on the other hand, has developed into a relatively new
      technological advance that has been utilized with favorable outcomes for more than a decade.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2007</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the effectiveness of the GreenLightÔ Model 120 Laser for the treatment (PVP)</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the effectiveness of the Laserscope GDD</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>20</enrollment>
  <condition>Benign Prostatic Hyperplasia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GreenLight Model 120 Laser System</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects must be male and over the age of 40 years.

          2. Subjects must present with symptomatic/obstructive symptoms secondary to BPH requiring
             surgical intervention, diagnosed using standard clinical practices (uroflowmetry).

          3. Subjects must present with LUTS secondary to BPH &gt; 3 months in duration.

          4. IPPS symptom score value of &gt; 12.

          5. Prostate size, as measured by transrectal ultrasonography, between 15 and 300 cc.

          6. Subjects that are in retention may be enrolled in the study provided that it is
             documented the primary cause of the retention is BPH.

          7. ASA classification of physical status, class 1-3.

          8. Subjects must read, understand, and sign the Informed Consent.

          9. Subjects must be willing and able to comply with all follow-up requirements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Unstable cardiopulmonary disorder, previously or recently diagnosed by standard
             methods.

          2. Subjects with a recent myocardial infarction or coronary artery stent placement.

          3. Subjects with systemic diseases that cause significant neurogenic lower urinary
             dysfunction.

          4. Subjects who have had major pelvic fractures that involved damage to the external
             urinary sphincter.

          5. Subjects who have recently completed definitive radiation therapy for prostate cancer.

          6. Subjects with prostate cancer who are considering brachytherapy (radioactive seed
             implantation) or cryotherapy as part of their definitive treatment.

          7. Subjects must not have active localized or systemic infections; including active
             urinary tract infection.

          8. Subjects with confirmed atonic bladders and/or neurogenic bladders, reflex
             dyssynergia, detrusor hyporeflexia/areflexia.

          9. Subjects diagnosed with active urethral strictures, bladder neck contracture, acute
             prostatitis affecting bladder function.

         10. Serum prostate specific antigen level &gt; 4 ng/ml, requiring prostate needle biopsy, and
             resultant positive pathology for malignancy of the prostate.

         11. Subjects with confirmed or suspected malignancy of the prostate or bladder.

         12. Subjects with renal ectasia by renal ultrasound.

         13. Immunocompromised subjects and deemed unfit for laser vaporization as determined by
             the attending physician.

         14. Any disorder or conditions of the subject that the investigator believes will
             contraindicate their inclusion in the study.

         15. Subjects who refuse to sign the Informed Consent document and/or comply with all
             follow-up requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexis Te, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York-Presbyterian Hospital Cornell Univeristy</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 11, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 14, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 15, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 16, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 16, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 17, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hyperplasia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Hyperplasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

