<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00360737</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AA24424 BT-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00360737</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Study of 7 Botulinum Antitoxin Serotypes Derived From Horses</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pharmacokinetics of a Heptavalent Equine-derived Botulinum Antitoxin (NP-018)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cangene Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Department of Health and Human Services</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cangene Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of the study is to evaluate the safety of the 7 Botulinum Antitoxin
      Serotypes derived from horses using various laboratory measurements, clinical examinations
      and adverse events. In addition, following intravenous (injected into the vein)
      administration assessing how much 7 Botulinum Antitoxin remains in the body.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Clostridial toxins are amongst the most toxic substances known to science (Middlebrook,
      1995). In the United States and other countries, human exposure to Clostridium botulinum
      toxins usually occurs through food poisoning, wound botulism and colonizing infections in
      neonates. Recent events have heightened concern about the possibility of botulinum toxins
      being used in a bioterrorist attack. In order to be prepared for a biological attack as well
      as the usual human exposures, numerous therapeutic products have been or currently are
      undergoing development to treat or prevent botulism, including the use of human or equine
      derived antibodies for post-exposure prophylaxis of botulinum toxin exposure (Gelzleichter et
      al, 1999; Hibbs et al, 1996; Metzger and Lewis, 1979 and Keller and Stiehm, 2000).

      Botulinum antitoxins have been in use to treat adult exposure to botulinum toxin for at least
      40 years (Cupo et al, 2001). The use of botulinum antitoxins to treat individuals exposed to
      botulinum toxin is similar to the use of passive immune therapy with immune globulins
      collected from immunized or convalescing human donors to treat a wide range of bacterial and
      viral infectious diseases (Chippaux et al, 1998).

      NP-018 (heptavalent equine-derived botulinum antitoxin) is prepared from plasma obtained from
      horses that have been immunized with a specific subtype of botulinum toxoid and toxin. Each
      individual horse is immunized against a single botulinum toxin subtype. Plasma is pooled from
      horses that have been immunized with the same botulinum toxin subtype. For each antitoxin
      serotype (A-G), a despeciated product will be produced by pepsin digestion of the IgG monomer
      in the equine plasma, yielding predominantly F(ab¢)2 fragment. Following the formulation, the
      seven antitoxin serotypes will be blended into a heptavalent product and filled into
      single-use vials.

      The present clinical study is intended to assess the pharmacokinetics and safety of NP 018
      following intravenous administration. The pharmacokinetics of NP 018 will be comparable to
      other equine derived antitoxin products. NP 018 will be safe to administer to normal healthy
      volunteers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>Yes</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum for Antitoxins and Pk analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>(Day 2 Screening, 30 minutes, 4 hours, 8 hours, Day 1 [24 hours], Day 3, Day 7, Day 14, Day 21, Day 28 or early withdrawal)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood Chemistry Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>(Day 1 Screening, Baseline, Day 7 and Day 28 or early withdrawal)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinalysis Assessment (</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 Screening, Baseline, Day 7 and Day 28 or early withdrawal)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Examination</measure>
    <time_frame>(Day 1 Screening, Day 28 or early withdrawal)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concomitant Medications</measure>
    <time_frame>(Day 1 Screening, Day 2 Screening, Baseline, Day 0 [Time 0], 30 minutes, 4 hours, 8 hours, Day 1 [24 hours], Day 3, Day 7, Day 14, Day 21, Day 28 or early withdrawal)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital Signs</measure>
    <time_frame>(Day 1 Screening, Baseline, Day 0 [Time 0], 30 minutes, 4 hours, 8 hours, Day 1 [24 hours], Day 7, Day 28 or early withdrawal)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>(Day 1 Screening, Day 2 Screening, Baseline, Day 0 [Time 0], 30 minutes, 4 hours, 8 hours, Day 1 [24 hours], Day 3, Day 7, Day 14, Day 21, Day 28 or early withdrawal)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hematology Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>(Day 1 Screening, Baseline, Day 3, Day 7, Day 14, Day 21, Day 28 or early withdrawal)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NP-018</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects received one or two vials of NP-018 administered intravenously.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Botulinum Antitoxin Heptavalent (A B C D E F G) - (EQUINE)</intervention_name>
    <description>Biological/Vaccine NP-018 Experimental with 8 Cohorts of 5 Subjects each evaluating 2 Dosage levels of 1 or 2 vials of NP-018 administered intravenously.</description>
    <arm_group_label>NP-018</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Botulism Antitoxin (BAT)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Body-mass index of 20 to 30 with minimum body weight of 111 lb (50 kg).

          -  For female subjects that are not surgically sterilized, willingness to use an
             effective method of contraception throughout the trial including:

          -  Using hormonal contraception (oral or injectable or implant) continuously for 3 months
             prior to the start of the trial and willing to continue to use hormonal contraception
             throughout the entire trial.

          -  IUD inserted at least 2 months prior to dosing.

          -  For female subjects who are postmenopausal less than 2 years an FSH &gt;= 40 mIU/mL must
             be obtained. IF the FSH is &lt; 40 mIU/mL the subject must agree to use an acceptable
             form of contraception (see above for acceptable forms of contraception.

          -  Normal and healthy as determined by medical history, physical examination, ECG, vital
             signs and test of liver, kidney and hematological functions.

          -  Written Informed Consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any known or documented allergies to horses (e.g. rash, wheezing, rhinitis etc. after
             exposure to horses)

          -  Any known or documented allergies to horse serum (observation of adverse events after
             treatment with any kind of products containing horse serum)

          -  Any severe food allergies, seasonal allergies or hay fever requiring therapy such as
             treatment with immunosuppressive drugs

          -  Known acute or chronic asthma requiring treatment with immunosuppressive drugs

          -  History of hypersensitivity to blood products derived from a human or equine source

          -  Heavy smokers (&gt;10 cigarettes a day)

          -  Use of nicotine containing products

          -  Use of any investigational product within the past 30 days

          -  Pregnancy or lactation

          -  Positive serological test for HIV, HBV, or HCV

          -  History of, or suspected substance abuse problem (including alcohol) or failure of
             alcohol or drug screen at screening or at baseline

          -  Individuals with a history of allergy to latex or rubber

          -  Hemoglobin level of &lt; 12 g/dL.

          -  Significant blood loss or blood donation within 56 days prior to dosing.

          -  Any plasma donation within 7 days prior to dosing.

          -  Demonstrated potential for allergic reaction to NP-018 based on positive horse dander
             (E3) IgE test or positive NP-018 skin sensitivity test prior to dosing
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark J. Allison, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>MDS Pharma Services</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MDS Pharma Services</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85044</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Middlebrook JL. Protection strategies against botulinum toxin. Adv Exp Med Biol. 1995;383:93-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8644518</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gelzleichter TR, Myers MA, Menton RG, Niemuth NA, Matthews MC, Langford MJ. Protection against botulinum toxins provided by passive immunization with botulinum human immune globulin: evaluation using an inhalation model. J Appl Toxicol. 1999 Dec;19 Suppl 1:S35-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10594898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hibbs RG, Weber JT, Corwin A, Allos BM, Abd el Rehim MS, Sharkawy SE, Sarn JE, McKee KT Jr. Experience with the use of an investigational F(ab')2 heptavalent botulism immune globulin of equine origin during an outbreak of type E botulism in Egypt. Clin Infect Dis. 1996 Aug;23(2):337-40.</citation>
    <PMID>8842274</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Metzger JF, Lewis GE Jr. Human-derived immune globulins for the treatment of botulism. Rev Infect Dis. 1979 Jul-Aug;1(4):689-92.</citation>
    <PMID>399376</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keller MA, Stiehm ER. Passive immunity in prevention and treatment of infectious diseases. Clin Microbiol Rev. 2000 Oct;13(4):602-14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11023960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cupo P, de Azevedo-Marques MM, Sarti W, Hering SE. Proposal of abolition of the skin sensitivity test before equine rabies immune globulin application. Rev Inst Med Trop Sao Paulo. 2001 Jan-Feb;43(1):51-3.</citation>
    <PMID>11246284</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chippaux JP, Lang J, Eddine SA, Fagot P, Rage V, Peyrieux JC, Le Mener V. Clinical safety of a polyvalent F(ab')2 equine antivenom in 223 African snake envenomations: a field trial in Cameroon. VAO (Venin Afrique de l'Ouest) Investigators. Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg. 1998 Nov-Dec;92(6):657-62.</citation>
    <PMID>10326114</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 19, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 3, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 7, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 8, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 8, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 9, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Fran Yadao, Manager Clinical Operations</name_title>
    <organization>Cangene Corp.</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Clinical Trials</keyword>
  <keyword>Investigational Drug</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteers</keyword>
  <keyword>Botulinum Antitoxin</keyword>
  <keyword>Phoenix, Arizona</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antitoxins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Botulinum Antitoxin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

