<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00368043</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>060223</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>06-CH-0223</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00368043</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Endocrine and Psychological Evaluation of Adopted Children</brief_title>
  <official_title>Biobehavioral Study of Recently Adopted Children</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The deleterious effects of institutionalized care on the health and growth and development of
      children have been described. Early studies have shown that the effects of institutionalized
      care on a child's growth and development may not be fully reversible. The exact mechanism
      through which these early stresses affect bio-behavioral outcomes has yet to be determined. A
      likely mechanism in which environmental influences could regulate both biological and
      psychosocial development may be through the hypothalamic pituitary adrenal axis (HPA). Recent
      advances in the area of brain research have enriched our understanding of the importance of
      early life experiences on physical, cognitive, developmental, mental and behavioral health
      outcomes. Children adopted from orphanages in countries as diverse as the former Soviet Union
      and Guatemala provide an opportunity to learn more about the effect of deprivation on
      neuro-endocrine function, physical growth, and developmental outcomes, including cognitive,
      and behavioral measures.

      This protocol proposes to study the changes of the HPA axis of the post-institutionalized
      adoptive child, ages 10 months to 4 years, which may help elucidate the etiology of the
      complex findings in this population. We will recruit 60 adopted children who experienced
      institutionalized care and were recently adopted by a US family and 60 controls. Our primary
      hypothesis is that a number of adopted children will have biochemical evidence of
      stress-induced activation of the HPA axis and sympathetic adrenal medullary system. HPA
      dysfunction will be evident by abnormal diurnal salivary cortisol levels, increased cortisol
      and/or catecholamine excretion in 24 hours urine measurements, and dysregulation of autonomic
      nervous system activity We also hypothesize that many of these responses will not normalize
      with time and that there will be a correlation between these responses and growth and
      behavioral disorders. In addition, we will examine nutritional intake and sleep patterns to
      determine their effect on growth and developmental outcome....
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The deleterious effects of institutionalized care on the health and growth and development of
      children have been described. Early studies have shown that the effects of institutionalized
      care on a child's growth and development may not be fully reversible. The exact mechanism
      through which these early stresses affect bio-behavioral outcomes has yet to be determined. A
      likely mechanism in which environmental influences could regulate both biological and
      psychosocial development may be through the hypothalamic pituitary adrenal axis (HPA). Recent
      advances in the area of brain research have enriched our understanding of the importance of
      early life experiences on physical, cognitive, developmental, mental and behavioral health
      outcomes. Children adopted from orphanages in countries as diverse as the former Soviet Union
      and Guatemala provide an opportunity to learn more about the effect of deprivation on
      neuro-endocrine function, physical growth, and developmental outcomes, including cognitive
      and behavioral measures.

      This protocol proposes to study the changes of the HPA axis of the post-institutionalized
      adoptive child, ages 10 months to 4 years, which may help elucidate the etiology of the
      complex findings in this population. We will recruit 60 adopted children who experienced
      institutionalized care and were recently adopted by a US family and 60 controls. Our primary
      hypothesis is that a number of adopted children will have biochemical evidence of
      stress-induced activation of the HPA axis and sympathetic adrenal medullary system. HPA
      dysfunction will be evident by abnormal diurnal salivary cortisol levels, increased cortisol
      and/or catecholamine excretion in 24 hours urine measurements, and dysregulation of autonomic
      nervous system activity We also hypothesize that many of these responses will not normalize
      with time and that there will be a correlation between these responses and growth and
      behavioral disorders. In addition, we will examine nutritional intake and sleep patterns to
      determine their effect on growth and developmental outcome.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 18, 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date>March 30, 2015</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment type="Actual">38</enrollment>
  <condition>Psychosocial Adjustment</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        A. The patient sample will be children ages 10 months to 4 years old (pre-pubertal, Tanner
        I) referred to the International Adoption Center or Johns Hopkins University Medical Center
        for an initial evaluation within two to four weeks after they arrive from their country of
        origin (Eastern Europe/Russia).

        A total of 60 children, ages 10 months to 6 years, will be recruited for a control group
        and will be frequency matched with the adopted subjects into four strata: 10 to 42 month
        old boys, 10 to 42 month old girls, 43 to 72 month old boys, and 43 to 72 month old girls.

        The controls will be healthy children with no history of medical or psychological disorders

        The controls will be healthy children with no history of medical or psychological
        disorders.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Children with known documented growth hormone deficiency, and/or history of chronic
             illness such as renal failure, severe chronic lung disease (restrictive, obstructive)
             diabetes, hypothyroidism.

          2. Children with known genetic or chromosomal abnormalities.

          3. Children with medical conditions known to be associated with permanent developmental
             delay (i.e. fetal alcohol syndrome).

          4. Children with chronic medication use.

          5. Children with behavior problems receiving psychiatric treatment

          6. Children with documented infectious diseases (AIDS, Hepatitis, etc).

          7. Children with clinical signs of puberty; only children in Tanner-I pubertal stage will
             be allowed in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>4 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Margaret F Keil, C.R.N.P.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aguila MC, Pickle RL, Yu WH, McCann SM. Roles of somatostatin and growth hormone-releasing factor in ether stress inhibition of growth hormone release. Neuroendocrinology. 1991 Nov;54(5):515-20.</citation>
    <PMID>1684229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Albers LH, Johnson DE, Hostetter MK, Iverson S, Miller LC. Health of children adopted from the former Soviet Union and Eastern Europe. Comparison with preadoptive medical records. JAMA. 1997 Sep 17;278(11):922-4.</citation>
    <PMID>9302245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Academy of Pediatrics Committee on Early Childhood, Adoption &amp; Dependent Care: Initial medical evaluation of an adopted child. Pediatrics. 1991 Sep;88(3):642-4.</citation>
    <PMID>1881750</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 30, 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 23, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 23, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 24, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pituitary</keyword>
  <keyword>Adrenal</keyword>
  <keyword>Growth</keyword>
  <keyword>Cortisol</keyword>
  <keyword>Stress Response</keyword>
  <keyword>Adoption</keyword>
  <keyword>Thyroid Hormone</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychosocial Adjustment</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

