<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01956383</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MRCZ/A/1628 Nurses Study</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01956383</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of the PrePex Device Circumcision When Performed by Nurses</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase III of Study of Safety and Efficacy of the PrePex Device for MC Programs in Zimbabwe (Nurses Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ministry of Health and Child Welfare, Zimbabwe</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ministry of Health and Child Welfare, Zimbabwe</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The protocol, approved by the Medical Research Council, was issued to assess the safety and
      efficacy of the non-surgical device for applying it to the national scale up of adult male
      circumcision in Zimbabwe
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Models show that to have the highest impact on the HIV epidemic, circumcision of up to 80% of
      men in high prevalence countries, where MC rates are low, needs to be achieved (UNAIDS 2009;
      Manicaland HIV/STD Prevention Project, 2008; Bollinger, et al, 2009). Hallett and colleagues
      in 2008 showed that for Zimbabwe specifically, HIV incidence could be reduced between 25% to
      35% if about 50% of men are circumcised. All modelings conducted show that MC programs must
      be part of a comprehensive HIV prevention package as MC alone will not tip the HIV epidemic
      into a terminal decline.

      The PrePex Device offers hope for rapid scale up of adult male circumcision in resource
      limited settings.

      Once the safety and efficacy have been established, it is important to conduct operations
      research to determine how best to implement both device and surgical circumcisions in the
      national program. Thus, the Zimbabwe MOHCW is planning a three phase trial in order to
      determine the safety of the PrePexTM device, its performance and the ease of use in an
      implementation roll out.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the safety of the PrePex device when circumcision is performed by nurses</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the safety of the PrePex device by means of the following parameters: Clinical significant adverse event rate when circumcision is performed by nurses</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the training needs of PrePexTM deployment using nurses</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>PrePex Procedure time and the resulting cost of provider's time
Cost Effectiveness • Cost of device
Evaluation of the PrePex training needs and efficacy
Acceptability of the PrePex procedure by the patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Observation of in-field usability of device</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Observation of in-field usability of device using questionnaires</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Obtain user feedback from nurses</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Obtain user feedback from nurses by questionnaires</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess safety compared to physician deployment</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>1. To assess the safety of the PrePex device by means of the following parameters: Clinical significant adverse event rate, when circumcision is performed by nurses comparing to Physicians.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess practicality and acceptability among nurses and patients</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assess practicality and acceptability among nurses and patients using questionnaires.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess satisfaction of procedure among nurses and patients</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assess satisfaction of procedure among nurses and patients using questionnaires.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine cost-effectiveness compared to surgical procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>1. Evaluating the cost-effectiveness when taking into account the following parameters: i. PrePex Procedure time and the resulting cost of provider's time compared to surgical procedure ii. Cost of device compared to surgical procedure iii. Cost of device training compared to surgical procedure training iv. Cost of staff time for follow-up visits compared to compared to surgical procedure staff time v. Cost of equipment and supplies needed for the circumcision procedure for both PrePex and surgical circumcision.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">603</enrollment>
  <condition>Circumcision Adult</condition>
  <condition>HIV CDC Category B2</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PrePex™ device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Adult male circumcision by the PrePex™ device</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PrePex™ device</intervention_name>
    <description>PrePex™ device for adult male circumcision. The PrePex™ device facilitates adult male circumcision that is bloodless with no anesthesia and no sutures</description>
    <arm_group_label>PrePex™ device</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ages 18 - 30 years

          -  Uncircumcised

          -  Wants to be circumcised

          -  Agrees to be circumcised by any of the study methods ,PrePex or Surgical as
             appropriate

          -  HIV sero-negative

          -  Able to understand the study procedures and requirements

          -  Agrees to abstain from sexual intercourse and to keep caution not to directly rub the
             cut area if masturbating, for 8 weeks post removal (9 weeks total)

          -  Agrees to return to the health care facility for follow-up visits (or as instructed)
             after his circumcision for a period of 8 weeks post removal (9 weeks total)

          -  Subject able to comprehend and freely give informed consent for participation in this
             study and is considered by the investigator to have good compliance for the study

          -  Subject agrees to anonymous video and photographs of the procedure and follow up
             visits

          -  Agrees to stay overnight at the Hospital in order to follow pain measurements in the
             first 16 hours

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Active genital infection, anatomic abnormality or other condition, which in the
             opinion of the investigator prevents the subject from undergoing a circumcision

          -  HIV sero-positive

          -  Subject with the following diseases/conditions: phimosis, paraphimosis, warts under
             the prepuce, torn or tight frenulum, narrow prepuce, hypospadias, epispadias

          -  Known bleeding / coagulation abnormality

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes

          -  Subject that to the opinion of the investigator is not a good candidate

          -  Subject does not agree to anonymous video and photographs of the procedure and follow
             up visits

          -  Refusal to take HIV test.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gerald Gwinji, MBChB, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>PS- MoHCW</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Znfpc Spilhaus Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Harare</city>
        <country>Zimbabwe</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Zimbabwe</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mrcz.org.zw/</url>
    <description>MRCZ</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 19, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 6, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 8, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 6, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 6, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 8, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ministry of Health and Child Welfare, Zimbabwe</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof. Mufuta Tshimanga</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Public Health Physician, Department of Community Medicine, University of Zimbabwe</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>male circumcision</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Zimbabwe</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

