<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01953666</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12053</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01953666</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Efficiency of Word Prediction Software to Text Input Speed for Tetraplegia</brief_title>
  <acronym>Smartwrite</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase 1 Evaluation of the Influence of Settings of Word Prediction Software (Phase 1)and the Efficiency of Rehabilitation Programm (Phase 2)to Text Input Speed for People With Spinal Cord Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre d'Investigation Clinique et Technologique 805</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre d'Investigation Clinique et Technologique 805</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Computers now play an important role in the lives of most individuals.Access to computers is
      crucial for people with disabilities and may improve their quality of life. The use of
      computers can facilitate mainstreaming at school, for example, and the Internet may provide a
      valuable means of communication. However, the use of computers requires a certain degree of
      motor ability. People with motor disabilities frequently experience difficulties using a
      standard keyboard and standard pointing input systems such as a mouse. Many solutions exist
      to facilitate computer access, depending on the person's specific impairments and the purpose
      for which the computer is used. The most common solution relies on the use of a virtual
      keyboard which is directly displayed on the computer screen. The selection of the desired key
      on the virtual keyboard can be handled by a large variety of input devices, from a
      microgravity mouse to single switch devices supplemented by a process of dynamic scanning of
      the keyboard.Although such assistive devices render computers accessible to people with
      disabilities, the actual inputting of text can be very slow. A method to increase text input
      speed is to display words which are predicted from the letters previously typed. Word
      prediction reduces the number of necessary key strokes by avoiding having to type the whole
      word. The effect on text input speed is, however uncertain and results in the literature are
      inconclusive. Indeed, word prediction software provide a enhancement of cognitive load which
      decrease text input speed.The reduction of cognitive load could therefore be based in part on
      the optimization settings of the software and / or achievement of a rehabilitation
      program.Our hypothesis are for people with spinal cord injury : i) optimization settings word
      prediction software and ii) a rehabilitation program could improve the text input speed.The
      investigators propose to study the influence of settings word prediction software on text
      input speed and the influence of a rehabilitation program provided by a therapist, focused on
      word prediction software to help integrate them. The aim is to increase the performance of
      people with spinal cord injury and their satisfaction.

      The first phase of this research is to select the word prediction software and configuration
      that provides the best user support.The second phase corresponds to the objective of
      evaluating the efficiency of a rehabilitation program .
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PHASE 1 : The first phase studied the repeated measurement of the efficiency of typing text
      topics in various situations. Each subject will copy a text different in each test and in a
      random order. Similarly, if the word prediction software has a capacity for self-improvement
      the internal dictionary, it will be disabled.

      the investigators will study one setting of the configuration word prediction software. Are
      available the length of the list of proposals for which three options are selected: 1, 3 or 5
      words, according to the literature and to the results of a questionnaire.This questionnaire
      was sent to identify the use of people with spinal cord injury and professionals about word
      prediction software.

      The list of words is in the upper position of the screen based on the results of the
      questionnaire.

      Four combinations will be tested on each subject. Twelve Tetraplegics will be required in
      each group (one group using a virtual keyboard and one group using the physical keyboard)
      Each combination will be tried for 10 minutes.

      PHASE 2 :

      The second phase will evaluate the effeciency of a rehabilitation program reduced cognitive
      load generated by the software predictions words.

      The investigators propose an evaluation of the effects of 12 training sessions in a
      controlled, randomized, three parallel groups (experimental group : rehabilitation program, a
      group : a self-learning and a group : no learning).

      Text input tests will be performed before and after the training sessions for people who have
      rehabilitation program. For the other two groups, those will be reviewed one month after the
      first test.

      For this evaluation, a different text but with the same difficulty will be used. The order of
      execution will be randomized.

      At the end of the month the three groups will be evaluated according to the same procedures
      for the firts test.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Text Input Speed at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Phase 1 After every test (10 minutes) Phase 2 : 1 months</time_frame>
    <description>text input speed (characters/minute)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Errors at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Phase 1 After every test (10 minutes) Phase 2 : 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>We record errors in text entry test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Bit Rate at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Phase 1 After every test (10 minutes) Phase 2 : 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Bit rate de Wolpaw = log2N+P.log2P+(1-P).log2.((1-P)/(N-1))</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from item selection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Phase 1 After every test (10 minutes) Phase 2 : 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>items/total time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from rate enhancement at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Phase 1 After every test (10 minutes) Phase 2 : 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>rate enhancement: text input speed with word prediction software versus text input speed without word prediction software</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Keystrokes Saving at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Phase 1 After every test (10 minutes) Phase 2 : 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Number of keystrokes saved with word prediction software</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Prediction use at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Phase after every test (10 minutes) Phase 2 : 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Number of use of word prediction software</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Phase 1 After every test (10 minutes) Phase 2 : 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Satisfaction of people with spinal cord injury about word prediction software (visual analogue scale)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Cognitive load at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Phase 1 After every test (10 minutes) Phase 2 : 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Cognitive load of people with spinal cord injury (visual analogue scale)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Fatigue</measure>
    <time_frame>Phase 1 Before and After every test (10 minutes) Phase 2 : 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Fatigue of people with spinal cord injury (visual analogue scale)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Speed sensation at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>Phase 1 After every test (10 minutes) Phase 2 : 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>speed sensation of people with spinal cord injury with word prediction software (visual analogue scale)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Canadian Occupational Performance Measure (COPM) at 1 month</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>The Canadian Occupational Performance Measure (COPM)© is an individualized outcome measure designed for use by occupational therapists. The measure is designed to detect change in a client's self-perception of occupational performance over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Settings Word Prediction Software</condition>
  <condition>Rehabilitation Program</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rehabilitation Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>People with spinal cord injury who have a rehabilitation program on a word prediction software with an occupational therapist.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Self Training at Home Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>People with spinal cord injury who don't have a rehabilitation program with an occupational therapist but who have instructions for learning at home on a word prediction software</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No treatment Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>People with spinal cord injury who don't have instructions, rehabilitation programm on word prediction software. They have no treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rehabilitation program</intervention_name>
    <description>Rehabilitation program with an occupational therpasit
3 training sessions (one hour) per week for a month (12 sessions)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rehabilitation Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Self - Training at home</intervention_name>
    <description>Only instructions for a self - training at home</description>
    <arm_group_label>Self Training at Home Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>No rehabilitation program No instructions</description>
    <arm_group_label>No treatment Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        People with spinal cord injury : tetraplegia
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Tetraplegia (between C4 and C8 ASIA) more than 6 months.

          -  Can read and write

          -  No visual problems preventing the use of computers.

          -  Recipient of a Health Insurance Plan

          -  Having read information note.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Moving in progress or predictable
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Djamel Bensmail, MDPHD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>HOPITAL RAYMOND POINCARE</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Raymond Poincare</name>
      <address>
        <city>Garches</city>
        <zip>92380</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 26, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 1, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Centre d'Investigation Clinique et Technologique 805</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Pouplin Samuel</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>ergotherapeute (Occupational Therapist)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>word prediction software, text input speed, copm, occupational therapist, rehabilitation, spinal cord injury</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

