<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02768064</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>065015-HMO-CTIL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02768064</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Temporary Pacemaker in Transcatheter Aortic Valve Implantation Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>PAMIT</acronym>
  <official_title>Temporary Pacemaker in Transcatheter Aortic Valve Implantation Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hadassah Medical Organization</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hadassah Medical Organization</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      During Transcatheter aortic valve implantation (TAVI) procedure, a new valve is implanted.
      The valve can be CoreValve (Medtronic Company) or Edward SAPIENS (Edwards Company).

      All TAVI patients require a temporary pacemaker(PMK), which is usually performed by insertion
      of a standard temporary electrode through the femoral vein. The temporary PMK is associated
      with a small but significant rate of complications.

      The PMK is usually removed immediately at the end of the TAVI procedure, only when using the
      Edward SAPIENS valve. The CoreValve valve is more associated with conduction complications,
      and thus the PMK is later removed in these cases.

      PMK Complications seen include:

        -  Right Ventricle perforation by temporary electrode, leading to Pericardial bleeding, in
           some cases with Tamponade

        -  Infection

        -  Electrode dislocation causing In-effective pacing (and/or sensing)

        -  Prolonged bed rest

        -  Prolonged hospitalization

        -  Access related problems (hematoma, pneumothorax) In a review of a large cohort (1) of
           patients from Milan (JACC 2012) the rate of tamponade was 4.3% most of which was
           associated with the temporary PMK.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators had experienced not infrequent occurrences of temporary electrode
      associated tamponade, either acutely after Transcatheter aortic valve implantation (TAVI)
      completion, or delayed, in association with the electrode removal.

      The tamponade rate in patients with a temporary pacemaker(PMK) was 14/150 (9.3%). Not all
      tamponade cases were related to the temporary PMK, 2 occurred in the setting of catastrophic
      annular rupture and one of the first cases was related to the Left Ventricle stiff wire.

      The investigators also noted a significant prolongation of bed rest and hospital stay in
      patients with temporary PMK.

      Using a flexible permanent pacing electrode which is actively fixed to the Right Ventricle
      and is placed through the jugular vein will reduce pacing-related complication rates (due to
      the flexibility of the electrode), time to ambulation (due to the fixation of the electrode),
      hospital stay and also unnecessary PMK. Cost will also be reduced due to prevention of
      complications and reduction in Intensive Cardiac Care Unit time.

      Procedure time might be slightly prolonged since the placement of the standard electrode is
      more timely, however this prolongation is negligible, and the benefits of the flexible
      permanent pacing electrode are worth this prolongation
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with pericardial effusion with or without tamponade</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Pericardial effusion estimated by echocardiography, will be done during the hospitalization. It will be described as minimal/mild/moderate/large</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with Electrode Dislocation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Electrode Dislocation (sensing / pacing problems, requiring lead re-positioning).
The dislocation will be diagnosed by chest X ray or by sensing / pacing parameters.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with Bleeding complications</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Bleeding complications, described as local hematoma within the area of the electrode insertion, during the procedure or the hospitalization.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with Infections complications</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Infections complications, described as fever above 38.0 celsius degree or positive blood culture during the hospitalization after the procedure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with access site complications</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Access site complications describe as perforation of near organs (jugular artery)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with Pneumothorax</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Pneumothorax diagnosed by clinical examination and CXR within 3 days after the procedure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with pacemaker failure</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Rates of Pacing or sensing failure during the procedure, or the days after,</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>An implantation of permanent pacemaker</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>An implantation of permanent pacemaker (of any company, of any reason) within a year after TAVI in any hospital. The data will be collect from the hospital medical record system, and the patient report</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The time (in days) the patient was able to get down from his bed to a chair, after the procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>week</time_frame>
    <description>The number of days from the TAVI procedure to the first time the patient was able to get down from his bad and sit on a chair. The data will be collected from the nurse description in the medical record.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The time (in days) the patients has stayed in Intensive Cardiac Care Unit</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The number of days the patient was hospitalized in Intensive Cardiac Care Unit. The number will be calculated from the end of the TAVI procedure, till the patient went home or moved into the Cardiology department.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Cost of Pacing equipment</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Will be calculate by the sum of the electrode cost and the vascular shith cost</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The TAVI procedure time</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Will be taken from the technician report of starting and ending of the TAVI procedure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The TAVI fluoroscopic time</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Will be taken from technician report of Fluoroscopic time</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The permanent pacemaker activation (if implanted)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>If a pacemaker was implanted to the patient, the data will be collected from the interrogation of the pacemaker.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Aortic Stenosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Flexible screwed electrode</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the TAVI patients, during the intervention procedure, a temporary pacemaker will be implanted, using a flexible screwed electrode.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stiff standard electrode</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the TAVI patients, during the intervention procedure, a temporary pacemaker will be implanted, using a stiff standard temporary electrode</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>temporary pacemaker insertion</intervention_name>
    <description>Insertion of pacemaker electrode (Medtronic flow direct pacing catheter), connect to external pacemaker (Medtronic).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Flexible screwed electrode</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Stiff standard electrode</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All TAVI patients

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Existing contraindication for either femoral or jugular venous access

          -  Refused informed consent

          -  Permanent PMK

          -  Platelets count less than 50 K.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amir Orlev, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hadassah Medical Organization</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amir Orlev, Dr</last_name>
    <phone>972-2-6776564</phone>
    <email>amir.orlev@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>David Luria, Dr</last_name>
    <phone>972-2-6776564</phone>
    <email>dluria33@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Webb JG, Wood DA. Current status of transcatheter aortic valve replacement. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2012 Aug 7;60(6):483-92. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2012.01.071. Epub 2012 Jun 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22749306</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barbash IM, Waksman R, Pichard AD. Prevention of right ventricular perforation due to temporary pacemaker lead during transcatheter aortic valve replacement. JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2013 Apr;6(4):427. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2013.01.135.</citation>
    <PMID>23597613</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rezq A, Basavarajaiah S, Latib A, Takagi K, Hasegawa T, Figini F, Cioni M, Franco A, Montorfano M, Chieffo A, Maisano F, Corvaja N, Alfieri O, Colombo A. Incidence, management, and outcomes of cardiac tamponade during transcatheter aortic valve implantation: a single-center study. JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2012 Dec;5(12):1264-72. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2012.08.012.</citation>
    <PMID>23257375</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 10, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 10, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 11, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 10, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 10, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 11, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hadassah Medical Organization</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Orlev Amir</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aortic Valve Stenosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

