<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02768532</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1608051</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2016-001587-11</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02768532</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Value of Pharmacokinetic Assays in the Prediction of Induction and Maintenance Therapeutic Response in Crohn's Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>VEDO-PREDIRESP</acronym>
  <official_title>VEDO-PREDIRESP Project: Value of Pharmacokinetic Assays (Vedolizumab and Anti-vedolizumab Antibody) in the Prediction of Induction and Maintenance Therapeutic Response in Crohn's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Saint Etienne</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>theradiag</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre Hospitalier Universitaire de Saint Etienne</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Vedolizumab (VDZ) is a monoclonal antibody which has shown its efficacy in Crohn's disease by
      inducing and maintaining clinical response/remission. The French marketing authorization was
      obtained for Crohn's disease in patients in failure with anti-TNF (Tumor Necrosis Factor)
      agents.

      For Crohn's disease patients treated with vedolizumab, a strong association between
      vedolizumab serum levels and clinical response to induction and maintenance was demonstrated
      by anterior studies.

      It could be of paramount interest to early identify Crohn's Disease patients under
      vedolizumab who will be responders to vedolizumab induction and to identify those who will
      achieve clinical remission under maintenance therapy with vedolizumab.

      Researchers decided to assess the clinical response to vedolizumab induction at week 10. For
      clinically non-responders at week 10, an additional dose of 300 mg of vedolizumab will be
      infused at week 10 and then every four weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Vedolizumab (VDZ) is a monoclonal antibody that binds to the heterodimer alpha 4 beta 7
      integrin and which has shown its efficacy in Crohn's disease by inducing and maintaining
      clinical response/remission. The French marketing authorization was obtained for Crohn's
      disease in patients in failure with anti-TNF (Tumor Necrosis Factor) agents.

      For Crohn's disease patients treated with vedolizumab, a strong association between
      vedolizumab serum levels and clinical response to induction and maintenance was demonstrated
      by anterior studies.

      It could be of paramount interest to early identify Crohn's Disease patients under
      vedolizumab who will be responders to vedolizumab induction and to identify those who will
      achieve clinical remission under maintenance therapy with vedolizumab.

      Researchers decided to assess the clinical response to vedolizumab induction at week 10, as
      the Gemini III trial has reported, among patients who had experienced previous TNF (Tumor
      Necrosis Factor) antagonist failure. 15% of those given vedolizumab were in remission at week
      6 (P=0.433) versus 12% under placebo. At week 10, 26% under vedolizumab were in remission
      versus 12% in the placebo arm.

      Moreover, at week 10, the proportion of patients presenting a clinical response was
      significantly higher in Crohn's Disease patients treated with vedolizumab (46% vs 24%).

      In this study, for clinically non-responders at week 10, an additional dose of 300 mg of
      vedolizumab will be infused at week 10 and then every four weeks. In a post hoc analysis of
      GEMINI 2, additional dose of vedolizumab in patients clinically non responders to vedolizumab
      obtained a clinical remission in 33% of case.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vedolizumab concentration at week 6</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>The primary objective is to determine the optimal threshold of Vedolizumab serum concentration measured at week 6 capable to predict the clinical response at week 10 with Vedolizumab.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vedolizumab concentration at week 14</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 14</time_frame>
    <description>Determine the optimal threshold of Vedolizumab serum concentration measured at week 14 capable to predict the clinical remission at week 54 with Vedolizumab.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of Vedolizumab at week 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2</time_frame>
    <description>Investigating whether the Vedolizumab concentrations measured at week 2 are predictive of a clinical response and clinical remission at week 10.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of specific antibodies (anti-integrins) at week 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2</time_frame>
    <description>Investigating whether the presence of specific antibodies (anti-integrins) measured at week 2 are predictive of a clinical response and clinical remission at week 10.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of Vedolizumab at week 14</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 14</time_frame>
    <description>Investigating whether the Vedolizumab concentrations measured at week 14 are predictive of a clinical response and clinical remission at week 54.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of specific antibodies (anti-integrins) at week 14</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 14</time_frame>
    <description>Investigating whether the presence of specific antibodies (anti-integrins) measured at week 14 are predictive of a clinical response and clinical remission at week 54.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vedolizumab and calprotectin levels at week 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 2</time_frame>
    <description>Analyzing the value of Vedolizumab trough levels measured at week 2 to predict a subsequent normalization of fecal calprotectin levels (&lt; 250 micro grams/gram of stools) at week 10 under induction therapy with Vedolizumab in Crohn's Disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vedolizumab and calprotectin levels at week 14</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 14</time_frame>
    <description>Analyzing the value of Vedolizumab trough levels measured at week 14 to predict a subsequent normalization of fecal calprotectin levels (&lt; 250 micro grams/gram of stools) at week 54 under maintenance therapy with Vedolizumab in Crohn's Disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra and inter-individual heterogeneity of Vedolizumab levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 54</time_frame>
    <description>Investigating the intra and inter-individual heterogeneity of Vedolizumab levels within the time-course of Vedolizumab therapy, including the induction and maintenance phases. The dosage of Vedolizumab in patients blood will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of loss of clinical response</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 54</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing the proportion of loss of clinical response in responder Crohn's Disease patients as well as in primary non-responders requiring Vedolizumab dose-intensification within one-year of follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vedolizumab serum levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 54</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing the Vedolizumab serum levels prior and after Vedolizumab optimization in primary non-responder patients or experiencing a loss of response (secondary non-response) requiring additional infusions of Vedolizumab.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of Vedolizumab at week 54</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 54</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing the level of Vedolizumab between patients achieving a clinical remission or not at week 54.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific antibodies (anti-integrins) level at week 54</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 54</time_frame>
    <description>Comparing the specific antibodies (anti-integrins) levels between patients achieving a clinical remission or not at week 54.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">93</enrollment>
  <condition>Crohn Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Crohn's disease patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients will receive vedolizumab in compliance with the marketing authorization regimen (300 mg at weeks 0, 2, 6 and then every 8 weeks) in Crohn's Disease patients in clinical failure or intolerant to anti-TNF (Tumor Necrosis Factor) drugs. In case of lack of clinical response at week 10 or loss of response in the follow-up, all patients will be optimized with vedolizumab 300 mg at week 10 (additional infusion) and every following 4 weeks in contrast with responder patients at week 10 who will not have vedolizumab infusion at this time-point but will receive the next vedolizumab infusion at week 14 and then every 8 weeks, as recommended.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vedolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>During each 8 visits (screening, V0, V1, V2, V3, V4, V5, V6) at weeks-1, 0, 2, 6, 10, 14, 22, 54, respectively), the following parameters will be systematically recorded: Crohn's disease Activity Index (CDAI), adverse events.
Blood and fecal samples will be systematically collected at weeks 0, 2, 6, 10, 14, 22 and 54 for routine serum ultrasensitive CRP (C-Reactive Protein) and fecal calprotectin assessments and for vedolizumab pharmacokinetic parameters, including the vedolizumab trough levels and the specific anti-Vedolizumab antibodies. In case of loss of response, an additional measurement of serum CRP (C-Reactive Protein), fecal calprotectin and Vedolizumab pharmacologic parameters will be performed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Crohn's disease patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Entyvio</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria :

          -  Aged over 18 years

          -  Men or non-pregnant women

          -  Patients with a diagnosis of Crohn's disease who requires to start Vedolizumab

          -  Moderate to severe active Crohn's disease defined as a Crohn's disease Activity Index
             (CDAI) ranging from 220 to 450 points and fecal calprotectin levels &gt; 400 μg/g of
             stool

          -  Crohn's Disease patients with previous failure with TNF (Tumor Necrosis Factor)
             antagonist agents and unacceptable side-effects from steroids, and/or
             immunosuppressive agents (i.e., azathioprine, 6-mercaptopurine, or methotrexate). In
             France, Vedolizumab has to be prescribed only in patients in failure or intolerant to
             anti-TNF.

          -  Stable doses of oral prednisone (≤30 mg per day) or budesonide (≤9 mg per day),
             concomitant immunosuppressive agents, mesalamine, and antibiotics are allowed at
             stable dose for at least three months before inclusion. Steroid tapering has to be set
             up at Week 10 after starting Vedolizumab, according to the European Crohn and Colitis
             Organisation (ECCO) recommendations with a progressive decrease of steroids of 5
             mg/day every week until complete withdrawn.

          -  Informed written consent given.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Existing pregnancy, lactation, or intended pregnancy within the next 15 months

          -  Minors or History of disease, including mental/emotional disorder that might interfere
             with their participation in the study

          -  Serious secondary illnesses of an acute or chronic nature, which in the opinion of the
             investigator renders the patient unsuitable for inclusion into the study

          -  Inability to comply with the protocol requirements

          -  Inability to fill in the diary cards during the last 7 days before each visit

          -  Presence of an ileo-/colonic stoma

          -  Patients with known colonic stricture and exclusive or predominant anal or perineal
             Crohn's disease lesions

          -  Known previous or concurrent malignancy (other than that considered surgically cured,
             with no evidence for recurrence for 5 years)

          -  Short bowel syndrome

          -  Previous treatments with vedolizumab, natalizumab, efalizumab or rituximab.

          -  Previous treatment with adalimumab within 30 days prior enrollment or infliximab and
             certolizumab pegol within 60 days before enrollment

          -  Prior extensive colonic resection, obstructive (symptomatic) intestinal stricture,
             abdominal abscess, active or latent tuberculosis,

          -  Clostridium difficile superinfection;

          -  Indeterminate colitis

          -  Concomitant leukocyte apheresis.

          -  Any contraindication to vedolizumab therapy

          -  Patients who denied the protocol, not ability to accept or sign consent of the
             protocol

          -  Subject involved in another clinical trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xavier Roblin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CHU SAINT ETIENNE</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Xavier Roblin, MD</last_name>
    <email>xavier.roblin@chu-st-etienne.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Florence Rancon, CRA</last_name>
    <email>florence.rancon@chu-st-etienne.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Kremlin Bicetre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <state>Le Kremlin-Bicêtre</state>
        <zip>94270</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Franck CARBONNEL, MD</last_name>
      <email>fcarbonnel7@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Franck Carbonnel, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU d'Amiens</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amiens</city>
        <zip>80000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jean-Louis Dupas, MD</last_name>
      <email>dupas.jean-louis@chu-amiens.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jean-Louis Dupas, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU L'Archet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nice</city>
        <zip>06200</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jérôme Filippi</last_name>
      <email>filippi.j@chu-nice.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jérôme Filippi, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Lyon-Sud, Hospices Civils de Lyon, PIERRE-BENITE</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pierre Bénite</city>
        <zip>69230</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Stephane Nancey, MD</last_name>
      <email>stephane.nancey@chu-lyon.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephane Nancey, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gilles Boschetti, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chu Saint Etienne</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Etienne</city>
        <zip>42055</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Xavier Roblin, MD</last_name>
      <email>xavier.roblin@chu-st-etienne.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Xavier Roblin, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nicolas Willet, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Emilie Del Tedesco, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pauline Veyrard, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 2, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 10, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 11, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 19, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 19, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Crohn's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Vedolizumab</keyword>
  <keyword>TNF (Tumor Necrosis Factor)</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical response</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical remission</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Crohn Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vedolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

