<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02762591</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ACP-103-036</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02762591</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Expanded Access of Pimavanserin for Patients With PD Psychosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Expanded Access Program of Pimavanserin in Patients With Parkinson's Disease Psychosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ACADIA Pharmaceuticals Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ACADIA Pharmaceuticals Inc.</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this program is to provide patients with PDP access to pimavanserin until the
      product receives marketing approval from the FDA and is commercially available.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Approved for marketing</overall_status>
  <study_type>Expanded Access</study_type>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease Psychosis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pimavanserin tartrate</intervention_name>
    <description>Pimavanserin tartrate 40 mg, tablet, taken as two 20 mg tablets, once daily by mouth</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient meets one of the following criteria:

               1. Patient has participated in a previous study of pimavanserin for Parkinson's
                  disease psychosis (PDP)

               2. New (&quot;De novo&quot;) patients

          2. A clinical diagnosis of Parkinson's disease with a minimum duration of 1 year

          3. Female patients must be of non-childbearing potential

          4. Psychotic symptoms must have developed after Parkinson's disease diagnosis was
             established

          5. Patient that has received stereotaxic surgery for subthalamic nucleus deep brain
             stimulation must be at least 6 months post-surgery and the stimulator settings must
             have been stable for at least 1 month prior to Study Day 1 (Baseline) and must remain
             stable during the trial

          6. The patient or Legally Authorized Representative (LAR) is willing and able to provide
             consent

          7. The patient or LAR is willing and able to adequately communicate in English.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient has a history of significant psychotic disorders prior to or concomitantly
             with the diagnosis of Parkinson's disease including, but not limited to, schizophrenia
             or bipolar disorder

          2. Patient has had dementia prior to or concurrently with their diagnosis of Parkinson's
             disease that may be inconsistent with a Parkinson's diagnosis

          3. Patient has current evidence of a serious and/or unstable cardiovascular, respiratory,
             gastrointestinal, renal, hematologic, or other medical disorder, including cancer or
             malignancies, which would affect the patient's ability to participate in the program

          4. Patient has had a myocardial infarction in last six months

          5. Patient has any surgery planned during the screening, treatment, or follow-up periods

        Patients will be evaluated at screening to ensure that all criteria for study participation
        are met. These evaluations will include specific measures of psychosis severity, delirium,
        dementia, cardiovascular condition, and pregnancy status. Patients may be excluded from the
        study based on these assessments (and specifically if it is determined that their baseline
        health and psychiatric condition do not meet all pre-specified entry criteria).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 5, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 17, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 17, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pimavanserin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

