<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02761707</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>827731</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02761707</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Biomarkers in Neural Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Biomarkers in Neural Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Michael J. Fox Foundation for Parkinson's Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study seeks to establish the sensitivity and specificity of what appears to be a unique
      brainstem biomarker of Parkinson's Disease (PD) - an electrically induced olygosynaptic
      nasotrigeminal reflex response - in differentiating early stage PD from normal controls and
      from patients with various other neurodegenerative diseases. This study will additionally
      compare the biomarker to olfactory testing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Parkinson's disease (PD), a devastating age-related disease that is clinically defined by its
      effects on the motor system, afflicts more than six million people worldwide, imposing
      enormous burdens on patients, relatives, caretakers, and society in general. Diagnostic
      errors are common, particularly as symptoms first arise. The most common misdiagnoses are
      Alzheimer's disease (AD), essential tremor, and vascular pseudo-Parkinson's Disease. An
      accurate diagnosis is typically made at a later stage of the disease when marked and
      irreversible damage has occurred within the motor control system of the brain. Sensitive and
      specific biomarkers of the early stages of PD are urgently needed. Identification of such
      markers is critical for the development and assessment of medications and other interventions
      designed to eliminate or reduce the gradual and irreversible decline of neurons involved in
      the disorder. This study seeks to establish the sensitivity and specificity of what appears
      to be a unique brainstem biomarker of PD - an electrically induced trigeminal nerve blink
      reflex response - in differentiation of early stage PD from normal controls and such
      neurodegenerative diseases as early stage AD, progressive supranuclear palsy (PSP), and
      diffuse Lewy Body disease (DLBD). This study will additionally compare the biomarker to
      olfactory test results.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Latency, amplitude, and area under the curve of brainstem reflex response</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Hour</time_frame>
    <description>Latency, amplitude, and area under the curve of electrical brainstem reflex response of trigeminal nerve branches measured on the face musculature (before and after short-term visual deprivation).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Score on the University of Pennsylvania Smell Identification Test</measure>
    <time_frame>20 Minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The number of correct odor identification responses out of 40 from the standardized University of Pennsylvania Smell Identification Test (before and after short-term visual deprivation).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Score on the Odor Discrimination/Memory Test</measure>
    <time_frame>30 Minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The number of correct responses in picking out an odor previously presented from three foils 10, 30, and 60 sec later using the standardized Odor Detection/Discrimination Test (before and after short-term visual deprivation).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Score on an Odor Detection Threshold Test</measure>
    <time_frame>20 Minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The average of 7 reversals in a staircase odor detection threshold test that employs phenyl ethyl alcohol (rose oil) concentrations ranging from -7 to -2 log dilutions in light mineral oil.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>11</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">440</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Alzheimer's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Progressive Supranuclear Palsy</condition>
  <condition>Essential Tremor</condition>
  <condition>Multiple System Atrophy</condition>
  <condition>Drug Induced Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Diffuse Lewy Body Disease</condition>
  <condition>Myasthenia Gravis</condition>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injuries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson's Disease</arm_group_label>
    <description>Non-smokers, ages 18-80, diagnosed with Parkinson's Disease. Must be Hoehn and Yahr stage 2 or less with a history of motor symptoms less than two years.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alzheimer's Disease</arm_group_label>
    <description>Non-smokers, ages 18-80, diagnosed with Alzheimer's Disease. Must meet the 2011 National Institute on Aging-Alzheimer's Association and the 1984 National Institute for Neurological and Communicative Disorders and Stroke-Alzheimer's disease and Related Disorders Association criteria for probable AD.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Progressive Supranuclear Palsy</arm_group_label>
    <description>Non-smokers, ages 18-80, diagnosed with Progressive Supranuclear Palsy. Must meet the NINDS-SPSP criteria for probable PSP, which requires vertical supranuclear gaze palsy, prominent postural instability, and falls in the first year of onset, as well as a number of other clinical features.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Essential Tremor</arm_group_label>
    <description>Non-smokers, ages 18-80, diagnosed with Essential Tremor.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Drug-Induced Parkinson's Disease</arm_group_label>
    <description>Non-smokers, ages 18-80, diagnosed with Drug-Induced Parkinson's Disease.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Myasthenia Gravis</arm_group_label>
    <description>Non-smokers, ages 18-80, diagnosed with Myasthenia Gravis.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Multiple System Atrophy</arm_group_label>
    <description>Non-smokers, ages 18-80, who have been diagnosed with Multiple System Atrophy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Diffuse Lewy Body Disease</arm_group_label>
    <description>Non-smokers, ages 18-80, diagnosed with Diffuse Lewy Body Disease. Must meet the Consensus Criteria for the clinical diagnosis of DLBD.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Non-smokers, ages 18-80, with no neurodegenerative disease, and no first-degree relatives with a neurodegenerative disease.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Spinal Cord Injury</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Asymptomatic Relatives</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Electrical Brainstem Responses</intervention_name>
    <description>Eye blink responses will be induced using standard stimulating electrodes employed in surface electromyography (EMG). The subjects will recline with their eyes gently closed. Sticky electrodes will be placed to the left and below the left eye. 6 different facial regions will be stimulated. The electrical stimulation will be kept constant during the test sessions. To prevent habituation, the stimuli will be delivered randomly at intervals of 45-60 sec. Four 0.2 msec pulses will be presented. In some cases, paired pulse stimulation will be performed, and a conditioning stimulus will be applied to the target facial regions at the following intervals: 10, 200, 400, 600 and 800 msec. 4 pulses will be presented at each stimulus interval with randomized interval and pulse sequences.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson's Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Alzheimer's Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Progressive Supranuclear Palsy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Essential Tremor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Drug-Induced Parkinson's Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Myasthenia Gravis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Multiple System Atrophy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Diffuse Lewy Body Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Spinal Cord Injury</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Asymptomatic Relatives</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Electromyography</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Olfactory Tests</intervention_name>
    <description>Olfactory testing will be performed using standard tests. The University of Pennsylvania Smell Identification Test (UPSIT) assesses a subjects ability to identify odors in a forced choice format. The Snap and Sniff Threshold Test provides a threshold measure of phenyl ethyl alcohol. Short-term odor memory will be assessed using a standardized 12-item four-alternative forced-choice Odor Memory Test. This non-lexical test employs 10-, 30-, and 60-second delay intervals between the presentation of the target odorant and the first of four successively presented odors from which the target is to be selected.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson's Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Alzheimer's Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Progressive Supranuclear Palsy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Essential Tremor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Drug-Induced Parkinson's Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Myasthenia Gravis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Multiple System Atrophy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Diffuse Lewy Body Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Spinal Cord Injury</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Asymptomatic Relatives</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Visual Deprivation</intervention_name>
    <description>During a 2-hour visual deprivation period, subjects will wear comfortable light-tight goggles with lenses that have been blackened by flat black paint. Subjects will be given the opportunity to recline comfortable in a padded reclining chair during this time.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson's Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peripheral Nerve Stimulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Electrical stimulation will be applied to a nerve of your arm. Sticky electrode pads will also be placed on a hand muscle. You will receive electrical stimulations that lasts less than a second. The stimulations will make your muscle twitch.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Parkinson's Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Alzheimer's Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Progressive Supranuclear Palsy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Essential Tremor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Drug-Induced Parkinson's Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Myasthenia Gravis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Multiple System Atrophy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Diffuse Lewy Body Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Spinal Cord Injury</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Asymptomatic Relatives</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Repetitive Nerve Stimulation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Normal controls and patients with such neural disorders as Parkinson's Disease(PD),
        Alzheimer's disease (AD), progressive supranuclear palsy (PSP), essential tremor (ET),
        dementia with Parkinson's disease (D-PD), myasthenia gravis (MG), multiple system atrophy
        (MSA), diffuse Lewy body disease (DLBD), and Spinal Cord Injury (SCI). None will be
        cigarette smokers. The patients will be diagnosed accord to current consensus criteria. The
        healthy controls will be matched to the PD patients on such variables as sex, age,
        education level, and ethnicity. The Healthy Controls will be asked to answer questions
        regarding the disease state of their first degree family members to ensure that these first
        degree family members do not have a neurodegenerative diseases. Every effort will be made
        to include women and minority subjects.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The Parkinson's disease (PD) patients will be Hoehn and Yahr stage 2 or less with a
             history of motor symptoms less than two years.

          -  The Alzheimer's disease (AD) patients will meet the 2011 National Institute on
             Aging-Alzheimer's Association and the 1984 National Institute for Neurological and
             Communicative Disorders and Stroke-Alzheimer's disease and Related Disorders
             Association criteria for probable AD.

          -  The progressive supranuclear palsy (PSP) patients will have met the NINDS-SPSP
             criteria for probable PSP, which requires vertical supranuclear gaze palsy, prominent
             postural instability, and falls in the first year of onset, as well as a number of
             other clinical features.

          -  The DLBD patients will meet the Consensus Criteria for the clinical diagnosis of DLBD.

          -  The healthy controls will be matched to the PD patients on such variables as sex, age,
             education level, and ethnicity.

          -  The essential tremor (ET), multiple system atrophy (MSA), myasthenia gravis (MG),
             multiple system atrophy (MSA), Parkinson's disease dementia (D-PD), and Spinal Cord
             Injury (SCI) patients will meet the generally-accepted diagnostic criteria for these
             disorders.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Drug abuse.

          -  Any other known and potentially confounding condition that could reasonably be
             expected to interfere with the study assessments.

          -  Under age 18.

          -  Over age 80.

          -  Smoker.

          -  Pregnant or nursing.

          -  Healthy control with a first degree relative who has a neurodegenerative disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fidias Leon-Sarmiento, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard L Doty, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Fidias Leon-Sarmiento, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>215-662-6580</phone>
    <email>feleones@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Richard L Doty, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>215-662-6580</phone>
    <email>Richard.Doty@uphs.upenn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard Doty, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>215-662-6580</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Fidias Leon-Sarmiento, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>215-662-6580</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 18, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 4, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Essential Tremor</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myasthenia Gravis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Supranuclear Palsy, Progressive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple System Atrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Shy-Drager Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lewy Body Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

