<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02769052</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>51799115.3.1001.5404</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02769052</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TENS Self-applied in the Complementary Treatment of Deep Endometriosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>tici_mira</acronym>
  <official_title>Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation (TENS) Self-applied as Complementary Treatment for Pain and Its Impact on Biomechanics, Quality of Life and Sexuality of Women With Deep Endometriosis: Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Campinas, Brazil</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Campinas, Brazil</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective: to evaluate the effectiveness of Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation
      (TENS) self-applied for the treatment of pain and the impact of this therapy on biomechanics,
      quality of life and sexuality of women with deep endometriosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  Women will be selected to participate in the study between June 2016 to June 2017, from
           medical records research and routine queries in Endometriosis clinic of the Gynecology's
           Hospital of University of Campinas (UNICAMP) and the clinic of Gynecology (Endometriosis
           routine queries) of the Hospital of University of São Paulo (USP). All women will
           respond to the Check List for inclusion in the study and will sign an informed consent
           form.

        -  The women selected will be randomized into two distinct groups: follow-up/treatment
           group (FTG) composed of three phases of 8 weeks each or treatment/monitoring group (TFG)
           consists of two phases of 8 weeks each. The randomization will be through sealed brown
           envelopes, whose numerical sequence will be generated by computer programming in
           Statistical Analysis System (SAS), held by a person not participating in the study. Once
           allocated, all women respond to a clinical and socio-demographic questionnaire, Visual
           analog scale; Deep Dyspareunia scale; Diagram of Location and characterization of Pain;
           Endometriosis Health Profile (EHP-30); Female Sexual Function Index pre-and
           post-treatment. In addition, the woman will fill a daily control of pain. After
           completing the filling of the instruments will be held a postural evaluation for image
           capture. The woman will be accompanied by 12 months with regular contact to the review
           board.

      All procedures of the study will be carried out by the same researcher, to enforce the search
      protocol. After the end of the collection, all data will be entered in the Excel program for
      Windows and conferred for a second digitizer.

        -  The sample size calculation was based on the pilot study developed by Mira et al. (2015)
           whereas the use of the TENS for relief of chronic pelvic pain and deep dyspareunia
           generated by endometriosis, whose pre-and post-treatment discomfort was assessed by
           Visual analog scale (EVA). The number of women in this study was of 22 women divided
           into two treatment groups. Applied for the calculation of sample size, the t test for
           independent variables to the study cited and given a power of test 90% and significance
           level of 5%, the sample size obtained was of 24 patients in total. Considering the
           following loss of 20%, the total number shall be 29 women, divided into two groups:
           follow-up/treatment group (n = 15) and treatment/monitoring group (n = 14). For better
           quantification of all the variables involved, we will seek ideally a total of 80 women,
           divided into two groups (n = 40).

        -  The data loss for any reason, will not be considered in the analysis and will be
           reported.

        -  The data obtained will be described by mean ± standard deviation. The results will be
           tested for normal distribution using the Shapiro-Wilk test. For analysis of the second
           sample groups, features will be used the Fisher exact test. For comparison of means
           obtained from scales and questionnaires, pre-and post-intervention, t-test will be used
           or non-parametric analog, for each variable, previously cited. The comparison of
           variables between groups will be analyzed by t test or nonparametric analog.
           Significance will be considered through the value p &lt;.05. The data will be analyzed by
           intention to treat. The software used for statistical analysis SAS version 9.2.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of Pelvic Pain</measure>
    <time_frame>up to one year</time_frame>
    <description>The chronic pelvic pain will be evaluated by specific instrument (Visual Analogue Scale).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of Pain during the relation</measure>
    <time_frame>up to one year</time_frame>
    <description>The deep dyspareunia will be evaluated by specific instrument (Deep Dyspareunia Scale).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of The global pain</measure>
    <time_frame>up to one year</time_frame>
    <description>The global pain will be evaluated by Diagram Localization and Characterization of Pain (design body representation and adaptation McGill).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>up to one year</time_frame>
    <description>The quality of life will be accessed by one specific questionnaire for endometriosis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of Sexuality</measure>
    <time_frame>up to one year</time_frame>
    <description>The sexuality will be accessed by questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of Posture</measure>
    <time_frame>up to one year</time_frame>
    <description>The posture will be evaluated through image capture.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Endometriosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Follow-up/Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Composed of three phases of 8 weeks each (follow-up - treatment - follow-up). The treatment using the self-applied Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation (TENS) will prescribe with daily application, twice a day for 20 minutes each application.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment/Follow-up Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Composed of two phases of 8 weeks each (treatment - follow-up). The treatment using the self-applied Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation (TENS) will prescribe with daily application, twice a day for 20 minutes each application.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcutaneous Electrical Nerve Stimulation (TENS)</intervention_name>
    <description>Electrotherapy through self-applied device .</description>
    <arm_group_label>Follow-up/Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment/Follow-up Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women at reproductive age;

          -  18 and 50 years;

          -  diagnosis of deep endometriosis (cul-de-sac and intestinal lesions);

          -  using hormonal treatment at least 3 months;

          -  persistence of chronic pelvic pain and/or dyspareunia.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with decreased skin sensitivity;

          -  pregnant women;

          -  women with pacemaker implants;

          -  cutaneous hypersensitivity (allergic reactions to gel or electrode);

          -  women with epilepsy;

          -  cardiac (cardiac arrhythmia);

          -  osteosynthesis in the application place;

          -  a solution of discontinuity of the skin;

          -  malignant tumors;

          -  acute inflammatory disease;

          -  other gynecological associated pathologies;

          -  a cognitive deficiency that precludes the understanding of instruments and/or
             instructions for self-applied of TENS.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ticiana AA Mira, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Campinas</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cristina L Benetti-Pinto, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Campinas</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gynecology Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Campinas</city>
        <state>São Paulo</state>
        <zip>13.083-881</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dizerega GS, Barber DL, Hodgen GD. Endometriosis: role of ovarian steroids in initiation, maintenance, and suppression. Fertil Steril. 1980 Jun;33(6):649-53.</citation>
    <PMID>6769717</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kennedy S, Bergqvist A, Chapron C, D'Hooghe T, Dunselman G, Greb R, Hummelshoj L, Prentice A, Saridogan E; ESHRE Special Interest Group for Endometriosis and Endometrium Guideline Development Group. ESHRE guideline for the diagnosis and treatment of endometriosis. Hum Reprod. 2005 Oct;20(10):2698-704. Epub 2005 Jun 24.</citation>
    <PMID>15980014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ferrero S, Esposito F, Abbamonte LH, Anserini P, Remorgida V, Ragni N. Quality of sex life in women with endometriosis and deep dyspareunia. Fertil Steril. 2005 Mar;83(3):573-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15749483</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chwalisz K, Brenner RM, Fuhrmann UU, Hess-Stumpp H, Elger W. Antiproliferative effects of progesterone antagonists and progesterone receptor modulators on the endometrium. Steroids. 2000 Oct-Nov;65(10-11):741-51. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11108885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carpenter SE, Tjaden B, Rock JA, Kimball A. The effect of regular exercise on women receiving danazol for treatment of endometriosis. Int J Gynaecol Obstet. 1995 Jun;49(3):299-304.</citation>
    <PMID>9764869</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Melzack R, Wall PD. Pain mechanisms: a new theory. Science. 1965 Nov 19;150(3699):971-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>5320816</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scott J, Huskisson EC. Graphic representation of pain. Pain. 1976 Jun;2(2):175-84.</citation>
    <PMID>1026900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones G, Kennedy S, Barnard A, Wong J, Jenkinson C. Development of an endometriosis quality-of-life instrument: The Endometriosis Health Profile-30. Obstet Gynecol. 2001 Aug;98(2):258-64.</citation>
    <PMID>11506842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mengarda CV, Passos EP, Picon P, Costa AF, Picon PD. [Validation of Brazilian Portuguese version of quality of life questionnaire for women with endometriosis (Endometriosis Health Profile Questionnaire--EHP-30)]. Rev Bras Ginecol Obstet. 2008 Aug;30(8):384-92. Portuguese.</citation>
    <PMID>19142521</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Minson FP, Abrão MS, Sardá Júnior J, Kraychete DC, Podgaec S, Assis FD. [Importance of quality of life assessment in patients with endometriosis]. Rev Bras Ginecol Obstet. 2012 Jan;34(1):11-5. Portuguese.</citation>
    <PMID>22358342</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosen R, Brown C, Heiman J, Leiblum S, Meston C, Shabsigh R, Ferguson D, D'Agostino R Jr. The Female Sexual Function Index (FSFI): a multidimensional self-report instrument for the assessment of female sexual function. J Sex Marital Ther. 2000 Apr-Jun;26(2):191-208.</citation>
    <PMID>10782451</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 6, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 10, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 11, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Campinas, Brazil</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ticiana Aparecida Alves de Mira</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MSc</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>endometriosis</keyword>
  <keyword>dyspareunia</keyword>
  <keyword>physical therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>sexuality</keyword>
  <keyword>transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Endometriosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

