<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02764541</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-052</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02764541</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Palbociclib and Endocrine Therapy for LObular Breast Cancer Preoperative Study (PELOPS)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Palbociclib and Endocrine Therapy for LObular Breast Cancer Preoperative Study (PELOPS): A Randomized Phase II Study of Palbociclib With Letrozole Versus Letrozole Alone for Invasive Lobular Carcinoma and Invasive Ductal Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This research study is evaluating how well Breast Cancer responds to preoperative treatment
      with Endocrine treatment in combination with a drug called Palbociclib or Endocrine treatment
      alone as possible treatments for Hormone Receptor Positive Breast Cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open label phase II neoadjuvant clinical trial of Palbociclib in combination with
      endocrine therapy for hormone receptor positive early-stage breast cancer. The planned sample
      size is 180 participants. The study includes a &quot;window treatment&quot; phase followed by a
      treatment phase. In the window phase, participants will be treated with a two-week course of
      tamoxifen (Arm A) or letrozole (Arm B). In the treatment phase participants will be
      randomized to receive endocrine therapy in combination with palbociclib (Arm C) or endocrine
      therapy alone (Arm D) for a total duration of 24 weeks. Premenopausal patients with either
      invasive lobular or ductal carcinoma will be eligible to enroll directly into the treatment
      phase of the study. The study has two co-primary objectives: 1) To evaluate the difference in
      anti-proliferative activity of letrozole versus tamoxifen measured by changes in Ki67 from
      baseline to research biopsy (day 15) within cohorts of hormone receptor positive breast
      cancer for patients with invasive lobular and ductal carcinoma. 2) To evaluate the pathologic
      complete response (pCR) of endocrine therapy plus palbociclib and of endocrine therapy alone
      in breast cancer patients diagnosed with hormone receptor positive invasive breast cancer.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Window Phase:To evaluate the difference in anti-proliferative activity of letrozole versus tamoxifen within cohorts of hormone receptor positive breast cancer for patients with invasive lobular and ductal carcinoma.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Anti-proliferative activity will be calculated by the fold-change in percent of Ki67 from baseline and Day 15 research biopsy samples.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Phase: To evaluate the pathologic complete response (pCR) of endocrine therapy plus palbociclib and of endocrine therapy alone in breast cancer patients diagnosed with hormone receptor positive invasive breast cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
    <description>Pathologic response will be reported as the Residual Cancer Burden (RCB). RCB will be calculated using the MD Anderson Residual Cancer Burden calculator.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overrall Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progressive Free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">180</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A Tamoxifen followed by Endocrine Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tamoxifen is given in the Window of Treatment phase for 2 weeks followed by Endocrine Therapy for 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B Letrozole Followed By Endocrine Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Letrozole is given in the Window of Treatment phase for 2 weeks followed by Endocrine Therapy for 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tamoxifen Followed By Endocrine Therapy and Palbociclib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tamoxifen is given in the Window of Treatment phase for 2 weeks followed by Endocrine Therapy in combination with Palbociclib for 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Letrozole Followed By Endocrine Therapy and Palbociclib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Letrozole is given in the Window of Treatment phase for 2 weeks followed by Endocrine Therapy in combination with Palbociclib for 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Letrozole</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B Letrozole Followed By Endocrine Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Letrozole Followed By Endocrine Therapy and Palbociclib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Femara</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tamoxifen</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A Tamoxifen followed by Endocrine Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Tamoxifen Followed By Endocrine Therapy and Palbociclib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Soltanox</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Palbociclib</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Tamoxifen Followed By Endocrine Therapy and Palbociclib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Letrozole Followed By Endocrine Therapy and Palbociclib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ibrance</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endocrine Therapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A Tamoxifen followed by Endocrine Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B Letrozole Followed By Endocrine Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Tamoxifen Followed By Endocrine Therapy and Palbociclib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Letrozole Followed By Endocrine Therapy and Palbociclib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nolvadex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have Stage I to III histologically confirmed invasive carcinoma of the
             breast. A minimum tumor size of at least 1.5 cm determined by physical exam or imaging
             (whichever is larger) is required.

          -  Patients must have histologically confirmed hormone receptor positive (ER and/or PR),
             HER2 negative, invasive breast cancer. ER, PR and HER2 measurements should be
             performed according to institutional guidelines, in a CLIA-approved setting in the US
             or certified laboratories for Non-US regions. Cut-off values for positive/negative
             staining should be in accordance with current ASCO/CAP (American Society of Clinical
             Oncology/College of American Pathologists) guidelines. Central confirmation is not
             required for ER, PR, or HER statuses.

          -  Patients with equivocal HER2 in situ hybridization results according to current
             ASCO/CAP guidelines are allowed, as long as the clinician has determined that they
             should be treated as HER2 negative.

          -  For the window phase: Patients must have histologically confirmed invasive lobular
             carcinoma or invasive ductal carcinoma. No central confirmation of histological
             subtype is necessary for enrollment.

          -  For the treatment phase: Patients with any histological subtype are eligible.

          -  Women 18 years of age. Men are not eligible.

          -  ECOG performance status 0 or 1

          -  Required laboratory values:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1,500/mm3

               -  Platelets ≥ 100,000/mm3

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 10g/dL

               -  Total serum bilirubin ≤ ULN; or total bilirubin ≤ 3.0 × ULN with direct bilirubin
                  within normal range in patients with documented Gilbert's Syndrome

               -  Aspartate amino transferase (AST or SGOT) and alanine amino transferase (ALT or
                  SGPT) ≤ 2.0 × institutional ULN

               -  Serum creatinine within normal institutional limits or creatinine clearance ≥ 60
                  mL/min/1.73 m2 for patients with serum creatinine levels above institutional ULN

          -  Postmenopausal patients defined as no spontaneous menses ≥1 year (12 months) or post
             bilateral surgical oophorectomy. Premenopausal patients are eligible to participate
             provided they are considered in chemical menopause. Premenopausal patients should
             receive ongoing treatment with LHRH agonists (goserolin or leuprolide). Premenopausal
             patients must be enrolled directly into the treatment phase of the study.

          -  Patient must agree to the required research biopsies at baseline and after the
             two-week treatment with endocrine therapy in the initial part of the study (&quot;window
             phase&quot;); or at baseline and after two-week treated with endocrine therapy plus or
             minus palbociclib for those patients enrolled directly into the treatment phase of the
             study.

          -  Patients must be able and willing to swallow and retain oral medication without a
             condition that would interfere with enteric absorption.

          -  Breast imaging should include imaging of the ipsilateral axilla. For subjects with a
             clinically negative axilla, a sentinel lymph node biopsy will be performed either
             before or after preoperative therapy at the discretion of the subject's physicians.
             For subjects with a clinically positive axilla, a needle aspiration, core biopsy or
             SLN procedure will be performed to determine the presence of metastatic disease in the
             lymph nodes.

          -  Patients with multifocal or multicentric disease are eligible if the treating
             clinician has determined the patient should be treated as ER+ and HER2- negative.

          -  Bilateral breast cancers are allowed if the treating clinician has determined the
             patient should be treated as ER+ and HER2- negative.

          -  Serum or urine pregnancy test must be negative in women judged premenopausal within 7
             days of randomization, or in women with amenorrhea of less than 12 months at time of
             randomization. Pregnancy testing does not need to be pursued in patients who are
             judged as postmenopausal before randomization, as determined by local practice, or who
             have undergone bilateral oophorectomy, total hysterectomy, or bilateral tubal
             ligation.

          -  Premenopausal patients must agree to use adequate contraception for the duration of
             protocol treatment and for 6 months after the last treatment with palbociclib.
             Adequate contraception is defined as one highly effective form (i.e. abstinence, male
             or female sterilization) OR two effective forms (e.g. non-hormonal IUD and
             condom/occlusive cap with spermicidal foam / gel / film / cream/ suppository).
             Hormonal contraceptive methods are not allowed.

          -  Patients with a history of ipsilateral or contralateral DCIS are eligible.

          -  Patients may concurrently receive bisphosphonates or rank ligand inhibitors while on
             this study if necessary for treatment or prevention of osteopenia or osteoporosis.
             Prior treatment with LHRH agonists is allowed for premenopausal women. Topical vaginal
             estrogen therapy is allowable.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Concurrent therapy with other Investigational Products.

          -  Prior therapy with any CDK inhibitor.

          -  Patients with Stage IV breast cancer are not eligible. Baseline staging to document
             absence of metastatic disease is not required, however is recommended as determined by
             institutional practice (in patients where there may be a reasonable suspicion of
             advanced disease e.g., large tumors, clinically positive axillary lymph nodes, signs
             and symptoms). If performed, reports of these examinations must be available.
             Examination type for staging, i.e. X-ray, sonography, bone scans, CT, MRI, and/or
             PET-CT, is at the discretion of the investigator.

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of chemical or biologic
             composition similar to palbociclib.

          -  Patients receiving any medications or substances that are potent inhibitors or
             inducers of CYP3A isoenzymes within 7 days of randomization

          -  Uncontrolled illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active infection,
             symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia,
             diabetes, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements. Ability to comply with study requirements is to be assessed by
             each investigator at the time of screening for study participation.

          -  Pregnant women, or women of childbearing potential without a negative pregnancy test
             (serum or urine) within 7 days prior to randomization, irrespective of the method of
             contraception used, are excluded from this study because the effect of palbociclib on
             a developing fetus is unknown. Breastfeeding must be discontinued prior to study
             entry.

          -  Patients with a history of any malignancy are ineligible except for the following
             circumstances:

               -  Patients with a malignancy history other than invasive breast cancer are eligible
                  if they have no active malignancy and are deemed by the investigator to be at low
                  risk for recurrence of that malignancy.

               -  Patients with the following cancers are eligible: ductal carcinoma in situ of the
                  breast, cervical cancer in situ, and non-metastatic non-melanomatous skin
                  cancers.

          -  Patients on combination antiretroviral therapy, i.e. those who are HIV-positive, are
             ineligible because of the potential for pharmacokinetic interactions or increased
             immunosuppression with palbociclib. HIV testing is not required, but patients must not
             be known to be HIV-positive.

          -  Patients receiving concurrent exogenous hormone therapy (hormone replacement therapy,
             oral or any other hormonal contraceptives such as hormonal contraceptive coil are not
             eligible.

          -  Patients are not eligible if they have previously received endocrine therapy within 5
             years prior to diagnosis of the current malignancy. This includes use for prophylactic
             reasons, including treatment of osteoporosis or cancer prevention with tamoxifen,
             raloxifene, or AI.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Otto Metzger, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Otto Metzger, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-632-3352</phone>
    <email>ometzger@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stamford Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stamford</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06904</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>K.M. Steve Lo, MD</last_name>
      <email>slo@stamhealth.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Eastern Maine Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brewer</city>
        <state>Maine</state>
        <zip>04412</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Thomas H. Openshaw, MD</last_name>
      <email>topenshaw@emhs.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Come, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-667-4599</phone>
      <email>scome@bidmc.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Otto F Metzger, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-632-3800</phone>
      <email>ometzger@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Otto F Metzger, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lifespan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Providence</city>
        <state>Rhode Island</state>
        <zip>02903</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mary Anne Fenton, MD</last_name>
      <email>mfenton@lifespan.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sarah Cannon Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Denise A. Yardley, MD</last_name>
      <email>dyardley@tnonc.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 4, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 5, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 6, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Otto Metzger</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Otto Metzger, MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Invasive Lobular Carcinoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Letrozole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Palbociclib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tamoxifen</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

