<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02765152</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Universidade Cidade Sao Paulo</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02765152</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Training Rhythmic and Discrete Aiming Movements on Arm Control and Functionality After Stroke</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Training Rhythmic and Discrete Aiming Movements on the Upper Limb Control and Functionality After Stroke: Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidade Cidade de Sao Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade Cidade de Sao Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to verify the additional effects of rhythmic specific training,
      discrete specific training additional to conventional therapy on the upper limb after chronic
      stroke subjects on the outcomes: motor control and functionality.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Seventy-five patients will be randomized into three groups to receive conventional therapy,
      consisting of a combination of mobility exercises joint, muscle stretching, strength
      training, motor coordination exercises, unilateral and bilateral motor tasks as well as
      oriented tasks training upper limb with a focus on functional tasks. The other groups will
      receive additional intervention consisting of aiming movement practice according two
      different protocols: discrete movements to targets placed in different directions and
      distances; and rhythmic movements also to targets placed in different directions and
      distances. Both additional interventional interventions will be conducted for 30 minutes over
      a 5 week-period (total: 10 sessions).

      Clinical outcomes (motor control), functional and kinematic will be collected at baseline and
      at five weeks. Functional results will be collected at the beginning, after 5 weeks and 3
      months after randomization. Data will be collected by a blinded assessor on patients'
      allocation group. All statistical analyzes will be carried out following the principles of
      intention to treat analysis and differences between groups will be performed using linear
      mixed models.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke Impact Scale (SIS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Five weeks after randomization and 3 months after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Functionality: questionnaire which evaluates functionality. In this study will be evaluated four areas (arm muscle strength, hand function, activities of daily living and social participation)(Duncan et al., 1999). Each domain is scored from 1 to 5 (1 point corresponds to the worst possible outcome and 5 points to the best result). For the four areas the lowest possible score is 28 points and the highest is 125 points.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Motor Activity Log (MAL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Five weeks and 3 months after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Arm function: individuals are asked to rate Quality of Movement (QOM) and Amount of Movement (AOM) during 30 daily functional tasks (original MAL) (Uswatte et al., 2005).
Items scored on a 6-point ordinal scale, where 0 corresponds to the weaker arm was not sued at all for that activity (never). Patients with a score 5 show the ability to use the weaker arm for that activity was as good as before the stroke (normal).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fugl-Meyer Assessment Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Five weeks after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Motor control: this scale assesses sensorimotor function of upper limb, with score 0-66 points with scores 0-66 points for motor function and 0-126 points for sensory-motor function (Fugl-Meyer, 1975). A higher score is better motor function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>kinematics assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Five weeks after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Functional capacity: It will be used an experimental apparatus that analyzes the motor behavior the aiming movement (Ribeiro et al., 2014). They will evaluate the movement time (measured in milliseconds), reaction time (in milliseconds) and smoothness (expressed in units of motion). The movement time is the time interval between the beginning and the end of the movement. Reaction time is defined as the time between the start of the imperative stimulus to the beginning of the movement. The smoothness is evaluated by computing the number of times the acceleration zero crossing (positive to negative and vice versa). The resultant variable error (in centimeters) is a measure of variability for both the medial-lateral direction as anteroposterior, assessing the accuracy to hit the target.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Grip strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Five weeks after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Body function and structure: it will measure the strength of grip and pinch through dynamometer. The results will be presented in kilogram-force (Kgf) (Mathiowetz et al., 1985)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Ashworth Spasticity Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Five weeks after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Body function and structure: they will be assessed flexors elbow, wrist and fingers, and forearm pronators. A measurement scale from 0 to 4 points, with 0 representing normal muscle tone and 4 is the highest possible degree of spasticity (Bohannon and Smith, 1987)</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Physical Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual therapy: joint mobility exercises, stimulating joint movement of the main active components of the upper limb; major muscle groups stretching, especially in the affected muscles by tone impairment; manual resistance training according to the degree of the patient's muscle strength, prioritizing the functional specificity of the upper limb, so the majority of the exercises will be held in open chain; motor coordination exercises, unilateral and bilateral motor tasks as well as task-oriented training of the upper limb with a focus on functional tasks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>discrete movement training group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Aiming movements training with the affected upper limb (unilateral training) or both limbs (bilateral training) on the surface of a table. The starting point of the movement and its target are predetermined. Targets will be placed in different directions and distances from the starting point and the therapist ask for variations on speed and assistance, if necessary.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>rhythmic movement training group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Aiming movements training with the affected upper limb (unilateral training) or both limbs (bilateral training) on the surface of a table. The movement begins in a predetermined starting point, directed to a target and returns to the starting point. This activity is performed several times with rhythmic movements. Targets will be placed in different directions and distances from the starting point and the therapist ask for variations on speed and assistance, if necessary.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional Physical Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Combination of joint mobility exercises, specific exercises for muscle strength and motor coordination exercises, unilateral and bilateral motor tasks as well as task-oriented training of the upper limb with a focus on functional tasks. Patients will receive 10 sessions of treatment over a period of five weeks (two sessions/week)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Physical Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Discrete movement training group</intervention_name>
    <description>Aiming movements training with the affected upper limb (unilateral training) or both limbs (bilateral training) on the surface of a table. The starting point of the movement and its target are predetermined. Targets will be placed in different directions and distances from the starting point and the therapist ask for variations on speed and assistance, if necessary.</description>
    <arm_group_label>discrete movement training group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rhythmic movement training group</intervention_name>
    <description>Aiming movements training with the affected upper limb (unilateral training) or both limbs (bilateral training) on the surface of a table. The movement begins in a predetermined starting point, directed to a target and returns to the starting point. This activity is performed several times with rhythmic movements. Targets will be placed in different directions and distances from the starting point and the therapist ask for variations on speed and assistance, if necessary.</description>
    <arm_group_label>rhythmic movement training group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:patients who participate in the survey, adult stroke survivors (&gt;18
        years), with primary diagnosis of first-ever unilateral stroke (ischaemic or haemorrhagic),
        stroke experienced &gt; 6 months prior to study enrollment and score ≥ 20 on the Folstein Mini
        Mental Status Examination.

        Exclusion criteria: patients with excessive pain in the paretic hand, arm or shoulder
        excessive spasticity at the paretic elbow and wrist as defined as a score of 4 on the
        Modified Ashworth Spasticity Scale and upper limb comorbidities that could limit their
        functional recovery (e.g., arthritis, pain, other neurological disorders).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sandra R Alouche, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Universidade Cidade São Paulo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sandra R Alouche, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+551121781565</phone>
    <email>sandra.alouche@unicid.edu.br</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Leonardo OP Costa, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+551121781565</phone>
    <email>leonardo.costa@unicid.edu.br</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universidade Cidade de Sao Paulo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sao Paulo</city>
        <zip>03071-000</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sandra R Alouche, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+551121781565</phone>
      <email>sandra.alouche@unicid.edu.br</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cauraugh JH, Summers JJ. Neural plasticity and bilateral movements: A rehabilitation approach for chronic stroke. Prog Neurobiol. 2005 Apr;75(5):309-20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15885874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naghdi S, Ansari NN, Mansouri K, Hasson S. A neurophysiological and clinical study of Brunnstrom recovery stages in the upper limb following stroke. Brain Inj. 2010;24(11):1372-8. doi: 10.3109/02699052.2010.506860.</citation>
    <PMID>20715900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harris JE, Eng JJ. Paretic upper-limb strength best explains arm activity in people with stroke. Phys Ther. 2007 Jan;87(1):88-97. Epub 2006 Dec 19.</citation>
    <PMID>17179441</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Faria-Fortini I, Michaelsen SM, Cassiano JG, Teixeira-Salmela LF. Upper extremity function in stroke subjects: relationships between the international classification of functioning, disability, and health domains. J Hand Ther. 2011 Jul-Sep;24(3):257-64; quiz 265. doi: 10.1016/j.jht.2011.01.002. Epub 2011 Mar 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21420279</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sirtori V, Corbetta D, Moja L, Gatti R. Constraint-induced movement therapy for upper extremities in stroke patients. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2009 Oct 7;(4):CD004433. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD004433.pub2. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015;10:CD004433.</citation>
    <PMID>19821326</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liepert J. Evidence-based therapies for upper extremity dysfunction. Curr Opin Neurol. 2010 Dec;23(6):678-82. doi: 10.1097/WCO.0b013e32833ff4c4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20852418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ada L, O'Dwyer N, O'Neill E. Relation between spasticity, weakness and contracture of the elbow flexors and upper limb activity after stroke: an observational study. Disabil Rehabil. 2006 Jul 15-30;28(13-14):891-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16777777</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oujamaa L, Relave I, Froger J, Mottet D, Pelissier JY. Rehabilitation of arm function after stroke. Literature review. Ann Phys Rehabil Med. 2009 Apr;52(3):269-93. doi: 10.1016/j.rehab.2008.10.003. Epub 2009 Apr 9. Review. English, French.</citation>
    <PMID>19398398</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cauraugh JH, Lodha N, Naik SK, Summers JJ. Bilateral movement training and stroke motor recovery progress: a structured review and meta-analysis. Hum Mov Sci. 2010 Oct;29(5):853-70. doi: 10.1016/j.humov.2009.09.004. Epub 2009 Nov 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19926154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Delden AE, Peper CE, Beek PJ, Kwakkel G. Unilateral versus bilateral upper limb exercise therapy after stroke: a systematic review. J Rehabil Med. 2012 Feb;44(2):106-17. doi: 10.2340/16501977-0928. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22266762</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chang JJ, Tung WL, Wu WL, Huang MH, Su FC. Effects of robot-aided bilateral force-induced isokinetic arm training combined with conventional rehabilitation on arm motor function in patients with chronic stroke. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2007 Oct;88(10):1332-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17908578</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smits-Engelsman BC, Swinnen SP, Duysens J. The advantage of cyclic over discrete movements remains evident following changes in load and amplitude. Neurosci Lett. 2006 Mar 20;396(1):28-32. Epub 2005 Dec 2.</citation>
    <PMID>16326008</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duncan PW, Wallace D, Lai SM, Johnson D, Embretson S, Laster LJ. The stroke impact scale version 2.0. Evaluation of reliability, validity, and sensitivity to change. Stroke. 1999 Oct;30(10):2131-40.</citation>
    <PMID>10512918</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uswatte G, Taub E, Morris D, Vignolo M, McCulloch K. Reliability and validity of the upper-extremity Motor Activity Log-14 for measuring real-world arm use. Stroke. 2005 Nov;36(11):2493-6. Epub 2005 Oct 13.</citation>
    <PMID>16224078</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fugl-Meyer AR, Jääskö L, Leyman I, Olsson S, Steglind S. The post-stroke hemiplegic patient. 1. a method for evaluation of physical performance. Scand J Rehabil Med. 1975;7(1):13-31.</citation>
    <PMID>1135616</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ribeiro Coqueiro P, de Freitas SM, Assunção e Silva CM, Alouche SR. Effects of direction and index of difficulty on aiming movements after stroke. Behav Neurol. 2014;2014:909182. doi: 10.1155/2014/909182. Epub 2014 Jan 28.</citation>
    <PMID>24803738</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mathiowetz V, Kashman N, Volland G, Weber K, Dowe M, Rogers S. Grip and pinch strength: normative data for adults. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1985 Feb;66(2):69-74.</citation>
    <PMID>3970660</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bohannon RW, Smith MB. Interrater reliability of a modified Ashworth scale of muscle spasticity. Phys Ther. 1987 Feb;67(2):206-7.</citation>
    <PMID>3809245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 19, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 3, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 6, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 30, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidade Cidade de Sao Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Renata Morales Banjai</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>rhythmic movement</keyword>
  <keyword>discrete movement</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

