<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02769455</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SM2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02769455</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Online Experimental Supermarket</brief_title>
  <acronym>SUPERNET</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of front-of Pack Nutrition Labels on Purchase Intentions in an Online Supermarket-A Series of Randomized Trials</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Paris 13</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Intitut National du Cancer</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Paris 13</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Front-Of-Pack (FOP) nutrition labelling, providing simplified information on nutritional
      content at a glance, in order to help consumer make informed choices, has been identified as
      of major interest by public health specialists of many countries. French health authorities
      are currently considering the endorsement of a FOP nutrition label, but no specific format
      has yet been determined. A more simplified FOP nutrition label has been put forward in
      France, the 5-Colour Nutrition Label (5-CNL). Recent data suggests that the 5-CNL FOP label
      is well perceived and understood by consumers. The introduction of a FOP nutrition labelling
      system has been identified as challenging in certain population groups, due to their lower
      level of nutrition knowledge and unhealthier diets.

      The aim of the investigators is to evaluate the impact of FOP nutrition labels on the
      nutritional quality of the shopping cart in an online experimental supermarket in various
      nutritionally at-risk populations. Two FOP systems will be tested to a control situation
      without FOP labelling: the Reference Intakes (RI), currently in use by some manufacturers and
      present in a portion of food products sold in France, and the 5-Colour Nutrition Label
      (5-CNL).

      Three 3 arm parallel arm randomized trials are designed, each targeting a specific
      population. The methodology and interventions are identical across trials. Trials will be
      conducted in: 1) Working adults between 30-50 years old with low income, 2) Students and 3)
      Older subjects with identified chronic diseases. The intervention consists in the application
      of FOP nutrition labels on all food products, either the RI label, currently in use in some
      products in France, and the 5-CNL label. A control situation with no FOP will also be used.
      Participants will be asked to perform a shopping session in an experimental online
      supermarket, in one of the three experimental conditions described. The main outcome will be
      the overall nutritional quality of the shopping cart, assessed using the mean Food Standards
      Agency Nutrient profiling system score of the items in the shopping cart.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Front-Of-Pack (FOP) nutrition labelling, providing simplified information on nutritional
      content at a glance, in order to help consumer make informed choices, has been identified as
      of major interest by public health specialists of many countries. Modelling studies suggested
      that adoption of effective nutrition labelling would be cost-effective and provide health
      benefits. French health authorities are currently considering the endorsement of a FOP
      nutrition label, but no specific format has yet been determined. A more simplified FOP
      nutrition label has been put forward in France, the 5-Colour Nutrition Label (5-CNL). Recent
      data suggests that the 5-CNL FOP label is well perceived and understood by consumers.
      Moreover, a recent randomized trial, based on an online experimental supermarket, showed that
      the 5-CNL displayed the highest difference in nutritional quality compared to the control
      situation. The introduction of a FOP nutrition labelling system has been identified as
      challenging in certain population groups, due to their lower level of nutrition knowledge and
      unhealthier diets. Subjects with lower levels of income, or the young appear as a key target
      in which the impact of FOP nutrition labels has been poorly explored. Moreover, the impact of
      such a label on subjects suffering from a chronic condition for which dietary modifications
      are part of the treatment should be carefully considered, in order to avoid potential
      undesirable effects of the label in these populations.

      The aim of the investigators is to evaluate the impact of FOP nutrition labels on the
      nutritional quality of the shopping cart in an online experimental supermarket in various
      nutritionally at-risk populations. Two FOP systems will be tested to a control situation
      without FOP labelling: the Reference Intakes (RI), currently in use by some manufacturers and
      present in a portion of food products sold in France, and the 5-Colour Nutrition Label
      (5-CNL).

      Three 3 arm parallel arm randomized trials are designed, each targeting a specific
      population. The methodology and interventions are identical across trials. Trials will be
      conducted in: 1) Working adults between 30-50 years old with low income, 2) Students and 3)
      Older subjects with identified chronic diseases. The intervention consists in the application
      of FOP nutrition labels on all food products, either the RI label, currently in use in some
      products in France, and the 5-CNL label. A control situation with no FOP will also be used.
      Participants will be asked to perform a shopping session in an experimental online
      supermarket, in one of the three experimental conditions described. The main outcome will be
      the overall nutritional quality of the shopping cart, assessed using the mean Food Standards
      Agency Nutrient profiling system score of the items in the shopping cart.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>FSA Score</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mean nutritional quality of the items in the shopping cart, using the mean Food Standards Agency nutrient profiling system (FSA score) of the items in the shopping cart. The FSA score for foods and beverages is computed taking into account nutrient content for 100g. It allocates positive points (0-10) for content in energy (KJ), total sugar (g), saturated fatty acids (g) and sodium (mg). Negative points (0-5) are allocated to content in fruits, vegetables, legumes and nuts (%), fibers (g) and proteins (g). Scores for foods and beverages were therefore based on a discrete continuous scale from -15 (most healthy) to +40 (less healthy). Modifications to the original score were used in order to ensure a higher consistency with French nutritional recommendations for beverages, cheese and added fats</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Calories (/100g)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mean calorie density of the items in the shopping cart. Calorie content per 100g for each item is taken into account. No weighing on total energy or weight of the shopping cart.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Saturates (g/100g)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mean saturated fat content of the items in the shopping cart. Saturates content per 100g for each item is taken into account. No weighing on total energy or weight of the shopping cart.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sugar (g/100g)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mean sugar content of the items in the shopping cart. Sugar content per 100g for each item is taken into account. No weighing on total energy or weight of the shopping cart.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sodium (mg/100g)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mean sodium content of the items in the shopping cart. Sodium content per 100g for each item is taken into account. No weighing on total energy or weight of the shopping cart.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fibers (g/100g)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mean fiber content of the items in the shopping cart. Fiber content per 100g for each item is taken into account. No weighing on total energy or weight of the shopping cart.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proteins (g/100g)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mean protein content of the items in the shopping cart. Protein content per 100g for each item is taken into account. No weighing on total energy or weight of the shopping cart.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fruits and vegetables (%/100g)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mean fruit and vegetables content of the items in the shopping cart. Fruits and vegetables content per 100g for each item is taken into account. No weighing on total energy or weight of the shopping cart.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6000</enrollment>
  <condition>Food Selection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will not be exposed to any FOP nutrition labels</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Front-of-pack labelling (Reference Intakes)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The second group will be exposed to a FOP nutrition label which is already in use on a portion of food products in France: the 'Reference Intakes' (RIs). The RIs are presented in the form of a chain of rectangles presenting the contribution of a portion of the product to a reference balanced diet of an average person (2000kcal) for each of the following nutrients: energy, lipids, saturated fat, sugars and sodium.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Front-of-pack labelling (5-CNL)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The 5-CNL was developed as a colour-coded summary system nutrition label, following the elements pointed out in reviews.
The format of the 5-CNL system therefore includes five categories of nutritional quality of food products, ranging from green (Associated with the A grade) for foods of the highest nutritional quality to red (associated with the E grade), for products with lower nutritional quality. The format is presented in the form of a continuous chain of rectangles, each with its own letter/colour, the letter/colour corresponding to the product being enlarged.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Reference intakes</intervention_name>
    <description>FOP nutrition label which is already in use on a portion of food products in France: the 'Reference Intakes' (RIs). The RIs are a chain of rectangles presenting the contribution of a portion of the product to a reference balanced diet of an average person (2000kcal) for each of the following nutrients: energy, lipids, saturated fat, sugars and sodium.
The presentation of the products will always include the label affixed on it. Moreover, the product pages will include two pictures of the product: one with only the package (including the RI as FOP labelling), and a picture with both the package and a larger version of the label, so that it is more visible to the participant. These elements ensure higher visibility, awareness and understanding of the label.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Front-of-pack labelling (Reference Intakes)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>5-CNL</intervention_name>
    <description>The 5-CNL was developed as a colour-coded summary system nutrition label, following the elements pointed out in reviews.
The format includes five categories, ranging from green (Associated with the A grade) for foods of the highest nutritional quality to red (associated with the E grade), for products with lower nutritional quality. The format is presented in the form of a continuous chain of rectangles, each with its own letter/colour, the one corresponding to the product being enlarged.
The presentation of the products will always include the label affixed on it. Two pictures of the product will be included: one with only the package (including the 5-CNL as FOP labelling), and a picture with both the package and a larger version of the label, so that it is more visible to the participant.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Front-of-pack labelling (5-CNL)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        TRIAL n°1

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects 30-50 years old

          -  Having finished their studies and currently active (either working or unemployed)

          -  Income/UC &lt;1200€/month

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Student, retired

          -  Subjects living outside of mainland France

          -  Subjects never engaging in grocery shopping

        TRIAL N°2

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject 18-25 years old

          -  Self-declared as student

        Exclusion Criteria:

        • Subjects never engaging in grocery shopping

        TRIAL N°3

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects &gt;50 years-old

          -  Diagnosed with one or more of the following chronic conditions (self-reported) : type
             2 diabetes, dislipidemia (elevated cholesterol levels, low HDL cholesterol levels,
             elevated triglycerides levels), hypertension, cardiovascular disease, obesity

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects declaring suffering from none of the mentioned chronic conditions

          -  Subjects never engaging in grocery shopping
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Serge Hercberg</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nutritional Epidemiology Research Team</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Equipe de Recherche en Epidémiologie Nutritionnelle</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bobigny</city>
        <zip>93017</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 9, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 9, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 11, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 29, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 29, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 3, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Paris 13</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Serge HERCBERG</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Nutritional Epidemiology Research Team</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Food Labelling</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

