<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02764099</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R34DA034888</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02764099</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Testing a Multilevel Preventive Intervention in Youth Courts</brief_title>
  <official_title>Testing a Multilevel Preventive Intervention in Youth Courts</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Health Promotion Associates, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Health Promotion Associates, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed research is designed to adapt and test an evidence-based drug abuse prevention
      approach for use in youth courts among first-time, non-violent, adolescent offenders. The
      ultimate goal is to reduce the adverse health, legal, and social consequences of youth drug
      abuse, violence, and delinquency. Planned project activities include conducting: 1) key
      informant interviews of youth court directors regarding logistical and intervention features
      of effective youth court programming; and, 2) a randomized controlled efficacy trial of an
      adapted version of Life Skills Training, an evidence-based drug and violence prevention
      program. It is anticipated that the findings will provide critical information on
      implementing evidence-based prevention programs for new populations and settings and will
      support preparations for a large-scale effectiveness trial in youth peer courts.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Adolescents in under-served, urban communities are disproportionately involved in the
      juvenile justice system. This early engagement has been shown to be a strong predictor of
      more serious offenses in adulthood, such that youth involvement in the court system is a
      significant public health concern. Juvenile justice approaches have traditionally emphasized
      individualized treatment efforts combined with discipline and punishment. More recently,
      however, juvenile justice professionals have questioned the adequacy of this approach and are
      increasingly adopting an asset-based perspective referred to as &quot;positive youth justice&quot;
      (PYJ). The PYJ approach encourages youth court participants to build upon their existing
      strengths, while learning and mastering new life skills, through development of pro-social
      relationships within their peer group, family, and community. These &quot;core assets&quot; are posited
      to promote the successful entry into young adulthood. For this project, the investigative
      team will adapt and test a multilevel, multi-component, intervention that has strong
      potential to reduce substance use and delinquency while correspondingly promoting positive
      youth justice among youth court participants and staff. The first component of the current
      project involves interviewing program directors from a representative sample of youth courts
      throughout the U.S to gain formative feedback about logistical and programming concerns. The
      second component of the project is designed to promote individual-level change among youth
      participants and consists of an adapted version of the Life Skills Training (LST) program, an
      evidence-based drug and violence prevention program which teaches personal self-management
      skills, social skills, drug refusal skills, and other life skills needed to successfully
      navigate developmental tasks, increase resilience, and facilitate healthy psycho-social
      development. Several youth courts have used the Life Skills Training program, suggesting that
      it meets a perceived need and is feasible in this setting. However, LST has never been
      rigorously tested in the youth court setting. The proposed research will involve a randomized
      efficacy trial with 560 adolescents in youth court. The investigative team will examine
      intervention effects on substance use, delinquent behavior, school performance, and
      recidivism rates using mixed qualitative (assessment of dosage, fidelity, and provider and
      participant feedback to determine their impact on program efficacy) and quantitative (survey
      assessments at pretest, post-test, and six-month follow-up) methods to estimate the effect
      size of the adapted and combined program. By intervening with both youth court participants
      and youth court staff, the proposed multilevel intervention can have a broad impact on risk
      and protective factors at multiple levels of influence. The ultimate goal of this research is
      to promote the use of an evidence-based prevention approach adapted specifically for
      implementation in youth courts in order to reduce the adverse consequences of drug abuse,
      violence, and delinquency among youth offenders.

      The specific aims of this project will be to:

        1. Conduct key informant interviews with a diverse sample of youth court program
           coordinators;

        2. Conduct expert review of the LST intervention materials to ensure accuracy and
           appropriateness for the youth court setting and revise appropriately for an efficacy
           trial;

        3. Evaluate the efficacy of the combined youth court intervention (staff training plus LST)
           in preventing substance use, delinquency and violence, improving hypothesized mediators
           of intervention effects, including knowledge, attitudes and life skills, and promoting
           effective youth placements in community settings;

        4. Examine the degree to which process variables such as dosage and fidelity moderate
           intervention effects;

        5. Examine all recruitment, incentive, consent, tracking and assessment procedures in
           preparation for a subsequent national effectiveness trial.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Substance Use Behavior, Intentions, Attitudes and Perceived Norms at Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-test (prior to participating in the first session of the intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Substance Use Behavior and Intentions: For 13 substance-related items (e.g., alcohol, tobacco, cocaine, methamphetamines, steroids), participants will be asked to indicate frequency of use. Drug Attitudes: Sixteen items will be used to assess participants' attitudes about drug use, perceived characteristics of drug users and the perceived social benefits of drug use. Drug Norms &amp; Knowledge: Normative expectations related to drug use will be assessed including perceived prevalence of drug use among peers and among adults. Friends' and adult substance use will be measured. Drug Refusal Skills will be assessed using five items that measure the ability to resist peer pressure to engage in substance use.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Baseline Substance Use Behavior, Intentions, Attitudes and Perceived Norms at Post-Intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-test (within 2 weeks of completing final session of the intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Substance Use Behavior and Intentions: For 13 substance-related items (e.g., alcohol, tobacco, cocaine, methamphetamines, steroids), participants will be asked to indicate frequency of use. Drug Attitudes: Sixteen items will be used to assess participants' attitudes about drug use, perceived characteristics of drug users and the perceived social benefits of drug use. Drug Norms &amp; Knowledge: Normative expectations related to drug use will be assessed including perceived prevalence of drug use among peers and among adults. Friends' and adult substance use will be measured. Drug Refusal Skills will be assessed using five items that measure the ability to resist peer pressure to engage in substance use.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Baseline Substance Use Behavior, Intentions, Attitudes and Perceived Norms at 6-months</measure>
    <time_frame>6-month followup (within 6-7 months of completing final session of intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Substance Use Behavior and Intentions: For 13 substance-related items (e.g., alcohol, tobacco, cocaine, methamphetamines, steroids), participants will be asked to indicate frequency of use. Drug Attitudes: Sixteen items will be used to assess participants' attitudes about drug use, perceived characteristics of drug users and the perceived social benefits of drug use. Drug Norms &amp; Knowledge: Normative expectations related to drug use will be assessed including perceived prevalence of drug use among peers and among adults. Friends' and adult substance use will be measured. Drug Refusal Skills will be assessed using five items that measure the ability to resist peer pressure to engage in substance use.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aggressive, Violent, and Delinquent Behavior at Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-test (prior to participating in the first session of the intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Aggressive, violent, and delinquent behaviors will be assessed using the items from the Reactive/Proactive Aggression Scale (RPAS). The RPAS provides respondents with a sequence of aggressive/violent behaviors and prompts them to indicate the frequency of each behavior. Beliefs about aggressive and violent behavior will be measured using the items from the Normative Beliefs about Aggression Scale (NBAS). The 20-item NBAS contains 2 sections: retaliation belief questions and general belief questions, which can be tallied to calculate a measure of total approval of aggression. Delinquent and disciplinary behavioral data will be gathered using the Rochester Youth Development Self-Reported Delinquency Scale, a self-report measure of delinquency and problem behavior developed by the Rochester Youth Development Study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Baseline Aggressive, Violent, and Delinquent Behavior at Post-Intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-test (within 2 weeks of completing final session of the intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Aggressive, violent, and delinquent behaviors will be assessed using the items from the Reactive/Proactive Aggression Scale (RPAS). The RPAS provides respondents with a sequence of aggressive/violent behaviors and prompts them to indicate the frequency of each behavior. Beliefs about aggressive and violent behavior will be measured using the items from the Normative Beliefs about Aggression Scale (NBAS). The 20-item NBAS contains 2 sections: retaliation belief questions and general belief questions, which can be tallied to calculate a measure of total approval of aggression. Delinquent and disciplinary behavioral data will be gathered using the Rochester Youth Development Self-Reported Delinquency Scale, a self-report measure of delinquency and problem behavior developed by the Rochester Youth Development Study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Baseline Aggressive, Violent, and Delinquent Behavior at 6-months</measure>
    <time_frame>6-month followup (within 6-7 months of completing final session of intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Aggressive, violent, and delinquent behaviors will be assessed using the items from the Reactive/Proactive Aggression Scale (RPAS). The RPAS provides respondents with a sequence of aggressive/violent behaviors and prompts them to indicate the frequency of each behavior. Beliefs about aggressive and violent behavior will be measured using the items from the Normative Beliefs about Aggression Scale (NBAS). The 20-item NBAS contains 2 sections: retaliation belief questions and general belief questions, which can be tallied to calculate a measure of total approval of aggression. Delinquent and disciplinary behavioral data will be gathered using the Rochester Youth Development Self-Reported Delinquency Scale, a self-report measure of delinquency and problem behavior developed by the Rochester Youth Development Study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">560</enrollment>
  <condition>Drug Abuse</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Life Skills Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All youth who consent to participate in the proposed study will 1) complete the youth peer court sanction delivered by the jury of peers (e.g., apologies or essays, restitution, curfew and travel restrictions, counseling, etc.), which will constitute &quot;treatment as usual&quot;; and 2) complete pre, post, and six-month follow-up surveys. Those randomized to the intervention condition (n=280) will participate in the LST program concurrently during the weeks when they serve as peer court jurors.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>All youth who consent to participate in the proposed study will 1) complete the youth peer court sanction delivered by the jury of peers (e.g., apologies or essays, restitution, curfew and travel restrictions, counseling, etc.), which will constitute &quot;treatment as usual&quot;; and 2) complete pre, post, and six-month follow-up surveys. Those randomized to the control group (n=280) will not participate in LST but will participate in a ten session, lecture-style, didactic health education course. This course will include general information on several health-related topics, but will not contain any type of skill building exercises.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Life Skills Training</intervention_name>
    <description>The Life Skills Training (LST) program is a comprehensive competence enhancement prevention approach that teaches resistance skills while also emphasizing generic personal and social skills training. The LST program content and skills training is delivered to youth participants by trained providers through instruction, demonstration, behavioral rehearsal with feedback and social reinforcement, extended practice through homework assignments, and didactic teaching methods.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Life Skills Training</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LST</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inclusion criteria for youth participants will include regular participation in youth
             court activities and informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Exclusion criteria for youth participants will include significant cognitive
             impairment or severe learning disabilities, as screened by staff at the youth court

          -  Any previous experience with the intervention program will also exclude adolescents
             from participating
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher Williams, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Health Promotion Associates</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christopher Williams, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>914-421-2525</phone>
    <phone_ext>204</phone_ext>
    <email>cwilliams@nhpamail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Kenneth W Griffin, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>914-421-2525</phone>
    <phone_ext>215</phone_ext>
    <email>kgriffin@nhpamail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 29, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 5, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 6, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 5, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 5, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 6, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National Health Promotion Associates, Inc.</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Christopher Williams</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Vice President</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

