<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02765672</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB201500871</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>JW 140063</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02765672</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of a Driving Intervention on Safe Community Mobility for Returning Combat Veterans</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of a Driving Intervention on Safe Community Mobility for Returning Combat Veterans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States Department of Defense</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Western Ontario, Canada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main objective of this study is to discern if an Occupational Therapy Driving
      Intervention (OT-DI) improves fitness to drive abilities of Combat Veterans and also
      investigate if results leads to reduced driving errors on the driving simulator and an
      on-road test. The driving behavior of 260 Combat Veterans will be studied on a driving
      simulator at baseline after which they will be randomized into control and intervention
      groups. The intervention group will receive sessions of Occupational Therapy Driving
      Intervention by a trained driving rehabilitation specialist. The control group on the other
      hand will receive driving safety education sessions by a driving safety professional. Both
      groups will be evaluated for driving performance on the driving simulator to ascertain
      whether there have been changes in the number of driving errors at two and three months upon
      enrollment. Caregiver responses on driving behavior of Combat Veteran and public driving
      records from The Department of Motor Vehicles will be analyzed to for changes in number of
      driving errors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This research study is being done to determine if Occupational Therapy Driving intervention
      (OT-DI) can improve the safe driving performance immediately following intervention and
      intermediate term (3months).

      Baseline testing to post test1 will include Clinical battery of tests and a Simulated Driving
      test, a Brief Driving Questionnaire, Community Integration Questionnaire, and Satisfaction
      with Life Questionnaire. Caregivers/family member will rate the participants' driving
      behaviors using a Fitness-to-Drive Screening Measure (FTDS). After baseline testing the 260
      participants (and associated caregivers) will be randomly assigned to balanced intervention
      and control groups.

      The intervention group receives Occupational Therapy Driving Intervention (OT-DI) consisting
      of three x 1hour sessions will include Sessions1: Driving evaluator reviews explicit driving
      errors with participants; Session 2: Driving evaluator provides tailored strategies to
      mitigate errors; Session 3: Participants drive simulator with targeted feedback from driving
      evaluator.

      The control group will receive from a driving safety professional, three x 1 hour general
      safety sessions (session 1: general traffic safety discussion; Session 2: Rules of the road
      and acknowledgement of the road discussion; Session 3: drive the simulator without any
      feedback from a driving safety professional). Immediately after session 3, Post test1 will
      occur using the same standardized protocol outline for baseline testing.

      Post test2: will consist of testing with the same standardized protocol as administered
      during baseline testing. Caregivers/family members will rate the participants driving
      behavior using FTDS in addition the investigators will obtain driving data from the
      Department of Motor Vehicles which include citations, violations, driving mishaps that have
      occurred for each participant.

      To ascertain impact of the OT-DI and driving safety education on real world driving, a subset
      of 30 participants will be created from the control and intervention groups to perform
      on-road driving test. The results from this test will be compared with driving performance on
      the simulated drives.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Simulator driving errors changes within the experimental and control groups at baseline, months 2 and 5</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes in baseline at months 2 and 5</time_frame>
    <description>Simulator driving errors will be quantified at baseline and at month 2 and 5 for the experimental and control groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>On-road driving errors changes within the experimental and control groups at baseline and month 5</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes in baseline at months 5</time_frame>
    <description>Driving errors will be calculated during an on-road test at baseline and at month 5, for the experimental and control groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">550</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury (TBI)</condition>
  <condition>Post Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this group will have the following performed: Institute of Mobility Activity and Participation's clinical battery tests and a simulated driving evaluation, a Brief Driving Behavior Interview, Propensity for Angry Driving Scale, Clinical Driving Assessment, Community Integration Questionnaire, Fitness-to-Drive Screening Measure (FTDS), and a Satisfaction with Life Questionnaire. Driving Safety Education by a traffic safety professional, three x 1 hour sessions to discuss traffic safety rules regarding person, vehicle, environmental factors.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this group will have the following performed: Institute of Mobility Activity and Participation's clinical battery tests and a simulated driving tests, a Brief Driving Behavior Interview, Propensity for Angry Driving Scale, Clinical Driving Assessment, Community Integration Questionnaire, Fitness-to-Drive Screening Measure(FTDS), and a Satisfaction with Life Questionnaire. Occupational Therapy Driving Intervention (OT-DI) consisting of three x 1 hour sessions to review explicit driving errors, strategies to mitigate errors and receiving feedback from the evaluator after driving the simulator.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Caregiver Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Caregiver control group will fill out a Fitness-to-Drive Screening Measure (FTDS) questionnaire at baseline and at the end of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Caregiver Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Caregivers of the experimental group will fill out a Fitness-to-Drive Screening Measure (FTDS) questionnaire at baseline and at the end of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>On-road driving Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A subset of 30 Combat Veterans will be drawn from the control group (15 no.) and experimental group (15 no.). This group of Combat Veterans will will undergo an on-road driving test at baseline and month 5</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Simulator-drives Evaluation Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will comprise of 30 Combat Veterans who will be drawn outside of the randomized experimental and and control groups participants. This group will only perform simulator driving triggers evaluation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Driving Behavior Interview</intervention_name>
    <description>This will be completed thrice, at baseline, post-test1 and at post-test2 (3 months after post test 1)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clinical Driving Assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Clinical Driving Assessment includes Optec vision screening, Useful Field of View, Range of Motion, Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) and Strength tests. This will be completed thrice, at baseline, post-test1 and at post-test2 (3 months after post test 1)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Propensity for Angry Driving Scale</intervention_name>
    <description>This will be completed thrice, at baseline, post-test1 and at post-test2 (3 months after post test 1)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Community Integration Questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>This will be completed thrice, at baseline, post-test1 and at post-test2 (3 months after post test 1)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Satisfaction with Life</intervention_name>
    <description>This will be completed thrice, at baseline, post-test1 and at post-test2 (3 months after post test 1</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fitness-to-Drive Screening Measure (FTDS)</intervention_name>
    <description>Fitness-to-Drive-Screening Measure will be completed twice, at baseline and at end of study</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Caregiver Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Caregiver Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Simulated Driving Evaluation</intervention_name>
    <description>This involves driving a simulator fitted simulated drives engineered to to address Veteran's driving concerns such as reactions to other drivers and road conditions(e.g. debris). The simulator is used at baseline and at post-test1 and 2. The intervention and traffic safety education session 3 also occurs using the driving simulator.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Driving Safety Education</intervention_name>
    <description>This involves the following: Session1: general traffic safety discussion; Session 2: Rules of the road and acknowledgement of the road discussion and Session 3: driving the simulator without any feedback from traffic safety professional</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Occupational Therapy Driving Intervention (OT-DI)</intervention_name>
    <description>This has three sessions: 1. Driving evaluator reviews explicit driving errors with Combat Veteran; 2. driving evaluator provide tailored strategies to mitigate errors; Combat Veteran drives simulator with targeted feedback from driving evaluator.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>On-road driving test</intervention_name>
    <description>This involves and on-road driving test supervised by Driving Rehabilitation Specialist. To be completed at baseline and at month 5</description>
    <arm_group_label>On-road driving Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Driving triggers evaluation</intervention_name>
    <description>The simulator-drives evaluation group will evaluate the current simulator-triggers prior to baseline testing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Simulator-drives Evaluation Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Combat Veterans with polytrauma (mild traumatic brain injury (TBI)/ with accompanying
             post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), traumatic limb amputation/fractures) who drove
             prior to injury/condition.

          -  Have a valid driver's license or are eligible for a driver's license.

          -  Are community dwelling.

          -  Combat Veterans without formal diagnoses who report driving issues (either formal such
             as violations, citations or motor vehicle crashes, or informal including risky driving
             or driving stress and/or anxiety)

          -  Have potential for following driving safety recommendations Mini-Mental State
             Examination (MMSE 24/30)

          -  Are able to participate in a driving evaluation battery.

          -  Inclusion criterion for caregivers is based on their ability to complete a driving
             questionnaire pre and post intervention.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Combat Veterans who have severe psychiatric (e.g., psychoses) or physical conditions
             (e.g., missing both arms and/or legs) that will limit ability to drive;

          -  Have multiple psychotropic medications that may impact mental or physical (due to
             side-effects) functioning as per the consulting physician;

          -  Have severe, un-remediable medical conditions (e.g., severe TBI) as per the consulting
             physician;

          -  Pregnant females or those planning pregnancy as determined by self-report.

          -  Exclusion criterion for caregivers is based on the presence of a cognitive or physical
             impairment that would hinder their ability to complete the questionnaires or make an
             active contribution.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sherrilene Classen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sherrilene Classen, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(352) 273-6883</phone>
    <email>sclassen@phhp.ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Abraham Yarney, MS</last_name>
    <phone>(352) 273-6043</phone>
    <email>ayarney@phhp.ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Malcom Randall VA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32608</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Myers Keith, MD</last_name>
      <phone>352-376-1611</phone>
      <email>Keith.Myers2@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Bruce Mueller</last_name>
      <phone>(352) 379-4129</phone>
      <email>bruce.mueller@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Charles Levy, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Fitzgerld, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida, Occupational Therapy Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32610</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>William Mann, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>352-273-6817</phone>
      <email>wmann@phhp.ufl.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Rebecca Harty</last_name>
      <phone>(352) 273-6817</phone>
      <email>rharty@phhp.ufl.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Babette Brumback, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Marsiske, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sherrilene Classen, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 5, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 5, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 6, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Combat Veterans</keyword>
  <keyword>Automobile Driving</keyword>
  <keyword>Fitness to Drive</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

