<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01892787</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013RC01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-001103-36</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>13/ES/0050</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01892787</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Particle Size in Small Airways Dysfunction</brief_title>
  <acronym>MAN03</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomised Controlled Single and Chronic Dosing Crossover Comparison of Extra Fine Particle Formoterol and Coarse Particle Salmeterol in Asthmatic Patients With Persistent Small Airways Dysfunction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Dundee</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Chiesi Farmaceutici S.p.A.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Dundee</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The airways in the lungs get smaller the further into the lungs they go. Most simple
      measurements of lung function only reflect the larger 'central' airways and do not provide
      information on the smaller 'peripheral' airways. Newer measurements have been developed that
      can now give us accurate information on how the smaller airways are working. Indeed the small
      airways seem to play a significant role in asthma in terms of inflammation and airway
      narrowing. Recently, new types of inhaler formulations have been developed that have a much
      smaller particle size than other standard formulations. These formulations have been shown to
      go further into the lungs, thus getting into the smaller airways. In this study we aim to
      compare the two extremes of available long acting beta agonists in terms of particle size
      i.e. extra fine formoterol (Atimos) versus coarse particle salmeterol (Serevent)in asthmatics
      with abnormal small airway function using a breathing test called impulse oscillometry. By
      using this test we will be able to find out whether using an extrafine particle inhaler
      improves small airway function.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The small airways are gaining greater recognition for their role in the pathophysiology of
      persistent asthma and as a relevant target for asthma treatment(1). Pathological
      abnormalities in the small airways have been demonstrated regardless of asthma severity and
      seem to persist even in patients with stable asthma(2, 3).

      Historically, the small airways have been difficult to assess. Spirometry generally reflects
      large airways function although the mean forced expiratory flow (FEF) between 25% and 75% of
      FVC (FEF25-75) has been used to assess small airway obstruction.(4) More recently, impulse
      oscillometry (IOS) has been used to assess the role of small airways in asthma(5). IOS is an
      effort-independent test, using oscillation of differing sound waves to derive a variety of
      output measurements determining both the degree of total and peripheral airway resistance.
      Resistance at 5 Hz reflects total airway resistance and central airway resistance is
      approximated using resistance at 20 Hz (R20). The peripheral or small airway component can
      thus be evaluated by calculating the difference between these two measurements i.e. R5 - R20.

      We have identified from our database of primary care referrals, a cohort of patients who
      appear to have evidence of an unmet physiological need in terms of persistent small airways
      dysfunction, on the basis of impairment of R5 and R5-R20 despite taking step 2/3/4 asthma
      treatment(6). Approximately 32% of patients across steps 2/3/4 had severely abnormal values
      for both R5-R20 (&gt;0.05 kPa/L.s) and R5 (&gt; 150%). Such small airway dysfunction at step 3/4
      occurred despite patients being prescribed ICS with LABA, although there were no patients
      being prescribed extra fine ICS/LABA or extra fine LABA (i.e. Fostair or Atimos). In terms of
      the ICS moiety, observational data has shown that patients taking extra fine
      HFA-beclometasone solution (Qvar) have equal or better control than those taking Fluticasone
      suspension, while receiving a lower maintenance dose of ICS(7). In another study, patients
      switched from beclometasone suspension to solution at half the dose had an improvement in
      asthma quality of life. In neither of these studies was there any information available
      regarding small airway dysfunction in order to explain the potential improvements with
      HFA-beclometasone(8).

      There is a paucity of information on the potential benefits of extra fine formoterol on the
      small airways. In a single dosing study comparing extra fine HFA versus coarse particle dry
      powder formulations of formoterol, there was a 30% difference (absolute difference of 2.9
      kPa/L.s.min)in R5 AUC0-60min and 63% difference (absolute difference of 2.4 kPa/L.s.min) in
      R5-R20 AUC0-60min, although this was not the primary end point(9).

      1.2 RATIONALE Thus, the primary objective for the present study is to compare the two
      extremes of available long acting beta-agonist formulations - i.e. extra fine HFA formoterol
      ( Atimos ) versus coarse particle DPI salmeterol (i.e. Serevent Accuhaler). If there turns
      out to be a significant improvement in small airways function conferred by extra fine
      formoterol, then this would in turn support the rationale for performing a further chronic
      study to assess the clinical impact of treating persistent small airways dysfunction at step
      3/4 by switching patients to Fostair HFA and comparing to Seretide DPI, in terms of improving
      asthma control in patients with the small airway phenotype who are already taking
      conventional ICS/LABA formulations. We will use impulse oscillometry to assess the small
      airways response using the difference between resistance measured at 5Hz and 20Hz (R5-R20) as
      the primary outcome. In this regard we have previously reported in asthmatic patients
      receiving propranolol that there was a 104.1 % (95%CI 22.6-185.6%) worsening of R5-R20 in
      terms of the bronchoconstrictor response to propranolol, and following subsequent histamine
      challenge, there was a 115.6 % (95%CI 55.6-175.7% ) improvement in R5-R20 in terms of the
      bronchodilator response to nebulised salbutamol.(10)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in R5-R20 as change from baseline after first and last dose</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline &amp; after 1-2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>R5 - Resistance at 5Hz, R20 - Resistance at 20Hz</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in remaining impulse oscillometry variables (R5,R20,X5,AX,RF) after first and last dose</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and after 1-2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>R5 - Resistance at 5Hz, R20 - Resistance at 20Hz, X5 - Reactance at 5Hz, RF - Frequency of resonance, AX - Area under reactance curve</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the curve from 0 to 60 min</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1-2 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spirometry</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline &amp; 1-2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1); forced vital capacity (FVC); forced expriatory flow between 25-75% of vital capacity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Domiciliary peak expiratory flow</measure>
    <time_frame>1-2 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Asthma Control Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>1-2 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exhaled nitirc oxide</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">17</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Formoterol (Atimos Modulite)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Atimos Modulite 1 puff (12 micrograms) twice a day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Salmeterol (Serevent Accuhaler)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Serevent Accuhaler 1 puff (50 micrograms) of twice a day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Formoterol</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants receive Atimos for 1 to 2 weeks.Partcipants then enter a washout period and after the washout period receive the alternative treatment arm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Formoterol (Atimos Modulite)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Atimos Modulite</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Salmeterol</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants receive Serevent for 1 to 2 weeks. Participants then enter a washout period and after the washout period receive the alternative treatment arm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Salmeterol (Serevent Accuhaler)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Serevent Accuhaler</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female volunteers aged at least 16 years with a diagnosis of asthma

          -  Persistent severe small airways dysfunction on impulse oscillometry with R5 &gt; 150% and
             R5-R20 &gt; 0.05 kPa/L.s despite taking ICS or inhaled corticosteroids / long-acting
             beta-agonists

          -  FEV1 &gt; 60 %

          -  Ability to give informed consent

          -  Agreement for their GP to be made aware of study participation and to receive feedback
             as relevant to the participant's well being

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants already receiving extra-fine particle long-acting beta agonists

          -  Other respiratory diseases such as chronic obstructive pulmonary disease,
             bronchiectasis or alergic allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis

          -  An asthma exacerbation or respiratory tract infection requiring systemic steroids
             and/or antibiotics within 3 months of the study commencement

          -  Smoking within one year or 10 pack year history

          -  Any clinically significant medical condition that may endanger the health or safety of
             the participant

          -  Participation in another trial within 30 days before the commencement of the study

          -  Pregnancy or lactation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian Lipworth, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Dundee</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Arvind Deva Manoharan, MBChB</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Dundee</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brian Lipworth</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dundee</city>
        <zip>DD1 3AU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 1, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 1, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 4, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 4, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 4, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 5, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Dundee</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Brian J Lipworth</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Allergy and Pulmonolgy</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>Small airways</keyword>
  <keyword>Extra fine particle long-acting beta agonists</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Formoterol Fumarate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Salmeterol Xinafoate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

