<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01890018</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>817167</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1C1CMS331009-01-00</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01890018</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Partners and Alerts: A Study of Social Forces in Medication Adherence</brief_title>
  <official_title>Partners and Alerts: A Study of Social Forces in Medication Adherence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall objectives of this study are to improve medication adherence of patients and
      subsequent health outcomes.

      This study is designed to examine the existence of strong associations between social
      networks and health behavior. This study intends to demonstrate that social forces are
      particularly effective at building enduring habits for healthy behavior, specifically
      adherence to statin medication for this study. The investigators believe the improved
      medication adherence will result in fewer additional vascular events, following the most
      recent of these events, and will result in fewer patient hospitalizations. The investigators
      will leverage insights from the fields of social comparison (being provided with information
      about the actions of others prompts social comparison that can significantly influence
      behavior), social pressures (encouragement or discouragement from others is a powerful social
      force that can influence individual behavior), and social triggers (cues in the environment
      can motivate people to take certain actions and have powerful effects on purchasing
      behavior).

      The results of this study and experience gained from the implementation of these
      interventions will be used to inform new versions of a larger trial intervention to be tested
      in new patient cohorts in a rapid cycle framework.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a 4-arm pilot study involving 248 patients (62 per arm) who are on a once-a-day
      statin who have a medication adherence ratio (MPR) that is less than 80%. Patients in all
      arms would receive a GlowCap, manufactured by Vitality Inc., which records pill-bottle
      openings and be asked to use the GlowCap for that medication for the duration of the study.

      The study arms leverage two strategies that the investigators think will be particularly
      effective at improving adherence and may be even more effective when used in tandem. Patients
      in some arms will be asked to select an adherence partner: another person who can help them
      adhere to their medication regimen. The investigators will contact this adherence partner and
      ask them to officially accept this role and provide guidance of their choosing as to how they
      can help the patient adhere. In addition, patients in some arms will receive an alert
      whenever two full days pass without their GlowCap being opened (i.e. 48 hours of
      non-adherence). This alert will encourage them to begin taking their medication again. The
      design allows for some patients to have both an adherence partner and to receive alerts after
      48 hours of non-adherence. In these arms, the adherence partner would also receive the alert
      after 48 hours of non-adherence. This introduces a two-by-two design.

      Subjects would spend 6 months in their randomly assigned treatment, and the investigators
      will compare adherence of subjects in each of the arms to one another.

      The investigators plan to track daily adherence of patients to a prescribed chronic disease
      drug using a new technology that electronically monitors when a pill bottle has been opened.
      In our control condition, patients will be monitored but not be provided with any reminders,
      adherence information, or inclusion of friend of family member to help them adhere to their
      medication. Our four additional treatments will either: (1) email the patient after 48 hours
      of non-adherence; (2) allow the patient to select friend or family member to encourage
      medication adherence; (3) email the patient, as well as patient-selected friends or family
      members after 48 hours of non-adherence; or (4) provide the patient with a daily email, text
      message, or phone call reminder to take the pill.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glowcap bottle openings/Medication Adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Primary outcome will measure the the number of days the GlowCap pill bottle is opened at least 1 time over the 6 month enrollment period, to be measured at 6 months after enrollment for each participant. Medication adherence for this study is considered to be at least 1 registered GlowCap opening for each day enrolled on the study. (N days at least 1 opening/180 days = Medication Adherence %)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient pharmacy benefits-this will be a composite outcome measure assessing MPR</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary outcomes will be gap ratios and medication possession ratios.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Claims records - this will be a composite outcome measure assessing frequency of hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary outcomes will be the number of repeat vascular events, following a similar approach to MI-FREEE, hospitalization, repeat or new cardiovascular procedures, and cost.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">178</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myocardial Infarction (AMI)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will use GlowCaps to have their adherence tracked with no additional modifications:
Arm 1. Control group no modifications
Electronic Pill Bottle tracking</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Feedback group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will use GlowCaps to have their adherence tracked with the following modifications:
Arm 2. Feedback group participants will receive an adherence message after 48 hours of not using the GlowCaps
Electronic Pill Bottle tracking; Adherence Messaging</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adherence partner group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will use GlowCaps to have their adherence tracked with the following modifications:
Arm 3. Adherence partner group participants will designate a family member or friend who will serve as an adherence partner, encouraging adherence of the patient
Electronic Pill Bottle tracking; Social Influence</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adherence partner along with feedback</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will use GlowCaps to have their adherence tracked with the following modifications:
Arm 4. Adherence partner along with feedback group participants will designate a family member or friend who will serve as an adherence partner, encouraging adherence of the patient, both the patient and partner will receive a message after 48 hours of not using the GlowCaps
Electronic Pill Bottle tracking; Adherence Messaging; Social Influence</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Electronic Pill Bottle tracking</intervention_name>
    <description>All 4 groups will use the GlowCaps, a remote monitoring bottle, to take their statin medications</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Feedback group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Adherence partner group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Adherence partner along with feedback</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adherence Messaging</intervention_name>
    <description>Some arms will receive adherence messages if they have not used the Glowcap bottles for 2 of the last 3 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Feedback group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Adherence partner along with feedback</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Social Influence</intervention_name>
    <description>Some arms will select their own adherence feedback partner who will provide support in taking their medication as scheduled.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Adherence partner group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Adherence partner along with feedback</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients must have

          -  experienced an AMI and have been placed on a once-a-day statin and have a medication
             adherence ratio (MPR) that is less than 80%.

          -  access to internet to create an account on Way to Heath.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  There are no exclusion criterial for patients able to provide consent and who meet the
             eligibility criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Judd B Kessler, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 9, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 26, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 1, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acute Myocardial Infarction (AMI)</keyword>
  <keyword>taking a statin medication</keyword>
  <keyword>also have a medication adherence ratio (MPR)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

