<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01891058</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20130331</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>G-13-0002756</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01891058</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Electrical Versus Pharmacological Cardioversion for RAFF in the ED</brief_title>
  <acronym>RAFF-2</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Controlled Comparison of Electrical Versus Pharmacological Cardioversion for Emergency Department Patients With Recent-Onset Atrial Fibrillation and Flutter (RAFF)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Ottawa Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Atrial fibrillation (AF) and atrial flutter (AFL) are cardiac rhythm problems where there is
      an irregular, rapid heart rate. Investigators plan to study Emergency Department (ED)
      patients with recent-onset episodes of AF or AFL (RAFF) where rapid heart rate requires
      urgent treatment to restore normal heart rhythm. RAFF is the most common rhythm disorder
      managed in the ED. Investigators recently showed that doctors use a wide variety of treatment
      approaches in Canadian EDs for RAFF. Also, the Canadian Cardiovascular Society Guidelines
      indicate that there have not been enough studies to know if the best treatment is to use an
      electrical shock (Shock Only) or drugs followed by shock (Drug-Shock). Investigators believe
      that Drug-Shock approach will be more effective and will help avoid an electric shock for
      many patients. Investigators also do not know if electrical shocks should be given with the
      electrode pads on the front (antero-lateral) or front and back (antero-posterior).

      Investigators intend to conduct 2 randomized protocols within one study (partial factorial
      design) in order to answer these two questions. 1. Will initial drug treatment followed by
      electrical shock if necessary (Drug-Shock) lead to more patients being converted to normal
      heart rhythm than a strategy of only electrical shock (Shock Only)? 2. Will the
      antero-posterior pad position be more effective than the antero-lateral position?
      Investigators plan to enroll 468 RAFF patients at 8 large Canadian EDs. Patients will be
      randomized to 1 of 2 arms for each of the two protocols. Investigators primary outcome will
      be conversion to normal heart rhythm. Other outcomes will include heart rhythm at discharge,
      need for hospital admission, length of stay in ED, adverse events, patient satisfaction, and
      14-day follow-up status.

      Investigator results will add important information about the best and safest ways to treat
      RAFF patients in Canadian EDs. Ultimately Investigators expect to see fewer patients admitted
      to hospital and more patients rapidly and safely returned to their normal activities.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Atrial fibrillation (AF) is characterized by disorganized atrial electrical
      depolarization leading to an irregular and rapid heart rate and is the most common arrhythmia
      seen in the emergency department (ED). Atrial flutter (AFL) is a less common arrhythmia with
      similar pathophysiology. Investigators will focus on recent-onset episodes of AF and AFL
      (RAFF), which have usually been present less than 48 hours, are highly symptomatic, and may
      be a first or recurrent event. There is a surprising lack of evidence regarding many
      important ED RAFF management questions and the 2011 Canadian Cardiovascular Society AF
      Guidelines indicate clinical equipoise for most facets of early care. In Canadian EDs, most
      physicians use the rhythm control approach, where attempts are made to cardiovert patients to
      sinus rhythm in the ED, either pharmacologically or electrically (DC cardioversion). Canadian
      ED physicians seem equally divided between those who prefer to attempt rhythm control
      initially with drugs and then move to DC cardioversion if necessary (Drug-Shock strategy) and
      those who prefer to start immediately with DC cardioversion (Shock Only strategy).
      Investigators recently completed a prospective cohort RAFF study (N=1,065, funded by the
      Heart and Stroke Foundation of Ontario) at 6 Canadian EDs. 73.3% of all patients underwent ED
      rhythm control with 34.4% receiving rhythm control drugs first and 38.9% receiving electrical
      shock first. There is also much variation in whether the DC cardioversion electrodes are
      placed in the front and back (antero-posterior) or front and side (antero-lateral) position
      (Figure 1).

      Investigators believe that the Drug-Shock strategy has many advantages over a Shock Only
      strategy. Most Canadian EDs have a single physician on duty, which is a barrier to safe
      procedural sedation and DC cardioversion. Even in larger EDs, DC cardioversion requires 4
      professional staff, has a risk associated with sedation, and can be frightening for patients.
      Investigators expect that the Drug-Shock strategy will be more effective because procainamide
      will facilitate DC cardioversion and prevent early return of AF. Even if the Drug-Shock
      strategy is not more effective overall, its use can prevent the need for DC cardioversion in
      50-60% of patients. Regarding DC cardioversion pad placement, no randomized trials have ever
      been done with RAFF patients using modern biphasic devices at high energy levels.

      Study Objectives: Investigators primary aim is to compare conversion to sinus rhythm between
      the strategies of i) attempted pharmacological cardioversion with intravenous procainamide
      followed by DC cardioversion if necessary (Drug-Shock) and ii) DC cardioversion alone (Shock
      Only). Investigators secondary aim is to compare the effectiveness of the i) antero-posterior
      and ii) antero-lateral pad positions.

      Methods: Design and Interventions: Investigators propose a partial factorial study design
      with 2 protocols (Figure 2). All patients will participate in Protocol 1 (N=468) and most in
      Protocol 2 (N=356). 1. Drug versus Shock Protocol. This will be a randomized, blinded,
      placebo-controlled comparison of: i) attempted pharmacological cardioversion with intravenous
      procainamide (15mg/kg over 30 minutes) followed by DC cardioversion (200 joules x 3) if
      necessary (Drug-Shock), and ii) only DC cardioversion (Shock Only) (Hypothesis 1). 2. Pad
      Position Protocol. For the subset of patients who undergo DC cardioversion, this will be a
      randomized, open-label comparison of i) the antero-posterior pad position, and ii) the
      antero-lateral pad position (Hypothesis 2). Management protocols will be standardized.
      Randomization will be stratified by site and by rhythm (AF or AFL). Setting: 8 EDs of large,
      tertiary care Canadian hospitals. Subjects: Stable patients with primary diagnosis of RAFF
      where acute rhythm control is a safe option. Investigators will obtain patient consent.
      Outcomes: The primary outcome measure will be conversion to sinus rhythm and maintenance of
      sinus rhythm for at least 60 minutes; other outcomes will include sinus rhythm at discharge,
      hospital admission, length of stay in ED, adverse events, patient satisfaction, and 14-day
      follow-up status. Patients will be telephoned at 6 months and 1 year after the original ED
      visit to determine stroke-free status and medication changes. Data Analysis: Primary analysis
      will be intention-to-treat using chi-square testing. Sample Size: Investigators will require
      213 evaluable patients per group to detect a minimal clinically important absolute difference
      of 10% between groups. Allowing for 10% non-compliance, investigators plan to enroll 468
      patients.

      Importance: This study will answer two important questions about the early management of ED
      RAFF patients, leading to higher rhythm conversion rates and lower admission rates. The
      results will inform future efforts to create effective, safe, and efficient pathways for RAFF
      patient management in Canada.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>conversion to sinus rhythm</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome for both hypotheses will be conversion to sinus rhythm following randomization and maintenance of sinus rhythm for at least 30 minutes. Patients who have not converted by the time 3 DC shocks have been delivered or who revert to AF/AFL during the 30 minutes following the shocks will be considered treatment failures. Spontaneous conversion after randomization but prior to study interventions will be considered a treatment success.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outcomes during ED Visit</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Being in normal sinus rhythm at the time of ED disposition</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>ED disposition</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>ED disposition - admission or discharge;</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Length of stay in ED</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Length of stay in ED in minutes from time of arrival to time of discharge or admission</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Time to conversion to sinus rhythm</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Time to conversion to sinus rhythm in minutes from time of randomization; a 60 minute adjustment will be made for those randomized to placebo infusion.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events:
i) conduction problems: development of new bundle branch block or QT lengthening &gt;25% from baseline; ii) dysrhythmias: bradycardia (heart rate &lt; 50 bpm), ventricular tachyarrhythmias (torsade de pointes, sustained ventricular tachycardia &gt; 30 seconds, or ventricular fibrillation), or cardiac arrest; iii) hypotension: systolic BP &lt; 90 mm-Hg; iv) respiratory events: hypoxia (O2 saturation &lt; 90%), aspiration, or airway manoeuvres (e.g., jaw positioning, oral airway, BVM ventilation, intubation).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Physician Comments</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Physician comments on the protocol gathered as narrative by research staff.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">468</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <condition>Atrial Flutter</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>drug-shock vs shock only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>For ED patients with RAFF, Investigators will compare conversion to normal sinus rhythm between the two strategies of i) attempted pharmacological cardioversion with intravenous procainamide followed by DC cardioversion if necessary (Drug-Shock), and ii) DC cardioversion alone (Shock Only).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>pad positions</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>For ED RAFF patients undergoing DC cardioversion, Investigators will compare conversion to normal sinus rhythm between the i) antero-posterior and ii) antero-lateral pad positions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>drug-shock vs shock only</intervention_name>
    <description>procainamide followed by electrocardioversion if necessary vs cardioversion only.</description>
    <arm_group_label>drug-shock vs shock only</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  include stable (see below) patients presenting with an episode of RAFF of at least 3
             hours duration,

          -  where symptoms require urgent management and where pharmacological or DC cardioversion
             is a reasonable option because there is a clear history of:

          -  onset within 48 hours, or

          -  onset within 7 days and adequately anticoagulated for &gt; 4 weeks (warfarin and INR &gt;
             2.0 or newer oral anticoagulants [dabigatran, rivaroxaban, and apixaban]), or

          -  onset within 7 days and no left atrial thrombus on TEE. Of note, Investigators will
             not exclude patients with prior episodes of RAFF.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Investigators will exclude patients for the reasons listed below.

          -  who are unable to give consent;

          -  who have permanent (chronic) AF;

          -  whose episode did not clearly start within 48 hours [or 7 days if anticoagulated /
             normal TEE];

          -  who are deemed unstable and require immediate cardioversion: i) systolic blood
             pressure &lt;100 mmHg; ii) rapid ventricular preexcitation (Wolff-Parkinson-White
             syndrome); iii) acute coronary syndrome - chest pain and acute ischemic changes on
             ECG; or iv) pulmonary edema - severe dyspnea requiring immediate IV diuretic,
             nitrates, or BIPAP;

          -  whose primary presentation was for another condition; examples include pneumonia,
             pulmonary embolism, and sepsis;

          -  who convert spontaneously to sinus rhythm prior to randomization; or

          -  who were previously enrolled in the study.

        Safety Exclusions:

          1. who are known to have severe heart failure (left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;30% or
             have clinical or radiological evidence of acute HF);

          2. whose heart rate &lt; 55 bpm;

          3. who have 3rd degree AV block or complete LBBB or a history of 2nd or 3rd degree AV
             block (in the absence of a permanent pacemaker or implantable
             cardioverter-defibrillator [ICD]);

          4. whose ECG shows QTc &gt;460ms;

          5. who have Brugada syndrome (genetic disease with increased risk of sudden cardiac
             death);

          6. who currently take class I or III antiarrhythmic drugs (last dose &lt; 5 half-lives
             before enrolment) except Amiodarone;

          7. who have hypersensitivity to procainamide, procaine, other ester-type local
             anesthetics, or any component of the formulation;

          8. who have had a recent myocardial infarction (&lt; 3 months);

          9. who have these chronic diseases: renal failure (GFR &lt;60 mL/min/1.73m2) or liver
             disease; or

         10. who are breast feeding or pregnant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ian G Stiell, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ian Stiell, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>613-798-5555</phone>
    <phone_ext>18683</phone_ext>
    <email>istiell@ohri.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Foothills Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>2TN 1M7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrew McRae, MD</last_name>
      <phone>403-944-5484</phone>
      <email>amcrae@ucalgary.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eddy Lang, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew McRae, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rockyview General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrew McRae, MD</last_name>
      <email>amcrae@ucalgary.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alberta Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 2B7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Brian Rowe, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(780) 407-6707</phone>
      <email>Brian.Rowe@ualberta.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Brian Rowe, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vancouver General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V5Z 1M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Corinne Hohl, MD</last_name>
      <email>chohl@mail.ubc.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Corinne Hohl, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kingston General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kingston</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K7L 2V7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert Brison, MD</last_name>
      <phone>613-549-6666</phone>
      <phone_ext>4217</phone_ext>
      <email>brisonr@kgh.kari.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Brison, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marco LA Sivilotti, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1Y 4E9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ian Stiell, MD, MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 1X5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shelley McLeod, MSc</last_name>
      <phone>416-586-4800</phone>
      <phone_ext>8330</phone_ext>
      <email>SMcLeod@mtsinai.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bjug Borgundvaag, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Montreal Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H1T 1C8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alain Vadeboncoeur, MD</last_name>
      <email>alain.vadeboncoeur@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alain Vadeboncoeur, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Laurent Macle, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Du Sacre-Coeur</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Judy Morris, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital de L'Enfant-Jesus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Quebec City</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eric Mercier, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Marcel Emond, MD</last_name>
      <email>marcelemond1@me.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 27, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 2, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrial Flutter</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

