<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01894763</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1063-04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01894763</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Comparison of Large vs. Small Diameter Esophageal Stents for Palliation of Malignant Dysphagia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized, Prospective Comparison of Large vs. Small Diameter Esophageal Stents for Palliation of Malignant Dysphagia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tenwek Hospital, Bomet, Kenya</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Esophageal cancer often causes difficulty swallowing (dysphagia) that can be relieved by
      placement of a stent (a flexible, expandable tube that props open the blockage caused by the
      cancer). Stents are effective but can cause complications. Stents come in different
      diameters. The purpose of this study is to learn if stents of different diameters are more or
      less effective for treatment of dysphagia caused by esophageal cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This prospective, randomized study was conducted at Tenwek Hospital in Bomet, Kenya, and was
      approved by the hospital's institutional review board (IRB) as well as the Kenya Medical
      Research Institute's Ethical Review Committee. Participants with dysphagia were recruited and
      provided signed informed consent prior to endoscopy. During endoscopy and after dilation of
      an obstructing esophageal tumor sufficient to permit passage of an endoscope, eligible
      participants were enrolled and randomized to receive either an 18 mm shaft/23 mm flange or 23
      mm shaft/28 mm flange partially covered Ultraflex esophageal stent (Boston Scientific,
      Natick, Massachusets, USA). Stents were either 10 or 12 cm in length, and the endoscopist
      chose a stent length based on the length of the malignant stricture. One stent was placed in
      each subject. Follow-up was then obtained at scheduled intervals after stent placement (7 and
      28 days, 3 months, then every 3 months), until the participant's death. Earlier follow-up
      visits were arranged if participants reported any new health concerns.

      Block randomization was performed using the sealed envelope technique, with 10 participants
      in each block; none of the study personnel at Tenwek Hospital had knowledge of the
      randomization sequence. Allocation was concealed from participants, caregivers, and study
      personnel until randomization occurred during an endoscopic procedure. After randomization,
      stent diameters were known to the endoscopy staff and listed in the medical record. All
      randomized participants correctly received a stent of the allocated diameter, and remained
      blinded to the stent diameter they received.

      At baseline and each follow-up visit body weight was recorded, as well as Karnofsky
      performance status score, dysphagia score (0=normal, no dysphagia; 1=can swallow most foods;
      2=can swallow a soft diet; 3=can swallow fluids only; 4=unable to swallow saliva), current
      medications, and the presence or absence of 15 symptoms and 9 diagnoses (weakness, fever,
      vomiting, vomiting blood, melena, weak voice, difficulty breathing, cough, sputum,
      palpitations, heartburn, chest pain, hiccoughs, recurrent dysphagia, abdominal pain; anemia,
      gastrointestinal bleeding, esophago-respiratory fistula, arrhythmia, pneumonia, metastases,
      stent occlusion, stent migration, gastroesophageal reflux disease). In addition, all interval
      clinic visits, test results, endoscopy reports, and hospitalizations were reviewed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relief of dysphagia</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month following stent placement</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with improvement in dysphagia score to &lt;2</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications</measure>
    <time_frame>from stent placement to death or 5 years of follow-up, whichever comes first</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants who experience stent-related symptoms (including chest pain, recurrent dysphagia, hematemesis, melena, palpitations) or complications (including gastrointestinal hemorrhage, esophago-respiratory fistula, stent migration, stent occlusion) from the time of stent placement until death or 5-year follow-up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>from stent placement to death or 5 years of follow-up, whichever comes first</time_frame>
    <description>Time (in days) from stent placement to death, assessed by Kaplan-Meier analysis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Endoscopic re-intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>from stent placement to death or 5 years of follow-up, whichever comes first</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants undergoing repeat endoscopy to diagnose or treat a stent-related problem at any time from stent placement to death or 5 year follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>performance status</measure>
    <time_frame>from stent placement to death or 5 years of follow-up, whichever comes first</time_frame>
    <description>Karnofsky performance status, assessed by Kaplan Meier analysis, from stent placement to death or 5-year follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Small-diameter stent</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placement of a 23 mm self-expandable metal stent</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Large-diameter stent</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placement of a 28-mm self-expandable metal stent</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Self-expandable metal stent</intervention_name>
    <description>Placement of a self-expandable metal stent in the esophagus</description>
    <arm_group_label>Small-diameter stent</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Large-diameter stent</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ultraflex Esophageal Stents</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age ≥ 18 years

          -  dysphagia due to unresectable esophageal cancer

          -  participant resides within 50 km of Tenwek Hospital

          -  tumor is ≤ 9 cm in length and &gt; 2 cm distal to the upper esophageal sphincter (UES)

          -  no esophago-respiratory fistula (ERF) or suspected perforation is present

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  unable to provide written informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Russell White, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tenwek Hospital, Bomet, Kenya</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tenwek Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bomet</city>
        <country>Kenya</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Kenya</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 4, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 10, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 4, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 4, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 10, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mark Topazian</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>esophagus</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

