<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01892124</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>44890-G</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P60MD006909</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01892124</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Motivational Interviewing and Cognitive Behavioral Therapy-based Intervention for Cardiovascular Disease Prevention Amongst American Indians With Diabetic and Depressive Symptoms</brief_title>
  <official_title>Healthy Hearts, Healthy Minds</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities (NIMHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Washington</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      American Indians (AIs) living in the Northwest have very high rates of diabetes, obesity,
      tobacco use, depression, and other risk factors associated with cardiovascular disease.
      Depression and diabetes have a pernicious effect on CVD risk and susceptibility. This study
      seeks to build upon the success of the 1-month, 5-session motivational interviewing (MI) CVD
      prevention component of the həli?dxw Project (aka Healthy Hearts-originally funded under
      RFA-HL-06-002; U01 HL HL087322-05). həli?dxw successfully culturally adapted MI for CVD
      prevention for AIs, trained AIs to implement the intervention, and conducted a preliminary
      feasibility and efficacy trial. Initial results indicated that participants enthusiastically
      embraced the MI component of the program; however, observations of the counselors, survey
      data, and feedback from participants suggest that depressive symptomatology served as a
      barrier to achieving CVD preventive behaviors and desired outcomes; and, that more time and
      attention to underlying depressive symptomatology may enhance motivation and CVD prevention
      behaviors, particularly among AIs with pre-diabetes and Type 2 diabetes. Building upon solid
      preliminary CVD epidemiological data, preliminary acceptability and feasibility of utilizing
      an MI approach, and motivated by the need to address elevated depression and diabetes
      profiles from the həli?dxw study, the investigators will develop a 3-month, 10-session
      MI-based cognitive-behavioral-adherence (MI-CBT-CVD) treatment program to address underlying
      depressive symptomatology, activate CVD prevention behaviors, and decrease BMI and CVD risk
      behaviors among 50 pre-and recently diagnosed diabetic AIs at risk for CVD. The study
      proposes three innovative and significant aims. First, in line with community-based
      participatory (CBPR) principles and pre-established indigenous research protocols with the
      tribal community, the investigators will conduct formative research to develop the MI-CBT-CVD
      intervention. Second, the investigators will conduct a pilot randomized two-group,
      single-site waitlist-controlled clinical trial of a 10-session, 3-month MI-based
      cognitive-behavioral treatment for CVD prevention (MI-CBT-CVD) among 50 pre-and recently
      diagnosed diabetic AI adults with depressive symptomatology and who are also at risk for CVD.
      Assessments will be conducted at pre and post intervention and at 6-months (3 month
      follow-up). Third, the investigators will disseminate the findings to the tribe as well as
      research outlets and prepare an RO1 to conduct a full-scale RCT should the pilot intervention
      be efficacious, acceptable to the community, and feasible. The primary objectives will be to
      determine the effect of the proposed culturally-grounded behavioral intervention program on
      (a) reducing weight as measured by BMI (7-10% reduction in BMI); (b) decreasing depressive
      symptomatology; (c) increasing physical activity; (d) decreasing sedentary activities; (d)
      increasing healthful food habits; and (e) improving biomedical outcomes (e.g., blood lipid
      profiles, glucose, hemoglobin A1C, and blood pressure). The intervention will be culturally
      relevant and utilize existing Native resources and personnel wherever possible.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Body Mass Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, 3 month, and 6 month timepoints</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will compare changes in body mass index between the wait-list control group and the immediate intervention group, and also for each individual over time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Depressive Symptoms using the Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-D)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, 3 month, and 6 month timepoints</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will compare changes in depressive symptoms as measured by the CES-D 10-item scale between the wait-list control group and the immediate intervention group, and also for each individual over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Blood Lipids</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, 3 month, and 6 month timepoints</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will compare changes in mg/dL of blood lipids (Total cholesterol, HDL-C, LDL-C, triglycerides) between the wait-list control group and the immediate intervention group, and also for each individual over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Blood Glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, 3 month, and 6 month timepoints</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will compare changes in mg/dL blood glucose between the wait-list control group and the immediate intervention group, and also for each individual over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Hemoglobin A1c</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, 3 month, and 6 month timepoints</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will compare changes in percent hemoglobin A1c between the wait-list control group and the immediate intervention group, and also for each individual over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, 3 month, and 6 month timepoints</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will compare changes in mmHg blood pressure levels between the wait-list control group and the immediate intervention group, and also for each individual over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Physical Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, 3 month, and 6 month timepoints</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will compare changes in physical activity levels between the wait-list control group and the immediate intervention group, and also for each individual over time.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Sedentary Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, 3 month, and 6 month timepoints</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will compare changes in sedentary activity levels between the wait-list control group and the immediate intervention group, and also for each individual over time.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Food Habits</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, 3 month, and 6 month timepoints</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will compare changes in food habits between the wait-list control group and the immediate intervention group, and also for each individual over time.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">34</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Dysthymic Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Motivational Interviewing/Cognitive Behavioral-based Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receives an immediate weekly 10 session intervention based on a culturally-adapted, motivational interviewing and Cognitive Behavioral Therapy grounded protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wait-List Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Receives a weekly 10 session intervention based on a culturally-adapted, motivational interviewing and Cognitive Behavioral Therapy grounded protocol after a three month, no-intervention waiting period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Motivational Interviewing/Cognitive Behavioral-based Therapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Motivational Interviewing/Cognitive Behavioral-based Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Wait-List Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Be 18 years of age or older

          -  Be an American Indian/Alaska Native

          -  Currently reside on or within 20 miles of the Tribal reservation boundary

          -  Have a Body Mass Index &gt; 25

          -  Have a PSS (10 item) score &gt; 15

          -  Be pre-diabetic for Type 2 diabetes (via self-report, health provider referral, or
             previous glucose reading or hemoglobin A1c reading indicating pre-diabetes within the
             past 12 months) or have been diagnosed as having Type 2 diabetes

          -  If a woman, not currently pregnant

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Referred to their physician for approval of participation during the baseline
             assessment process and the physician does not give approval or the participant refused
             to follow-up on the referral

          -  Unstable or exhibits serious psychiatric symptoms as determined by project's tribal
             mental health specialist
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karina L Walters, MSW, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rachelle McCarty, ND, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington, Indigenous Wellness Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.iwri.org/</url>
    <description>Indigenous Wellness Research Institute at the University of Washington</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walters KL, LaMarr J, Levy RL, Pearson C, Maresca T, Mohammed SA, Simoni JM, Evans-Campbell T, Fredriksen-Goldsen K, Fryberg S, Jobe JB; həli?dxw Intervention Team. Project həli?dx(w)/Healthy Hearts Across Generations: development and evaluation design of a tribally based cardiovascular disease prevention intervention for American Indian families. J Prim Prev. 2012 Aug;33(4):197-207. doi: 10.1007/s10935-012-0274-z.</citation>
    <PMID>22965622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mohammed SA, Walters KL, Lamarr J, Evans-Campbell T, Fryberg S. Finding middle ground: negotiating university and tribal community interests in community-based participatory research. Nurs Inq. 2012 Jun;19(2):116-27. doi: 10.1111/j.1440-1800.2011.00557.x. Epub 2011 Jul 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22530859</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 28, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 28, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 3, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 11, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 11, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 15, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Washington</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Karina Walters</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, School of Social Work; Director, Indigenous Wellness Research Institute</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Motivational Interviewing</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Community-Based Participatory Research</keyword>
  <keyword>Indians, North American</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dysthymic Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

