<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01892514</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AVN-13</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01892514</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Randomized Clinical Trial for the Treatment of Osteonecrosis of the Femoral Head</brief_title>
  <acronym>AVN-13</acronym>
  <official_title>Combined Treatment of Early and Advanced Osteonecrosis of the Femoral Head With Core Decompression and Grafting With Demineralized Bone Matrix (DBM) or Homologous Lyophilized Bone Chips (LBC) Together With Platelet-rich-fibrin (PRF) and Concentrated Bone Marrow (CBM)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Istituto Ortopedico Rizzoli</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Istituto Ortopedico Rizzoli</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Femoral head avascular necrosis is a relatively common disease (10,000 - 20,000 yearly new
      United States of America cases) characterized by ischemic cell necrosis in a hip proximal
      epiphysis area frequently requiring total Hip Arthroplasty (THA).

      Even though THA resolves symptoms and restores good joint function, young patients are prone
      to major disabilities and require prosthesis revision surgeries.

      In this clinical trial a comparison between two groups of patients, treated with the same
      procedure but with two different regenerative techniques, will be performed:

        1. 52 patients with necrosis in an early stage, without deformity of the femoral epiphysis
           (stage 2A-B-C in Association for Research on Osseous Circulation (ARCO) classification,
           will undergo wide decompression of the necrotic area and reconstruction with homologous
           Lyophilized Bone Chips (LBC), growth factors from platelet concentrate Platelet-Rich
           Fibrin (PRF) and Concentrated Bone Marrow (CBM).

        2. 52 patients with necrosis of similar features, without deformity of the femoral
           epiphysis, will undergo wide decompression of the necrotic area and reconstruction with
           Demineralized Bone Matrix (DBM), growth factors from Platelet-Rich-Fibrin (PRF) and
           Concentrated Bone Marrow (CBM).

      Patients will be evaluated post-surgery at 6 weeks, 3, 6, 12, and 24 months to assess joint
      damage evolution by ARCO classification, and hip function by clinical scores (Harris Hip
      Score (HHS), Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Arthritis Index (WOMAC) Score, and
      Visual Analogic Scale (VAS)).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale. In vitro study and animal models have shown that Mesenchymal Stromal Cells (MSC)
      have the capacity to differentiate into osteoblastic lineage and that platelet reach fibrin
      can represent a clinical source of growth factors, able to accelerate the processes of tissue
      repair. This study intend to highlight how these factors, associated to two different
      preparations of bone allograft, may accelerate the formation of new host bone in patients
      with osteonecrosis of the femoral head that represents a common condition in clinical
      practice with an high socio-economic impact.

      Primary objective of the study is to delay or avoid total hip replacement in patients with
      early necrosis of the femoral head, using different methods of regenerative medicine.

      Secondary end points are described below:

        -  To assess differences in outcome related to features, etiology and localization of the
           necrosis of the femoral head and to assess variation in post-operative return to daily
           activities.

        -  To characterize the osteogenetic and angiogenic potential of marrow-derived Mesenchymal
           Stromal Cells (MSC) in patients with avascular necrosis of the femoral head, and to
           correlate these features with medical history and clinical outcome.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction of the total necrotic area by Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, and 12 months after surgery</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain reduction by measurement of the Visual Analog Scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, and 6 weeks, 3, 6, 12, 24 months after surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional status evaluated by Harris Hip Score (HHS) and Western Ontario McMaster Universities Arthritis Index (WOMAC)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, and 6, 12, 24 months after surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>maintenance of structural integrity of the joint by Radiography (RX)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, and 6 weeks, 3, 6, 12, 24 months after surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">104</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteonecrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Demineralized Bone Marrow (DBM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>core decompression of necrotic area and graft with a biological product based on Demineralized Bone Matrix (DBM), Platelet-Rich-Fibrin (PRF) and Concentrated Bone Marrow (CBM)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lyophilized Bone Chips (LBC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>core decompression of the necrotic area and graft with a biological product based on homologous Lyophilized Bone Chips (LBC), Platelet-Rich Fibrin (PRF) and Concentrated Bone Marrow (CBM)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>core decompression</intervention_name>
    <description>core decompression of necrotic area and graft with Platelet-Rich Fibrin (PRF) and Concentrated Bone Marrow (CBM)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Demineralized Bone Marrow (DBM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Lyophilized Bone Chips (LBC)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with necrosis of the femoral head without fracture of the subchondral bone
             and without flattening of the head itself (according to ARCO classification 2A, B, C).

          -  Age between 18 and 60 years.

          -  Any etiology

          -  Patients who had undergone a previous orthopaedic treatment for traumatology
             interventions

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients under the age of 18 years or more than 60 years.

          -  Patients not able to provide informed consent to treatment.

          -  Patients suffering from apparent local infective processes.

          -  Patients with active neoplastic diseases.

          -  Patients with necrosis of the femoral head of advanced stages (ARCO 3A, B, C, 4).

          -  Pregnant patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dante Dallari, Surgeon</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rizzoli Orthopaedic Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>3rd Orthopaedic and Traumatologic Clinic, prevalently oncologic, Rizzoli Orthopaedic Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bologna</city>
        <zip>40136</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>S.S.D. Conservative Orthopaedic Surgery and Innovative Techniques, Rizzoli Orthopaedic Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bologna</city>
        <zip>40136</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Orthopaedic and Traumatologic Department Policlinico di Modena</name>
      <address>
        <city>Modena</city>
        <zip>41124</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ior.it/remod/wp4</url>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dallari D, Fini M, Stagni C, Torricelli P, Nicoli Aldini N, Giavaresi G, Cenni E, Baldini N, Cenacchi A, Bassi A, Giardino R, Fornasari PM, Giunti A. In vivo study on the healing of bone defects treated with bone marrow stromal cells, platelet-rich plasma, and freeze-dried bone allografts, alone and in combination. J Orthop Res. 2006 May;24(5):877-88.</citation>
    <PMID>16609976</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dallari D, Savarino L, Stagni C, Cenni E, Cenacchi A, Fornasari PM, Albisinni U, Rimondi E, Baldini N, Giunti A. Enhanced tibial osteotomy healing with use of bone grafts supplemented with platelet gel or platelet gel and bone marrow stromal cells. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2007 Nov;89(11):2413-20.</citation>
    <PMID>17974883</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 25, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 1, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 4, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 30, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>osteonecrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>bone marrow concentrate</keyword>
  <keyword>demineralized bone matrix</keyword>
  <keyword>homologous lyophilized bone chips</keyword>
  <keyword>autologous platelet rich fibrin</keyword>
  <keyword>mesenchymal stromal cells</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteonecrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

