<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01894009</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VGFOUSKB-43121</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01894009</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Foot Manipulation for Pregnancy Related Pelvic Girdle Pain</brief_title>
  <acronym>PPGP</acronym>
  <official_title>Effect of Foot Manipulation for Relief of Pregnancy Related Pelvic Girdle Pain. A Randomised Clinical Trial in Primary Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kaj Stenlof</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vastra Gotaland Region</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Asymmetrical foot posture influences the pelvic girdle stability and might give
      pain in the pelvic region. The objective was to investigate if foot manipulation to correct
      foot asymmetry can relieve pregnancy related pelvic girdle pain (PPGP) and shorten sick leave
      periods.

      Design: Randomized single blinded (patients and evaluators) clinical trial comparing foot
      with sham manipulation at 6 weekly treatment sessions.

      Setting: Five physiotherapy out-patient clinics (10 physiotherapists) in Skaraborg Primary
      Care, Sweden.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study was performed at the physiotherapy clinics at five Health Care Centres in Skaraborg
      from September 2009 to August 2011. Women with suspected PPGP were referred by midwifes or
      physicians or contacted the physiotherapists directly. Inclusion criteria were
      Swedish-speaking women in gestational weeks 12-31 with PPGP determined by specific
      provocation tests, including the 4P test (posterior pelvic pain provocation test), Patrick`s
      test, ASLR (active straight leg raise test), modified Trendelenburg test and palpation of
      symphysis pubis. Women with twin pregnancies, lumbar pain, rheumatic or other serious disease
      were excluded as well as non-Swedish-speaking woman and those who had had foot manipulation
      earlier. The feet were inspected in standing position to estimate whether they were straight,
      rotated outwards or inwards and if the load was flat, pronated or supinated. Movement in the
      subtalar joints was investigated as well as elasticity of the tarsal bones and the lateral
      malleoli. All women that were included had asymmetric position of one or both feet.

      Study procedure Patients were randomized to either foot or sham manipulation using sealed
      envelopes (n=150; 75 for each treatment). The envelopes were administered and mixed centrally
      and depending on size the physiotherapy clinic were assigned an appropriate number of
      envelopes. Ten physiotherapists participated pair-wise in the treatments, one treated the
      patient (physiotherapist unblinded, patient blinded), and the other made the evaluation
      (double blinded). All patients got the same information about PPGP and 6 visits once a week
      during 6 weeks, and follow-up visits one week after end of treatment and three months after
      delivery. All patients were encouraged not to talk to other pregnant women or to the
      evaluators about details of their treatment.

      Data were registered in protocols separated from the medical records, not accessible for the
      evaluators, and included group assignment, results of diagnostic tests, Vorlauf tests and
      Visual Analogue Scales (VAS). The blinded evaluator administered the follow-up three months
      after delivery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in Pregnancy related pelvic girdle pain and Vorlauf test outcome</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after treatment at assessments during 6 weeks and three months after childbirth.</time_frame>
    <description>Pain reduction:
Pain in pelvic girdle,(pain in pelvis, sacroiliac joint (SIJ) and symphysis)during 6 weeks after start of treatment and 3 months after childbirth using VAS a diary with VAS graded from 0 to 100 rating their pain each morning and evening.
Vorlauf test:
Both posterior superior iliac spines (PSIS) were identified with the patient sitting by a grip underneath the lower edge of the spines. The grip was maintained as the patient rose and the levels of the PSIS were noted. If the levels differed (positive Vorlauf test), the lowest was compensated with a plate measuring 2-5 mm under the corresponding foot after which, the patient bent forward to evaluate Vorlauf. Thwew tests were performed by a physiotherapist blinded to the kind of treatment the woman was exposed to. An asymmetric movement of PSIS indicated a locking of the sacroiliac joint.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in number of days of Sick leave</measure>
    <time_frame>Before and after treatment at assessments during 6 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Sick leave:
During 6 weeks after start of treatment and 3 months after childbirth using a diary in which they indicated whether they were on sick leave 25%, 50%, 75% or 100% of full time. Net days of sick leave were calculated as the number of days multiplied with the degree of sick leave.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">97</enrollment>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Foot manipulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Asymmetry of the feet was treated by thrusting of the cuboid bone and the subtalar joint was treated with gapping thrust. Mobilisation of the distal tibia-fibula was repeated 10 times. Home training programs in order to maintain the mobility in the joints were given with morning exercises. Four types of exercises were recommended: 1) Foot training with pro-and supination of the feet from dorsal to plantar flexion. 2)&quot;Caterpillar walk&quot;. 3) Training the take off of the great toes along a normal walking line and 4) Mobility of lateral malleoli and the talo-crural joint by dorsal flexion of feet while bending the knees.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham foot manipulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sham manipulation included downsizing (a massage technique) the section underneath the heel from back forwards with four grips and palpation of the five metatarsal bones with the patient in the supine position on a psoas pillow. Further, light pressure on the Achilles tendon, with the patient standing against a wall with the feet 40 cm off the wall with bent knees on order to simulate the tibio-fibular mobilisation. Home exercises in the mornings to be repeated 8 times.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Foot manipulation</intervention_name>
    <description>The subtalar joint was treated with gapping thrust with patient lying on the contra-lateral side. Mobilisation of the distal tibia-fibula was performed with the patient squatting and was repeated 10 times. Home training programs in order to maintain the mobility in the joints were given.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Foot manipulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham foot manipulation</intervention_name>
    <description>Sham manipulation included downsizing (a massage technique) the section underneath the heel from back forwards with four grips and palpation of the five metatarsal bones. Sham manipulations were repeated 10 times. This group was also recommended home exercises in the mornings.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham foot manipulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Women with suspected PPGP were referred by midwifes or physicians or contacted the
        physiotherapists directly.

        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Swedish-speaking women in gestational weeks 12-31

          -  Pregnancy Related Pelvic Girdle Pain (PPGP) determined by provocation tests (4P test,
             posterior pelvic pain provocation test; Patrick`s test, ASLR (active straight leg
             raise test), modified Trendelenburg test and pain on palpation of symphysis pubis

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Women with:

          -  twin pregnancies

          -  lumbar pain

          -  rheumatic or other serious disease

          -  non-Swedish-speaking woman

          -  those who had had experinced foot manipulation earlier
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Camilla Melkersson, Physiother</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>R&amp;D Centre, Skaraborg Primary Care, Skövde, Sweden</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Närhälsan Tibro Rehabmottagningen, Centrumgatan 11-17</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tibro</city>
        <zip>S-54381</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 20, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 2, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 9, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 2, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 2, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 9, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Vastra Gotaland Region</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kaj Stenlof</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Osteopathic manipulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy pelvic girdle pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pelvic Girdle Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

