<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00024479</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>010227</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>01-AR-0227</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00024479</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Natural History of Rheumatic Diseases in Minority Communities</brief_title>
  <official_title>Studies of the Natural History of Rheumatic Disease in Minority Communities</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will explore the causes of rheumatic diseases and why many of them affect certain
      minority communities more severely. Rheumatic diseases may cause joint pain, stiffness or
      swelling. Some can involve bones, muscles, tendons or ligaments. Some cause abnormalities of
      the immune system the body s defense against disease. Some rheumatic diseases are painful or
      deforming and some can be life threatening. Information obtained from this study will be used
      to learn about the disparities in rheumatic disease in the minority community and to design
      further, more targeted, research studies to address this issue.

      Patients with known or suspected rheumatic disease 18 years of age or older may be eligible
      for this study. Candidates will undergo a medical history and physical examination to confirm
      the diagnosis of rheumatic disease and determine what is needed for evaluation and treatment.

      Participants will receive standard medical care for rheumatic disease and arthritis. No
      experimental treatments, medications or procedures will be included in this study. Procedures
      may include routine blood tests for blood chemistries, cell counts, and antibodies commonly
      found in patients with rheumatic disease; a urine test for proteins and cells; and X-rays and
      other imaging tests to check for abnormalities in the lungs or other organs. All medical
      information will be kept confidential.

      Patients who are found to be eligible for other current NIH research studies will be offered
      an opportunity to participate in these studies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This protocol will permit the evaluation and treatment of subjects who are members of the

      minority community, for the purpose to facilitate understanding the pathogenesis and natural
      history of rheumatic diseases in this community. Patients will be evaluated with a history
      and physical examination and routine laboratory studies will be obtained as needed to assess
      diagnosis, disease activity, disease complications and to monitor for treatment related
      responses and toxicities. Patients eligible for other research protocols will be offered an
      opportunity to participate in these studies by signed informed consent. Any medical care
      recommended or provided to the patient will be consistent with routine standards of practice
      and will be provided in consultation with the patient s referring physician. All patients
      referred to this study must have a primary care provider provide a referral. The
      establishment of this protocol will provide a means to evaluate and treat patients from the
      minority community, and to generate hypotheses and protocols based on this clinical
      experience that will address questions of health disparities in the rheumatic diseases.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 12, 2001</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To generate hypotheses relating to basis and/or effects of health disparities in the community, which may serve as basis for subsequent research efforts based in the community and/or at NIH Clinical Center.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100000</enrollment>
  <condition>Rheumatic Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects with known or suspected rheumatic disease.

        Age greater than or equal to 18 years.

        Willingness and capacity to provide informed consent.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients who cannot meet the inclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James D Katz, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>James D Katz, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-6807</phone>
    <email>james.katz@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2001-AR-0227.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reveille JD, Moulds JM, Ahn C, Friedman AW, Baethge B, Roseman J, Straaton KV, Alarcón GS. Systemic lupus erythematosus in three ethnic groups: I. The effects of HLA class II, C4, and CR1 alleles, socioeconomic factors, and ethnicity at disease onset. LUMINA Study Group. Lupus in minority populations, nature versus nurture. Arthritis Rheum. 1998 Jul;41(7):1161-72.</citation>
    <PMID>9663471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lawrence RC, Helmick CG, Arnett FC, Deyo RA, Felson DT, Giannini EH, Heyse SP, Hirsch R, Hochberg MC, Hunder GG, Liang MH, Pillemer SR, Steen VD, Wolfe F. Estimates of the prevalence of arthritis and selected musculoskeletal disorders in the United States. Arthritis Rheum. 1998 May;41(5):778-99.</citation>
    <PMID>9588729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jordan JM. Effect of race and ethnicity on outcomes in arthritis and rheumatic conditions. Curr Opin Rheumatol. 1999 Mar;11(2):98-103. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10319211</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 1, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2001</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 13, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 14, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Minorities</keyword>
  <keyword>Rheumatic Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Community Based</keyword>
  <keyword>Ethnicity</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Disparities</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rheumatic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Collagen Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

