<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00023075</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>010241</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>01-N-0241</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00023075</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nuclear Magnetic Spectroscopy Imaging to Evaluate Primary Lateral Sclerosis, Hereditary Spastic Paraplegia and Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Nuclear Magnetic Spectroscopy for the Evaluation of Primary Lateral Sclerosis, Hereditary Spastic Paraplegia and Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will use a magnetic resonance imaging technique called nuclear magnetic
      spectroscopy (H-MRS) to define the pathology and progression of primary lateral sclerosis,
      hereditary spastic paraplegia and amyotrophic lateral sclerosis and assess the usefulness of
      this technique in evaluating patients' response to therapy. H-MRS will be used to examine
      metabolic changes in the parts of the brain and spinal cord (motor cortex and corticospinal
      tract) involved in movement.

      Normal volunteers and patients with primary lateral sclerosis, hereditary spastic paraplegia
      or amyotrophic lateral sclerosis between 21 and 65 years of age may be eligible for this
      study. Participants will have up to five H-MRS studies, including baseline and follow-up
      tests. For this procedure, the subject lies on a stretcher that is moved into a strong
      magnetic field. Earplugs are worn to muffle the loud knocking noise that occurs during
      switching of radio frequencies. The subject will be asked to lie still during each scan, for
      1 to 8 minutes at a time. Total scanning time varies from 20 minutes to 2 hours, with most
      examinations lasting between 45 and 90 minutes. Communication with the medical staff is
      possible at all times during the scan.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Standard MRI imaging of the brain shows no consistent abnormalities in many degenerative
      disorders with progressive upper motor neuron symptoms, including primary lateral sclerosis,
      hereditary spastic paraparesis, and amyotrophic lateral sclerosis. Nuclear magnetic resonance
      spectroscopy (H-MRS) is able to evaluate certain cerebral metabolites that reflect the
      functioning and integrity of neurons. The objective of this protocol is to study metabolic
      changes in the motor cortex and corticospinal tract using MRS in these disorders to
      characterize the pathology, the progression of the diseases, and assess the utility of MRS to
      follow the response to therapies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date>August 2003</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>55</enrollment>
  <condition>Primary Lateral Sclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Hereditary Spastic Paraplegia</condition>
  <condition>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Adult patients with PLS, HSP, and ALS already evaluated by protocol #01-N-0148.

        Adult normal volunteers

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Pregnancy, implanted devices such as pacemakers, medication pumps or defibrillators, metal
        in the cranium except the mouth, intracardiac lines, history of eye shrapnel injury or any
        other condition/device that may contraindicate or prevent the acquisition of an MRI.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonneau D, Rozet JM, Bulteau C, Berthier M, Mettey R, Gil R, Munnich A, Le Merrer M. X linked spastic paraplegia (SPG2): clinical heterogeneity at a single gene locus. J Med Genet. 1993 May;30(5):381-4.</citation>
    <PMID>8320699</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chan S, Shungu DC, Douglas-Akinwande A, Lange DJ, Rowland LP. Motor neuron diseases: comparison of single-voxel proton MR spectroscopy of the motor cortex with MR imaging of the brain. Radiology. 1999 Sep;212(3):763-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10478245</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Comi G, Rovaris M, Leocani L. Review neuroimaging in amyotrophic lateral sclerosis. Eur J Neurol. 1999 Nov;6(6):629-37. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10529749</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2003</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 22, 2001</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 22, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 23, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuromuscular Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>N-Acetyl Aspartate</keyword>
  <keyword>Choline</keyword>
  <keyword>Creatine</keyword>
  <keyword>Spasms</keyword>
  <keyword>Spasticity</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary Lateral Sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Hereditary Spastic Paraplegia</keyword>
  <keyword>Spastic Paraparesis</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <keyword>Normal Control</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Motor Neuron Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscle Spasticity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paraplegia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spastic Paraplegia, Hereditary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

