<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00027482</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>020066</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>02-I-0066</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00027482</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immune Responses to HIV in Blood Cells in HIV-Infected and HIV-Uninfected Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Studies of Specific Immune Responses in HIV-Infected and HIV-Uninfected Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will explore the responses of the immune system to infection with HIV and other
      pathogens and the changes in these responses over time.

      Healthy normal volunteers and HIV-infected patients 18 years of age or older may be eligible
      for this study.

      Prior to enrollment and yearly thereafter, vital signs, height and weight will be recorded. A
      medical history will be obtained if relevant to the laboratory research for which the sample
      will be used. A more extensive history and physical exam is not required but may be performed
      if deemed necessary by the VRC clinician. A complete blood count will be performed on the day
      of enrollment and yearly thereafter. Samples will be collected in the following manner:

      Blood will be drawn from a needle in an arm vein one or more times during the course of the
      study. From 20 to 150 cc (4 to 30 teaspoonfuls) of blood will be collected at a time. No more
      than 450 cc (less than 1 pint) of blood will be drawn during any 6-week period.

      Urine and saliva samples will be collected by the volunteer in private.

      Swab samples will be collected by a nurse or doctor, using a cotton swab to brush inside the
      mouth.

      Samples may be used for the following tests:

        -  Hepatitis and other viral screening-This may include screening for different types of
           viral liver infections, such as hepatitis A, B, C, D, E, or G; for cytomegalovirus
           (related to the herpes virus); and for varicella zoster virus (responsible for chicken
           pox in children and shingles in adults).

        -  Genetic testing-DNA in blood cells may be examined for genetic mutations (physical or
           chemical changes) or deletions (missing pieces) that affect substances involved in the
           body's ability to mount an inflammatory immune response. Alterations in the genes for
           some of these substances have been shown to influence HIV infection.

        -  HLA testing-HLA type is a genetic marker of the immune system. Determining HLA type is
           necessary in order to do certain research studies. Some HLA types have been associated
           with an increased risk of diseases like arthritis and other rheumatologic problems. HLA
           testing may be used to try to identify factors associated with the rate of progression
           of HIV disease or related conditions.

        -  Other laboratory tests as clinically indicated or required for research needs.

      Some samples collected in this study may be stored for future research.They will be labeled
      without identifying information.

      Those with interesting or strongly positive immune responses may be asked to return to the
      VRC Clinic to provide samples of urine or oral secretions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Vaccine Research Center (VRC) is studying specific immune responses to HIV infection and
      other pathogens in order to characterize protective responses that can prevent new infection
      in uninfected individuals, as well as define those responses that lead to successful control
      of viral replication in persons already infected with the pathogen. We wish to define the
      specific human immune responses to HIV infection, other pathogens and vaccines using human
      peripheral blood mononuclear cells, plasma, serum, urine, or oral secretions as a model.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 4, 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date>August 27, 2008</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <condition>HIV Infection</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Willing to be tested for HIV.

                  Note: Subjects known to be HIV-infected will routinely have results of plasma HIV
                  RNA obtained at or within 90 days of the enrollment visit recorded; volunteers
                  believed to be HIV uninfected will usually have HIV ELISA (Western blot if
                  needed) and/or HIV RNA within 28 days of the enrollment visit recorded. Test
                  results do not have to be available before proceeding with enrollment. Consent to
                  be tested is required, but the testing itself does not have to be completed if
                  not needed by the research lab as subjects are eligible regardless of HIV status.

               2. Age: 18 years of age or older.

               3. Ability to provide informed consent

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Refusal to consent to follow study site policy on partner notification (if newly
             diagnosed as HIV-positive while participating in this study).

          2. Refusal to permit research specimens to be stored (frozen) for potential future
             studies.

          3. Any medical condition that, in the opinion of the Principal Investigator, would make
             the subject inappropriate for protocol participation (such as coagulopathy or
             inadequate venous access).

          4. Women known to be pregnant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Betts MR, Casazza JP, Patterson BA, Waldrop S, Trigona W, Fu TM, Kern F, Picker LJ, Koup RA. Putative immunodominant human immunodeficiency virus-specific CD8(+) T-cell responses cannot be predicted by major histocompatibility complex class I haplotype. J Virol. 2000 Oct;74(19):9144-51.</citation>
    <PMID>10982361</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allen TM, O'Connor DH, Jing P, Dzuris JL, Mothé BR, Vogel TU, Dunphy E, Liebl ME, Emerson C, Wilson N, Kunstman KJ, Wang X, Allison DB, Hughes AL, Desrosiers RC, Altman JD, Wolinsky SM, Sette A, Watkins DI. Tat-specific cytotoxic T lymphocytes select for SIV escape variants during resolution of primary viraemia. Nature. 2000 Sep 21;407(6802):386-90.</citation>
    <PMID>11014195</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koup RA, Safrit JT, Cao Y, Andrews CA, McLeod G, Borkowsky W, Farthing C, Ho DD. Temporal association of cellular immune responses with the initial control of viremia in primary human immunodeficiency virus type 1 syndrome. J Virol. 1994 Jul;68(7):4650-5.</citation>
    <PMID>8207839</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 27, 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 7, 2001</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 6, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 7, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>T Cell</keyword>
  <keyword>B Cell</keyword>
  <keyword>Flow Cytometry</keyword>
  <keyword>Cell-Mediated Immunity</keyword>
  <keyword>Thymus</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunity</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphocytes</keyword>
  <keyword>Monocytes</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <keyword>Normal Control</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

