<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00021788</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DK55347 (completed)</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>DK55347</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00021788</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Islet Cell Transplantation Alone in Patients With Type I Diabetes Mellitus: Steroid-free Immunosuppression</brief_title>
  <official_title>Immunomodulation for Islet Transplantation in Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of islet cell transplantation in patients with Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus is to
      provide constant normal blood glucose levels. This may eliminate the need for insulin
      altogether or provide a significant reduction in the amount of insulin necessary to maintain
      constant normal blood glucose levels. This normalization may prevent or slow progression of
      diabetic complications. Furthermore, the participant may enjoy a healthier lifestyle and a
      better quality of life.

      If you meet the initial inclusion criteria for the trial, you must be able to give informed
      consent personally. Then you will need to participate in an extensive screening process that
      involves many standard tests and collection of laboratory samples to make sure that the
      transplant is suitable and safe for you.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The trial may/will utilize the following immunosuppressive medications: tacrolimus
      (life-long), sirolimus (life-long), daclizumab and infliximab You will be maintained on the
      lowest doses possible with all the medications.

      GROUP (1A): The first four participants will be assigned to Group A. These participants will
      receive an islet cell transplant alone from two donors. They will receive the following
      immunosuppressive medications: tacrolimus (lifelong), sirolimus (lifelong), and daclizumab.
      They will not receive the immunosuppressive medication infliximab. GROUP (1B): The second
      four participants will be assigned to group B. These participants will receive an islet cell
      transplant alone from one donor. They will receive the following immunosuppressive
      medications: tacrolimus (lifelong), sirolimus (lifelong), daclizumab and infliximab. Patients
      in this group who are not able to stop injecting insulin by three months after the transplant
      may be eligible to receive a second islet cell transplant.

      Further participants will alternate group assignments in the same above-mentioned manner. The
      participants in both groups will receive the following immunosuppressive medications for
      life, tacrolimus and sirolimus. All participants will be required to live no more than two
      hours from the transplantation center.

      When the islets become available, you will be notified to come immediately to the hospital
      for your transplant. At that time numerous tests and laboratory samples will be performed to
      make sure you are ready and healthy for your transplant.

      You will have your islet cell transplant done in a special radiology procedure room in a
      hospital. You will have local anesthetic in the area of your liver on your right side along
      with sedatives that will minimize any discomfort the procedure might cause. A very small
      (thin) needle will be inserted through your liver into your portal vein where the islet cells
      are then injected.

      All participants will need to be followed at the Diabetes Research Institute after transplant
      for laboratory sampling, testing and for general islet cell transplant care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date>December 2001</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>islet cell transplantation</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Candidates must be between the ages of 18 and 65

          -  Candidates must have had IDDM for at least 5 years and been under physician care for
             at least 6 months prior to enrollment in trial.

          -  Eligible candidates will have poorly controlled insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus
             (IDDM) and manifest signs and symptoms severe enough to be incapacitating. These
             symptoms can include episodes of hypoglycemic unawareness (failure to recognize blood
             glucose levels &lt; 54 mg/dl) or episodes requiring the assistance of others.

          -  Candidates may have poor diabetes control despite intensive insulin therapy (HbA1c &gt;
             8.0%).

          -  Creatinine clearance should be &gt; 60 ml/min)

          -  Body Mass Index should be less than 26

          -  Women of child-bearing age must have a negative pregnancy test and agree to follow
             effective contraceptive measures for the duration of the trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous or concurrent organ transplant

          -  Previous or concurrent malignancy

          -  Untreated proliferative diabetic retinopathy

          -  Unstable cardiovascular status, including positive stress echocardiography (if &gt; age
             35)

          -  Active infections, including x-ray evidence of pulmonary infection

          -  Peptic ulcer disease, gall stones, or portal hypertension

          -  Abnormal liver function tests

          -  Presence of panel reactive antibodies &gt; 20%

          -  Creatinine clearance &lt; 60 ml/min

          -  HbA1c 12%

          -  Serological evidence of HIV, HbsAg, or HCV

          -  Anemia (hemoglobin &lt; 12.0)

          -  Any condition or circumstance, including psychogenic factors, that preclude
             therapeutic compliance or otherwise make it unsafe to undergo an islet cell
             transplant.

          -  PSA &gt; 4 in males
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rodolfo Alejandro, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Miami Diabetes Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami Diabetes Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alejandro R, Lehmann R, Ricordi C, Kenyon NS, Angelico MC, Burke G, Esquenazi V, Nery J, Betancourt AE, Kong SS, Miller J, Mintz DH. Long-term function (6 years) of islet allografts in type 1 diabetes. Diabetes. 1997 Dec;46(12):1983-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9392484</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McAlister VC, Gao Z, Peltekian K, Domingues J, Mahalati K, MacDonald AS. Sirolimus-tacrolimus combination immunosuppression. Lancet. 2000 Jan 29;355(9201):376-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10665560</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 4, 2001</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 3, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 6, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 9, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Type I Diabetes Mellitus</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunosuppression</keyword>
  <keyword>Islet Cell Transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>PercutaneousTranshepaticPortalVein Catheterization</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

