<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00024843</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>988</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL065133</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00024843</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Family Based Interventions: Preschool Children and Parent</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess the efficacy of a 2-year family-based weight prevention program in a cohort of
      overweight preschool children and overweight parent pairs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      The proposal targets a population of individuals of great public health importance who are of
      high risk for weight gain: pre-school children of overweight parents. Family-based
      interventions are both theoretically and functionally reasonable approaches for use with
      these subjects, and the choice to focus on both increased physical activity and healthier
      food choices in the context of the family's environment is appropriate. The decision to
      include weight management outcomes on the parent as secondary endpoint is strategically wise
      and may provide important insights into the process of weight management. A broad array of
      data is to be collected and strong justification is provided for the inclusion of each.

      The study is in response to an initiative issued by the National Institute of Diabetes and
      Digestive and Kidney Diseases and entitled &quot;Innovative Approaches to the Prevention of
      Obesity&quot;. The resulting grant was later reassigned to the National Heart, Lung, and Blood
      Institute.

      DESIGN NARRATIVE:

      Approximately fifty child/parent pairs were recruited and randomized evenly to one of two
      groups: usual care versus an intervention focused on diet and activity strategies that
      included weekly group visits (24 weeks), biweekly group visits for parents (12 weeks),
      monthly group visits for parents (6 months) and quarterly group visits (12 months).
      Cognitive-behavioral therapy was used to guide interventions, which focussed on empowering a
      parent as the primary medium by which lifestyle changes were made. Major data collection at
      baseline, twelve, and 24 months included measures of weight; food and activity records;
      activity monitor recordings; biopsychosocial profiles; blood lipids, glucose, and insulin;
      process measures; parenting behavior; and child behavior. The primary study outcome measure
      was age- and gender-appropriate changes in BMI (expressed as a binomial response). Additional
      outcomes of particular interest were weight changes in the parent, diet and physical activity
      levels, parenting skills, and biopsychosocial measures.

      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;End Date&quot; entered in
      the Protocol Registration and Results System (PRS) record.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2003</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        No eligibility criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sachiko St. Jeor</last_name>
    <affiliation>University of Nevada, Las Vegas</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>St Jeor ST, Perumean-Chaney S, Sigman-Grant M, Williams C, Foreyt J. Family-based interventions for the treatment of childhood obesity. J Am Diet Assoc. 2002 May;102(5):640-4.</citation>
    <PMID>12008987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2004</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 28, 2001</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 27, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 28, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 13, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

