<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00023296</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>010223</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>01-H-0223</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00023296</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00021684</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nitric Oxide and Transfusion Therapy for Sickle Cell Patients With Pulmonary Hypertension</brief_title>
  <official_title>Inhaled Nitric Oxide and Transfusion Therapy for Patients With Sickle Cell Anemia and Secondary Pulmonary Hypertension</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mallinckrodt</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will test whether inhaling nitric oxide (NO) gas mixed with room air can improve
      pulmonary hypertension (high blood pressure in the lungs) in patients with sickle cell
      anemia.

      Patients with sickle cell disease 18 years of age or older may be eligible to participate in
      one or more parts of this three-stage study, as follows:

      Stage 1

      Patients undergo the following tests to determine the cause of their pulmonary hypertension:
      blood tests; echocardiogram (heart ultrasound); asthma test; oxygen breathing study with
      measurement of arterial blood oxygen levels; chest X-ray; lung scans; MRI of the heart;
      6-minute walk test; night-time oxygen measurement while sleeping; and exercise studies.

      Stage 2

      Patients have a detailed MRI evaluation of the heart and are admitted to the NIH Clinical
      Center intensive care unit (ICU) for the following test: A plastic tube is placed in a vein
      in the patient's arm and another tube is placed in a deeper neck or leg vein. A third tube is
      inserted through the vein into the heart and the lung artery to measure blood pressures in
      the heart and lungs directly. Following baseline measurements, three medications (inhaled
      oxygen, infused prostaglandin, and inhaled NO) are delivered for 2 hours each, separated by a
      30-minute washout period. A small blood sample is drawn during the NO administration.

      Patients who cannot be treated with nitric oxide or for whom the treatment does not work may
      receive monthly exchange transfusions for 3 months. For this procedure, 3 to 5 five units of
      the patient's blood is removed and replaced with 3 to 5 units that do not have sickle
      hemoglobin. Some patients who do not respond to NO or exchange transfusions may receive an
      alternative therapy, such as oxygen, prostacyclin, L-arginine, bosentan or sidenafil.

      Stage 3

      Patients remain in the ICU with catheters in place for another 24 hours. During this time
      they breathe NO. Lung pressures are measured every 4 hours and blood is drawn every 8 hours.
      They then stay in the hospital 1 more day for observation. Patients then breathe nitric oxide
      continuously for 2 months using a tank of gas that delivers the NO through tubes placed in
      the nose. They may do this at home on an outpatient basis or may remain in the hospital for
      the 2 months.

      Patients have an echocardiogram and blood tests every week and do a 6-minute walk test every
      2 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sickle cell anemia is an autosomal recessive disorder and the most common genetic disease
      affecting African-Americans. Approximately 0.15% of African-Americans are homozygous for
      sickle cell disease, and 8% have sickle cell trait. Acute pain crisis, acute chest syndrome
      (ACS), and secondary pulmonary hypertension are common complications of sickle cell anemia.
      Pulmonary hypertension has now been identified as a major cause of death in adults with
      sickle cell disease. Inhaled nitric oxide (NO) has been proposed as a possible therapy for
      both primary and secondary pulmonary hypertension. Furthermore, a number of recent studies
      have suggested that NO may have a favorable impact on sickle red cells at the molecular level
      and could improve the abnormal microvascular perfusion that is characteristic of sickle cell
      anemia. In addition, chronic exchange transfusion therapy may reduce the progression and/or
      severity of pulmonary hypertension in these patients.

      This clinical trial is designed (1) to determine the pathophysiologic processes that are
      associated with and potentially contribute to secondary pulmonary hypertension in adult
      patients with sickle cell anemia, by comparing the cardio-pulmonary status of patients with
      sickle cell disease with and without pulmonary hypertension (2) to determine the relative
      acute vasodilatory effects of oxygen, intravenous prostacyclin, and inhaled nitric oxide on
      pulmonary artery pressures and other hemodynamic parameters in patients with secondary
      pulmonary hypertension and sickle cell anemia, (3) to determine the effects of two months of
      inhaled nitric oxide on pulmonary artery pressures, other hemodynamic parameters, exercise
      tolerance, and symptoms in this patient population, and (4) to determine the effects of three
      months of exchange transfusion on pulmonary artery pressures, other hemodynamic parameters,
      exercise tolerance, and symptoms in patients who do not receive or fail to respond to NO
      therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 27, 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 9, 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2, 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the pathophysiologic processes that are associated with and potentially contribute to secondary pulmonary hypertension in adult patients with sickle cell anemia.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the relative acute vasodilatory of oxygen, intravenous prostacyclin, and inhaled nitric oxide on pulmonary artery pressures and other hemodynamic parameters in patients with secondary pulmonary hypertension and sickle cell anemia.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">59</enrollment>
  <condition>Sickle Cell Anemia</condition>
  <condition>Pulmonary Hypertension</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nitric Oxide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>INO Pulse - NO Delivery System</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA

        For Stage I for Pulmonary Hypertension Subjects:

        Male or female, 18 years of age or older.

        Diagnosis of sickle cell disease (electrophoretic documentation of SS, SC, or S
        beta-halassemia genotype is required).

        Hematocrit greater than 18% (with an absolute reticulocyte count greater than 100,000/ml if
        hematocrit is 18-24%).

        Mild to severe pulmonary hypertension with systolic pulmonary artery pressures greater than
        or equal to 30 mm Hg (tricuspid regurgitant velocity greater than 2.5 m/sec, assuming right
        atrial pressure greater than 5 cm H20) or right ventricular enlargement. We will compare
        these studies to a control group of sickle cell patients that do not have pulmonary
        hypertension.

        For Stage I Controls:

        Males or females, 18 years of age or older.

        Diagnosis of sickle cell disease (electrophoretic documentation of SS, SC, or S
        beta-halassemia genotype is required).

        Hematocrit greater than 18% (with an absolute reticulocyte count greater than 100,000/ml if
        hematocrit is 18-24%).

        Tricuspid regurgitant velocity less than or equal to 2.4 m/sec, matched for age, gender,
        hydroxyurea therapy status and fetal hemoglobin levels with the pulmonary hypertension
        subjects.

        For Stage II:

        Male or female, 18 years of age or older.

        Diagnosis of sickle cell disease (electrophoretic documentation of SS, SC, or S
        beta-thalassemia genotype is required).

        Hematocrit greater than 18% (with an absolute reticulocyte count greater than 100,000/ml if
        hematocrit is 18-24%).

        Mild to severe pulmonary hypertension with systolic pulmonary artery pressures greater than
        or equal to 30 mm Hg (tricuspid regurgitant velocity greater than 2.5 m/sec, assuming right
        atrial pressure greater than 5 cm H20) or right ventricular enlargement.

        For Stage III:

        Male or female, 18 years of age or older.

        Diagnosis of sickle cell disease (electrophoretic documentation of SS, SC, or S
        beta-thalassemia genotype is required).

        Hematocrit greater than 18 % (with an absolute reticulocyte count greater than 100,000/ml
        if hematocrit is 18-24%).

        Able to walk at least 100 m in six minutes at baseline.

        Mild to severe pulmonary hypertension with mean pulmonary artery pressures greater than or
        equal to 25 mm Hg, measured by pulmonary artery catheterization.

        Pulmonary artery wedge pressure or left ventricular end-diastolic pressure less than or
        equal to 18 mm Hg or echocardiographic criteria to exclude left ventricular dysfunction.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

        For Stage I

        Current pregnancy or lactation

        For Stage II

        Current pregnancy or lactation

        Any of the following medical conditions:

        Significant renal insufficiency (patient on hemodialysis or estimated creatinine clearance
        less than 30% of normal; Stroke within the last six weeks; New diagnosis of pulmonary
        embolism within the last three months; History of retinal detachment.

        Hematocrit less than 18 % will not be eligible for the study; may return for evaluation at
        a later date.

        Patients taking prostacyclin (inhaled or intravenous) will be excluded from the study.
        Patients taking calcium channel blockers will be allowed to participate provided they are
        on a stable dose for greater than one month.

        For Stage III

        Current pregnancy or lactation

        Any of the following medical conditions:

        Significant renal insufficiency (patient on hemodialysis or estimated creatinine clearance
        less than 30%of normal; Stroke within the last six weeks; Left ventricular end-diastolic
        pressure greater than or equal to 18 mm Hg (determined by the pulmonary artery occlusion
        pressure) or echocardiographic criteria for left ventricular dysfunction; New diagnosis of
        pulmonary embolism within the last three months; History of retinal detachment;

        Hematocrit less than 18 % will not be eligible for the study; may return for evaluation at
        a later date.

        Patients taking prostacyclin (inhaled or intravenous) will be excluded from the study.
        Patients taking calcium channel blockers will be allowed to participate provided they are
        on a stable dose for greater than one month.

        Patients who are in other research studies for the treatment of pulmonary hypertension or
        who are on treatment specific for pulmonary hypertension will be excluded from stage III of
        this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John F Tisdale, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Suburban Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20814</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Platt OS, Brambilla DJ, Rosse WF, Milner PF, Castro O, Steinberg MH, Klug PP. Mortality in sickle cell disease. Life expectancy and risk factors for early death. N Engl J Med. 1994 Jun 9;330(23):1639-44.</citation>
    <PMID>7993409</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vichinsky EP, Styles LA, Colangelo LH, Wright EC, Castro O, Nickerson B. Acute chest syndrome in sickle cell disease: clinical presentation and course. Cooperative Study of Sickle Cell Disease. Blood. 1997 Mar 1;89(5):1787-92.</citation>
    <PMID>9057664</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Castro O, Brambilla DJ, Thorington B, Reindorf CA, Scott RB, Gillette P, Vera JC, Levy PS. The acute chest syndrome in sickle cell disease: incidence and risk factors. The Cooperative Study of Sickle Cell Disease. Blood. 1994 Jul 15;84(2):643-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7517723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 9, 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 3, 2001</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 1, 2001</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 3, 2001</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acute Chest Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood Flow</keyword>
  <keyword>Nitric Oxide</keyword>
  <keyword>NO Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaso-Occlusive Crisis</keyword>
  <keyword>Sickle Cell Anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Sickle Cell</keyword>
  <keyword>ACS</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Hypertension</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension, Pulmonary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Sickle Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nitric Oxide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

