<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00021385</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000068774</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UCLA-0001004</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>MAGA-MSI-1256F-203</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-G01-1987</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00021385</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Squalamine Lactate Plus Carboplatin in Treating Patients With Recurrent or Refractory Stage III or Stage IV Ovarian Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase IIA Trial of Continuous Five Day Infusions of MSI-1256F (Squalamine Lactate) Plus Carboplatin for Therapy of Refractory and Resistant Stage III and IV Ovarian Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Squalamine lactate may stop or slow the growth of ovarian cancer by stopping blood
      flow to the tumor. Drugs used in chemotherapy use different ways to stop tumor cells from
      dividing so they stop growing or die. Combining squalamine lactate with carboplatin may kill
      more tumor cells.

      PURPOSE: Phase II trial to study the effectiveness of combining squalamine lactate and
      carboplatin in treating patients who have recurrent or refractory stage III or stage IV
      ovarian cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Determine the response rate and time to progression in patients with recurrent
      or refractory stage III or IV ovarian cancer treated with squalamine lactate and carboplatin.
      II. Determine the safety profile of this regimen in these patients.

      OUTLINE: Patients receive carboplatin IV over 15-30 minutes on day 1 and squalamine lactate
      IV continuously on days 1-5. Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for 6 courses in the absence of
      disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients are followed at approximately 1 month.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: Approximately 45 patients will be accrued for this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>May 2001</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>carboplatin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>squalamine lactate</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: Histologically confirmed stage III or IV ovarian cancer Refractory
        disease Progression on prior primary paclitaxel and carboplatin OR Resistant disease
        Recurrence within 12 months of initial response after completion of prior paclitaxel and
        carboplatin Recurrence within 12 months of initial response to a prior secondary or
        tertiary regimen allowed Bidimensionally measurable or evaluable disease OR Elevated CA125
        level CA125 at least 100 U/mL (risen from prior lower levels) OR CA125 greater than 50 U/mL
        but less than 100 U/mL (at least doubled from prior lower levels) No known brain metastases
        unless clinically stable after treatment with prior surgery and/or radiotherapy

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: Age: 18 and over Performance status: ECOG 0-1 OR SWOG 0-1 Life
        expectancy: Not specified Hematopoietic: WBC at least 4,000/mm3 OR Absolute neutrophil
        count at least 1,500/mm3 Platelet count at least 100,000/mm3 Hepatic: Bilirubin no greater
        than 2 times upper limit of normal (ULN) AST less than 5 times ULN Renal: Creatinine no
        greater than 1.5 mg/dL OR Creatinine clearance at least 60 mL/min Cardiovascular: No
        significant cardiac disease No uncontrolled high blood pressure No unstable angina No
        congestive heart failure No myocardial infarction within the past year No serious cardiac
        arrhythmia requiring medication Other: No clinically significant neuropathy No other active
        malignancy No uncontrolled serious active infection No uncontrolled diabetes mellitus No
        other condition that would preclude study Not pregnant or nursing Negative pregnancy test
        Fertile patients must use effective contraception during and for at least 30 days after
        study

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY: Biologic therapy: No prior biological response modifiers No prior
        anti-angiogenesis agents No prior squalamine lactate No concurrent growth factors, except
        for epoetin alfa Chemotherapy: See Disease Characteristics Received 1-3 prior chemotherapy
        regimens for ovarian cancer At least 5 years since prior chemotherapy for other malignancy
        Endocrine therapy: Concurrent hormonal therapy allowed if therapy initiated at least 6
        months prior to study Radiotherapy: See Disease Characteristics Recovered from prior
        radiotherapy At least 5 years since prior radiotherapy for other malignancy No prior
        radiotherapy to only area of measurable or evaluable disease unless that site had
        subsequent disease progression Concurrent localized radiotherapy for pain or symptom relief
        allowed if other methods are ineffective and measurable and/or evaluable disease remains
        outside the radiotherapy portals Surgery: See Disease Characteristics Other: At least 30
        days since prior investigational therapy No prior enrollment in this study No other
        concurrent antitumor treatment No other concurrent investigational therapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Linnea Chap, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center, UCLA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095-1781</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2002</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 11, 2001</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 3, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 4, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 17, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 17, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 18, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>stage III ovarian epithelial cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV ovarian epithelial cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent ovarian epithelial cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>ovarian stromal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III ovarian germ cell tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IV ovarian germ cell tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrent ovarian germ cell tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>borderline ovarian surface epithelial-stromal tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>ovarian sarcoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Squalamine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

