<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02448615</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1000047574</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02448615</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Birth Cohort in Coast Province, Kenya</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Longitudinal Birth Cohort Study in Coast Province, Kenya</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Hospital for Sick Children</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>March of Dimes</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Grand Challenges Canada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aga Khan University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Hospital for Sick Children</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In 2010, 7.6 million children under the age of five died worldwide and yet the causes of only
      2.7% (0.205 million) of these deaths were medically certified. A thorough understanding of
      the causes of child mortality is necessary to guide research efforts aimed at tackling this
      important global health problem. Prospective birth cohort studies present an opportunity to
      examine the relationships between early-life exposures and multiple health and non-health
      related outcomes including death, illness, and socioeconomic factors. In this study, the
      investigators will provide insight into the underlying causes of child mortality by
      collecting data on early-life exposures and health and non-health related outcomes in the
      first year of life.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In 2010, 7.6 million children under the age of five died worldwide, mainly from preventable
      and treatable conditions (Liu et al., 2012). Notably, the burden of under-five mortality
      varies dramatically by country. The majority of child deaths are seen in Africa (3.6 million)
      and southeast Asia (2.1 million deaths), compared to 0.16 million and 0.28 million under-five
      deaths in Europe and the Americas, respectively (Liu et al., 2012). In Kenya, over 120,000
      under-5 deaths were estimated in 2010 and approximately 35% of these deaths occurred in the
      neonatal period.

      A thorough understanding of the etiology of child mortality is necessary to guide research
      efforts aimed at tackling this important global health problem. Importantly, in 2010, the
      causes of only 2.7% (0.205 million) of all deaths in children under the age of five were
      medically certified (Liu et al., 2012), highlighting the need to gather data on the causes of
      mortality.

      Prospective longitudinal birth cohort studies present an opportunity to examine temporal
      relationships between early-life exposures (i.e. prenatal, pregnancy, and early postnatal
      exposures) and multiple health and non-health related outcomes including mortality,
      morbidity, and socioeconomic circumstances. It is well documented that exposures that occur
      early in life, including genetic, environmental, socioeconomic, and lifestyle factors, may
      have long-lasting effects on growth, development, and health outcomes throughout an
      individual's entire life course (Lynch &amp; Smith, 2005). Thus, data on exposures during
      pregnancy and early childhood are valuable and may provide clues to the etiology of long-term
      outcomes.

      Additional value can be gained through cross-cohort collaborations and comparisons (Larsen et
      al., 2013)(Paternoster et al., 2012)(Brion et al., 2011). Notably, by pooling data from
      multiple cohort studies, causal inferences can be made with greater confidence. For example,
      if a similar relationship is observed across multiple populations, each with their own
      distinct set of confounding variables, it is less likely that the observed association is
      being driven by confounders. Similarly, cross-cohort comparisons enable researchers to
      investigate patterns associated with health, social, and economic outcomes in distinct
      regions of the world. These types of analyses may provide valuable insight into the
      underlying causes of global health inequalities.

      The objective of this study is to implement a longitudinal prospective birth cohort study in
      Kenya to obtain extensive information on early-life exposures and health and non-health
      related outcomes in the first year of life.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child mortality within the first year of life</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months (Day 3 of life, Month 6 of life, Month 12 of life)</time_frame>
    <description>Death from any cause within the first year of life will be assessed by questionnaire.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Morbidity within the first year of a child's life</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months (Day 3 of life, Month 6 of life, Month 12 of life)</time_frame>
    <description>The most common types of illness within the first year of a child's life will be assessed by questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Development/behaviour of children aged 6 and 12 months in the Coast Province, Kenya</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 6 of life, Month 12 of life</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by questionnaire (month 6) and questionnaire and Kilifi Developmental Inventory at month 12. Linear growth and weight are collected at day 3, month 6 and month 12.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">283</enrollment>
  <condition>Mortality</condition>
  <condition>Morbidity</condition>
  <condition>Child Development</condition>
  <condition>Child Behaviour</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Birth Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>The cohort will comprise approximately 1500 pregnant women and their unborn babies, enrolled to participate in the control arm of a cluster-randomized controlled intervention trial (NCT02208960).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All pregnant women (and their unborn newborns) who consent to participate in the control
        arm of the previously approved trial &quot;An integrated toolkit to save newborn lives and
        brains in Kenya&quot; (NCT02208960) will be eligible for enrollment in this study. At the time
        of consent, participants will be informed that they are free to consent to the neonatal kit
        trial without consenting to the birth cohort study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        i. All pregnant women and their home- or facility-born live newborns that consent to
        participate in the control arm of the study &quot;An integrated toolkit to save newborn lives
        and brains in Kenya&quot; (NCT02208960) will be eligible for this study. The maternal inclusion
        criteria will be:

          1. All pregnant women in parts of study clusters covered by CHW program and their home-
             or facility-born live newborns.

          2. Mothers intending to maintain residence in study area for first 12 months of newborn's
             life.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        i. Did not consent to participate in the control arm of &quot;An integrated toolkit to save
        newborn lives and brains in Kenya&quot; (NCT02208960).

        ii. Failure to provide consent to enroll in this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>1 Year</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shaun K Morris, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Hospital for Sick Children</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Armstrong, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Aga Khan University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Community</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kwale</city>
        <state>Coast Province</state>
        <country>Kenya</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aga Khan University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nairobi</city>
        <country>Kenya</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Kenya</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu L, Johnson HL, Cousens S, Perin J, Scott S, Lawn JE, Rudan I, Campbell H, Cibulskis R, Li M, Mathers C, Black RE; Child Health Epidemiology Reference Group of WHO and UNICEF. Global, regional, and national causes of child mortality: an updated systematic analysis for 2010 with time trends since 2000. Lancet. 2012 Jun 9;379(9832):2151-61. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60560-1. Epub 2012 May 11. Erratum in: Lancet. 2012 Oct 13;380(9850):1308.</citation>
    <PMID>22579125</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lynch J, Smith GD. A life course approach to chronic disease epidemiology. Annu Rev Public Health. 2005;26:1-35. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15760279</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larsen PS, Kamper-Jørgensen M, Adamson A, Barros H, Bonde JP, Brescianini S, Brophy S, Casas M, Charles MA, Devereux G, Eggesbø M, Fantini MP, Frey U, Gehring U, Grazuleviciene R, Henriksen TB, Hertz-Picciotto I, Heude B, Hryhorczuk DO, Inskip H, Jaddoe VW, Lawlor DA, Ludvigsson J, Kelleher C, Kiess W, Koletzko B, Kuehni CE, Kull I, Kyhl HB, Magnus P, Momas I, Murray D, Pekkanen J, Polanska K, Porta D, Poulsen G, Richiardi L, Roeleveld N, Skovgaard AM, Sram RJ, Strandberg-Larsen K, Thijs C, Van Eijsden M, Wright J, Vrijheid M, Andersen AM. Pregnancy and birth cohort resources in europe: a large opportunity for aetiological child health research. Paediatr Perinat Epidemiol. 2013 Jul;27(4):393-414. doi: 10.1111/ppe.12060. Erratum in: Paediatr Perinat Epidemiol. 2013 Sep;27(5):505. Charles, Marie-Aline[added].</citation>
    <PMID>23772942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brion MJ, Zeegers M, Jaddoe V, Verhulst F, Tiemeier H, Lawlor DA, Smith GD. Intrauterine effects of maternal prepregnancy overweight on child cognition and behavior in 2 cohorts. Pediatrics. 2011 Jan;127(1):e202-11. doi: 10.1542/peds.2010-0651. Epub 2010 Dec 27.</citation>
    <PMID>21187310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paternoster L, Standl M, Chen CM, Ramasamy A, Bønnelykke K, Duijts L, Ferreira MA, Alves AC, Thyssen JP, Albrecht E, Baurecht H, Feenstra B, Sleiman PM, Hysi P, Warrington NM, Curjuric I, Myhre R, Curtin JA, Groen-Blokhuis MM, Kerkhof M, Sääf A, Franke A, Ellinghaus D, Fölster-Holst R, Dermitzakis E, Montgomery SB, Prokisch H, Heim K, Hartikainen AL, Pouta A, Pekkanen J, Blakemore AI, Buxton JL, Kaakinen M, Duffy DL, Madden PA, Heath AC, Montgomery GW, Thompson PJ, Matheson MC, Le Souëf P; Australian Asthma Genetics Consortium (AAGC), St Pourcain B, Smith GD, Henderson J, Kemp JP, Timpson NJ, Deloukas P, Ring SM, Wichmann HE, Müller-Nurasyid M, Novak N, Klopp N, Rodríguez E, McArdle W, Linneberg A, Menné T, Nohr EA, Hofman A, Uitterlinden AG, van Duijn CM, Rivadeneira F, de Jongste JC, van der Valk RJ, Wjst M, Jogi R, Geller F, Boyd HA, Murray JC, Kim C, Mentch F, March M, Mangino M, Spector TD, Bataille V, Pennell CE, Holt PG, Sly P, Tiesler CM, Thiering E, Illig T, Imboden M, Nystad W, Simpson A, Hottenga JJ, Postma D, Koppelman GH, Smit HA, Söderhäll C, Chawes B, Kreiner-Møller E, Bisgaard H, Melén E, Boomsma DI, Custovic A, Jacobsson B, Probst-Hensch NM, Palmer LJ, Glass D, Hakonarson H, Melbye M, Jarvis DL, Jaddoe VW, Gieger C; Genetics of Overweight Young Adults (GOYA) Consortium, Strachan DP, Martin NG, Jarvelin MR, Heinrich J, Evans DM, Weidinger S; EArly Genetics &amp; Lifecourse Epidemiology (EAGLE) Consortium. Meta-analysis of genome-wide association studies identifies three new risk loci for atopic dermatitis. Nat Genet. 2011 Dec 25;44(2):187-92. doi: 10.1038/ng.1017.</citation>
    <PMID>22197932</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 15, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 19, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 14, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Hospital for Sick Children</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Shaun Morris</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinician-Scientist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Kenya</keyword>
  <keyword>Cohort</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

