<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02449993</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MammaTyper_1.neo-adjuvant st.</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02449993</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Re-Examination of Tumor Material and Re-Evaluation of Patient Data From Patients Treated With Neo-adjuvant Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the MammaTyper Kit, Ref 90020/90021 Performed on Clinical Material Obtained From Patients With Early Breast Cancer: Re-Examination of Tumor Material and Re-Evaluation of Patient Data From Patients Treated With Neo-adjuvant Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Biontech Diagnostics GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Biontech Diagnostics GmbH</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective examination of ribonucleic acid (RNA) extracted from tumor material of
      breast cancer patients treated with a neo-adjuvant therapy. The RNA will be analysed for
      expression of estrogen receptor (ER 1), progesterone receptor (PgR), HER2 and Ki-67 with
      MammaTyper™.

      According to the determined values for the individual parameters at least 4 subtypes can be
      distinguished to date

        -  Luminal A-type

        -  Luminal B-type

        -  HER2-type

        -  Triple-negative-type As non-clinical endpoint, the agreement of new subtyping with
           Immunohistochemical methods will be evaluated.

      As clinical objective, the 5 year Distant metastasis free survival (DMFS) and Overall
      survival (OS) will be reevaluated according to the new subtyping.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Tumor material collected from patients who received neoadjuvant therapy either with four
      cycles of doxorubicin 60 mg/m² plus pemetrexed 500 mg/m² on day 1 every 21 days followed by
      four cycles of docetaxel 100 mg/m² on day 1 every 21 days or four cycles of doxorubicin 60
      mg/m² plus cyclophosphamide 600 mg/m² on day 1 every 21 days followed by four cycles of
      docetaxel 100 mg/m² on day 1 every 21 days will be re-analyzed with the MammaTyper Kit. The
      Kit is an in-vitro molecular diagnostic test for molecular subtyping of breast cancers into
      Luminal A &amp; B, HER2 and Triple negative. It allows quantitative detection of the RNA
      expression status of the genes for estrogen receptor (ESR1), PgR, HER2 and Ki-67 on the basis
      of their mRNA present in the samples. This prospective diagnostic study will investigate the
      subtyping-results of the MammaTyper™ analysis and will compare them to the subtyping of the
      former immunohistochemical analysis performed. Based on the MammaTyper™-subtypes the
      efficiency of the therapy regimen and the outcome will be re-evaluated from the patient data.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Agreement of new subtyping assessed as rate of patients in MammaTyper-subtype groups compared to rate of patients in subtype groups according to immunohistochemical analysis according to St. Gallen Guideline 2013</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>For each MammaTyper and immunohistochemical based subtype categorization, percent agreement, positive and negative percent agreement as well as kappa-statistics are calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess difference of 5 year OS of breast cancer subgroup Luminal A vs. combined subgroup (Luminal B (HER2 positive / HER2 negative), HER2 positive, triple negative), based on subtyping with MammaTyper™</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years from the date of patient registration</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed as rate of patients in subgroup Luminal A with 5 year OS vs. rate of patients in combined subgroups with 5 year OS based on MammaTyper subtyping</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimation of difference in prediction of pathologic complete remission for MammaTyperTM Ki-67 vs. local Ki-67 visual scoring assessment for Luminal tumors, whereby a positive difference is expected</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed as rate of patients with complete response and Ki-67 determination according to MammaTyper and visual scoring assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ESR1 mRNA is predictive for 5 year OS with low expression of ESR1 mRNA being associated with adverse outcome (rate of patients with 5 year OS and high or low expression of ESR1 mRNA)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years from the date of patient registration</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed as rate of patients with 5 year OS and high or low expression of ESR1 mRNA</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">101</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MammaTyper™</arm_group_label>
    <description>MammaTyper™ will be used to assess tumor material of patients treated with neo-adjuvant therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MammaTyper™</intervention_name>
    <description>MammaTyper™ is an in vitro molecular diagnostic test for the quantitative detection of the biomarkers estrogen receptor (ESR1), progesterone receptor ( PgR), Human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2) and proliferation antigen Ki-67 on the basis of the values of the messenger ribonucleic acid (mRNA).</description>
    <arm_group_label>MammaTyper™</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        See Eligibility Criteria
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women aged 18-70 years with histologically confirmed primary invasive breast cancer
             stages T2-T4/N0-N2/M0 with a tumor size of ≥ 2 cm as measured by ultrasound

          -  The patient provides a written informed consent for analysis of tumor material

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior anticancer therapy with an anthracycline or other prior antitumor therapy for
             breast cancer

          -  Inflammatory or exulcerating breast cancer

          -  A second primary malignancy [except carcinoma in situ (CIS) of the cervix or
             adequately treated nonmelanoma skin cancer] unless diagnosed and treated ≥ 5 years ago
             with no evidence of recurrence

          -  Any serious concomitant systemic disorder
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 6, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 20, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 21, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 17, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 17, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>diagnostic study</keyword>
  <keyword>analysis of estrogen receptor</keyword>
  <keyword>progesterone receptor</keyword>
  <keyword>Human epidermal growth factor receptor 2</keyword>
  <keyword>Ki-67</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Progesterone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

