<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02444247</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GFHNRC400</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02444247</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Motivation to Exercise</brief_title>
  <acronym>Motiv2Ex</acronym>
  <official_title>Motivation to Exercise</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>USDA Grand Forks Human Nutrition Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>USDA Grand Forks Human Nutrition Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to understand how to make exercise more attractive to people.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This investigation will address increased physical activity and will yield empirical evidence
      to inform developing tools to help individuals make healthy choices regarding physical
      activity (PA) and maintenance of healthy body weight. Behavioral Choice Theory provides a
      framework for understanding choices people make and how to shift an individual's choice
      toward healthier alternatives. The theory holds that choice is based on the relative
      motivating values of alternatives. One way to shift choice toward a healthier alternative is
      to increase the relative reinforcing value (RRV), or motivating value, of that alternative.
      Thus, increasing the RRV of PA behaviors could shift choice towards PA and away from less
      healthy, sedentary alternatives.

      Increasing the RRV of PA may allow PA to compete with more reinforcing, sedentary behaviors,
      resulting in a shift in behavioral choice. This process is termed &quot;incentive sensitization&quot;,
      which was originally proposed to explain drug addiction. Incentive Sensitization theory
      posits that the RRV of a behavior is increased through repeated exposures, which produce
      neuroadaptations that increase craving of the behavior - after repeated exposures to a
      stimulus, a 'sensitization' or hypersensitivity to the incentive motivational effects of the
      stimulus follows. Another factor that influences motivation for a behavior is the development
      of tolerance to unpleasant aspects of that behavior. Opponent-Process Theory would account
      for the acquisition of motives where the initial reinforcer may be negative - the affect
      experienced after repeated exposures is opposite to that experienced during the first few
      presentations. For exercise, this would include tolerance to any discomfort, pain, fatigue
      and displeasure and a greater positive post-exercise affective response: the affect
      experienced during and after exercise has a greater motivational significance in PA
      participation than knowledge and beliefs regarding health benefits. Therefore, the
      investigators propose that repeated exposures to PA will produce tolerance to unpleasant
      aspects while increasing the post-exercise affect. Sensitizing PA reinforcement and
      increasing discomfort tolerance may be associated with increasing the duration and intensity
      of daily activity. There are likely to be individual differences in sensitization of PA
      reinforcement and development of discomfort tolerance. Single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs)
      that alter dopamine tone in the central dopaminergic reward system and SNPs associated with
      altered pain perception may contribute to such individual differences. The investigators
      anticipate that a moderate PA dose (300 kilocalorie [kcal] expenditure) will produce greater
      incentive sensitization and tolerance than a low dose (150 kcal) and that SNPs related to
      central dopamine tone and pain perception may contribute to individual differences in
      incentive sensitization and changes in physical activity after repeated exposures to physical
      activity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relative Reinforcing Value (RRV) of Exercise as assessed by indicator</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>RRV of Exercise will be assessed by evaluating the number of responses (mouse button presses) a participant is willing to complete to gain access to a physical activity or alternative sedentary reinforcer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relative Reinforcing Value (RRV) of Exercise as assessed by indicator</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>RRV of Exercise will be assessed by evaluating the number of responses (mouse button presses) a participant is willing to complete to gain access to a physical activity or alternative sedentary reinforcer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Relative Reinforcing Value (RRV) of Exercise as assessed by indicator</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>RRV of Exercise will be assessed by evaluating the number of responses (mouse button presses) a participant is willing to complete to gain access to a physical activity or alternative sedentary reinforcer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">93</enrollment>
  <condition>Overweight</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High Dose Exercise vs Sedentary Option</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Relative Reinforcing Value of high dose exercise (300 kcal expenditure per session) versus sedentary activity will be determined.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low Dose Exercise vs Sedentary Option</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Relative Reinforcing Value of low dose exercise (150 kcal expenditure per session) versus sedentary activity will be determined.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Exercise vs Sedentary Option</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Relative Reinforcing Value of no exercise (0 kcal expenditure per session) versus sedentary activity will be determined.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High Dose Exercise (300 kcal)</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will participate in 3 physical activity sessions per week expending 300 kcal per session and rate their liking of exercise.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High Dose Exercise vs Sedentary Option</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Low Dose Exercise (150 kcal)</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will participate in 3 physical activity sessions per week expending 150 kcal per session and rate their liking of exercise.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low Dose Exercise vs Sedentary Option</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No Exercise (0 kcal)</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will participate in 3 sessions per week expending 0 kcal per session and rate their liking of exercise.</description>
    <arm_group_label>No Exercise vs Sedentary Option</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sedentary Option</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will rate their liking of sedentary activities (reading magazines, playing word games, puzzles) as an alternative to exercise.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High Dose Exercise vs Sedentary Option</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Low Dose Exercise vs Sedentary Option</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No Exercise vs Sedentary Option</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  BMI within 19-35 kg/m2

          -  Healthy enough to exercise

          -  Sedentary (not regularly engaging in exercise more than once per week)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Taking any medications that affect energy expenditure or eating

          -  Have gained or lost more than 10 pounds over the past 3 months

          -  Use tobacco

          -  Pregnant or lactating or plan to become pregnant in the next 6 months

          -  Have any medical conditions that prevent the individual from safely joining in
             physical activity

          -  Have high work-related activity such as construction and farm work
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James N Roemmich, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>USDA Grand Forks Human Nutrition Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>USDA Grand Forks Human Nutrition Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grand Forks</city>
        <state>North Dakota</state>
        <zip>58203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 7, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 11, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 14, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>USDA Grand Forks Human Nutrition Research Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>James Roemmich</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

