<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02440360</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15-016</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>15-16168</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02440360</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pay For Success: Permanent Supportive Housing for the Chronically Homeless</brief_title>
  <acronym>PFS:PSH-CH</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Provision of Permanent Supportive Housing for Chronically Homeless Individuals Through Pay for Success</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Santa Clara Valley Health &amp; Hospital System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Santa Clara County has partnered with Abode Services to provide 112 units of permanent
      supportive housing (PSH) for up to 6 years for chronically homeless individuals with multiple
      co-morbidities who are high cost users of services in the County. Because the target
      population of high cost users who are chronically homeless greatly exceeds the supply of
      permanent supportive housing to be made available via this mechanism, the County plans to use
      this opportunity to examine the effectiveness of PSH compared to treatment as usual by
      ethically allocating a limited resource using a lottery type system for eligible individuals
      who consent to participate in the Pay For Success (PFS) initiative. Specifically, while there
      are estimated to be over 2,500 people in Santa Clara who would be eligible for participation
      on any given night, the PFS program will only provide 112 PSH units at any given time. As the
      study duration will last six years, the investigators anticipate that approximately 150-200
      people will be housed via this mechanism. Outcomes will be reported to the Institutional
      Review Board (IRB) on a quarterly basis and will be based on scheduled quarterly reports
      provided to the county.

      This evaluation will be a randomized controlled trial comparing the outcomes for chronically
      homeless individuals randomized to receive PSH to those who are randomized to receive usual
      care. The aims of this study are to:

        1. measure months of stable tenancy for individuals who are placed in PSH;

        2. examine differences in utilization of health services and the criminal justice system;
           and

        3. monitor the changes in use of longitudinal care.

      All data utilized for this evaluation will be County administrative data. The investigators
      hypothesize that some costly and acute health services utilization will decrease over time
      for the intervention group, while other more sustaining health services will increase.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recruitment: Screening Tool

      Eligible homeless individuals will be identified using a Screening Tool developed by the
      University of California, San Francisco (UCSF) evaluators that uses County administrative
      data to identify the most costly users of health and social services in the County based on
      their medical and behavioral health conditions, length of homelessness, and County services
      utilization history (&quot;Eligible Homeless Individuals&quot;).

      Abode Services (Abode) is the housing service provider selected by the County for this PFS
      project. Abode will obtain 112 units of permanent supportive housing over the course of the
      first year of this study and place referred clients into those units.

      Eligibility Confirmation/Assessment/Consent

      Individuals identified by the Screening Tool who have been located by the Study Team will
      have their eligibility confirmed through administrative data and be screened in-person to
      determine key inclusion and exclusion criteria. Following eligibility confirmation, a
      designated Study Team member who has been trained in the process of informed consent will ask
      the individual if he/she is interested in learning about the project.

      The explanation of the study prior to administration of informed consent will be standardized
      so that all potentially eligible participants are approached in the same manner and receive
      the same information about the study prior to undergoing informed consent. This process will
      be conducted in the potential participants' language of choice. The investigators anticipate
      that the most common language choice for those with limited English proficiency is Spanish
      and Vietnamese. Study Team members will be fluent in those languages, as well as provide
      consent forms in those languages. For languages other than Spanish and Vietnamese, the
      investigators will use trained medical interpreters, who will interpret the consent process
      and attest to their interpretation on the consent form. The Study Team will use the &quot;teach
      back&quot; method to ensure comprehension of the study goals and risks as part of their informed
      consent procedure. Any individual who is unable to give informed consent, as expressed by
      inability to repeat back the risks and benefits of the study after three successive teach
      backs, will be deemed ineligible.

      Upon granting informed consent, eligible participants will be randomized to either the
      intervention or control groups.

      RCT &quot;Intervention&quot; and &quot;Usual Care&quot; Groups: Intervention Group

      Individuals randomized to the intervention group will be referred to Abode Services for the
      opportunity to be placed in permanent supportive housing. Specifically, Abode will provide
      individuals with access to a housing unit, along with a broad array of services designed to
      achieve sustained residential stability and wellness. These services are designed to end the
      participants' homelessness, increase income (primarily through enrollment in Supplemental
      Security Income), and provide increased access to ongoing physical and behavioral health
      services. Abode will use a modified Assertive Community Treatment (ACT) team model of service
      delivery. Abode's modified ACT model will provide community-based clinical services,
      integrated with a flexible array of housing options delivered through an Housing First
      approach to provide housing and supportive services for the most vulnerable members of the
      chronically homeless population who most frequently use costly emergency services.

      As part of the PSH service model and Abode's overall service delivery approach, Abode will
      offer a range of supportive services to participants, including, but not limited to:

        -  Permanent/Temporary Supportive Housing placement and retention

        -  Specialty mental health services

        -  Substance abuse services

        -  Medication support and education

        -  Social and community living skills

        -  Case management / housing skills

        -  Educational / vocational support

        -  Money management

        -  Leisure / Spiritual opportunities

        -  Connection to primary care providers

        -  Management of complex health issues

        -  Daily living skills

      RCT &quot;Intervention&quot; and &quot;Usual Care&quot; Groups: Usual Care Group

      Chronically homeless individuals who are in the control group will have access to all
      existing safety-net services that are available to homeless individuals in the County. In
      addition, since chronically homeless individuals often have complex conditions that make them
      high users of safety-net services, chronically homeless individuals who are not in the
      treatment group may be eligible for the array of other programs that are designed for high
      users of specific systems. These programs include Full Service Partnerships for individuals
      with a serious mental illness including those who are involved in the criminal justice
      system, and the upcoming Acute Mental Health Pay of Success project. Finally, members of the
      control group will also have access to other all other permanent supportive housing programs
      for chronically homeless persons in the County.

      Enrollment and Randomization Procedures

      Enrollment will occur in &quot;batches&quot; in order to provide Abode with sufficient participants to
      fill the units at a pace that will maximize both occupancy of available units and efficient
      use of Abode resources. The number of eligible individuals who are ultimately randomized and
      the pace of randomization will be based on

        -  The number of available housing units to which Abode has access over a given time
           period, and

        -  The number of individuals to whom Abode will need to outreach in order to enroll enough
           participants to fill those units. This number will be based on a referral plan agreed
           upon by Abode and the County.

      Each time new housing units become available, the County will enable the screening tool to be
      applied to a batch of incoming individuals. Potentially eligible homeless individuals whom
      have not been enrolled in the study will be offered study enrollment.

      Individuals randomized to the treatment group who are referred to and then located by the
      housing provider will be offered enrollment in the permanent supportive housing (PSH)
      intervention program. If an individual agrees to enroll in the PSH intervention, the
      individual will begin to receive case management services from the housing provider
      immediately, even if a housing unit is not yet available, and will be offered a housing unit
      once it becomes available. The intervention group will continue to receive case management
      services throughout the study, whether or not they remain housed successfully.

      Data Collected

      Individuals will be identified using data from multiple data sets that track health and
      criminal justice system use within Santa Clara County. UCSF will receive identifiable data
      from the following data sources from the County based on the provisions of the data-sharing
      Memorandum Of Understanding (MOU) that exists between UCSF and Santa Clara County. If the
      data are not linked by the County, UCSF will link the data using the participants' unique
      county identifier. UCSF will discard these identifiers once data are linked for the purpose
      of the analysis, and will retain only the unique study identifier (ID). The unique study ID
      can only be linked back to participating individuals' names via a master document that links
      name to study ID, which will be kept under password protection by the evaluators and will
      only be available to participating study staff. This master document will be destroyed at the
      conclusion of the study period or after a pre-determined period of time put forth by the IRB
      after the study's conclusion. The main anticipated data sources are as follows:

        -  Santa Clara Valley Health and Hospital System, including Santa Clara Valley Medical
           Center (HealthLink)

        -  Homeless Management Information System (HMIS)

        -  Criminal Justice Information Control (CJIC)

      Tenancy in permanent supportive housing will be reported by the housing service provider and
      verified by the investigator.

      Analysis Plan

      For the randomized controlled trial (RCT) framework used to evaluate health utilization
      outcomes, the study team will use an intention-to-treat (ITT) analysis, in which all
      participants randomly assigned to one of the groups are analyzed together, regardless of
      whether or not they completed or received that treatment. In this case, individuals who are
      randomized to the permanent supportive housing intervention will be retained in the treatment
      group even if they are not able to be located, if they are located but never enter housing,
      or are located, enrolled, and enter housing, but are not retained in housing long-term.
      Individuals randomized to the control group will be followed administratively using data
      provided by the County in order to track the outcomes outlined above in comparison to those
      in the intervention group.

      The randomization will be evaluated by comparing the characteristics (e.g., demographics,
      chronic health conditions) of the intervention and control groups using chi-square and
      non-parametric tests. The associations of baseline characteristics, medical conditions, and
      social factors with stable tenancy will be evaluated using logistic or Cox regression
      analyses. The health services use outcomes (i.e., emergency department and hospital services,
      social services and criminal justice system utilization) and their associations with stable
      tenancy will be evaluated using logistic, ordinal, or linear regression, as appropriate.
      Comparisons of rates of service utilization will be performed at α = 0.95 with one-tailed
      tests of the outcomes in direction hypothesized (e.g., emergency department (ED) visits in
      the treatment group will be ≤ ED visits in the control group). However, we will also test for
      trends over time, since it may be likely that health services utilization increases in the
      treatment group in the short term as services are more readily available and participants are
      more accessible, and then decreases in the longer term as the participant's health improves
      and stabilizes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stable tenancy</measure>
    <time_frame>Six years</time_frame>
    <description>evaluated in months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Utilization of health services and the criminal justice system</measure>
    <time_frame>Six years</time_frame>
    <description>A composite measure of health services utilization (including, but not limited to, inpatient medical and psychiatric hospitalizations, emergency department use, and ambulance use) and use of the criminal justice system (including, but not limited to, arrests and jail stays).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Longitudinal health care</measure>
    <time_frame>Six years</time_frame>
    <description>A composite measure of health services utilization (including, but not limited to, regular attendance at primary care, and engagement with ambulatory mental health and substance use treatment).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Homelessness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Permanent Supportive Housing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Permanent Supportive Housing (PSH) is subsidized housing with closely linked or on-site supportive services that typically include case management, physical and mental health care, substance use treatment services and vocational support.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual Care consists of public benefits (e.g., General Assistance and CalFresh), integrated medical and behavioral health services provided by Valley Medical Center and the rest of the County Health &amp; Hospital System including those offered by Valley Homeless Healthcare Program, specialty mental health and substance abuse treatment services and housing programs, and approximately 2,000 year-round beds of emergency shelter and transitional housing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PSH</intervention_name>
    <description>Please see arm description.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Permanent Supportive Housing</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Permanent Supportive Housing</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Please see arm description.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronically homeless (HUD definition)

          -  Past high utilization of County health services and/or the criminal justice system

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently incarcerated or in custody

          -  Individual has been recently housed

          -  Individual no longer lives in the County

          -  Individual is currently connected to and chooses not to leave another specialty Mental
             Health or other intensive case management program

          -  For hospitalized potential participants, treating physician(s) plan to discharge the
             potential participant to a skilled nursing facility or inpatient hospice

          -  Individual is not able to give informed consent, (see below) as determined by
             inability to complete teach-back
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maria Raven, MD, MPH, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maria Raven, MD, MPH, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>(415) 353-8309</phone>
    <email>maria.raven@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Margot Kushel, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(415) 206-8655</phone>
    <email>margot.kushel@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Santa Clara Valley Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santa Clara</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95118</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steve Monte, MSW</last_name>
      <phone>408-793-0568</phone>
      <email>Steve.Monte@hhs.sccgov.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kushel MB, Vittinghoff E, Haas JS. Factors associated with the health care utilization of homeless persons. JAMA. 2001 Jan 10;285(2):200-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11176814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kushel MB, Perry S, Bangsberg D, Clark R, Moss AR. Emergency department use among the homeless and marginally housed: results from a community-based study. Am J Public Health. 2002 May;92(5):778-84.</citation>
    <PMID>11988447</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kushel MB, Evans JL, Perry S, Robertson MJ, Moss AR. No door to lock: victimization among homeless and marginally housed persons. Arch Intern Med. 2003 Nov 10;163(20):2492-9.</citation>
    <PMID>14609786</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 5, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 6, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 12, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 26, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>chronic homelessness</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

