<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02446639</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RC13_0056</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02446639</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment the Dosage of Troponin T Hypersensitive Dosage in a Patient Population Hemodialysis and Peritoneal Dialysis</brief_title>
  <acronym>ECHOTnT</acronym>
  <official_title>Assessment the Dosage of Troponin T Hypersensitive Dosage in a Patient Population Hemodialysis and Peritoneal Dialysis (ECHOTnT)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nantes University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nantes University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      &quot;Troponin T (TnT) is a component of the contractile apparatus of the striated musculature.
      Although the function of TnT is the same in all striated muscles found in the heart to form a
      TNT (cardiac TnT) differing significantly TnT of the skeletal muscles. Because of its high
      tissue specificity, cardiac TnT is a specific marker and highly sensitive of myocardial
      injury.

      Asymptomatic elevations of troponins is frequently found in patients with chronic renal
      failure in stage V, which present no clinical signs of acute or electrical myocardial injury.

      Many studies have been conducted in recent years to explain the origin and clinical
      significance of this elevation, but the results are controversial: cardiac dysfunction, left
      ventricular hypertrophy or chronic inflammation.

      Besides the effect of the dialysis session was evaluated on this biological parameter in
      different studies which together do not find Impact hemodialysis session on the value of
      troponin Achieving dosages rate hypersensitive serum troponin T in a dialysis population,
      will:

        -  to determine the evolution of TnT in time and what are the characteristics of the
           patients for whom this rate varies

        -  to know what its evolution during the session,

        -  to identify if possible the criteria that are responsible for the variation in the
           direction of increasing and / or its reduction

        -  and to characterize patients whose base rate is higher than the 99 percentile in the
           absence of clinical symptoms which could lead to establish reference population for this
           specific normal values. The Purpose of this study is to evaluate the serum troponin T in
           a hypersensitive dialysis population and verify what is the influence of the
           hemodialysis session, the session parameters and intradialytic events on changes in
           serum troponin T hypersensitive after a hemodialysis session. &quot;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Current care study, single-center, uncontrolled, no randomised, open and prospective.

      Two hundred fifty patients on hemodialysis and / or peritoneal dialysis for more than 3
      months may be included in the study for a total period of 7 months.

      Hemodialysis patients will be informed at the weekly routine visits. Regarding peritoneal
      dialysis patients, a meeting can be organized with the physician. And the oral agreement of
      the patient will be collected during a second visit or meeting.

      The protocol provides four follow-up visits: at baseline, 4 weeks, 12 and 24 weeks.

      During these visits, the patient will have a clinical examination and a measure of the serum
      troponin T. Blood samples are realized in the usual conditions of the center - for
      hemodialysis patients: midweek as instructed by the usual protocol of the center. - for
      peritoneal dialysis patients: when the monthly routine consultation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 22, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess serum troponin T in a hypersensitive dialysis population</measure>
    <time_frame>At the time of the inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of serum troponin T hypersensitive measured just before the second dialysis week (at the time of inclusion).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To estimate the influence of the session of haemodialysis</measure>
    <time_frame>At the time of the inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>For the patients in haemodialysis, measures of the serum troponin before and after dialysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To estimate the evolution of the serum Troponin T</measure>
    <time_frame>At the time of the inclusion, at 4 weeks, at 12 weeks and at 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>measures of the serum troponin T before dialysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the measures of serum troponin T between the patients diabetics and the patients not diabetics, between the patients with cardiac histories and the patients without histories</measure>
    <time_frame>At the time of the inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the evolution of the measures of the serum Troponin T between the patients having undergone one cardiac event and the patients not having presented cardiac events</measure>
    <time_frame>At the time of the inclusion, at 4 weeks, at 12 weeks and at 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the measures of the serum Troponin T according to the technique of dialysis: Hemodialysis versus peritoneal dialysis.</measure>
    <time_frame>At the time of the inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Failure Chronic Requiring Dialysis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood collection</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients undergoing haemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis for more than 3 months
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient in Hemodialysis and/or peritoneal dialysis for more than 3 months

          -  Major patient

          -  Patient who can express his consent

          -  Collection of the not opposition

          -  Affiliated to the national insurance scheme

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Encircled woman

          -  Patients in poor condition general or whose likely survival does not exceed 6 months

          -  Patient presenting an evolutionary acute pathology or a neoplastic disease

          -  Patient with significant cardiac problems

          -  Rhabdomyolysis known muscular disease and active

          -  Patient presenting an unchecked active infection,HIV

          -  Patient included in another protocol of search which could interfere with the
             objectives of this study

          -  Patient psychiatric or incapable to give an informed consent or to pursue the study.

          -  Minor Patient

          -  Under guardianship patient
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre ECHO</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rezé</city>
        <zip>44200</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 28, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 13, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 18, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypersensitivity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

