<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02441309</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OCTO_039</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02441309</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Eurosarc Study of Mifamurtide in Advanced Osteosarcoma (MEMOS)</brief_title>
  <acronym>MEMOS</acronym>
  <official_title>A Mechanistic Study Of Mifamurtide (MTP-PE) In Patients With Metastatic And/Or Recurrent Osteosarcoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Millennium: The Takeda Oncology Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute for Health Research, United Kingdom</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oxford University Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Commission</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Bayesian designed multi-arm, multi-centre, open label phase II study. The target
      sample size of 40 patients will be recruited from up to 8 EU countries, but this may be
      revised in light of the interim analysis. Patients with relapsed or metastatic osteosarcoma
      will be divided into three treatment groups. They will all either have surgery or a biopsy
      before and after six weeks exposure to either Mifamurtide alone, Ifosfamide alone, or
      Mifamurtide combined with Ifosfamide. They will then receive further treatment to a maximum
      of 42 or 36 weeks in total (depending on Arm), with all patients being able to receive 36
      weeks of Mifamurtide treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Osteosarcoma (OS) is the most common primary tumour arising from bones. There is currently no
      approved treatment other than surgery for metastatic or recurrent osteosarcoma refractory to
      chemotherapy. Patients deemed unresectable normally receive chemotherapy prior to attempted
      resection. The addition of chemotherapy to surgery for metastatic or recurrent osteosarcoma
      may improve response rates. MEPACT (Mifamurtide, MTP-PE) is licensed for use in the adjuvant
      osteosarcoma setting; indicated in children, adolescents and young adults for the treatment
      of high-grade resectable non-metastatic osteosarcoma after macroscopically complete surgical
      resection. It is used in combination with post-operative multi-agent chemotherapy. This is a
      Bayesian designed multi-arm, multi-centre open-label phase II study in patients with
      metastatic and/or recurrent osteosarcoma, which will investigate why some patients with
      osteosarcoma may respond better than others to mifamurtide given alone or in combination with
      ifosfamide. Patients with relapsed or metastatic osteosarcoma will be divided into three
      treatment groups (Arms). Depending on their current disease status, patients may be either
      Registered to Arm A (resectable group), to receive Mifamurtide alone; or Randomised to Arm
      B/C (non-resectable group), to receive mifamurtide in combination with ifosfamide. Arm A -
      Mifamurtide alone; Arm B - Ifosfamide alone for 6 weeks then Ifosfamide + mifamurtide for 6
      weeks, then mifamurtide alone for 30 weeks; Arm C - Ifosfamide + mifamurtide for 12 weeks
      then mifamurtide alone for 24 weeks. All participants will receive 36 weeks or more of
      mifamurtide. Biopsies (or resected tumour samples) will be obtained before and after 6 weeks
      of therapy interval in order to determine the pharmacodynamic endpoints. The target sample
      size is 40 patients. An interim analysis will be performed for the primary efficacy endpoint.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 4, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 4, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Biological response data based on pharmacodynamic endpoints on tumour biopsy material</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline to after 6 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Biological response data based on pharmacodynamic endpoints on tumour biopsy material including macrophage infiltration and innate immune activation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Radiological response defined as complete or partial response and assessed using RECIST criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline to after 6 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Radiological response defined as complete or partial response and assessed using RECIST criteria</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective radiological response based on RECIST 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline to after 6, 12, 18, 24 &amp; 36 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Objective radiological response based on RECIST 1.1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity (graded according to the CTCAE criteria)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 42 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Toxicity measured and graded according to the CTCAE criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Laboratory abnormalities (grade 3-4)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 42 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Laboratory abnormalities grade 3 and 4</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease specific overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 42 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The time from registration/randomisation to death due to the disease. Surviving patients and deaths due to other cause will be censored at their last follow-up date. Patients lost to Follow-up without an event will be censored at the date of their last consultation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival on serial CT scan</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 42 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Time from randomisation for deemed non-resectable groups, or time from registration for deemed resectable group to first event, where an event is progression as (defined by RECIST criterion) or death due to any cause. Patients who have not had an event will be censored at their last follow-up date. Patients lost to follow-up without an event will be censored at the date of their last consultation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">8</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteosarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A. Mifamurtide only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive Mifamurtide only.
Treatment Weeks 1-6 (post 1st biopsy/resection):
Mifamurtide 2mg/m2, IV infusion, twice/week, with each infusion given at least 3 days apart, for 6 weeks.
Treatment Weeks 7-12 (post 2nd biopsy/resection):
Mifamurtide 2mg/m2, IV infusion, twice/week, with each infusion given at least 3 days apart, for 6 weeks.
Treatment Weeks 13-36:
Mifamurtide 2mg/m2, IV infusion, once/week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B. Ifosfamide (Followed by Mifamurtide)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive Ifosfamide alone initially, followed by ifosfamide plus mifamurtide, then mifamurtide alone.
Treatment Weeks 1-6: Day 1 of 21: Ifosfamide 12-15g/m2 IV infused over 4-5 days as per local practice. Repeated every 21 days for 2 cycles (3 weeks=1 cycle).
Treatment Weeks 7-12 (post 2nd biopsy/resection): Day 1 of 21: Ifosfamide 12-15g/m2 IV infused over 4-5 days once every 21 days for two cycles (3 weeks=1 cycle). Ifosfamide administered as per local practice, including concurrent dosing with mesna. Plus mifamurtide 2mg/m2, IV infusion, twice/week. Ifosfamide infusion must be started 24 hours prior to mifamurtide. Mifamurtide should be given on day 2 and either day 5 or day 6.
Treatment Weeks 13-18: Mifamurtide 2mg/m2, IV infusion, twice/week. Treatment Weeks 19-42: Mifamurtide 2mg/m2, IV infusion, once/week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>C. Ifosfamide + Mifamurtide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive mifamurtide combined with ifosfamide initially.
Treatment Weeks 1-6:
Day 1 of 21: Ifosfamide 12-15g/m2 IV infusion infused over 4-5 days once every 21 days for two cycles (3 weeks=1 cycle).
Plus Mifamurtide 2 mg/m2, IV infusion, twice per week, with each infusion given at least 3 days apart, for 6 weeks.
Ifosfamide infusion must be started 24 hours prior to mifamurtide. Mifamurtide should be given on day 2 and either day 5 or day 6.
Treatment Weeks 7-12 (post 2nd biopsy/resection):
Day 1 of 21: Ifosfamide 12-15g/m2 IV infusion infused over 4-5 days once every 21 days for two cycles (3 weeks = 1 cycle).
Plus Mifamurtide 2mg/m2, IV infusion, twice per week, with each infusion given at least 3 days apart, for 6 weeks. Ifosfamide infusion must be started 24 hours prior to mifamurtide. Mifamurtide should be given on day 2 and either day 5 or day 6.
Treatment Weeks 13-36: Mifamurtide 2mg/m2, IV infusion, once/week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mifamurtide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>A. Mifamurtide only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>B. Ifosfamide (Followed by Mifamurtide)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>C. Ifosfamide + Mifamurtide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ifosfamide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>B. Ifosfamide (Followed by Mifamurtide)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>C. Ifosfamide + Mifamurtide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Relapsed osteosarcoma (first, second, third or any relapse, patient has recovered from
             chemotherapy and any other investigational drug/agent treatment, radiotherapy or
             surgical procedure).

          2. Histological confirmed diagnosis of osteosarcoma at original presentation.

          3. Tumour at biopsy accessible or resectable site.

          4. Progressive disease documented by imaging within 3 months of entry into the trial.

          5. At least one measurable lesion on CT scan (RECIST) performed in past 21 days prior to
             trial entry.

          6. Male or female, age ≥ 16 years to 65 (or ≥18 based on institutional practice for
             Teenage and Young Adult Cancer patients).

          7. Life expectancy of at least 3 months.

          8. WHO performance score of 0 - 2.

          9. The patient is willing and able to comply with the protocol and scheduled follow-up
             visits and examinations.

         10. Written (signed and dated) informed consent.

         11. Cardiac shortening fraction ≥ 28% or ejection fraction ≥ 45%

         12. Renal function is adequate for ifosfamide treatment (GFR as per table below, other
             renal function screening tests as per local practice)

         13. Haematological and biochemical indices within the ranges shown below:

        Lab Test Value required

          -  Haemoglobin (Hb) ≥ 9 g/dL (Previous transfusion is allowed)

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;=1.0 x 10*9/L without growth factor support

          -  Platelet count &gt; 80.x 10*9/L (Previous transfusion is allowed)

          -  Total bilirubin &lt;1.5 times the upper limit of normal (ULN) for age (except for
             Gilbert's syndrome patients)

          -  Serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and/or Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &lt;2.5 ×
             ULN for age, &lt;2.5 × ULN for age

          -  Serum creatinine Normal range for age

          -  Glomerular filtration rate (GFR) (calculated as 51Cr-EDTA/99mTc-DTPA clearance)
             &gt;40ml/min if deemed resectable (for Arm A), &gt;60ml/min if not deemed resectable (for
             Arm B or C)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant or breast-feeding woman. Men or women of childbearing potential unless
             effective methods of contraception are used during study treatment and for at least 7
             days after the last mifamurtide dose (see section 5.1 Informed consent -
             Contraceptive/ Pregnancy counselling).

          2. Previous treatment with mifamurtide or a mifamurtide-like drug* in a clinical trial
             setting for the treatment of metastatic and/or recurrent osteosarcoma in the six
             months prior to registration.

          3. Contraindications to lung biopsies.

          4. Hypersensitivity to ifosfamide or any component of the formulation.

          5. Previously diagnosed brain metastases.

          6. Significant active cardiac disease including: uncontrolled high blood pressure (no
             greater than 2 standard deviations above the mean for age for systolic blood pressure
             (SBP) and diastolic blood pressure (DBP), unstable angina, congestive heart failure,
             myocardial infarction within the previous 6 months, or serious cardiac arrhythmias and
             with a history of pericarditis and myocarditis

          7. Treatment with any other investigational agent, or participation in another
             interventional clinical trial within 21 days prior to enrolment.

          8. Major surgery within 21 days prior to first study biopsy

          9. Currently taking high-dose non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) or
             corticosteroid treatment

         10. Concurrent use of ciclosporin or other calcineurin inhibitors.

         11. Any psychological, social or medical condition, physical examination finding or a
             laboratory abnormality that the Investigator considers would make the patient a poor
             trial candidate or could interfere with protocol compliance or the interpretation of
             trial results.

         12. Any other active malignancy, with the exception of adequately treated cone-biopsied in
             situ carcinoma of the cervix uteri and non-melanoma skin lesions.

         13. Patients who are known to be serologically positive for Hepatitis B, Hepatitis C or
             HIV.

               -  mifamurtide-like drugs include GCSF, GMCSF, interferon and other macrophage
                  activating molecules.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bass Hassan, BSc(Hon) BMBCh MRCP DPhil FRCP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pediatric Hematology and Oncology, University Hospital Münster</name>
      <address>
        <city>Münster</city>
        <zip>48149</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istituti Ortopedici Rizzoli</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bologna</city>
        <state>Emilia-Romagna</state>
        <zip>40136</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Clinical Oncology, Leiden University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leiden</city>
        <state>Postzone K1-P</state>
        <zip>P.O. Box 9600</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Radium Hospital, Oslo University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oslo</city>
        <zip>0310</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leeds Teaching Hospitals NHS Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leeds</city>
        <zip>LS9 7TF</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University College London Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>NW1 2BU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Christie Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <zip>M20 4BX</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oxford University Hospitals NHS Foundations Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <zip>OX3 7LE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Norway</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.octo-oxford.org.uk/alltrials/trials/MEMOS.html</url>
    <description>Information about the trial on the Oncology Clinical Trials Office (OCTO) website. OCTO run the trial on behalf of the sponsor, the University of Oxford</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 12, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Metastatic and/or Recurrent Osteosarcoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteosarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ifosfamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Isophosphamide mustard</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mifamurtide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acetylmuramyl-Alanyl-Isoglutamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>July 6, 2017</submitted>
    <submission_canceled>Unknown</submission_canceled>
    <submitted>July 25, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>December 15, 2017</returned>
    <submitted>March 8, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

