<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00348621</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01AG015812</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01AG015812</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00348621</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Interventions to Reduce Disability From Visual Loss in Nursing Home Residents</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Trial of Interventions for Visual Loss in Nursing Home Residents</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this clinical trial is to determine if interventions within the nursing home
      to restore vision, or cope with visual loss, in residents with visual impairment result in
      improvement or less decline in mobility scores, and socialization scores, compared to
      residents with visual impairment in nursing homes with no such intervention. The
      investigators hypothesized that nursing home residents with visual loss who receive cataract
      surgery, or refractive correction, or low vision aids would have have better socialization
      scores and mobility scores at 6 months and 12 months compared to nursing home residents with
      visual impairment who are advised to seek services, but have no specific program.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this project was to quantify the impact of visual acuity impairment on
      socialization and physical function of nursing home residents, and to determine the cost
      effectiveness of a visual impairment intervention program designed to enhance access to eye
      care services. To accomplish these aims, the investigators enrolled a complete sample of
      visually impaired persons from 28 nursing homes in the Lower Eastern Shore of Maryland and
      Delaware. From the same facilities, the investigators also enrolled a random sample of
      non-visually impaired residents, with sample size equal to the sample of visually impaired.
      The group of visually impaired residents was randomized (by facility) to an intervention
      program or &quot;usual care&quot; group. The intervention program facilitated the utilization of eye
      care services of the three main causes of visual impairment: refractive error, cataract, and
      low vision associated with age-related eye diseases. All study groups provided data at
      baseline, six and twelve months from intervention, and data on eye care utilization,
      hospitalizations, use of psychoactive medications and mortality collected every other month
      (bi-monthly). Patients had a screening test of visual acuity, using standard letter/symbol
      charts, and grating charts. The mental status was tested using the MiniMental State
      Examination. Social function, physical function, and mobility were assessed through
      questionnaires asked of nursing home staff familiar with the patient, and the questions were
      modeled on the Minimum Data Set questions or specially designed for nursing home residents.

      The investigators compare the mobility scores, and socialization scores, of nursing home
      residents with visual loss randomized to the intervention homes to the scores of nursing home
      residents with visual loss randomized to control homes. The investigators use the mobility
      and socialization scores of those without visual loss at baseline and follow up to compare
      with the trajectory of decline in those with visual loss.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2002</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2001</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mobility score</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>questionnaire to nurses in charge of nursing home patients on specific items on mobility, which were used to create mobility score</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>socialization score</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>questionnaire to nurses in charge of nursing home patients on items specific to subject socialization, used to create socialization score</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2544</enrollment>
  <condition>Cataract</condition>
  <condition>Refractive Error</condition>
  <condition>Low Vision</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Visual impairment intervention program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>enhanced access to eye care services</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>family and nursing home was apprised of ocular exam results; eye care services left to family/nursing home arrangements</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Visual impairment intervention program</intervention_name>
    <description>enhanced access to eye care services</description>
    <arm_group_label>Visual impairment intervention program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Nursing homes in Eastern Shore of Maryland,within 1.5 hour drive of Salisbury MD

          -  Nursing home administrators and resident committees approved the study

          -  Nursing home residents:

          -  Age 65 and older

          -  more than 30 day length of Stay

          -  Capable of acuity testing

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Nursing home residents:

          -  staff assessment noted imminent death likely (within 3 months)

          -  resident unable to provide informed consent and guardian not locatable

          -  resident's only language was not understood by nursing staff
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sheila West</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Friedman DS, Munoz B, Massof RW, Bandeen-Roche K, West SK. Grating visual acuity using the preferential-looking method in elderly nursing home residents. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2002 Aug;43(8):2572-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12147587</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>West SK, Friedman D, Muñoz B, Roche KB, Park W, Deremeik J, Massof R, Frick KD, Broman A, McGill W, Gilbert D, German P. A randomized trial of visual impairment interventions for nursing home residents: study design, baseline characteristics and visual loss. Ophthalmic Epidemiol. 2003 Jul;10(3):193-209.</citation>
    <PMID>12815493</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Friedman DS, West SK, Munoz B, Park W, Deremeik J, Massof R, Frick K, Broman A, McGill W, Gilbert D, German P. Racial variations in causes of vision loss in nursing homes: The Salisbury Eye Evaluation in Nursing Home Groups (SEEING) Study. Arch Ophthalmol. 2004 Jul;122(7):1019-24.</citation>
    <PMID>15249367</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Friedman DS, Muñoz B, Roche KB, Massof R, Broman A, West SK. Poor uptake of cataract surgery in nursing home residents: the Salisbury Eye Evaluation in Nursing Home Groups study. Arch Ophthalmol. 2005 Nov;123(11):1581-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16286622</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 3, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 3, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 4, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cataract surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>refractive correction</keyword>
  <keyword>low vision services</keyword>
  <keyword>nursing home</keyword>
  <keyword>visual impairment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cataract</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Refractive Errors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vision, Low</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

