<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00340119</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999905125</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>05-C-N125</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00340119</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genetic Susceptibility to Cardiovascular Disease in Patients on Kidney Dialysis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Study of Inflammatory Markers and Genes as Predictors of Atherosclerotic Cardiovascular Disease in Dialysis Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study, done in collaboration with Johns Hopkins University School of Public Health in
      Baltimore, Maryland, will examine the role of genes in the development of atherosclerotic
      cardiovascular disease (CVD) in patients undergoing kidney dialysis. The rate of illness and
      death from CVD among patients on dialysis is extraordinarily high, accounting for about 50
      percent of deaths. Blood levels of inflammatory markers are elevated in these patients,
      strongly predicting illness and death from CVD. The discovery of gene variants related to the
      inflammatory process in atherosclerotic CVD may lead to better medical treatments and
      improved survival in patients with end-stage kidney disease.

      Participants of John's Hopkins University's CHOICE (Choices for Healthy Outcomes in Caring
      for End-Stage Renal Disease) program are included in this study. Blood samples previously
      collected from these patients will be analyzed in the laboratory for genes that might be
      associated with the inflammatory process and atherogenesis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      The CHOICE (Choices for Healthy Outcomes in Caring for End stage renal disease) study is a
      national prospective cohort study of 1,041 incident dialysis patients aged 19 to 95 recruited
      in 81 dialysis clinics between October 1995 and June 1998, and is overseen by the Johns
      Hopkins University School of Public Health.

      The discovery of genetic associations offers the potential to direct clinical management in
      order to prevent ASCVD (Atherosclerotic Cardiovascular Disease) and improve survival in
      patients with end stage renal disease (ESRD).

      Objectives:

      In Collaboration with investigators of the CHOICE cohort, we propose to assess the role of
      variants in genes related to the inflammatory process on atherosclerotic cardiovascular
      disease (ASCVD) incidence.

      Eligibility:

      Eligibility is independent of age, race, ethnicity, and gender. However, no participants in
      this cohort are less than 19 years of age.

      Design:

      Frozen buffy coats from 871 patients will be sent to the LGD, and DNA will be extracted.

      Singles nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) within coding regions, upstream or downstream
      regulatory regions or in intronic regions of candidates genes will be genotyped.

      The first candidate genes under study include IL6, IL10, TGFB1, Beta Fibrinogen, LTA, and
      STAT3.

      Blood samples and relevant clinical data will be provided by Johns Hopkins University School
      of Public Health, Department of Epidemiology with only numerical code which links samples and
      clinical data. While Johns Hopkins University will retain patient identifier information, the
      LGD will have no way of identifying the person from whom the blood, subsequent DNA, and
      clinical data are obtained.

      The samples are maintained in our repository and curated through our central Laboratory
      database.

      Destruction or loss of clinical samples or data will be recorded in our database and cannot
      impact the study participants in any way.

      At the completion of this protocol, we will retain the samples for future use. We understand
      that studies subsequent to the completion of this protocol will require additional OHSR/IRB
      approval prior to commencement.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 21, 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date>March 1, 2012</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">871</enrollment>
  <condition>End Stage Renal Disease</condition>
  <condition>ESRD</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Original eligibility criteria for enrollment in the CHOICE cohort included: 1) new onset of
        chronic outpatient renal replacement therapy in the last 3 months, 2) ability to give
        informed consent to participate in the study, 3) age 19 years or older, 4) ability to speak
        English or Spanish.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        The entire set of 871 samples available to the LGD will be analyzed. No subject will be
        excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Dean, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Longenecker JC, Coresh J, Klag MJ, Levey AS, Martin AA, Fink NE, Powe NR. Validation of comorbid conditions on the end-stage renal disease medical evidence report: the CHOICE study. Choices for Healthy Outcomes in Caring for ESRD. J Am Soc Nephrol. 2000 Mar;11(3):520-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10703676</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Longenecker JC, Coresh J, Powe NR, Levey AS, Fink NE, Martin A, Klag MJ. Traditional cardiovascular disease risk factors in dialysis patients compared with the general population: the CHOICE Study. J Am Soc Nephrol. 2002 Jul;13(7):1918-27.</citation>
    <PMID>12089389</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Georges JL, Loukaci V, Poirier O, Evans A, Luc G, Arveiler D, Ruidavets JB, Cambien F, Tiret L. Interleukin-6 gene polymorphisms and susceptibility to myocardial infarction: the ECTIM study. Etude Cas-Témoin de l'Infarctus du Myocarde. J Mol Med (Berl). 2001 Jun;79(5-6):300-5.</citation>
    <PMID>11485024</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 1, 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 21, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>CHOICE Cohort</keyword>
  <keyword>End Stage Renal Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Epidemiology</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms</keyword>
  <keyword>ESRD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

