<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00342303</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999993027</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>OH93-AA-N027</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00342303</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Activity of Essential Fatty Acid Elongation/Desaturation Pathway During Early Life in Human Infants, In Vivo</brief_title>
  <official_title>Essential Fatty Acid Metabolism in the Newborn: Equivalence of Precusors and Mediators in the Synthesis of Long Chain Polyunsaturated Fatty Acids of the n-6 and n-3 Series</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We will test the following hypotheses:

        1. The activity of the desaturating/elongating enzymes assessed by the in vivo conversion
           of deuterated a-linolenic and linoleic acids to DHA and AA, respectively, will be
           related to the duration of gestation and to postnatal age.

        2. Dietary w-3 and w-6 LCPUFAs in human milk or DHA and AA supplemented formula will
           inhibit the desaturation/elongation of deuterated a-linolenic and linoleic acids
           demonstrating in vivo inhibition of the metabolic pathway by respective products.

      Present evidence suggests that the parent essential fatty acids (EFA), linoleic acid (18:2
      w-6) and a-linolenic acids (18:3 w-3) are insufficient to fully satisfy EFA nutrition during
      early life in the human. A possible need for long chain (LC, longer than 18 C chain length)
      EFAs in the human is suggested by the accretion rates of elongated and desaturated products
      in the developing fetus; the altered plasma and red cell fatty acid patterns, and the
      abnormal visual function observed in infants receiving solely the parent EFAs; and by the
      relatively high concentration of LC EFAs in human milk. Most milk formula, as compared to
      human milk, are lower in oleic acid, higher in linoleic, have little a-linolenic acid and
      virtually no LC w-3 or w-6 polyunsaturated FA (LC PUFA). This study will evaluate the
      capacity of human infants to form w-3 and w-6 LCPUFAs from the parent EFAs as affected by
      developmental stage and dietary EFA supply. The precursors will be labeled with deuterium and
      the products analyzed by gas chromatography / mass spectrometry GC/MS. The main products of
      the desaturation / elongation pathway are docosahexaenoic (DHA) and arachidonic (AA) acids
      for the w-3 and w-6 series, respectively. Infants will be fed human milk or formulas with or
      without supplemental LCPUFAs as part of a study to evaluate the effect of EFAs on CNS
      functional development. Infants included in this study of the effect of developmental stage
      on EFA desaturation/elongation will be 2-5 days of age (before any fat is administered
      enterally or parenterally) and 28, 32, 36 or 40 weeks gestation. In addition, infants born at
      28 and 40 weeks gestation will be studied 2 and 6 weeks postnatally after dietary fat has
      been provided for at least 7 days and energy intake is sufficient to assure growth. To
      evaluate the effect of dietary EFA on DHA and AA formation we will assess elongation/
      desaturation in infants receiving 3 diets: human milk (which contains w-3 and w-6 LCPUFAs);
      cow milk based formula providing 18:2 w-6 and 18:3 w-3 but no LCPUFAs; or formula
      supplemented with added LCPUFAs (DHA and AA). This study should provide new information on
      the effects of developmental stage and w-3 and w-6 LCPUFA supply in determining the activity
      of EFA elongation/desaturation in the human. This knowledge may help in improving early
      neonatal nutritional practices to assure meeting the EFA needs of the developing CNS.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We will test the following hypotheses:

        1. The activity of the desaturating/elongating enzymes assessed by the in vivo conversion
           of deuterated a-linolenic and linoleic acids to DHA and AA, respectively, will be
           related to the duration of gestation and to postnatal age.

        2. Dietary w-3 and w-6 LCPUFAs in human milk or DHA and AA supplemented formula will
           inhibit the desaturation/elongation of deuterated a-linolenic and linoleic acids
           demonstrating in vivo inhibition of the metabolic pathway by respective products.

      Present evidence suggests that the parent essential fatty acids (EFA), linoleic acid (18:2
      w-6) and a-linolenic acids (18:3 w-3) are insufficient to fully satisfy EFA nutrition during
      early life in the human. A possible need for long chain (LC, longer than 18 C chain length)
      EFAs in the human is suggested by the accretion rates of elongated and desaturated products
      in the developing fetus; the altered plasma and red cell fatty acid patterns, and the
      abnormal visual function observed in infants receiving solely the parent EFAs; and by the
      relatively high concentration of LC EFAs in human milk. Most milk formula, as compared to
      human milk, are lower in oleic acid, higher in linoleic, have little a-linolenic acid and
      virtually no LC w-3 or w-6 polyunsaturated FA (LC PUFA). This study will evaluate the
      capacity of human infants to form w-3 and w-6 LCPUFAs from the parent EFAs as affected by
      developmental stage and dietary EFA supply. The precursors will be labeled with deuterium and
      the products analyzed by gas chromatography / mass spectrometry GC/MS. The main products of
      the desaturation / elongation pathway are docosahexaenoic (DHA) and arachidonic (AA) acids
      for the w-3 and w-6 series, respectively. Infants will be fed human milk or formulas with or
      without supplemental LCPUFAs as part of a study to evaluate the effect of EFAs on CNS
      functional development. Infants included in this study of the effect of developmental stage
      on EFA desaturation/elongation will be 2-5 days of age (before any fat is administered
      enterally or parenterally) and 28, 32, 36 or 40 weeks gestation. In addition, infants born at
      28 and 40 weeks gestation will be studied 2 and 6 weeks postnatally after dietary fat has
      been provided for at least 7 days and energy intake is sufficient to assure growth. To
      evaluate the effect of dietary EFA on DHA and AA formation we will assess elongation/
      desaturation in infants receiving 3 diets: human milk (which contains w-3 and w-6 LCPUFAs);
      cow milk based formula providing 18:2 w-6 and 18:3 w-3 but no LCPUFAs; or formula
      supplemented with added LCPUFAs (DHA and AA). Also, the relative efficiency of conversion of
      the 18-C precursors will be compared to the 20-C precursors with respect to their metabolic
      endpoints. This study should provide new information on the effects of developmental stage
      and w-3 and w-6 LCPUFA supply in determining the activity of EFA elongation/desaturation in
      the human. This knowledge may help in improving early neonatal nutritional practices to
      assure meeting the EFA needs of the developing CNS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 8, 1993</start_date>
  <completion_date>July 13, 2010</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Fatty Acid Metabolism</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Newborns with birth weights appropriate for their gestational age born at 28, 32, 36 and 40
        weeks gestation that are recovering from common neonatal morbidity will be recruited to
        enter the study before 5 days of age. This disease condition will not be life threatening
        at the time of study.

        The typical disease conditions expected based on the pilot phase of study are infants
        recovering from asphyxia, infants recovering from transient tachypnea, infants recovering
        from suspect pneumonia, infants recovering from hyaline membrane disease.

        Hyperbilirubinemia in conjunction with disease condition will not be a reason for
        exclusion.

        Newborns with birth weights below the tenth percentile of the weight distribution for a
        given gestational age born at 30-34 and 36-38 weeks gestation.

        Will include infants born at 28 to 40 weeks who are free of major neonatal morbidity and
        will be recruited to enter the study at 10 days of age.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Maternal factors which may affect their fatty acid metabolism of the neonate.

          -  Vegetarian or vegan diet during pregnancy

          -  Metabolic disease which may affect essential fatty acid status of the fetus
             (hyperlipidemia, diabetes)

        Postnatal factors:

        Birth weight inadequate for gestational age (birth weight below the 10th percentile or
        above the 90th percentile for gestational age)

        Significant acute neonatal morbidity which interferes with normal lipid metabolism during
        the study period. Infants who are recovering from common neonatal morbidities that do not
        have obvious effects on elongase/desaturase activity will not be excluded.

        Feeding other than prescribed for the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinica Presbiteriana Madre Hijo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santiago</city>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Luis Tisne</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santiago</city>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Chile</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee AG, East JM, Froud RJ. Are essential fatty acids essential for membrane function? Prog Lipid Res. 1986;25(1-4):41-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2962202</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glomset JA. Fish, fatty acids, and human health. N Engl J Med. 1985 May 9;312(19):1253-4.</citation>
    <PMID>3990716</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sprecher H. Biochemistry of essential fatty acids. Prog Lipid Res. 1981;20:13-22.</citation>
    <PMID>7342077</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 13, 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 21, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Premature Infants</keyword>
  <keyword>Fatty Acid Metabolism</keyword>
  <keyword>Polyunsaturated Fatty Acids</keyword>
  <keyword>Infant Formula</keyword>
  <keyword>Gas-chromatography</keyword>
  <keyword>Mass Spectrometry</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

