<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00341523</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999995026</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>OH95-C-N026</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00341523</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00005885</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Detection of Esophageal Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Early Detection of Esophageal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Esophageal cancer is a common malignancy with a very poor prognosis. The principal reason for
      its poor prognosis is that most tumors are asymptomatic and go undetected until they have
      spread beyond the esophageal wall and are unresectable. Significant reduction in esophageal
      cancer mortality will require successful strategies to diagnose and treat more cases at
      earlier, more curable stages of disease. A successful early detection program will require an
      accurate, patient-acceptable screening test, confirmatory tests that can localize precursor
      and early invasive lesions, and one or more curative therapies that are acceptable to
      asymptomatic patients. This project includes five studies designed to evaluate techniques
      that may be useful in such an early detection program:

        1. The Cytology Sampling Study will estimate and compare the sensitivity of several
           cytologic samplers for identifying biopsy-proven dysplasia and cancer of the esophagus.

        2. The Mucosal Staining Study will evaluate whether mucosal straining can improve
           endoscopic localization of esophageal dysplasia and cancer.

        3. The Endoscopic Staging Study will evaluate how accurately endoscopic techniques can
           stage dysplasia and early invasive cancer of the esophagus.

        4. The Endoscopic Therapy Pilot Study will evaluate the feasibility, safety, acceptability
           and preliminary efficacy of endoscopic therapies for removing or ablating focal
           high-grade dysplasias and early invasive cancers of the esphagus.

        5. The Chemoregression Study will evaluate the ability of oral chemopreventive agents to
           reduce progression or cause regression of low-grade squamous dysplasia of the esophagus.

      This project will be carried out in Linxian, China, a county with extraordinary rates of
      esophageal cancer and a correspondingly high prevalence of the asymptomatic precursor and
      early invasive lesions that are needed for these studies. The project will be a collaborative
      effort of investigators from NCI, the Cancer Institute of the Chinese Academy of Medical
      Sciences, and several U.S. universities....
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Esophageal cancer is a common malignancy with a very poor prognosis. The principal reason for
      its poor prognosis is that most tumors are asymptomatic and go undetected until they have
      spread beyond the esophageal wall and are unresectable. Significant reduction in esophageal
      cancer mortality will require successful strategies to diagnose and treat more cases at
      earlier, more curable stages of disease. A successful early detection program will require an
      accurate, patient-acceptable screening test, confirmatory tests that can localize precursor
      and early invasive lesions, and one or more curative therapies that are acceptable to
      asymptomatic patients. This project includes six studies designed to evaluate techniques that
      may be useful in such an early detection program:

        1. The Cytology Sampling Study will estimate and compare the sensitivity of several
           cytologic samplers for identifying biopsy-proven dysplasia and cancer of the esophagus.

        2. The Mucosal Staining Study will evaluate whether mucosal staining can improve endoscopic
           localization of esophageal dysplasia and cancer.

        3. The Endoscopic Staging Study will evaluate how accurately endoscopic techniques can
           stage dysplasia and early invasive cancer of the esophagus.

        4. The Endoscopic Therapy Pilot Study will evaluate the feasibility, safety, acceptability
           and preliminary efficacy of endoscopic therapies for removing or ablating focal
           high-grade dysplasias and early invasive cancers of the esophagus.

        5. The Chemoregression Study will evaluate the ability of oral chemopreventive agents to
           reduce progression or cause regression of low-grade squamous dysplasia of the esophagus.

        6. The Human Papillomavirus Tissue Study will evaluate the hypothesis that HPV is involved
           in the pathogenesis of esophageal squamous cell carcinoma and/or gastric cardia
           adenocarcinoma.

      This project will be carried out in Linxian, China, a county with extraordinary rates of
      esophageal cancer and a correspondingly high prevalence of the asymptomatic precursor and
      early invasive lesions that are needed for these studies. The project will be a collaborative
      effort of investigators from NCI, and the Cancer Institute of the Chinese Academy of Medical
      Sciences.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1, 1994</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Esophageal squamous dysplasia</measure>
    <time_frame>Single time point, when samples are collected</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Esophageal squamous cell carcinoma (ESCC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Clinical diagnosis of ESCC</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Death from any cause</measure>
    <time_frame>Death</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8000</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Stomach Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Endoscopy, Gastrointestinal</condition>
  <condition>Digestive System Endoscopic Surgical Procedures</condition>
  <condition>Cytology</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Resident of Linxian, Henan Province, People's Republic of China.

        40-69 years of age at the time of EGD screening.

        Visible esophageal lesions with mild or moderate squamous dysplasia found at the t(-6) EGD
        screening exam.

        Confirmation of a visible index lesion at the t(0)EGD baseline exam.

        Willing to abstain from chronic NSAID use (defined as greater than 3 times per week for
        more than 2 weeks), with the exception of low-dose aspirin (less than or equal to 100 mg
        per day), for the duration of the study.

        If a subject is female and of child-bearing potential (premenopausal or less than 2 years
        postmenopausal and not surgically sterile), she must be willing to use adequate
        contraception (abstinence, IUD, birth control pills, or spermicidal gel with diaphragm or
        condom) for the duration of the study.

        Appropriate laboratory values within 2 weeks of the baseline evaluation for:

        hemoglobin greater than 11.0 g/dl;

        WBC greater than 3000/mm(3);

        platelet count greater than 100,000;

        creatinine less than or equal to 1.5 times the upper limit of normal;

        AST less than or equal to 1.5 times the upper limit of normal;

        Alkaline phosphatase less than or equal to 1.5 the upper limit of normal;

        Pregnancy test negative serum or urine (women of childbearing potential only).

        Only those patients with mild or moderate dysplasia based on the t(-6) histology and
        endoscopically visible lesions at the t(0) evaluation will be eligible for participation
        and inclusion in the study.

        To be eligible at t(0), subjects must have a confirmed, endoscopically visible lesion.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Diagnosed cancer at any site, except non-melanoma skin cancer.

        Current symptoms suggestive of an upper gastrointestinal tract malignancy, including
        dysphagia, odynophagia, hematemesis, or weight loss of greater than 10% body weight within
        the past 6 months.

        Contraindications to the EGD exams, including hypersensitivity to lidocaine or iodine,
        uncontrolled congestive heart failure, unstable angina, bleeding disorder or severe
        pulmonary disease.

        Contraindications to use of the intervention agents, including hypersensitivity to
        selenomethionine, COX-2 inhibitors, NSAIDs, salicylates, or sulfonamides.

        Treated for peptic ulcer disease within the past month prior to the baseline evaluation.

        Acute or chronic kidney disease, liver disease, or asthma.

        Pregnant or nursing an infant.

        Other serious health condition that might preclude study completion (at the discretion of
        the investigators).

        Currently using fluconazole or lithium.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sanford M Dawsey, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sanford M Dawsey, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 594-2930</phone>
    <email>dawseys@dcpcepn.nci.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer Institute, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <zip>100021</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Guiqi Wang</last_name>
      <phone>Not Listed</phone>
      <email>wangguiq@126.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pan QJ, Roth MJ, Guo HQ, Kochman ML, Wang GQ, Henry M, Wei WQ, Giffen CA, Lu N, Abnet CC, Hao CQ, Taylor PR, Qiao YL, Dawsey SM. Cytologic detection of esophageal squamous cell carcinoma and its precursor lesions using balloon samplers and liquid-based cytology in asymptomatic adults in Llinxian, China. Acta Cytol. 2008 Jan-Feb;52(1):14-23. Erratum in: Acta Cytol. 2008 Mar-Apr;52(2):276.</citation>
    <PMID>18323271</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dawsey SM, Fleischer DE, Wang GQ, Zhou B, Kidwell JA, Lu N, Lewin KJ, Roth MJ, Tio TL, Taylor PR. Mucosal iodine staining improves endoscopic visualization of squamous dysplasia and squamous cell carcinoma of the esophagus in Linxian, China. Cancer. 1998 Jul 15;83(2):220-31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9669803</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taylor PR, Abnet CC, Dawsey SM. Squamous dysplasia--the precursor lesion for esophageal squamous cell carcinoma. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev. 2013 Apr;22(4):540-52. doi: 10.1158/1055-9965.EPI-12-1347.</citation>
    <PMID>23549398</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 8, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 21, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Cytology</keyword>
  <keyword>Endoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Esophageal Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Early Detection</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stomach Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

