<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00342446</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999996019</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>OH96-C-N019</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00342446</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Follow-up Study of Women Evaluated and Treated for Infertility</brief_title>
  <official_title>Follow-Up Study of Women Evaluated and Treated for Infertility</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess the relations of infertility causes and treatment to cancer risk, we will conduct a
      retrospective cohort study of approximately 12,000 women evaluated for infertility between
      1965-1988. These women will be ascertained from several large infertility clinics and private
      practices in various geographic locations in the United States: Boston, Chicago, Detroit, New
      York, and Palo Alto. These practices were selected on the basis of their having large number
      of patients who received ovulation stimulating drugs many years in the distant past.
      Abstractors reviewed clinic medical records to identify eligible study participants and
      abstract data needed to classify causes of infertility and document therapies employed. Using
      a variety of tracing sources (including the National Death Index, credit bureaus, and
      postmasters), the vital status and location of the study subjects were determined. Subjects
      who were traced and identified as alive are being sent a detailed questionnaire that requests
      information on their health status as well as on a number of lifestyle practices. For
      subjects who report a cancer, medical verification is being sought from the diagnosing
      physicians and/or facilities. Death certificates are being sought for deceased subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND: We previously conducted a retrospective cohort study of 12,193 patients evaluated
      for infertility between 1960-1988 at five clinical sites. Detailed information abstracted
      from the medical records, along with questionnaires administered to located patients and
      cancer incidence and mortality data derived from cancer registries and the National Death
      Index, allowed us to examine cancer risk related to different causes of infertility and
      treatments while controlling for other patient characteristics. Although there were some
      increases of certain cancers related to various causes of infertility, we generally did not
      observe substantial relationships related to use of different fertility drugs. The one
      exception was some increased risk of uterine cancers with clomiphene use, of interest given
      the drug's chemical similarity to tamoxifen. Our numbers of patients with certain cancers
      (e.g., ovarian, uterine) were, however, limited and we had insufficient power to evaluate
      subgroup effects (e.g., drug relationships among nulligravid women).

      OBJECTIVES: We therefore conducted an updated follow-up of these patients in order to assess
      cancer risk in relation to causes of infertility and therapeutic regimens used to treat these
      causes.

      ELIGIBILITY: This study gained an additional 10 years of follow-up among the patients deemed
      eligible for the previous investigation. This included women with both primary and second
      infertility. Approximately 39% of the cohort previously were prescribed clomiphene citrate,
      while 10% received gonadotrophins.

      DESIGN: Passive follow-up was attempted for patients who previously did not participate and
      for whom only information available in clinic records could be retained. All other patients
      were traced for active as well as passive follow-up. Active follow-up involved requesting
      that patients complete a short questionnaire, whereas passive follow-up was via linkage to
      cancer registries and the National Death Index. While cancer risks were assessed in relation
      to the general population, the majority of comparisons were internal ones, involving the
      calculation of relative risks (RRs) associated with different causes of infertility or
      treatment regimens while controlling for other cancer risk predictors.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 5, 1996</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12193</enrollment>
  <condition>Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Endometrial Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Thyroid Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Colrectal Cancer, Melanoma</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        The following criteria for inclusion in the study cohort will apply:

        Patient is female.

        Patient was evaluated for infertility between (and including) 1965 and 1988.

        Patient had a U.S. address at the time of evaluation for infertility.

        Patient was seen twice by the physician, or was seen once but had a referral from another
        physician.

        Patient's infertility was not due to gonadal dysgenesis or congenital abnormalities of the
        reproductive system.

        Patient's visit to the infertility specialist was not to have a tubal ligation reversed.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Britton L Trabert, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032-3784</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bamford PN, Steele SJ. Uterine and ovarian carcinoma in a patient receiving gonadotrophin therapy. Case report. Br J Obstet Gynaecol. 1982 Nov;89(11):962-4.</citation>
    <PMID>7171506</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carter ME, Joyce DN. Ovarian carcinoma in a patient hyperstimulated by gonadotropin therapy for in vitro fertilization: a case report. J In Vitro Fert Embryo Transf. 1987 Apr;4(2):126-8.</citation>
    <PMID>3110335</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Atlas M, Menczer J. Massive hyperstimulation and borderline carcinoma of the ovary. A possible association. Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand. 1982;61(3):261-3.</citation>
    <PMID>7124357</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 3, 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 21, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GONADOTROPIN</keyword>
  <keyword>CLOMIPHENE</keyword>
  <keyword>Ovulation-Stimulating Drugs</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infertility</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thyroid Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

