<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00343395</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>128-013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00343395</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rosiglitazone and Metformin: Outcomes Trial in Nondiabetic Patients With Stable Coronary Syndromes (Romance) Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-Center, Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trial of Combined Rosiglitazone/Metformin (Avandamet®) vs. Placebo on Serological Outcomes in Non-Diabetic Patients With Stable Coronary Syndromes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Intermountain Health Care, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Intermountain Health Care, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Nearly half of all Americans will die from cardiovascular disease caused by the build up of
      atherosclerotic plaque within coronary arteries. Most deaths in these patients arise from the
      development of acute coronary syndromes (ACS) such as myocardial infarction, unstable angina,
      or sudden death. ACS is characterized by coronary plaque erosion or rupture, which is
      triggered by endothelial changes, including inflammation, and thrombosis. Diabetes, with
      insulin resistance as a major component, has been shown to engender adverse metabolic events
      within the endothelial cell [1], including impaired endothelial function, augmented
      vasoconstriction, increased inflammation and thrombosis. Activation of the transcription
      factors nuclear factor KB (NF-KB) and activator protein 1 (AP-1) induces inflammatory gene
      expression, with liberation of leukocyte-attracting chemokines, increased production of
      inflammatory cytokines, and augmented expression of cellular adhesion molecules. These
      metabolic processes may therefore play a significant role in the development of ACS.The
      hypothesis is that rosiglitazone and metformin, or the combination of both may provide
      positive anti-atherogenic effect, even among patients without diabetes. This pilot study
      proposes to evaluate the effect of placebo vs. combined rosiglitazone/metformin (Avandamet®)
      on surrogate blood markers of atherosclerosis activity among non-diabetic and pre-diabetic
      patients with known stable coronary syndromes. This will provide further evidence justifying
      a large definitive outcomes-based clinical trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-center, randomized, double-blind trial comparing combined
      rosiglitazone/metformin (Avandametä) to placebo in subjects with normal or intermediate
      fasting glucose (IFG) and stable coronary artery disease.Subjects meeting entry criteria will
      be randomized in a 1:1 ratio to receive either placebo or combined rosiglitazone/metformin
      (Avandametä) 4/1000 mg. Laboratory specimens including high sensitivity C-reactive protein
      (hs-CRP), glucose, HgbA1C, complete lipid profile, will be obtained after a 10 hour fast as
      specified by study visits. Subjects will return for repeat study visits at 2, 4, 6 and 8
      months for repeat laboratory evaluations, including safety labs consisting of serum
      creatinine, liver enzymes, and a CBC. Additionally, subjects will have IL-6 and TNF-a
      measured for research purposes at baseline and subsequent follow-up visits. All subjects will
      be followed for a minimum of 8 months. This pilot study proposes to evaluate the effect of
      placebo, or combined rosiglitazone/metformin onsurrogate blood markers of atherosclerosis
      activity among non-diabetic and pre-diabetic patients with known stable coronary syndromes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    FDA concerns regarding Avandamet
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>June 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate the effect (change from baseline) of each study intervention on hs-C-reactive protein.</measure>
    <time_frame>Study completion</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate the safety of the interventions on clinical outcomes (death, MI, cardiovascular hospitalizations) and serious drug-related adverse events.</measure>
    <time_frame>Study completion</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate the effect (change from baseline) of each study intervention on lipid levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Study completion</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate the effect (change from baseline) of each study intervention on inflammatory marker levels other than hs-CRP</measure>
    <time_frame>Study completion</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate the effect (change from baseline) of each study intervention on HgbA1C</measure>
    <time_frame>Study completion</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To demonstrate the effect (change from baseline) of each study intervention on fasting blood glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>Study completion</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety: Differences in adverse events between the two arms</measure>
    <time_frame>Interim; completion of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Avandamet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>AVANDAMET 2/500 mg</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AVANDAMET</intervention_name>
    <description>2/500 mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Avandamet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The patient (male or non-pregnant female) must be &gt; 18 years of age.

          -  The patient or legally authorized representative must sign a written informed consent,
             prior to the procedure, using a form that is approved by the local Institutional
             Review Board.

          -  Angiographically documented coronary artery disease defined as the presence of at
             least one 50% or greater stenosis of a major coronary artery.

          -  Stabilized post any prior ACS event (i.e., without ongoing ischemic rest pain,
             congestive heart failure, or malignant arrhythmias) for at least 3 months

          -  Fasting blood glucose 87-125 mg/dL

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt;18 years

          -  Known hypersensitivity to metformin or rosiglitazone

          -  Renal insufficiency defined as calculated creatinine clearance (CrCl) &lt;40 mL/min using
             the following formula:

        Men: CrCL (mL/min) = Weight (kg) x (140-age) 72 x serum creatinine (mg/dL) Women: 0.85 x
        the value calculated for men

          -  Pregnant and/or lactating women, and women of child bearing potential are excluded
             from this trial

          -  Co-morbidity such that the patient is not expected to survive &gt;2 years

          -  Current therapy with rosiglitazone or metformin

          -  PCI within the previous six months (other than for the qualifying event)

          -  Prior CABG within the previous two months, scheduled CABG, or a decision to perform
             CABG made prior to enrollment

          -  Overt diabetes mellitus (FBG&gt;126 or antidiabetic therapy)

          -  Any diagnosis of congestive heart failure

          -  Obstructive hepatobiliary disease or other significant hepatic disease (defined as the
             presence of at least one of the following: AST, ALT, GGT, total bilirubin, or alkaline
             phosphatase &gt;3x upper limit normal, not related to MI

          -  Participation in any other clinical trials involving investigational or marketed
             products within 30 days prior to entry in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph B Muhlestein, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Intermountain Healthcare, LDS Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Intermountain Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Murray</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 21, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 21, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 23, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 15, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 15, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 17, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>J. Brent Muhlestein, MD</name_title>
    <organization>Intermountain Healthcare</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>rosiglitazone</keyword>
  <keyword>metformin</keyword>
  <keyword>hs-CRP</keyword>
  <keyword>inflammation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rosiglitazone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

