<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01908530</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13SM0639</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01908530</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Assessment of a Novel Microprobe Array Continuous Glucose Monitor for Type 1 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Assessment of a Novel Microprobe Array Continuous Glucose Monitor for Type 1 Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Imperial College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Imperial College London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to assess the safety and efficacy of the Imperial College
      Microprobe Array Continuous Glucose Sensor in healthy volunteers and in subjects with type 1
      diabetes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Continuous knowledge of ambient glucose levels will be of benefit to patients with T1DM,
      especially those with troublesome hypoglycaemia. Existing monitors require skin puncture to
      access interstitial fluid and sense its glucose content. Despite their clinical benefits,
      their use is associated with discomfort and their accuracy is questionable in hypoglycaemia.
      The development of a painless continuous glucose monitor is regarded as the top research
      priority by patients with diabetes. A novel continuous glucose monitoring device has been
      developed at Imperial College based on microprobe technology. It consists of a small,
      wearable patch (~1 cm2), the size of a conventional postage stamp, containing microscopic
      projections (microprobes) that penetrate only the outermost skin layer. It accesses
      interstitial fluid to sense its glucose content without stimulating skin nerve fibres or
      reaching blood vessels within skin layers. The microprobe surface has the consistency of
      sandpaper. It is pushed into the skin with an applicator allowing it to penetrate through the
      skin layers and access the interstitial fluid in a minimally invasive manner. The device is
      disposable and optimum performance will be assessed over five days. The advantages of
      microprobe technology have been demonstrated in other clinical situations and include
      painless insertion, absence of bleeding and a low infection risk. The large surface area
      utilised in our microprobe device has the potential to improve device sensitivity and
      accuracy. Pre-clinical validation tests have demonstrated the ability of the device to
      respond accurately to variable glucose concentrations and to penetrate the outermost skin
      layer without fracture. We aim now to further develop the device through clinical studies in
      non-diabetic subjects and subjects with type 1 diabetes to allow painless accurate continuous
      glucose monitoring.

      The study will recruit 16 non-diabetic subjects and 20 subjects with type 1 diabetes.

      It will be conducted over four phases;

      oPhase 1 will assess safety, as a primary outcome, and efficacy, as a secondary outcome, in
      non-diabetic subjects over six hours in the clinical research facility where the device will
      be fitted and a cannula inserted for venous sampling every 15 minutes to measure venous blood
      glucose (YSI). Safety will be assessed with regards to skin inflammation and pain. Efficacy
      will be assessed in this phase by assessing magnitude of current measured by the microprobe
      array sensor and comparison of measured ISF glucose concentrations to simultaneous venous
      blood glucose samples (YSI).

      oPhase 2 will also assess safety, as a primary outcome, and efficacy, as a secondary outcome,
      in non-diabetic subjects over a period of 24 hours. The first six hours in the clinical
      research facility (same as phase 1), then subject will be allowed to go home with the device
      to assess safety over that period.

      oPhase 3 aims to assess efficacy of the device as a primary outcome and safety as a secondary
      outcome. This will be in subjects with type 1 diabetes over 24 hours as inpatients. Efficacy
      will be assessed mechanically (by the ability to penetrate the stratum corneum) and
      functionally (by the ability to accurately sense ISF glucose). The derived ISF glucose levels
      will be compared with simultaneous venous glucose samples (YSI) and with a commercially
      available CGM device (iPro2, Medtronic). Assessment of microprobe penetration of the stratum
      corneum will be performed using confocal microscopy, optical coherence tomography and in skin
      biopsies.

      oPhase 4 aims to assess efficacy of the device as a primary outcome and safety as a secondary
      outcome. This will be in subjects with type 1 diabetes over 5 days in ambulatory situation.
      Efficacy will be assessed by comparing microprobe sensor derived ISF glucose levels against
      ISF glucose levels measured using a commercially available CGM device (iPro2, Medtronic).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Skin inflammation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Phases 1 &amp; 2 of the study aims to assess safety of the use of microprobe array continuous glucose sensor with regards to skin inflammation. This will be in healthy volunteers over 6 hours initially (phase 1) then over 24 hours (phase 2). This is a secondary outcome for phases 3 and 4.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation with venous blood glucose &amp; ISF glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Phases 3 &amp; 4 of the study aim to assess efficacy of the device in people with type 1 diabetes. This will be done in comparison to venous blood glucose and ISF glucose (using Medtronic iPro2 CGM system, Northridge, California) in a controlled environment over 24 hours (phase 3) then compared to ISF glucose in ambulatory situation over five days (phase 4).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The study aims to assess safety of the device with regards to pain degree in comparison to venflon insertion and insertion of an existing continuous glucose monitor (Medtronic iPro2 CGM system, Northridge, California). This will be done at each phase of the four study phases.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Skin Penetration</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>This will be done using Optical Coherence Tomography and Confocal Microscopy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Detectable signal</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>This is a secondary outcome for phases 1 &amp; 2.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation with venous blood glucose</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>This is a secondary outcome for phases 1 and 2. It is a primary outcome for phase 3.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Magnitude of current</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clarke error grid</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>This is a secondary outcome for phases 3 and 4.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Microprobe Glucose Sensor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The microprobe array continuous glucose sensor will be applied to healthy volunteers (in phases 1 and 2) and then to participants with type 1 diabetes (in phases 3 and 4).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Microprobe glucose sensor</intervention_name>
    <description>Assessment of safety and accuracy of a novel continuous glucose monitor based on microprobe technology.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Microprobe Glucose Sensor</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Microprobe Array Continuous Glucose Monitor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        For phases 1 and 2:

        Inclusion Criteria:

        • Adults over 18 years of age

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of upper limb neuropathy or radiculopathy

          -  History of pre-existing skin condition

          -  Pregnant or planning pregnancy in next 12 months

          -  Breastfeeding

          -  Enrolled in other clinical trials

          -  uncontrolled concurrent illness

          -  Have active malignancy or under investigation for malignancy

        For phases 3 and 4:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults over 18 years of age.

          -  Diagnosed with Type 1 diabetes for greater than 1 year.

          -  HbA1c less than or equal to 9.0 % (75 mmol/mol).

          -  Registered with a General Practitioner.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  History of diabetic dermopathy or pre-existing skin condition

          -  History of upper limb neuropathy or radiculopathy

          -  Pregnant or planning pregnancy in next 12 months

          -  Breastfeeding

          -  Enrolled in other clinical trials

          -  uncontrolled concurrent illness

          -  physical or visual impairment preventing sensor's use

          -  Have active malignancy or under investigation for malignancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Desmond Johnston, PhD, FRCP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Professor of Diabetes &amp; Endocrinology - Imperial College London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Imperial College London</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>W2 1PG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>El-Laboudi A, Oliver NS, Cass A, Johnston D. Use of microneedle array devices for continuous glucose monitoring: a review. Diabetes Technol Ther. 2013 Jan;15(1):101-15. doi: 10.1089/dia.2012.0188. Epub 2012 Dec 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23234256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pickup JC, Freeman SC, Sutton AJ. Glycaemic control in type 1 diabetes during real time continuous glucose monitoring compared with self monitoring of blood glucose: meta-analysis of randomised controlled trials using individual patient data. BMJ. 2011 Jul 7;343:d3805. doi: 10.1136/bmj.d3805.</citation>
    <PMID>21737469</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Battelino T, Phillip M, Bratina N, Nimri R, Oskarsson P, Bolinder J. Effect of continuous glucose monitoring on hypoglycemia in type 1 diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2011 Apr;34(4):795-800. doi: 10.2337/dc10-1989. Epub 2011 Feb 19.</citation>
    <PMID>21335621</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khanna P, Strom JA, Malone JI, Bhansali S. Microneedle-based automated therapy for diabetes mellitus. J Diabetes Sci Technol. 2008 Nov;2(6):1122-9.</citation>
    <PMID>19885301</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Juvenile Diabetes Research Foundation Continuous Glucose Monitoring Study Group, Tamborlane WV, Beck RW, Bode BW, Buckingham B, Chase HP, Clemons R, Fiallo-Scharer R, Fox LA, Gilliam LK, Hirsch IB, Huang ES, Kollman C, Kowalski AJ, Laffel L, Lawrence JM, Lee J, Mauras N, O'Grady M, Ruedy KJ, Tansey M, Tsalikian E, Weinzimer S, Wilson DM, Wolpert H, Wysocki T, Xing D. Continuous glucose monitoring and intensive treatment of type 1 diabetes. N Engl J Med. 2008 Oct 2;359(14):1464-76. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0805017. Epub 2008 Sep 8.</citation>
    <PMID>18779236</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 23, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 23, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 25, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes,Continuous Glucose Monitoring,Microprobes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

