<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01905800</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013/980</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01905800</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BPPV Treatment in Biaxial Rotational Chair</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Multicenter Study of Benign Paroxysmal Positional Vertigo Treatment in Biaxial Rotational Chair</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Haukeland University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Haukeland University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Benign paroxysmal positional vertigo (BPPV) represents the most common cause of labyrinthine
      vertigo with a lifetime prevalence of 2.4 percent. Onset is most common between the fifth and
      seventh decades of life. The disease can be a major handicap for the affected patient, and
      causes a great expense for society. The traditional manual treatment with repositioning
      maneuvers has greatly improved the possibilities for treatment of BPPV the last decade.
      However some patients are still difficult to diagnose and treat, and there are some who for
      health reasons cannot undergo traditional manual treatment. In this perspective there is a
      demand for a reliable, effective and precise method to treat all semicircular canals for the
      differentiated patient groups, and the techniques are under continuous development.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There has been extended research to improve the techniques and develop better and more
      reliable methods for diagnosing and treating BPPV efficiently. An important part in this
      technique evolution is the development of biaxial rotational chairs that can treat the
      patients regardless of other health problems.

      Mechanical assistance chairs have been designed to diagnose, differentiate and treat more
      precisely all forms of positional vertigo. The patient is strapped to a chair and fitted with
      infrared video goggles which identify and quantify the nystagmus in different positions. Dr.
      John M. Epley developed the Epley Omniax System, an automated, power driven, multi axial
      patient positioning device that can move the patient into any position to treat the affected
      canal. This chair is electronically managed. Another mechanical assistance chair, the TRV
      chair, developed by Thomas Richard-Vitton in Marseille France, became commercially available
      in 2005. This chair has a vertical and a horizontal axis of rotation and is lockable in
      preset positions. It is manually handled and can swivel between two axes in all planes of the
      semicircular canals for up to 360 degrees or more. Velocity of rotation can be regulated
      freely.

      The TRV chair is used by 34 centers worldwide today. Bergen (Norway) was the first place in
      North-Europe to acquire this chair, and have used it since December 2009. In 2013
      Rigshospitalet Denmark started using the TRV chair as well and Oslo University Hospital
      Rikshospitalet, will have their chair in 2013. The TRV chair opens for treatment that
      previously was not possible.

      The aim of this study is to:

        -  Evaluate the presence of positional nystagmus in the normal population

        -  Evaluate the efficacy of D-BBC treatment compared to S-BBC for treatment of lateral
           canal BPPV in TRV chair

        -  Examine the serum level of vitamin D in BPPV patients

        -  Give a detailed description of the method.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment of lateral semicircular BPPV, a randomized study comparing dynamic &quot;barbecue&quot; (D-BBC) (rotation about a horizontal axis from head to feet from a supine position) to stepwise barbecue (S-BBC) treatment in a biaxial rotational chair.</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
    <description>The patients will fill in questionnaires: SF-36, VSS, VAS, Pain chart and DHI before being treated, DHI, VSS and VAS, one week after last treatment, and at the final evaluation three months after last treatment.
Dynamic/static posturography platform tests will be performed before treatment, one week after last treatment and at end evaluation three months after last treatment.
Diagnostic and treatment maneuvers will be made with a TRV chair (SYNAPSYS, TRV chair) and positional nystagmus will be analyzed with videonystagmoscopic examination and videonystagmography recording,(SYNAPSYS, model Ulmer VNG) by at least two independent doctors before treatment, one week after last treatment and at end evaluation three months after last treatment.
Vitamin D status will be checked. Clinical endpoint will be evaluation of treatment efficacy with acceleration and without acceleration in a TRV chair.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence and treatment of BPPV in a biaxial rotational chair (TRV chair).</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
    <description>Outcome measure will be the same as described in primary outcome measure, but treatment will be for patients with anterior, posterior and horizontal BPPV.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of positional nystagmus in a normal population.</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
    <description>We will record and analyze the positioning nystagmic features in a normal population.
Dynamic/static posturography platform tests will be performed Diagnostic maneuvers will be made with a mechanical assistance TRV chair (SYNAPSYS, TRV chair) and positional nystagmus will be analyzed with videonystagmoscopic examination and videonystagmography recording,(SYNAPSYS, model Ulmer VNG) by at least two independent doctors.
Vitamin D status will be checked.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">170</enrollment>
  <condition>Benign Paroxysmal Positional Vertigo</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nystagmus in normal population</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Investigate positional nystagmus in normal population using a biaxial rotational chair.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BPPV treatment in TRV chair</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BPPV treatment in Biaxial rotational chair, describe and measure efficacy of treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Barbecue treatment without acceleration</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment of horizontal BPPV with adapted maneuvers using a biaxial rotational chair and infrared videoscopy goggle. The patient is positioned in supine position and rotated 30 degrees stepwise towards the unaffected ear, thus applying an overall 360 degrees rotation. The patient remains in each position for 30 seconds</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Barbecue treatment with acceleartion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment of horizontal BPPV with adapted maneuvers using a biaxial rotational chair and infrared videoscopy goggle. The patient starts in supine position and will be rotated about a horizontal axis from head to feet. The patient will be rotated 360 degrees with a succession of eight fast rounds in the axial plane towards the unaffected side.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biaxial rotational chair</intervention_name>
    <description>This chair has a vertical and a horizontal axis of rotation and is lockable in preset positions. It is manually handled and can swivel between two axes in all planes of the semicircular canals for up to 360 degrees or more. Velocity of rotation can be regulated freely.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nystagmus in normal population</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BPPV treatment in TRV chair</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Barbecue treatment without acceleration</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Barbecue treatment with acceleartion</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TRV chair</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  subjects over 18 years with benign paroxysmal positional vertigo(BPPV)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  BPPV previously treated with reposition maneuvers within the last 12 months.

          -  Cochlear Implant (CI).

          -  Asymmetrical hearing loss.

          -  Unusual headache.

          -  Neurological disease.

          -  Inner ear disease other than BPPV.

          -  Semicircular canal paresis.

          -  Drug that causes dizziness/nystagmus.

          -  Chemotherapy.

          -  Hospital admission due to head trauma within the last 12 months.

          -  Closeness to study group.

          -  Downbeating nystagmus or upbeating nystagmus without torsional component.

          -  Extensive spontaneous nystagmus that complicates gait interpretation.

          -  Cannot tolerate both treatments.

          -  Pregnancy.

          -  Bilateral affection of the semicircular canals.

          -  More than two semicircular canals affected on one side.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Camilla Martens, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Haukeland University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stein Helge Nordahl Glad</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Haukeland University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Haukeland University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bergen</city>
        <zip>5021</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 15, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 18, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 23, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Haukeland University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Camilla Martens</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Cand.med</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vertigo and dizziness.</keyword>
  <keyword>semicircular canals</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vertigo</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dizziness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Benign Paroxysmal Positional Vertigo</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We do not plan to make individual participant data (IPD) available</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

