<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01901705</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DMR101-IRB1-261</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>DMR101-IRB1-261</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01901705</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Topical Indigo Naturalis Treatment in Patients With Mild to Moderate Plaque-type Psoriasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study of Topical Indigo Naturalis Treatment in Patients With Mild to Moderate Plaque-type Psoriasis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>China Medical University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>China Medical University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Psoriasis is a common, chronic skin disease for which only remissive, as opposed to curative,
      treatments are available. Traditional Chinese medicine is one of the most frequently chosen
      alternative therapies in China and Taiwan, and psoriasis has been treated for centuries with
      topical and oral herbal preparations. Topical indigo naturalis ointment has been reported to
      exhibit potential anti-psoriatic efficacy. The study objective is to investigate
      pharmacological effect and explore targeting mechanisms of Traditional Chinese Medicine (TCM)
      Indigo Naturalis topical ointment as a single treatment agent in Chinese subjects with mild
      to moderate plaque-type Psoriasis.

      This was a single site, randomized, double-blinded, placebo controlled study of topical
      indigo naturalis vs. vehicle alone (placebo) to treat mild to moderate plaque-type psoriasis
      during an 8-week period. Pharmacological effect will be evaluated by biomarker evaluation and
      clinical evaluation. The trial was conducted at the China Medical University Hospital (CMUH),
      Taichung, Taiwan. All patients provided written informed consent before inclusion in the
      study. The study protocol was approved by the institutional review board (IRB) of CMUH.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Estimated enrollment:

      Total of 24 subjects:

      mild to moderate psoriasis patients will be randomized into treatment group (n=16) placebo
      group (n=8)

      Study evaluation:

      A baseline and end of the study evaluation on the patients will be performed, including
      physical examination, hemogram and blood biochemical analysis (including glutamic-oxaloacetic
      transaminase, glutamic-pyruvic transaminase, and creatinine measurement). The baseline and
      end of the study of total body surface area involvement and Psoriasis Area Severity Index
      (PASI), PGA, OTPSS scores will be also calculated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in Overall Target Plaque Severity Score at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>OTPSS(Overall Target Plaque Severity Score ) Score Description 0 No evidence of disease (except possible residual discoloration)
Mild overall plaque elevation, scaling and/or erythema of the target plaque
Moderate overall plaque elevation, scaling and/or erythema of the target plaque
Severe overall plaque elevation, scaling and/or erythema of the target plaque
Very severe overall plaque elevation, scaling and/or erythema of the target plaque *Grades 1, 3, 5 &amp; 7 are midpoints between the defined grades 0, 2, 4, 6 &amp; 8</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Psoriasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Indigo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Indigo naturalis ointment will be provided and patients are instructed to use it twice daily for 8 weeks or achieve completely skin clearing whichever comes first.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Placebo will be provided and patients are instructed to use it twice daily for 8 weeks or achieve completely skin clearing whichever comes first.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Indigo naturalis ointment</intervention_name>
    <description>The Indigo naturalis ointment was composed of a 1:10 mixture of Indigo naturalis powder and a vehicle consisting of Vaseline: microcrystalline wax: olive oil (5:6:9 ratio)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Indigo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>The placebo was a mixture of blue dye powder (54.8% Indigo carmine aluminum lake [Blue #32] and 45.2% Allura Red AC aluminum lake [Red #40] powders), Vaseline, microcrystalline wax, and olive oil.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  men or women at ages between 20 - 65 years old with at least 6 months diagnosis of
             moderate to mild plaque-type psoriasis who have a screening and at time of study agent
             treatment Psoriasis Global Assessment (PGA)=2-3, and have under 20% of their total
             body surface area (BSA) involved. , with a target plaque for at least 4 sq cm

          -  In good general health, as evidenced by physical examination, and hematology and blood
             chemistry tests within normal ranges with the exception of liver function test value
             &lt;=1.5ULN

          -  If of childbearing age, agreement to continue using birth control measures for the
             duration of the study

          -  Patients who agreed to participate and signed the consent form

          -  Patients who agreed to return for follow-up visits and provide all required biopsies.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently have non-plaque forms of psoriasis (e.g., erythrodermic, guttate, or
             pustular psoriasis), or rebound or flare of chronic plaque psoriasis

          -  Currently or had history of psoriatic arthritis

          -  Have current drug-induced psoriasis (e.g., a new onset of psoriasis or an exacerbation
             of psoriasis from beta blockers, calcium channel blockers, or lithium).

          -  Are pregnant, nursing, or planning pregnancy (both men and women) while enrolled in
             the study.

          -  Have used any biologic within the previous 3 months or 5 times the half-life of the
             biologic, whichever is longer

          -  Have received phototherapy or any systemic treatment that could affect psoriasis
             (including, but not limited to, (eg, retinoids, methotrexate, cyclosporine, psoralens,
             sulfasalazine, hydroxyurea, fumaric acid derivatives, herbal treatment or traditional
             Chinese medicine) within 4 weeks of receiving study treatment

          -  Have used topical treatment that could affect psoriasis (eg. corticosteroid
             tazarotene, and tacrolimus, tar, anthralin, calcipotriene, topical vitamin D
             derivatives, retinoids, tazarotene, methoxsalen, trimethylpsoralens, topical
             traditional Chinese medicines) within 2 weeks of receiving study treatment

          -  Have used any systemic immunosuppressants (eg, MTX, azathioprine, cyclosporine,
             6-thioguanine, mercaptopurine, mycophenolate mofetil, hydroxyurea, and tacrolimus)
             within 4 weeks of receiving study treatment

          -  Are currently receiving lithium, antimalarials, or intramuscular gold, or have
             received lithium, antimalarials, or intramuscular gold within 4 weeks of receiving
             study treatment

          -  Positive screening tests for HIV, hepatitis B surface antigen, or hepatitis C antibody

          -  A history of alcohol or other drug abuse

          -  Clinically significant laboratory abnormality in blood, renal function, or liver
             function

          -  A history of sensitivity to Chinese herbs, olive oil, yellow wax, or petroleum jelly

          -  Have current signs or symptoms of severe, progressive, or uncontrolled renal, hepatic,
             hematological, gastrointestinal, endocrine, pulmonary, cardiac, neurologic, cerebral,
             or psychiatric disease

          -  Be participating in another trial using an investigational agent or procedure.

          -  Any other conditions that in the view of investigator, the subject should not be
             enrolled.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hui man cheng</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>China Medical University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>China Medical University Hospital,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taichung,</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 9, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 17, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Psoriasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Indigo Naturalis</keyword>
  <keyword>chinese medicine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

