<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01901276</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAL3307</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01901276</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Gastric Acid on Colonic Microbiome</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Gastric Acid Suppression on the Colonic Microbiome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Daniel Freedberg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The colonic microbiome is essential in human health and disease. Clostridium
      difficile-associated diarrhea (CDAD), a highly morbid form of infectious diarrhea, is caused
      by antibiotics which perturb the microbiome and allow C. difficile to proliferate. Proton
      pump inhibitors (PPIs) are powerful suppressors of gastric acid and among the most common
      medicines in the United States. Dozens of observational studies show that longterm PPI use is
      associated with CDAD. However, the mechanism by which PPIs cause CDAD is unknown. We believe
      that PPIs cause CDAD by inducing alterations in the human colonic microbiome. We will confirm
      or refute the hypothesized mechanism for the association between PPIs and CDAD using an
      unblinded, single-armed study design. We will use pyrosequencing of the hypervariable V4
      region of the bacterial 16S ribosomal subunit gene in human fecal samples to describe the
      colonic flora. We will collect fecal samples from volunteers before and after PPIs given for
      different durations and test the microbiome to determine 1) whether PPIs diminish overall
      diversity, 2) whether PPIs diminish relative abundance of Bacteroidetes, 3) whether increased
      duration of PPIs affects diversity, and 4) whether there is recovery of diversity after
      completing a defined course of PPIs. We believe that PPIs will cause a pattern of diminished
      overall microbiome diversity and reduced anaerobes — the same pattern seen after use of
      antibiotics. Furthermore, we believe that increased PPI duration will further diminish
      diversity and that the microbiome will return to pre-PPI levels of diversity after PPIs are
      stopped. These results will facilitate biologically-based clinical interventions to reduce
      rates of CDAD among patients who require acid suppression.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Design We will recruit 12 adult volunteers for a crossover study with a total duration
      of 12 weeks. Subjects will be observed off of PPIs for 4 weeks and then will be placed on
      PPIs for 4 weeks. Subsequently, subjects will be randomized to receive an additional 4 weeks
      of PPIs or no therapy. Stool samples will be collected at 4 separate time points.

      Study Outcomes and Statistical Analyses The primary outcome will be change in overall
      diversity of fecal flora after 4 weeks of PPIs compared to 4 weeks of no acid suppression.
      Additional outcomes to be assessed include the effect of PPIs on the relative abundance of
      Bacteroidetes at week 4 and change in the diversity of fecal flora at week 8.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Microbiome diversity</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>In order to assess the diversity of the colonic microbiome, three Bray-Curtis indices will be calculated for each subject:
After four weeks of no acid suppression (Week 0 vs. Week -4)
After four weeks of twice daily PPI (Week 4 vs. Week 0)
After 8 weeks of twice daily PPI or four weeks of &quot;washout&quot; (Week 8 vs. Week 4)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Clostridium Difficile</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Omeprazole 40 mg bid x 4-8 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>See study description for further details.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Omeprazole 40 mg bid</intervention_name>
    <description>As above.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Omeprazole 40 mg bid x 4-8 weeks</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Brand name: Prilosec</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 or more years old

          -  Able to give informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of systemic antibiotics within the past year

          -  Use of acid suppression medications (PPIs or H2-receptor antagonists) within the past
             year (antacids permitted if more than one month from date of enrollment)

          -  History of chronic gastrointestinal mucosal disease (e.g. inflammatory bowel disease,
             celiac disease, microscopic colitis)

          -  Any clinically significant or uncontrolled major morbidity, including but not limited
             to serious cardiac or respiratory disease or uncontrolled HIV

          -  Abnormal bowel frequency (minimum once every 2 days, maximum 3 times per day)

          -  Use of clopidogrel or medications with potential significant interaction with PPIs

          -  Osteoperosis or history of non-traumatic bone fracture

          -  History of adverse reactions to PPIs

          -  Initiation of any new medication within the month prior to enrollment

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Inability to give informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julian A Abrams, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 15, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 17, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 13, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 13, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniel Freedberg</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Proton Pump Inhibitors</keyword>
  <keyword>Microbiome</keyword>
  <keyword>Clostridium difficile</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Omeprazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>July 25, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>September 8, 2016</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

