<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00742365</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HP-00043574</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R34MH073797</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>DSIR 83-ATSO</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>H-28845</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00742365</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Predicting Effectiveness of Light Treatment for Winter Seasonal Affective Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>Predicting Light Treatment's Effectiveness on Reducing Depression and Cardiovascular Risk in Seasonal Affective Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Maryland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Maryland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate a possible tool for predicting future effectiveness of bright light
      in treating seasonal affective disorder, winter subtype, and will examine secondary effects
      of bright light on cardiovascular risk factors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The winter subtype of seasonal affective disorder (SAD) is characterized by episodes of major
      depression in the fall and winter, with remission of these episodes in the spring and summer.
      SAD disrupts the lives of millions of Americans, who experience symptoms such as restless
      agitation, increased appetite and weight gain, and reduced energy and motivation. Bright
      light treatment, while shown to be effective in improving SAD in 75% of cases, only causes a
      full remission in 50% of cases. If doctors had a diagnostic tool to determine which patients
      would respond to bright light therapy, they could make better decisions about whether to
      prescribe bright light as treatment. This study will examine a possible diagnostic tool—a
      single, 1-hour bright light session—for predicting improvement in SAD symptoms over an
      extended course of bright light treatment. Additionally, because many symptoms of SAD (like
      weight gain and sedentary lifestyle) correspond to cardiovascular risk, this study will
      examine whether bright light treatment correlates with improved cardiovascular health.

      Participants with SAD will be randomly assigned to first receive a 1-hour session of either
      bright light or the placebo, red light. Then all participants will switch and receive a
      1-hour session of the other type of light. Red light has been accepted as a placebo in
      previous SAD studies because it does not suppress melatonin or shift circadian rhythms.
      Before and after each light session, participants will have their SAD symptoms evaluated in a
      clinical interview and self-report measure. After these two light sessions, all participants
      will receive instructions for administering bright light treatment on their own at home. For
      the next 6 weeks, participants will administer the bright light to themselves for 1 hour
      every morning. Every week they will undergo clinical interviews by phone and will mail in
      self-report measures, some completed daily and some weekly, to the researchers. The
      participants will have checkups and interviews in person on Weeks 4 and 6. At the two time
      periods, SAD symptoms and indicators of cardiovascular risk, such as appetite and sleep loss,
      will be evaluated. The participant responses to bright light and red light at the initial
      session will be compared with the participant responses to the subsequent 6-week treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hamilton rating scale for depressional seasonal affective disorder (SIGH SAD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline, 1 hour after light treatment, and weekly for 6 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hunger questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured daily for 6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Three factor eating questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured weekly for 6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep log</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured weekly for 6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food craving questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured daily for 6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Side effects questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured weekly for 6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured weekly for 6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Profile of Mood States</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline, 1 hour after light treatment, and weekly for 6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Depression Inventory-II (BDI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline, 1 hour after light treatment, and weekly for 6 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">41</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants will be given a 1-hour lab test of bright light treatment, then the bright light treatment for 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants will be given a 1-hour treatment of the red light placebo, then the bright light treatment for 6 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bright light</intervention_name>
    <description>One hour of exposure to bright light daily upon awakening for 6 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Brite light III light box (Apollo) 10,000 lux.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Red light placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>One hour of exposure to red light.</description>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dim red light box (Apollo) 50 lux.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with history of recurrent winter depression
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Current major depressive disorder, by structured diagnostic interview (SCID), or
             current bipolar II disorder, if no prior history of rapid cycling, by SCID

          -  Prior history of major depressive disorder or bipolar II disorder with seasonal
             specifier, by SCID

          -  Score of 21 or greater on Hamilton Rating Scale for Depression - Seasonal Affective
             Disorder Version (SIGH-SAD), met at three time points (informed consent session, 24
             hours prior to first light therapy session, and at first light therapy session)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current bipolar I disorder, psychotic disorder, or cognitive disorder, by SCID

          -  Illicit drug use in the past year, by self-report, or alcohol abuse by SCID

          -  History of systemic lupus erythematosus

          -  History of heart attack or stroke

          -  No antidepressant, mood stabilizer, or antipsychotic medication treatment 30 days
             before treatment

          -  Current occupation involves shift work

          -  Current sensitivity to bright light or vision problems not correctable by glasses, by
             self-report

          -  Inability to distinguish colors or see stars at night because of increased light
             sensitivity, by self-report

          -  Current suicidal ideation, by self-report during SCID interview

          -  Women of childbearing potential who are pregnant, nursing, or trying to become
             pregnant. Female participants of childbearing potential must agree to one of the
             following types of birth control: oral, transdermal, or implantable hormonal
             contraceptives; intrauterine device; diaphragm plus spermicide; or female condom plus
             spermicide.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Teodor T. Postolache, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Maryland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uzoma HN, Reeves GM, Langenberg P, Khabazghazvini B, Balis TG, Johnson MA, Sleemi A, Scrandis DA, Zimmerman SA, Vaswani D, Nijjar GV, Cabassa J, Lapidus M, Rohan KJ, Postolache TT. Light treatment for seasonal Winter depression in African-American vs Caucasian outpatients. World J Psychiatry. 2015 Mar 22;5(1):138-46. doi: 10.5498/wjp.v5.i1.138.</citation>
    <PMID>25815263</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reeves GM, Rohan KJ, Langenberg P, Snitker S, Postolache TT. Calibration of response and remission cut-points on the Beck Depression Inventory-Second Edition for monitoring seasonal affective disorder treatment outcomes. J Affect Disord. 2012 Apr;138(1-2):123-7. doi: 10.1016/j.jad.2011.12.003. Epub 2012 Jan 25.</citation>
    <PMID>22277151</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reeves GM, Nijjar GV, Langenberg P, Johnson MA, Khabazghazvini B, Sleemi A, Vaswani D, Lapidus M, Manalai P, Tariq M, Acharya M, Cabassa J, Snitker S, Postolache TT. Improvement in depression scores after 1 hour of light therapy treatment in patients with seasonal affective disorder. J Nerv Ment Dis. 2012 Jan;200(1):51-5. doi: 10.1097/NMD.0b013e31823e56ca.</citation>
    <PMID>22210362</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Virk G, Reeves G, Rosenthal NE, Sher L, Postolache TT. Short exposure to light treatment improves depression scores in patients with seasonal affective disorder: A brief report. Int J Disabil Hum Dev. 2009 Jul;8(3):283-286.</citation>
    <PMID>20686638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 25, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 25, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 27, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Maryland</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Teodor Postolache</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Seasonal Affective Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Light Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Seasonal Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychiatric Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Bright Light</keyword>
  <keyword>Major Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Bipolar Disorder</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mood Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Seasonal Affective Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

