<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00745680</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>200701057R</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00745680</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Speckle Tracking Imaging and Realtime 3 Dimensional Echocardiograhy to Study LV Function and Remodeling After Acute Myocardial Infarction (AMI)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Morphodynamic Study of Left Ventricular Remodeling With Possible Mechanisms for Pharmacologic Therapy: Assessment by Real-time 3-dimensional Echocardiography and 2-dimensional Speck Tracking Imaging.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Taiwan University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Taiwan University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Left ventricular (LV) remodeling after acute myocardial infarction (AMI) has been well
      described in previous studies. However, there is a paucity of data on the incidence of and
      risk factors for LV remodeling in modern clinical practice that incorporates widespread use
      of acute reperfusion strategies and almost systematic use of &quot;antiremodeling&quot; medications,
      such as angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitors and beta blockers. The recent improvements
      in AMI management do not abolish LV remodeling, which remains a relatively frequent event
      after an initial anterior wall AMI. As a leading cause of heart failure, postinfarction LV
      remodeling represents an important target for therapeutic interventions. Within the
      ventricular mass, size, shape, connections and orientation in a three-dimensional space of
      every single constituent determine its functional behavior. The complex architecture of the
      ventricular mass creates multiple inhomogeneities of electrical and mechanical loads at the
      cellular and the microscopic tissue level, that cause cardiac function to be 'stochastic in
      nature'. The myocardial infarction will altered the ventricular shape and functional
      inhomogeneities carrying the morphodynamic advantages such as impaired suction for diastole
      after diminishing recoil relaxation with decreased twisting strain in systole. The alteration
      in contractile mechanics interacts with the intraventricular fluid dynamic filed that
      influence the regional myocardial shearing stress. Altered LV transmural wall strains have
      been proposed to cause infarct extension and may have an important role in propagating LV
      remodeling.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We are currently witnessing the advent of new diagnostic tools and therapies for heart
      diseases, but,without serious scientific consensus on fundamental questions about normal and
      diseased heart structure and function. During the last decade, three successive,
      international, multidisciplinary symposia were organized in order to setup fundamental
      research principles, which would allow us to make a significant step forward in understanding
      heart structure and function. (Kocica MJ et al., 2006) Helical ventricular myocardial band
      (HVMB, Figure 2-1) of Torrent-Guasp is the revolutionary new concept in understanding global,
      three-dimensional, functional architecture of the ventricular myocardium. This concept
      defines the principal, cumulative vectors, integrating the tissue architecture (i.e. form)
      and net forces developed (i.e. function) within the ventricular mass. Helical ventricular
      myocardial band of Torrent-Guasp may also, hopefully, allow overcoming some difficulties
      encountered in contemporary efforts to create a comprehensive mathematical model of the
      heart.

      Within the ventricular mass, size, shape, connections and orientation in a three-dimensional
      space of every single constituent determine its functional behavior. This kind of spatial
      dependence allows the ventricular myocardial mass to be considered as the source of
      interdependent vectorial forces (i.e.

      electrical and mechanical), being generated on different length and time scales. The ultimate
      net result of these vectorial forces is to translate uniaxial sarcomere shortening into
      efficient three-dimensional deformation of the ventricular cavity. The complex architecture
      of the ventricular mass creates multiple inhomogeneities of electrical and mechanical loads
      at the cellular and the microscopic tissue level, that cause cardiac function to be
      'stochastic in nature'. However, at macroscopic (i.e. organ) level, these stochastic events
      become average and appear consistent with a continuous medium. This dialectic coexistence of
      complexity and simplicity, discreetness and continuity suggests the existence of certain
      rule-based assignment, which 'may be applied equally well to all the ventricular myocardial
      fibers', enabling the ventricular myocardial mass to assemble abundant, dynamic, stochastic
      vectorial forces and produce apparently smooth, averaged, continuous, global response.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>October 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2011</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Congestive Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Mitral Regurgitation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <description>A: AMI patient</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients after AMI
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Structurally normal mitral and aortic valve;

          -  Technically adequate color flow Doppler image;

          -  Technically adequate real-time 3D echocardiographic image of the LV chamber and the
             mitral apparatus (annulus and leaflets) to allow analysis of 3D geometry;

          -  Normal sinus rhythm.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Recurrent MI or coronary reintervention during the follow up period;

          -  Clinical or echocardiographic evidence of other cardiac diseases, such as organic
             valvular, pericardial, congenital, or infiltrative heart disease;

          -  Right ventricular alterations resulting in abnormal position or movement of the
             septum.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lung-chun Lin, Ph D</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>National Taiwan University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lung-Chun Lin, PhD.</last_name>
    <email>anniejou@ms28.hinet.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NTUH</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Fun-Yu Lin, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>23123456</phone>
      <phone_ext>5433</phone_ext>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 31, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 2, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 3, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 20, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 20, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 24, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Lung-Chun Lin</name_title>
    <organization>National Taiwan University Hospital</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Left ventricular remodeling, acute myocardial infarction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mitral Valve Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ventricular Remodeling</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

