<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00741741</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR015295</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00741741</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TMC278-TiDP15-C150: Trial to Examine Safety, Tolerability and Plasma Pharmacokinetics of Multiple Doses of TMC278LA.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I, Double Blind, Randomized, Placebo-controlled Trial to Examine the Safety, Tolerability and Plasma Pharmacokinetics of Multiple (Monthly) Intramuscular and Subcutaneous Doses of TMC278LA.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tibotec Pharmaceuticals, Ireland</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tibotec Pharmaceuticals, Ireland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is: to determine the safety, (local) tolerability and plasma
      exposure over time of single intramuscular (IM) doses of 600 and 1200 mg of a new formulation
      (F006) of TMC278LA, to determine the safety, (local) tolerability and long-term plasma
      exposure over time of 2 dose regimens of 4 monthly IM doses of a new formulation (F006) of
      TMC278LA., To determine the safety, (local) tolerability and long-term plasma exposure over
      time of 1 dose regimen of 4 monthly subcutaneous (SC) doses of a new formulation (F006) of
      TMC278LA.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1)-infected patients are routinely being treated
      with combinations of 3 or 4 drugs (highly active antiretroviral therapy [HAART]), including
      nucleoside/nucleotide analogue reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NRTIs/NtRTIs),
      non-nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NNRTIs), and protease inhibitors (PIs), to
      reduce the risk of viral resistance development. TMC278 is a new potent and selective NNRTI
      under development. It may be able to prevent replication of the virus and by consequence,
      prevent new HIV-1 infection. For this novel indication, a sustained release parenteral (IM =
      Intramuscular or SC = Subcutaneous) formulation, named TMC278LA, allowing sporadic dosing is
      under development. As a second perspective, the TMC278LA has been designed to cope, for
      therapeutic treatment in patients, with pill burden and the obligation of having
      uninterrupted NNRTI treatment at very regular time intervals, imposing considerable
      compliance constraints on HIV-infected patients. This formulation intends to improve the
      quality of life of the patient and the drug compliance of the NNRTI treatment. This is a
      randomized, double-blind (neither patient nor the physician know the name of the study drug),
      placebo-controlled clinical study to evaluate the safety, (local) tolerability and plasma
      pharmacokinetics of multiple doses of a novel formulation (nanosuspension) of TMC278LA,
      containing 300 mg of TMC278 per mL. A total of 30 healthy volunteers will be selected and
      equally divided into 3 panels. This study will be conducted in male or female volunteers. The
      clinical study may not necessarily be balanced regarding gender, but it is intended to aim at
      50% of each gender. For safety reasons, females must be post-menopausal or surgically
      sterile. The clinical study consists of 3 panels: Panel 1 (Multiple Dose 1 = MD1), Panel 2
      (Multiple Dose 2 = MD2) and Panel 3 (Multiple Dose 3 = MD3). MD1, MD2 and MD3 will receive a
      multiple dosing regimen of the new formulation of TMC278LA consisting of 4 successive IM
      doses (at a 1-month interval) in the Gluteus maximus (MD1 and MD2) or 4 successive SC doses
      (at a 1- month interval) in the periumbilical region (MD3). The first dose (the loading dose)
      is twice as high as the following 3 doses. Data collected after the first dose in each
      regimen will serve as a substitute for a single dose. The dosing regimens are:
      MD1=600/300/300/300 mg; MD2=1200/600/600/600 (IM) and MD3=1200/600/600/600 mg (SC). The study
      population will include a total of 30 healthy adult volunteers. Ten volunteers will be
      enrolled in MD1, MD2 and MD3 (6 on active, 2 on vehicle, 2 on saline). Each IM dose will be
      given at one Injection Site (IS) (in the Gluteus maximus muscle), except for the 1200 mg dose
      in MD2 for which 600 mg will be injected in each muscle (left and right Gluteus maximus
      muscle). Likewise, the SC doses will be given at one IS (periumbilical region), except for
      the 1200 mg loading dose for which 600 mg will be injected in two ISs on either site of the
      umbilicus. The new formulation has a concentration of 300 mg/mL of TMC278LA. Hence, the
      maximum volume to be injected per injection site is 2 mL. For the multiple injection panels,
      rotation of the injected site is recommended. The purpose of the dose sequence in all 3 MD
      panels is to provide a loading dose for the 300 mg (MD1) and 600 mg (MD2, 3) once monthly
      regimens. In pharmacokinetics, a loading dose refers to an initial higher dose of a drug that
      may be given at the beginning of a course of treatment before dropping down to a lower
      maintenance dose. A first safety review is planned after the first 3 patients and if no acute
      effects are observed, the following 3 patients will be dosed. A 2nd safety review is planned
      and if no acute effects are observed, the last 4 patients will be dosed. Within each Panel,
      the second dose will only be administered when the first dose was considered safe and well
      tolerated. The first dose of MD2 will start 1 month after start of MD1, when the first IM
      dose of MD1 has been evaluated in a Data Review Meeting (DRM), approximately 3 weeks after
      dosing, and is considered safe and well tolerated. Similarly, MD3 will start after the first
      dose in MD2 is considered safe and well tolerated during a DRM. An extra DRM will be planned
      approximately 3 weeks after the 4th dose of each panel, in order to evaluate the safety and
      (local) tolerability after 4 successive doses given at a 1-month interval. Dose Limiting
      Toxicities and stopping rules will guide decision making during the DRMs. At the DRMs, all
      safety, local tolerability, systemic tolerability and pharmacokinetic data collected till and
      including 2 weeks after dosing will be evaluated. Based on these data collected after the
      loading dose (1st dose), the investigator and the sponsor will decide whether it is safe to
      proceed to the next dose in a given panel. The next dose can be adjusted, if required, based
      on safety or pharmacokinetic data available at that time, but will not exceed 600 mg in MD1
      and 1200 mg in MD2 and MD3. Such a dose adjustment is applicable to all patients of that
      particular panel. Upon unblinding on Week 24, patients who were on placebo treatment are
      allowed to leave the study. In addition, patients who received active treatment and for which
      the TMC278 plasma concentration in the last sample taken prior to unblinding (= WK20) is
      below 20 ng/mL are allowed to leave the study as well, provided that there are no persistent
      AEs that require further follow-up. All patients on active treatment with TMC278 plasma
      concentrations above 20ng/mL in the last sample taken prior to unblinding, or patients with
      AEs that require further follow up will be followed up until plasma exposure of TMC278 is
      below 20 ng/mL or until pending adverse events are resolved or stabilized, respectively.
      Based on results of the TMC278-TiDP15-C146 clinical study, more than 90% of TMC278 is
      expected to be washed out within 20 weeks after the last dose. In case TMC278 exposure is
      still above 20 ng/mL at the WK 32 visit or in case of a persistent AE that needs further
      follow up, the follow up period will be extended until TMC278 plasma exposure is below 20
      ng/mL, or until the AE is resolved or stabilized. The decision to extent the follow-up period
      will be communicated to the respective subjects at WK33. These patients will be asked to
      visit the site once every 4 weeks in case of follow-up on TMC278 plasma exposures. Frequency
      of on-site follow-up on safety will be determined by the investigator on a case by case
      basis. In this Phase-I study in healthy volunteers no further treatment or medical care is
      planned after the end of the clinical study. There are 3 panels, and patients will be
      randomized to treatment with either TMC278LA (n=6), vehicle (n=2) or saline (n=2). The dosing
      regimens consist of 4 successive doses at a 1-month interval. Dosing regimens are MD1 =
      600/300/300/300 mg (IM), MD2 = 1200/600/600/600 mg (IM) and MD3 = 1200/600/600/600 mg (SC).
      Patients who received saline or vehicle, or who have TMC278 plasma exposures below 20 ng/ml,
      will leave the study at WK24. Other patients will continue till WK32 or beyond.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Strategic decision
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>July 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety, (local) tolerability and TMC278 PK of multiple doses of a novel formulation of TMC278LA throughout the study till WK24, WK28, WK32 or beyond WK32 (i.e. till TMC278 is below 20 ng/ml and till all AEs are resolved/stabilized)</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV-1</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TMC278</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients aged between 18 and 55 years, extremes included

          -  Non-smokers for at least 3 months prior to selection

          -  Normal weight as defined by a Body Mass Index (BMI: weight in kg divided by height in
             meters squared) of 18.0 to 30.0 kg/m2, extremes included

          -  Informed Consent Form signed voluntarily

          -  Able to comply with protocol requirements

          -  Normal 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) (in triplicate) at screening including: a)
             normal sinus rhythm (heart rate [HR] between 40 and 100 bpm), b) QTc interval &lt;= 450
             ms, c) QRS interval lower than 120 ms, d) PR interval &lt;= 220 ms

          -  Healthy on the basis of a pre-study physical examination, medical history, vital signs
             and the results of blood biochemistry and hematology tests and a urinalysis carried
             out at screening

          -  Patient agrees not to participate in any other clinical trial until 6 weeks after
             being informed that his/her TMC278 exposure is below 20 ng/ml (all panels)

          -  Females participating in the clinical study must be of non-childbearing potential
             (e.g. surgically sterilized or postmenopausal with no menstrual bleeding for at least
             2 years prior the clinical study

          -  If the patient is a sexually active man and not surgically sterilized, he must be
             willing to abstain from sexual intercourse, or use a condom plus another form of
             contraception (e.g., spermicide, IUD, birth control pills taken by female partner,
             diaphragm with spermicide) if engaging in sexual intercourse with a woman who could
             become pregnant. This will avoid pregnancy caused by possibly damaged sperm. Males
             must use a condom during sexual intercourse with pregnant or lactating females. Male
             patients must not father a child from administration of the first dose and up to one
             month after the last dose of the IMP.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Past history of heart arrhythmias (extrasystolic, tachycardia at rest) or having
             baseline prolongation of QTc interval &gt; 450 ms, history of risk factors for Torsade de
             Pointes syndrome (hypokalemia, family history of long QT Syndrome)

          -  History or suspicion of alcohol, barbiturate, amphetamine, recreational or narcotic
             drug use that could impact compliance to protocol requirements and/or safety

          -  Hepatitis A infection (confirmed by hepatitis A antibody), or hepatitis B infection
             (confirmed by hepatitis B surface antigen), or hepatitis C infection (confirmed by
             hepatitis C virus antibody) or HIV-1 or HIV-2 infection at screening

          -  A positive urine drug test at study screening. Urine will be tested for the presence
             of amphetamines, benzodiazepines, cocaine, cannabinoids, opioids, methadone and
             barbiturates

          -  Currently active or underlying gastro-intestinal, cardiovascular, nervous system,
             psychiatric, metabolic, renal, hepatic, respiratory, inflammatory or infectious
             disease

          -  History of clinically relevant skin disease such as, but not limited to, dermatitis,
             eczema, drug rash, drug allergy, psoriasis, food allergy, urticaria

          -  History of drug allergy such as, but not limited to, sulfonamides and penicillins, or
             drug allergy witnessed in previous clinical studies with experimental drugs

          -  Use of concomitant medication, including over-the-counter products, herbal medication
             (including St. John's Wort) and dietary supplements, except for paracetamol
             (acetaminophen) or ibuprofen in a period of 14 days before the first IMP
             administration

          -  Participation in an investigational drug trial within 30 days prior to the first
             injection with IMP, Donation of blood or plasma in the 60 days preceding the injection
             with the IMP, Having previously participated in a clinical study with oral TMC278
             (previously known as R278474) or TMC278LA, Vulnerable subjects (e.g., persons kept in
             detention)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tibotec Pharmaceuticals Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Tibotec Pharmaceutical Limited</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 22, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 22, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 26, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 22, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 22, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 26, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>TMC278-C150</keyword>
  <keyword>TMC278-TiDP15-C150</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV-1 infected patients</keyword>
  <keyword>Intramuscular or subcutaneous injection</keyword>
  <keyword>Nanosuspension</keyword>
  <keyword>Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy volunteers</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV Infections</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rilpivirine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

