<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02503098</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RRR-023</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02503098</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Optimizing a Smartphone Application for Individuals With Eating Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Optimizing a Smartphone Application for Individuals With Eating Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Recovery Record Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Recovery Record Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will augment an existing mobile application for individuals with eating disorders
      by developing adaptive, tailored content targeting remediation of cognitive distortions. The
      adaptive application will be deployed and assessed for efficacy relative to the standard
      product in a randomized controlled trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Eating Disorders (ED) are common and serious psychological disorders. Anorexia Nervosa (AN)
      has a prevalence estimated at between 0.48% and 0.70% among young females. Bulimia Nervosa
      (BN) is a serious mental health problem, with a prevalence of between 1-2% of young women
      while clinically significant bulimic behaviors occur in an additional 2-3%. There are
      significant barriers to access of evidence-based treatments and current models of individual
      psychotherapy will likely never meet the enormous need for psychological services for ED.
      Unfortunately, even with treatment, rates of recovery are modest with the best performing
      treatments achieving remission in only about 50% of cases while relapse rates are high,
      especially if the ED becomes chronic. It is widely acknowledged that a major shift in
      intervention practice is needed and that smartphone apps will almost certainly play a role
      due to their reach and breadth of functionality.

      As the first commercially available smartphone app for EDs, Recovery Record (RR) has
      established wide reach and user acceptability. The app provides users with meal and ED
      symptom self-monitoring and coping skill strategies in an evidence-based CBT format.
      Preliminary pilot data suggest that for a proportion of RR users, using RR is associated with
      clinically significant symptom reduction. However, a limitation of the current app is that it
      is a &quot;one-size-fits-all&quot; product that does not account for the heterogeneity of ED symptoms.
      Genetic, personality and neurocognitive data support distinct clusters of ED presentations
      that also differ according to response to treatment, course and outcome. Pilot data confirm
      that clinical response to RR is not homogenous across groups and that extent of cognitive
      distortions is the most potent factor to predict outcome. There is considerable opportunity
      to increase RR's effectiveness across a range of ED symptoms and behaviors by creating
      adaptive and tailored content focused on remediation of cognitive distortions.

      During Phase 1 of this study screening algorithm will be validated against an unseen,
      prospective test dataset of approximately 2,000 users. All candidate predictor variables will
      be entered into a Signal Detection Analysis to confirm the sensitivity and specificity of the
      screen. Informed by the resultant algorithms, adaptive content will be developed that targets
      ED-specific cognitive distortions. To evaluate acceptability, adapted content will be piloted
      with approximately 200 individuals for a period of one month. Participant feedback and
      utilization data will inform content acceptability and feasibility. By the end of the first
      phase tailored content that is acceptable to individuals with specific symptom presentations
      will be developed.

      Phase 2 will focus on an evaluation of whether an adaptive app offering tailored content
      addressing eating related cognitive distortions in a stepped way can outperform the current
      standard app. The adaptive content will be integrated into a new, dynamic version of the app
      (RR-A) that will then be evaluated against the current app (RR-S). Approximately 5,000
      registered users of RR will be randomized to receive either RR augmented with targeted
      content (RR-A), or RR in its current standard format (RR-S) over a two-month period. Outcome
      data will be measured at baseline, one month, end of treatment, and at six-month follow-up.
      At the end of the study period it is predicted that the resultant evidence-based product will
      have demonstrated ability to bring about clinically significant reduction in symptoms in more
      users than the current app, and thus will have potential to make a substantial public health
      impact.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 23, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 23, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 23, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Eating Disorder Severity</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at the start of treatment (baseline), week 4, week 8 and 6 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported eating disorder symptom severity. To measure changes in eating disorder severity over time, the Eating Disorder Evaluation Questionnaire (EDE-Q) will be used.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Binge eating and purging episode frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at the start of treatment (baseline), week 4, week 8 and 6 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported disordered behavior frequency will be assessed via behaviors self-monitored in the application in addition to symptom frequency questions in the Eating Disorder Evaluation Questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Clinical Impairment Severity</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at the start of treatment (baseline), week 4, week 8 and 6 months follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>To measure changes in eating disorder related clinical impairment over time, the self-reported Clinical Impairment Assessment (CIA) will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of the 8-week trial</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported satisfaction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to the mobile application intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured from the start of application utilization (baseline) to 8-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Adherence will be measured via dichotomous outcome of drop-out (an individual will be considered a system drop-out if they fail to login to the app at all for a period of 14 consecutive days). Adherence will be assessed through application usage data.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to self-monitoring tasks</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured from the start of application utilization (baseline) to 8-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of self-monitoring entries will be tracked automatically through the program server.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5000</enrollment>
  <condition>Eating Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Binge Eating Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Bulimia Nervosa</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Recovery Record adaptive smartphone application (RR-A)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will have access to all Recovery Record standard functions and will additionally receive tailored, algorithm-generated content targeting cognitive distortions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Recovery Record standard smartphone application (RR-S)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will have access to all Recovery Record standard functions, including meal monitoring, motivational enhancement, social support, and coping skill strategies.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Recovery Record adaptive smartphone application</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Recovery Record adaptive smartphone application (RR-A)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Recovery Record standard smartphone application</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Recovery Record standard smartphone application (RR-S)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Meets criteria for clinically significant symptoms of eating disorder using
             self-report measures

          -  Has an Android or iPhone and is willing to use phone for the study

          -  Is able to speak and read English

          -  Lives within the United States of America

          -  Is at least 16 years of age

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has visual, hearing, voice, or motor impairment that would prevent completion of study
             and treatment procedures

          -  Has any psychiatric condition for which participation in a clinical trial of
             psychotherapy may be either inappropriate or dangerous (e.g., psychotic disorders,
             bipolar disorders, severe post traumatic stress disorder, etc.).

          -  Exhibits severe suicidality, including ideation, plan, and intent.

          -  Currently receiving weekly psychotherapy or planning to receive weekly psychotherapy
             for eating disorder during the 12 weeks of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jenna P Tregarthen</last_name>
    <phone>6504047098</phone>
    <email>jenna@recoveryrecord.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alison M Darcy, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>650 736 7972</phone>
    <email>adarcy@stanford.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Recovery Record Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jenna P Tregarthen</last_name>
      <phone>650-404-7098</phone>
      <email>jenna@recoveryrecord.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jenna P Tregarthen, PgDip</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University School of Medicine, Department of Psychiatry and Behavioral Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alison Darcy, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>650-736-7972</phone>
      <email>adarcy@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Lock, M.D., PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alison Darcy, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kim J Piak, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.recoveryrecord.com</url>
    <description>Recovery Record smartphone application website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 15, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 20, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 16, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 16, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 20, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Eating Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive Behavioral Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Mobile Phone</keyword>
  <keyword>Smartphone</keyword>
  <keyword>App</keyword>
  <keyword>Binge Eating Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Bulimia Nervosa</keyword>
  <keyword>Signal Detection Analysis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Feeding and Eating Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bulimia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Binge-Eating Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bulimia Nervosa</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

