<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02500108</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Q13-02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02500108</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Domperidone and Risk of Sudden Cardiac Death</brief_title>
  <official_title>Domperidone Use in Parkinson's Disease and Risk of Sudden Cardiac Death</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Canadian Network for Observational Drug Effect Studies, CNODES</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Drug Safety and Effectiveness Network, Canada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Canadian Network for Observational Drug Effect Studies, CNODES</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the risk of serious cardiac events, specifically
      ventricular tachyarrhythmia and sudden cardiac death (VT/SCD), associated with the use of
      domperidone in a population of patients with Parkinson's disease. The hypothesis for this
      study is that the risk of VT/SCD will be higher among domperidone users, especially at a
      higher dose.

      The investigators will conduct a retrospective population-based cohort study using health
      care databases in eight jurisdictions in Canada and the UK. The study cohort will be defined
      by the initiation of a new antiparkinsonian drug or a new diagnosis of Parkinson's disease.
      The results from the separate sites will be combined by meta-analysis to provide an overall
      assessment of the risk of VT/SCD in users of domperidone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the risk of serious cardiac events associated with the
      use of domperidone in a cohort of patients with Parkinson's disease. More specifically, the
      study objective is to assess the risk of ventricular tachyarrhythmia and sudden cardiac death
      associated with the use of domperidone compared to no use in patients with Parkinson's
      disease. In addition, the investigators would also like to determine whether the risk of
      ventricular arrhythmia and sudden cardiac death increases with the dose of domperidone in
      patients with Parkinson's disease.

      The investigators will use a common-protocol approach to conduct retrospective cohort studies
      using health care data from eight jurisdictions (the Canadian provinces of Alberta, British
      Columbia, Manitoba, Nova Scotia, Ontario, Quebec, and Saskatchewan, as well as the United
      Kingdom (UK) Clinical Practice Research Datalink [CPRD]). The Canadian databases contain
      population-level data on physician billing, diagnoses and procedures from hospital discharge
      abstracts, vital statistics, and dispensations for prescription drugs. The CPRD is a clinical
      database that is representative of the UK population and contains the records for patients
      seen at over 680 general practitioner practices in the UK; these data will be linked to the
      Hospital Episode Statistics (HES) database, which contains in-hospital diagnosis and
      procedure data.

      Study Population

      In each jurisdiction, the investigators will assemble a study cohort that includes all
      patients with a new diagnosis of Parkinson's disease or a first-ever prescription of an
      antiparkinsonian drug between January 1, 1990 (or 1 year after site-specific data is
      available, whichever is later) and June 30, 2012. Patients will be followed from the date of
      study cohort entry until the occurrence of either study endpoint (defined below) or censoring
      due to death, departure from the database, loss of continuous health plan or drug plan
      enrolment, entry into a long-term care facility, or the end of the study period (or the last
      date of data availability at that site), whichever occurs first. Data from Alberta, Ontario,
      and Nova Scotia will be restricted to patients aged 66 years and older as prescription data
      are not available for younger patients.

      Case-control selection

      The cohort defined above will be analyzed using a nested case-control approach, where cases
      are defined as a first diagnosis of ventricular tachyarrhythmia (VT) or sudden cardiac death
      (SCD) any time after cohort entry. For each case, up to 30 controls will be randomly selected
      among the cohort members in the risk sets defined by the case, after matching on age, sex,
      date of cohort entry (±1 year), and duration of follow-up. Matching on duration of follow-up
      (i.e., our best estimate of duration of the disease) will serve as a proxy to control for the
      potential for confounding by progression and severity of Parkinson's disease.

      Exposure Assessment

      The clinically relevant exposure period considered for data analysis will be the year
      preceding the index date, and exposure to domperidone will be classified according to
      prescriptions dispensed during this time period. For all cases and their matched controls,
      the investigators will identify all prescriptions for domperidone from the computerized
      medical records during the year prior to the index date. Current exposure to domperidone will
      be defined as a prescription dispensed within 30 days before the index date (35 days for
      Saskatchewan). Recent use, past use, and no use will also be explored as mutually exclusive
      exposure categories. Recent use will be defined as a prescription dispensed between 31 and 90
      days before the index date, and past use as a prescription dispensed between 91 and 365 days
      before the index date. No use will be defined as no prescription of domperidone in the year
      preceding the index date and will be the reference category.

      Statistical analyses

      Conditional logistic regression will be used to estimate the odds ratios and corresponding
      95% confidence intervals (CIs) of the association between domperidone use and the risk of
      VT/SCD. In secondary analyses, VT/SCD will be analyzed according to duration of domperidone
      use (&lt;=30 days, &gt;30 days), and to the daily dose of domperidone (&lt;=30 mg per day, &gt;30 mg per
      day). In addition, several sensitivity analyses will be conducted, all defined a priori, to
      assess the robustness of the results. Finally, all site-specific estimates will be
      meta-analyzed using fixed and random effects models. The amount of between-site heterogeneity
      will be estimated using the I square statistic.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ventricular tachyarrhythmia (VT) or sudden cardiac death (SCD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will be followed from the date of study cohort entry until the occurrence of VT or SCD, censoring, or for up to 16 years.</time_frame>
    <description>VT/SCD will be defined as patients with one of the following diagnostic codes:
VT: ICD-9 codes 427.1, 427.4; ICD-10 codes I47.0, I47.2, I49.0. SCD/ cardiac arrest: ICD-9 codes: V12.53, 427.5, 798.1, 798.2, 798.9; ICD-10 codes: Z86.74, I46.0, I46.1, I46.9, R96.0, R96.1, R98.
All potential cases will be subjected to a computer algorithm to exclude non-relevant events (such as events due to non-arrhythmic cardiac causes or acute life-threatening non-cardiac causes); all potential cases that are not excluded by the algorithm will be reviewed in each centre to exclude cases that do not meet the inclusion and exclusion criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">214962</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treated with domperidone</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who received a new prescription for domperidone (ATC A03FA03) in the year prior to the index date.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Unexposed (reference) group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with no prescription for domperidone in the year prior to the index date.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Domperidone</intervention_name>
    <description>Current exposure to domperidone will be defined as a prescription dispensed within 30 days before the index date.
Recent exposure to domperidone will be defined as a prescription dispensed between 31 and 90 days before the index date (without a dispensing during the 30 days period preceding index date).
Past exposure to domperidone will be defined as a prescription dispensed between 91 and 365 days before the index date (without prescription in the 90 days period prior index date).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treated with domperidone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population will consist of all subjects with a diagnosis of Parkinson's disease
        or a prescription for an antiparkinsonian drug who were registered for provincial medical
        services coverage or registered in a clinical practice (CPRD) at any time between January
        1, 1990 (or 1 year after site-specific data is available, whichever is later) and June 30,
        2012.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients with a diagnosis of Parkinson's disease or a prescription for an antiparkinsonian
        drug, with at least 365 days of information in the database prior to cohort entry.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt; 50 on the cohort entry date; or age &lt; 66 in databases with seniors only

          -  Missing gender

          -  Less than 1 year of provincial Medicare enrollment and equivalent enrollment in the
             CPRD preceding cohort entry

          -  Patients in a long term care facility

          -  Diagnosis of PD or dispensing (prescription in CPRD) of an antiparkinsonian drug in
             the year preceding cohort entry

          -  Patients with a prescription for an antiparkinsonian drug without a diagnosis of
             Parkinson's disease but with another indication such as atypical Parkinsonism or
             secondary Parkinsonism, restless legs syndrome, hyperprolactinemia, or acromegaly in
             the year before cohort entry

          -  All patients with a prescription for domperidone in the year before cohort entry

          -  All patients with a history of ventricular tachyarrhythmia, aborted cardiac arrest,
             implantation of a cardiac defibrillator, cancer other than non-melanoma skin cancer

          -  Cohort entry date same as cohort exit date (no follow-up)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christel Renoux, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Lady Davis Institute for Medical Research, Jewish General Hospital - McGill University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lady Davis Institute for Medical Research, Jewish General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3T1E2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cnodes.ca</url>
    <description>This organization's website describing general functions, other CNODES projects, and investigator profiles.</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Renoux C, Dell'Aniello S, Khairy P, Marras C, Bugden S, Turin TC, Blais L, Tamim H, Evans C, Steele R, Dormuth C, Ernst P; Canadian Network for Observational Drug Effect Studies (CNODES) investigators. Ventricular tachyarrhythmia and sudden cardiac death with domperidone use in Parkinson's disease. Br J Clin Pharmacol. 2016 Aug;82(2):461-72. doi: 10.1111/bcp.12964. Epub 2016 May 19.</citation>
    <PMID>27062307</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 14, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 14, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 16, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 15, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 15, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 19, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Domperidone</keyword>
  <keyword>Ventricular Tachyarrhythmia</keyword>
  <keyword>Sudden cardiac death</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Adverse events</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Death</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Death, Sudden, Cardiac</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Domperidone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

