<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02507921</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ST/0112/15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02507921</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Resistance in HIV+ in North and South</brief_title>
  <acronym>RHINOS</acronym>
  <official_title>Comparing Type and Prevalence of HIV Drug Resistance in Treatment Experienced and naïve HIV-infected Adults in Uganda and Switzerland</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Infectious Diseases Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Zurich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Makerere University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators aim to assess type and frequency of HIV drug resistance in adults
      presenting to the Infectious Diseases Institute (IDI) in Kampala, Uganda, and compare this
      data to patients from the Swiss HIV Cohort Study (SHCS). This study is a single-site,
      cross-sectional study. The Investigators' goal is to perform viral load measurements in 2750
      HIV-infected patients who have been on ART for 6 months or more. Presuming a detectable viral
      load in 10%, resistance testing would then be performed in 250 patients on ART. All adult
      patients attending will be screened for enrollment. Furthermore, the investigators' goal is
      to perform resistance testing in 250 ART naive patients in order to detect transmitted
      resistance mutations. Investigators will therefore consecutively screen and enroll 250 ART
      naive patients who attend the clinic during the study period. For each participant, a case
      report form (CRF) form will be completed which includes social, as well as medical
      information. Investigators will ask each participant for permission to store plasma in case
      resistance testing must be repeated, and serum, in case of future research questions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background &amp; Rational Uganda and Switzerland are two examples of regions in the world that
      have experienced the era of antiretroviral treatment (ART) in substantially different ways.
      While European patients had access to ART from the beginning of drug development, ART was
      made accessible to patients from sub-Saharan Africa many years later. HIV-infected patients
      in resource-limited settings were not subjected to the early days of treatment, were mono
      therapy was tried or combinations of drugs that are off the market nowadays. Furthermore, in
      contrast to European patients, patients from resource-limited settings were constantly
      confronted with economic constraints leading to stock-outs for instance. Cultural aspects,
      such as stigma and fear of disclosure, differ as well, and are well known to influence
      individual adherence and treatment outcome substantially.

      Today similar first-line treatment choices are made by Ugandan and Swiss physicians, but
      monitoring strategies still differ. As in other countries of sub-Saharan Africa, treatment of
      HIV-infected patients is monitored immunologically and clinically, while viral load
      measurement is reserved for selected patients. In accordance with WHO recommendations
      treatment failure is therefore determined clinically (new or recurrent WHO stage III or IV
      condition) and/or by the decline of a patient's CD4 cell count to or below baseline, which
      usually occurs late during insufficient treatment. Viral rebound and emergence of resistance
      may thereby arise. Moreover, misclassification of treatment failure (e.g. patients with
      immunological failure in the absence of virological failure or complete non-adherence to
      treatment) may result in premature switching to more costly second-line treatment options.

      The currently available information on transmitted drug resistance (TDR) in Ugandan adults
      shows lower rates compared to patients from European countries, including Switzerland. Yet,
      available studies were conducted with small patient numbers. Newer data from Uganda,
      especially under new WHO treatment recommendations, is not available yet.

      To the best of investigators' knowledge, so far no study has directly compared HIV drug
      resistance data from a resource-limited country to a resource-rich country. Little is known
      about the effects of historically, culturally and economically different ART experiences on
      resistance. With the 2013 WHO guidelines, ART roll-out will be enhanced globally and the
      continued success of these large-scale treatment programs will depend on the prevention of
      further emergence of drug resistance.

      Study Design:

      Cross-sectional, single-site, observational Enrolment period: May 1st - July 31st 2015
      Patients: All HIV-infected adults above the age of 18 years that have been on a stable first-
      or second-line ART regimen ≥6 months presenting to the Infectious Diseases Institute (IDI)
      during the study period and are able to give written informed consent will be enrolled. The
      goal is to perform viral load testing in 2750 patients on ART. Presuming a detectable viral
      load in 10%, resistance testing would then be performed in 250 patients on ART. Treatment
      naive HIV-infected patients above the age of 18 years presenting to the IDI during the study
      period will be offered resistance testing. The goal is to perform resistance testing in 250
      ART naive patients.

      Laboratory tests: A blood sample is used for resistance testing in treatment naive patients.
      For patients on ART, the initial sample will be used for HIV viral load measurement at the
      IDI. Part of the sample will be frozen (-80°C) and stored at the IDI for later resistance
      testing in case of detectable viral load (plasma viral load &gt;1000 copies/ml). Resistance
      testing will be done at the Ugandan Virus Research Institute (UVRI) in Entebbe, Uganda.

      Statistical Methods:

      Type and frequency of mutations in treatment-naive will be identified and compared to the
      data from the SHCS. Investigators will compare treatment-naive patients from the SHCS who
      were tested in the same time-frame (in the year 2014). Additionally, investigators will
      identify a time-frame in the SHCS where a similar proportion of patients had detectable viral
      loads on ART as now in Uganda (the time-frame will depend on the findings in Uganda). Uni-
      and multivariate logistic regressions will be performed to identify risk factors for the
      detection of HIV drug resistance mutations.

      Type and frequency of mutations in treatment-experienced patients will also be analyzed and
      compared to patients from the SHCS. For comparison, investigators will match patients from
      the SHCS with the same age, gender and ART. To identify risk factors for the detection of
      mutations in treatment-experienced patients, the investigators will also perform logistic
      regression models.

      To study the diagnostic performance of clinical/immunological testing investigators will
      calculate the sensitivity, specificity, positive and negative predictive value compared to
      virological testing (gold standard).

      These analyses will be performed for all drug-resistance mutations pooled together
      (outcome-variable= patient has any drug resistance mutation), for drug resistance mutations
      against individual drug classes (outcome = patient has any drug resistance mutation to a
      particular drug class), and for the two resistance mutations (M184V and K103N) that have been
      most prevalent in previous studies in resource-limited settings.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>May 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>1 Day</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV drug resistance in treatment-naive patients</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12hrs</time_frame>
    <description>Type and frequency of transmitted HIV drug resistance mutations detected in treatment naive patients and comparison to naive patients in the Swiss HIV Cohort Study (SHCS)
• Identification of risk factors associated with the occurrence of transmitted HIV drug resistance mutations in treatment-naive patients</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV drug resistance in treatment-experienced patients</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12hrs</time_frame>
    <description>• Type and frequency of HIV drug resistance mutations detected in patients on ART with virological failure and comparison to patients on treatment the Swiss HIV Cohort Study (SHCS) Identification of risk factors associated with the detection of HIV drug resistance mutations in treatment-experienced patients</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Viroligical failure</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12hrs</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of HIV-infected patients with detectable viral load in the absence of immunological and/or clinical treatment failure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Viroligical failure</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12hrs</time_frame>
    <description>• Diagnostic performance of immunological/clinical criteria for the detection of treatment failure compared to virological testing (gold standard)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Viroligical failure</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12hrs</time_frame>
    <description>•Type and frequency of HIV drug resistance mutations detected in ART naive and experienced patients in Uganda and comparison to migrants from sub-Saharan Africa in the SHCS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Viroligical failure</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12hrs</time_frame>
    <description>•Assessment of local risk factors for treatment failure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2750</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Drug Resistance</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Plasma for HIV viral load and serum for storage
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study participants will be all HIV-1 infected adults presenting to the Infectious Disease
        Institute in Kampala during a defined study period, who are either treatment naïve or have
        been on a stable antiretroviral regimen for longer than 6 months.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Evidence of a personally signed and dated informed consent document indicating that
             the participant (or a legal representative) has been informed of all pertinent aspects
             of the study.

          -  Participants who are willing and able to comply with scheduled visits, laboratory
             tests, and other study procedures.

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  ART naïve OR on stable ART regimen ≥ 6 months (first- or second-line)

        Exclusion Criteria:

        There are no exclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amrei von Braun, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+256-414-307000</phone>
    <phone_ext>370</phone_ext>
    <email>abraun@idi.co.ug</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christine Sekaggya-Wiltshire, MMED</last_name>
    <phone>+256312307000</phone>
    <phone_ext>370</phone_ext>
    <email>csekaggya@idi.co.ug</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Infectious Diseases Institute, Makerere University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kampala</city>
        <zip>22418</zip>
        <country>Uganda</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amrei von Braun, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+256312307000</phone>
      <phone_ext>370</phone_ext>
      <email>abraun@idi.co.ug</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Christine Sekaggya-Wiltshire, MMED</last_name>
      <phone>+256312307000</phone>
      <phone_ext>370</phone_ext>
      <email>csekaggya@idi.co.ug</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Uganda</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 22, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 24, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 24, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Makerere University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Infectious Diseases Institute</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

