<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02504905</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>150167</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>15-N-0167</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02504905</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Propensity to Develop Plasticity in the Parieto- and Cerebello-Motor Networks in Dystonia From the Perspective of Abnormal High-Order Motor Processing</brief_title>
  <official_title>Propensity to Develop Plasticity in the Parieto- &amp; Cerebello-Motor Networks in Dystonia From the Perspective of Abnormal High-Order Motor Processing</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - People with dystonia have muscle contractions they can t control. These cause slow,
      repeated motions or abnormal postures. People with dystonia have abnormalities in certain
      parts of the brain. Researchers want to study the activity of two different brain areas in
      people with writer s cramp and cervical dystonia.

      Objective:

      - To compare brain activity in people with dystonia to that in healthy people.

      Eligibility:

        -  Right-handed people ages of 18 60 with cervical dystonia or writer s cramp.

        -  Healthy volunteers the same ages.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam. They will answer questions about
           being right- or left-handed.

        -  At study visit 1, participants will:&lt;TAB&gt;

        -  Have a neurological exam.

        -  Answer questions about how their disease impacts their daily activities.

        -  Have a structural magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan. Participants will lie on a
           table that can slide &lt;TAB&gt;in and out of a metal cylinder. This is surrounded by a strong
           magnetic field.

        -  Do 2 simple computer tasks.

        -  At study visit 2:

        -  Participants will have transcranial magnetic stimulations (TMS) at 2 places on the head.
           Two wire &lt;TAB&gt;coils will be held on the scalp. A brief electrical current creates a
           magnetic pulse that affects brain &lt;TAB&gt;activity. Muscles of the face, arm, or leg might
           twitch. Participants may have to tense certain muscles or do simple tasks during TMS.
           They may be asked to rate any discomfort caused by TMS.

        -  Muscle activity in the right hand will be recorded by electrodes stuck to the skin of
           that hand.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective

      The purpose of this protocol is to improve understanding of the pathophysiology of dystonia
      by performing an electrophysiological study using plasticity induction protocols based on
      dual-site transcranial magnetic stimulation (TMS). We hypothesize that dystonic patients have
      enhanced responsiveness to plasticity induction in the parieto-motor network. In another
      exploratory study, we will also explore the responsiveness to plasticity induction of the
      cerebello-motor network. The clinical significance of such an enhanced plasticity will be
      evaluated by correlating the plasticity measurements with subjects' performance on two tasks
      engaging high-order motor processing and involving the parietal cortex and the cerebellum.

      Study Population

      There will be one main study and one exploratory study with similar designs; the former will
      explore the parieto-motor network (PAR study) and the latter, the cerebello-motor network
      (CER study). There will be two independent arms in each study: one will compare patients with
      writer s cramp (WC) and age-matched healthy volunteers (HV); and the other one will compare
      patients with cervical dystonia (CD) with age-matched HVs. The power analysis of the main
      (PAR) study indicates that we need to enroll 17 patients and 17 healthy volunteers in each
      arm, with an additional 3 added to account for drop-outs. Therefore, we request a maximum of
      20 subjects per patient group and 40 subjects for the control groups. A second power analysis
      for the exploratory CER study indicates that we need to enroll 13 healthy volunteers and 13
      patients in each arm, with an additional 3 added to account for drop-outs. Thus, we request a
      maximum of 16 subjects per patient group and 32 subjects in the control groups.

      Design

      Subjects will come for one screening visit and two outpatient study visits. During the first
      study visit patients will be scored clinically for dystonia and cerebellar signs. They will
      also undergo a structural magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) to locate the parietal target
      during the stimulation session. They will perform two motor learning tasks: a reaching task
      with visuomotor conflict and a predictive motor timing task. At least 24 hours later, during
      study visit two, subjects will receive TMS. TMS-induced electromyographic (EMG) activity of
      hand muscles will be recorded as motor evoked potentials (MEPs). Using single TMS shocks, we
      will measure at baseline, the input-output (I-O) curve for the right first dorsal
      interosseous (FDI) muscle MEPs. Then, the subjects will receive a plasticity induction
      protocol aiming to induce plasticity in the pathway linking the posterior parietal (PP)
      cortex and the primary motor cortex (M1). To that end, transcranial stimulation will be
      applied repeatedly (100 pairs) to the left angular gyrus in the PP cortex and to the left M1.
      At the end of the intervention, the I-O curve will be measured again over the next 50
      minutes. The exploratory CER study will have the same experimental design. It differs from
      the PAR study only by the type of plasticity induction protocol used. Specifically, the
      cerebellum will be stimulated rather than the PP cortex.

      Outcome Measures

      The amplitude of the MEPs in the I-O curves gives information about corticospinal
      excitability as a function of TMS stimulation. The primary outcome measure will be MEP size
      with respect to time (before and 15-20 min after the plasticity intervention). The difference
      in MEP size will be compared between the HV and the patient groups using a T test. The
      performances on the behavioral tasks will be correlated with the primary outcome measure.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 21, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome measure will be the percentage of change in MEP size between, before, and 15-20 min after PAS intervention (MEP post intervention/MEP pre intervention). The amplitude of the MEP in the EMG signal is the outcome measure giving...</measure>
    <time_frame>15-20 min</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The duration of the post-effects will be assessed by the MEP size at the 4 time points.</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre &amp;amp; 5,15,25 ml</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Performance on the reaching task with a visuomotor conflict.Performance on the Predictive motor timing task.</measure>
    <time_frame>on going</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">144</enrollment>
  <condition>Writer's Cramp</condition>
  <condition>Healthly Volunteers</condition>
  <condition>Cervical Dystonia</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Between the ages of 18 and 65 years

          -  Right-handed

          -  English speaking

          -  For patients only: confirmed diagnosis of cervical dystonia (CER-CD and PAR-CD
             studies) or writer s cramp (for CER-WC and PAR-WC studies).

          -  For patients treated with anticholinergics and/or benzodiazepines, they must be
             willing and safely able to abstain from any of these medication for a period of at
             least 5 plasma half-lives of the individual drug prior to study participation (2 days
             for trihexyphenidyl which has a plasma half life around 4 hours; 12 days, for
             clonazepam which has a half-life of 18-50 hours).

          -  For HVs only: absence of dystonia or other neurological disorder with any effect on
             the motor or sensory systems

          -  Ability to give informed consent

          -  Ability to comply with all study procedures, based on the judgment by the
             investigator(s).

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Any of the following will exclude patients from the study:

          -  Secondary forms of dystonia, including tardive dyskinesia.

          -  Dystonic tremor where the tremor is the sole or principal abnormality.

          -  Botulinum toxin treatment &lt; 3 months prior to visit.

        Any of the following will exclude patients or healthy controls from the study:

          -  Illegal drug use within the past 6 months based on history alone. The intent is to
             exclude those with drug use that may affect study results.

          -  Self-reported consumption of 7 alcoholic drinks a week for women and &gt;14 alcoholic
             drinks a week for man.

          -  Abnormal findings on neurologic exam (other than dystonia in patient group).

          -  History of or current brain tumor, stroke, head trauma with loss of consciousness &gt;
             few seconds, epilepsy or seizures.

          -  Current diagnosis of major depression or any major mental disorders (axis I
             disorders).

          -  Current diagnosis of neurologic disorder other than dystonia.

          -  Presence of pacemaker, intracardiac lines, implanted pumps or stimulators, or metal
             objects inside the eye or skull. Dental fillings and dental braces are allowed.

          -  Known hearing loss.

          -  Open scalp wounds or scalp infection.

          -  Current pregnancy.

          -  Taking benzodiazepines at the time of the study or within 12 days prior to the study.

          -  Taking anticholinergics at the time of the study or within 2 days prior to the study.

          -  Taking at the time of the study or within 2 weeks prior to the study any medication
             that acts as a central nervous system stimulant or that is known to lower seizure
             threshold, including, imipramine, amitriptyline, doxepine, nortriptyline, maprotiline,
             chlorpromazine, foscarnet, ganciclovir, ritonavir, amphetamines, ketamine,
             gamma-hydroxybutyrate (GHB), theophylline, mianserin, fluoxetine, fluvoxamine,
             paroxetine, sertraline, citalopram, reboxetine, venlafaxine, duloxetine, bupropion,
             mirtazapine, fluphenazine, pimozide, haloperidol, olanzapine, quetiapine,
             aripiprazole, ziprasidone, risperidone, chloroquine, mefloquine, imipenem, penicillin,
             ampicillin, cephalosporins, metronidazole, isoniazid, levofloxacin, cyclosporin,
             chlorambucil, vincristine, methotrexate, cytosine arabinoside, BCNU, lithium,
             antihistamines, and sympathomimetics.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Hallett, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Elaine P Considine, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-8518</phone>
    <email>considinee@ninds.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2015-N-0167.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hubsch C, Roze E, Popa T, Russo M, Balachandran A, Pradeep S, Mueller F, Brochard V, Quartarone A, Degos B, Vidailhet M, Kishore A, Meunier S. Defective cerebellar control of cortical plasticity in writer's cramp. Brain. 2013 Jul;136(Pt 7):2050-62. doi: 10.1093/brain/awt147.</citation>
    <PMID>23801734</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chao CC, Karabanov AN, Paine R, Carolina de Campos A, Kukke SN, Wu T, Wang H, Hallett M. Induction of motor associative plasticity in the posterior parietal cortex-primary motor network. Cereb Cortex. 2015 Feb;25(2):365-73. doi: 10.1093/cercor/bht230. Epub 2013 Aug 22.</citation>
    <PMID>23968834</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 27, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 21, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 21, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 22, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parietal Lobe</keyword>
  <keyword>Plasticity</keyword>
  <keyword>Cerebellum</keyword>
  <keyword>Dystonia</keyword>
  <keyword>Transcranial Magnetic Stimulation (TMS)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dystonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dystonic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Torticollis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

