<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02500901</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HCRN GU14-202</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02500901</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Enzalutamide and Niraparib in the Treatment of Metastatic Castrate-Resistant Prostate Cancer (CRPC)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Combined Targeting of the Androgen Receptor in Metastatic Castrate-Resistant Prostate Cancer With Enzalutamide and the Poly (ADP- Ribose) Polymerase (PARP) Inhibitor Niraparib: Hoosier Cancer Research Network GU14-202</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Paul Mathew, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hoosier Cancer Research Network</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tesaro, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hoosier Cancer Research Network</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase I study to determine the safety and feasibility of the combination of
      enzalutamide and niraparib in subjects with metastatic castration-resistant prostate cancer
      (CRPC).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OUTLINE: This is a multi-center trial.

      INVESTIGATIONAL TREATMENT:

      Each eligible subject will begin treatment with a 28-day enzalutamide 160 mg/day lead-in
      cycle. If a subject is able to tolerate the lead-in enzalutamide cycle without Grade 2 or
      Grade 2-4 drug-related toxicity, dose reduction, or missed doses due to toxicity, cycle 1 of
      combined enzalutamide and niraparib will commence. Enzalutamide will continue at 160 mg
      daily.

      Niraparib will be dosed daily starting at 100mg (dose level 1). Six subjects will be enrolled
      per dose level. If less than 33% of the subjects experience a dose-limiting toxicity (DLT) at
      the beginning of cycle 2, then the daily dose of niraparib will escalate to 200mg (dose level
      2). If dose level 2 is similarly tolerated, then the daily dose of niraparib escalate to
      300mg (dose level 3).

      The following required laboratory values must be obtained within 14 days prior to
      registration for protocol therapy:

      Hematopoietic:

        -  White blood cell count (WBC) ≥ 1500/mm3

        -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) ≥ 9 g/dL

        -  Platelets ≥ 150,000/µL

        -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1500/mm3

      Renal:

        -  Calculated creatinine clearance of ≥ 40 cc/min using the Cockcroft-Gault formula

      Hepatic:

        -  Bilirubin ≤ 1.5 × upper limit of normal (ULN)

        -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST, SGOT) ≤ 2.5 × ULN
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Suspended by funder
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>March 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 10, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 10, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) for subjects receiving enzalutamide with niraparib without experiencing dose-limiting toxicity(s) (DLT)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the start of combination treatment D29 until 30 days after last dose of study treatment per CTCAE v4, assessed up to 52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>MTD of niraparib in combination with enzalutamide and MTD for phase II testing.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS) with enzalutamide and niraparib combination therapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of enrollment until the criteria for disease progression is met as defined by RECIST 1.1 or death from any cause, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>PFS per RECIST v1.1 for subjects on this combination therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response (OR) rates for all subjects with confirmed Partial Response (PR) or Complete Response (CR) outcomes, per RECIST v1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of enrollment until the date of documented disease progression or the date of death from any cause, whichever occurs first, assessed up to 52 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>OR outcomes for subjects on this combination therapy, per RECIST v1.1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive enzalutamide 160 mg/day PO in a 28-day lead-in cycle to assess tolerability. If well-tolerated, cycle 1 of combined enzalutamide and niraparib will commence. Enzalutamide will continue at 160 mg PO daily. Niraparib will be administered in three dose-escalation cohorts of 100mg PO, 200mg PO or 300 mg PO daily. Six subjects will be enrolled at each dose level. Each cycle will be 28 days. Combination treatment will continue until documented progression, unmanageable toxicity, or subject or treating investigator decision to discontinue for any reason.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enzalutamide</intervention_name>
    <description>Following completion of 28-day lead-in cycle, enzalutamide 160 mg PO daily will continue to be administered in 28-day cycles until documented progression, unmanageable toxicity, or decision to discontinue for any reason.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Xtandi</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Niraparib</intervention_name>
    <description>Niraparib will be administered daily in three dose-escalation cohorts of 6 subjects per dose levels of 100mg PO, 200mg PO or 300mg PO in 28-day cycles until documented progression, unmanageable toxicity, or decision to discontinue for any reason.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Written informed consent and Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act
             (HIPAA) authorization for release of personal health information. NOTE: HIPAA
             authorization may be included in the informed consent or obtained separately.

          -  Age ≥ 18 years at the time of consent.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status of 0-1 within 14 days
             prior to registration.

          -  Men who are not surgically sterile (vasectomy) must agree to use an acceptable method
             of contraception. Male subjects with female sexual partners who are pregnant, possibly
             pregnant, or who could become pregnant during the study must agree to use condoms from
             the first dose of study drug through at least 120 days after the last dose of study
             drug. Total abstinence for the same study period is an acceptable alternative.

          -  Documented histologically or cytologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the prostate.

          -  Ongoing androgen deprivation therapy with a Gonadotropin Releasing Hormone (GnRH)
             analogue or bilateral orchiectomy. Subjects who have not undergone orchiectomy must
             plan to continue GnRH analogue therapy for the duration of the trial.

          -  All subjects on oral anti-androgen therapy must have been off therapy for at least 4
             weeks prior to registration (6 weeks for bicalutamide) to exclude an anti-androgen
             withdrawal response. Patients who received secondary anti-androgen therapy and did not
             exhibit a &gt;50% PSA decline, or subjects with any rise in PSA, objective or symptomatic
             progression following anti-androgen withdrawal will not be required to meet this
             withdrawal requirement.

          -  Documented metastatic disease with prostate-specific antigen (PSA) progression,
             radiographic progression, or both, despite receiving luteinizing hormone releasing
             hormone (LHRH) analogue therapy or orchiectomy with a serum testosterone level of 50
             ng/dL or less.

               -  PSA progression is defined as three successive rising PSA values with an interval
                  of at least one week between determinations.

               -  Radiographic progression is defined by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid
                  Tumors (RECIST) 1.1 criteria or at least two new lesions on bone scan.

          -  At screening the serum testosterone must be 50 ng/dL or less and the PSA must be
             greater or equal to 2 ng/mL.

          -  Estimated life expectancy &gt; 6 months

          -  Prior treatment of CRPC, including docetaxel, cabazitaxel, sipuleucel-T, or Radium-223
             is allowed.

          -  Prior therapy with abiraterone allowed for a maximum of 9 subjects.

          -  Prior chemotherapy must be completed at least 28 days prior to registration and the
             participant subject must have recovered from the acute toxic effects.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior enzalutamide or other next-generation androgen receptor- (AR) targeting therapy.

          -  Prior PARP-inhibitor therapy.

          -  History of or active central nervous system (CNS) metastases. Subjects with
             neurological symptoms must undergo a head computed tomography (CT) scan or brain
             magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) to exclude brain metastasis.

          -  Radioisotope or external beam radiation exposure in the last 4 weeks. Exposure to
             strontium, regardless of when exposure occurred.

          -  Prior radiation to 25% or more of the bone marrow.

          -  Treatment with any investigational agent within 28 days prior to registration.

          -  Known significant immunodeficiency as determined by the site investigator.

          -  Prior malignancy except for adequately treated basal cell or squamous cell skin
             cancer, or other cancer for which the subject has been disease-free or stable for at
             least one year.

          -  Prolonged QTc over 470 ms.

          -  History of seizure.

          -  Clinically significant active infections on systemic therapy as judged by the site
             investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Mathew, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Hoosier Cancer Research Network</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tufts Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.hoosieroncologygroup.org</url>
    <description>Hoosier Cancer Research Network Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 2, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 16, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 17, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 22, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hoosier Cancer Research Network</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paul Mathew, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Sponsor-Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Enzalutamide</keyword>
  <keyword>Niraparib</keyword>
  <keyword>PARP-1 inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>PARP-2 inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Castrate-Resistant Prostate Cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Niraparib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

