<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02501434</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15.0662</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02501434</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Aneurysmal Subarachnoid Hemorrhage Trial RandOmizing Heparin</brief_title>
  <acronym>ASTROH</acronym>
  <official_title>A Blind-adjudication Multi-center Phase II Randomized Clinical Trial of Continuous Low-dose Intravenous Heparin Therapy in Coiled Low-grade Aneurysmal Subarachnoid Hemorrhage Patients With Significant Hemorrhage Burden</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Robert F James, MD, FACS, FAANS</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Louisville</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A Blind-adjudication Multi-center Phase II Randomized Clinical Trial of Continuous Low-dose
      Intravenous Heparin Therapy in Coiled Low-grade Aneurysmal Subarachnoid Hemorrhage Patients
      with Significant Hemorrhage Burden.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to investigate the safety and clinical effect of a
      continuous low-dose intravenous unfractionated heparin (LDIVH) infusion for the prevention of
      aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage (aSAH) induced neurocognitive dysfunction and other
      delayed neurological deficits.

      Additionally, increased blood and CSF levels of certain inflammatory biomarkers (IL-6, hsCRP,
      etc) have been correlated to aSAH patients with poor clinical outcomes. Unfractionated
      heparin (UFH) has known anti-inflammatory actions. As a result, a secondary objective of this
      study will be to evaluate whether LDIVH can reduce blood and CSF inflammatory biomarkers
      levels compared to controls and whether there is any association between inflammatory
      biomarker levels and cognitive outcomes in aSAH.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA)</measure>
    <time_frame>90-day follow-up visit</time_frame>
    <description>Primary Clinical Outcome Measure- mean score compared between groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of &quot;Major Bleeding&quot; or &quot;Clinically Relevant Non-Major Bleeding&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will be followed for the duration of the hospital stay; an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>As defined by the International Society of Thrombosis and Heamostasis (ISTH) Primary Safety Outcome Measure-</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of &quot;Major Bleeding&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of the hospital stay, an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>As defined by the International Society of Thrombosis and Haemostasis (ISTH)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Type II Heparin Induced Thrombocytopenia (HIT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrollment through 90-day follow-up visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Deep Venous Thrombosis (DVT) or Pulmonary Embolism (PE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrollment through 90-day follow-up visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All Cause - Mortality Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrollment through 90-day follow-up visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Any Fever (&gt; 38.3 degrees C; &gt; or = 101.0 degrees F)</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of the hospital stay, an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of multiple fevers (&gt; 2 episodes)</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of the hospital stay, an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean daily fever burden</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of the hospital stay, an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Daily fever burden = Sum of hourly fever burden over 24 hours; Hourly fever burden = Any hourly temperature recording &gt; 37 degrees C - (minus) 37 degrees C; if temperature is less than or equal to 37 degrees C then the hourly fever burden would be zero.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glasgow Coma Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrollment, post-enrollment days #2, 4, 6, 10, discharge, and 90-day follow-up visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>National Institutes of Health Stroke Scale (NIHSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrollment, post-enrollment days #2, 4, 6, 10, upon discharge from hospital stay an expected average of about 3 weeks after admission, 90-day follow-up visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrollment, post-enrollment days #6, 10, 1 year follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Mean between groups and rate of MoCA score of 20 or less between groups</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CES-D)</measure>
    <time_frame>90-day follow-up visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Trail Making Test Parts A&amp;B</measure>
    <time_frame>90-day follow-up visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cerebral Vasospasm</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of the hospital stay, an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of moderate and severe radiographic cerebral vasospasm (catheter angiogram, CTA, MRA) or incidence OR moderate and severe vasospasm by transcranial doppler (TCD) criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of clinical cerebral vasospasm requiring rescue therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of the hospital stay, an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Rescue therapy = vasopressors or endovascular therapy for the purposes of reversing clinical vasospasm; it does not include Triple H (Hyperdynamic Therapy)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of CT or MRI imaging demonstrating cerebral vasospasm related cerebral infarction</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of the hospital stay, an expected average of 3 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ordinal Regression Analysis of the modified Rankin Scale score (mRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>90-day follow-up visit and 1 year follow-up visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relative frequency of &quot;good outcome&quot; as defined by dichotomized mRS score 0-2</measure>
    <time_frame>90-day follow-up visit and 1 year follow-up visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Barthel Index</measure>
    <time_frame>90-day follow-up visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Return to work status</measure>
    <time_frame>90-day follow-up and 1 year follow-up visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lawton instrumental activities of daily living (IADL)</measure>
    <time_frame>90-day follow-up visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life in Brain Injury - Overall Scale (QOLIBRI-OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>90-day follow-up visit and 1 year follow-up visit</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma biomarker levels (hsCRP, procalcitonin, IL-6, TNF-alpha, P-Selectin, sICAM-1, HMGB-1, MRP-8/14)</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrollment, post-enrollment days #2,4,6,10</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cerebrospinal Fluid (CSF) biomarker levels (hsCRP, procalcitonin, IL-6, TNF-alpha, P-Selectin, sICAM-1, HMGB-1, MRP8/14)</measure>
    <time_frame>Enrollment, post-enrollment days #2,4,6,10</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>From enrollment through 90-Day follow-up visit</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary Safety Outcome Measure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Subgroup analysis for the following subgroups: (Clinical Site, Gender, Admission CT Hijdra Sum Score &lt;23, WFNS grade, aneurysm location, anterior circulation aneurysm vs posterior circulation aneurysm location, infection requiring antibiotic treatment,</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of the hospital stay, an expected average of 3 weeks, 90-day follow-visit and 1 year follow-up visit</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">88</enrollment>
  <condition>Aneurysmal Subarachnoid Hemorrhage</condition>
  <condition>Neurobehavioral Manifestations</condition>
  <condition>Vasospasm, Intracranial</condition>
  <condition>Intracranial Aneurysm</condition>
  <condition>Heparin-induced Thrombocytopenia Type II</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of Care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LDIVH (Unfractionated Heparin)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Continuous Low-Dose IV Unfractionated Heparin Infusion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Continuous Low-Dose IV Unfractionated Heparin Infusion</intervention_name>
    <description>Continuous intravenous infusion of a low-dose unfractionated heparin drip</description>
    <arm_group_label>LDIVH (Unfractionated Heparin)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Heparin</other_name>
    <other_name>Unfractionated Heparin</other_name>
    <other_name>Heparin drip</other_name>
    <other_name>IV Heparin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 18 and ≤ 70 years

          2. Historical modified Rankin Scale Score 0-1

          3. WFNS SAH Scale grade ≤ 2, due to a spontaneous subarachnoid hemorrhage attributable to
             a ruptured cerebral aneurysm. Cranial nerve deficit (e.g. CN III paresis) is
             permissible even for WFNS grade 2.

             • Initial WFNS grade may be determined at admission or enrollment, preferably after
             the patient's mental status has been optimized by resuscitation and interval treatment
             of hydrocephalus (i.e., placement of intraventricular catheter) or
             reversal/wearing-off of sedating medications used commonly during patient transfers
             and transport or procedure related anesthesia.

          4. Admission head CT showing modified Fisher grade 3 aSAH primarily in the supratentorial
             space. Snapshot images of up to four relevant axial cuts from the admission head CT
             will need to be uploaded via the imaging database to confirm the modified Fisher grade
             3 eligibility of the potential subject prior to enrollment. Minimal intraventricular
             hemorrhage is acceptable.

             The Modified Fisher CT rating scale: Grade 1 (minimal or diffuse thing SAH without
             IVH); Grade 2 (minimal or thin SAH with IVH), Grade 3 (thick cisternal clot without
             IVH), Grade 4 (thick cisternal clot with IVH) [From: Claassen J et al. Effect of
             cisternal and ventricular blood on risk of delayed cerebral ischemia after
             subarachnoid hemorrhage: the Fisher scale revisited. Stroke 2001;32:2012-2020.]

          5. Location and pattern of the SAH must have the majority of the SAH in the
             supratentorial space caused by either an intradural anterior circulation aneurysm OR a
             basilar apex posterior circulation aneurysm with primarily supratentorial hemorrhage
             extension. Angiographic location of the aneurysm will be confirmed by catheter digital
             subtraction angiography (DSA) usually obtained during the coil embolization procedure.
             Patients with PICA or other posterior circulation aneurysms as the cause of the SAH
             will be excluded.

          6. Onset of symptoms of aSAH (ictus) occurred &lt; 24 hours prior to presentation at the
             treating facility.

          7. Initiation of aneurysm securement procedure occurred &lt; 48 hours from the ictus AND
             less than 36 hours from admission to the treating facility.

             • In patients where the exact time of the ictus is uncertain, an estimated time of
             ictus may be assigned and that time will be used for the inclusion criteria above
             assuming the estimation is deemed to be reasonably reliable [i.e., actual time is
             highly likely to be within 6 hours of estimated time].

          8. All aneurysm(s) suspected to be responsible for the hemorrhage or potentially
             responsible for the hemorrhage must be secured in the following manner prior to
             enrollment:

             • Endovascular Coil Embolization with a post-embolization Raymond-Roy Score of 1
             (Complete) or 2 (Residual Neck)

          9. Ability to screen the patient and obtain a head CT 2-12 hours after the completion of
             the coiling procedure and then ability to initiate the study drug 12 ± 4 hours after
             the completion of aneurysm coiling procedure..

         10. After recovering from anesthesia following the aneurysm coiling procedure, the patient
             must remain a WFNS SAH grade ≤ 2 without evidence of a significant new focal
             neurological deficit including monoparesis / monoplegia, hemiparesis / hemiplegia, or
             receptive, expressive or global aphasia. New minor cranial nerve defect without any
             other new findings is permissible. If an NIHSS score was obtained prior to the
             aneurysm coiling procedure, a post-coiling (pre-enrollment) NIHSS score must not have
             increased by ≥ 4 points and GCS score must not be decreased by ≤ 2 points. The
             clinician at the local site should use their best clinical judgment as to whether a
             significant neurological decline has occurred due to the procedure.

         11. Patient is willing and able to return for study follow-up visits.

         12. Patient or their Legally Authorized Representative (LAR) has provided written informed
             consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Angio-negative SAH.

          2. A likely hemorrhage event within several days prior to admission related hemorrhage
             ictus due to the increased risk of early vasospasm. Prior sentinel headache with
             negative CT or prior sentinel headache where the patient did not seek medical
             attention does not exclude the patient.

          3. Surgical clipping of the ruptured aneurysm or any non-ruptured aneurysm on the same
             admission prior to enrollment.

          4. SAH not caused by aneurysm rupture or aneurysm is identified to be traumatic, mycotic,
             blister or fusiform type by catheter DSA.

          5. Any intracranial stent placement or non-coil intra-aneurysmal device (i.e., stent-
             assisted coiling with Neuroform, Enterprise, LVIS, LVIS Jr, Barrel Stent, Pulse Rider,
             WEB, LUNA, Medina or a similar device) where the stent device is implanted to treat
             the ruptured aneurysm and / or antiplatelet therapy is needed.

          6. Patient has remaining aneurysm(s) that are untreated and could reasonably be
             considered a possible alternate cause of the aSAH based on the observed bleeding
             pattern. Adequate treatment of these aneurysms by coiling embolization would result in
             the aneurysms no longer causing an exclusion. MRI may be used in some situations to
             determine that the associated aneurysms did not rupture based on lack of blood seen
             adjacent to the additional aneurysms.

          7. Femoral arteriotomy stick above the inferior epigastric artery OR angiographic, CT, or
             clinical evidence of an arteriotomy related retroperitoneal hematoma or large flank
             hematoma. A stable groin hematoma is not an exclusion.

          8. Patient received heparin in any form within the last 100 days prior to admission (not
             including coiling procedure).

          9. Thrombocytopenia (platelet count less than 100,000 - assuming clumping has been ruled
             out as a cause), confirmed active disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) at the
             time of enrollment OR a documented history of coagulopathy or bleeding diathesis.

         10. Diagnosis of sepsis (SIRS criteria plus the presence of known or suspected infection)
             or current documented active bacterial or viral infection prior to enrollment
             (Example: significant URI, community-acquired pneumonia). A minor non- complicated
             community-aquired urinary tract infection would not be an exclusion but should be
             treated promptly.

         11. New parenchymal hemorrhage or new infarction larger the 15cc in volume, or significant
             increased mass effect as seen on the post coiling pre-enrollment head CT when compared
             to baseline admission head CT. New hyyperdensity on CT scan related to contrast
             staining is not an exclusion.

         12. Patient has a documented history of heparin induced thrombocytopenia (HIT)

         13. Patient developed SAH-induced cardiac stunning prior to enrollment, with an ejection
             fraction&lt; 40%, or requiring IV medicaitons for blood pressure maintenance.

         14. Pre-admission daily antiplatelet therapy or any oral or subcutaneous anticoagulation
             therapy prior to, or during the coil embolization procedure. A single 325 mg Aspirin
             (or lower dose) given duiring the coil embolization peri-procedural period is
             acceptable if this is the local standard of care, but should be documented.

         15. Thrombolytic therapy within 24 hours prior to enrollment (rtPA, urokinase, etc.)

         16. Plan for antiplatelet or oral anticoagulation therapy from the time of the coil
             embolization procedure until 14 full days after enrollment. Antiplatelet therapy may
             be resumed after the 14-day window.

         17. Concurrent significant intracranial pathology identified prior to enrollment,
             including but not limited to, Moyamoya disease, high suspicion or documented CNS
             vasculitis, severe fibromuscular dysplasia, arteriovenous malformation, arteriovenous
             fistula, significant cervical or intracranial atherosclerotic stenotic disease (≥70%),
             or malignant brain tumor.

         18. Uncontrollable hypertension (&gt;180 systolic and/or &gt;110 diastolic) that is not
             correctable prior to enrollment.

         19. Known seizure or epilepsy disorder (diagnosed prior to this aSAH diagnosis) where
             anti-epileptic medication was previously taken by the patient or have been recommended
             to be taken by the patient. Childhood seizures that have resolved and no longer
             require treatment are not part of this exclusion criteria

         20. Serious co-morbidities that could confound study results including but not limited to:
             Multiple Sclerosis, dementia, severe major depression, cancer likely to cause death in
             2 years, multi-system organ failure, or any other conditions that could cause any
             degree of cognitive impairment.

         21. Immunosuppression therapy including chronic corticosteroid usage.

         22. Remote history of previous ruptured cerebral aneurysm.

         23. History of gastrointestinal hemorrhage or major systemic hemorrhage within 30 days,
             hemoglobin less than 8 g/dL, INR ≥1.5, severe liver impairment (AST&lt; ALT&lt; AP&lt;GGT &gt; 2 x
             normal or cirrhosis), creatinine &gt; 2.0 mg/dL, or estimated GFR &lt; 60 ml/min.

         24. Major surgery (including open femoral, aortic, or carotid surgery) within previous 30
             days.

         25. Currently pregnant.

         26. Enrollment in another research study that would conflict with this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert F James, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Louisville</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>J Marc Simard, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Maryland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>J Mocco, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kevin N Sheth, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yale University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ann Jerde, RN</last_name>
    <phone>502-438-8787</phone>
    <email>ann.jerde@louisville.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rachel A Sheppard, MBA</last_name>
    <phone>502-852-2162</phone>
    <email>CTU@exchange.louisville.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rush University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Louisville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Louisville</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jerrad R Businger, MD</last_name>
      <phone>419-957-7202</phone>
      <email>j0busi01@exchange.louisville.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ann Jerde, RN</last_name>
      <phone>502-438-8787</phone>
      <email>ann.jerde@louisville.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Ichan School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of South Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Southwestern</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simard JM, Schreibman D, Aldrich EF, Stallmeyer B, Le B, James RF, Beaty N. Unfractionated heparin: multitargeted therapy for delayed neurological deficits induced by subarachnoid hemorrhage. Neurocrit Care. 2010 Dec;13(3):439-49. doi: 10.1007/s12028-010-9435-1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20809188</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Al-Khindi T, Macdonald RL, Schweizer TA. Cognitive and functional outcome after aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage. Stroke. 2010 Aug;41(8):e519-36. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.110.581975. Epub 2010 Jul 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20595669</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schweizer TA, Al-Khindi T, Macdonald RL. Mini-Mental State Examination versus Montreal Cognitive Assessment: rapid assessment tools for cognitive and functional outcome after aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage. J Neurol Sci. 2012 May 15;316(1-2):137-40. doi: 10.1016/j.jns.2012.01.003. Epub 2012 Jan 26.</citation>
    <PMID>22280947</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wong GK, Lam SW, Ngai K, Wong A, Mok V, Poon WS. Quality of Life after Brain Injury (QOLIBRI) Overall Scale for patients after aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage. J Clin Neurosci. 2014 Jun;21(6):954-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jocn.2013.09.010. Epub 2013 Nov 9.</citation>
    <PMID>24373816</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hong CM, Tosun C, Kurland DB, Gerzanich V, Schreibman D, Simard JM. Biomarkers as outcome predictors in subarachnoid hemorrhage--a systematic review. Biomarkers. 2014 Mar;19(2):95-108. doi: 10.3109/1354750X.2014.881418. Epub 2014 Feb 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24499240</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Romero FR, Bertolini Ede F, Figueiredo EG, Teixeira MJ. Serum C-reactive protein levels predict neurological outcome after aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage. Arq Neuropsiquiatr. 2012 Mar;70(3):202-5.</citation>
    <PMID>22392113</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fountas KN, Tasiou A, Kapsalaki EZ, Paterakis KN, Grigorian AA, Lee GP, Robinson JS Jr. Serum and cerebrospinal fluid C-reactive protein levels as predictors of vasospasm in aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage. Clinical article. Neurosurg Focus. 2009 May;26(5):E22. doi: 10.3171/2009.2.FOCUS08311.</citation>
    <PMID>19409001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tosun C, Kurland DB, Mehta R, Castellani RJ, deJong JL, Kwon MS, Woo SK, Gerzanich V, Simard JM. Inhibition of the Sur1-Trpm4 channel reduces neuroinflammation and cognitive impairment in subarachnoid hemorrhage. Stroke. 2013 Dec;44(12):3522-8. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.113.002904. Epub 2013 Oct 10.</citation>
    <PMID>24114458</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Simard JM, Aldrich EF, Schreibman D, James RF, Polifka A, Beaty N. Low-dose intravenous heparin infusion in patients with aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage: a preliminary assessment. J Neurosurg. 2013 Dec;119(6):1611-9. doi: 10.3171/2013.8.JNS1337. Epub 2013 Sep 13.</citation>
    <PMID>24032706</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>James RF, Shao EY, Page PS, Nazar RG, Martin LB, Dvorak J, Kanaan HK, Daniels MJ, Craycroft J, Rai SN, Everhart DE, Simard JM. Low-dose IV heparin preserves cognitive function in aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage patients. [Unpublished Data]. Presented at AANS 82nd Annual Scientific Meeting. April 5-9, 2014. San Francisco, CA; Abstract #16572.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 13, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 15, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 17, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 23, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 23, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Louisville</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Robert F James, MD, FACS, FAANS</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor and Chief, Vascular Neurosurgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage</keyword>
  <keyword>unfractionated heparin</keyword>
  <keyword>neurobehavioral manifestations</keyword>
  <keyword>delayed ischemic neurological deficits</keyword>
  <keyword>cerebral aneurysm</keyword>
  <keyword>coil embolization</keyword>
  <keyword>Montreal Cognitive Assessment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aneurysm</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombocytopenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Subarachnoid Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intracranial Aneurysm</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurobehavioral Manifestations</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vasospasm, Intracranial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Calcium heparin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heparin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is no plan to share data other than through publication or requests to Robert James by other investigators.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

