<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02503852</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>003-A-II</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02503852</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>STYLE -- A Trial of Cell Enriched Adipose For Androgenetic Alopecia</brief_title>
  <acronym>STYLE</acronym>
  <official_title>Subcutaneous Transplantation of Autologous Cell Enriched Adipose Tissue For Follicular Niche Stimulation in Early Stage Alopecia Androgenetica (STYLE): a Randomized, Blinded, Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kerastem Technologies, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kerastem Technologies, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to evaluate the safety and feasibility of the Celution
      and Puregraft Systems in the processing and preparation of an autologous fat graft enriched
      with adipose-derived regenerative cells (ADRCs) in the treatment of early alopecia
      androgenetica.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The STYLE Trial is a prospective, randomized, multi-center device trial intended to evaluate
      the safety and efficacy of the Celution and Puregraft Systems in the processing and
      preparation of an autologous fat graft enriched with adipose-derived regenerative cells
      (ADRCs) in the treatment of early alopecia androgenetica. Patients may be included if they
      are undergoing an elective cosmetic liposuction. Following informed consent and screening
      evaluations, eligible subjects will undergo pre-operative testing. Subjects will then undergo
      a fat harvest using local anesthesia with or without conscious sedating. Subjects will be
      randomly assigned to receive a fat graft cell enriched with ADRCs (available in two different
      doses),a fat graft without cell enrichment using a visually-matched blood saline solution
      (fat alone control), or a saline injection (no-fat control) in a 2:2:2:1 ratio.

      While undergoing liposuction, lipoaspirate will be processed in the Puregraft System to
      remove the lipoaspirate of impurities and in the Celution System to isolate and concentrate
      ADRCs. After the liposuction is completed), patients will have, under a ring block local
      anesthesia (see further description below), a subcutaneous scalp injection of either
      Puregraft purified autologous fat or saline (no-fat control) followed by a separate second
      injection, of either ADRCs (available in two different doses),a visually-matched blood saline
      solution (fat alone control), or saline (no-fat control) in a 2:2:2:1 ratio.

      The STYLE Clinical Trial will have a sample size of 70 patients at up to eight (8) centers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety &amp; Tolerability Assessment of SAE/AE</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of SAE/AE</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hair Growth Assessment by Trichogram</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment by Trichogram</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hair Density Assessment by Trichogram</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment by Trichogram</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global Photography Photographic assessment of scalp hair</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Photographic assessment of scalp hair</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hair Investigator Satisfaction Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of treatment outcome by treating physician</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Alopecia, Androgenetic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fat + High Dose ADRC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Kerastem Therapy includes micro-liposuction followed by subcutaneous scalp injection of purified adipose prepared with the Puregraft System + 1,000,000 ADRC prepared with the Celution System per square centimeter of scalp.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fat + Low Dose ADRC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Kerastem Therapy includes micro-liposuction followed by subcutaneous scalp injection of purified adipose prepared with the Puregraft System + 500,000 ADRC prepared with the Celution System per square centimeter of scalp.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fat Alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Micro-liposuction followed by subcutaneous scalp injection of purified adipose prepared with the Puregraft System per square centimeter of scalp.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Fat Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Micro-liposuction followed by subcutaneous scalp injection of normal saline per square centimeter of scalp.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Puregraft System</intervention_name>
    <description>The Puregraft System prepares purified adipose tissue for subcutaneous scalp injection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fat + High Dose ADRC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fat + Low Dose ADRC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fat Alone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Celution System</intervention_name>
    <description>The Celution System prepares adipose derived regenerative cells (ADRCs) for subcutaneous scalp injection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fat + High Dose ADRC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fat + Low Dose ADRC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Kerastem Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>The Kerastem Therapy is the subcutaneous scalp injection of purified adipose prepared with the Puregraft System enriched with ADRCs prepared from the Celution System.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fat + High Dose ADRC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fat + Low Dose ADRC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Liposuction</intervention_name>
    <description>Tissue collection involving the micro-harvest of subcutaneous adipose tissue.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fat + High Dose ADRC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fat + Low Dose ADRC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fat Alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No Fat Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males with a diagnosis of Alopecia Androgenetica

          2. Females with a diagnosis of Alopecia Androgenetica

          3. Males with hair loss consistent with Grades III, IIIA, III-Vertex, IV, IV-A, based on
             Norwood-Hamilton Scale (Figure 1)

          4. Females with hair loss consistent with Grades I-3, I-4, II-1, II-2 based on the Savin
             Scale (Figure 2)

          5. Provide written informed consent and comply with the study requirements

          6. For women of childbearing potential: Negative pregnancy test at screening visit plus
             subject agrees to maintain two forms of contraception for the duration of the study.

          7. Subject is willing to maintain a consistent hair length and natural hair color,
             without the use of any coloring agents, during the study period.

          8. Ability to complete study procedures, patient surveys, and pictures.

          9. Subject is ≥ 18 years of age.

         10. Body Mass Index &lt; 40kg/m2

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects who have used minoxidil, or any oral or topical medication including over the
             counter and herbal medications for the treatment of hair loss within 6 months of study
             screening, or finasteride or dutasteride within 12 months of study screening

          2. Treatment with an investigational product or procedure within 30 days or plans to
             participate in another clinical study

          3. Subject who has previously failed or has been deemed non-responsive to a previous
             experimental hair loss treatment.

          4. Subject must have no previous hair transplant, cell treatment, micro needling, or any
             other treatment in the last 6 months in the scalp.

          5. Subject is currently suffering from an active autoimmune disease such as serum lupus
             erythematosus, or alopecia areata. Subject is currently suffering from dermatologic
             condition in the treatment area or has a significant scar in the hair treatment area
             that, in the opinion of the investigator, will make hair growth difficult (such as
             systemic burns, etc.).

          6. History of autoimmune disease or organ transplantation or a patient on
             immunosuppressive medication(s).

          7. Diagnosis of cancer, receiving active treatment

          8. Active systemic infection

          9. Requires chronic antibiotics, systemic corticosteroids

         10. Use of systemic agents that increase bleeding or clotting, or disorders associated
             with these effects, including patients receiving GIIB/IIIa inhibitors within 2 weeks
             prior to the study procedure through to 1 week after the study procedure.

         11. Clinically significant medical or psychiatric illness currently or within 30 days of
             study screening as determined by the investigator

         12. Prior surgery in the treatment area

         13. Any disease or condition (medical or surgical) that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, might compromise dermatologic, hematologic, cardiovascular, pulmonary,
             renal, gastrointestinal, hepatic, or central nervous system function; or any condition
             that would place the subject at increased risk

         14. Pregnant or lactating women or women trying to become pregnant

         15. Known allergic reaction to components of study treatment and/or study injection
             procedure

         16. Subject has any disorder that may prevent compliance to study procedures and visits

         17. Subject who is part of the study staff, a family member or friend

         18. Diabetes or thyroid disorder

         19. Subject who has a sensitive, irritated, or abraded scalp area.

         20. Women who have an alternate diagnosis that is associated with hair loss.

         21. Body Mass Index &lt; 18kg/m2

         22. Clinically significant abnormal findings on laboratory screening panels, including
             hemoglobin ≤ 10 g/dL.

         23. Hepatic dysfunction, as defined as aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine
             aminotransferase (ALT), or bilirubin levels &gt; 1.5 times the upper limit of normal
             range (x ULN) prior to randomization.

         24. Chronic renal insufficiency as defined as a serum creatinine &gt; 1.2 mg/dL for women and
             &gt; 1.5 mg/dL for men.

         25. An elevated PT/PTT, INR, or platelet count &lt; 100 x 109/L
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ken Washenik, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Bosley Medical/NYU</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tower Outpatient Surgery Center--Dr. Joel Aronowitz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>920048</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Foundation For Hair Restoration</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Glasgold Surgery Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Highland Park</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08904</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Laser &amp; Skin Surgery Center of New York</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Festa E, Fretz J, Berry R, Schmidt B, Rodeheffer M, Horowitz M, Horsley V. Adipocyte lineage cells contribute to the skin stem cell niche to drive hair cycling. Cell. 2011 Sep 2;146(5):761-71. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2011.07.019.</citation>
    <PMID>21884937</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhu M, Zhou Z, Chen Y, Schreiber R, Ransom JT, Fraser JK, Hedrick MH, Pinkernell K, Kuo HC. Supplementation of fat grafts with adipose-derived regenerative cells improves long-term graft retention. Ann Plast Surg. 2010 Feb;64(2):222-8. doi: 10.1097/SAP.0b013e31819ae05c.</citation>
    <PMID>20098110</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 17, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 20, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 21, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Female Pattern Baldness</keyword>
  <keyword>Male Pattern Baldness</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetic Alopecia</keyword>
  <keyword>Androgenic Alopecia</keyword>
  <keyword>Hair Loss</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alopecia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alopecia Areata</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

