<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01306695</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAI0022</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P60MD000206-08S1</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P60MD000206</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01306695</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Northern Manhattan Caregiver Intervention Project</brief_title>
  <acronym>NOCIP</acronym>
  <official_title>Comparative Effectiveness of the NYU Caregiver Intervention in Latinos in Northern Manhattan</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities (NIMHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Elderly Hispanics have a higher burden of dementia compared to Non-Hispanic Whites.
      Furthermore, Hispanic caregivers tend to have a higher burden of care for their relatives
      with dementia. The objective of this project is to conduct a randomized trial in 160 Hispanic
      relative caregivers of persons with dementia comparing the effectiveness of New York
      University Caregiver Intervention to a case management intervention lead by community health
      workers(CHW). This trial will last 6 months. The main outcomes in the trial will be changes
      in depressive symptoms measured with the Geriatric Depression Scale and caregiver burden
      measured with the Zarit Caregiver Burden Scale. This research project will be conducted by
      the Northern Manhattan Center of Excellence in Comparative Effectiveness Research for
      Eliminating Disparities (NOCERED) funded by the National Institute on Minority Health and
      Health Disparities.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to compare the effectiveness of an existing evidence-based dementia
      family caregiver intervention, the New York University Caregiver Intervention (NYUCI), to
      community-based case management using community health workers (CHWs) in Hispanic caregivers
      in Northern Manhattan. The investigators will randomize 160 relative caregivers of persons
      with dementia to case management alone or NYUCI in addition to case management. The total
      duration of followup will be 6 months. We will call this project the Northern Manhattan
      Caregiver Intervention Project (NOCIP).

      The primary aim is to compare changes from baseline to 6 months in caregiver depressive
      symptoms, measured with the geriatric depression scale (GDS), and in caregiver burden using
      the Zarit caregiver burden interview (ZBI), between the randomization arms using an Intent to
      treat approach. The investigators hypothesize that depressive symptoms and caregiver burden
      will improve or deteriorate less in the NYUCI arm compared to the case management arm at 6
      months.

      This project addresses one of the priority areas for comparative effectiveness research (CER)
      from the Institute of Medicine, &quot;interventions for caregivers of persons with dementia&quot;. It
      also addresses 2 priority conditions from the Agency for Health Care Research and Quality
      (AHRQ): Dementia and Depression. Dementia caregiver burden is a major source of disparities
      in Northern Manhattan. The prevalence of dementia in Hispanics is twice that of Non-Hispanic
      Whites. In addition, Hispanic families tend to be reluctant to delegate the care of their
      relatives with dementia and consider it a family affair. Thus, the burden of care-giving for
      persons with dementia is much higher in Hispanic families. NOCIP will be the first study to
      test the effectiveness of an existing caregiver intervention, the New York University
      Caregiver Intervention, in the Hispanic community of Northern Manhattan. In addition, the
      NYUCI has been tested in spouse caregivers, and NOCIP will be the first randomized clinical
      trial to include non-spouse caregivers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Caregiver Depressive Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months from study completion</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the geriatric depression scale (GDS)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Caregiver Burden</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months from study completion</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the Zarit Caregiver Burden Interview.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">139</enrollment>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NYUCI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>New York University Caregiver Intervention (NYUCI) in addition to community-based case management using community health workers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CHW</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Community-based case management using community health workers (CHWs).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>New York University Caregiver Intervention (NYUCI)</intervention_name>
    <description>The NYU Caregiver Intervention (NYUCI) has substantial evidence of efficacy. This intervention is unique in its emphasis on family support and in providing ongoing availability of the counselor. While the NYUCI is being implemented in several communities, its effectiveness in the Hispanic community of Northern Manhattan has not been tested. The first component of the intervention consists of two individual and four family counseling sessions that include relatives suggested by the caregiver. The second component of the intervention is participation in a support group to provide the caregiver with continuous emotional support and education. The third component of the treatment is &quot;ad hoc&quot; counseling the continuous availability of counselors to caregivers and families to help them deal with crises and with the changing nature and severity of their relatives' symptoms over the course of the disease.</description>
    <arm_group_label>NYUCI</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NYU Caregiver Intervention</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Community Health Worker (CHW) Case Management</intervention_name>
    <description>The CHW intervention will consist of 2 visits in month 1, followed by monthly visits until month 6. The main role of the CHW will be to provide access to existing education and referral resources about dementia and caregiving. In addition, CHW will assess other health and social issues and provide information on existing resources on Northern Manhattan. The CHW will carry a blackberry or iPhone type device with real time access to email, text, the internet, and telephone. Thus, the CHW will be able to provide participants with real time information from pertinent websites such as CUMC, Alianza, and the NY chapter of the Alzheimer's Association. CHW will also provide participants with their phone number and email address for ad-hoc contacts.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CHW</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CHW</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must be caring for a relative with a clinical diagnosis of dementia and have the
             primary responsibility for their care. All people with dementia must be living at home
             with their caregiver when they enroll in the study.

          -  In each family, the person with dementia or the caregiver has to have at least one
             relative living in the New York City metropolitan area.

          -  The caregiver must be emotionally and physically capable of participating. Caregivers
             with clinical depression or other serious mental illness will be referred.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jose Luchsinger, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luchsinger J, Mittelman M, Mejia M, Silver S, Lucero RJ, Ramirez M, Kong J, Teresi JA. The Northern Manhattan Caregiver Intervention Project: a randomised trial testing the effectiveness of a dementia caregiver intervention in Hispanics in New York City. BMJ Open. 2012 Sep 14;2(5). pii: e001941. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001941. Print 2012.</citation>
    <PMID>22983877</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andrieu S, Aboderin I, Baeyens JP, Beard J, Benetos A, Berrut G, Brainin M, Cha HB, Chen LK, Du P, Forette B, Forette F, Franco A, Fratiglioni L, Gillette-Guyonnet S, Gold G, Gomez F, Guimaraes R, Gustafson D, Khachaturian A, Luchsinger J, Mangialasche F, Mathiex-Fortunet H, Michel JP, Richard E, Schneider LS, Solomon A, Vellas B. IAGG workshop: health promotion program on prevention of late onset dementia. J Nutr Health Aging. 2011 Aug;15(7):562-75.</citation>
    <PMID>21808935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luchsinger JA, Tipiani D, Torres-Patiño G, Silver S, Eimicke JP, Ramirez M, Teresi J, Mittelman M. Characteristics and mental health of Hispanic dementia caregivers in New York City. Am J Alzheimers Dis Other Demen. 2015 Sep;30(6):584-90. doi: 10.1177/1533317514568340. Epub 2015 Jan 29.</citation>
    <PMID>25635108</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 28, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 1, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 2, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 8, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 8, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 9, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>José A. Luchsinger</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine and Epidemiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>Depressive symptoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Caregiver Burden</keyword>
  <keyword>Hispanic</keyword>
  <keyword>Latino</keyword>
  <keyword>Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Geriatric Depression Scale</keyword>
  <keyword>Zarit Caregiver Burden Scale</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

