<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01309659</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00028687</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01AG034661</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>PACTTE_01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01309659</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT01413919</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial To Evaluate the Efficacy of Intravenous Iron in Older Adults With Unexplained Anemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Open-Label, Wait-list Control Trial To Evaluate the Efficacy of Intravenous Iron in Older Adults With Unexplained Anemia and a Serum Ferritin Between 20 and 200 ng/mL</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether treatment of unexplained anemia in older
      adults with a short course of weekly intravenous iron infusions can improve physical activity
      and therefore quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is a tremendous morbidity and mortality associated with anemia in the elderly and the
      increasing proportion of elderly adults underscores the population's attributable risk of
      anemia. As a potentially modifiable factor, an urgent need exists to delineate the impact of
      anemia correction in the elderly. The Partnership for Anemia: Clinical and Translational
      Trials in the Elderly (PACTTE) consortium has been created to focus on treatment strategies
      for anemia in elderly patients. The data presented in this protocol provides a compelling
      rationale to evaluate the impact of a well-tolerated IV iron preparation in community
      dwelling older anemic adults with intermediate serum ferritin values.

      Subjects will be 65 years or older adults with unexplained anemia and a serum ferritin
      between 20 and 200 ng/mL.

      Subjects will be randomized on a 1:1 basis to either receive a 5 week course of treatment
      with intravenous iron immediately or to a waitlist control group who will receive treatment
      with intravenous iron following a 12 week observation period. Both groups will ultimately
      receive 200mg of intravenous iron sucrose weekly for 5 weeks to determine if this can lead to
      improvement in 6 Minute Walk Test results. The primary endpoint is change in 6 Minute Walk
      Test distances from baseline to 12 weeks. The procedures in this protocol will include the
      use of outcomes tools that have been selected for their ability to show improvement in
      quality of life in this patient population. Blood samples will also be collected for analysis
      both at the local lab (safety tests - eg hemoglobin or Hb) or at a central lab for research
      purposes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Lack of Enrollment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 6 Minute Walk Test Results</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects were asked to walk for 6 minutes, unassisted. The distance walked was recorded in meters at baseline (time of randomization) and 12 weeks after baseline (time of randomization). The change from baseline to 12 weeks, related to distance, is compared and documented.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Who Had a Hemoglobin Increase &gt;= 1g/dL</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the efficacy of IV iron sucrose in improving Hemoglobin by at least 1 g/dL; an increase from baseline to week 12.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Cognitive Outcome Measures as Determined by Trail Making Test Part B</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on cognitive outcomes based on the Trail Making Test (TMT) Part B as measured by subjects drawing a line from 25 circled numbers to letters in 300 seconds. The change in seconds per completed circle from baseline to week 12.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Self Reported Outcomes Measures as Reported by Short Form-36 (SF-36) Physical Component Score (PCS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on self-reported outcomes measures by change in SF36 physical component score. The SF-36 form identifies self-report physical function and global measure of quality of life and is a multi-purpose, short-form health survey consisting of 36 questions. The Physical Component Summary (PCS) is a subscale of the SF-36 that correlates with physical health domains of the SF-36 ( Physical Function, Role-Physical, and Bodily Pain). The change is calculated and compared from baseline to week 12. The SF-36 PCS score is a norm based sore with a mean of 50 and standard deviation of 10 where results above and below 50 are above and below the average, respectively, in the 2009 general US population.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation Between Baseline Serum Ferritin, Serum Iron, and Transferrin Saturation and the Change in Hemoglobin (HB)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation between baseline serum ferritin, serum iron, and transferrin saturation and the change in HB from baseline to 12 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Frailty Component Related to Fatigue/ Exhaustion</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Subjective fatigue/exhaustion: If any of the following three criteria are met, the patient will be classified as frail for fatigue/exhaustion:
&quot;In the past month, on average, have you been feeling unusually tired during the day?&quot; is answered &quot;yes&quot; and indicated as &quot;all of the time&quot; or &quot;most of the time.&quot;
&quot;In the past month, on average, have you felt unusually weak?&quot; is answered &quot;yes&quot; and indicated as &quot;all of the time&quot; or &quot;most of the time.&quot;
Energy level on a scale of 0 (no energy) to 10 (most energy) reported as ≤ 3. If the subject answers YES to any of the above noted 3 questions, then they are classified as FRAIL.
The change in frailty for fatigue/ exhaustion is defined as changing from frail at baseline to not frail at week 12 as reported by the subject.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Cognitive Outcome Measures as Determined by Speed of Processing</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 Week</time_frame>
    <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on cognitive outcomes based on speed of processing was derived using the z-scores of the following three tests: (1) TMT Part A seconds per completed circle, (2) simple reaction time from the CogState Detection Task, and (3) choice reaction time from the CogState Identification Task. The composite score for a subject at each time point was defined as the mean of the Z-scores for the three tests at the time point. For each subject, the Z-score for each test at time point was derived by subtracting the subject's score at the time point from the overall baseline mean of the test and then dividing by the overall baseline standard deviation of the test. Positive z-scores indicate a better performance compared to the baseline average.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Cognitive Outcome Measures as Determined by Composite Complex Attention/Executive Processing</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 week</time_frame>
    <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on cognitive outcomes based on Complex attention/executive processing was derived using the z-scores of the following three tests: (1) TMT Part B seconds per completed circle, (2) time score from the CogState One Back Task, and (3) accuracy score from the CogState One Back Task. The composite score for a subject at each time point was defined as the mean of the Z-scores for the three tests at the time point. For each subject, the Z-score for each test at time point was derived by subtracting the overall baseline mean of the test from the subject's score at the time point (accuracy score) or by subtracting the subject's score at the time point from the overall baseline mean of the test (TMT and time score) and then dividing by the overall baseline standard deviation of the test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Cognitive Outcome Measures as Determined by Composite Learning and Memory</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 week</time_frame>
    <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on cognitive outcomes based on Learning and memory was derived using the z-scores of the following three tests: (1) CogState ISL immediate recall score (total score from three learning trials), (2) CogState ISL immediate recall score from the first learning trial, and (3) CogState ISL delayed recall scores. The composite score for a subject at each time point was defined as the mean of the Z-scores for the three tests at the time point. For each subject, the Z-score for each test at time point was derived by subtracting the overall baseline mean of the test from the subject's score at the time point and then dividing by the overall baseline standard deviation of the test. Higher numbers indicated a better response.There is no scale, as the results are normalized variables.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Self Reported Outcomes Measures as Reported by FACIT-AN Total Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on self -reported outcomes measures by subjects answering 47 questions for patients with anemia and or fatigue. This test detects self-report functional changes and QoL. Change from baseline to 12 weeks. Scores range from 0-188 with higher scores indicating better function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Frailty Component as Determined by Self-reported Activity Level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 week</time_frame>
    <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on change in the frailty as measured by change in self-reported activity level. Frailty for activity level is classified by subjects responses to 6physical activity questions on the short version of the Minnesota Leisure Time Activity Questionnaire , were related to walking for exercise, moderately strenuous outdoor chores, dancing, bowling, and regular exercise. The Women's Health And Aging Study (WHAS) scoring algorithm was used to define frailty for self-reported activity level. The answers to these questions were used to calculate kilocalories (Kcals) per week, using the WHAS algorithm, which is further satisfied by by gender. For men, Kcals &lt; 128 per week is frail. For women, Kcals &lt; 90 per week is frail. This is a categorical measurement of yes or no. The outcome is the number of participants who were classified as &quot;frail&quot; at baseline and changed to &quot;not frail&quot; at week 12.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Frailty Component as Determined by Grip Strength</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on change in the frailty as measured by change in grip strength. Subjects squeeze the grip strength machine 3 times with each hand. For the frailty outcome the maximum grip strength from the dominant hand is used. (change from frail at baseline to not frail at week 12). Grip strength is stratified by gender and BMI. For men with (BMI &lt;= 24 and a grip strength (GS) &lt;= 29) or (BMI 24.1-28 and grip strength &lt;= 30) or (BMI &gt;28 and a grip strength &lt;= 32) were classified as &quot;frail&quot;. For women with (BMI &lt;= 23 and a grip strength of &lt;= 17) or (BMI 23.1-26 and a GS &lt;= 17.3) or (BMI 26.1-29 and a GS &lt;= 18) or (BMI &gt; 29 and a GS &lt;= 21) were classified as &quot;frail&quot;.The outcome is the number of participants who were classified as &quot;frail&quot; at baseline and changed to &quot;not frail&quot; at week 12.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Frailty Component as Determined by the 4 Meter Walk Speed</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on change in the speed of the 4 meter walk speed. Subjects are asked to walk as fast as they can for 4 meters. Frailty was determined by the subject's speed. (change from frail at baseline to not frail at week 12). 4 m walking speed is stratified by gender and height. For men, (height of &lt;= 173 cm and a walking speed of &lt;= 0.65 meter/sec) or a (height &gt; 173, &lt;= .76 meter/sec) were classified as &quot;frail&quot;. For women, (height of &lt;= 159 cm and a walking speed of &lt;=.65 meter/sec) or (height &gt;159 cm &lt;= 0.76 meter/sec) were classified as &quot;frail&quot;.The outcome is the number of participants who were classified as &quot;frail&quot; at baseline and changed to &quot;not frail&quot; at week 12.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation Between Baseline Soluble Transferrin Receptor and the Change in HB From Baseline to 12 Weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor and the change in hemoglobin from the baseline to 12 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation Between Baseline Soluble Transferrin Receptor Index (Soluble Receptor/Log Ferritin) and the Change in Hemoglobin</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor index (soluble receptor/log ferritin) and the change in hemoglobin from baseline to 12 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation Between Baseline Serum Ferritin, Serum Iron, and Transferrin Saturation and the Change in 6 Minute Walk Test Distance</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation between baseline serum ferritin, serum iron, and transferrin saturation and the change in 6 Minute Walk Test distance from baseline to 12 weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation Between Baseline Soluble Transferrin Receptor and the Change in the 6 Meter Walk Test Distance</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor and the change in the 6 Meter Walk Test distance from baseline to 12 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation Between Baseline Soluble Transferrin Receptor Index (Soluble Receptor/Log Ferritin) and the Change in the 6 Minute Walk Test Distance</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor index (soluble receptor/log ferritin) and the change in the 6 Minute Walk Test Distance from baseline to 12 weeks</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">19</enrollment>
  <condition>Anemia</condition>
  <condition>Unexplained Anemia (UAE)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wait List Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>iron sucrose</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Immediate Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Venofer®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>iron sucrose</intervention_name>
    <description>Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Wait List Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Venofer®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 65 years old

          -  Hemoglobin concentration ≥ 9.0 g/dL and &lt; 11.5 g/dL (women) or &lt; 12.7 g/dL (men)

          -  Unexplained anemia

          -  Serum ferritin level ≥ 20 and ≤ 200 ng/mL

          -  Able to walk without the use of a walker, motorized device or the assistance of
             another person.

          -  Able to understand and willing to provide written informed consent in the absence of
             dementia

          -  Must be able to understand and speak in English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Red blood cell transfusions within the past 3 months

          -  Use of erythropoiesis stimulating agents (ESA) in the past 3 months

          -  Intravenous Iron Infusions within the past 3 months

          -  Distance on baseline 6MWT (6 minute walk test) above the median for age and sex

          -  History of unstable angina or myocardial infarction in the past 3 months

          -  History of stroke or TIA (transient ischemic attack) the past 3 months

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension (diastolic blood pressure &gt; 100 mm Hg or systolic blood
             pressure &gt; 160 mm Hg on 2 separate occasions)

          -  Positive fecal occult blood test within the screening period

          -  Elevated AST (aspartate aminotransferase) or ALT (alanine aminotransferase) ≥ 2x upper
             limit of normal

          -  Documented anaphylactic reaction to iron sucrose infusion in the past

          -  Subjects initiated on oral iron supplementation within the last 6 weeks, or those
             initiated on oral iron within the last 3 months who have had at least a one gram/dL
             improvement in Hb since starting oral iron supplementation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Price, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University MC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stanley Schrier, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andrew Artz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Chicago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Illinois, Chicago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chicago Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University Geriatrics Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Case Western Reserve University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute For Advanced Studies in Aging</name>
      <address>
        <city>Falls Church</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22042</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://pactte.dcri.duke.edu/</url>
    <description>PACTTE Consortium website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 17, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 4, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 7, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>July 30, 2014</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>September 5, 2014</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">September 8, 2014</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 7, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 7, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 5, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Unexplained anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>elderly</keyword>
  <keyword>geriatric</keyword>
  <keyword>older adults</keyword>
  <keyword>UAE</keyword>
  <keyword>over 65</keyword>
  <keyword>iron</keyword>
  <keyword>pactte</keyword>
  <keyword>pactee</keyword>
  <keyword>aging</keyword>
  <keyword>aged</keyword>
  <keyword>old</keyword>
  <keyword>older</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Iron</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ferric oxide, saccharated</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ferric Compounds</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
          <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Wait List Control</title>
          <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="9"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="10"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="9"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="9"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Protocol Violation</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
          <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Wait List Control</title>
          <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="9"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="10"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="19"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="19"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="11"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>American Indian or Alaska Native</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Asian</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Black or African American</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>White</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>More than one race</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Ethnicity (NIH/OMB)</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Hispanic or Latino</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Not Hispanic or Latino</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="17"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Unknown or Not Reported</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="19"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>hemoglobin</title>
          <units>g/dl</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="11.19" spread="0.64"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="11.3" spread=".80"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="11.25" spread=".71"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Change in 6 Minute Walk Test Results</title>
        <description>Subjects were asked to walk for 6 minutes, unassisted. The distance walked was recorded in meters at baseline (time of randomization) and 12 weeks after baseline (time of randomization). The change from baseline to 12 weeks, related to distance, is compared and documented.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in 6 Minute Walk Test Results</title>
          <description>Subjects were asked to walk for 6 minutes, unassisted. The distance walked was recorded in meters at baseline (time of randomization) and 12 weeks after baseline (time of randomization). The change from baseline to 12 weeks, related to distance, is compared and documented.</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random.</population>
          <units>meters</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="9"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="8.05" spread="55.48"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-11.45" spread="49.46"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Number of Participants Who Had a Hemoglobin Increase &gt;= 1g/dL</title>
        <description>To assess the efficacy of IV iron sucrose in improving Hemoglobin by at least 1 g/dL; an increase from baseline to week 12.</description>
        <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Participants Who Had a Hemoglobin Increase &gt;= 1g/dL</title>
          <description>To assess the efficacy of IV iron sucrose in improving Hemoglobin by at least 1 g/dL; an increase from baseline to week 12.</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="10"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in Cognitive Outcome Measures as Determined by Trail Making Test Part B</title>
        <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on cognitive outcomes based on the Trail Making Test (TMT) Part B as measured by subjects drawing a line from 25 circled numbers to letters in 300 seconds. The change in seconds per completed circle from baseline to week 12.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. The number of participants analyzed is correct as 4 subjects for the wait list control group did not respond to this during their clinic visit.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in Cognitive Outcome Measures as Determined by Trail Making Test Part B</title>
          <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on cognitive outcomes based on the Trail Making Test (TMT) Part B as measured by subjects drawing a line from 25 circled numbers to letters in 300 seconds. The change in seconds per completed circle from baseline to week 12.</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. The number of participants analyzed is correct as 4 subjects for the wait list control group did not respond to this during their clinic visit.</population>
          <units>change in seconds per completed circle</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="5"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-0.77" spread="3.54"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-4.96" spread="8.14"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in Self Reported Outcomes Measures as Reported by Short Form-36 (SF-36) Physical Component Score (PCS)</title>
        <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on self-reported outcomes measures by change in SF36 physical component score. The SF-36 form identifies self-report physical function and global measure of quality of life and is a multi-purpose, short-form health survey consisting of 36 questions. The Physical Component Summary (PCS) is a subscale of the SF-36 that correlates with physical health domains of the SF-36 ( Physical Function, Role-Physical, and Bodily Pain). The change is calculated and compared from baseline to week 12. The SF-36 PCS score is a norm based sore with a mean of 50 and standard deviation of 10 where results above and below 50 are above and below the average, respectively, in the 2009 general US population.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. Number of participants analyzed is correct- 2 subjects for Waitlist Group did not respond.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in Self Reported Outcomes Measures as Reported by Short Form-36 (SF-36) Physical Component Score (PCS)</title>
          <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on self-reported outcomes measures by change in SF36 physical component score. The SF-36 form identifies self-report physical function and global measure of quality of life and is a multi-purpose, short-form health survey consisting of 36 questions. The Physical Component Summary (PCS) is a subscale of the SF-36 that correlates with physical health domains of the SF-36 ( Physical Function, Role-Physical, and Bodily Pain). The change is calculated and compared from baseline to week 12. The SF-36 PCS score is a norm based sore with a mean of 50 and standard deviation of 10 where results above and below 50 are above and below the average, respectively, in the 2009 general US population.</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. Number of participants analyzed is correct- 2 subjects for Waitlist Group did not respond.</population>
          <units>t score</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="8"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-1.89" spread="2.44"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-3.17" spread="10.95"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Correlation Between Baseline Serum Ferritin, Serum Iron, and Transferrin Saturation and the Change in Hemoglobin (HB)</title>
        <description>Correlation between baseline serum ferritin, serum iron, and transferrin saturation and the change in HB from baseline to 12 weeks.</description>
        <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Correlation Between Baseline Serum Ferritin, Serum Iron, and Transferrin Saturation and the Change in Hemoglobin (HB)</title>
          <description>Correlation between baseline serum ferritin, serum iron, and transferrin saturation and the change in HB from baseline to 12 weeks.</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random.</population>
          <units>correlation coefficient</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="10"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Correlation btw baseline ferritin &amp; change in Hgb</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.383"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.189"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Correlation btw baseline iron &amp; change in Hgb</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.323"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.541"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Correlation btw baseline TST &amp; change in Hgb</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.200"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.584"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.308</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between ferritin and change in hemoglobin in the immediate intervention group. Testing the correlation equal to 0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.601</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between ferritin and change in hemoglobin in the waitlist group. Testing the correlation = 0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.396</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between iron and change in hemoglobin in the intermediate intervention group. Testing the correlation = 0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.106</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between iron and change in hemoglobin in the waitlist group. Testing the correlation = 0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.606</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between transferrin saturation and change in hemoglobin in the immediate intervention group. Testing the correlation = 0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.077</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between transferrin saturation and change in hemoglobin in the waitlist group. Testing the correlation = 0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in Frailty Component Related to Fatigue/ Exhaustion</title>
        <description>Subjective fatigue/exhaustion: If any of the following three criteria are met, the patient will be classified as frail for fatigue/exhaustion:
“In the past month, on average, have you been feeling unusually tired during the day?” is answered “yes” and indicated as “all of the time” or “most of the time.”
“In the past month, on average, have you felt unusually weak?” is answered “yes” and indicated as “all of the time” or “most of the time.”
Energy level on a scale of 0 (no energy) to 10 (most energy) reported as ≤ 3. If the subject answers YES to any of the above noted 3 questions, then they are classified as FRAIL.
The change in frailty for fatigue/ exhaustion is defined as changing from frail at baseline to not frail at week 12 as reported by the subject.</description>
        <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. Results reported by number of participants reporting change from their baseline exhaustion, and low energy.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in Frailty Component Related to Fatigue/ Exhaustion</title>
          <description>Subjective fatigue/exhaustion: If any of the following three criteria are met, the patient will be classified as frail for fatigue/exhaustion:
“In the past month, on average, have you been feeling unusually tired during the day?” is answered “yes” and indicated as “all of the time” or “most of the time.”
“In the past month, on average, have you felt unusually weak?” is answered “yes” and indicated as “all of the time” or “most of the time.”
Energy level on a scale of 0 (no energy) to 10 (most energy) reported as ≤ 3. If the subject answers YES to any of the above noted 3 questions, then they are classified as FRAIL.
The change in frailty for fatigue/ exhaustion is defined as changing from frail at baseline to not frail at week 12 as reported by the subject.</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. Results reported by number of participants reporting change from their baseline exhaustion, and low energy.</population>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="10"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Frailty change - self reported exhaustion</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="10"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Frailty change - self-reported low energy</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in Cognitive Outcome Measures as Determined by Speed of Processing</title>
        <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on cognitive outcomes based on speed of processing was derived using the z-scores of the following three tests: (1) TMT Part A seconds per completed circle, (2) simple reaction time from the CogState Detection Task, and (3) choice reaction time from the CogState Identification Task. The composite score for a subject at each time point was defined as the mean of the Z-scores for the three tests at the time point. For each subject, the Z-score for each test at time point was derived by subtracting the subject's score at the time point from the overall baseline mean of the test and then dividing by the overall baseline standard deviation of the test. Positive z-scores indicate a better performance compared to the baseline average.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline, 12 Week</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random.The number of participants analyzed is correct as 1 subject for the Immediate Intervention Group did not respond to this during their clinic visit.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in Cognitive Outcome Measures as Determined by Speed of Processing</title>
          <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on cognitive outcomes based on speed of processing was derived using the z-scores of the following three tests: (1) TMT Part A seconds per completed circle, (2) simple reaction time from the CogState Detection Task, and (3) choice reaction time from the CogState Identification Task. The composite score for a subject at each time point was defined as the mean of the Z-scores for the three tests at the time point. For each subject, the Z-score for each test at time point was derived by subtracting the subject's score at the time point from the overall baseline mean of the test and then dividing by the overall baseline standard deviation of the test. Positive z-scores indicate a better performance compared to the baseline average.</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random.The number of participants analyzed is correct as 1 subject for the Immediate Intervention Group did not respond to this during their clinic visit.</population>
          <units>change in Z-Score</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="8"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="9"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.62" spread="1.00"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1.08" spread="0.88"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in Cognitive Outcome Measures as Determined by Composite Complex Attention/Executive Processing</title>
        <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on cognitive outcomes based on Complex attention/executive processing was derived using the z-scores of the following three tests: (1) TMT Part B seconds per completed circle, (2) time score from the CogState One Back Task, and (3) accuracy score from the CogState One Back Task. The composite score for a subject at each time point was defined as the mean of the Z-scores for the three tests at the time point. For each subject, the Z-score for each test at time point was derived by subtracting the overall baseline mean of the test from the subject's score at the time point (accuracy score) or by subtracting the subject's score at the time point from the overall baseline mean of the test (TMT and time score) and then dividing by the overall baseline standard deviation of the test.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline, 12 week</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random.The number of participants analyzed is correct as 1 subject for the Wait List Control did not respond to this during their clinic visit.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in Cognitive Outcome Measures as Determined by Composite Complex Attention/Executive Processing</title>
          <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on cognitive outcomes based on Complex attention/executive processing was derived using the z-scores of the following three tests: (1) TMT Part B seconds per completed circle, (2) time score from the CogState One Back Task, and (3) accuracy score from the CogState One Back Task. The composite score for a subject at each time point was defined as the mean of the Z-scores for the three tests at the time point. For each subject, the Z-score for each test at time point was derived by subtracting the overall baseline mean of the test from the subject's score at the time point (accuracy score) or by subtracting the subject's score at the time point from the overall baseline mean of the test (TMT and time score) and then dividing by the overall baseline standard deviation of the test.</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random.The number of participants analyzed is correct as 1 subject for the Wait List Control did not respond to this during their clinic visit.</population>
          <units>change in Z-score</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="8"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.36" spread="1.28"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.69" spread="1.19"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in Cognitive Outcome Measures as Determined by Composite Learning and Memory</title>
        <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on cognitive outcomes based on Learning and memory was derived using the z-scores of the following three tests: (1) CogState ISL immediate recall score (total score from three learning trials), (2) CogState ISL immediate recall score from the first learning trial, and (3) CogState ISL delayed recall scores. The composite score for a subject at each time point was defined as the mean of the Z-scores for the three tests at the time point. For each subject, the Z-score for each test at time point was derived by subtracting the overall baseline mean of the test from the subject's score at the time point and then dividing by the overall baseline standard deviation of the test. Higher numbers indicated a better response.There is no scale, as the results are normalized variables.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline, 12 week</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random.The number of participants analyzed is correct as 2 subjects for each of the groups did not have a response for this data.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in Cognitive Outcome Measures as Determined by Composite Learning and Memory</title>
          <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on cognitive outcomes based on Learning and memory was derived using the z-scores of the following three tests: (1) CogState ISL immediate recall score (total score from three learning trials), (2) CogState ISL immediate recall score from the first learning trial, and (3) CogState ISL delayed recall scores. The composite score for a subject at each time point was defined as the mean of the Z-scores for the three tests at the time point. For each subject, the Z-score for each test at time point was derived by subtracting the overall baseline mean of the test from the subject's score at the time point and then dividing by the overall baseline standard deviation of the test. Higher numbers indicated a better response.There is no scale, as the results are normalized variables.</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random.The number of participants analyzed is correct as 2 subjects for each of the groups did not have a response for this data.</population>
          <units>change in Z-score</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="7"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="7"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.41" spread="1.50"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1.39" spread="2.36"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in Self Reported Outcomes Measures as Reported by FACIT-AN Total Score</title>
        <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on self -reported outcomes measures by subjects answering 47 questions for patients with anemia and or fatigue. This test detects self-report functional changes and QoL. Change from baseline to 12 weeks. Scores range from 0-188 with higher scores indicating better function.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random.The number of participants analyzed is correct as for each of the groups there was missing responses for subjects.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in Self Reported Outcomes Measures as Reported by FACIT-AN Total Score</title>
          <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on self -reported outcomes measures by subjects answering 47 questions for patients with anemia and or fatigue. This test detects self-report functional changes and QoL. Change from baseline to 12 weeks. Scores range from 0-188 with higher scores indicating better function.</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random.The number of participants analyzed is correct as for each of the groups there was missing responses for subjects.</population>
          <units>change in the total score</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="8"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="6"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="10.6" spread="10.0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.0" spread="34.7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in the Frailty Component as Determined by Self-reported Activity Level</title>
        <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on change in the frailty as measured by change in self-reported activity level. Frailty for activity level is classified by subjects responses to 6physical activity questions on the short version of the Minnesota Leisure Time Activity Questionnaire , were related to walking for exercise, moderately strenuous outdoor chores, dancing, bowling, and regular exercise. The Women's Health And Aging Study (WHAS) scoring algorithm was used to define frailty for self-reported activity level. The answers to these questions were used to calculate kilocalories (Kcals) per week, using the WHAS algorithm, which is further satisfied by by gender. For men, Kcals &lt; 128 per week is frail. For women, Kcals &lt; 90 per week is frail. This is a categorical measurement of yes or no. The outcome is the number of participants who were classified as “frail” at baseline and changed to “not frail” at week 12.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline, 12 week</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. Two subjects in the immediate intervention group and 5 subjects in the wait list group did not respond.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in the Frailty Component as Determined by Self-reported Activity Level</title>
          <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on change in the frailty as measured by change in self-reported activity level. Frailty for activity level is classified by subjects responses to 6physical activity questions on the short version of the Minnesota Leisure Time Activity Questionnaire , were related to walking for exercise, moderately strenuous outdoor chores, dancing, bowling, and regular exercise. The Women's Health And Aging Study (WHAS) scoring algorithm was used to define frailty for self-reported activity level. The answers to these questions were used to calculate kilocalories (Kcals) per week, using the WHAS algorithm, which is further satisfied by by gender. For men, Kcals &lt; 128 per week is frail. For women, Kcals &lt; 90 per week is frail. This is a categorical measurement of yes or no. The outcome is the number of participants who were classified as “frail” at baseline and changed to “not frail” at week 12.</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. Two subjects in the immediate intervention group and 5 subjects in the wait list group did not respond.</population>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="7"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="5"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in Frailty Component as Determined by Grip Strength</title>
        <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on change in the frailty as measured by change in grip strength. Subjects squeeze the grip strength machine 3 times with each hand. For the frailty outcome the maximum grip strength from the dominant hand is used. (change from frail at baseline to not frail at week 12). Grip strength is stratified by gender and BMI. For men with (BMI &lt;= 24 and a grip strength (GS) &lt;= 29) or (BMI 24.1-28 and grip strength &lt;= 30) or (BMI &gt;28 and a grip strength &lt;= 32) were classified as &quot;frail&quot;. For women with (BMI &lt;= 23 and a grip strength of &lt;= 17) or (BMI 23.1-26 and a GS &lt;= 17.3) or (BMI 26.1-29 and a GS &lt;= 18) or (BMI &gt; 29 and a GS &lt;= 21) were classified as &quot;frail&quot;.The outcome is the number of participants who were classified as “frail” at baseline and changed to “not frail” at week 12.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. Three subjects in both the immediate intervention group and the wait list control groups were missing responses.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in Frailty Component as Determined by Grip Strength</title>
          <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on change in the frailty as measured by change in grip strength. Subjects squeeze the grip strength machine 3 times with each hand. For the frailty outcome the maximum grip strength from the dominant hand is used. (change from frail at baseline to not frail at week 12). Grip strength is stratified by gender and BMI. For men with (BMI &lt;= 24 and a grip strength (GS) &lt;= 29) or (BMI 24.1-28 and grip strength &lt;= 30) or (BMI &gt;28 and a grip strength &lt;= 32) were classified as &quot;frail&quot;. For women with (BMI &lt;= 23 and a grip strength of &lt;= 17) or (BMI 23.1-26 and a GS &lt;= 17.3) or (BMI 26.1-29 and a GS &lt;= 18) or (BMI &gt; 29 and a GS &lt;= 21) were classified as &quot;frail&quot;.The outcome is the number of participants who were classified as “frail” at baseline and changed to “not frail” at week 12.</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. Three subjects in both the immediate intervention group and the wait list control groups were missing responses.</population>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="6"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="7"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change in Frailty Component as Determined by the 4 Meter Walk Speed</title>
        <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on change in the speed of the 4 meter walk speed. Subjects are asked to walk as fast as they can for 4 meters. Frailty was determined by the subject's speed. (change from frail at baseline to not frail at week 12). 4 m walking speed is stratified by gender and height. For men, (height of &lt;= 173 cm and a walking speed of &lt;= 0.65 meter/sec) or a (height &gt; 173, &lt;= .76 meter/sec) were classified as &quot;frail&quot;. For women, (height of &lt;= 159 cm and a walking speed of &lt;=.65 meter/sec) or (height &gt;159 cm &lt;= 0.76 meter/sec) were classified as &quot;frail&quot;.The outcome is the number of participants who were classified as “frail” at baseline and changed to “not frail” at week 12.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. Five subjects were missing responses in the immediate intervention group and four subjects were missing responses in the wait list control group.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in Frailty Component as Determined by the 4 Meter Walk Speed</title>
          <description>To quantify the impact of anemia treatment by IV iron sucrose on change in the speed of the 4 meter walk speed. Subjects are asked to walk as fast as they can for 4 meters. Frailty was determined by the subject's speed. (change from frail at baseline to not frail at week 12). 4 m walking speed is stratified by gender and height. For men, (height of &lt;= 173 cm and a walking speed of &lt;= 0.65 meter/sec) or a (height &gt; 173, &lt;= .76 meter/sec) were classified as &quot;frail&quot;. For women, (height of &lt;= 159 cm and a walking speed of &lt;=.65 meter/sec) or (height &gt;159 cm &lt;= 0.76 meter/sec) were classified as &quot;frail&quot;.The outcome is the number of participants who were classified as “frail” at baseline and changed to “not frail” at week 12.</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. Five subjects were missing responses in the immediate intervention group and four subjects were missing responses in the wait list control group.</population>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="4"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="6"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Correlation Between Baseline Soluble Transferrin Receptor and the Change in HB From Baseline to 12 Weeks</title>
        <description>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor and the change in hemoglobin from the baseline to 12 weeks.</description>
        <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. One subject in both the immediate intervention and the wait list control groups were missing responses.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Correlation Between Baseline Soluble Transferrin Receptor and the Change in HB From Baseline to 12 Weeks</title>
          <description>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor and the change in hemoglobin from the baseline to 12 weeks.</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. One subject in both the immediate intervention and the wait list control groups were missing responses.</population>
          <units>correlation coefficient</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="8"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="9"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-0.192"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-0.886"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.649</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between soluble transfer receptor and change in hemoglobin in the immediate intervention group. Testing the correlation =0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.001</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between soluble transfer receptor and change in hemoglobin in the wait list group. Testing the correlation =0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Correlation Between Baseline Soluble Transferrin Receptor Index (Soluble Receptor/Log Ferritin) and the Change in Hemoglobin</title>
        <description>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor index (soluble receptor/log ferritin) and the change in hemoglobin from baseline to 12 weeks.</description>
        <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. Four subjects were missing responses from both the immediate intervention group and the wait list control group.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Correlation Between Baseline Soluble Transferrin Receptor Index (Soluble Receptor/Log Ferritin) and the Change in Hemoglobin</title>
          <description>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor index (soluble receptor/log ferritin) and the change in hemoglobin from baseline to 12 weeks.</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. Four subjects were missing responses from both the immediate intervention group and the wait list control group.</population>
          <units>correlation coefficient</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="5"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="6"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-0.500"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-0.714"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.391</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor index (soluble receptor/log ferritin) and the change in hemoglobin in the immediate intervention group. Testing correlation =0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.111</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor index (soluble receptor/log ferritin) and the change in hemoglobin in the wait list control group. Testing correlation =0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Correlation Between Baseline Serum Ferritin, Serum Iron, and Transferrin Saturation and the Change in 6 Minute Walk Test Distance</title>
        <description>Correlation between baseline serum ferritin, serum iron, and transferrin saturation and the change in 6 Minute Walk Test distance from baseline to 12 weeks.</description>
        <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. One subject was missing responses from the wait list control group.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Correlation Between Baseline Serum Ferritin, Serum Iron, and Transferrin Saturation and the Change in 6 Minute Walk Test Distance</title>
          <description>Correlation between baseline serum ferritin, serum iron, and transferrin saturation and the change in 6 Minute Walk Test distance from baseline to 12 weeks.</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. One subject was missing responses from the wait list control group.</population>
          <units>correlation coefficient</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="9"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Correlation for ferritin</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.617"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.100"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Correlation for iron</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.332"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-0.133"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Correlation TSAT</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.400"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-0.350"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.077</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between baseline serum ferritin and the change in 6 Minute Walk Test distance in the immediate intervention group. Testing correlation =0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.798</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between baseline serum ferritin and the change in 6 Minute Walk Test distance in the wait list group. Testing correlation =0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.383</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between baseline iron and the change in 6 Minute Walk Test distance in the immediate intervention group. Testing correlation =0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.732</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between baseline iron and the change in 6 Minute Walk Test distance in the wait list group. Testing correlation =0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.286</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between baseline transferrin saturation and the change in 6 Minute Walk Test distance in the immediate intervention group. Testing correlation =0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.356</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between baseline transferrin saturation and the change in 6 Minute Walk Test distance in the wait list group. Testing correlation =0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Correlation Between Baseline Soluble Transferrin Receptor and the Change in the 6 Meter Walk Test Distance</title>
        <description>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor and the change in the 6 Meter Walk Test distance from baseline to 12 weeks</description>
        <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. One subject was missing responses in the immediate intervention group and one subject was missing responses in the wait list control group.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Correlation Between Baseline Soluble Transferrin Receptor and the Change in the 6 Meter Walk Test Distance</title>
          <description>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor and the change in the 6 Meter Walk Test distance from baseline to 12 weeks</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. One subject was missing responses in the immediate intervention group and one subject was missing responses in the wait list control group.</population>
          <units>correlation coefficient</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="8"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="9"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.192"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.349"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.649</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor and the change in the 6 Meter Walk Test distance of the immediate intervention group. Testing correlation =0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.396</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor and the change in the 6 Meter Walk Test distance of the wait list group. Testing correlation =0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Correlation Between Baseline Soluble Transferrin Receptor Index (Soluble Receptor/Log Ferritin) and the Change in the 6 Minute Walk Test Distance</title>
        <description>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor index (soluble receptor/log ferritin) and the change in the 6 Minute Walk Test Distance from baseline to 12 weeks</description>
        <time_frame>baseline, 12 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. Four subjects were missing responses in the immediate intervention group and four subjects were missing responses in the wait list control group.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Wait List Control</title>
            <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Correlation Between Baseline Soluble Transferrin Receptor Index (Soluble Receptor/Log Ferritin) and the Change in the 6 Minute Walk Test Distance</title>
          <description>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor index (soluble receptor/log ferritin) and the change in the 6 Minute Walk Test Distance from baseline to 12 weeks</description>
          <population>All intent-to-treat patients were included in the primary analysis with an assumption that any missing data were missing completely at random. Four subjects were missing responses in the immediate intervention group and four subjects were missing responses in the wait list control group.</population>
          <units>correlation coefficient</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="5"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="6"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-0.300"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.486"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.624</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor index (soluble receptor/log ferritin) and the change in the 6 Minute Walk Test Distance in the intermediate intervention group. Testing correlation =0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.329</p_value>
            <p_value_desc>Correlation between baseline soluble transferrin receptor index (soluble receptor/log ferritin) and the change in the 6 Minute Walk Test Distance in the wait list group. Testing correlation =0.</p_value_desc>
            <method>t-test, 2 sided</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Immediate Intervention Group</title>
          <description>Subjects randomized to the immediate treatment group will be scheduled to begin treatment with IV iron infusion immediately (or within 2 business days). They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 19 weeks of follow up.
iron sucrose: Patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Wait List Control</title>
          <description>Subjects randomized to the wait list control group will have an observation visit at week 6 and week 12. After that they will begin treatment with IV iron infusion. They will receive 200mg IV iron sucrose a week for 5 weeks followed by 7 weeks of follow up
iron sucrose: Following 12 weeks of observation patients will receive intravenous iron sucrose preparation at a dose of 200 mg per week through a peripheral intravenous catheter.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Hepatobiliary disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cholecystitis acute</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Escherichia urinary tract infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Injury, poisoning and procedural complications</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pelvic Fracture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Nervous system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Syncope</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Diarrhoea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nausea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Feeling hot</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Infusion site bruising</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Spinal Pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Upper respiratory tract infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Gastrointestinal infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Urinary tract infecction</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Injury, poisoning and procedural complications</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Arthropod sting</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Contusion</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Investigations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Liver function test abnormal</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pain in extremity</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Joint swelling</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Myalgia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Back pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Psychiatric disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Anxiety</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dyspnoea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cough</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Sneezing</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Skin hyperpigmentation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Vascular disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Orthostatic hypotension</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="9"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>Small sample size.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Harvey J Cohen, MD</name_or_title>
      <organization>Duke University Medical Center</organization>
      <phone>919-660-7502</phone>
      <email>harvey.cohen@dm.duke.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

