<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01304407</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-27088</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01AR059063</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01304407</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Calcium Absorption in Patients With Rothmund-Thomson Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Calcium Absorption in Patients With Rothmund-Thomson Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>USDA Beltsville Human Nutrition Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Gilson Lowenbaugh Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Osteosarcoma is the most common malignant bone tumor in children and adolescents. Because
      cure rates for osteosarcoma have remained stagnant for the past several decades despite
      numerous trials of chemotherapy agents, novel therapies based on the understanding of the
      molecular pathogenesis of osteosarcoma are needed. Rothmund-Thomson Syndrome (RTS) is a
      genetic disorder affecting many parts of the body and resulting in major skeletal
      abnormalities. This disease also has the propensity to increase the risk of developing
      cancer, particularly osteosarcoma. Two-thirds of RTS patients have a high risk of developing
      osteosarcoma. Therefore, it is important to understand the impact of RTS on the skeletal
      phenotype (as measured by calcium absorption and bone mineralization) in order to develop
      effective therapies to battle osteosarcoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a laboratory experiment to evaluate bone calcium deposition in patients with
      Rothmund-Thomson Syndrome (RTS).

      This study includes one study visit during which subjects will be admitted to the inpatient
      unit in the Pediatric GCRC at TCH where they will undergo comprehensive clinical evaluations
      by a team of physicians familiar with RTS as well as bone-specific studies divided into four
      parts. Procedures for this study may be combined with procedures for H-9106, another protocol
      for patients with RTS by Dr. Wang.

      Subjects will arrive at the GCRC at TCH after an overnight fast. Per TCH pain management
      protocols, numbing creams and sprays will be offered to the subject prior to the blood draw.
      Tylenol per TCH pain protocol is allowed. All food and beverages consumed at the GCRC will be
      pre-arranged by the study dietitian and weighed by the GCRC nutrition staff. Additional food
      is not allowed unless approved by the study dietitian.

      Subjects will be asked to provide a 3-day written dietary history as well as food preferences
      for the GCRC study day. For the first meal of the study day, subjects will consume 180 mL of
      low-fat milk or orange juice to which 20 micrograms of 46Ca will have been added. (If milk is
      used as the vehicle for the isotope, the 46Ca will be added 18-24 hours in advance.)

      Immediately after breakfast, subjects will receive 5 mg of 42Ca intravenously over 2-3
      minutes. The beginning of this infusion will serve as Time 0. After the infusion is complete,
      the catheter hub will be changed in preparation for the subsequent blood draws. Samples for
      calcium isotope ratio measurement (0.5 ml of whole blood) will be obtained at 6, 12, 20, 40,
      120, 180, 240, and 480 minutes after the infusion.

      GCRC will provide weighed diets for the study day as directed by the study dietitian. Each
      meal should contain approximately 300 mg of calcium and each snack should provide negligible
      calcium. A complete 24-hour urine collection in 8 hour aliquots will be performed while at
      the GCRC starting with the first void after the isotopes are given.

      After completion of this 24 hour period, the subjects will be discharged. They will continue
      to collect all of their urine in 8 hour aliquots for an additional 24 hours and then will
      collect three spot urine samples each day for the next 6 days. These samples will then be
      mailed to the CNRC research laboratory of Dr. Steven Abrams where they will be analyzed for
      isotope ratios by mass spectrometry analysis.

      Upon discharge, subjects will receive a food scale and instruction sheets on recording their
      dietary intake for the next 3 days (i.e., weighed food record). While inpatient, the study
      dietitian will instruct the family on the guidelines for recording this intake. After the 3
      days, the food scale and records will be returned to the CNRC for analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Enrolling by invitation</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To characterize the human skeletal phenotype of RTS</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Day (inpatient for 24 hrs) plus 7 days of home urine collections</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the human skeletal phenotype of RTS through detailed clinical evaluation of Rothmund-Thomson patients by examining them and performing bone specific studies including IV calcium bone deposition studies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To understand the bone-specific consequences of RTS</measure>
    <time_frame>Study Day (inpatient for 24 hrs) plus 7 days of home urine collections</time_frame>
    <description>To understand the bone-specific consequences of RTS and how that plays a role in the development of osteosarcoma and bone disease, including osteoporosis, in order to devise more specific therapies for osteosarcoma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Rothmund-Thomson Syndrome</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with Rothmund-Thomson Syndrome (RTS)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients at least four years of age who have been diagnosed clinically with RTS by a
             physician.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any person who does not meet the inclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lisa Wang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Baylor College of Medicine / Texas Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 23, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 24, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 25, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 25, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 25, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 27, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Steve Abrams, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Rothmund-Thomson Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Calcium absorption</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone density</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rothmund-Thomson Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Calcium, Dietary</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>March 13, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>April 21, 2017</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

