<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02124070</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140101</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-HG-0101</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02124070</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Therapeutic Effect of Recombinant Human Growth Hormone (rhGH) on the Myopathy of Cystinosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Therapeutic Effect of Recombinant Human Growth Hormone (rhGH) on the Myopathy of Cystinosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      -(Degree)ystinosis is an inherited disease. If not treated correctly, it can cause muscle
      wasting and weakness and kidney damage. Researchers want to learn if growth hormone (GH) can
      help people with cystinosis.

      Objective:

      - To learn if GH treatment can slow or reverse muscle wasting and improve muscle strength in
      people with cystinosis.

      Eligibility:

      - People 18 and older who are already enrolled in protocol 78-HG-0093.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be admitted to the clinic for eight 3 4 day visits, mostly four months
           apart.

        -  At each visit, participants will have a history and physical exam and give urine and
           blood samples.

        -  At month 0 or 13, participants will take tests that will be repeated at their 12- or
           25-month visit:

        -  They will have an eye exam, medical consultations, and strength and movement tests.

        -  They will complete questionnaires.

        -  They may have tests of heart activity and lung function.

        -  They will have ultrasound imaging of their arm and hand muscles. They will have a scan
           of their legs while lying in a magnetic resonance imaging machine (a big metal
           cylinder). They will have a DEXA bone scan (two X-ray beams measure body composition).
           They will also swallow barium while X-ray imaging records the throat muscles.

        -  Participants will be randomly assigned to either receive or not receive GH for the first
           12 months. Then, at month 13, if they received GH, they will switch for the next 12
           months.

        -  Participants will take GH as a daily injection. They will be taught how to give the
           injections.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cystinosis is an autosomal recessive storage disorder due to defective transport of the amino
      acid cystine out of cellular lysosomes. Cystine accumulation leads to cellular dysfunction in
      most of organs and tissues. Available treatment with the cystine-depleting agent, cysteamine,
      can prevent or delay organ damage, including that of muscles. In poorly treated patients,
      however, a progressive vacuolar myopathy with muscle wasting beginning in the second decade
      of life significantly debilitates some patients. Muscle biopsy demonstrates prominent
      unrimmed vacuoles with small ring fibers but no evidence of endomysial inflammation. Plasma
      and muscle carnitine deficiency, impairing mitochondrial fatty acid metabolism, might also
      limit muscle energy production. Growth Hormone (GH) can potentially counter the muscle
      wasting of cystinosis patients. It has consistently induced anabolic effects in patients in
      malnourished or catabolic states, by enhancing the growth and development of bone, connective
      tissue, viscera, fat, and musculoskeletal muscles. GH, at doses of approximately 0.006 to 0.1
      mg/kg/day, has proven safe and effective in HIV/AIDS wasting, parenteral nutrition-dependent
      short bowel syndrome, pediatric chronic kidney disease, and adult and pediatric GH-deficiency
      states. The current protocol is a randomized (to treatment or no treatment) crossover
      clinical trial to determine if GH (0.03 mg/kg/day) is beneficial for muscle wasting in
      cystinosis. Patients are examined at the NIH Clinical Research Center every 4 months for 2
      years. Change in muscle mass will serve as the primary outcome parameter, and rhGH
      (Humatrope) will be provided by Eli Lilly. HumatropeR (somatropin) is currently approved by
      the FDA for:

        -  Treatment of children with short stature or growth failure associated with growth
           hormone (GH) deficiency, Turner syndrome, idiopathic short stature, SHOX deficiency, and
           failure to catch up in height after small for gestational age birth.

        -  Treatment of adults with either childhood-onset or adult-onset GH deficiency.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 26, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 6, 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 6, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase in muscle mass and improve muscle strengths</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Cystinosis</condition>
  <condition>Myopathy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rh Growth Hormone</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Age 18-70 years, either gender

          -  Diagnosis of nephropathic cystinosis confirmed by leucocyte cystine levels

          -  Evidence of muscle involvement such as decrease of muscle mass, weakness or EMG
             findings and/or documented abnormal swallowing study and PFT results

          -  Ability to travel to the NIH Clinical Research Center for admissions

          -  Ability to consent

          -  Compliant with cysteamine treatment regimen

          -  Availability of local medical follow-up

        ENCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Not able to self administer daily subcutaneous injections, or not able to identify a
             family member/caregiver to administer them to you.

          -  Age &lt;18

          -  Psychiatric illness or neurological disease that interferes with compliance or
             communication with health care personnel

          -  Current malignancy or history of malignancy

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension (blood pressure &gt;180 systolic or &gt;95 diastolic)

          -  Poor controlled hyperglycemia (fasting blood glucose level &gt;160)

          -  Serum creatinine level &gt;1.8 mg/dL

          -  Pregnancy

        Children are excluded because the critical issues of dosage and safety can be answered in
        adults, and because children with cystinosis are rarely affected with the symptoms of
        myopathy. Patients with chronic renal failure, treated with hemodialysis will not be
        excluded from the study, as GH is not contraindicated for such patients. Patients received
        renal transplants are not excluded from the study as GH treatment are not a
        contraindication for such patients. Enrolled patients must be able to travel to the NIH in
        case adverse events occur locally after discharge from the NIH Clinical Research Center.
        Other medical exclusions will help to avoid the spurious assignation of side effects to
        rhGH.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Galina V Nesterova, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Human Genome Research Institute (NHGRI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gahl WA, Balog JZ, Kleta R. Nephropathic cystinosis in adults: natural history and effects of oral cysteamine therapy. Ann Intern Med. 2007 Aug 21;147(4):242-50.</citation>
    <PMID>17709758</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Markello TC, Bernardini IM, Gahl WA. Improved renal function in children with cystinosis treated with cysteamine. N Engl J Med. 1993 Apr 22;328(16):1157-62.</citation>
    <PMID>8455682</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nesterova G, Gahl W. Nephropathic cystinosis: late complications of a multisystemic disease. Pediatr Nephrol. 2008 Jun;23(6):863-78. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18008091</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 6, 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 25, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 25, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 28, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 19, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 19, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 20, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cystinosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Myopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Recombiant Growth Hormone</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cystinosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hormones</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

