<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02128971</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AM-FEB-INDO-2013-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02128971</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Compare the Gastrointestinal Tolerability of Ferrochel®, Sumalate®,Ferrous Fumarate, Ferrous Sulfate, Ferric Glycinate, and Placebo</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study to Compare the Gastrointestinal Tolerability of Ferrochel®, Sumalate®,Ferrous Fumarate, Ferrous Sulfate, Ferric Glycinate, and Placebo</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Albion</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sprim Advanced Life Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Albion</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the gastrointestinal (GI) tolerability of 5 different
      iron supplements (Ferrochel®, Sumalate®,ferrous fumarate, ferrous sulfate and ferric
      glycinate) at the same dose (90mg) and placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Anemia, the most common disorder of blood, is characterized by a decrease in number of red
      blood cells (RBCs) or less than normal quantity of hemoglobin in blood.Hemoglobin is an
      oxygen-carrying protein inside RBCs that transports oxygen from the respiratory organs to the
      rest of body. Several vitamins, minerals and nutrients are required for the development and
      production of RBCs, such as vitamin B12, folic acid and iron. Iron is an essential component
      of hemoglobin. Iron deficiency accounts for half of the anemia cases worldwide, and iron
      deficiency anemia is the most common nutritional disorder in the world.Iron deficiency can be
      the result of inadequate intake in the diet, poor absorption, the extra needs during growth
      or pregnancy, and blood loss. Thus, children and women are at highest risk.

      Full blood count and hemoglobin measurements are used to diagnose anemia, and measurement of
      serum ferritin level (cutoff of 12-15 mg/l) is considered as the best single and non-invasive
      test for the diagnosis of iron-deficiency. Treatment of anemia depends on the cause and the
      severity. Oral iron supplement is the simplest and most cost-effective option to treat anemia
      and replenish body storage.

      The objective of this clinical trial is to compare the gastrointestinal (GI) tolerability of
      5 different iron supplements (Ferrochel®, Sumalate®,ferrous fumarate, ferrous sulfate and
      ferric glycinate) at the same dose (90mg)and placebo. The primary objective is to compare the
      gastrointestinal tolerability of the above quoted products through:

        -  Self-assessment questionnaires - Gastrointestinal Symptoms Questionnaire5

        -  Self reported diaries

      The Secondary objective of the study is to assess the change from baseline of the parameters
      below:

        -  Hemoglobin level

        -  Hematocrit level

        -  Ferritin level

      This prospective clinical trial is a single-center, six-arms, randomized, double-blinded,
      parallel study. Subject will be screened according to inclusion exclusion criteria, and blood
      sample will be collected to ensure the hemoglobin and ferritin levels. Subject also will be
      asked to complete the Gastrointestinal Symptoms Questionnaire. The study product will be
      administered 30 days, orally once daily in the morning after breakfast. The study plan as
      follow:

      Visit 1: Screening / Baseline (day -7)

        1. Protocol information will be given by the investigator to potential subjects. Each
           participant will sign a consent form that further explains what is entailed by
           participating in the study as well as providing subjects with information on how to
           report any adverse events (AEs) that may arise.

        2. Collection of demographic information and medical history.

        3. A 10-mL blood sample will be collected by venipuncture for lab analysis of hemoglobin
           and ferritin.

        4. Subjects will complete the Gastrointestinal Symptoms Questionnaire for baseline record.

        5. Subjects that meet the inclusion and exclusion criteria will be scheduled for visit 2

      Visit 2: Day 0

        1. PI or designee will assign an unique subject ID number to each eligible subject in
           ascending order; the subject ID corresponds to an assigned investigational product code
           on the subject list and to the label on the investigational product (IP) given to the
           subject.

        2. Subjects will complete the Gastrointestinal Symptoms Questionnaire.

        3. A 10-ml blood sample will be collected by venipuncture for lab analysis of hemoglobin,
           ferritin and hematocrit.

        4. Subject diary will be dispensed.

        5. The PI or designee will dispense the investigational product capsules to subjects,
           according to the subject list provided. Each subject will receive sufficient
           investigational product capsules to last for 30 days.

        6. Subjects will begin to consume the investigational product capsule once a day, at the
           same time after breakfast, for 30 days starting on Day 1.

      Visit 3: Day 15 Window period ± 2 days will be allowed for this visit

        1. A 10-ml blood sample will be collected by venipuncture for lab analysis of hemoglobin,
           ferritin and hematocrit.

        2. Subjects will bring their unused IP to the study site. Compliance will be monitored by
           counting the remaining investigational product capsules. The remaining IP capsules will
           then be returned to the subject.

        3. Subjects will complete the Gastrointestinal Symptoms Questionnaire.

        4. Subject's diary will be collected and new diary will be dispensed.

      Visit 4: Day 30 Window period ± 2 days will be allowed for this visit

        1. A 10-mlblood sample will be collected by venipuncture for lab analysis of hemoglobin,
           ferritin and hematocrit.

        2. The PI or designee will collect any remaining investigational product. Compliance will
           be monitored by counting the remaining investigational product capsules.

        3. Subjects will complete the Gastrointestinal Symptoms Questionnaire.

        4. Subject's diary will be collected.

        5. New Subject diary will be dispensed.

      Visit 5: Day 37 Window period ± 2 days will be allowed for this visit

        1. Subjects will complete the Gastrointestinal Symptoms Questionnaire.

        2. Subject diaries will be collected.

      Adverse Event and Serious Adverse Event will be recorded since the subjects begin consuming
      the investigational product and throughout the study. SAE should be recorded in the SAE form
      and reported to Sponsor or CRA within 24 hours. All SAE will be reported to Ethic Committee
      and Regulatory Authority.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Gastrointestinal questionnaire to measure the gastrointestinal tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>change from baseline in Gastrointestinal questionnaire on 7 days after the last dose of 30 days investigational product consumption</time_frame>
    <description>The gastrointestinal tolerability of the products will be assessed by self-assessment questionnaires and self-reported diaries at baseline (screening), day 0, day 15, day 30 of investigational product consumption, and 7 days after finished the investigational product.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the laboratory result to measure the change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 30 days of investigational product consumption</time_frame>
    <description>hemoglobin levels of each subject will be measured at baseline (screening), day 0, day 15 and day 30 of investigational product consumption</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the laboratory result to measure the change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 30 days of investigational product consumption</time_frame>
    <description>Hematocrit levels of each subject will be measured at baseline (screening), day 0, day 15 and day 30 of investigational product consumption</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the laboratory result to measure the change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 30 days of investigational product consumption</time_frame>
    <description>Ferritin levels of each subject will be measured at baseline (screening), day 0, day 15 and day 30 of investigational product consumption</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">108</enrollment>
  <condition>Anemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ferrochel® 90 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ferrochel® capsule 90 mg OD for 30 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sumalate® 90 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sumalate® capsule 90 mg OD for 30 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ferrous Fumarate 90 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ferrous Fumarate capsule 90 mg OD for 30 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ferrous Sulfate 90 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ferrous Sulfate capsule 90 mg OD for 30 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ferric glycinate 90 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ferric glycinate capsule 90 mg OD for 30 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo capsule OD for 30 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ferrochel® 90 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Ferrochel® capsule 90 mg, administered orally once daily in the morning after breakfast, for 30 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ferrochel® 90 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ferrous Bisglycinate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sumalate® 90 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Sumalate® capsule 90 mg, administered orally once daily in the morning after breakfast, for 30 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sumalate® 90 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ferrous aspartoglycinate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ferrous fumarate 90 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Ferrous fumarate capsule 90 mg, administered orally once daily in the morning after breakfast, for 30 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ferrous Fumarate 90 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ferrous Sulfate 90 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Ferrous Sulfate capsule 90 mg, administered orally once daily in the morning after breakfast, for 30 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ferrous Sulfate 90 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ferric Glycinate 90 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Ferric Glycinate capsule 90 mg, administered orally once daily in the morning after breakfast, for 30 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ferric glycinate 90 mg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo capsule, administered orally once daily in the morning after breakfast, for 30 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Women, 18-50 years of age, inclusive

          2. Hemoglobin 8 g/dl - 11 g/dl

          3. Ferritin levels &lt; 20 mcg/l (20 ng/mL)

          4. Subject, or subject's acceptable representative, has voluntarily signed and dated an
             informed consent form, approved by a local Ethics Committee/Institutional Review Board
             prior to any participation in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant or lactating

          2. Amenorrhea

          3. Severe anemia (hemoglobin 7 g/dl) or other blood abnormality (e.g., leukopenia,
             thrombocytopenia, polycythemia vera)

          4. Serious illness that may confound study results or interfere with compliance

          5. Subjects that have followed specific diet, eg. high protein diet, within 30 days prior
             to study start

          6. Subjects that have taken iron supplements within 30 days prior to study start

          7. Subjects that are allergic to any of the ingredients in the products

          8. Participation in other clinical trials within three months prior to screening

          9. Known intolerance to oral iron supplements

         10. Habitual smokers (more than 3 cigarettes per week)

         11. Other medical conditions that, in the investigator's opinion, may confound study
             results or prelude the subject's ability to safely complete the trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yahdiana Harahap, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Laboratory Faculty of Pharmacy, Universitas Indonesia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eka Windari Rusman</last_name>
    <phone>+62 21 83701201</phone>
    <email>eka.windari@sprim.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jennifer Hartle</last_name>
    <phone>8017734631</phone>
    <email>jhartle@albionminerals.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Laboratory Faculty of Pharmacy, Universitas Indonesia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Depok</city>
        <state>West Java</state>
        <zip>16424</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yahdiana Harahap, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>+62-21-7270031</phone>
      <email>yahdiana.ms@ui.ac.id</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Indonesia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 21, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 30, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 1, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 5, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 5, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 6, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Iron supplement study</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ferrous fumarate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glycine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

