<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02124967</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014-0029-B</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02124967</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Mosque-Based Intervention to Promote Physical Activity in South Asian Muslim Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Exploring the Feasibility, Acceptability, and Effectiveness of a Mosque-Based Intervention to Promote Physical Activity in South Asian Muslim Women: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Women's College Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Women's College Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      South Asian (SA) women living in Ontario have a higher risk of developing type 2 diabetes and
      coronary heart disease (CHD) compared to the general population. Various explanations for
      these differences have been established, one of which is based on low levels of physical
      activity in people of SA origin, particularly in Muslim women.

      This pilot trial will test the feasibility, acceptability and effectiveness of a Mosque-based
      exercise and educational intervention designed for SA Muslim women.

        1. What is the feasibility of a mosque-based intervention to promote physical activity that
           is culturally and gender sensitive to South Asian Muslim women?

        2. What is the acceptability of a mosque-based intervention to promote physical activity
           that is culturally and gender sensitive to South Asian Muslim women?

        3. What is the effectiveness of a mosque-based intervention to promote physical activity
           that is culturally and gender sensitive to South Asian Muslim women?
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      South Asian (SA) women (people with origins in Pakistan, India, Bangladesh or Sri Lanka)
      living in Ontario have a higher risk of developing type 2 diabetes and coronary heart disease
      (CHD) compared to the general population. Various explanations for these differences have
      been established, one of which is based on low levels of physical activity in people of SA
      origin, particularly in Muslim women. Studies suggest that they participate in less physical
      activity or recreational exercise compared to other SA women. Practical barriers (e.g. lack
      of time, childcare) are often interwoven with cultural barriers, such as restrictions leaving
      the home alone to enter mixed-gender settings, and lack of socialization into sporting and
      other outdoor activities) inhibit participation.

      The provision of culturally and gender sensitive facilities, such as women-only exercise
      sessions at mosques could serve as a solution for Ontario SA Muslim women to be more active.
      Studies indicate health promotion programs in religious institutions (e.g. churches) have
      demonstrated clinical and psychosocial benefit to women of various ethnic groups. Similar to
      Canadian churches, mosques have key elements identified in the literature to be beneficial in
      providing physical activity opportunities for Muslim women: partnerships, available and
      accessible space and supportive social relationships.

      To the investigators' knowledge, mosque-based physical activity interventions for SA Muslim
      women have not been implemented and evaluated in Ontario. Such interventions are needed to
      help attenuate the risk of diabetes and CHD in this ethnic group who represent a significant
      part of the Ontario population.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of exercise sessions attended</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Participants are eligible to attend up to 3 exercise sessions per week over a period of 10 weeks. The number of sessions attended will be counted.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Duke Activity Status Index (DASI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in DASI at 10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The DASI is a self-administered questionnaire that measures functional capacity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the International Physical Activity Questionaire (IPAQ)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline in IPAQ at 10 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>The IPAQ measures health related physical activity.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Physical Activity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A one hour exercise session which includes both aerobic activity and resistance training</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>A one hour exercise class including both aerobic activity and resistance training</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Muslim women attending Madinah Mosque

        Exclusion Criteria:

        men
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer AD Price, RN,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Women's College Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ananya T Banerjee, RegKin,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Women's College Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jennifer Price</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5S 1B2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anand SS, Yusuf S, Vuksan V, Devanesen S, Teo KK, Montague PA, Kelemen L, Yi C, Lonn E, Gerstein H, Hegele RA, McQueen M. Differences in risk factors, atherosclerosis, and cardiovascular disease between ethnic groups in Canada: the Study of Health Assessment and Risk in Ethnic groups (SHARE). Lancet. 2000 Jul 22;356(9226):279-84.</citation>
    <PMID>11071182</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chiu M, Austin PC, Manuel DG, Tu JV. Cardiovascular risk factor profiles of recent immigrants vs long-term residents of Ontario: a multi-ethnic study. Can J Cardiol. 2012 Jan-Feb;28(1):20-6. doi: 10.1016/j.cjca.2011.06.002. Epub 2011 Aug 9.</citation>
    <PMID>21827964</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Banerjee AT, Gupta M, Singh N. Patient characteristics, compliance, and exercise outcomes of South Asians enrolled in cardiac rehabilitation. J Cardiopulm Rehabil Prev. 2007 Jul-Aug;27(4):212-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17667016</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bryan SN, Tremblay MS, Pérez CE, Ardern CI, Katzmarzyk PT. Physical activity and ethnicity: evidence from the Canadian Community Health Survey. Can J Public Health. 2006 Jul-Aug;97(4):271-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16967744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Williams ED, Stamatakis E, Chandola T, Hamer M. Physical activity behaviour and coronary heart disease mortality among South Asian people in the UK: an observational longitudinal study. Heart. 2011 Apr;97(8):655-9. doi: 10.1136/hrt.2010.201012. Epub 2010 Dec 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21131381</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carroll R, Ali N, Azam N. Promoting physical activity in South Asian Muslim women through &quot;exercise on prescription&quot;. Health Technol Assess. 2002;6(8):1-101. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12000689</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lawton J, Ahmad N, Hanna L, Douglas M, Hallowell N. 'I can't do any serious exercise': barriers to physical activity amongst people of Pakistani and Indian origin with Type 2 diabetes. Health Educ Res. 2006 Feb;21(1):43-54. Epub 2005 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>15955792</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campbell MK, Hudson MA, Resnicow K, Blakeney N, Paxton A, Baskin M. Church-based health promotion interventions: evidence and lessons learned. Annu Rev Public Health. 2007;28:213-34. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17155879</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Banerjee AT, Boyle MH, Anand SS, Strachan PH, Oremus M. The relationship between religious service attendance and coronary heart disease and related risk factors in Saskatchewan, Canada. J Relig Health. 2014 Feb;53(1):141-56. doi: 10.1007/s10943-012-9609-6.</citation>
    <PMID>22576676</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Banerjee AT, Strachan PH, Boyle MH, Anand SS, Oremus M. Attending religious services and its relationship with coronary heart disease and related risk factors in older adults: a qualitative study of church pastors' and parishioners' perspectives. J Relig Health. 2014 Dec;53(6):1770-85. doi: 10.1007/s10943-013-9783-1.</citation>
    <PMID>24132458</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rolfe DE, Sutton EJ, Landry M, Sternberg L, Price JA. Women's experiences accessing a women-centered cardiac rehabilitation program: a qualitative study. J Cardiovasc Nurs. 2010 Jul-Aug;25(4):332-41. doi: 10.1097/JCN.0b013e3181c83f6b.</citation>
    <PMID>20539167</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Price J, Landry M, Rolfe D, Delos-Reyes F, Groff L, Sternberg L. Women's cardiac rehabilitation: improving access using principles of women's health. Can J Cardiovasc Nurs. 2005;15(3):32-41. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16295796</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hlatky MA, Boineau RE, Higginbotham MB, Lee KL, Mark DB, Califf RM, Cobb FR, Pryor DB. A brief self-administered questionnaire to determine functional capacity (the Duke Activity Status Index). Am J Cardiol. 1989 Sep 15;64(10):651-4.</citation>
    <PMID>2782256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Craig CL, Marshall AL, Sjöström M, Bauman AE, Booth ML, Ainsworth BE, Pratt M, Ekelund U, Yngve A, Sallis JF, Oja P. International physical activity questionnaire: 12-country reliability and validity. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2003 Aug;35(8):1381-95.</citation>
    <PMID>12900694</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 24, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 25, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 28, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 10, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 10, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 11, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Women's College Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jennifer Price</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Advance Practice Nurse, Cardiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

