<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02127112</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14.0265</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02127112</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ridge Augmentation Comparing a Block Allograft to a Demineralized Bone Matrix Allograft.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Ridge Augmentation Comparing the Clinical and Histologic Healing of a Cancellous Block Allograft Plus Optecure Containing Cortico-Cancellous Chips Versus Optecure Containing Cortico-Cancellous Chips Alone.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Louisville</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Louisville</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study with compare the ridge dimension changes for a block allograft vs. a demineralized
      bone matrix moldable allograft.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The patients' treatment will be randomly assigned by coin toss done by the mentor immediately
      after flap reflection. The examiner will be blinded to the treatment and will not have access
      to information indicating treatment assignment. The examiner will never see the patient
      between the time of grafting and complete healing at 4 months. The surgical procedure will
      consist of the reflection of a split-thickness flap to expose the alveolar ridge. Following
      complete exposure of the surgical site, vertical measurements will be taken with the acrylic
      occlusal stent in place, and horizontal measurements with a specially designed digital
      caliper. After initial surgical measurements, numerous cortical perforations will be
      performed with a round bur in the area of the augmentation. The control group will receive a
      block graft and bone screw for stabilization, with voids being filled by the Optecure+CCC®.
      The test group therapy will include graft with the Optecure+CCC® and the use of Bone Pin® for
      space maintenance. Horizontal dimension will be established by graft dimensions, bone screws,
      or bone pins when necessary, for each planned implant area. Longer span edentulous spaces
      will be divided into individual sites as follows: 5 mm from natural teeth to future
      mid-implant sites and 7 mm between two future mid-implant sites. The bone pins and bone
      blocks with bone screws will be placed to allow enough exposure for augmentation to achieve 9
      mm horizontal width available for implant placement. Vertical and horizontal measurements
      will again be taken with the acrylic occlusal stent and calipers prior to flap closure. An
      resorbable membrane will cover both test and control groups. A monofilament suture material
      will be used. The surgical procedures will be documented with clinical photographs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Site width (horizontal) changes by comparing the pre- to post-augmentation dimensions of hard tissues.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of the horizontal changes will be completed with a manual periodontal probe</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Site height (vertical) changes by comparing the pre- to the post-augmentation dimensions of hard tissues.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of of height will be used with an acrylic stent and a manual periodontal probe.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Histologic composition of the healed ridge.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 month</time_frame>
    <description>At the time of re-entry, a trephine core specimen will be taken. This specimen will be examined under a microscope to determine the vital bone characteristics.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Alveolar Process Defect</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Block Allograft plus Matrix Allograft</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The positive control treatment will include a block allograft plus a demineralized bone matrix moldable allograft.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Moldable Matrix Allograft</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the test arm of the study the treatment will include a demineralized bone matrix moldable allograft.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Block Allograft plus Matrix Allograft</intervention_name>
    <description>A cancellous block allograft plus a demineralized bone matrix allograft will be used as the positive control treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Block Allograft plus Matrix Allograft</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cancellous block allograft</other_name>
    <other_name>Optecure + CCC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Moldable Matrix Allograft</intervention_name>
    <description>The test arm of this study will include a demineralized bone matrix allograft placed over resorbable bone pins.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Block Allograft plus Matrix Allograft</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Moldable Matrix Allograft</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Optecure + CCC</other_name>
    <other_name>Resorbable bone pins</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  At least a one tooth area with a ridge defect, treatment planned to receive a dental
             implant. The site must be bordered by at least one tooth.

          -  Healthy person that is at least 18 years old.

          -  Patient understands and signs an informed consent approved by the University of
             Louisville Human Studies Committee.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with debilitating systemic diseases, diseases that significantly affect the
             periodontium, or psychological problems that would interfere with treatment.

          -  Previous head and neck radiation or chemotherapy within the previous 12 months.

          -  Patients with known allergy to any of the materials that will be used in the study.

          -  Smokers.

          -  Patients who need prophylactic antibiotics prior to dental procedures.

          -  Patients on long-term steroid therapy or oral bisphosphonates &gt; 3 years or any IV
             bisphosphonates.

          -  Patients who are pregnant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Henry Greenwell, DMD, MSD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Louisville</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Graduate Periodontics Clinic, University of Louisville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Louisville</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>U of L Dental School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Louisville</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 28, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 28, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 30, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 6, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 6, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 8, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Louisville</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Henry Greenwell</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ridge Augmentation</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone regeneration</keyword>
  <keyword>Guided Bone Regeneration</keyword>
  <keyword>Partially Edentulous</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

