<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02125487</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PED.RS1.03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02125487</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hybrid Simulation in Teaching Clinical Breast Examination</brief_title>
  <acronym>HS-CBE</acronym>
  <official_title>The Use of Hybrid Simulation (HS) of the Breast in Teaching Clinical Breast Examination (CBE) to Medical Students.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>American University of Beirut Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>American University of Beirut Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether the use of hybrid simulation of the breast
      are more effective in teaching CBE technique and culturally sensitive doctor-patient
      communication skills to medical students than the traditional method.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Breast cancer is a Lebanese national problem. Campaigns for mammography screening are
      effective but recommendations on breast examinations screening for breast tumors are lacking.
      On one hand, the Lebanese population is culturally diverse, with women's beliefs ranging from
      liberal to extremely conservative. On the other hand, Clinical Breast Examination (CBE) is
      traditionally taught to medicine III students in a lecture, followed by practice on a
      low-fidelity breast model. The opportunity to clinically practice CBE depends on patient
      availability and her willingness to be examined by students. This is further limited by some
      Lebanese women's cultural and religious beliefs. Little is known about the effect of patient
      cultural practices on the efficacy of CBE.

      In this project, we focus on the need for an effective educational tool for teaching CBE to
      physicians-in-training. The proposed teaching method in this study is hybrid simulation:
      breast model jacket (simulator) worn by a trained actress (standardized patient, SP). In this
      study, we compare this standardized educational tool to the traditional teaching method which
      consists of a lecture and training on a low-fidelity (unrealistic) breast model on a desk (no
      SP).

      We hypothesize that the use of this hybrid simulation tool, as compared to the traditional
      teaching method, will result in a more complete CBE, better lesion detection and improved
      culturally sensitive communication skills in terms of awareness of, and ability to deal with,
      cultural differences related to breast examination.

      In order to do so, we will evaluate medical students' performance and examine their attitudes
      and cultural competencies when they perform CBEs on 3 culturally different standardized
      patients using hybrid simulation scenarios. Through an experimental design that minimizes
      biases related to selection of students (randomized controlled), we will compare hybrid
      simulation (intervention) with low-fidelity simulation (control) in teaching CBE.

      Medicine-III students rotating in the Obstetrics and Gynecology department at the American
      University of Beirut Medical Center (AUBMC) will be asked to participate; they are free to
      refuse without any effect on their grades in the rotation. The students will be assessed in
      an Objective Structured Clinical Examination (OSCE) setting similar to their usual oral
      clinical exams but not contributory to their academic evaluation in the Faculty of Medicine.
      The OSCE setting will include encounters with 3 culturally different Standardized Patients (1
      &quot;outgoing&quot; woman, 1 with &quot;chador&quot;, and 1 moderately conservative woman). The assessment tools
      are questionnaires that are either objective (filled by SP) or self-reporting (filled by
      students) about (1) met learning objectives, (2) student's attitude, and (3) clinical
      cultural competency.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CBE completeness (in OSCE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Each participant will be assessed once, after an average of 2-3 weeks following the intervention (teaching activity)</time_frame>
    <description>SPs will be objectively grading the students on a scoring sheet</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Student's attitude about the teaching activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Each participant will be assessed once, after an average of 2-3 weeks following the intervention (teaching activity)</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported questionnaires</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cultural communication skills (in OSCE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Each participant will be assessed once, after an average of 2-3 weeks following the intervention (teaching activity)</time_frame>
    <description>SPs will be objectively grading the students on a scoring sheet</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Student's attitude about the assessment activity (OSCE)</measure>
    <time_frame>On the day of the assessment activity, after an average of 2-3 weeks following the intervention (teaching activity)</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported questionnaires</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">82</enrollment>
  <condition>Medical Education</condition>
  <condition>Clinical Breast Examination</condition>
  <condition>Medical Simulation</condition>
  <condition>Standardized Patient</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Low-Fidelity Simulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Teaching using traditional method</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hybrid Simulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Teaching using Hybrid Simulation of breast examination</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Teaching using Hybrid Simulation of breast examination</intervention_name>
    <description>Students in the &quot;intervention/experimental&quot; group will receive the regular lecture given at the American University of Beirut and will attend a screening of an educational video on the technique of CBE, in addition to the hybrid simulation teaching activities in the simulation lab (standardized patient wearing breast examination simulator jackets)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hybrid Simulation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Standardized Patient wearing breast jacket</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Teaching using traditional method</intervention_name>
    <description>Students in the &quot;control&quot; group will receive the regular lecture given at the American University of Beirut and will attend the usual simulation lab teaching activities (single breast silicone model without any actors). The only new introduction to the curriculum is an educational video on the technique of CBE.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Low-Fidelity Simulation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lecture with low-fidelity breast model</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Third year medical students (Med III) at the American University of Beirut

          -  Rotating in the Obstetrics and Gynecology department at the American University of
             Beirut Medical Center

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Abdul Karim Sleiman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>American University of Beirut Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rana Sharara-Chami, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>American University of Beirut Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>American University of Beirut Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beirut</city>
        <country>Lebanon</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Lebanon</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coleman EA, Stewart CB, Wilson S, Cantrell MJ, O'Sullivan P, Carthron DO, Wood LC. An evaluation of standardized patients in improving clinical breast examinations for military women. Cancer Nurs. 2004 Nov-Dec;27(6):474-82.</citation>
    <PMID>15640625</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Costanza ME, Luckmann R, Quirk ME, Clemow L, White MJ, Stoddard AM. The effectiveness of using standardized patients to improve community physician skills in mammography counseling and clinical breast exam. Prev Med. 1999 Oct;29(4):241-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10547049</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Facione NC, Katapodi M. Culture as an influence on breast cancer screening and early detection. Semin Oncol Nurs. 2000 Aug;16(3):238-47. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10967796</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pugh CM, Salud LH; Association for Surgical Education. Fear of missing a lesion: use of simulated breast models to decrease student anxiety when learning clinical breast examinations. Am J Surg. 2007 Jun;193(6):766-70.</citation>
    <PMID>17512293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schubart JR, Erdahl L, Smith JS Jr, Purichia H, Kauffman GL, Kass RB. Use of breast simulators compared with standardized patients in teaching the clinical breast examination to medical students. J Surg Educ. 2012 May-Jun;69(3):416-22. doi: 10.1016/j.jsurg.2011.10.005. Epub 2011 Nov 25.</citation>
    <PMID>22483147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 18, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 28, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 29, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 22, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 22, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>American University of Beirut Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rana Sharara</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Simulation Program Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Clinical Breast Examination</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer detection</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast Simulator</keyword>
  <keyword>Hybrid Simulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient Simulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Standardized Patient</keyword>
  <keyword>Medical student education</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Communication</keyword>
  <keyword>Communication Barriers</keyword>
  <keyword>Cultural competency</keyword>
  <keyword>Cultural</keyword>
  <keyword>Middle East</keyword>
  <keyword>Lebanon</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

