<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02122770</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C15011</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1155-6191</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02122770</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Fluconazole and Itraconazole CYP3A-Mediated Inhibition on the Pharmacokinetics, Safety, and Tolerability of MLN4924 in Participants With Advanced Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1 Study to Evaluate the Effects of Fluconazole and Itraconazole CYP3A-Mediated Inhibition on the Pharmacokinetics, Safety, and Tolerability of MLN4924 in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this study is to assess the effect of multiple-dose administration of
      fluconazole on the single-dose intravenous (IV) pharmacokinetics (PK) of MLN4924; and to
      assess the effect of multiple-dose administration of itraconazole on the single-dose IV PK of
      MLN4924.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The drug being tested in this study is MLN4924. MLN4924 is being evaluated to assess
      drug-drug interactions (DDIs) with the moderate and strong CYP3A inhibitors, fluconazole and
      itraconazole, respectively, in participants with advanced solid tumors. This study will look
      at the blood concentrations of MLN4924 as it relates to treatment with fluconazole and
      itraconazole.

      The study will enroll approximately 52 participants. In Part A, participants will be
      administered MLN4924 via a 1-hour (+- 5 minutes) intravenous (IV) infusion in combination
      with either fluconazole or itraconazole administered orally. After participants complete Part
      A, they will have the opportunity to begin treatment in Part B. In Part B, participants will
      be administered MLN4924 via a 1-hour (+- 5 minutes) IV infusion in combination with either
      docetaxel or carboplatin + paclitaxel, the three of which would also be administered
      intravenously.

      This multi-center trial will be conducted in the United States. Participation in Part A of
      this study will include a screening visit and two weeks of treatment; participation in Part B
      of this study will include up to an 8-week drug washout period (from last dosing in Part A)
      and treatment until participants experience symptomatic deterioration, progressive disease,
      until treatment is discontinued for another reason, or until the study is stopped.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 5, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 5, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax: Maximum Observed Plasma Concentration for MLN4924 (Part A)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 8 predose, end of infusion, and 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48, and 72 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>Maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax) is the peak plasma concentration of a drug after administration, obtained directly from the plasma concentration-time curve.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC(0-tlast): Area Under the Plasma Concentration-Time Curve From Time 0 to the Time of the Last Quantifiable Concentration for MLN4924 (Part A)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 8 predose, end of infusion, and 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48, and 72 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>AUC(0-tlast) is a measure of total plasma exposure to the drug from time 0 to time of the last quantifiable concentration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC(0-inf): Area Under the Plasma Concentration-time Curve From Time 0 to Infinity for MLN4924 (Part A)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 8 predose, end of infusion, and 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48, and 72 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>AUC(0-inf) is a measure of total plasma exposure to the drug from time zero extrapolated to infinity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events (TEAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>First dose of study drug through 30 days (+ 10 days) after last dose of study drug; serious adverse events will be recorded from signing of the informed consent form through 30 days (+ 10 days) after last dose of study drug.</time_frame>
    <description>TEAEs are defined as any unfavorable and unintended sign, symptom or disease temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product reported from first dose of study drug through 30 days (+ 10 days) after the last dose of study drug or, if a serious adverse event, reported from the signing of the informed consent form through 30 days (+ 10 days) after the last dose of study drug.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Potentially Clinically Significant Laboratory Evaluation Findings</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Laboratory tests for hematology, serum chemistry and urinalysis will be performed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Weight Measurements (Part A)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to Day 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Potentially Clinically Significant Vital Sign Findings</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Participants with at least one potentially clinically significant post-baseline vital sign finding. Vital signs will include body temperature (oral temperature), sitting blood pressure (after sitting for 5 minutes), and pulse (bpm).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clearance (CL) Pharmacokinetic Parameter (Part A)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 8 predose, end of infusion, and 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48, and 72 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>Clearance of the drug from the plasma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tmax: Time to Reach the Maximum Plasma Concentration (Cmax) for MLN4924 (Part A)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 8 predose, end of infusion, and 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48, and 72 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>Time to reach the maximum plasma concentration (Cmax), equal to time (hours) to Cmax.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Volume-Steady State (Vss) Pharmacokinetic Parameter (Part A)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 8 predose, end of infusion, and 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48, and 72 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>Volume of distribution at steady state.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal Elimination Half-life (T1/2) Pharmacokinetic Parameter for MLN4924 (Part A)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 8 predose, end of infusion, and 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48, and 72 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>Terminal Phase Elimination Half-life (T1/2) is the time required for half of the drug to be eliminated from the plasma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood to plasma (B/P) ratio for MLN4924 (Part A)</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 and 8 predose, end of infusion, and 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 8, 12, 24, 48, and 72 hours postdose</time_frame>
    <description>The B/P ratio of MLN4924 will be derived from plasma and whole blood concentration data.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of Disease Response (Part B)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 15 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Based on investigator's assessment using the Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) guideline (Version 1.1).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MLN4924 + Fluconazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Part A: MLN4924, 8 milligram per square meter (mg/m^2), intravenously, once on Days 1 and 8; and fluconazole, 400 milligram (mg), tablets, orally, once on Day 4, and 200 mg, once daily on Days 5-10.
Part B: MLN4924, at a dose previously deemed tolerable, given on Days 1, 3, and 5 of each 21-day Cycle (Study C15010, Clinicaltrials.gov Identifier # NCT01862328) in combination with docetaxel or carboplatin + paclitaxel at standard dose regimen on Day 1 of each 21-day Cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MLN4924 + Itraconazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Part A: MLN4924, 8-mg/m^2, intravenously, once on Days 1 and 8; and itraconazole, 200 mg, oral solution, once daily on Days 4-10.
Part A (safety lead-in step): MLN4924, 15mg/m^2, intravenously, once on Days 1 and 8; and itraconazole, 200 mg, oral solution, once daily on Days 4-10.
Part A: MLN4924, 20mg/m^2, intravenously, once on Days 1 and 8; and itraconazole, 200 mg, oral solution, once daily on Days 4-10.
Part B: MLN4924, at a dose previously deemed tolerable given, on Days 1, 3, and 5 of each 21-day Cycle (Study C15010, ClinicalTrails.gov Identifier # NCT01862328) in combination with docetaxel or carboplatin + paclitaxel at standard dose regimen on Day 1 of each 21-day Cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MLN4924</intervention_name>
    <description>MLN4924 intravenous solution.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MLN4924 + Fluconazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MLN4924 + Itraconazole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluconazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Fluconazole tablets.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MLN4924 + Fluconazole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Itraconazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Itraconazole oral solution.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MLN4924 + Itraconazole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Docetaxel intravenous solution.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MLN4924 + Fluconazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MLN4924 + Itraconazole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Carboplatin intravenous solution.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MLN4924 + Fluconazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MLN4924 + Itraconazole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Paclitaxel intravenous solution.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MLN4924 + Fluconazole</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MLN4924 + Itraconazole</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female participants 18 years of age or older.

          2. Must have a histologically or cytologically confirmed metastatic or locally advanced
             and incurable solid tumor that is deemed appropriate for treatment with 1 of the 2
             chemotherapy regimens in Part B of this study, or have progressed despite standard
             therapy, or for whom conventional therapy is not considered effective. The tumor must
             be radiographically or clinically evaluable or measurable.

          3. Recovered (that is, less than or equal to (&lt;=) Grade 1 toxicity) from the effects of
             prior antineoplastic therapy.

          4. Suitable venous access for the study-required blood sampling for MLN4924
             pharmacokinetic (PK) and pharmacodynamic assessments.

          5. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status (PS) of 0 or 1.

          6. Clinical laboratory values as specified below within 3 days before the first dose of
             study drug:

               1. Hemoglobin greater than or equal to (&gt;=) 9 gram per deciliter (g/dL)

               2. Absolute neutrophil count &gt;=1,500 per cubic millimeter (/mm^3), not supported by
                  growth factor

               3. Platelet count &gt;=100,000/mm^3

               4. Total bilirubin &lt;=upper limit of normal (ULN)

               5. Prothrombin time (PT) and activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) &lt;=1.5*ULN

               6. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), and alkaline
                  phosphatase (ALP) &lt;=2.5*ULN

                  • For participants to be treated with MLN4924 + docetaxel in Part B, AST and ALT
                  must be &lt;=1.5*ULN, and total bilirubin should be within the normal range.

               7. Serum creatinine &lt;=1.2 mg/dL or calculated/measured creatinine clearance &gt;=50
                  mL/minute

          7. Female participants who:

               1. Are postmenopausal for at least 1 year before the screening visit, OR

               2. Are surgically sterile, OR

               3. If they are of childbearing potential, agree to practice 2 effective methods of
                  contraception, at the same time, from the time of signing the informed consent
                  through four months after the last dose of study drug, or

               4. Agree to practice true abstinence, when this is in line with the preferred and
                  usual lifestyle of the participant. (Periodic abstinence [example, calendar,
                  ovulation, symptothermal, postovulation methods] and withdrawal are not
                  acceptable methods of contraception.)

               5. Male participants, even if surgically sterilized (that is, status postvasectomy),
                  who:

               6. Agree to practice effective barrier contraception during the entire study
                  treatment period and through 4 months after the last dose of study drug, or

               7. Agree to practice true abstinence, when this is in line with the preferred and
                  usual lifestyle of the participant. (Periodic abstinence [example, calendar,
                  ovulation, symptothermal, postovulation methods for the female partner] and
                  withdrawal are not acceptable methods of contraception.)

          8. Voluntary written consent must be given before performance of any study-related
             procedure not part of standard medical care, with the understanding that consent may
             be withdrawn by the participant at any time without prejudice to future medical care.

          9. Participants who are willing to refrain from donating blood for at least 90 days after
             their final dose of MLN4924 and (for male participants) willing to refrain from
             donating semen for at least 4 months after their final dose of MLN4924.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior treatment with MLN4924; however, prior treatment with docetaxel, paclitaxel, and
             carboplatin is allowed.

          2. Treatment with any systemic antineoplastic therapy or investigational products within
             21 days before the first dose of study treatment.

          3. Radiotherapy within 14 days before the first dose of study treatment.

          4. Prior treatment with radiation therapy involving &gt;= 25 percent (%) of
             hematopoietically active bone marrow.

          5. Known hypersensitivity or history of severe intolerance or toxicity to study-assigned
             chemotherapy. Note: History of severe hypersensitivity reactions to docetaxel
             (polysorbate 80-based formulations) for participants to be treated with MLN4924 +
             docetaxel; history of hypersensitivity to carboplatin for participants to be treated
             with MLN4924 + carboplatin + paclitaxel; or history of severe hypersensitivity to
             paclitaxel (Cremophor-based formulations) for participants to be treated with MLN4924
             + carboplatin + paclitaxel in Part B.

          6. Known hypersensitivity/allergy to fluconazole or itraconazole or their respective
             excipients.

          7. Systemic treatment with moderate and strong cytochrome P450 (CYP) CYP3A inhibitors or
             inducers must be discontinued at least 14 days before the first dose of MLN4924.
             Moderate and strong CYP3A inhibitors and CYP3A inducers are not permitted during the
             study. Participants must have no history of amiodarone use in the 6 months before the
             first dose of MLN4924.

          8. Any life-threatening or serious medical or psychiatric illness unrelated to cancer
             that could, in the investigator's opinion, potentially interfere with the completion
             of treatment according to this protocol.

          9. Major surgery within 14 days before the first dose of study treatment.

         10. Active uncontrolled infection or severe infectious disease, such as pneumonia,
             meningitis, septicemia, or methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus infection.

         11. Clinically significant central nervous system disease defined as untreated,
             progressive, or requiring steroids for control of symptoms.

         12. Known gastrointestinal (GI) disease or GI procedure that could interfere with the oral
             absorption or tolerance of fluconazole or itraconazole including difficulty swallowing
             capsules.

         13. Persistent diarrhea (&gt;= Grade 2) lasting greater than (&gt;) 3 days within 2 weeks before
             the first dose of study treatment.

         14. Known hepatic cirrhosis, hepatitis B surface antigen-positive status, or suspected
             active hepatitis C infection. Note: Participants who have isolated positive hepatitis
             B core antibody (that is, in the setting of negative hepatitis B surface antigen and
             negative hepatitis B surface antibody) must have an undetectable hepatitis B viral
             load.

         15. Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive status.

         16. Female participants who are lactating and breastfeeding or have a positive serum
             pregnancy test during the Screening period or a positive urine pregnancy test on Day 1
             before first dose of study drug.

         17. Uncontrolled high blood pressure (that is, systolic blood pressure &gt;180 millimeter of
             mercury [mmHg], diastolic blood pressure &gt;95 mmHg).

         18. Left ventricular ejection fraction &lt; 50% as assessed by echocardiogram or radionuclide
             angiography.

         19. Congestive heart failure New York Heart Association Class III or IV, or Class II with
             a recent decompensation requiring hospitalization within 4 weeks before screening.

         20. Cardiomyopathy or history of ischemic heart disease.

             o Participants with ischemic heart disease who have had acute coronary syndrome (ACS),
             myocardial infarction (MI), or revascularization (example, coronary artery bypass
             graft, stent) in the past 6 months are excluded. However, participants with ischemic
             heart disease who have had ACS, MI, or revascularization greater than 6 months before
             screening and who are without cardiac symptoms may enroll.

         21. Arrhythmia (example, history of polymorphic ventricular fibrillation or torsade de
             pointes). However, participants with &lt; Grade 3 atrial fibrillation for a period of at
             least 6 months may enroll. Grade 3 atrial fibrillation is defined as symptomatic and
             incompletely controlled medically, or controlled with device (example, pacemaker) or
             ablation, and is excluded. Participants with paroxysmal atrial fibrillation are
             permitted to enroll.

         22. Prolonged rate corrected QT interval (QTc) &gt;=500 millisecond (msec), calculated
             according to institutional guidelines.

         23. Implantable cardioverter defibrillator.

         24. Participants with a cardiac pacer whose heart rate is set at a fixed rate and
             participants on concomitant medication that may limit increase in heart rate in
             response to hypotension (example, high-dose beta blocker).

         25. Moderate to severe aortic or mitral stenosis or other valvulopathy (ongoing).

         26. Known moderate to severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), interstitial
             lung disease, pulmonary fibrosis, and pulmonary arterial hypotension.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director Clinical Science</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Winship Cancer Institute at Emory University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Siteman Cancer Center - South County</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sarah Cannon Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mary Crowley Medical Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75230</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 23, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 23, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 25, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug Therapy</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albumin-Bound Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Itraconazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxyitraconazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluconazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

