<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02129582</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CASE9Z13</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-00837</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CASE9Z13</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA043703</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02129582</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Targeted Marrow Irradiation, Fludarabine Phosphate, and Busulfan Before Donor Progenitor Cell Transplant in Treating Patients With Hematologic Malignancies</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Trial of Escalated Doses of Targeted Marrow Irradiation (TMI) Combined With Fludarabine and Busulfan as Conditioning Regimen for Allogeneic Hematopoietic Progenitor Cell Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and best dose of targeted marrow irradiation when
      given with fludarabine phosphate and busulfan before donor progenitor cell transplant in
      treating patients with hematologic malignancies. Targeted marrow irradiation is a type of
      specialized radiation therapy that delivers a high dose of radiation directly to the cancer
      cells, which may kill more cancer cells and cause less damage to normal cells. Giving
      targeted marrow irradiation and chemotherapy drugs, such as fludarabine phosphate and
      busulfan, before a donor progenitor cell transplant may help stop the growth of cancer cells.
      It may also stop the patient's immune system from rejecting the donor's progenitor cells.
      When the healthy progenitor cells from a donor are infused into the patient they may help the
      patient's bone marrow make progenitor cells, red blood cells, white blood cells, and
      platelets.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the maximum tolerated dose of targeted marrow irradiation given in
      combination with fludarabine (fludarabine phosphate) and busulfan as conditioning regimen for
      allogeneic hematopoietic progenitor cell transplantation.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To describe the toxicity profile of the conditioning regimen of targeted marrow
      irradiation (TMI), fludarabine and busulfan for allogeneic hematopoietic progenitor
      transplantation.

      II. To describe the use of two techniques of delivering TMI, volumetric modulated arc therapy
      (VMAT) and TomoTherapy, on patient's computed tomography (CT) simulation images and describe
      differences in organ avoidance and target coverage, planning time, and treatment delivery
      time.

      III. To determine the disease response status 100 days after allogeneic hematopoietic
      progenitor cell transplantation with the conditioning regimen of TMI, fludarabine and
      busulfan.

      IV. To determine the rates of acute graft versus host disease after allogeneic hematopoietic
      progenitor cell transplantation with the conditioning regimen of TMI, fludarabine and
      busulfan.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose-escalation study of TMI.

      CONDITIONING: Patients undergo TMI twice daily (BID) on days -10 to -7. Patients also receive
      fludarabine phosphate intravenously (IV) over 1 hour on days -6 to -2 and busulfan IV or
      orally (PO) on days -5 and -4.

      TRANSPLANT: Patients undergo allogeneic hematopoietic progenitor cell transplant on day 0.

      GRAFT-VERSUS-HOST DISEASE (GVHD) PROPHYLAXIS: Patients receive anti-thymocyte globulin IV on
      days -3 and -2, tacrolimus IV or PO beginning on day -1 for at least 6 months with taper
      beginning at 4 months, and methotrexate IV on days 1, 3, 6, and 11.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 100 days, 6 months, and 12
      months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 6, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose of targeted marrow irradiation defined as the dose level immediately below that in which greater than or equal to 2/6 subjects experience a dose limiting toxicity assessed using NCI CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 32</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of toxicities assessed using NCI CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to day 32</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 100</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Organ avoidance</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Will be compared between the two techniques of delivering TMI (VMAT and TomoTherapy) using patients' CT simulation images.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Target coverage</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Will be compared between the two techniques of delivering TMI (VMAT and TomoTherapy) using patients' CT simulation images.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Planning time</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Will be compared between the two techniques of delivering TMI (VMAT and TomoTherapy) using patients' CT simulation images.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment delivery time</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Will be compared between the two techniques of delivering TMI (VMAT and TomoTherapy) using patients' CT simulation images.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease response status, assessed by standard criteria for the presence of relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 100</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rates of acute GVHD, graded and staged according to the Blood and Marrow Transplant Clinical Trials Network Manual of Operations</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 100 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">78</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Hematologic Malignancies</condition>
  <condition>Acute Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Non Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Myeloid Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Myelofibrosis</condition>
  <condition>Myeloproliferative Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (TMI, fludarabine, busulfan, allogeneic HPCT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CONDITIONING: Patients undergo TMI BID on days -10 to -7. Patients also receive fludarabine phosphate IV over 1 hour on days -6 to -2 and busulfan IV or PO on days -5 and -4.
TRANSPLANT: Patients undergo allogeneic hematopoietic progenitor cell transplant on day 0.
GVHD PROPHYLAXIS: Patients receive anti-thymocyte globulin IV on days -3 and -2, tacrolimus IV or PO beginning on day -1 for at least 6 months with taper beginning at 4 months, and methotrexate IV on days 1, 3, 6, and 11.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>total marrow irradiation</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo TMI</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (TMI, fludarabine, busulfan, allogeneic HPCT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fludarabine phosphate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (TMI, fludarabine, busulfan, allogeneic HPCT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>2-F-ara-AMP</other_name>
    <other_name>Beneflur</other_name>
    <other_name>Fludara</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>busulfan</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV or PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (TMI, fludarabine, busulfan, allogeneic HPCT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BSF</other_name>
    <other_name>BU</other_name>
    <other_name>Misulfan</other_name>
    <other_name>Mitosan</other_name>
    <other_name>Myeloleukon</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>myeloid progenitor cell transplantation</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo allogeneic hematopoietic progenitor cell transplant</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (TMI, fludarabine, busulfan, allogeneic HPCT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MPCT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>anti-thymocyte globulin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (TMI, fludarabine, busulfan, allogeneic HPCT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ATG</other_name>
    <other_name>ATGAM</other_name>
    <other_name>lymphocyte immune globulin</other_name>
    <other_name>Thymoglobulin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>tacrolimus</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV or PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (TMI, fludarabine, busulfan, allogeneic HPCT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FK 506</other_name>
    <other_name>Prograf</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>methotrexate</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (TMI, fludarabine, busulfan, allogeneic HPCT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>amethopterin</other_name>
    <other_name>Folex</other_name>
    <other_name>methylaminopterin</other_name>
    <other_name>Mexate</other_name>
    <other_name>MTX</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (TMI, fludarabine, busulfan, allogeneic HPCT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients ineligible to receive full myeloablative conditioning regimen for allogeneic
             hematopoietic progenitor cell transplant due to age or comorbidities

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically diagnosis of hematologic
             malignancies with an indication for allogeneic hematopoietic progenitor cell
             transplantation, who are ineligible to receive a full ablative conditioning regimen as
             part of their transplantation, including:

               -  Acute myeloid leukemia

               -  Acute lymphocytic leukemia

               -  Non Hodgkin lymphoma

               -  Hodgkin lymphoma

               -  Multiple myeloma

               -  Myelodysplastic syndrome

               -  Chronic lymphocytic leukemia

               -  Chronic myeloid leukemia:

               -  Myeloproliferative syndromes including myelofibrosis

          -  Complete remission is not necessary for enrollment in this protocol

          -  Patients must have an allogeneic hematopoietic progenitor cell donor (HPCT), either a
             matched sibling, mismatched (1 allele) sibling, or a matched unrelated donor (MUD) or
             a mismatched (1 allele) unrelated donor

               -  Previous hematopoietic progenitor cell transplantation is allowed; a minimum of 6
                  months should have elapsed from prior autologous hematopoietic progenitor cell
                  transplantation and a minimum of 6 months should have elapsed since prior
                  allogeneic hematopoietic progenitor cell transplantation; prior transplantation
                  with conditioning regimens using total body irradiation is not allowed

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status 0-2

          -  Life expectancy of &gt; 12 weeks, in the opinion of and as documented by the investigator

          -  Patients must have adequate hepatic, and renal function as defined below: there is no
             exclusion for the presence of cytopenias

               -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 times the institutional upper limit of normal

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase [SGOT])
                  ≤ 2.5 X institutional upper limit of normal

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT]) ≤
                  2.5 X institutional upper limit of normal

               -  Creatinine clearance (calculated by the Cockroft-Gault formula) ≥ 60 ml/min

               -  Pulmonary Function Tests (FEV1, FVC, DLCO) 40%.

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (double barrier method of birth control or abstinence) from the time of study entry,
             for the duration of study participation and for 3 months after completing treatment;
             should a woman become pregnant or suspect that she is pregnant while she or her
             partner is participating in this study, she should inform the treating physician
             immediately

          -  Subjects must have the ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written
             informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior non-hematologic treatment toxicities must be resolved to ≤ grade 1 according to
             National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE)
             version 4.0, with the exception of the following grade 2 toxicities: alopecia; dry
             skin; spleen disorders, hearing impairment; tinnitus; hypothyroidism; hyperthyroidism;
             endocrine disorders; blurred vision; cataracts; constipation; gastroesophageal reflux;
             fatigue; abnormal coagulation tests INR and/or aPTT; weight gain or weight loss;
             anorexia; glucose intolerance; hypoalbuminemia; hypokalemia; muscle weakness;
             dysgeusia; paresthesias; peripheral motor and/or sensory neuropathy; hot flashes;
             hypertension.

          -  Patients must not have received other investigational agents within 14 days of
             initiation of the conditioning regimen

          -  Patients with untreated brain metastases should be excluded from this clinical trial

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to fludarabine and or busulfan or other agents used in this study

          -  Prior allogeneic hematopoietic progenitor cell transplantation

          -  Prior autologous hematopoietic progenitor cell transplantation if the conditioning
             regimen included total body irradiation

          -  Patients with uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to ongoing
             or active infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris,
             cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit
             compliance with study requirements; this exclusion criterion does not include the
             underlying disease for which the patient is undergoing hematopoietic progenitor cell
             transplantation

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women are excluded from this study; breastfeeding should be
             discontinued

          -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-positive patients on combination antiretroviral
             therapy are ineligible

          -  Patients with a history of therapy with radiation therapy are excluded

          -  Due to technical limitations of TMI, patients must be no taller than 1.9 m (6 feet 4
             inches), and no wider from elbow to elbow in the supine position than 60 cm.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paolo Caimi</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospitals Cleveland Medical Center, Seidman Cancer Center, Case Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44106-5065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paolo F. Caimi</last_name>
      <phone>216-844-0139</phone>
      <email>paolo.caimi@case.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paolo F. Caimi</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 30, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 2, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hodgkin Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Primary Myelofibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myeloproliferative Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tacrolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Busulfan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thymoglobulin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antilymphocyte Serum</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vidarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

