<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02129114</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MP-CT-RK2014</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02129114</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Dural Repair Patch in Neurosurgical Repairs</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multi-Center,Randomized,Non-Inferiority and Positively Controlled Clinical Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Dural Repair Patch in Neurosurgical Repairs</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medprin Regenerative Medical Technologies Co.,Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medprin Regenerative Medical Technologies Co.,Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      1. Most of dural defects may lead to subcutaneous effusion and Cerebral Spinal Fluid (CSF)
           leakage, which may result in infection; besides, direct adhesion of brain tissues with
           sub-scalp tissues also increase the risk of epilepsy, in severe cases, dural defect is
           considered a life-threatening condition. So, it's important to repair the dura mater for
           restoring its full integrity .

        2. Dural Repair Patch(ReDura Onlay) manufactured by Guangzhou Medprin Regenerative Medical
           Technologies Co., Ltd. As a product made of clinical absorbable polymer materials by
           using bionic technology, Dural Repair Patch has highly bionic 3-dimensional structure
           which is proved to facilitate migration and growth of regenerative cells, as well as to
           accelerate the growth and repairing of regenerative meninges. While the material is
           degraded gradually and absorbed by the body, regenerative meningeal tissue is gradually
           formed, achieving true reconstruction of the dura mater.

        3. To evaluate the safety and effectiveness of Dural Repair Patch in neurosurgical repairs
           of dural defects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Dura mater is an important structural cell layer on the surface of brain serving as an
           important barrier for brain protection. Dural defects could be caused by a vast variety
           of factors, including trauma, tumor invasion, increased volume of the intra-cranial
           contents, certain congenital diseases, surgical procedures and etc. Most of dural
           defects may lead to subcutaneous effusion and CSF leakage, which may result in
           infection; besides, direct adhesion of brain tissues with sub-scalp tissues also
           increase the risk of epilepsy, in severe cases, dural defect is considered a
           life-threatening condition. Repairing of dura mater to restore its full integrity is
           proved to reduce the incidences of its complications, such as CSF leakage, epilepsy and
           etc. In particular, the outcomes of neurosurgeries are largely dependent of the
           post-operative integrity of dura mater.

        2. most of the currently available products require surgical dural suturing, which elongate
           the duration of operation; nevertheless, some surgical site are unsuitable for suturing.
           The currently marketed non-suture dural substitutes and mainly made of a single material
           with a single-layered structure, which are significantly different from the natural
           structure of extracellular matrix, poorly mimicking the microstructure of dural mater;
           hence, the structures and surface properties of such products do not meet the
           requirements for local cellular regeneration post dural repairs, resulting in poor
           repair outcomes. Besides, the increased contractility of these products after water
           absorption also impose a certain extent of risk in practical application, since dural
           repairing surgeries are mainly conducted on the defective site of soft cerebral tissues.

        3. As a product prepared by using bionic technology, Dural Repair Patch manufactured by
           Guangzhou Medprin Regenerative Medical Technologies Co., Ltd. is able to mimic porous
           fiber biomimetic structure that facilitate the cellular growth on the stent. Through
           effective control over the bionic technology parameters, the diameter, aperture and
           porosity of the fiber are almost identical to the in vivo tissue structure, so as to
           improve the cellular adhesion and growth on the sten. Increased strength, suitable
           ductility and improved hydrophilicity all contribute to the excellent flexibility and
           adhesiveness of the finished product able to adhesive closely to the autologous tissues,
           meeting the clinical requirements. Being made of absorbable polymer materials widely
           accepted in clinical product, the product has a highly bionic 3-dimensional structure
           which is proved to facilitate migration and growth of regenerative cells, as well as to
           accelerate the growth and repairing of regenerative meninges. While the material is
           degraded gradually and absorbed by the body, regenerative meningeal tissue is gradually
           formed, achieving true reconstruction of the dura mater.

        4. Design and methods

      4.1 Subjects who meet the inclusion criteria are randomized in accordance with the admission
      time; routine blood test, liver and kidney function test, as well as cellular and humoral
      immunity test are conducted prior to the surgery.

      4.2 Location, characteristics and size of the defects,as well as the conditions of surgical
      incision are all observed intra-operatively.

      4.3 Dura mater membrane repairing surgeries are conducted by closely attaching either an
      appropriately-sized test product or reference product to the defected part of dura mater
      membrane, before the incision in the skull is closed by using a conventional approach.

      4.4 The subjects'conditions are reviewed on Day 1, 3, 5, 7 and 10 post operations,
      respectively.

      4.5 Lumbar puncture is conducted on Day 10±2 post operation based on the subject's
      conditions, in order to measure the intracranial pressure and test for cerebrospinal fluid
      leakage; routine blood, liver and kidney function, as well as cellular and humoral immunity
      are re-tested on Day 10±2 post operation and the values obtained are compared with the
      pre-operative baseline measurements and recorded, so as to evaluate the clinical
      significance; On Day 10±2 post operation, cerebrospinal fluid leakage or subcutaneous
      effusion are examined by CT scan and clinical examinations, so as to assess the relationship
      of such events to the test/reference product.

      4.6 For subjects who received a re-operation in the same location or a second neurosurgery,
      the conditions of test product or reference product in the repairing site is observed, e.g.
      examine (combined with histological test) product adhesion with cerebral tissues and etc.

      4.7 The subjects are asked to attend a return visit or a telephone follow-up session on Day
      90±10 and 180±20 post operation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of successful prevention of CSF leakage</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 10±2 post operation</time_frame>
    <description>on Day 10±2 post operation, occurrence of CSF leakage is checked on both CT and clinical examination</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Healing of scalp incision</measure>
    <time_frame>6 month</time_frame>
    <description>the healing of scalp incision is reviewed on Day 3, Day 5, Day7, Day 10, Month 3 and Month 6, respectively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">132</enrollment>
  <condition>Neurosurgical Repairs</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ReDura Onlay</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Dural Repair Patch manufactured by Guangzhou Medprin Regenerative Medical Technologies Co., Ltd.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DuraGen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dural Graft Matrix manufactured by Integra LifeSciences (U.S.) Corporation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ReDura Onlay</intervention_name>
    <description>Subject will be clinically followed post-surgery until hospital discharge or within ten (10) days of the procedure and at three (3) months and six (6) months. The data up to and including the 6 month follow-up visit will be used in demonstrating the performance of ReDura Onlay.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ReDura Onlay</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DuraGen</intervention_name>
    <description>Subject will be clinically followed post-surgery until hospital discharge or within ten (10) days of the procedure and at three (3) months and six (6) months. The data up to and including the 6 month follow-up visit will be used in demonstrating the performance of DuraGen.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DuraGen</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. male or female aged 18-65 years;

          2. whose expected survival is not less than 12 months

          3. Patients with dura mater defects which occurred in a variety of neurosurgeries
             (including traumatic brain injury, brain tumors, cerebrovascular disease, congenital
             neurological diseases, intra-spinal diseases and etc.) and required surgical
             repairing.

          4. All the enrolled subjects should not present obvious pre-operative inflammation
             symptoms,

          5. Written informed consents were obtained from all of the patients and/or their
             guardians.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient who present severe visceral (heart, liver, kidney, circulation system or etc.)
             diseases.

          2. Patient with unstable vital signs.

          3. Pregnant or lactating women.

          4. Patient who have a past history of serious allergy

          5. Patient who have a past history of severe immunodeficiency disease.

          6. Other undesirable conditions set by investigators.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ke Yi Quan, professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Southern Medical University, China</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tian Quan, Manager</last_name>
    <phone>020-32296115</phone>
    <email>tianquan@medprin.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zhujiang Hospital of Southern Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>GuangZhou</city>
        <state>Guangdong</state>
        <zip>510000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ke Yi Quan, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>020-61643266</phone>
      <email>net_chn@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 1, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 2, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 8, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Estradiol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Polyestradiol phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Estradiol 3-benzoate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Estradiol 17 beta-cypionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Estradiol valerate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

