<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02129153</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB#13-001638</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02129153</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Linking Families Together Study- A Randomized Trial to Raise Parental Monitoring</brief_title>
  <acronym>LIFT</acronym>
  <official_title>Linking Families Together Study- A Randomized Trial to Raise Parental Monitoring</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study, we will evaluate the efficacy and sustainability of the Linking Families
      Together (LIFT) intervention to improve parental monitoring during the transition from middle
      to high school a particularly risky time for students' academic performance and health
      behaviors. This study is based in middle schools around Los Angeles County a region with a
      high prevalence of teen risky health behaviors.

      The aims of our study are:

        1. To conduct a randomized trial of the LIFT intervention and examine whether providing
           detailed academic information to parents during their child's 7th and 8th grade
           increases parental monitoring at the end of the two year intervention and one year
           follow up. We will partner with 3-10 middle schools and recruit 500 student-parent
           dyads: 250 will be randomized to the intervention arm and 250 to the usual care control
           group.

        2. To determine whether the LIFT intervention improves students' academic outcomes, as
           measured by grades, attendance, and standardized test scores at the end of the two year
           intervention and one year follow up.

        3. To evaluate whether the LIFT intervention lowers rates of adolescent risky health
           behaviors, specifically substance use (alcohol, marijuana, inhalants, and other drugs)
           at the end of the two year intervention and one year follow up.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Despite parental monitoring and school involvement being among the most important protective
      factors leading to positive teen academic and health trajectories, few theoretically based
      rigorously evaluated interventions test strategies to support low income parents as their
      adolescents transition from middle to high school, a particularly risky time for students'
      academic and health behaviors.

      In a successful pilot study, student's missing assignments information was communicated
      directly to parents. Intervention parents were nearly twice as likely to report their child
      not telling them enough about his or her school work than control parents. After just 6
      months, intervention students had a 0.19 standard deviation increase in GPA over the control
      group and 0.20 standard deviation higher standardized math test score.

      In the proposed study, we will evaluate the efficacy and sustainability of an intervention to
      improve parental monitoring and thus improve academic outcomes and reduce risky health
      behaviors. The adapted intervention will also include sessions for parents to build positive
      parent-child communication and awareness of school expectations.

      We propose a randomized controlled trial with 2 arms examining whether providing parents
      detailed information on their child's academic and behavioral performance in school in
      combination with basic parenting support, increases parental monitoring for low-income,
      minority families. We hypothesize that better parental monitoring will lead to improved
      academic and behavioral performance. Using this design we can determine whether the impact of
      the information and parenting intervention is also protective of teens engaging in risky
      health behaviors. We will compare the experimental and control group parents to examine
      whether providing high-quality academic information to parents of middle school students
      increases parental monitoring, student academic performance, and teen health outcomes during
      middle school and beyond.

      If the intervention boosts adolescent academic and health outcomes as hypothesized, the
      results of the proposed study offer schools low-cost strategies to simultaneously positively
      influence student academic and health trajectories. These findings have the potential to
      stimulate new research to improve health through innovative interventions to bolster parent
      teen relationships for gains accrued throughout the life span.

      The aims of our study are:

        1. To conduct a randomized trial of the LIFT intervention and examine whether providing
           detailed academic information to parents during their child's 7th and 8th grade
           increases parental monitoring at the end of the two year intervention and one year
           follow up. We will partner with 3-10 middle schools and recruit 500 student-parent
           dyads: 250 will be randomized to the intervention arm and 250 to the usual care control
           group.

        2. To determine whether the LIFT intervention improves students' academic outcomes, as
           measured by grades, attendance, and standardized test scores at the end of the two year
           intervention and one year follow up.

        3. To evaluate whether the LIFT intervention lowers rates of adolescent risky health
           behaviors, specifically substance use (alcohol, marijuana, inhalants, and other drugs)
           at the end of the two year intervention and one year follow up.

      Thus the proposed study builds on and extends the earlier pilot study by recruiting more
      middle schools around Los Angeles, offering parents additional supports through parenting
      workshops, and assessing the program's impact on adolescent behavioral outcomes. Successfully
      implementing this study will allow us to demonstrate feasibility for a future randomized
      controlled trial and assess effect size for parental monitoring and health outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 1, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 1, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 30, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants in the study do not know if they are in the intervention group.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in student 30 day alcohol use</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, two year, three year (i.e. one year follow up)</time_frame>
    <description>Student self report: During the past 30 days, on how many days did you have at least one drink of alcohol?</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in student 30 day marijuana use</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, two year, three year (i.e. one year follow up)</time_frame>
    <description>Student self report: During the past 30 days, on how many days did you use marijuana?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in parental monitoring</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, two year, three year (i.e. one year follow up)</time_frame>
    <description>Student completing validated 9-item parental monitoring scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in student standardized test scores</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, two year, three year (i.e. one year follow up)</time_frame>
    <description>Student standardized test scores</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">318</enrollment>
  <condition>Adolescent Behaviors</condition>
  <condition>Substance Abuse</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LIFT (Parent information)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>LIFT (Parent information): during their child's 7th and 8th grade years research staff will 1. communicate with parents about their child's academic and behavioral performance in school, roughly twice-monthly 2. invite parents to participate in a 2-hour parent support session to help teach parents to communicate better with their child and support better academic and behavioral performance in school
students take a baseline survey then 3 surveys (one/year)
parents take a baseline survey then 2 surveys (one/year)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care control group/No Intervention consists of neither communication of academic information to parents nor invitation to parent support sessions.
students take a baseline survey then 3 surveys (one/year)
parents take a baseline survey then 2 surveys (one/year)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LIFT (Parent Information)</intervention_name>
    <description>Parents will receive specific information about class assignments that the student missed or about poor performance on tests/quizzes. Parents will also be notified about behavioral problems, such as poor attention and class disruption. RA will communicate with parents in Spanish or English by text message, phone, email according to the parents preference for communication
Parents will be invited to parenting seminars to discuss parenting strategies regarding what to do with their child's academic and behavioral information once they receive it from research staff. Sessions will take place at school and last 2 hours. Multiple sessions will be offered throughout the academic year and parents may attend as many sessions as they wish.</description>
    <arm_group_label>LIFT (Parent information)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Information/ Linking Families Together (LIFT)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  For adults, must be a parent/guardian of a student at a participating middle school

          -  For minors, must be a student at a participating middle school

          -  Must speak English or Spanish

          -  Entering 7th grade in Fall 2014 at one of the middle schools participating in the
             study

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>11 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>15 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mitchell D Wong, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 30, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 2, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 6, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 6, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Mitchell Wong</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Randomized controlled trial</keyword>
  <keyword>Population, School Age</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

