<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02120729</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RUAN004090HE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02120729</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacogenetic Decision Support IT System for Psychiatric Hospitalization: RCT</brief_title>
  <acronym>CYP-GUIDES</acronym>
  <official_title>Pharmacogenetic Decision Support IT System for Psychiatric Hospitalization: RCT</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hartford Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hartford Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Randomized Clinical Trial (RCT) compares outcomes in 1500 patients with major depressive
      disorder (MDD) treated according to the patient's CYP2D6 genotype status (N=1000) versus
      empiric &quot;standard-of-care&quot; psychotropic therapy (N=500). The hypothesis is that provision of
      medication based on the functional status of the patient's CYP2D6 enzyme inferred from
      genotype results within 48 hours of admission to treating clinicians will, through refined
      selection of psychotropic medication during hospitalization, decrease length of psychiatric
      hospitalization stay and decrease the rate of 30 day re-admission.

      The trial setting is the Hartford Hospital Institute of Living (IOL). The IOL operates the
      Clinical Evaluation and Monitoring System (CEMS), an innovative electronic messaging system
      developed by Co-Investigator Dr. J.W. Goethe. The Hartford Hospital Genetics Research Center
      (GRC) performs the genotype testing. CYP2D6 genotype analysis detects all known polymorphisms
      that result in an enzyme with sub-normal or supra-normal function. In this study, CEMS
      transmits clinically actionable guidance based on the patient's genotype to the clinician,
      advancing the medication alerts in real time.

      The RCT will test the effects of timely incorporation of medication recommendations based on
      CYP2D6 genotype into CEMS. The RCT assigns 500 patients to standard therapy (Group S) for
      whom CYP2D6 genetic information is determined but not transmitted to the treating clinician,
      allowing psychotropic therapy to be empirically determined, and 1000 to genetically guided
      therapy (Group G) where genotyping result and treatment recommendations are furnished via
      CEMS to the clinician within 24 hours of DNA sampling and 48 hours of admission. For patients
      in Group G who are poor or rapid metabolizers, medications primarily metabolized by the
      CYP2D6 enzyme are proscribed.

      The primary outcome is hospital length of stay and the secondary outcome, the frequency of 30
      day hospital readmission. Additional genetic stratification of both Group S and Group G will
      allow investigation of specific psychotropic usage.

      The expected benefits are 1) quantitative understanding of the effect of providing CYP2D6
      pharmacogenetic information on length of hospitalization, 30 day readmission rate, and
      associated costs; and 2) objective benchmarking for the comparative effectiveness of CYP2D6
      genotyping for guiding psychotropic therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Over 1.4 million hospitalizations for mental health conditions occur annually in the United
      States (3.4% of all hospitalizations), and more than half are for major depressive disorder
      (MDD). Remarkably, of the 30 antidepressant and antipsychotic medications available to treat
      MDD, nearly 50% are primarily metabolized by the liver enzyme encoded by the CYP2D6 gene. The
      CYP2D6 gene is notable for common sequence and structural polymorphisms which markedly affect
      the enzyme's capacity, causing a decrease or increase in drug metabolism in 60% of patients,
      and creating challenges for therapeutic management. The metabolic alterations caused by
      CYP2D6 gene polymorphisms may require longer hospitalizations due to &quot;trial-and-error&quot;
      prescribing, which delays improvement in health status and consumes resources. Reliable
      genotype testing is now available to detect an array of 19 gene alterations. Prescribing
      psychotropics using knowledge of the patient's CYP2D6 gene status is potentially cost
      effective.

      For this research, the Genetics Research Center performs the CYP2D6 genotyping, and the
      Institute of Living's Clinical Evaluation and Monitoring System (CEMS) transmits explicit
      alerts regarding prescription or proscription of specific psychotropics.

      The RCT will compare outcomes in patients whose treatment is guided by CYP2D6 functional
      status and pharmacogenetic alerts versus standard-of-care treatment to test the hypothesis
      that the provision of clinically actionable prescription or proscription information can
      decrease hospitalization length of stay and reduce subsequent readmission.

      Using funds from AHRQ R01 HS022304-01, the RCT will enroll 1500 patients admitted to IOL over
      the next 5 years with a diagnosis of MDD and who are receiving psychotropic therapy at the
      time of admission or who will receive psychotropic therapy during hospitalization. 500
      patients will be assigned to standard-of-care pharmacotherapy (Group S), where CYP2D6
      genotype is determined but not transmitted to the clinician and psychotropic therapy follows
      the institutional norm. 1000 patients will be assigned to genetically-guided pharmacotherapy
      (Group G) where pharmacogenetic alerts based on CYP2D6 genotype are furnished via CEMS to the
      clinician within 48 hours of admission. Genotyping encompasses 19 common polymorphisms in
      CYP2D6 and their quantification into a drug metabolism reserve index to establish levels of
      sub-normal function (poor metabolizer) or supra-normal function (rapid metabolizer). For the
      estimated 40% of patients in Group G who are poor or rapid metabolizers, CEMS will proscribe
      medications which are major CYP2D6 substrates.

      The PI is Dr. Gualberto Ruaño, Director of GRC, and the lead clinician and Co-I is Dr. John
      Goethe, Director of IOL's Burlingame Research Center. Drs. Ruaño and Goethe have previously
      collaborated for 8 years on the pharmacogenetics of CYP450 and psychotropics. Dr. Theodore
      Holford of Yale University serves as statistical consultant and Dr. Richard Flockhart of
      Indiana University serves a medical consultant. The expected benefits are quantitative
      understanding of CYP2D6 pharmacogenetic information on outcomes and associated costs of
      psychiatric hospitalization. Importantly, this Program will provide objective benchmarking
      data for the comparative effectiveness of CYP2D6 genotyping for guiding psychiatric inpatient
      prescription.

      The Specific Aims are:

        1. RCT RECRUITMENT: To recruit 1500 patients with Major Depressive Disorder admitted to the
           IOL and randomly assign 1000 to Group G (genetically guided) and 500 to Group S
           (standard of care).

        2. RCT INTERVENTION: To conduct CYP2D6 genotyping of null alleles (*3, *4, *4XN, *5, *6,
           *7, *8, *11, *12, *14, *15), deficient alleles (*9, *10, *17, *41), functional variants
           (*1, *2), and rapid alleles (*1XN, *2XN, *2a) for all patients. In Group G the
           genotyping result is communicated to the treating clinician with prescription and
           proscription alerts for CYP2D6 substrate drugs; in Group S, the genotype is withheld.

        3. PRIMARY ENDPOINT: To compare length of hospitalization for all patients in Groups G vs.
           S.

        4. SECONDARY ENDPOINT: To compare the rates of 30-day psychiatric hospital readmission in
           Group G vs. S.

        5. ANCILLARY STUDIES: To assess the impact of genetic stratification in Groups G vs. S.
           with regard to the primary and secondary endpoints and specific drug utilization
           (removals, additions, co-prescriptions).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of Hospitalization Stay</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days following discharge from index hospitalization</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days hospitalized for the current psychiatric admission</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Readmission to Psychiatric Hospital within 30 days</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days following discharge from index hospitalization</time_frame>
    <description>Readmission to a hospital for psychiatric treatment within 30 days of discharge from index (current) hospitalization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1500</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>500 patients assigned to standard-of-care pharmacotherapy, for whom CYP2D6 genotype is determined but not utilized to guide drug prescription and psychotropic therapy follows the institutional norm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Genotype-guided Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>1000 patients assigned to genetically-guided pharmacotherapy, for whom CYP2D6 genotype is determined but not utilized to guide drug prescription as part of psychotropic therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Genotype-guided care</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmacogenetic alerts are furnished to the clinician within 1 day of analysis of patient consent, and 2 days of admission. Buccal cell DNA is analyzed for 19 common CYP2D6 polymorphisms and results quantified into a drug metabolism reserve index to establish levels of sub-normal function (poor metabolizer) or supra-normal function (rapid metabolizer). For the estimated 50% of patients who are poor or rapid metabolizers, CEMS will proscribe medications which are major CYP2D6 substrates.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Genotype-guided Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Men or women aged 18 y or older.

          2. Patients who have been admitted to the Institute of Living and having a diagnosis of
             major depressive disorder

          3. The ability to understand the requirements of the study.

          4. The ability to comply with study procedures and protocol.

          5. A woman is eligible to enter the study if she is of child-bearing potential and not
             pregnant or nursing, or not of child-bearing potential.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Children and adolescents

          2. Hospital admission within previous 30 d of current admission.

          3. History of dementia or Alzheimer's disease

          4. History of chronic kidney disease (CKD).

          5. Surgery within 6 wk.

          6. Ischemic stroke within 6 wk.

          7. Any history of hemorrhagic stroke or subarachnoid hemorrhage.

          8. Current enrollment in an investigational drug or device study that has not reached the
             time of the primary end point
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>95 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gualberto Ruano, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hartford Hospital Genetics Research Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John W Goethe, M.D., M.Ed.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Living, Hartford Healthcare</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Saskia T Campbell, BS</last_name>
    <phone>860-972-2196</phone>
    <email>Saskia.Campbell@hhchealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gualberto Ruano, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>860-972-3774</phone>
    <email>Gualberto.Ruano@hhchealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Living at Hartford Hospital, Hartford Healthcare</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hartford</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Saskia T Campbell, B.S.</last_name>
      <phone>860-972-2196</phone>
      <email>Saskia.Campbell@hhchealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Gualberto Ruano, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>860-972-3774</phone>
      <email>Gualberto.Ruano@hhchealth.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John W Goethe, M.D., M.Ed.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruaño G, Szarek BL, Villagra D, Gorowski K, Kocherla M, Seip RL, Goethe JW, Schwartz HI. Length of psychiatric hospitalization is correlated with CYP2D6 functional status in inpatients with major depressive disorder. Biomark Med. 2013 Jun;7(3):429-39. doi: 10.2217/bmm.13.16.</citation>
    <PMID>23734807</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 7, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 21, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 23, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 7, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 7, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 8, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pharmacogenetics</keyword>
  <keyword>CYP2D6 Mutations</keyword>
  <keyword>Major Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychiatric Inpatients</keyword>
  <keyword>Length of Stay</keyword>
  <keyword>30 Day Readmission Rate</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychiatric hospital inpatients</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

