<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01324726</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IM.ZK.05</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01324726</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Colonization With Extended-Spectrum Beta-Lactamase (ESBL)-Producing Organisms</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sites of Colonization in Hospitalized Patients With Infections Caused by Extended-Spectrum Beta-Lactamase Producing Escherichia Coli and Klebsiella Pneumoniae</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>American University of Beirut Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>American University of Beirut Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There has been a great increase in the incidence of infections caused by bacteria that are
      resistant to antibiotic agents. Many of these infections result in worse outcomes of patients
      and increased costs to the healthcare system. The study aims to survey two germs that are
      resistant to a wide range of antibiotics used today. The investigators are particularly
      interested in studying the potential to stop the spread and prevent outbreaks of these germs
      through contact isolation of patients affected by these germs. Patients will be included in
      the study if they have an antibiotic resistant infection caused by any of the 2 bacteria: E.
      coli and K. pneumoniae. The research team will then perform rectal, skin (armpit, groin,
      umbilicus), throat, urine, and, if applicable, wound cultures to determine other sites where
      the germ may be present but not causing an infection. The study coordinator will furthermore
      examine the patient's medical record and conduct a short interview in order to evaluate
      specific information about the bacteria that have been recovered. This research does not
      involve any interventions beyond collection of specimens and there are no added risks to the
      patients from the conduction of the study. Neither will there be a benefit at the patient
      level. The benefit will be at the level of the patient population, i.e. at a larger scale
      once the information collected is analyzed. Only the principal investigator and study
      coordinators will have access to all patient-specific information. Once all information is
      collected, all patient identifiers, such as name and medical record number, will be deleted.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The rising incidence of infections caused by extended-spectrum beta-lactamase (ESBL)
      producing Enterobacteriaceae is of worldwide dimensions, particularly in developing
      countries. At the American University of Beirut Medical Center (AUB-MC), the proportion of
      ESBL producing E. coli (ESBL-EC) and K. pneumoniae (ESBL-KP) strains has risen from 2.5% and
      9.8% to 22% and 27%, respectively between 1999 and 2008. The rapid spread of these multi drug
      resistant pathogens prompted the study of factors aiming at limiting the ongoing transmission
      of these organisms. Infection control interventions, such as contact isolation of infected
      patients, have been used to control outbreaks of infections caused by ESBL producing
      organisms in settings where the pathogens were isolated from rectal and axillary samples, as
      well as from upper respiratory tract secretions. These few reports raise concern for
      colonization of infected patients at sites other than the primary site of infection.
      Colonization in the absence of outbreaks has so far not been looked at systematically,
      especially in a high-endemicity area such as Lebanon. The present study ultimately aims at
      assessing the usefulness of placing patients with ESBL-EC and ESBL-KP infections on contact
      isolation during their hospital stay, and whether this practice would limit the spread of
      such infections. This is a prospective study screening hospitalized patients with ESBL-EC and
      ESBL-KP infections for colonization with the same organism at sites other than the primary
      site of infection through cultures of the rectum, skin, nasopharynx, urine and, if
      applicable, wounds. Cases will be identified through the Clinical Microbiology Laboratory at
      AUBMC and study subjects will be enrolled according to the inclusion/exclusion criteria. In
      addition to cultures of multiple body sites, molecular analysis will be performed on the
      isolated ESBL-producing strains to identify clonal relatedness. Cultures will be repeated
      monthly for a period of 6 months. The sample size is estimated at 100 patients over a two
      year period. The results of this study will have implications on infection control practices
      and will constitute a prerequisite for further studies in the future.

      The objective of this proposal is to evaluate the extent of colonization with ESBL-EC and
      ESBL-KP in hospitalized patients with active infections and designing recommendations
      accordingly.

      The specific aims include:

        1. Identify hospitalized patients with infections due to ESBL-producing organisms at a
           primary site

        2. Screen patients for colonization with ESBL-producing organisms at body sites other than
           the primary site of infection through cultures of:

             -  Rectum

             -  Skin (axillae, groin, umbilicus)

             -  Nasopharynx

             -  Urine

             -  Wound (if applicable)

        3. Perform susceptibility testing on all the collected isolates to detect ESBL-EC and
           ESBL-KP

        4. Perform molecular testing on ESBL-producing pathogens isolated from sites of
           colonization and compare them to the organisms recovered from the primary site in order
           to identify clonal relatedness

        5. Perform follow up cultures from the above mentioned sites after treatment for the
           primary infection is completed to determine duration of colonization

        6. Draw conclusions regarding extent of colonization with ESBL-producing organisms in
           hospitalized patients with a primary infection and to evaluate infection control
           implications (particularly with respect to placing patients on isolation precautions)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of colonization sites</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>This describes the number of body sites at which the patient is colonized other than the primary site of infection.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time until clearance of colonization</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This describes the time until various body sites become clear of colonizing pathogens.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Escherichia Coli Infections</condition>
  <condition>Klebsiella Pneumonia</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Cultures of urine, nasopharynx, rectum, skin, and wounds
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Cultures from clinical specimens growing ESBL-EC and ESBL-KP will be identified through the
        Clinical Microbiology Laboratory at AUBMC. Patients will be selected for enrollment
        according to the inclusion and exclusion criteria previously set. Permission from the
        patient's primary physician will be sought at the time of identification before approaching
        the patient.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Hospitalized patients with infection caused by ESBL-EC or ESBL-KP

          2. Type of infections:

               -  Urinary tract infections

               -  Respiratory tract infections

               -  Skin and skin structure infections

               -  Bloodstream infections

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Age &lt; 18 years

          2. Infection with the same antibiotic-resistant organism within the preceding year

          3. Intake of effective antibiotics based on susceptibility testing for longer than 48
             hours at the time of enrolment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>American University of Beirut Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beirut</city>
        <zip>1107 2020</zip>
        <country>Lebanon</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Lebanon</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 28, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 28, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 29, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 22, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 22, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 24, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>American University of Beirut Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zeina Kanafani</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Doctor, Internal Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bacterial colonization</keyword>
  <keyword>Extended spectrum beta lactamase producing organisms</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Klebsiella Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Escherichia coli Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

