<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01329354</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LFNK</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2009-017829-19</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01329354</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rituximab and Autologous Effector Lymphocytes in Non-Hodgkin Follicular Lymphoma in Response to First Line Chemotherapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Clinical Trial of Immunotherapy With Rituximab and Autologous Effector Lymphocytes in Patients With Non-Hodgkin Follicular Lymphoma in Response to First Line Chemotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Clinica Universidad de Navarra, Universidad de Navarra</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Spanish National Health System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Clinica Universidad de Navarra, Universidad de Navarra</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Nowadays, therapy with monoclonal antibodies is considered to be a standard treatment that
      increases the rate of remissions and the overall survival in patients with follicular
      lymphoma. Nevertheless there are an important number of patients who do not benefit from this
      therapy. A way to improve the efficiency of monoclonal antibodies therapy could be to improve
      the activity of the effector arm of the immune system. A strategy that has been proposed to
      obtain this improvement is the utilization of lymphocyte activated killer (LAK) cells. In
      addition, the combination of LAK cells with monoclonal antibodies might obtain an additive
      effect across the stimulation of the antibody dependent cellular cytotoxicity (ADCC)activity.

      The present clinical assay proposes to study the feasibility, safety and effectiveness of
      treatment with autologous effector cells expanded ex vivo associated with a standard
      maintenance treatment with rituximab in patients with follicular lymphoma in remission after
      first-line treatment. In addition, we plan to analyse various biological parameters that can
      predict the susceptibility of patients to treatment with rituximab. Specifically, we propose
      to study the polymorphisms of Fc receptor, polymorphisms related to the ability of complement
      activation, to study both the complement activity and peripheral blood cell subpopulations
      that can mediate directly or indirectly dependent antibody cytotoxic effect. We will also try
      to correlate any of these biological parameters with the response to treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There are many mechanisms involved in the antitumor effect of the antibodies including the
      induction of apoptosis, blocking angiogenesis, blockade of intracellular signaling pathways,
      and activation of complement leading to lysis of tumor cells. However it appears that the
      antibody-dependent cellular cytotoxicity (ADCC) is one of the predominant mechanisms of
      action. It is important to note that in order to obtain a powerful ADCC effect it is
      necessary the action of the antibody but also the activity of the effector cell, and thus the
      competence of the immune system of the guest. There are different cellular subpopulations
      that mediate the ADCC effect. CTL and NK are two of these subpopulations that can be reduced
      in patients with cancer.

      A way to improve the efficiency of the monoclonal antibodies would be to improve the activity
      of the effector arm of the immune system. A strategy that that has been planed is the
      utilization of LAK cells. The culture of lymphocytes of peripheral blood with IL-2 activates
      the subpopulations of killer cells. This population of killer cells activated with cytokines
      (LAK: lymphokine activated killer) has a high number of NK and CTL cells, both with increased
      cytotoxic capacity. It has been demonstrated that the immunotherapy with LAK cells might be
      an effective and sure treatment for patients with follicular lymphoma.

      In a murine model it has been demonstrated that LAK cells associated with monoclonal
      antibodies increase the antitumoral activity when compared to the administration of
      antibodies alone. In addition, in this model the combination was also superior to the
      administration of monoclonal antibodies + IL-2 (Schultz et al., 1990). Other investigators
      have demonstrated similar results. This information supports the idea of the combined therapy
      consisting in LAK with anti-CD20 antibodies. This therapy can induce a destruction of CD20
      positive cells greater than that with the monoclonal antibodies alone. In addition, it has
      been reported that the administration of systemic IL-2 and LAK cells improves the ADCC in
      lymphoma patients treated with rituximab. It is a small pilot study, with 10 patients. Seven
      of them received LAK cells following a programmed way. The safety of the treatment and the
      promising results demonstrated in this study encourage to investigate in this line.

      Since one of the mechanisms of action of the monoclonal antibodies is to promote ADCC , our
      hypothesis is that the treatment with a suspension of autologous effector lymphocytes
      expanded ex-vivo with culture should modify the biological effect of the treatment with
      rituximab in follicular lymphoma patients, with an acceptable safety profile, and probably
      increasing the efficiency of the monoclonal antibodies. In order to evaluate this hypotesis
      we propose an open, prospective, historically controlled, phase II clinical study in patients
      with follicular lymphoma who have achieved a remission after first-line therapy including the
      anti-CD20 monoclonal antibody rituximab and chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS) from the entry in the study.</measure>
    <time_frame>01/03/2015</time_frame>
    <description>The PFS is defined as the time from the entry in the study up to the progression of the disease.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Event free survival from the entry in the study</measure>
    <time_frame>01/03/2015</time_frame>
    <description>Event: progression, relapse, death for any reason, or institution of a new anti-lymphoma treatment (chemotherapy, radiotherapy or immunotherapy).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to the next anti-lymphoma treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>01/03/2015</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the time from the registry of the patient up to the institution of a new regimen (chemotherapy, radiotherapy or immunotherapy).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>01/03/2015</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the time from the first complete response documented up to the relapse</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>01/01/2012</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the incidence of toxicity of all the treatments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">38</enrollment>
  <condition>Follicular Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Follicular Non-Hodgkin´s Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Autologous Effector Lymphocytes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Autologous effector lymphocytes</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Autologous effector lymphocytes expanded ex-vivo</intervention_name>
    <description>Maintenance therapy with Rituximab every two months is the standard of care for patients with follicular lymphoma after induction therapy. The intervention consists on the administration of autologous effector lymphocytes expanded ex-vivo every two Rituximab administrations.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Autologous effector lymphocytes</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>LAK</other_name>
    <other_name>LAK cells</other_name>
    <other_name>Activated lymphocytes</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with histologically-confirmed follicular lymphoma CD20-positive grade 1, 2 ó
             3a.

          -  Patients with aptitude to sign the written informed consent and to express his desire
             to fulfill all the requirements of the protocol during the period of study.

          -  Patients not treated before. The induction treatment with rituximab and chemotherapy
             must be the first line for the patients who are included in the study.

          -  Patients undergoing maintenance therapy with rituximab every two/three months.

          -  Ann Arbor stage II, III o IV before receiving the induction treatment with rituximab
             and chemotherapy.

          -  The patient must have achieved a partial or complete response based on the revised
             International Workshop Response Criteria (IWRC) (Cheson, et al 2007) following the
             induction treatment.

          -  Age &gt;18 years and &lt;75 years.

          -  Performance status &lt;2 following the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG).

          -  Screening laboratory values obtained 28 days before registry (unless due to lymphoma
             involvement of the bone marrow): Hemoglobin &gt; 8,0 g/dL (5,0 mmol/L), Neutrophil
             absolute count &gt; 1,5 x 109/L,Platelets &gt; 100 x 109/L

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with transformed follicular lymphoma into diffuse large B-cell lymphoma.

          -  Patients with evidence of follicular lymphoma grade 3b.

          -  Patients with evidence of primary cutaneous or gastrointestinal follicular lymphoma.

          -  Patients with evidence of current central nervous system involvement.

          -  Patients who received previous induction treatment other than rituximab and
             chemotherapy.

          -  Patients receiving chronic immunosuppressive agents in the last 4 weeks. Patients may
             be receiving stable chronic doses of corticosteroids with a maximum dose of 20 mg/day
             of prednisone or equivalent.

          -  Patients who have a history of another primary malignancy &lt; 3 years, with the
             exception of non-melanoma skin cancer and carcinoma in situ of the uterine cervix.

          -  Decompensated renal function: serum creatininea &gt; 2,0 mg/dL (197 u.mol/L.

          -  Decompensated hepatic function: total bilirrubine &gt; 2,0 mg/dL (34 umol/L), AST (SGOT)
             &gt; 3 x ULN, unless due to lymphoma involvement

          -  Patients with a known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) seropositivity,
             chronic hepatitis or other active viral infections due to hepatitis B virus (HBV) or
             hepatitis C virus (HVC).

          -  Patients with underlying serious diseases that in the criteria of the investigator
             could concern the capacity of the patient to take part in the test (for example,
             infection in process, not controlled diabetes mellitus, gastric ulcers, autoimmune
             active disease).

          -  Life expectancy &lt;6 months.

          -  Female patients who are pregnant or breast feeding.

          -  Patients with known hypersensitivity to rituximab or other murine proteins or to any
             of the excipients.

          -  Patients who are using other investigational agents or who have received
             investigational drus 30 days prior to study drug start.

          -  Any other medical or psychological coexistent condition that rejects the participation
             in the study or compromises the aptitude to give the informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Carlos Panizo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pamplona</city>
        <state>Navarra</state>
        <zip>31008</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 1, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 4, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 5, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 23, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 23, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 24, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Follicular lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Follicular non-Hodgkin´s lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Autologous effector lymphocytes</keyword>
  <keyword>Cell Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Maintenance therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Rituximab</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Follicular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

