<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01322516</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>114231</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01322516</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Outcomes of Pandemic Influenza in Pregnancy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Outcomes of Pandemic Influenza in Pregnancy: an Observational Cohort Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dalhousie University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dalhousie University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We propose to follow a cohort of pregnant and post-partum Canadian women through the fall and
      winter of 2009/2010 and the anticipated second and third waves of the current pandemic in
      order to better understand the incidence, complications and risk factors for severe disease
      due to H1N1 influenza in pregnant women, and to contribute data on the safety and
      effectiveness of antivirals and vaccines in this population.

      The primary hypotheses to be tested are:

      (i) pandemic influenza infection in the second and third trimester of pregnancy is associated
      with an increase in adverse fetal outcomes (fetal loss, stillbirth, neonatal mortality,
      significant neonatal morbidity, prematurity) (ii) close contact with young children (&lt;2 yrs)
      at home or work is the most important risk factor for influenza in pregnant women (iii)
      higher scores on a scale of community infection prevention (a combination of self-reported
      hand hygiene adherence, avoidance of ill persons and avoidance of crowds) are protective
      against influenza (iv) receipt of seasonal influenza vaccine from 2007 to 2009 will increase
      the risk of illness due to influenza A(H1N1)v in the second and third waves of the pandemic.

      (v) pandemic influenza vaccine is effective in preventing symptomatic influenza in pregnant
      women.

      (vi) vaccination of pregnant women against a particular strain of influenza protects their
      infants against influenza infection in the first six months of life.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subjects will be consented to participate in the study. They will complete a web-based
      baseline questionnaire. Participants will be given a nasal swab kit with instructions for
      obtaining swabs. Baseline blood (10mls) will be drawn for influenza serology and for
      measurement of total IgG and IgG subtypes. An email will be sent to each participant within
      24 hours of their enrolment to welcome them to the study.

      Participants will be asked to complete a weekly diary using web-based data entry. An email
      will be sent to each participant every Monday during the study reminding the participant to
      complete their weekly diary and to report and submit a nasal swab if they have any symptoms
      of an acute respiratory illness. Reminder emails will be sent 48 hours later if the weekly
      form remains incomplete. Participants will be telephoned if forms remain incomplete for three
      weeks. Weekly emails will also be used to update participants about vaccine availability,
      current vaccine recommendations, and any changes in expert recommendations for pregnant
      women.

      Once every four weeks additional questions will be asked on the weekly survey. If any
      participant develops symptoms compatible with an acute viral respiratory illness they will be
      asked to collect and submit a nasal swab as soon as possible after the onset of symptoms and
      to complete an illness starting the day of symptom onset and ending when all symptoms are
      either absent or mild, or for 3 days, whichever is longer. Subjects will be notified if
      results are positive for influenza along with the local Medical Officer of Health. Treatment
      for influenza will be discussed with each infected participant by a physician investigator.

      Repeat serology and blood for total IgG and IgG subtype will be drawn at the time of delivery
      to the six week post partum. Women will notify the study when they are admitted for delivery
      or termination of pregnancy and will be interviewed either in person at the hospital, or over
      the telephone within 3 weeks of delivery. A chart review will be performed to identify any
      complications at delivery or termination, and to record neonatal outcomes. Post-partum,
      mothers will continue their own weekly and illness diaries and weekly diaries for their
      infants will be added.

      Pregnant women requiring hospital admission for influenza in hospitals participating in
      surveillance for the Toronto Invasive Bacterial Diseases Network (TIBDN) and Serious Outcomes
      Surveillance (SOS) for the PHAC/CIHR Influenza Research Network (PCIRN), as well as pregnant
      women with influenza admitted to intensive care units as part of the Canadian Critical Care
      Clinical Trials Group Influenza Surveillance System (ICU-Flu) will be approached. Risk factor
      data from the baseline and weekly questionnaires will be collected retrospectively from these
      women. With consent, women will be followed to delivery/termination, and the same information
      collected regarding neonatal outcomes as was collected for other women in the cohort.

      An email will be sent to all participating women requesting their consideration of three
      additional parts of the study:

        1. A questionnaire of development (the 8 month Ages and Stages® Questionnaire; see
           attached) to be completed by the parent

        2. An assessment with a physical examination at 7-9 months of age by a trained physician or
           a nurse practitioner

        3. Permission for the study to contact parents in the future about further follow-up.

      Mothers will also be asked to book an appointment for the 7-9 month assessment. Mothers who
      do not wish to have a pediatrician assessment will be asked over the telephone if they have
      any questions they wish to have answered about the study or the Ages and Stages®
      questionnaire, and if they consent to contact for future long term follow-up studies. If the
      child's score on the Ages and Stages® questionnaire raises a concern, mothers will be offered
      the chance to discuss this with a study physician, to have the results shared with her
      child's physician and/or to be referred to a pediatrician.

      Participants may choose to withdraw from the study at any time. When they do so, they will be
      asked if the data and blood samples that have been provided can be kept and used for study
      purposes. If a patient withdraws and cannot be contacted data that has been obtained will be
      retained, and blood will be used for the immediate study purpose, but will not be used for
      future studies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>September 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2012</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Influenza A(H1N1)v infection: will be as diagnosed by polymerase chain reaction(PCR) from nasal or nasopharyngeal (NP) swabs, and/or seroconversion to influenza A(H1H1)v.</measure>
    <time_frame>October 2009 to June 2010</time_frame>
    <description>Primary analysis for risk factors for infection will consider only symptomatic infection, defined as acute respiratory illness/ influenza like illness (fever (at least one measured T&gt;=38°C) and cough and one other local or systemic symptom compatible with influenza) during the pregnancy with seroconversion to A(H1N1)v not explained by vaccination. Seroconversion defined as a 4 fold increase in hemagglutination inhibition titer from 1st to 2nd serum sample.
Symptoms compatible with influenza defined as fever, cough, coryza, generalized myalgias, sore throat, headache, severe fatigue.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse fetal/neonatal outcome.</measure>
    <time_frame>October 2009-June 2010</time_frame>
    <description>Fetal loss &gt;12 weeks, stillbirth, neonatal mortality, significant neonatal morbidity, prematurity, or low birth weight, stillbirth, neonatal mortality, prematurity, live birth at less than 37 weeks gestational age, low birth weight, significant neonatal morbidity, severe congenital malformation, complicated influenza infection.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Nasopharyngeal swabs and serum
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        800 pregnant women followed through pregnancy during second and third waves of the 2009
        influenza pandemic, and 2009/10 influenza season. Forty percent are high risk pregnancies:
        either for maternal influenza complications (eg. underlying asthma, gestational diabetes
        mellitus in prior pregnancies) or high risk for obstetrical complications (eg. prior
        premature birth, multiple pregnancies). Recruitment from Halifax, Quebec City, Toronto,
        Hamilton, Calgary, Edmonton, and Vancouver. Plan to enroll all women before the beginning
        of the second wave; however, enrolment of women &lt;20 weeks pregnant will continue at each
        site until the second wave has peaked locally.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must:

               1. be and pregnant, and, at the time of enrolment, not more than 30 weeks gestation.

               2. be greater than or equal to 16 years of age

               3. give written informed consent prior to entry

               4. be available for follow-up during the study period

               5. have convenient access to a computer with internet access

               6. know basic skills for use of the internet

               7. have the ability to complete questionnaires in either English or French

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shelly McNeil, MD FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dalhousie University, Halifax, NS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Emmanuel Bujold, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Laval University, Montreal, Quebec</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Allison McGeer, MD FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Loeb, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>McMaster University, Hamiton, Ontario</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marie Louie, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Calgary, Calgary, Alberta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>George Zahariadis, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alberta, Edmonton, Alberta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Deborah Money, MDFRCSC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia, Vancouver, British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rachel Rodin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Public Health Agency of Canada, Ottawa, Ontario</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Calgary</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Edmonton</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>British Columbia's Women's and Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Elizabeth II Health Sciences Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Halifax</city>
        <state>Nova Scotia</state>
        <zip>B3K 6R8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McMaster University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Public Health Agency of Canada</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Laval University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 23, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 23, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 24, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 14, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 14, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 15, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Dr. Shelly McNeil, Principal Investigator</name_title>
    <organization>Dalhousie University</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

