<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01327937</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09-MOA-002-AG</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01327937</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Post Marketing Study of Apligraf in Non-healing Wounds of Subjects With Venous Leg Ulcers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Randomized, Controlled, Single-Site Post Marketing Study to Identify &amp; Characterize the Molecular Mechanisms of Apligraf in Non-healing Wounds of Subjects With Venous Leg Ulcers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Organogenesis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Organogenesis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall study objective is to use microarray technology to identify and characterize the
      gene expression of multiple relevant genes in biopsies of non-healing venous ulcers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subjects with a ≥5 cm2, non-infected target ulcer that has not reduced in area by ≥ 40% since
      the Screening visit will be randomized at Day 0 to either Apligraf or Control. After
      enrollment of 25 subjects, randomization will be discontinued and all remaining subjects will
      receive Apligraf.

      Once the target ulcer is assessed by the Investigator as healed at a study visit, the
      subject's participation in the study is completed (eg, assessed as healed at Week 3, subject
      would not be required to complete any subsequent study visits).

      Apligraf Group (Day 0 to Week 4) Prior to all applications, Apligraf will be fenestrated
      (perforated) in a standardized manner using a #11 blade with 6 fenestrations per 44 cm2.

      For those subjects randomized to the Apligraf group, after Apligraf application, the dressing
      regimen will include a foam dressing (eg. Mepilex) and a 4 layered compression bandage system
      (eg. Profore) which will be changed weekly by the Investigator.

      After the initial Apligraf application at study Day 0, Apligraf may be applied weekly
      thereafter for an additional 4 weeks at study Weeks 1, 2, 3, and 4, if, upon visual
      inspection, adherent Apligraf wound coverage is &lt; 100%.

      At Week 4, the area of the target ulcer will be compared to the area of the target ulcer at
      Day 0 to determine if the target ulcer is PTH or NPTH.

      Apligraf subjects that do not achieve CWC by Week 5 will enter the Follow-Up Phase at that
      time.

      Control Group (Day 0 to Week 4 [PTH] or Day 0 to Week 8 [NPTH] Beginning at Day 0, subjects
      randomized to the Control group will receive the standard dressing regimen which includes a
      foam dressing (e.g. Mepilex®) and a four layered compression bandage system (e.g. Profore™)
      which will be changed weekly by the Investigator.

      At study Week 4, the size of the ulcer will be compared to the size at study Day 0 to
      determine if the ulcer is demonstrating &quot;Predicted to Heal&quot; (PTH), defined as &gt;40% reduction
      in ulcer surface area compared with study Day 0, or &quot;Not Predicted to Heal (NPTH), defined as
      &lt;40% reduction in ulcer surface area compared with study Day 0.

      Control PTH subjects that do not achieve CWC by Week 4 will continue to receive Control
      treatment and will enter the Follow-Up Phase at Week 5.

      Control NPTH subjects will receive Apligraf beginning at Week 4. Prior to all applications,
      Apligraf will be fenestrated (perforated) in a standardized manner using a #11 blade with 6
      fenestrations per 44 cm2. After the initial Apligraf application at Week 4, Apligraf may be
      applied weekly thereafter for an additional 4 weeks at study Weeks 5, 6, 7, and 8 if upon
      visual inspection, adherent Apligraf wound coverage is &lt; 100%. After Apligraf application,
      the standard dressing regimen will be applied over the target ulcer. The dressing will be
      changed weekly by the Investigator. At Week 8, the area of the target ulcer will be compared
      to the area of the target ulcer at Week 4 to determine if the target ulcer is PTH or NPTH.

      Control NPTH subjects that do not achieve CWC by Week 9 will enter the Follow-up Phase at
      that time.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine changes in gene expression in subjects receiving Apligraf (includes Apligraf &amp; Control NPTH) compared to 1 week post treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Apligraf group - Day 0 &amp; Week 1; Control NPTH group-Weeks 4 &amp; 5</time_frame>
    <description>Not Predicted to Heal (NPTH) defined as &lt;40% reduction in ulcer surface area from Day 0 to Week 4</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine changes in gene expression in subjects receiving Apligraf (includes Apligraf &amp; Control NPTH)compared to subjects not receiving Apligraf at time of initial treatment and at 1 week post treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Apligraf group-Day 0 &amp; Week 1; Control NPTH group-Weeks 4 &amp; 5</time_frame>
    <description>NPTH defined as above</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine differences in gene expression in following groups (see description section)</measure>
    <time_frame>Apligraf group-Day 0 &amp; Week 1; Control NPTH group-Weeks 4 &amp; 5</time_frame>
    <description>Apligraf (APG) subjects Predicted to Heal (PTH) compared to Apligraf subjects Not Predicted to Heal (NPTH)
APG subjects PTH compared to Control subjects PTH
APG subjects NPTH compared to Control subjects NPTH
Control subjects PTH compared to Control subjects NPTH
All subjects (Apligraf and Control) PTH compared to all subjects NPTH
Also evaluate validity of surrogate endpoint (ulcer decrease of&gt;/= 40% from Day 0 to Week 4) for complete wound closure (CWC*) by Week 24
* CWC defined as 100% epithelialization with absence of drainage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Venous Ulcer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Apligraf Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Apligraf group - Applied at Day 0, Weeks 1-4 (maximum of 5 applications) Also cross-over at Week 4 for Control NPTH group - Apligraf applied at Week 4, Weeks 5-8 (maximum of 5 applications)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care Dressing Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of care dressing regimen - Foam dressing (eg, Mepilex) and 4 layered compression system (eg, Profore)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Apligraf</intervention_name>
    <description>Apligraf group - Applied at Day 0, Weeks 1-4 (maximum of 5 applications) Also cross-over at Week 4 for Control NPTH group - Apligraf applied at Week 4, Weeks 5-8 (maximum of 5 applications)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Apligraf Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard of Care Dressing Group</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard dressing regimen - Foam dressing (eg, Mepilex) and 4 layered compression system (eg, Profore)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care Dressing Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject has at least 1 clinically non-infected full-thickness venous leg ulcer (VLU)
             at least 5 cm2 in size.

          2. Subject is at least 18 years of age or older.

          3. Subject must have read, understood and signed an institutional review board (IRB)
             approved Informed Consent Form.

          4. Subject must be able and willing to follow study procedures and instructions.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects who require VAC® (Vacuum Assisted Closure™) therapy on or after Day 0 Study
             visit.

          2. Subject has arterial disease as determined by an Ankle Brachial Index (ABI)
             measurement of &lt;0.65.

          3. Subject with any systemic or congenital condition like uncontrolled diabetes mellitus,
             positive HIV test, or any disorder(s) that may compromise wound healing.

          4. Subjects with carcinomas located at the target ulcer with biopsy confirmed active
             malignancy. (Subjects with other carcinoma locations would not be excluded from entry
             into the study.)

          5. Subjects who are currently receiving, or have received at any time within 30 days
             prior to Screening visit, non-inhaled corticosteroids except topical steroids not at
             the target ulcer (Inhaled steroid therapy is acceptable on study.), immunosuppressive
             agents, radiation therapy, hemodialysis, peritoneal dialysis or chemotherapy.
             (Anticipated use of the above agents or therapies would exclude subject from entry
             into the study.)

          6. Clinical vasculitis, severe rheumatoid arthritis, and other collagen vascular
             diseases.

          7. Signs and symptoms of cellulitis or osteomyelitis at the target ulcer.

          8. Avascular target ulcer beds. (Ulcers of mixed etiology such as arterial disease with
             VLU will be excluded.)

          9. Target ulcer with exposed bone, tendon or fascia.

         10. Known hypersensitivity to bovine collagen or to the components of the Apligraf agarose
             shipping medium.

         11. Subject enrolled in any wound or investigational study (drug, biologic or device) for
             any disease within 30 days of the Screening visit.

         12. Subject previously treated with Apligraf, Dermagraft® or any other cell therapy at the
             target ulcer site within 30 days of the Screening visit.

         13. Subject with a history of alcohol or substance abuse within the previous year, which
             could interfere with study compliance such as inability to attend scheduled study
             visits.

         14. Subject who is a current smoker or has not ceased smoking 6 months prior to the
             Screening visit, or in the opinion of the Investigator, has a smoking history that may
             compromise wound healing.

         15. Subject who, in the opinion of the Investigator, for any reason other than those
             listed above, will not be able to complete the study per protocol.

         16. Target ulcer has not decreased in size by &gt; 40% from Screening to Day 0.

         17. Confirmed gene expression overlap between the subject's cells (buccal swab) and the
             cells contained in Apligraf.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Evangelos Badiavas, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Miami</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 31, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 31, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 4, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 23, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 23, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leg Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Varicose Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

