<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03130062</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13041978</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03130062</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Resistance Exercise in Woman With Primary Sjörgen Syndrome.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of Resistance Exercise in Daily Motor Activity Index and Functional Fitness in Women With Primary Sjögren Syndrome: a Randomized Clinical Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Federal University of São Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Federal University of São Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To analyze the effectiveness of 16-week resistance exercise in daily motor behavior and
      functional fitness in women with Primary Sjögren's Syndrome. The present study presents as
      hypothesis that a supervised resistance exercise program is effective and safe in improving
      the functional fitness and quality of life of patients with Primary Sjögren's Syndrome,
      making them more physically active, contributing positively to the capacity to perform daily
      life activities as household and / or professional tasks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sjögren's syndrome (SS) is a systemic autoimmune inflammatory disease that affects the
      exocrine glands and less frequently the internal organs, presenting intense lymphoplasmacytic
      infiltration mainly in the epithelium of the involved tissues, leading to the destruction and
      loss of the secretory function. SS can manifest itself in isolation, without association with
      other diseases, in this situation it is called Primary Sjögren's Syndrome (PSS), being
      considered the second most common autoimmune rheumatic disease, prevalent in women (9: 1).
      The inflammatory process can affect any organ, resulting in a generally severe clinical
      condition, and may involve the musculoskeletal, pulmonary, gastrointestinal, hepatic,
      hematological, vascular, dermatological, renal and neurological systems, leading to an
      evident decline of the physical functions with decrease in aerobic capacity, muscular
      strength, joint mobility and static balance, as well as psychological and social deficit.
      Patients with PSS also present a marked physiological characteristic with a high level of
      fatigue. Thus, resistance exercise becomes a non-drug strategy, aiming to improve
      musculoskeletal fitness, allowing the execution of daily activities with more independence,
      autonomy and safety, while influencing the patient's functional fitness. The aim of the
      present study is to analyze the effectiveness of resistance exercise in daily motor behavior
      and functional fitness in women with Primary Sjögren's Syndrome. After the use of actigraphy
      for 15 days, equipment that measures the level of daily physical activity, and evaluation of
      functional fitness, volunteers underwent a supervised resistance exercise program for 16
      weeks. The following muscular clusters were exerted: latissimus dorsi, deltoid, pectoralis
      major , triceps brachialis, biceps brachialis, quadriceps, hamstring, thigh adductor muscles,
      thigh abductor muscles and gastrocnemius. The subjects performed in each exercise 3 sets of
      10 maximum repetitions. The training sessions were held twice a week.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The division of the groups was obtained through randomization through a computer program. An opaque envelope containing the group allocation was given to the volunteer by the blind evaluator. After randomization, the sequential numbers were kept in opaque and closed envelopes and, as patients passed the initial evaluations, were allocated to one of the groups.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The collaborators who carried out these evaluations were unaware of the allocation of volunteers.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in functional fitness</measure>
    <time_frame>The subjects were assessed in 2 moments: before entering the resistance training program and after 16 weeks of intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>The protocol consists of a sequence of 7 tests that aim to mimic the neuromotor and cardiorespiratory needs involved in the daily life activities. This battrey test was designed and validated to evaluate the elderly without a ceiling effect, ensuring that the physical aspect measured represents the maximum of the individual.
The physiological components evaluated, based on the physical abilities performed in the daily activities are: upper and lower limb strength, aerobic capacity, upper and lower limb flexibility, as well as motor agility / dynamic balance. In addition, the authors added the body mass index (BMI), to estimate the body composition.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in daily motor activity index</measure>
    <time_frame>The subjects were assessed for 15 consecutive days belonging to the habitual routine of the volunteers. It was used in 2 moments: before entering the resistance training program and after 16 weeks of intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>To verify the daily movement index of the subjects we used a device called an actigraphy or actimeter.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life estimate</measure>
    <time_frame>The subjects were assessed in 2 moments: before entering the resistance training program and after 16 weeks of intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the quality of life, the &quot;Medical Outcomes Study SF-36&quot;, a generic questionnaire was translated and validated for the Brazilian population (Ciconelli, 1999). To evaluate, in a generic way, the quality of life. It is a multidimensional instrument composed of 36 items evaluating in 8 dimensions thus distributed: 10 items related to functional capacity; 4 physical appearance items; 2 items on pain; 5 items related to general health status; 4 items on vitality; 2 items with respect to social aspects; 3 items on emotional aspects; 5 items related to mental health and one more question of comparative evaluation between the current health conditions and that of a year ago.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimates of disease activity</measure>
    <time_frame>The subjects were assessed in 2 moments: before entering the resistance training program and after 16 weeks of intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>ESSDAI - Sjögren's Syndrome Disease Activity Index is a questionnaire that investigates the activity of SSP disease and has 12 domains (constitutional, lymphadenopathy, glandular, articular, cutaneous, respiratory, renal, muscular, peripheral nervous system, central nervous system, hematological, biological) (Seror et al. 2009). It was developed from a consensus study of the EULAR (European League Against Rheumatism) and the American group. His cross-cultural adaptation and validity for the Brazilian Portuguese language was performed by the Sjögren's syndrome clinic of the Rheumatology department of the Cassiano Antônio de Moraes University Hospital (HUCAM), in Vitória, Espírito Santo (Serrano et al., 2013). Disease activity is classified into 3 levels: mildly active, moderately active and highly active.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Primary Sjögren Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Volunteers underwent a supervised resistance exercise program for 16 weeks. The subjects performed 10 exercises with 3 sets of 10 maximum repetitions in each. The training sessions were held twice a week.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Volunteers in this group were instructed not to perform systematic physical exercises for 16 weeks (the same period of the GEX group training program), and only the SSP medication treatment was maintained, and they were followed up during the study period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise</intervention_name>
    <description>The following muscular clusters were exerted: latissimus dorsi, deltoid, pectoralis major , triceps brachialis, biceps brachialis, quadriceps, hamstring, thigh adductor muscles, thigh abductor muscles and gastrocnemius.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Exercise</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a diagnosis of PSS - according to the criteria of the American-European
             Society for the classification of Primary Sjögren's Syndrome (Vitali et al., 2002);

          -  Female gender

          -  Aged above 18 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who had cognitive difficulties, with diagnosis of Secondary Sjögren's
             Syndrome,

          -  A regular physical exercise practitioner or who were practicing physical exercise
             regularly up to 2 months before the interview.

          -  Patients in clinical conditions that prevented the practice of physical exercise
             according to previous medical evaluation, such as decompensated diabetes mellitus,
             decompensated thyroid disease, severe cardiorespiratory diseases, etc. - Use of
             medications that interfere with physical aspects, especially in response to the
             sensation of fatigue.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>PAULO A MINALI</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Federal University of São Paulo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Baillet A, Vaillant M, Guinot M, Juvin R, Gaudin P. Efficacy of resistance exercises in rheumatoid arthritis: meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Rheumatology (Oxford). 2012 Mar;51(3):519-27. doi: 10.1093/rheumatology/ker330. Epub 2011 Nov 24.</citation>
    <PMID>22120463</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Booth FW, Roberts CK, Laye MJ. Lack of exercise is a major cause of chronic diseases. Compr Physiol. 2012 Apr;2(2):1143-211. doi: 10.1002/cphy.c110025. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23798298</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cook DB, Nagelkirk PR, Poluri A, Mores J, Natelson BH. The influence of aerobic fitness and fibromyalgia on cardiorespiratory and perceptual responses to exercise in patients with chronic fatigue syndrome. Arthritis Rheum. 2006 Oct;54(10):3351-62.</citation>
    <PMID>17009309</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>O'Grady M, Fletcher J, Ortiz S. Therapeutic and physical fitness exercise prescription for older adults with joint disease: an evidence-based approach. Rheum Dis Clin North Am. 2000 Aug;26(3):617-46. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10989515</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Häkkinen A, Sokka T, Kautiainen H, Kotaniemi A, Hannonen P. Sustained maintenance of exercise induced muscle strength gains and normal bone mineral density in patients with early rheumatoid arthritis: a 5 year follow up. Ann Rheum Dis. 2004 Aug;63(8):910-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15249317</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Peterson MD, Rhea MR, Sen A, Gordon PM. Resistance exercise for muscular strength in older adults: a meta-analysis. Ageing Res Rev. 2010 Jul;9(3):226-37. doi: 10.1016/j.arr.2010.03.004. Epub 2010 Apr 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20385254</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rooks DS, Silverman CB, Kantrowitz FG. The effects of progressive strength training and aerobic exercise on muscle strength and cardiovascular fitness in women with fibromyalgia: a pilot study. Arthritis Rheum. 2002 Feb;47(1):22-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11932874</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Stenström CH, Minor MA. Evidence for the benefit of aerobic and strengthening exercise in rheumatoid arthritis. Arthritis Rheum. 2003 Jun 15;49(3):428-34. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12794800</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Champey J, Corruble E, Gottenberg JE, Buhl C, Meyer T, Caudmont C, Bergé E, Pellet J, Hardy P, Mariette X. Quality of life and psychological status in patients with primary Sjögren's syndrome and sicca symptoms without autoimmune features. Arthritis Rheum. 2006 Jun 15;55(3):451-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16739213</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Barendregt PJ, Visser MR, Smets EM, Tulen JH, van den Meiracker AH, Boomsma F, Markusse HM. Fatigue in primary Sjögren's syndrome. Ann Rheum Dis. 1998 May;57(5):291-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9741313</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Belenguer R, Ramos-Casals M, Brito-Zerón P, del Pino J, Sentís J, Aguiló S, Font J. Influence of clinical and immunological parameters on the health-related quality of life of patients with primary Sjögren's syndrome. Clin Exp Rheumatol. 2005 May-Jun;23(3):351-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15971423</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Dassouki T, Benatti FB, Pinto AJ, Roschel H, Lima FR, Augusto K, Pasoto S, Pereira RMR, Gualano B, de Sá Pinto AL. Objectively measured physical activity and its influence on physical capacity and clinical parameters in patients with primary Sjögren's syndrome. Lupus. 2017 Jun;26(7):690-697. doi: 10.1177/0961203316674819. Epub 2016 Oct 26.</citation>
    <PMID>27798360</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>d'Elia HF, Rehnberg E, Kvist G, Ericsson A, Konttinen Y, Mannerkorpi K. Fatigue and blood pressure in primary Sjogren's syndrome. Scand J Rheumatol. 2008 Jul-Aug;37(4):284-92. doi: 10.1080/03009740801907995.</citation>
    <PMID>18612929</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hackett KL, Newton JL, Frith J, Elliott C, Lendrem D, Foggo H, Edgar S, Mitchell S, Ng WF. Impaired functional status in primary Sjögren's syndrome. Arthritis Care Res (Hoboken). 2012 Nov;64(11):1760-4. doi: 10.1002/acr.21738.</citation>
    <PMID>23111856</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lendrem D, Mitchell S, McMeekin P, Bowman S, Price E, Pease CT, Emery P, Andrews J, Lanyon P, Hunter J, Gupta M, Bombardieri M, Sutcliffe N, Pitzalis C, McLaren J, Cooper A, Regan M, Giles I, Isenberg D, Vadivelu S, Coady D, Dasgupta B, McHugh N, Young-Min S, Moots R, Gendi N, Akil M, Griffiths B, Ng WF; UK primary Sjögren's Syndrome Registry. Health-related utility values of patients with primary Sjögren's syndrome and its predictors. Ann Rheum Dis. 2014 Jul;73(7):1362-8. doi: 10.1136/annrheumdis-2012-202863. Epub 2013 Jun 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23761688</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 16, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 21, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 26, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 25, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 25, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 27, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Federal University of São Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Paulo Minali</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Physical Education Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Resistance Exercise</keyword>
  <keyword>Functional Fitness</keyword>
  <keyword>Actigraphy</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary Sjögren Syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sjogren's Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The questionaries SF-36 and ESSDAI used in the present study were shared with other researches.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

