<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03131180</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB16-00537</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03131180</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rapid Learning Healthcare System in Pediatric Surgery</brief_title>
  <acronym>RLHS</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Controlled Trial: Rapid Learning Healthcare System in Pediatric Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Katherine Deans</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Society of University Surgeons</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nationwide Children's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Engaging patients and families to take an active role in their healthcare leads to improved
      outcomes. Providing physicians and families with near real-time data on outcomes in children
      with similar medical conditions can allow families to form realistic expectations and take an
      active role in their child's health. It also provides physicians with near real-time feedback
      on patient-reported outcome measures to guide both conversations and recommendations for
      therapy at the point-of-care.

      A rapid learning healthcare system (RLHS) is a system that merges clinical research and
      clinical care. It is designed to collect data during routine patient care and then utilize
      the data to rapidly generate evidence to improve patient care, provide information to
      patients and families, and track quality measures.

      The investigators created a RLHS that integrates pre-specified data elements and validated
      surveys within the clinical workflow in order to operationalize automated research data
      collection and integrate predictive analytics into the electronic health record (EHR).
      Patients, caregivers, and physicians can access data in order to make informed, shared
      decisions about care and align expectations about outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Functional disabilities such as functional constipation, and congenital anomalies such as
      anorectal malformations (ARM) and Hirschsprung disease (HD), are the leading indications for
      colon surgery in children. While these diseases have low mortality rates and surgical
      techniques can effectively restore anatomy, these patients have persistent and significant
      post-operative morbidity around fecal soiling and/or constipation. In addition to impairing
      growth and development, this affects all domains of health related quality of life (HRQoL).
      Patients, families, and healthcare providers of children with these diseases consistently
      report that bowel management strategies that prevent soiling comprise one of the most
      important areas for high quality outcomes research.

      Engaging patients and families to take an active role in their healthcare leads to improved
      outcomes. Providing physicians and families with near real-time data on outcomes in children
      with similar medical conditions can allow families to form realistic expectations and take an
      active role in their child's health. It also provides physicians with near real-time feedback
      on patient-reported outcome measures to guide both conversations and recommendations for
      therapy at the point-of-care. A rapid learning healthcare system (RLHS) is a system that
      merges clinical research and clinical care. It is designed to collect data during routine
      patient care and then utilize the data to rapidly generate evidence to improve patient care,
      provide information to patients and families, and track quality measures.

      The investigators created a RLHS that integrates pre-specified data elements and validated
      surveys within the clinical workflow in order to operationalize automated research data
      collection and integrate predictive analytics into the electronic health record (EHR). To
      date, we have over 800 patients enrolled in the colorectal RLHS. Patients, caregivers, and
      physicians can access data in order to make informed, shared decisions about care and align
      expectations about outcomes.

      The primary and secondary objective of this trial are as follows:

      Primary Objective: To assess the ability of a RLHS to improve healthcare satisfaction in
      pediatric patients with complex colorectal diseases.

      Secondary Objective: To assess the ability of a RLHS to improve patient-centered outcomes in
      pediatric patients with complex colorectal diseases.To characterize the usability of the RLHS
      by patients and caregivers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This trial is a single center randomized controlled trial to investigate the ability of the RLHS to improve patient-centered outcomes in pediatric patients with complex colorectal diseases. Patients and caregivers are randomized to either receive access to a website that displays the colorectal RLHS dashboard prior to standard consultation or to standard consultation alone.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improved healthcare satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the ability of a RLHS to improve healthcare satisfaction in pediatric patients with complex colorectal diseases. As measured by the PedsQL Healthcare Satisfaction questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improved patient-centered outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the ability of a RLHS to improve patient-centered outcomes in pediatric patients with complex colorectal diseases. As measured by the PedsQL Quality of Life questionnaire designed for both parents and children.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Usability of RLHS</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days post-enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the usability of the RLHS by patients and caregivers. As measured by the System Usability Scale designed by the investigators.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">126</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RLHS dashboard</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to RLHS website access are given instructions on how the RLHS dashboard works both by phone and by email and are given open access to the RLHS dashboard website immediately after enrollment and before meeting with the CCPR clinical team for their consultation. Each user has an access code, which allows them to track their access. They maintain access to the website throughout their care in the CCPR. Patients in the RLHS access group complete the System Usability Scale (SUS; a 10 item questionnaire to evaluate software, websites, and applications) after use of the RLHS at consultation. Those in the RLHS access group also complete a 7-item exit interview either via phone or on REDCap.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard consultation alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Those not randomized to RLHS access undergo standard consultation only.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rapid Learning Healthcare System</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigators created a Rapid Learning Healthcare System that integrates pre-specified data elements and validated surveys within the clinical workflow in order to operationalize automated research data collection and integrate predictive analytics into the electronic health record (EHR). Patients, caregivers, and physicians access data in order to make informed, shared decisions about care and align expectations about outcomes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>RLHS dashboard</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Interactive Patient Education Dashboard</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  English speaking patients aged 0-17 years with a diagnosis of ARM, HD, or functional
             constipation referred to our CCPR clinic between July 1, 2016 through June 1, 2017.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients previously treated at CCPR, those who are non-English speaking, and those
             without internet access.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Katherine Deans, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nationwide Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Katherine Deans, MD</last_name>
    <phone>614-722-0742</phone>
    <email>katherine.deans@nationwidechildrens.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Dani Gonzalez, MD</last_name>
    <phone>614-722-0742</phone>
    <email>dani.gonzalez@nationwidechildrens.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nationwide Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Katherine Deans, MD</last_name>
      <phone>614-722-0742</phone>
      <email>katherine.deans@nationwidechildrens.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Katherine Deans, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 19, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 24, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 27, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 27, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Nationwide Children's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Katherine Deans</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Center for Surgical Outcomes Research, Nationwide Children's Hospital; Assistant Professor of Surgery, The Ohio State University</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

