<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03139591</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IndonesiaUAnes014</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03139591</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison Between Lidocaine Inhalation and Intravenous Dexamethasone in Reducing Pain After Laryngeal Mask Insertion</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison Between Lidocaine Inhalation and Intravenous Dexamethasone to Reduce Pain After Laryngeal Mask Insertion</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Indonesia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indonesia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aimed to compare the efficacy between lidocaine inhalation vs intravenous
      dexamethasone to reduce pain after laryngeal mask insertion
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Approval from Ethical Committee of Faculty of Medicine Universitas Indonesia was acquired
      prior conducting the study. Subjects were given informed consent before enrolling the study
      and randomized into two groups (Lidocaine inhalation and Intravenous dexamethasone group).
      Intravenous (IV) cannula (18 or 20 G) , non-invasive blood pressure monitor, and
      pulse-oxymetry had been set on the subjects 10 minutes before anesthesia began. Vital signs
      were recorded. Lidocaine group received 1.5 mg/kg body weight (BW) of 2% lidocaine
      inhalation, diluted with 2-3 ml of normal saline until the total volume was 6 ml, and
      intravenous normal saline injection. Dexamethasone group received normal saline inhalation
      and 10 mg of intravenous dexamethasone. Subjects, authors, or inhalation giver were not aware
      of the content of any drug given. Coinduction was done using 0.05mg/kg BW of midazolam and
      2mcg/kg BW of fentanyl 5 minutes before the laryngeal mask airway (LMA) insertion. Induction
      was done using 2 mg/kg BW of 1% propofol and 0.5 mg/kg BW of atracurium 3 minutes before LMA
      insertion. Subjects were then given oxygenation using face mask without oropharyngeal airway.
      LMA was lubricated with normal saline. After 3 minutes of oxygenation, LMA was inserted using
      standard method. The LMA cuff was inflated with cuff pressure gauge of approximately 40 mmHg.
      After the position of LMA was confirmed to be correct, fixation was done using a tape.
      Maintenance of anesthesia was done using 50% oxygen in compressed air, 1% isoflurane, and
      atracurium. Thirty minutes before the surgery ended, 1 gram of paracetamol was given in 15
      minutes as post-surgery analgetic. After the surgery was ended, subjects were given 0.04
      mg/kg BW of neostigmine and 0.02 mg/kg BW of atropine. Mucus suction was performed on
      oropharynx and oral cavity gently, by using suction catheter 12F when subjects were still
      under anesthesia. After spontaneous breaths occured, LMA cuff was deflated and LMA was
      removed. Ventilation was continued using face mask without oropharyngeal airway. At the
      recovery room, pain on throat was assessed using Numerical Rating Scale. Assessment was done
      2 hours after surgery in the recovery room after subjects were fully alert with Aldrette
      score of 10. Throat pain was assessed during rest or swallowing. In addition, subjects were
      asked whether or not they experienced difficulty in swallowing or hoarseness.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 31, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 31, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Numerical rating scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Numerical rating scale for throat pain</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">196</enrollment>
  <condition>Adult Patients Undergoing Elective Surgery With General Anesthesia and LMA Insertion</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>lidocaine inhalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lidocaine inhalation group: 1.5 mg/kg body weight (BW) of 2% lidocaine inhalation, diluted with 2-3 ml of normal saline until the total volume was 6 ml, and intravenous normal saline injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>intravenous dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intravenous dexamethasone group: normal saline inhalation and 10 mg of intravenous dexamethasone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>lidocaine inhalation; intravenous dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>1.5 mg/kg body weight (BW) of 2% lidocaine inhalation, diluted with 2-3 ml of normal saline until the total volume was 6 ml, and intravenous normal saline injection; Intravenous dexamethasone group: normal saline inhalation and 10 mg of intravenous dexamethasone.</description>
    <arm_group_label>lidocaine inhalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>intravenous dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients aged 20-59 years old, with American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA)
             physical status of I-II who were planned to undergo any elective surgery at operating
             room in general anesthesia and needed LMA insertion

          -  Mallampati class I or II

          -  subjects had been explained about the study, and agreed to enroll and have signed the
             informed consent form

          -  Subjects without history of throat pain

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with cardiovascular disease, history of analgetic and steroid before surgery,
             surgical site of neck, oral cavity, pharynx, and larynx

          -  Subjects with upper respiratory tract infection

          -  Subjects with history of drug allergy used in the trial and possibility of difficult
             airway

          -  Pregnant, obese, active smoking, uncontrolled diabetic and hypertension subjects

          -  Subjects with history of peptic ulcer disease.

        Dropout Criteria:

          -  Subjects whose LMA insertion attempts more than once

          -  Subjects with surgery duration &gt; 150 minutes

          -  Subjects who needed mechanical ventilation after surgery, subjects who vomitted

          -  Subjects whose LMA converted to endotracheal tube during surgery

          -  Subjects who received additional opioid during surgery
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>59 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cipto Mangunkusumo Central National Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Central Jakarta</city>
        <state>DKI Jakarta</state>
        <zip>10430</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Indonesia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/22201173.2003.10873000</url>
    <description>Zuccherelli L. Postoperative upper airway problems. South Afr J Anaesth Analg. 2003;9(2):12-6.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>An J, Shin SK, Kim KJ. Laryngeal mask airway insertion in adults: comparison between fully deflated and partially inflated technique. Yonsei Med J. 2013 May 1;54(3):747-51. doi: 10.3349/ymj.2013.54.3.747.</citation>
    <PMID>23549825</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seet E, Yousaf F, Gupta S, Subramanyam R, Wong DT, Chung F. Use of manometry for laryngeal mask airway reduces postoperative pharyngolaryngeal adverse events: a prospective, randomized trial. Anesthesiology. 2010 Mar;112(3):652-7. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e3181cf4346.</citation>
    <PMID>20179502</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uztüre N, Menda F, Bilgen S, Keskin Ö, Temur S, Köner Ö. The Effect of Flurbiprofen on Postoperative Sore Throat and Hoarseness After LMA-ProSeal Insertion: A Randomised, Clinical Trial. Turk J Anaesthesiol Reanim. 2014 Jun;42(3):123-7. doi: 10.5152/TJAR.2014.35693. Epub 2014 Mar 11.</citation>
    <PMID>27366405</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sun L, Guo R, Sun L. Dexamethasone for preventing postoperative sore throat: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. Ir J Med Sci. 2014 Dec;183(4):593-600. doi: 10.1007/s11845-013-1057-0. Epub 2013 Dec 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24357270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 2, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 2, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 15, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 15, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Indonesia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Susilo Chandra</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Anesthesiologist Consultant</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lidocaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <study_docs>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_type>Textbook</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://books.google.co.id/books/about/Laryngeal_Mask_Anesthesia.html?id=XBJsAAAAMAAJ&amp;redir_esc=y</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>Problems. In: Brimacombe JR. Laryngeal Mask Anesthesia principles and practice. London: Saunders Ltd, 2004;551-71.</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
  </study_docs>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

