<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03138473</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17100078</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03138473</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Residual Syntax Score and Syntax Revascularization Index on Outcomes of ACS Patients With Multi-Vessel Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of Residual Syntax Score and Syntax Revascularization Index on Outcomes of Acute Coronary Syndrome Patients With Multi-Vessel Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators want to assess the use of the residual SYNTAX score and the SYNTAX
      Revascularization Index as predictors for in-hospital outcomes and mid-term (6 months to 1
      year) outcomes in patients with multi-vessel disease (MVD) who undergo PCI in the setting of
      STEMI or NSTEACS. Both values will be calculated in a number of patients over one year, and
      the relationship between both values and patient outcomes will be evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Significant non-culprit coronary stenosis is noted in 40-70% of patients with ST-elevation
      Myocardial Infarction (STEMI) undergoing primary percutaneous coronary intervention (PPCI).
      Presence of multivessel disease (MVD) has been associated with poorer clinical outcomes. MVD
      in STEMI may confer an increased risk of recurrent ischemia and mortality. However, the
      impact of MVD on prognosis in STEMI may vary depending on the characteristics of coronary
      artery disease (CAD) present.

      Current guidelines recommend that only the infarct-related artery should be treated. However,
      RCTs have suggested that a strategy of multivessel PCI, either at the time of primary PCI or
      as a planned, staged procedure, may be beneficial and safe in selected patients with STEMI.
      On the basis of these findings, the prior Class III (Harm) recommendation with regard to
      multivessel primary PCI in hemodynamically stable patients with STEMI has been upgraded and
      modified to a Class IIb recommendation to include consideration of multivessel PCI, either at
      the time of primary PCI or as a planned, staged procedure.

      Early invasive treatment in high-risk patients with non-ST-elevation acute coronary syndrome
      (NSTEACS) has been shown to improve their prognosis in terms of cardiovascular death and
      reinfarction. The prevalence of multivessel disease in these patients stands at about 50% and
      experts agree that performing complete revascularization is beneficial in such patients.

      Accordingly, the SYNergy between PCI with TAXus and cardiac surgery (SYNTAX) score has been
      developed in 2005 in Erasmus Medical Center in the Netherlands to evaluate the severity of
      coronary artery disease in the settings of left main or MVD.

      The investigators have observed a growing interest in residual disease burden after PCI. The
      residual SYNTAX score (rSS), described by Genereux and colleagues is a strong prognostic
      factor of coronary events and all-cause death in patients who have undergone PCI. This score
      has subsequently been validated by other groups and been shown to have good prognostic
      accuracy for adverse ischemic outcomes after PCI.

      The SYNTAX Revascularisation Index (SRI), which takes into account the severity and extent of
      baseline CAD (as assessed by the baseline SYNTAX score [bSS]) and the residual CAD after PCI
      (as assessed by the rSS) has been used in determining the proportion of CAD that has been
      treated, and has been shown to have prognostic utility in PCI for MVD.

      Here, the investigators want to assess the use of the residual SYNTAX score and the SYNTAX
      Revascularization Index as predictors for in-hospital outcomes and mid-term (6 months to 1
      year) outcomes in patients with multi-vessel disease (MVD) who undergo PCI in the setting of
      STEMI or NSTEACS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>In-hospital major adverse cardiac events (MACE)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>A composite of cardiac death (including periprocedural), non-fatal myocardial infarction, congestive heart failure, unplanned revascularization including target vessel revascularization (TVR), target lesion revascularization (TLR) and Coronary artery bypass graft (CABG).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The individual components of the primary end-point</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Cardiac death (including periprocedural), non-fatal myocardial infarction, congestive heart failure, unplanned revascularization including target vessel revascularization (TVR), target lesion revascularization (TLR) and Coronary artery bypass graft (CABG)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Major Bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>ACUITY defined major bleeding (Stone et al, 2004)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute kidney injury (AKI)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>a 25% relative or 0.5mg/dL (44.2µmol/L) absolute increase in presenting serum creatinine after PPCI.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6 months- 1 year MACE, and its individual components.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 Year</time_frame>
    <description>Cardiac death (including periprocedural), non-fatal myocardial infarction, congestive heart failure, unplanned revascularization including target vessel revascularization (TVR), target lesion revascularization (TLR) and Coronary artery bypass graft (CABG),and a composite of these components.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">108</enrollment>
  <condition>STEMI - ST Elevation Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <condition>Multi Vessel Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <condition>NSTEMI - Non-ST Segment Elevation MI</condition>
  <condition>ACS - Acute Coronary Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Main Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Acute Coronary Syndrome Patients With Multi-Vessel Disease. The Residual SYNTAX score (rSS) and the SYNTAX Revascularization Index (SRI) will be calculated in this group and its relationship with patient outcomes either in hospital or in 6 months to 1 year follow-up will be evaluated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Residual SYNTAX Score</intervention_name>
    <description>The baseline SYNTAX score and the residual SYNTAX score (rSS) are calculated by summing up the individual scores for each lesion with a diameter stenosis ≥50% in vessels with a diameter ≥ 1.5 mm in the angiography obtained before and after the procedure. The SYNTAX algorithm of scoring is fully described elsewhere.
The modified Age, Creatinine, and Ejection Fraction (ACEF) score is calculated based on the age, glomerular filtration rate (GFR) and left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF), using the formula age/LVEF +1 point for every 10 ml/min/1.73 m2 reduction of GFR below 60 ml/min/1.73 m2 (1 point for GFR between 59 and 50, 2 points for GFR between 49 and 40 and 3 points for GFR between 39 and 30 ml/min/1.73 m2). The GFR is calculated via the Cockroft-Gault equation using age, gender weight and serum creatinine before PCI. The baseline SYNTAX score was then multiplied by the modified ACEF score to obtain the baseline clinical SYNTAX score.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Main Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SYNTAX Revascularization Index</intervention_name>
    <description>The SYNTAX Revascularization Index (SRI), representing the proportion of CAD burden treated by PCI, was calculated using the following formula: SRI= (1-[rSS/bSS]) ×100.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Main Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All consecutive patients admitted to the Assiut University Hospitals Department of
        Cardiology will be collected over one year starting 1st of July 2017 till 30th of June
        2018.

        Considering the primary end-point of the study (MACE rate 28%) (Khan et al, 2016), the
        estimated sample size of the population, based on power of 85%, and alpha= 5%, is
        calculated to be = 108 patients.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All ACS (STEMI and NSTEACS) patients undergoing PCI in the setting of MVD.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients receiving fibrinolytic therapy.

          -  Patients with cardiogenic shock

          -  Post-CABG patients

          -  Patients with severe renal impairment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Salwa R. Dimitry, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Cardiology, Assiut University Faculty of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tarek A. Nagib, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Cardiology, Assiut University Faculty of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amr A. Othman, MBBCh</last_name>
    <phone>+201004674109</phone>
    <email>amr989@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assiut University Heart Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Assiut</city>
        <zip>71515</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hosam H. El-Araby, MD</last_name>
      <email>hosam_hasan@aun.edu.eg</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boden H, Velders MA, van der Hoeven BL, Cannegieter SC, Schalij MJ. In-hospital major bleeding and its clinical relevance in patients with ST elevation myocardial infarction treated with primary percutaneous coronary intervention. Am J Cardiol. 2013 Nov 15;112(10):1533-9. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2013.06.025. Epub 2013 Aug 14.</citation>
    <PMID>23953696</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Claessen BE, Dangas GD, Weisz G, Witzenbichler B, Guagliumi G, Möckel M, Brener SJ, Xu K, Henriques JP, Mehran R, Stone GW. Prognostic impact of a chronic total occlusion in a non-infarct-related artery in patients with ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction: 3-year results from the HORIZONS-AMI trial. Eur Heart J. 2012 Mar;33(6):768-75. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehr471. Epub 2012 Jan 12.</citation>
    <PMID>22240495</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Engstrøm T, Kelbæk H, Helqvist S, Høfsten DE, Kløvgaard L, Holmvang L, Jørgensen E, Pedersen F, Saunamäki K, Clemmensen P, De Backer O, Ravkilde J, Tilsted HH, Villadsen AB, Aarøe J, Jensen SE, Raungaard B, Køber L; DANAMI-3—PRIMULTI Investigators. Complete revascularisation versus treatment of the culprit lesion only in patients with ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction and multivessel disease (DANAMI-3—PRIMULTI): an open-label, randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2015 Aug 15;386(9994):665-71.</citation>
    <PMID>26347918</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farooq V, Serruys PW, Bourantas CV, Zhang Y, Muramatsu T, Feldman T, Holmes DR, Mack M, Morice MC, Ståhle E, Colombo A, de Vries T, Morel MA, Dawkins KD, Kappetein AP, Mohr FW. Quantification of incomplete revascularization and its association with five-year mortality in the synergy between percutaneous coronary intervention with taxus and cardiac surgery (SYNTAX) trial validation of the residual SYNTAX score. Circulation. 2013 Jul 9;128(2):141-51. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.113.001803. Epub 2013 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>23766350</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fox KA, Clayton TC, Damman P, Pocock SJ, de Winter RJ, Tijssen JG, Lagerqvist B, Wallentin L; FIR Collaboration. Long-term outcome of a routine versus selective invasive strategy in patients with non-ST-segment elevation acute coronary syndrome a meta-analysis of individual patient data. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2010 Jun 1;55(22):2435-45. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2010.03.007. Epub 2010 Mar 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20359842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garg S, Sarno G, Garcia-Garcia HM, Girasis C, Wykrzykowska J, Dawkins KD, Serruys PW; ARTS-II Investigators. A new tool for the risk stratification of patients with complex coronary artery disease: the Clinical SYNTAX Score. Circ Cardiovasc Interv. 2010 Aug;3(4):317-26. doi: 10.1161/CIRCINTERVENTIONS.109.914051. Epub 2010 Jul 20.</citation>
    <PMID>20647561</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Généreux P, Campos CM, Yadav M, Palmerini T, Caixeta A, Xu K, Francese DP, Dangas GD, Mehran R, Leon MB, Serruys PW, Stone GW. Reasonable incomplete revascularisation after percutaneous coronary intervention: the SYNTAX Revascularisation Index. EuroIntervention. 2015 Oct;11(6):634-42. doi: 10.4244/EIJY14M10_05.</citation>
    <PMID>25308300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Généreux P, Palmerini T, Caixeta A, Rosner G, Green P, Dressler O, Xu K, Parise H, Mehran R, Serruys PW, Stone GW. Quantification and impact of untreated coronary artery disease after percutaneous coronary intervention: the residual SYNTAX (Synergy Between PCI with Taxus and Cardiac Surgery) score. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2012 Jun 12;59(24):2165-74. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2012.03.010. Epub 2012 Apr 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22483327</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gershlick AH, Khan JN, Kelly DJ, Greenwood JP, Sasikaran T, Curzen N, Blackman DJ, Dalby M, Fairbrother KL, Banya W, Wang D, Flather M, Hetherington SL, Kelion AD, Talwar S, Gunning M, Hall R, Swanton H, McCann GP. Randomized trial of complete versus lesion-only revascularization in patients undergoing primary percutaneous coronary intervention for STEMI and multivessel disease: the CvLPRIT trial. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2015 Mar 17;65(10):963-72. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2014.12.038.</citation>
    <PMID>25766941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoebers LP, Vis MM, Claessen BE, van der Schaaf RJ, Kikkert WJ, Baan J Jr, de Winter RJ, Piek JJ, Tijssen JG, Dangas GD, Henriques JP. The impact of multivessel disease with and without a co-existing chronic total occlusion on short- and long-term mortality in ST-elevation myocardial infarction patients with and without cardiogenic shock. Eur J Heart Fail. 2013 Apr;15(4):425-32. doi: 10.1093/eurjhf/hfs182. Epub 2012 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23148116</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khan R, Al-Hawwas M, Hatem R, Azzalini L, Fortier A, Joliecoeur EM, Tanguay JF, Lavoie-L'Allier P, Ly HQ. Prognostic impact of the residual SYNTAX score on in-hospital outcomes in patients undergoing primary percutaneous coronary intervention. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2016 Nov;88(5):740-747. doi: 10.1002/ccd.26413. Epub 2016 Feb 1.</citation>
    <PMID>26833916</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee JH, Park HS, Chae SC, Cho Y, Yang DH, Jeong MH, Kim YJ, Kim KS, Hur SH, Seong IW, Hong TJ, Cho MC, Kim CJ, Jun JE, Park WH; Korea Acute Myocardial Infarction Registry Investigators. Predictors of six-month major adverse cardiac events in 30-day survivors after acute myocardial infarction (from the Korea Acute Myocardial Infarction Registry). Am J Cardiol. 2009 Jul 15;104(2):182-9. doi: 10.1016/j.amjcard.2009.03.010.</citation>
    <PMID>19576343</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levine GN, Bates ER, Blankenship JC, Bailey SR, Bittl JA, Cercek B, Chambers CE, Ellis SG, Guyton RA, Hollenberg SM, Khot UN, Lange RA, Mauri L, Mehran R, Moussa ID, Mukherjee D, Ting HH, O'Gara PT, Kushner FG, Ascheim DD, Brindis RG, Casey DE Jr, Chung MK, de Lemos JA, Diercks DB, Fang JC, Franklin BA, Granger CB, Krumholz HM, Linderbaum JA, Morrow DA, Newby LK, Ornato JP, Ou N, Radford MJ, Tamis-Holland JE, Tommaso CL, Tracy CM, Woo YJ, Zhao DX. 2015 ACC/AHA/SCAI Focused Update on Primary Percutaneous Coronary Intervention for Patients With ST-Elevation Myocardial Infarction: An Update of the 2011 ACCF/AHA/SCAI Guideline for Percutaneous Coronary Intervention and the 2013 ACCF/AHA Guideline for the Management of ST-Elevation Myocardial Infarction. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2016 Mar 15;67(10):1235-1250. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2015.10.005. Epub 2015 Oct 21. Review. Erratum in: J Am Coll Cardiol. 2016 Mar 29;67(12):1506.</citation>
    <PMID>26498666</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sianos G, Morel MA, Kappetein AP, Morice MC, Colombo A, Dawkins K, van den Brand M, Van Dyck N, Russell ME, Mohr FW, Serruys PW. The SYNTAX Score: an angiographic tool grading the complexity of coronary artery disease. EuroIntervention. 2005 Aug;1(2):219-27.</citation>
    <PMID>19758907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Task Force on the management of ST-segment elevation acute myocardial infarction of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC), Steg PG, James SK, Atar D, Badano LP, Blömstrom-Lundqvist C, Borger MA, Di Mario C, Dickstein K, Ducrocq G, Fernandez-Aviles F, Gershlick AH, Giannuzzi P, Halvorsen S, Huber K, Juni P, Kastrati A, Knuuti J, Lenzen MJ, Mahaffey KW, Valgimigli M, van 't Hof A, Widimsky P, Zahger D. ESC Guidelines for the management of acute myocardial infarction in patients presenting with ST-segment elevation. Eur Heart J. 2012 Oct;33(20):2569-619. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehs215. Epub 2012 Aug 24.</citation>
    <PMID>22922416</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stone GW, Bertrand M, Colombo A, Dangas G, Farkouh ME, Feit F, Lansky AJ, Lincoff AM, Mehran R, Moses JW, Ohman M, White HD. Acute Catheterization and Urgent Intervention Triage strategY (ACUITY) trial: study design and rationale. Am Heart J. 2004 Nov;148(5):764-75.</citation>
    <PMID>15523305</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toma M, Buller CE, Westerhout CM, Fu Y, O'Neill WW, Holmes DR Jr, Hamm CW, Granger CB, Armstrong PW; APEX-AMI Investigators. Non-culprit coronary artery percutaneous coronary intervention during acute ST-segment elevation myocardial infarction: insights from the APEX-AMI trial. Eur Heart J. 2010 Jul;31(14):1701-7. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehq129. Epub 2010 Jun 8.</citation>
    <PMID>20530505</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wald DS, Morris JK, Wald NJ, Chase AJ, Edwards RJ, Hughes LO, Berry C, Oldroyd KG; PRAMI Investigators. Randomized trial of preventive angioplasty in myocardial infarction. N Engl J Med. 2013 Sep 19;369(12):1115-23. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1305520. Epub 2013 Sep 1.</citation>
    <PMID>23991625</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wykrzykowska JJ, Garg S, Onuma Y, de Vries T, Goedhart D, Morel MA, van Es GA, Buszman P, Linke A, Ischinger T, Klauss V, Corti R, Eberli F, Wijns W, Morice MC, di Mario C, van Geuns RJ, Juni P, Windecker S, Serruys PW. Value of age, creatinine, and ejection fraction (ACEF score) in assessing risk in patients undergoing percutaneous coronary interventions in the 'All-Comers' LEADERS trial. Circ Cardiovasc Interv. 2011 Feb 1;4(1):47-56. doi: 10.1161/CIRCINTERVENTIONS.110.958389. Epub 2011 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>21205944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 1, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 1, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Amr Abdelbadee Abdelhameed Othman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Resident Physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>SYNTAX Score</keyword>
  <keyword>residual SYNTAX score</keyword>
  <keyword>SYNTAX Revascularization Index</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Coronary Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>ST Elevation Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glucuronyl glucosamine glycan sulfate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>IPD will not be shared with other researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

