<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03136341</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GCO 17-0592</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03136341</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Cross Over Pilot Study of Abobotulinum Toxin A (Dysport) as a Treatment for Task-dependent Upper Limb Tremor</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Placebo-controlled, Double-blind, Randomized, Cross Over Pilot Study of the Efficacy and Tolerability of Abobotulinum Toxin A (Dysport) as a Treatment for Task-dependent Upper Limb Tremor</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>David M. Simpson</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ipsen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Task-dependent upper limb tremor is a disorder that frequently impairs patients' function and
      quality of life. Few studies exist that quantify the improvements in motor performance and
      disability with botulinum toxin (injections). The study team aims to perform an exploratory
      pilot trial using toxin Type A (Dysport) in 25 patients with task-dependent upper limb
      tremor, to refine quantitative measures of performance using blinded video analysis,
      demonstrate efficacy and tolerability of injections, and provide power calculations for a
      potential future multi-centered double blinded clinical trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants are randomized to receive either study drug or placebo at the initial phase and cross over 12 weeks later and receive the alternative treatment</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Videos will be randomly provided to an outside assessor to determine benefit as a secondary outcome measure</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's Impression of Change</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>The principal outcome measure will be patient's impression of change using visual analog scale. Visual Analog Scale (VAS) 100 point scale from 0 (no improvement) to 100 (normal use).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's Impression of Change</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 18</time_frame>
    <description>The principal outcome measure will be patient's impression of change using visual analog scale. Visual Analog Scale is a 100 point scale from 0 (no improvement) to 100 (normal use).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician Global Impression of Change</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
    <description>Physician global impression of change is measured by using a visual analog scale. The CGI using a VAS is rated on a 100-point scale, with the severity of illness scale using a range of responses from 0 (no improvement) through to 100 (normal use).illness scale using a range of responses from 1 (normal) through to 7 (amongst the most severely ill patients).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Tremor, Limb</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Abobotulinum toxin A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Abobotulinum toxin A</intervention_name>
    <description>Dosing will be determined at each study visit based upon muscles involved</description>
    <arm_group_label>Abobotulinum toxin A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Dosing will be determined at each study visit based upon muscles involved</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with task-dependent essential tremor in upper limb. Tremor is present during
             at least one of the study functional tasks i. pointing task (touch between nose and a
             pen held 2 ft. in front. ii. pouring task (cup: pouring water out/in). iii. feeding
             task (weighted fork from plate on table to mouth). iv. string instrument bowing or
             holding instrument in static position. v. computer mouse (simple vertical or
             horizontal movements).

          -  Patients must be capable of performing informed consent.

          -  Patients on stable medications for treatment of task-dependent essential tremor for 1
             month prior to study entry and maintain them throughout the study.

          -  Patients previously treated with BoNT of any type must have occurred no sooner than 12
             weeks prior to study entry.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with no presence of tremor during study functional tasks.

          -  Presence of tremor during the functional task is below minimum amplitude required to
             be considered for injection based upon investigator's clinical judgment.

          -  Patients with unstable medical conditions or psychiatric conditions.

          -  Patients with a medical condition that precludes them from receiving BoNT injections.

          -  Pregnant women, or premenopausal women not willing to use contraceptive measures
             throughout the duration of the study.

          -  Lithium, Valproic acid, Amiodarone, typical and atypical neuroleptics. Exposure to
             other than the listed tremorogenic or potentially tremorogenic drugs is allowed only
             if, in the opinion of the investigator, this will not interfere with the study drug
             evaluations.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David M Simpson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mary-Catherine George</last_name>
    <phone>212-241-0784</phone>
    <email>Mary-Catherine.George@mssm.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mary-Catherine George</last_name>
      <phone>212-824-0784</phone>
      <email>mary-catherine.george@mssm.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>David M Simpson, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-241-8748</phone>
      <email>david.simpson@mssm.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David M Simpson, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jankovic J, Ashoori A. Movement disorders in musicians. Mov Disord. 2008 Oct 30;23(14):1957-65. doi: 10.1002/mds.22255. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18785647</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pullman SL, Hristova AH. Musician's dystonia. Neurology. 2005 Jan 25;64(2):186-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15668411</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Altenmüller E. Focal dystonia: advances in brain imaging and understanding of fine motor control in musicians. Hand Clin. 2003 Aug;19(3):523-38, xi. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12945651</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frucht SJ, Fahn S, Greene PE, O'Brien C, Gelb M, Truong DD, Welsh J, Factor S, Ford B. The natural history of embouchure dystonia. Mov Disord. 2001 Sep;16(5):899-906.</citation>
    <PMID>11746620</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elbert T, Pantev C, Wienbruch C, Rockstroh B, Taub E. Increased cortical representation of the fingers of the left hand in string players. Science. 1995 Oct 13;270(5234):305-7.</citation>
    <PMID>7569982</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Münte TF, Altenmüller E, Jäncke L. The musician's brain as a model of neuroplasticity. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2002 Jun;3(6):473-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12042882</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Altenmüller E, Jabusch HC. Focal dystonia in musicians: phenomenology, pathophysiology, triggering factors, and treatment. Med Probl Perform Art. 2010 Mar;25(1):3-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20795373</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schuele S, Jabusch HC, Lederman RJ, Altenmüller E. Botulinum toxin injections in the treatment of musician's dystonia. Neurology. 2005 Jan 25;64(2):341-3.</citation>
    <PMID>15668436</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pullman SL, Greene P, Fahn S, Pedersen SF. Approach to the treatment of limb disorders with botulinum toxin A. Experience with 187 patients. Arch Neurol. 1996 Jul;53(7):617-24.</citation>
    <PMID>8929169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carruthers J, Fournier N, Kerscher M, Ruiz-Avila J, Trindade de Almeida AR, Kaeuper G. The convergence of medicine and neurotoxins: a focus on botulinum toxin type A and its application in aesthetic medicine--a global, evidence-based botulinum toxin consensus education initiative: part II: incorporating botulinum toxin into aesthetic clinical practice. Dermatol Surg. 2013 Mar;39(3 Pt 2):510-25. doi: 10.1111/dsu.12148. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23458295</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pavicic T, Prager W, Klöppel M, Ravichandran S, Galatoire O. IncobotulinumtoxinA use in aesthetic indications in daily practice: a European multicenter, noninterventional, retrospective study. Clin Cosmet Investig Dermatol. 2015 Mar 5;8:135-42. doi: 10.2147/CCID.S74519. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>25834463</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brin MF, Lyons KE, Doucette J, Adler CH, Caviness JN, Comella CL, Dubinsky RM, Friedman JH, Manyam BV, Matsumoto JY, Pullman SL, Rajput AH, Sethi KD, Tanner C, Koller WC. A randomized, double masked, controlled trial of botulinum toxin type A in essential hand tremor. Neurology. 2001 Jun 12;56(11):1523-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11402109</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Louis ED, Barnes L, Wendt KJ, Ford B, Sangiorgio M, Tabbal S, Lewis L, Kaufmann P, Moskowitz C, Comella CL, Goetz CC, Lang AE. A teaching videotape for the assessment of essential tremor. Mov Disord. 2001 Jan;16(1):89-93.</citation>
    <PMID>11215599</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tröster AI, Pahwa R, Fields JA, Tanner CM, Lyons KE. Quality of life in Essential Tremor Questionnaire (QUEST): development and initial validation. Parkinsonism Relat Disord. 2005 Sep;11(6):367-73.</citation>
    <PMID>16103000</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 21, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 26, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 2, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David M. Simpson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Upper Limb</keyword>
  <keyword>Tremor</keyword>
  <keyword>task-dependent</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tremor</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>abobotulinumtoxinA</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Botulinum Toxins, Type A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>onabotulinumtoxinA</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

