<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03136029</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>F1311-R</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03136029</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exercise and NO in HFrEF</brief_title>
  <official_title>Overcoming Exercise Intolerance in Veterans With Heart Failure: The Role of NO.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Heart disease is the leading cause of death in the United States, accounting for one in every
      four deaths in 2010 and costing over $300 billion annually in health care, medication, and
      lost productivity. Heart failure with a reduced ejection fraction (HFrEF), a clinical
      syndrome that develops as a consequence of heart disease, now affects almost 6 million
      Americans. Within the VA Health Care System, HFrEF hospital admission rates continue to rise,
      and remain the number one reason for discharge from VA hospitals nationwide. Unfortunately,
      over one-third of all Veterans suffering from HFrEF die within two years of discharge despite
      optimized drug therapy, an unacceptably high number. This proposal is focused on how impaired
      muscle blood flow contributes to exercise intolerance in HFrEF, and on subsequently
      developing strategies for restoring exercise tolerance and slowing disease progression in
      this patient group. It is anticipated that knowledge gained from these studies will
      contribute to improved standard of care, quality of life, and prognosis in this VA patient
      group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Heart failure with reduced ejection fraction (HFrEF), a clinical syndrome that develops as a
      consequence of heart disease from multiple etiologies, now affects almost six million
      Americans, presenting an imminent need for further research addressing the pathophysiology of
      this pervasive disease. One of the most damaging consequences of the disease is an elevation
      in sympathetic nervous system (SNS) activity, which manifests peripherally as chronic
      vasoconstriction. In HFrEF patients, peripheral vasoconstriction acts to limit blood flow in
      the exercising muscle, promoting exercise intolerance, premature skeletal muscle fatigue,
      inactivity, and a subsequent acceleration in disease progression. Fortunately,
      disease-related sympathoexcitation may be remediable. Among the most influential modulators
      of peripheral SNS expression is the nitric oxide (NO) pathway. Thus, interventions focused on
      improving NO bioavailability may offer a new, unexplored strategy for inhibiting SNS
      overactivity in HFrEF, and thus represent a novel approach for improving and exercise
      tolerance.

      Specific Aim 1 will utilize an oral antioxidant (AOx) cocktail to study whether disruptions
      in oxidative stress can favorably influence exercise tolerance in HFrEF patients.

      Specific Aim 2 will examine the efficacy of oral tetrahydrobiopterin (BH4), a cofactor for
      endothelial nitric oxide synthase (eNOS), to improve exercise intolerance in HFrEF patients.

      Specific Aim 3 will examine the therapeutic potential of aerobic, knee-extensor (KE) exercise
      training to improve skeletal muscle blood flow and thus exercise tolerance in HF patients.
      Importantly, this exercise modality produces a potent training stimulus without the
      significant cardiopulmonary stress that accompanies more traditional, whole-body exercise. It
      is proposed that 12 weeks of supervised KE training will increase NO bioavailability and
      inhibit SNS activity, which will in turn improve vascular function and exercising limb blood
      flow.

      Specific Aim 4 will examine whether the interventional strategies in Aims 1-3 can improve
      adherence to an 8-week clinical cardiac rehabilitation program. It is hypothesized that
      chronic AOx consumption (Aim 1), BH4 consumption (Aim 2), and aerobic exercise training (Aim
      3) interventions will reduce the rate of attrition from Phase II outpatient Cardiac
      Rehabilitation in HFrEF patients compared to patients that did not participate in an
      interventional phase of the study.

      The investigators anticipate that disrupting this &quot;vicious cycle&quot; of vasoconstriction in
      HFrEF may improve overall vascular health to such a degree that significant improvements in
      exercise-related symptoms are realized, which could therefore improve enrollment in a cardiac
      rehabilitation program. In this context, findings from the proposed work may provide an
      important link between vascular and rehabilitative medicine, thus serving to refine current
      strategies for the treatment of Veterans with HFrEF, ultimately leading to enhanced quality
      of life in this cohort.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood Flow</measure>
    <time_frame>four years</time_frame>
    <description>ultrasound Doppler</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">140</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Failure With Reduced Ejection Fraction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral AOx</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>8 week oral antioxidant treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral AOx (placebo)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo for arm 1</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral BH4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>8 week oral tetrahydrobiopterin treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral BH4 (placebo)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo for arm 3</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ex training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>8-week knee-extensor exercise training program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ex training (attn con)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Attention control for arm 5</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Antioxidant</intervention_name>
    <description>Daily consumption of over-the-counter vitamins (600mg alpha lipoic acid, 1000mg vitamin c, 600IU vitamin E)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oral AOx</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Oral AOx (placebo)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tetrahydrobiopterin (BH4)</intervention_name>
    <description>Daily consumption of BH4 (10mg/kg)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oral BH4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Oral BH4 (placebo)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Kuvan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Exercise training</intervention_name>
    <description>Aerobic exercise training program (3x/week for 8 weeks, 1 hour per session)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ex training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Ex training (attn con)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        General Inclusion/Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The study group will include subjects with a history of stable cardiomyopathy
             (ischemic and non-ischemic, &gt;3 months duration, ages 45-75 yrs) despite a minimum of 6
             weeks of optimal treatment.

          -  Optimal therapy will be according to American Heart Association (AHA) /American
             College of Cardiology (ACC) and Heart Failure Society of America (HFSA) HF guidelines,
             including treatment with angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) and -blocker therapy (for
             at least 6 weeks), or have documented reason for variation, including medication
             intolerance, contraindication, patient preference, or personal physician's judgment.

          -  Patient enrollment will be limited to those individuals with New York Heart
             Association (NYHA) class II and III symptoms, left ventricular ejection fraction &lt;35%
             (LVEF), with no or minimal smoking history (&lt;15 pk yrs), and without pacemakers.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with atrial fibrillation or HF believed to be secondary to atrial
             fibrillation will be excluded.

          -  Patients with HF secondary to significant uncorrected primary valvular disease (except
             mitral regurgitation secondary to left ventricular dysfunction) will also be excluded.

          -  Patients will be sedentary, defined here as no regular physical activity for at least
             the prior 6 months and current activity level will be documented by an activity
             questionnaire.

          -  Patients must have no orthopedic limitations that would prohibit them from performing
             knee-extensor exercise.

          -  Due to the typical age of patients with HF, all women will be postmenopausal (either
             natural or surgical) defined as a cessation of menses for at least 2 years, and in
             women without a uterus, follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) &gt;40 IU/L.

          -  Women currently taking hormone replacement therapy (HRT) will be excluded from the
             proposed studies due to the direct vascular effects of HRT Comorbidity Exclusion
             Criteria: Patients with significant non-cardiac comorbidities, which if present could
             alter the study results, will be excluded.

               -  These include a diagnosis of Dementia

               -  Severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD)

               -  Peripheral Vascular Disease

               -  Anemia

               -  Sleep-related Breathing Disorder

               -  Severe Valvular Heart Disease

               -  Diabetes (if on insulin therapy)

               -  or End-stage Malignancy

          -  The investigators will also exclude morbidly obese patients (BMI &gt;40), patients with
             uncontrolled Hypertension (&gt;160/100), Anemia (Hgb&lt;9) and Severe Renal Insufficiency
             (individuals with creatinine clearance &lt;30 by the Cockcroft-Gault formula).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David W. Wray, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VA Salt Lake City Health Care System, Salt Lake City, UT</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David W Wray, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(801) 582-1565</phone>
    <phone_ext>4162</phone_ext>
    <email>David.Wray2@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Russell S Richardson, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(801) 582-1565</phone>
    <phone_ext>4344</phone_ext>
    <email>Russell.Richardson@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Salt Lake City Health Care System, Salt Lake City, UT</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84148</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David W Wray, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>801-582-1565</phone>
      <phone_ext>4162</phone_ext>
      <email>David.Wray2@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Douglas S Capps, BS</last_name>
      <phone>(801) 582-1565</phone>
      <phone_ext>4414</phone_ext>
      <email>scott.capps@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David W. Wray, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 27, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 27, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 2, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HFrEF</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise Intolerance</keyword>
  <keyword>Nitric Oxide</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antioxidants</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

