<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03135483</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Assiut university1711</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03135483</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Acute Kidney Injury as a Risk Factor for Myocardial Injury After Non Cardiac Surgery in Critical Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>clinical audit</acronym>
  <official_title>Assessment of Acute Kidney Injury as a Risk Factor for Myocardial Injury After Non Cardiac Surgery in Critical Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Acute kidney injury (AKI) affects approximately 20% of hospitalized patients and up to 67% of
      those admitted to an intensive care unit (ICU), making it among the most common organ
      dysfunctions among the critically ill.Major adverse cardiac events (MACE) after non cardiac
      surgery are a leading cause of morbidity and mortality. The reported incidence of
      postoperative myocardial infarction (POMI) among patients undergoing noncardiac surgery is
      between 3% and 6%.The aim of this study is to Identify the impact of acute kidney injury on
      the development of myocardial injury after non cardiac surgery and to correlate it with other
      risk factors of for MINS.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Acute kidney injury (AKI) is classically described as an abrupt or rapidly reversible
      reduction in the excretion of nitrogenous waste products, including urea, nitrogen, and
      creatinine. Acute kidney injury (AKI) affects approximately 20% of hospitalized patients and
      up to 67% of those admitted to an intensive care unit (ICU), making it among the most common
      organ dysfunctions among the critically ill. Depending on severity, AKI contributes to
      short-term mortality rates between 40% and 70%, and survivors are at increased risk for
      chronic kidney disease. Because surgical care and perioperative events and comorbidities
      interact to contribute to renal dysfunction in different patterns than in nonsurgical
      patients, surgical patients have unique risk factors for renal dysfunction.

      Major adverse cardiac events (MACE) after non cardiac surgery are a leading cause of
      morbidity and mortality. The reported incidence of postoperative myocardial infarction (POMI)
      among patients undergoing noncardiac surgery is between 3% and 6%. Early recognition and
      timely treatment of POMI after surgery are very important. Therefore, routinemonitoring of
      cardiac troponin has been recommended to identify patients at risk of early postoperative
      cardiovascular events after surgery. Myocardial injury after noncardiac surgery (MINS) is
      defined as follows: myocardial injury caused by ischemia (that may or may not result in
      necrosis), has prognostic relevance, and occurs duringor within 30 days after noncardiac
      surgery. MINS can be measured by postoperative troponin elevation in the presence or absence
      of clinical symptoms. MINS occurs in 8% to 22% of adults undergoing major non cardiacsurgery.
      To date, there have been few studies investigatingthe risk factors of MINS in critical
      patients.

      The postoperative AKI is a new risk factor of MINS in critical patients, and the impact of
      AKI on MINS has not been evaluated in previous studies.

      It is unclear by what mechanisms AKI influences theMINS in critical patients. A possible
      explanation of this finding is that in patientswith postoperativeAKI, disturbed autonomic
      nerve functions may induce postoperative hypotension and hypoperfusion, which may lead to
      MINS .

      Other idependent risk factors for myocardial injury after non cardiac surgery such as
      emergency surgery and long time operation.The aim of this study is to Identify the impact of
      acute kidney injury on the development of myocardial injury after non cardiac surgery and to
      correlate it with other risk factors of for MINS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>12 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of Acute Kidney Injury as a Risk Factor for Myocardial Injury after non Cardiac Surgery in Critical Patients</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>assessment of a risk factor</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Assesse Prevalence of Acute Kidney Injury and Myocardial Injury After Non Cardiac Surgery</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        adult above 18 years undergoe non cardiac surgery
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  -All patients aged 18 years or more undergoing non cardiac surgery under general or
             spinal anesthesia and expected length of postoperative hospital stay of at least 48
             hour.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  -Pregnancy

          -  Perioperative myocardial injury caused by a documented nonischemic etiology (eg,
             pulmonary embolism, sepsis, cardio version),

          -  Heart failure NYHA class III and IV.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 26, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 26, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 26, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 26, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ghada Safwat</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>assiut</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Kidney Injury</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>adult above 18years admitted to assiut university hospital intensive care units after non cardiac surgery</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

