<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03137654</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB201700206-N</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R03AA025430</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03137654</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sex Differences, Cognitive Training &amp; Emotion Processing</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sex Differences, Cognitive Training &amp; Emotion Processing</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (NIAAA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot project addresses two understudied questions related to neurocognitive deficits
      observed in treatment-seeking alcoholics. First, whether cognitive training improves
      performance and outcomes in alcoholics, and whether men and women differ in their response to
      this training. The second is whether directed training using affective materials (e.g.,
      emotional faces) is differentially effective compared to that using traditional (i.e.,
      neutral) stimuli.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This pilot project leverages the team's expertise in neurobehavioral assessment and focus on
      sex differences to examine the potential efficacy of cognitive training in treatment-seeking
      men and women with alcohol use disorders (AUDs). Specifically, the ask whether cognitive
      training interventions derived from current methods and conceptual models has differential
      benefits for treatment-seeking women vs. men. Although neurocognitive improvement during
      training is desired, of practical import is whether gains achieved transfer to other tasks
      and settings. Therefore, transfer of gains to tasks/domains varying in their similarity to
      training are assessed. Given noted sex differences in emotional processing and the purported
      role of emotional factors in women's substance use, training engaging emotional processing
      via the use of affective stimuli (faces and words) is included, predicting that women may
      differentially benefit from such training. Equal numbers of treatment-seeking men and women
      with AUDs will be randomly assigned to one of two active training interventions (neutral or
      affective stimuli). To control for abstinence-related recovery, a third group of
      participants, meeting identical selection criteria, will complete pre and post-intervention
      testing, but will not undergo the training intervention. Ss will complete baseline, 3 wks
      training (for active groups) and post-intervention testing and will be contacted monthly for
      3 months after discharge.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 16, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The primary design is a 3 (Training Condition: Neutral, Affective, Control) by 2 (Time: Baseline, Post-training) repeated measures design.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Emotional Stroop: Change from baseline in reaction time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Post-Training (3 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>An interference task involving target words presented over non-target visual stimuli. The primary dependent measure is change in reaction time on trials with incongruent stimuli (e.g., a negative word presented over a &quot;happy&quot; face) from baseline to post-training assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Trail-Making Task A: Change from baseline in task completion time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Post-Training (3 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>A psychomotor and visual perception task wherein participants connect numbered dots by drawing a continuous line. The primary dependent measure is change in task completion time from baseline to post--training assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Trail-Making Task B: Change from baseline in task completion time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Post-Training (3 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>A psychomotor and visual perception task with a set-shifting component wherein participants connect numbered and lettered dots by drawing a continuous line. The primary dependent measure is change in task completion time from baseline to post-training assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Digit Symbol Substitution: Change from baseline in translated symbols</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Post-Training (3 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>A psychomotor and set-shifting task involving translation between numbers and symbols. The primary dependent measure is the change in number of correctly translated symbols within 90 seconds from baseline to post-training assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Little Man Task: Change from baseline in response accuracy.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Post-Training (3 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>A visual perception task involving mental rotation. The primary dependent measure is the change in response accuracy from baseline to post-training assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Wisconsin Card Sorting Task: Change from baseline in response accuracy</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Post-Training (3 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>A reasoning and set-shifting task. Participants must determine novel rule sets for stimuli matching through trial and error. Ss must match each 'Test Card' with a 'Key Card'. Criteria for a successful match shift throughout the testing session and may include color, shape, and number of symbols. The primary dependent measure is the change in response accuracy from baseline to post-training assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sternberg Working Memory Task: Change from baseline in response accuracy</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Post-Training (3 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>A working memory task involving numbers presented visually. Ss are presented with a list of digits, one at a time, followed by a probe digit. They must determine if the probe digit was in the original set of digits and recall the digits. The primary dependent measure is the change in response accuracy from baseline to post-training assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroop Color-Word Task: Change from baseline in response time</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Post-Training (3 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>An interference task involving target words (e.g., red) presented in interfering colors (e.g., blue). The primary dependent measure is change in reaction time from baseline to post-training assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual-Perceptual Analysis Task: Change from baseline in response accuracy</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Post-Training (3 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>A discrimination task in which participants are asked to determine which complex shape differs among a set of three.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timeline Follow-back</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 30/60/90 days following post-training assessment</time_frame>
    <description>Measures frequency and quantity of daily substance use.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Moos Health and Daily Living Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 30/60/90 days following post-training assessment</time_frame>
    <description>Measures social support and activities.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Profile of Mood States</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 30/60/90 days following post-training assessment</time_frame>
    <description>Mood/affect assessment in which participants indicate whether presented words describe how they have felt during the past week on a scale from 0-4, where 0 indicates &quot;not at all&quot;; 1 indicates &quot;a little&quot;; 2 indicates &quot;moderately&quot;; 3 indicates &quot;quite a bit&quot;; and 4 indicates &quot;extremely&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mini Alcohol Craving Experience questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 30/60/90 days following post-training assessment</time_frame>
    <description>Indexes alcohol craving frequencies. Questions include:
Over the past week, how often did you have a strong urge to drink?
Over the past week, how often did you picture alcohol or drinking?
Over the past week, how often did you imagine what it would taste like?
Over the past week, how often did you imagine how your body would feel if you had a drink?
Over the past week, how often were these thoughts intrusive?
Participants respond on a scale from 1-10 for each question.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcohol Use Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Affective Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects complete baseline assessment, 3 wks of training with versions of the tasks using emotionally-laden stimuli, and a post-training assessment. Subjects will be contacted monthly for 3 months after discharge for follow-up interviews.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neutral Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects complete baseline assessment, 3 wks of training with versions of the tasks using neutral stimuli, and a post-training assessment. Subjects will be contacted monthly for 3 months after discharge for follow-up interviews.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control (Non-active)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects complete a baseline assessment and a secondary assessment approximately three weeks later. No active intervention is delivered. Subjects will be contacted monthly for 3 months after discharge for follow-up interviews.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Affective Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention includes up to 12 training sessions (~45 minutes each). Training sessions includes practice on cognitive tasks embedded with emotionally salient stimuli. Tasks include a dual modality n-back and a directed attend/ignore memory task.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Affective Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neutral Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention includes up to 12 training sessions (~45 minutes each). Training sessions includes practice on cognitive tasks embedded with neutral stimuli. Tasks include a dual modality n-back and a directed attend/ignore memory task.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neutral Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Minimum of 10 years of education

          -  Subjects must have 20/40 or better corrected vision (determined by Snellen chart)

          -  have no significant hearing impairment as determined by self-report and audiometric
             testing

          -  must meet criteria for DSM-IV alcohol dependence using the computerized Diagnostic
             Interview Schedule - IV

          -  A craving index is also administered to allow discussion in terms of DSM 5
             classification.

          -  Comorbid substance use including nicotine use is not exclusionary.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  May not have medical or psychiatric histories which would confound participation or
             data interpretation, e.g., epilepsy, stroke, untreated hypertension, psychotic
             disorders, anxiolytic medications.

          -  not be color blind (as determined by psuedoisochromatic plates)

          -  Endorsement of suicidal intent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>59 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sara Jo Nixon, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ben Lewis, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ben Lewis, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>352- 294-4920</phone>
    <email>Benlewis@ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Layla Lincoln, BS</last_name>
    <phone>352-294-4920</phone>
    <email>laylal@ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Sid Martin Bridge House</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32608</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UF Health Florida Recovery Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32608</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 28, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 28, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cognitive Training</keyword>
  <keyword>Emotion Processing</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

