<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03130829</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HiQ002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03130829</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>To Evaluate the QoL Improvement of Oral Oligo Fucoidan in Subjects Receiving Platinum-based Chemotherapy With NSCLC</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Parallel, Pilot Study to Evaluate the Quality of Life Improvement of Oral Oligo Fucoidan as an Adjuvant in Subjects Receiving Platinum-based Chemotherapy With NSCLC</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hi-Q Marine Biotech International, Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hi-Q Marine Biotech International, Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objectives:

      To evaluate the Quality of Life (QoL) score of adding oral Oligo Fucoidan to platinum-based
      chemotherapy in comparison with placebo in subjects with Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC).

      Secondary Objectives:

      To assess the progression-free survival (PFS) and objective response rate (ORR) of adding
      oral Oligo Fucoidan to platinum-based chemotherapy in comparison with placebo in subjects
      with NSCLC.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot, randomized, double-blind, multicenter study to evaluate the QoL score of
      Oligo Fucoidan plus platinum-based chemotherapy versus placebo plus platinum-based
      chemotherapy in subjects with NSCLC. Subjects will be randomized in a 1:1 ratio to receive
      4.4 g BID of Oligo Fucoidan or placebo BID. Subject randomization will be stratified by NSCLC
      disease stage (stage III and stage IV) and platinum-based drug (cisplatin and carboplatin).

      This is a two-part study. The study treatment will be planned as follow:

        1. Part I (Platinum-based Treatment Phase): Oligo Fucoidan/placebo in combination with 4~6
           cycles of platinum-based chemotherapy;

        2. Part II (Extension Phase): Continuous Oligo Fucoidan/placebo treatment after subject
           completed platinum-based chemotherapy.

      The total study treatment duration of investigational product from Part I to Part II will be
      6 months.

      Dosing of oral Oligo Fucoidan/placebo will begin on Study Day -2, 2 days prior to the start
      of the platinum-based chemotherapy regimen, and will continue twice a day (BID) through the
      following 6-months treatment period, which includes platinum-based treatment phase and
      extension phase, if there's no treatment interruption. All subjects will receive
      platinum-based IV infusion starting on Day 1 of each cycle, 3 weeks per cycle. Subjects will
      continue to receive Oligo Fucoidan/placebo for 6 months until develop of treatment toxicity
      which in the Investigator's opinion prohibits for further therapy, or until radiographic
      progression of disease. Subjects who experience toxicities due to chemotherapy may require a
      delay in the dosing schedule or a dose modification. Should a subject not receive
      platinum-based chemotherapy on a scheduled cycle, a rescheduled cycle will be designated when
      chemotherapy is reintroduced, but no more than 2 weeks delay.

      The visit for subjects who have completed platinum-based treatment phase will be considered
      as the End of Part I Visit (end of platinum-based treatment phase). The visit for subjects
      who have completed 6-months treatment period (Part I &amp; Part II) will be considered as the End
      of Treatment (EOT) Visit. It is preferable that EOT Visit procedures will be conducted for
      subjects prior to the initiation of another anticancer therapy.

      Radiographic tumor assessments will be conducted at screening period, Cycle 4, End of
      Platinum-based Treatment Phase, and EOT. Radiographic information will be collected according
      to the Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST) Version 1.1.

      Toxicities will be graded at each study visit according to the National Cancer Institute
      (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) Version 4.03.

      Quality of life assessment as measured by the European Organization for Research and
      Treatment of Cancer quality of life questionnaire (EORTC QLQ-C30) as well as health-related
      quality of life questionnaire designed by the National Health Research Institutes (NHRI),
      NHRI QLQ-TCM, based on traditional Chinese medicine (TCM) perspective. Both of them will be
      performed at Study Day -2, Day 8 of Cycle 1, Day 1 of Cycle 3 &amp; Cycle 5, and End of
      Platinum-based Treatment Phase.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized, double-blind, multicenter study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QoL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day -2 to complete of Platinum-based Treatment Phase(week18)</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of the QoL score changes from Study Day -2 to End of Platinum-based Treatment Phase between Oligo Fucoidan and placebo groups in intent to treat set (ITT) via the QoL questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QoL)</measure>
    <time_frame>tinumDay -2 to C1D8(week1), Cycle 3(week9), and Cycle 5(week15) of Platinum-based Treatment Phase</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of the QoL score changes from Study Day -2 to C1D8, C3D1, and C5D1 of Platinum-based Treatment Phase between Oligo Fucoidan and placebo groups in intent to treat set (ITT) via the QoL questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-Free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (baseline), Cycle 4(week12), complete of Platinum-based Treatment Phase(week18), EOT(week24), and 3 months post-treatment follow up if required</time_frame>
    <description>Progression-Free Survival will be evaluated according to radiographic progression per RECIST version 1.1 and survival information (death)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (baseline), Cycle 4(week12), complete of Platinum-based Treatment Phase(week18), EOT(week24), and 3 months post-treatment follow up if required</time_frame>
    <description>Objective Response Rate will be evaluated using measurements according to RECIST version 1.1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Cytokines</measure>
    <time_frame>Screening (baseline), Cycle 3 (week 9), and complete of Platinum-based Treatment Phase(week18)</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the changes of cytokine</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>NSCLC Stage IV</condition>
  <condition>NSCLC, Stage III</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oligo Fucoidan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oligo Fucoidan 4.4 g, sachet, oral, twice a day from Study Day -2 to End of Treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo 4.4 g, sachet, oral, twice a day from Study Day -2 to End of Treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oligo Fucoidan</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral, twice daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oligo Fucoidan</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral, twice daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female subjects must be ≥ 20 years of age, inclusive, at time of screening.

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 12 weeks.

          -  Subject must have cytologically or histologically confirmed NSCLC. Subjects with mixed
             histology tumors will be eligible. If cytology is used for diagnosis, the sample must
             be unequivocally NSCLC.

          -  Subject has Stage III or IV NSCLC disease at the time of screening.

          -  Subject is not amenable to surgical resection or radiation with curative intent and
             have not received chemotherapy for their NSCLC, no matter it is new diagnosis or
             relapse.

          -  Subject is planned to receive triweekly platinum-based chemotherapy regimen prior to
             randomization. (Platinum dose for cisplatin is 51~80 mg/m2, or carboplatin at AUC 4~6)

          -  Subject must have at least 1 measurable tumor lesion, not previously irradiated, as
             defined by RECIST (version 1.1).

          -  Subject must have no history of brain metastases or evidence of CNS tumors at
             screening assessment..

          -  Subject must have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Score of
             0-2.

          -  Subject must be able to take oral medication.

          -  Subject must have adequate bone marrow, renal and hepatic function as follows:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,500/mm3 (1.5 × 109/L);

               -  Platelets ≥ 100,000/mm3 (100 × 109/L);

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9.0 g/dL (5.6 mmol/L);

               -  Serum creatinine concentration within the normal range (according to the standard
                  value of each hospital);

               -  Hepatic function: AST and ALT ≤ 2.5 times upper limit of normal unless liver
                  metastases are present, then AST and ALT &lt; 5.0 times upper limit of normal;
                  bilirubin ≤ 1.5 times upper limit of normal (subjects with Gilbert's Syndrome may
                  have a bilirubin ≤ 3.0 times upper limit of normal).

          -  Female and male patients of childbearing potential and at the risk of pregnancy must
             agree to use at least one of highly effective contraception method throughout the
             study.

          -  Subject must be capable of understanding and complying with parameters as outlined in
             the protocol and able to sign inform consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has a known hypersensitivity to Fucoidan, platinum compounds and all other
             drug component of current chemotherapy.

          -  Subject has peripheral neuropathy ≥ grade 2.

          -  Subject has a history of seizure within 12 months prior to study entry.

          -  Subject has received more or equal to third-line biomarker-targeted therapy.

          -  Subject has received herbal remedies for cancer treatment, non-prescription
             anti-cancer supplements for cancer treatment, or traditional Chinese medicine with an
             approved anti-cancer indication within 2 weeks prior to randomization.

          -  Subject is undergone or planned to receive curative radiation therapy prior to
             randomization and during study. (The palliative radiation therapy such as for bony
             lesions is allowed, but irradiate on target lesion will not be allowed.)

          -  Subject has clinically significant and uncontrolled major medical condition(s)
             including but not limited to:

               -  Uncontrolled nausea/vomiting/diarrhea;

               -  Active uncontrolled infection;

               -  Symptomatic congestive heart failure;

               -  Unstable angina pectoris or cardiac arrhythmia;

               -  Psychiatric illness/social situation that would limit compliance with study
                  requirements;

               -  History of gross hemoptysis;

               -  Any medical condition, which in the opinion of the Investigator, places the
                  subject at an unacceptably high risk for toxicities.

          -  Subject is pregnant or lactating.

          -  Subject participates in study using an investigational drug within 30 days prior to
             screening.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Candy Tsai</last_name>
    <phone>+886 2 26980063</phone>
    <phone_ext>36</phone_ext>
    <email>candytsai@hiqbio.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shuang Ho Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Taipei City</city>
        <zip>235</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kang-Yun Lee, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+886 2 22490088</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kang-Yun Lee, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wan-Fang Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <zip>116</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gi-Ming Lai, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+886 2 29307930</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Gi-Ming Lai, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Taipei Medical University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Her-Shyong Shiah, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+886 27372181</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Her-Shyong Shiah, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 17, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 23, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 27, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 26, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 26, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 28, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>NSCLC</keyword>
  <keyword>QoL</keyword>
  <keyword>Fucoidan</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fucoidan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

