<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03132155</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>QUILT-3.031</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03132155</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>QUILT-3.031: AMG 337 in Subjects With Advanced or Metastatic Clear Cell Sarcoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2 Study of AMG 337 in Subjects With Advanced or Metastatic Clear Cell Sarcoma That Contains the Ewing Sarcoma Breakpoint Region 1-activating Transcription Factor-1 (EWSR1-ATF1) Gene Fusion</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NantPharma, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NantPharma, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase 2 study that will assess the efficacy of AMG 337 in subjects with advanced or
      metastatic clear cell sarcoma that contains the EWSR1-ATF1 gene fusion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The phase 2 study will assess efficacy of AMG 337 in subjects with advanced or metastatic
      clear cell sarcoma that contains the EWSR1-ATF1 gene fusion. The study will be conducted
      using Simon's two-stage optimal design. The null hypothesis of Simon's two-stage design
      states that the ORR will be ≤ 40% (poor response) and will be tested against a one-sided
      alternative.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Confirmed ORR (confirmed complete response or partial response) will be evaluated in accordance with RECIST Version 1.1.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events (Safety And Tolerability)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the safety of AMG 337 based on grade 3 or 4 non-hematologic toxicity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To determine PFS, evaluated in accordance with RECIST Version 1.1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To determine OS, defined as the time from the date of the first administration of therapy to the date of death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response (DOR)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To determine DOR, measured by RECIST Version 1.1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Control Rate (DCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>To determine DCR (confirmed CR, PR, or SD) lasting for at least 4 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Clear Cell Sarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AMG 337</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>AMG 337 will be administered in patients with advanced or metastatic clear cell sarcoma</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AMG 337</intervention_name>
    <description>6-{(1R)-1-[8-fluoro-6-(1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-4-yl)[1,2,4]triazolo[4,3-a]pyridin-3-yl]ethyl}-3-(2-methoxyethoxy)-1,6-naphthyridin-5(6H)-one•hydrate (1:1)</description>
    <arm_group_label>AMG 337</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Able to understand and provide a signed informed consent that fulfills the relevant
             Institutional Review Board (IRB) or Independent Ethics Committee (IEC) guidelines.

          2. Able to attend required study visits and return for adequate follow-up, as required by
             this protocol.

          3. Able to self-administer AMG 337 as a whole capsule by mouth every day.

          4. Age ≥ 16 years.

          5. Histologically confirmed, unresectable, locally advanced or metastatic tumors that
             contain the EWSR1-ATF1 gene fusion, as determined by fluorescent in situ hybridization
             (FISH) and confirmed by RNA sequencing (RNAseq).

          6. Have measurable disease evaluable in accordance with RECIST Version 1.1.

          7. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 to 2.

          8. Must have a recent Formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tumor biopsy specimen that
             was obtained following the conclusion of the most recent anticancer treatment. If an
             historic specimen is not available, the subject must be willing to undergo a biopsy
             during the screening period.

          9. Must be willing to undergo a biopsy during the treatment period, if considered safe by
             the investigator.

         10. Ability to attend required study visits and return for adequate follow-up, as required
             by this protocol.

         11. Hematologic function, as follows:

               1. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 × 109/L.

               2. Platelet count ≥ 50 × 109/L.

               3. Hemoglobin &gt; 8 g/dL.

               4. Prothrombin time (PT) or partial thromboplastin time (PTT) &lt; 1.5 × upper limit of
                  normal (ULN), except for subjects on anticoagulation therapy for venous
                  thromboembolism.

         12. Renal function, as follows:

             a. Calculated creatinine clearance &gt; 30 mL/min.

         13. Hepatic function, as follows:

               1. Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &lt; 2.5 × ULN
                  and total bilirubin &lt; 1.5 × ULN.

               2. Alkaline phosphatase (ALP) &lt; 2 × ULN (≤ 5 × ULN if bone or liver metastases are
                  present)

         14. Agreement to practice effective contraception (both male and female subjects, if the
             risk of conception exists).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Assessed by the investigator to be unable or unwilling to comply with the requirements
             of the protocol.

          2. Inability to attend required study visits and return for adequate follow-up, as
             required for this protocol.

          3. Known hypersensitivity to any component of the study medication(s).

          4. Women who are nursing, pregnant, or planning to become pregnant during the duration of
             the study.

          5. Current diagnosis or history of a second neoplasm, except the following:

             a. Adequately treated non-melanoma skin cancer, curatively treated in situ disease, or
             other solid tumors curatively treated with no evidence of disease for ≥ 2 years.

          6. History of bleeding diathesis.

          7. Uncontrolled hypertension (systolic &gt; 160 mmHg and/or diastolic &gt; 100 mmHg) or
             clinically significant cardiovascular disease, cerebrovascular accident/stroke, or
             myocardial infarction within 6 months before study day 1; unstable angina; congestive
             heart failure of New York Heart Association grade 2 or higher; or serious cardiac
             arrhythmia requiring medication.

          8. Baseline ECG Fridericia's formula QTcF &gt; 470 ms.

          9. Active infection requiring intravenous (IV) antibiotics within 2 weeks before study
             day 1.

         10. Significant gastrointestinal disorder (eg, Crohn's disease, ulcerative colitis,
             extensive gastrointestinal resection) that in the opinion of the Investigator may
             influence drug absorption.

         11. Positive result of screening test for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

         12. Evidence of acute hepatitis B and C. Subjects with chronic hepatitis B or C are
             eligible if their condition is stable and, in the opinion of the investigator, would
             not pose a risk to subject safety.

         13. Toxicities from prior anti-tumor therapy not resolved to CTCAE Version 4.03 grade 0 or
             1.

             a. Grade 2 toxicities from prior anti-tumor therapy that are considered irreversible
             (defined as having been present or stable for &gt; 4 weeks), such as stable grade 2
             peripheral neuropathy or ifosfamide-related proteinuria, may be allowed if they are
             not otherwise described in the exclusion criteria.

         14. Participation in this study or in an investigational study and/or procedure with any
             molecularly targeted agents reported to inhibit Mesenchymal epithelial transition
             factor (MET) within 14 days before study day 1.

         15. Anti-tumor therapy, including chemotherapy, antibody therapy, retinoid therapy, or
             other investigational therapy within 14 days before study day 1.

         16. Therapeutic or palliative radiation therapy within 14 days before study day 1.

         17. Major surgery within 28 days before study day 1.

         18. Any comorbidity that in the opinion of the investigator may increase the risk of
             toxicity.

         19. Concurrent or prior use of a strong CYP3A4 inhibitor within 14 days before study day
             1, including the following: ketoconazole, itraconazole, clarithromycin, indinavir,
             nefazodone, nelfinavir, ritonavir, saquinavir, telithromycin, and voriconazole.

         20. Concurrent or prior ingestion of grapefruit or grapefruit products, or other foods
             known to inhibit CYP3A4 within 7 days before study day 1.

         21. Concurrent or prior use of strong CYP3A4 inducers within 28 days before study day 1,
             including the following: phenytoin, carbamazepine, rifampin, rifabutin, rifapentin,
             phenobarbital, or the herbal supplement St. John's Wort.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jacqueline Ongwenyi</last_name>
    <phone>(310) 853-7876</phone>
    <email>Jacqueline.Ongwenyi@NantKwest.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jim Farmer</last_name>
    <phone>(310) 853-7522</phone>
    <email>Jim.Farmer@NantKwest.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chan Soon-Shiong Institute for Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>El Segundo</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90245</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 20, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 26, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 27, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma, Clear Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

