<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03139266</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HM20002923</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03139266</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Project UPLIFT to Reduce Anxiety and Depression in CF Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Project UPLIFT to Reduce Anxiety and Depression in CF Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Virginia Commonwealth University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Boston Children’s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University at Buffalo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Virginia Commonwealth University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      People with CF have elevated rates of anxiety and depression when compared to the general
      population. Anxiety and depression can have a negative impact on adherence and disease
      self-management, leading to worse CF health outcomes such as respiratory symptoms, functional
      capacity, and health-related quality of life (HRQOL).

      Project UPLIFT is a group mental health intervention that can be delivered by telephone or
      Web, though for this study the intervention will be web based only. Project UPLIFT was
      originally developed as a depression treatment and prevention program for people with
      epilepsy and was shown to be effective in reducing depression and increasing knowledge and
      skills. Recently, Project UPLIFT was revised to help people with CF manage their depression
      and anxiety and shown to be apparently successful in a pilot study that included adolescents
      and adults with CF.

      The goals of this project are to determine the effectiveness of Project UPLIFT in reducing
      anxiety and depression in adolescents and adults with CF, as well as increasing their quality
      of life and other physical health-related disease outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Project UPLIFT intervention was designed for delivery to groups of six to eight people by
      telephone or Internet, though for this study the intervention will be web based only. The
      telephone intervention comprised eight hour-long sessions, each including check-in,
      instruction, skill building, and discussion, with homework between sessions. The Web
      intervention contains the same elements: check-in, video instruction, skill building, a
      discussion board, and homework between sessions. Instruction focuses on increasing knowledge
      about depression, CF, CBT, and mindfulness and skills related to CBT and mindfulness.
      Participation in the sessions involves skills practice, discussions, and group exercises
      based on the sessions' main topics. CBT-related topics include thought monitoring,
      identifying cognitive distortions, self-esteem, problem identification, goal setting, and
      identifying supports. Relaxation exercises, including a body scan (i.e., a mindfulness
      exercise) and progressive muscle relaxation, are also used for coping and to facilitate
      awareness of the body. Mindfulness activities include attention to skin, sights, and sounds
      and other meditations. Participants will practice their skills between sessions through
      homework assignments including monitoring and changing thoughts, and practicing relaxation
      exercises, meditation exercises, and mindfulness. A week's homework is discussed at the
      beginning of the next session. The program is designed to guide participants from noticing,
      challenging, and changing thoughts (CBT components), to staying in the present moment with
      acceptance of and nonreactivity to those thoughts (mindfulness components). All sessions will
      be co-facilitated by a layperson with CF and a doctoral student in psychology, supervised by
      a licensed clinical psychologist.

      Once the subjects are recruited and enrolled, baseline assessment will take place and then
      they will be randomized into the intervention group or treatment-as-usual control group
      condition (recommendation to consider obtaining mental health services). All participants
      will complete questionnaires via the internet. Following the initial assessment, the groups
      will receive their assigned intervention (or control treatment) and there will be
      questionnaire based testing of mental health, QoL, and adherence at 2 months (immediately
      following the group intervention), 6 months, and 12 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 7, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduce symptoms of anxiety among UPLIFT Tx Group participants.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (at 0 week), Tx End (at 8 weeks), Follow-up (at 6 months post Tx End), Extended Follow-up (at 12 months post Tx End)</time_frame>
    <description>Anxiety symptoms will be assessed with the Generalized Anxiety Disorder-7 (GAD-7)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduce symptoms of depression among UPLIFT Tx Group participants.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (at 0 week), Tx End (at 8 weeks), Follow-up (at 6 months post Tx End), Extended Follow-up (at 12 months post Tx End)</time_frame>
    <description>Depressive Symptoms will be assessed with the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase quality of life among UPLIFT Tx Group participants.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (at 0 week), Tx End (at 8 weeks), Follow-up (at 6 months post Tx End), Extended Follow-up (at 12 months post Tx End)</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of Life will be assessed using the Cystic Fibrosis Questionnaire-Revised (CFQ-R).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase satisfaction with life among UPLIFT Tx Group participants.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (at 0 week), Tx End (at 8 weeks), Follow-up (at 6 months post Tx End), Extended Follow-up (at 12 months post Tx End)</time_frame>
    <description>Satisfaction with life will be measured using the Satisfaction with Life Scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improve medication adherence among UPLIFT Tx Group participants.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (at 0 week), Tx End (at 8 weeks), Follow-up (at 6 months post Tx End), Extended Follow-up (at 12 months post Tx End)</time_frame>
    <description>Medication adherence will be measured using the 8-item Morisky Medication Adherence Scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improve knowledge and skills regarding self-management of anxiety and depression among UPLIFT Tx Group participants.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (at 0 week), Tx End (at 8 weeks), Follow-up (at 6 months post Tx End), Extended Follow-up (at 12 months post Tx End)</time_frame>
    <description>Will be assessed using an 18-item true-false measure developed during the development of Project UPLIFT.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Increase self-efficacy among UPLIFT Tx Group participants.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (at 0 week), Tx End (at 8 weeks), Follow-up (at 6 months post Tx End), Extended Follow-up (at 12 months post Tx End)</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure this using the Depression Coping Self-Efficacy Scale (DCSES).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>(Exploratory) Change in CF disease severity status.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (at 0 week), Tx End (at 8 weeks), Follow-up (at 6 months post Tx End), Extended Follow-up (at 12 months post Tx End)</time_frame>
    <description>CF disease related measures will be collected from routine clinic visits that occur from the time of enrollment to final UPLIFT follow-up</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Cystic Fibrosis</condition>
  <condition>Anxiety</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>UPLIFT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Project UPLIFT intervention was designed for delivery to groups of six to eight people by telephone or Internet, though for this study the intervention will be web based only. The telephone intervention comprised eight hour-long sessions, each including check-in, instruction, skill building, and discussion, with homework between sessions. The Web intervention contains the same elements: check-in, video instruction, skill building, a discussion board, and homework between sessions. Instruction focuses on increasing knowledge about depression, cystic fibrosis (CF), cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT), and mindfulness and skills related to CBT and mindfulness.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment-as-usual</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>UPLIFT</intervention_name>
    <description>Participation in the sessions involves skills practice, discussions, and group exercises based on the sessions' main topics. CBT-related topics include thought monitoring, identifying cognitive distortions, self-esteem, problem identification, goal setting, and identifying supports. Relaxation exercises, including a body scan (i.e., a mindfulness exercise) and progressive muscle relaxation, are also used for coping and to facilitate awareness of the body. Mindfulness activities include attention to skin, sights, and sounds and other meditations. Participants will practice their skills between sessions through homework assignments including monitoring and changing thoughts, and practicing relaxation exercises, meditation exercises, and mindfulness.</description>
    <arm_group_label>UPLIFT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Treatment as usual</intervention_name>
    <description>The control group will receive the recommendation to consider maintaining mental health services</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        First, patients will have to agree to have their contact information shared with the study
        team in order to be eligible.

        Eligibility criteria:

          -  have been diagnosed with CF for at least 1 year;

          -  score 5-14 on the GAD-7 and/or a 5-19 on the PHQ-9;

          -  be ≥13 years of age;

          -  be English speaking; and

          -  not have a prominent cognitive impairment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Persons reporting active suicidal ideation on the PHQ-9 will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael S Schechter, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Virginia Commonwealth University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andrea Molzhon, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>804-628-4967</phone>
    <email>molzhonar@vcu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Commonwealth University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23298</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrea R Molzhon, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>804-628-4967</phone>
      <email>molzhonar@vcu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Michael S Schechter, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>804-828-5916</phone>
      <email>michael.schechter@vcuhealth.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 24, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 2, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cystic fibrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>mindfulness</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive behavioral therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>UPLIFT</keyword>
  <keyword>anxiety</keyword>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>web based intervention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cystic Fibrosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

