<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00878475</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>grmec62</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00878475</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dyspnea and Biomarkers in a Prehospital Setting</brief_title>
  <official_title>Quantitative Capnometry and Nt-proBNP in Differentiating of Acute Dyspnea in Pre-Hospital Emergency Setting</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Health Care Center Maribor</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Health Care Center Maribor</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In patients presenting with acute dyspnea in a pre-hospital setting, the early and correct
      diagnosis may present a significant clinical challenge. Physical examination, chest
      radiography, electrocardiography, and standard biological tests often fail to accurately
      differentiate heart failure (HF) from pulmonary causes of dyspnea. Timely differentiation of
      HF from other causes of dyspnea may permit the early institution of appropriate medical
      therapy. Brain natriuretic peptide (BNP) and amino-terminal pro-brain natriuretic peptide
      (NT-proBNP) have been proposed as early markers of HF and demonstrated to be useful for
      diagnosing and excluding HF in the emergency department. A combination of BNP or NT-proBNP
      testing and standard clinical assessment has been suggested to be superior to either tool
      used in isolation. Some previous studies have also suggested that quantitative capnometry
      (QC) may be useful in differentiating between cardiac and obstructive causes of respiratory
      distress. Therefore, the investigators hypothesized that a new combination of NT-proBNP
      testing, standard clinical assessment, and partial pressure of end-tidal CO2 (PetCO2) would
      optimize evaluation and differentiation of acute dyspnea in a pre-hospital setting.

      The aim of this study was to determine the accuracy of combination of QC, NT-proBNP, and
      clinical assessment in differentiating acute HF from obstructive pulmonary disease
      (COPD/asthma) as a cause of acute dyspnea in pre-hospital emergency setting.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">546</enrollment>
  <condition>Dyspnea</condition>
  <condition>Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <condition>COPD</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group with obstructive causes of dyspnea</arm_group_label>
    <description>Criteria for clinical assessment of severe asthma (diffuse polyphonic bilateral and particular expiratory wheezes, chest tightness, shortness of breath, using accessory muscles of breathing, signs of hyperinflation, atopic condition, personal or family history of asthma, tachypnea, previous asthma and asthma medications, and the value of modified Boston criteria for HF ≤ 5) and criteria for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) exacerbation (history of COPD, COPD medications, cough, worsening dyspnea, increased sputum production and volume, increased sputum purulence, rhonchi and rales, modified Boston criteria for HF ≤ 5)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Heart failure group</arm_group_label>
    <description>The investigators protocol for clinical assessment of HF-related acute dyspnea (the prehospital clinical assessment for HF) was designed based on Boston (13) and Framingham criteria for HF (14) (Table 1). The investigators did not use certain criteria from the original protocols, which were not available in the prehospital setting (e.g., chest radiography).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        During the period of the study, 546 consecutive patients with acute dyspnea were treated by
        emergency teams (emergency physician, register nurse, and medical technician/driver in an
        ambulance-car or at pre-hospital emergency medical center). After pre-hospital care, all
        patients were admitted to the University Clinical Center Maribor and followed until
        discharge.

        To be eligible for the study, a patient had to present with shortness of breath as the
        primary complaint (defined as either the sudden onset of dyspnea without history of chronic
        dyspnea or an increase in the severity of chronic dyspnea).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patient had to present with shortness of breath as the primary complaint (defined as
             either the sudden onset of dyspnea without history of chronic dyspnea or an increase
             in the severity of chronic dyspnea)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  age &lt;18 years

          -  history of renal insufficiency, trauma, severe coronary ischemia (unless patient's
             predominant presentation was dyspnea), and other causes of dyspnea:

               -  pneumonia

               -  pulmonary embolism

               -  carcinoma

               -  pneumothorax

               -  pleural effusion

               -  intoxications (drugs)

               -  anaphylactic reactions

               -  upper airway obstruction

               -  bronchial stenosis

               -  gastroesophageal reflux disorder

          -  according to the history, clinical status, and additional laboratory tests available
             in pre-hospital setting (D-dimer, troponin, C-reactive protein)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Štefek Grmec, Prof,MD,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Health Center, Center for emergency Medicine Maribor</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Health Center Maribor, Center for Emergency Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maribor</city>
        <zip>2000</zip>
        <country>Slovenia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Slovenia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 8, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 8, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 9, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 8, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 8, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 9, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Prof.Štefek Grmec, MD, PhD</name_title>
    <organization>Health Center Maribor, Emergency Medicine center</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Quantitative Capnometry</keyword>
  <keyword>N-Terminal Pro-Brain Natriuretic Peptide</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Heart Failure</keyword>
  <keyword>Diagnostic Accuracy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dyspnea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

