<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00878956</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H2007/02808</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00878956</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bicarbonate in Cardiac Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase IIb Multiple Blind Randomized Controlled Trial of Sodium Bicarbonate in Cardiac Surgery at High-risk of Acute Kidney Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Austin Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Austin Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      With over one million operations a year, cardiac surgery with cardiopulmonary bypass is one
      of the most common major surgical procedures worldwide (1). Acute kidney injury is a common
      and serious postoperative complication of cardiopulmonary bypass and may affect 25% to 50% of
      patients (2-4). Acute kidney injury carries significant costs (4) and is independently
      associated with increased morbidity and mortality (2,3). Even minimal increments in plasma
      creatinine are associated with an increase in mortality (5,6).

      Multiple causes of cardiopulmonary bypass-associated acute kidney injury have been proposed,
      including ischemia-reperfusion, generation of reactive oxygen species, hemolysis and
      activation of inflammatory pathways (7-10). To date, no simple, safe and effective
      intervention to prevent cardiopulmonary bypass-associated acute kidney injury in a broad
      patient population has been found (11-14).

      Urinary acidity may enhance the generation and toxicity of reactive oxygen species induced by
      cardiopulmonary bypass (10,15). Activation of complement during cardiac surgery (16) may also
      participate in kidney injury. Urinary alkalinization may protect from kidney injury induced
      by oxidant substances, iron-mediated free radical pathways, complement activation and tubular
      hemoglobin cast formation (9,17,18). Of note, increasing urinary pH - in combination with
      N-acetylcysteine (19,20) or without (21) - has recently been reported to attenuate acute
      kidney injury in patients undergoing contrast-media infusion.

      In a pilot double-blind, randomized controlled trial the investigators found sodium
      bicarbonate to be efficacious, safe, inexpensive and easy to administer. These findings now
      need to be confirmed or refuted by further clinical investigations in other geographic and
      institutional settings.

      Accordingly, the investigators hypothesized that urinary alkalinization might protect kidney
      function in patients at increased risk of acute kidney injury undergoing cardiopulmonary
      bypass needs to be confirmed in an international multicenter, double-blind, randomized
      controlled trial of intravenous sodium bicarbonate.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Renal impairment following cardiopulmonary bypass is common. While most of these patients do
      not require either short or long term renal replacement, the mortality of patients with acute
      renal failure is substantially greater than those who do not develop renal dysfunction.

      In a pilot double-blind, randomized controlled trial we found sodium bicarbonate to be
      efficacious, safe, inexpensive and easy to administer. These findings now need to be
      confirmed or refuted by further clinical investigations in other geographic and institutional
      settings.

      There is evidence that sodium bicarbonate affects the cardiovascular, respiratory and immune
      systems and may be of benefit to patients undergoing cardiac surgery.

      Study Design - overview and rationale

      Patients will be randomised to receive sodium bicarbonate from the induction of anaesthesia
      until 24 hours postoperatively, or a placebo (sodium chloride).

      Serum creatinine is the most commonly used clinical indicator of renal function along with
      urine output. Both will be measured for several days postoperatively - the time period during
      which renal impairment is most likely to develop.

      Randomisation The randomisation will be based on random numbers generated by computer. Once
      consent is obtained, the allocation of either treatment with sodium bicarbonate or placebo
      will be organised by an independent person (clinical trials pharmacist) who will dispense the
      coded and blinded infusion bags (shrink-wrapped in extra black plastic bags). This will be
      delivered to the anaesthetic staff looking after the patient in theatre, and the ICU nurse
      caring for the patient postoperatively.

      20 ml samples of heparinised blood and urine will be taken from the arterial line or urine
      catheter. Samples will be taken immediately after the preoperative insertion of the
      arterial/urine catheter, at 6, 24, 48, 72, 96 and 120 hours after commencement of
      cardiopulmonary bypass. Immediately following collection, the preoperative, 6 and 24 hour
      blood and urine will be centrifuged at low speed to separate the plasma from the cellular
      components. Urine and plasma will be stored in aliquots at -70 degrees prior to batch
      analysis.

      The following variables will be obtained:

      Code for patient, gender and age. Date and time of admission to ICU Operative procedure and
      date and time on and off cardiopulmonary bypass Preoperative assessment of left ventricular
      function, Comorbidities, Pre-, intra- and post-operative medication, Markers of renal
      function as described above, Doses of frusemide administered (or rate of frusemide infusion)
      Use of inotropes or vasopressors Cardiac output whenever measured for clinical purposes in
      the first 24 hours postoperatively Requirement of renal replacement therapy Urine output in
      each 6 hour period during the presence of urine catheter Acid base status and electrolytes at
      baseline, 6 and 24 hours after commencement of cardiopulmonary bypass, Time of intubation and
      extubation, Date and time of arrival on and discharge from ICU and hospital, death Resources
      required The principle of the study has been discussed with the involved cardiac
      anaesthetists, cardiac surgeons, intensivists and intensive care nurses, who have offered
      their co-operation. ICU research nurse to allocate patients and collect clinical data.
      Pharmacy will be required to prepare drug and placebo infusion bags. Clinical pathology will
      be required to perform 24 hour creatinine clearance estimation (in addition to those tests
      clinically indicated) Protocol violations All protocol violations will be recorded. It will
      then be decided whether the nature of such violation had been such that the patient should be
      excluded from primary data analysis. Such evaluation will be blinded to treatment.

      Withdrawal

      The treating clinician will have the right to withdraw the patient from the study if he or
      she believes that continued participation is jeopardising the patient's well being.

      Ethical Issues

      Sodium bicarbonate used in this study is considered to be very safe as has been demonstrated
      by its widespread clinical use in the management of critically ill patients with metabolic
      acidosis. We consider the potential benefit of this treatment theoretically significant.
      Given the balance of benefits and risks, we consider it ethical to proceed and seek informed
      consent.

      Indemnity

      This is an investigator-initiated study and, accordingly, no commercial sponsor's indemnity
      has been provided.

      Informed consent will be obtained from the patient prior to the operation by one of the
      investigators or the ICU research nurse. The clinical care of a patient who does not consent
      for any reason will not be affected.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients developing an increase in serum creatinine greater than 25% or 44 mmol/L (0.5 mg/dL) postoperative increase in serum creatinine after adjustment for relevant baseline variables</measure>
    <time_frame>within first five postoperative days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean changes in serum creatinine after adjustment for relevant baseline variables</measure>
    <time_frame>within first five postoperative days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>mean changes in serum cystatin C after adjustment for relevant baseline variables</measure>
    <time_frame>within first five postoperative days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>mean changes in urinary neutrophil gelatinase-associated lipocalin (NGAL)after adjustment for relevant baseline variables</measure>
    <time_frame>within first five postoperative days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of ventilation</measure>
    <time_frame>Until time of extubation from mechanical ventilation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients developing any of the RIFLE criteria: R, I or F</measure>
    <time_frame>within first five postoperative days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of post-operative atrial fibrillation</measure>
    <time_frame>within first five postoperative days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of stay in the intensive care unit (ICU)</measure>
    <time_frame>from admission to the ICU</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of stay in hospital</measure>
    <time_frame>from admission to discharge from hospital</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>90-day mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>during 90 days postoperatively</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in electrolyte status from baseline to peak</measure>
    <time_frame>within first 24-48hrs postoperatively</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">427</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Kidney Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In all patients body weight adjusted dose of study medication will be achieved by infusion of sodium bicarbonate at a dose of 0.5 mmol/kg body weight (=bolus) diluted in 250 mL over 1 hour immediately after the induction of anesthesia, prior to the first surgical incision followed by continuous intravenous infusion of 0.2 mmol/kg/hr (=maintenance) diluted in 1000 mL 23 hours (total dose of 5 mmol/kg over 24 hours).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In all patients body weight adjusted dose of study medication will be achieved by infusion of sodium chloride at a dose of 0.5 mmol/kg body weight (=bolus) diluted in 250 mL over 1 hour immediately after the induction of anesthesia, prior to the first surgical incision followed by continuous intravenous infusion of 0.2 mmol/kg/hr (=maintenance) diluted in 1000 mL 23 hours (total dose of 5 mmol/kg over 24 hours).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sodium Bicarbonate</intervention_name>
    <description>In all patients body weight adjusted dose of study medication will be achieved by infusion of sodium bicarbonate at a dose of 0.5 mmol/kg body weight (=bolus) diluted in 250 mL over 1 hour immediately after the induction of anesthesia, prior to the first surgical incision followed by continuous intravenous infusion of 0.2 mmol/kg/hr (=maintenance) diluted in 1000 mL 23 hours (total dose of 5 mmol/kg over 24 hours).</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sodium Chloride</intervention_name>
    <description>In all patients body weight adjusted dose of study medication will be achieved by infusion of sodium chloride at a dose of 0.5 mmol/kg body weight (=bolus) diluted in 250 mL over 1 hour immediately after the induction of anesthesia, prior to the first surgical incision followed by continuous intravenous infusion of 0.2 mmol/kg/hr (=maintenance) diluted in 1000 mL 23 hours (total dose of 5 mmol/kg over 24 hours).</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age above 70 years

          -  Pre-existing renal impairment (preoperative plasma creatinine concentration &gt; 1.4
             mg/dL

          -  New York Heart Association class III/IV or impaired left ventricular function (left
             ventricular ejection fraction &lt; 50%)

          -  Valvular surgery or concomitant valvular and coronary artery bypass graft surgery

          -  Redo cardiac surgery

          -  Insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  End stage renal disease (plasma creatinine concentration &gt; 3.4 mg/dL)

          -  Emergency cardiac surgery

          -  Planned off-pump cardiac surgery

          -  Known blood-borne infectious disease

          -  Chronic inflammatory disease on immunosuppression

          -  Chronic moderate to high dose corticosteroid therapy (&gt; 10 mg/d prednisone or
             equivalent)

          -  Enrolled in conflicting research study

          -  Age &lt; 18 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>70 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rinaldo Bellomo, MD, FRACP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Austin Hospital, Melbourne Australia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Frank van Haren, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Waikato Hospital, Hamilton, New Zealand</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shay McGuinness, MB ChB, FRCA, FANZCA</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Auckland City Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Austin Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3084</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Warringal Private Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3084</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Auckland City Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Auckland</city>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Waikato Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>New Zealand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 8, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 8, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 9, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 31, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 31, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 1, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Austin Health</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rinaldo Bellomo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of ICU Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cardiac surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiopulmonary bypass</keyword>
  <keyword>Oxidative stress</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute renal dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>Sodium bicarbonate</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acute Kidney Injury</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

