<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00872664</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>31886</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ANUS 0805</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00872664</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Skin and Serum Carotenoids in Preterm Infants Fed on a Formula Supplemented With Carotenoids</brief_title>
  <official_title>Skin and Serum Carotenoids in Preterm Infants Fed on a Formula Supplemented With Carotenoids</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Abbott</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Utah</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objectives of this study are to compare the serum and skin concentrations of
      beta-carotene, lutein, and lycopene in preterm infants fed preterm formulas with mixed
      carotenoids to serum concentrations in preterm infants fed preterm formulas with no added
      carotenoids and to human milk fed infants.

      The secondary objective of this study is to evaluate the effects of dietary carotenoids on
      the developing eye. Stages and zones of retinopathy of prematurity (ROP), retinal function,
      and retinal characteristics will also be examined.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Infants that are born prior to 37 weeks gestation often face complications resulting from
      their prematurity. Preterm infants are susceptible to morbidities that are not common in
      healthy term infants. Underdeveloped organs such as the lungs, eye, intestine, and brain can
      reveal conditions unique to prematurity: chronic lung disease, bronchopulmonary dysplasia
      (BPD), retinopathy of prematurity (ROP), necrotizing enterocolitis, intraventricular
      hemorrhage (IVH), etc. Infants in the Newborn Intensive Care Unit (NICU) have increased
      inflammation and oxidative stress in association with common diseases of prematurity and as
      well as the treatments used to combat their illnesses (Gitto et al 2004; Ochoa et al 2003;
      Saugstad 2003).

      According to the National Eye Institute (U.S. National Institutes of Health), retinopathy of
      prematurity affects approximately 50% of preterm infants that are born weighing 1250 g or
      less. While 90% of infants with retinopathy of prematurity (ROP) experience the milder form
      of the disease, which requires little or no medical treatment, severe ROP can lead to serious
      visual impairments or even blindness. This condition is of particular interest since Hylander
      et al. (Hylander et al 2001) have reported that human milk feeding of preterm infants (&lt;1500
      g birth weight) has been associated with a lower incidence of ROP and this association was
      proposed to be driven by the antioxidant content of human milk. Human milk provides a variety
      of antioxidants to the breastfed infant, including the carotenoids lutein, zeaxanthin,
      lycopene, and beta-carotene. As discussed earlier, lutein and zeaxanthin are concentrated to
      the eye and are thought to provide protection against both light-induced and metabolic
      oxidative damage.

      The retina and retinal vasculature are the last eye structures to develop in the human
      fetus/neonate. Eyes of children with a history of ROP are reported to have retinal thinning
      with diffuse hypopigmentation, mild linearization, or mild tortuosity of the major vessel
      branch, mottled pigmentation of the macula, and other peripheral retinal anomalies (Minicucci
      et al 1999). The lack of pigmentation in the retinal structure might be explained by the
      deficit of lutein acquired by the fetus (by placental transfer during late gestation) or by
      the neonate through the diet (by preterm infant formulas devoid of these carotenoids).
      Preterm infants are at a nutritional disadvantage at birth as they have been deprived of the
      period of maximal transfer of nutrients during the last few weeks of pregnancy. Blood levels
      of beta-carotene have been associated with gestational age (Ostrea et al 1986) and cord blood
      levels of beta-carotene (Herrera et al 2004; Kiely et al 1999; Yeum et al 1998), lutein
      (Kiely et al 1999), and lycopene (Herrera et al 2004; Kiely et al 1999) were reported to be
      significantly lower than maternal levels. Stores of fat-soluble antioxidant vitamins also
      could be compromised due to the minimal fat deposition in the preterm infant.

      It is therefore reasonable to suggest that providing preterm infants with a milk-based
      ready-to-feed (RTF) preterm infant formula with DHA and ARA supplemented with carotenoids,
      which are found in human milk, would result in serum carotenoid levels more like the
      breastfed infant. Further, increased dietary carotenoid intake by preterm infants might
      decrease the prevalence of morbidities that are associated with prematurity, such as ROP,
      bronchopulmonary dysplasia (BPD), and intraventricular hemorrhage (IVH).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary objective is to compare the serum and skin levels of carotenoids in preterm infants fed formulas with mixed carotenoids to serum and skin levels in preterm infants fed formulas/human milk with no added carotenoids.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The secondary objective of this study is to evaluate the effects of dietary carotenoids on the developing eye.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Retinopathy of Prematurity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>formula with added carotenoids</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Both arms are double-blinded. Infant will be assigned to receive preterm formula with added carotenoids. If infant is receiving human milk then the study formula will only be used as a supplement.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>formula without added carotenoids</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Both arms are double-blinded. This arm will use preterm formula as it is currently available, which is without any carotenoids. If the infant is receiving human milk, then the formula will be used as a supplement as needed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>carotenoids</intervention_name>
    <description>beta-carotene, lycopene, lutein</description>
    <arm_group_label>formula with added carotenoids</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>formula without added carotenoids</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Birth weight 500-1500 g.

          -  Less than 33 weeks gestational age (GA) at birth. Maternal dates will be used to
             estimate GA except in instances where a scan or the neonatologist's estimate differs
             by two weeks or more. In this instance, the scan or neonatologist's estimate of GA
             will be used. In the case where one neonatologist's estimate or scan confirms maternal
             dates and the other estimate does not confirm maternal dates, use the estimate of
             maternal dates.

          -  Randomization within 96 hours of initiation of enteral feeding of &gt;/= 60mL/kg/d of HM
             or formula

          -  Formula fed infants' feeding consists of no more than 20% from human milk.

          -  Enteral feeding initiated by 21 days of life (date of birth is Day 0 of life).

          -  Parent/LAR agrees to allow infants to receive the assigned SSC Advance or NeoSure
             Advance formula in-hospital starting with the first enteral feed after randomization.
             If mother is providing breast milk, formula will only be given if there is not
             sufficient mother's milk.

          -  Parent/LAR signed the informed consent.

          -  SGA infants and infants with PDA are eligible to participate.

          -  Singleton or twin births only. For twins to be eligible, both must meet inclusion
             criteria.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Serious congenital abnormalities that may affect growth and development.

          -  Grade III or IV IVH.

          -  Maternal incapacity: including maternal cocaine or alcohol abuse during pregnancy or
             current, or if the mother or infant is currently receiving treatment consistent with
             HIV therapy.

          -  History of major surgery (including surgery for NEC).

          -  Asphyxia (hypoxia and ischemia) as evident by severe and permanent neurological
             damage.

          -  Confirmed NEC (modified Bell's stage II or III) or positive blood cultures at the time
             of randomization

          -  Infants who are enrolled in this clinical study should be excluded from participation
             in other concomitant studies. This exclusion criterion can be reviewed on a
             case-by-case basis. For example, infants will not normally be excluded if only
             demographic data are being collected or outcome measures on treatment modalities
             common to current clinical practice are being gathered.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Days</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gary M Chan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Utah</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Utah Health Sciences Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84132</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 30, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 30, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 31, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 3, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 3, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 4, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Dr. Gary Chan</name_title>
    <organization>University of Utah</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ROP</keyword>
  <keyword>anti-oxidants</keyword>
  <keyword>carotenoids</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Retinopathy of Prematurity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carotenoids</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

