<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00876434</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>090116</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>09-EI-0116</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00876434</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Subconjunctival Sirolimus for the Treatment of Autoimmune Active Anterior Uveiti</brief_title>
  <official_title>Subconjunctival Sirolimus for the Treatment of Autoimmune Active Anterior Uveitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Uveitis is an inflammatory condition in which the patient's own immune system attacks
           the eye, causing eye inflammation and vision loss. Patients with uveitis may be treated
           with immunosuppressive medications to reduce the inflammation and prevent vision loss.

        -  Sirolimus is an immunosuppressive medication that is approved by the U.S. Food and Drug
           Administration (FDA) to prevent organ rejection following a kidney transplant.
           Researchers think that sirolimus may affect the part of the immune system that may be an
           important cause of uveitis, and may decrease the inflammation that causes uveitis.

        -  In this study, sirolimus will be given as an injection under the outer layer of your
           eye. The FDA has permitted the investigational use of sirolimus for this study.

      Objectives:

        -  To determine if subconjunctival injection of sirolimus is safe for treatment of uveitis.

        -  To see if sirolimus is an effective treatment for uveitis.

      Eligibility:

        -  Patients 18 years of age and older with active uveitis in one or both eyes. If a patient
           has uveitis in both eyes, the one in which the inflammation is worse will be treated
           during the study. The vision in the study eye must be at least 20/400.

        -  Patients must have good liver function, and must be willing to practice sun protection
           measures for 2 weeks following the treatment.

      Design:

        -  Treatment with sirolimus in the study eye:

        -  Antibiotic and numbing eye drops will be given before the sirolimus injection.

        -  1 dose of sirolimus will be injected directly into the subconjunctiva (white part of the
           eye).

        -  Antibiotic drops will be given for topical application 3 times per day for 2 days after
           the injection.

        -  Patients will be followed for 16 weeks after sirolimus injection (initial visit and
           follow-up visits in Weeks 2, 4, 8, 12, and 16).

        -  Evaluations during the treatment period and follow-up visits:

        -  Physical examination, including vital signs and body weight checks, and pregnancy test
           for women who can become pregnant.

        -  Full medical and ophthalmic history, involving questionnaires and discussion with
           researchers.

        -  Eye examination, dilation, and photography, including measurements of retinal thickness
           and fluorescent dye tests of blood flow in the eye.

        -  Blood and urine tests.

        -  Because of the increased risk of skin cancer associated with sirolimus, patients ...
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: Uveitis refers to intraocular inflammatory diseases that are an important cause of
      visual loss. Standard systemic immunosuppressive medications for uveitis can cause
      significant adverse effects and many patients continue to experience disease flare-ups.
      Sirolimus suppresses cytokine-driven T-cell proliferation and thus, inhibits the production,
      signaling and activity of many growth factors relevant to uveitis. Subconjunctival sirolimus
      administration could reduce or eliminate the need for topical and/or systemic
      immunosuppressive drugs that could result in reduced morbidity. This protocol will
      investigate subconjunctival sirolimus as a possible treatment for active anterior uveitis.

      Study Population: Five participants with active anterior uveitis will be initially accrued in
      this study. Participants must require treatment for their uveitis with systemic and/or
      topical anti-inflammatory medications at high frequency intervals [greater than or equal to
      three times daily (T.I.D.)] or local steroid treatment (periocular steroid injections) is
      contraindicated because of significant intraocular pressure (IOP) elevation with local
      steroid treatments in the past (i.e., steroid responder), have at least a grade of 1+ for
      anterior chamber cells and have visual acuity of at least 20/400 in the study eye. Up to
      seven participants may be enrolled, as up to two participants may be accrued to replace
      enrolled participants who withdraw from the study prior to receiving any study medication.

      Design: This is a Phase I, non-randomized, prospective, uncontrolled single-center study to
      evaluate subconjunctival sirolimus as a treatment for active anterior uveitis. All
      participants will receive a single 30-microL (1,320 microg) subconjunctival sirolimus
      injection in the study eye at baseline and will be followed for 16 weeks post-injection.

      Outcome Measures: The primary outcome is the number of participants who experience at least a
      2-step reduction in anterior chamber inflammation within four weeks post-injection. Secondary
      outcomes include changes in visual acuity and anterior chamber inflammation grading, the
      number of participants who experience a disease flare within the 16-week study duration and,
      of the participants who experience a disease flare, the number of days to disease flare from
      baseline. Secondary outcomes also include the presence or extent of cystoid macular edema.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 1, 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 10, 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 10, 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome is the number of participants who experience at least a 2-step reduction in inflammation within four weeks post-injection.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in VA; changes in AC cells &amp; flare-ups; number of disease flares, number of days until the first disease flare; the presence or extent of CME; the amount of retino-vascular leakage; and changes in retinal thickening.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Anterior Uveitis</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sirolimus</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Participant has the ability to understand and sign the informed consent document.

          -  Participant is 18 years of age or older.

          -  Participant's uveitis is considered active on current regimen.

          -  Participant has a diagnosis of non-infectious anterior uveitis requiring treatment to
             control their intraocular inflammatory disease with systemic and/or topical
             anti-inflammatory medications at high frequency intervals (greater than or equal to
             T.I.D.) or local steroid treatment (periocular steroid injections) is contraindicated
             because of significant IOP elevation with local steroid treatments in the past
             (steroid responder).

          -  Participant has anterior uveitis with at least a grade of 1+ for anterior chamber
             cells 1 in the study eye.

          -  Participant has visual acuity in the study eye of 20/400 or better (or ETDRS
             equivalent).

          -  Participant has normal renal or liver function, or no worse than mild abnormalities as
             defined by the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events v3.0 (CTCAE).

          -  Participant has no history of intraocular surgery within three months prior to study
             enrollment and agrees not to undergo elective ocular surgery (e.g., cataract
             extraction) for the duration of the study.

          -  Participant has an absolute neutrophil count (ANC) above 750/mm(3)

          -  Participant is able to undergo full ophthalmic examination for assessment of anterior
             chamber cells.

          -  Participant understands there is an increased risk for skin cancer with sirolimus
             usage and agrees to practice skin protective measures for two weeks following their
             injection. Skin protective measures include: 1) staying out of direct sunlight,
             especially between the hours of 10:00 a.m. and 3:00 p.m., if possible; 2) wearing
             protective clothing, including a hat and sunglasses; 3) applying a sun block product
             that has a skin protection factor (SPF) of at least 15 (some participants may require
             a product with a higher SPF number, especially if they have a fair complexion); 4)
             applying a sun block lipstick that has a SPF of at least 15 to protect the lips; and
             5) not using a sun lamp or tanning booth or bed.

          -  Participant is willing and able to comply with the study procedures.

          -  Female participants of childbearing potential must not be pregnant or breast-feeding,
             must have a negative urine pregnancy test at screening and must be willing to undergo
             urine pregnancy tests throughout the study.

          -  Both female participants of childbearing potential and male participants able to
             father a child must agree to practice two forms of adequate birth control throughout
             the course of the study and for three months post-injection. Acceptable methods of
             birth control include hormonal contraception (birth control pills, injected hormones
             or vaginal ring), intrauterine device, barrier methods with spermicide (diaphragm with
             spermicide, condom and spermicide) or surgical sterilization (hysterectomy, tubal
             ligation or vasectomy).

               -  Participants with a hysterectomy or vasectomy (or have a partner with a
                  hysterectomy or vasectomy) are exempt from using two methods of contraception.
                  However, female participants with a tubal ligation (or male participants who have
                  a female partner with a tubal ligation) are not exempt, and are required to
                  practice another acceptable method of birth control.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Participant has a significant active infection (an infection requiring treatment as
             determined by the medical team) or a history of chronic or recurrent infections.

          -  Participant has a history of cancer (other than a non-melanoma skin cancer) diagnosed
             within the past five years.

          -  Participant has used latanoprost (Xalatan (Registered Trademark)) within two weeks
             prior to study enrollment or is likely to need it at any point during the study as
             determined by the investigator.

          -  For participants with active anterior uveitis in both eyes, the participant's
             non-study eye is anticipated to require periocular steroids or it is anticipated that
             an increase in systemic immunosuppressive treatments including steroids may be
             required during the course of the study.

          -  Participant has a media opacity that precludes assessment of anterior chamber
             inflammation.

          -  Participant has active joint or systemic inflammation requiring immediate addition or
             increase in systemic anti-inflammatory medications.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jabs DA, Nussenblatt RB, Rosenbaum JT; Standardization of Uveitis Nomenclature (SUN) Working Group. Standardization of uveitis nomenclature for reporting clinical data. Results of the First International Workshop. Am J Ophthalmol. 2005 Sep;140(3):509-16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16196117</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gritz DC, Wong IG. Incidence and prevalence of uveitis in Northern California; the Northern California Epidemiology of Uveitis Study. Ophthalmology. 2004 Mar;111(3):491-500; discussion 500.</citation>
    <PMID>15019324</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wakefield D, Dunlop I, McCluskey PJ, Penny R. Uveitis: aetiology and disease associations in an Australian population. Aust N Z J Ophthalmol. 1986 Aug;14(3):181-7.</citation>
    <PMID>3768171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 10, 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 3, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 3, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 6, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Sirolimus</keyword>
  <keyword>Anterior Uveitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Autoimmune Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Uveitis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Uveitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uveitis, Anterior</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Iridocyclitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Everolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

