<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00874731</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>8669-037</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2009_569</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00874731</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Effect of MK-8669 (Ridaforolimus) on QTc Interval in Participants With Advanced Cancer (MK-8669-037 AM1)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Clinical Trial to Assess the Effect of Deforolimus (AP23573; MK-8669) on QTc Interval in Patients (Protocol 037)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess the potential for ridaforolimus to prolong the QTc interval (an effect on the
      electrical activity of the heart) in participants with advanced cancer. This study will be
      done in 2 parts. Part 1 will evaluate the effect of a single 100 mg dose of ridaforolimus on
      QT interval in participants with advanced cancer. Fridericias's correction (QTcF) will be
      used. In Part 2 participants will receive ridaforolimus at the current therapeutic dose (40
      mg x 5 days).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from Baseline to 0.5 hours in Fridericia's Correction to QT interval (QTcF) after single oral 100 mg dose of ridaforolimus versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Hour 0.5</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from Baseline to 1 hour in Fridericia's Correction to QT interval (QTcF) after single oral 100 mg dose of ridaforolimus versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Hour 1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from Baseline to 2 hours in Fridericia's Correction to QT interval (QTcF) after single oral 100 mg dose of ridaforolimus versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Hour 2</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from Baseline to 3 hours in Fridericia's Correction to QT interval (QTcF) after single oral 100 mg dose of ridaforolimus versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Hour 3</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from Baseline to 4 hours in Fridericia's Correction to QT interval (QTcF) after single oral 100 mg dose of ridaforolimus versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Hour 4</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from Baseline to 6 hours in Fridericia's Correction to QT interval (QTcF) after single oral 100 mg dose of ridaforolimus versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Hour 6</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from Baseline to 8 hours in Fridericia's Correction to QT interval (QTcF) after single oral 100 mg dose of ridaforolimus versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Hour 8</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from Baseline to 10 hours in Fridericia's Correction to QT interval (QTcF) after single oral 100 mg dose of ridaforolimus versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Hour 10</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change from Baseline to 24 hours in Fridericia's Correction to QT interval (QTcF) after single oral 100 mg dose of ridaforolimus versus placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Hour 24</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants experiencing adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>In Part 1, Day 1 for placebo and Day 2 for ridaforolimus 100 mg; Part 2, from Day 1 up to 30 days after the last ridaforolimus 40 mg dose (up to approximately 1 year).</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants who Discontinued From Study Drug due to Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>In Part 1, Day 1 for placebo and Day 2 for ridaforolimus 100 mg; Part 2, from Day 1 up to the last ridaforolimus 40 mg dose (up to approximately 1 year).</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">23</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic or Locally Advanced Cancer.</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ridaforolimus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Part 1: Participants receive a single oral dose of placebo (10 tablets) on Day 1 and a single oral dose of 100 mg ridaforolimus (10 x 10 mg tablets) on Day 2. Each dose to be followed by 24 hours of Holter electrocardiogram (ECG) monitoring for QTc assessment.
Part 2 (optional): Participants receive a weekly regimen of daily oral doses of 40 mg ridaforolimus (4 x 10 mg tablets) for 5 consecutive days followed by 2 days off-drug.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ridaforolimus 100 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Part 1: A single oral dose of 100 mg ridaforolimus (10 x 10 mg tablets) was given on Day 2.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ridaforolimus</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AP23573</other_name>
    <other_name>MK-8669</other_name>
    <other_name>deforolimus (until May 2009)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ridaforolimus 40 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Part 2 (optional): Ridaforolimus 40 mg (4 x 10 mg tablets) was received on a regimen of daily oral doses for 5 consecutive days followed by 2 days off-drug.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ridaforolimus</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>AP23573</other_name>
    <other_name>MK-8669</other_name>
    <other_name>deforolimus (until May 2009)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>A single oral dose of placebo (10 x placebo tablets) was given on Day 1.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ridaforolimus</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient must have metastatic or locally advanced cancer which has failed to respond to
             standard therapy or no therapy exists

          -  If the patient is a female, she must be postmenopausal or if she is of childbearing
             potential she must have blood pregnancy tests during the study and be willing to use 2
             methods of contraception

          -  If the patient is male and has female partners of child-bearing potential, he must
             agree to use a medically acceptable method of contraception during the study and for
             30 days after the last dose of study drug

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient has had chemotherapy, radiotherapy or biological therapy within the past 4
             weeks

          -  Patient is currently receiving other anti-cancer therapy

          -  Patient is currently participating or has participated in a study with an
             investigation drug or device within the last 30 days

          -  Patient has a primary central nervous system tumor or active brain metastases

          -  Patient has a psychiatric disorder

          -  Patient uses illegal drugs

          -  Patient is pregnant or breastfeeding

          -  Patient is known to be human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive

          -  Patient has a known history of Hepatitis B or C

          -  Patient has newly diagnosed diabetes

          -  Patient has an active infection

          -  Patient is unable to swallow capsules

          -  Patient has received a blood transfusion with one week of study entry

          -  Patient has a history of cardiac problems including heart failure, myocardial
             infarction, unstable angina, congestive heart failure or cardiac arrythmia

          -  Patient has a known sensitivity to the components of the study drug

          -  Patient has not adequately recovered from any prior surgical procedure

          -  Patient does not agree to refrain from use of herbal remedies and consumption of
             grapefruit juice for 2 weeks prior to and during the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Monitor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lush RM, Patnaik A, Sullivan D, Papadopoulos KP, Trucksis M, McCrea J, Cerchio K, Li X, Stroh M, Selverian D, Orford K, Ebbinghaus S, Agrawal N, Iwamoto M, Wagner JA, Tolcher A. A single supratherapeutic dose of ridaforolimus does not prolong the QTc interval in patients with advanced cancer. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol. 2012 Oct;70(4):567-74. Epub 2012 Aug 10.</citation>
    <PMID>22878520</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 31, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 1, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 2, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 18, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 18, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 19, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sirolimus</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

