<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00877500</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2008-0435</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2010-01033</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00877500</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Randomized Study of Ixabepilone Versus Observation in Patients With Significant Residual Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Randomized Study of Ixabepilone vs. Observation in Patients With Significant Residual Disease After Neoadjuvant Systemic Therapy for HER2/Neu-negative Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn about certain genes and proteins in
      tumors that do not respond well to treatment. These features will be compared with the status
      of the disease after surgery for breast cancer that does not express the HER2 protein, when
      patients either receive or do not receive ixabepilone. The safety of ixabepilone in this
      group of patients will also be studied.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Study Drug:

      Ixabepilone is designed to work by blocking cell division, which may cause cancer cell death.

      Surgery:

      You will have surgery as part of your standard of care. Your tissue will be tested to measure
      residual disease (leftover cancer). If there is a low amount of leftover disease, you will
      not be eligible to take part in this study.

      Study Groups:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will be randomly assigned (as
      in the flip of a coin) to 1 of 2 groups.

      If you are in Group 1, you will receive ixabepilone. You also will be treated with the
      standard of care treatments for the disease, including radiation and/or hormonal therapy (if
      appropriate).

      If you are in Group 2, you will not receive the study drug. You will be treated with the
      standard of care treatments for the disease, including radiation and/or hormonal therapy (if
      appropriate).

      Study Drug Administration for Group 1:

      If you are in Group 1, you will receive ixabepilone though a needle in your vein over 3 hours
      on Day 1 of each 21-day study cycle.

      Before the infusion, you will be given drugs, by vein, to help decrease the risk of an
      allergic reaction. These drugs will include Benadryl® (diphenhydramine), Tagamet®
      (cimetidine), and Decadron (dexamethasone). The infusion will last 30-45 minutes.

      If you experience severe side effects, future treatments may be delayed, the dose may be
      decreased, or you may be taken off study.

      Study Visits:

      Group 1:

      On Day 1 of each cycle, the following tests and procedures will be performed:

        -  Your medical history will be recorded.

        -  Your performance status will be recorded.

        -  Blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  You will be asked about any side effects you may be experiencing or may have experienced
           since the last visit.

      Group 2:

      At the end of radiation (or on the day of your baseline blood collection), and at Weeks 9 and
      18, you will have a physical exam and your medical history will be recorded.

      Circulating Tumor Cell (CTC) testing:

      Blood (about 2 tablespoons each time) will be drawn before surgery to measure the amount of
      CTCs in your blood. If you are in Group 1, blood will be drawn again at Cycles 4 and at the
      end of Cycle 6. If you are in Group 2, blood will be drawn again at Weeks 9 and 18.

      Length of Study:

      If you are in Group 1, you may receive the study drug for up to 6 cycles. You will be taken
      off study early if the disease gets worse or intolerable side effects occur.

      If you are in Group 2, you will be off study after Week 18.

      This is an investigational study. Ixabepilone is FDA approved and commercially available for
      metastatic (advanced) breast cancer.

      Up to 116 patients will take part in this multicenter study. Up to 116 may be enrolled at MD
      Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Genomic (transcriptional profiles) + Proteomic (pathway activation) Tumor Features</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood tests Day 1 of each 21-day cycle (up to 6 cycles)</time_frame>
    <description>Signaling pathway analysis through reverse phase protein arrays (RPPA) used to objectively quantify (phospho) protein expression. Functional activation of the pathway defined as an increase in phosphorylation of at least one half of the components of each pathway above the median RPPA quantified activation across the entire tumor set.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Circulating Tumor Cells (CTCs)</measure>
    <time_frame>At 18 weeks (+/- 7 days) of therapy following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Circulating Tumor Cells defined as the presence of any cell per 7.5 ml of whole blood.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">116</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 Ixabepilone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ixabepilone 40 mg/m^2 by vein over 3 hours on Day 1 of each 21-day study cycle for up to 6 cycles.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2 Observation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Standard of care treatments for disease.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ixabepilone</intervention_name>
    <description>40 mg/m^2 by vein over 3 hours on Day 1 of each 21-day study cycle for up to 6 cycles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1 Ixabepilone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BMS-247550</other_name>
    <other_name>Epothilone B analogue</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with histologic confirmation of invasive HER2/neu-negative breast cancer (IHC
             0-1+ or FISH-negative) that have received complete anthracycline and taxane
             neoadjuvant systemic therapy and that at the time of surgery are expected to have
             significant residual disease. Therapy should include at least 4 cycles of an
             anthracycline-based regimen (AC, FAC, FEC) and 12 weeks of a taxane-based regimen
             (weekly paclitaxel, every 3-week docetaxel).

          2. Patients who did not complete therapy due to disease progression are eligible.

          3. Age &gt;/= 18 years

          4. Patients with bilateral breast cancers are eligible.

          5. Patients should have a Karnofsky performance scale of =/&gt; 70%.

          6. Patient should have adequate bone marrow function, as defined by peripheral
             granulocyte count of &gt;/= 1500/mm^3, and platelet count &gt;/= 100000 mm^3.

          7. Patients must have adequate liver function with a bilirubin within normal laboratory
             values. Alkaline phosphatase and transaminases (ALT and AST) may be up to 1.5 x upper
             limit of normal (ULN) of the institution.

          8. Patients should have adequate renal function with creatinine levels within normal
             range.

          9. Negative serum pregnancy test for a woman of childbearing potential.

         10. Women of childbearing potential (WOCP) must use a reliable and appropriate
             contraceptive method during the study and 6 months after chemotherapy is completed.
             WOCBP are women who are not menopausal for 12 months or had no previous surgical
             sterilization.

         11. Patients must agree to have study tissue collections and blood sample collections.

         12. Patients must sign an informed consent indicating that they are aware of the
             investigational nature of the study, in keeping with institutional policy.

         13. Patients should have their surgical tissues evaluated for RCB and be used for
             correlative studies.

         14. Sexually active women of childbearing potential must use an effective method of birth
             control during the course fo the study, in a manner such that risk of failure is
             minimized. Prior to study enrollment, women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must be
             advised of the importance of avoiding pregnancy during trial participation and the
             potential risk factors for an unintentional pregnancy. In addition, men enrolled on
             this study should understand the risks to any sexual partner of childbearing potential
             and should practice an effective method of birth control.

         15. All WOCBP MUST have a negative pregnancy test within 7 days prior to first receiving
             investigational product. If the pregnancy test is positive, the patient must not
             receive investigational product and must not be enrolled in the study. In addition,
             all WOCBP will be instructed to contact the Investigator immediately if they suspect
             they might be pregnant (e.g., missed or late menstrual period) at any time during
             study participation. The PI will immediately notify BMS in the event of a confirmed
             pregnancy in a patient participating in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients whose tumors express HER2 protein or have HER2/neu gene amplification.

          2. Patients with a history of other invasive malignancies diagnosed and treated within
             the previous 5 years, except non-melanoma skin cancer and non-invasive cervical cancer

          3. Other concurrent severe and/or uncontrolled medical disease which could compromise
             participation in the study (i.e., uncontrolled diabetes, uncontrolled hypertension,
             severe infection, severe malnutrition, unstable angina, or congestive heart failure -
             New York Heart Association Class III or IV, ventricular arrhythmias, active ischemic
             heart disease, myocardial infarction within six months, chronic liver or renal
             disease, active upper GI tract ulceration)

          4. Patients with a pre-existing peripheral neuropathy &gt; grade 1.

          5. Evidence of distant metastases
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Funda Meric-Bernstam, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Advocate Christ Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oak Lawn</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60453</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lyndon B. Johnson General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77026</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 6, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 6, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 7, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 9, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 9, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HER2/neu-negative Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Residual Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Neoadjuvant Systemic Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>NST</keyword>
  <keyword>Ixabepilone</keyword>
  <keyword>BMS-247550</keyword>
  <keyword>Epothilone B analogue</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Epothilones</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epothilone B</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

