<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00844948</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2008P000110</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5R44MH068950-03</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00844948</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vocal Acoustic Biomarkers in Depression</brief_title>
  <acronym>Speech2</acronym>
  <official_title>Development of a Convenient, Automated, Objective Measure of Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Center for Psychological Research, Madison, WI</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Center for Psychological Research, Madison, WI</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Phase II SBIR study will replicate pilot study methods establishing computer-automated
      methods for assessing depression severity using interactive voice response system technology
      and demonstrating feasibility of obtaining measures of depression severity and treatment
      response through vocal acoustic analysis of speech samples obtained over the telephone. The
      study will automate vocal acoustic analysis methods, evaluate applicability to other patient
      populations (non-English speakers, children/young adult, and geriatric), and further develop
      multivariate acoustic models to enhance biomarker sensitivity to treatment response and
      prediction of the response likelihood for individual patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will incorporate IVR data collection procedures developed in a prior pilot study
      into a multi-site industry-sponsored Phase 4 randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled
      study (NCT00406952) using an established antidepressant at a therapeutically efficacious
      dose. The analytic procedures used to extract the vocal acoustic measures will be automated
      to facilitate near rapid turn around between speech sample acquisition and delivery of
      biomarker outcomes data. Multivariate models of vocal acoustic information to enhance the
      sensitivity of treatment response measurement and prediction of patient response likelihood
      will be further refined.

      A total of 150 subjects will be recruited in the proposed studies, a sample of 50 from each
      of three targeted depressed patient populations - young adults (18-25 years old), elderly
      patients (60 years and older), and recent Asian immigrants with financial, linguistic, and
      cultural barriers to health care access. Eligible subjects will meet diagnostic criteria for
      Major Depressive Disorder, provide written informed consent, and will have baseline
      depression severity scores of 10 or greater on the QIDS. Pregnant women, women of child
      bearing potential not using a medically accepted means of contraception, suicidal or
      homicidal patients, or those with unstable medical illness including cardiovascular, hepatic,
      renal, respiratory, endocrine, neurological, hematological disease, or with clinical or
      laboratory evidence of hypothyroidism will be excluded. Patients beginning a new treatment
      for depression will be clinically evaluated (QIDS-C) during face-to-face interviews at the
      beginning of treatment (Baseline), and followed up 4 (study midpoint) and 8 weeks later
      (end-point). After completing the clinical interviews study participants will complete a
      series of IVR-based assessments using a standard desktop touch-tone telephone.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Motoric and frequency-based change in the vocal acoustic properties of speech associated with clinical improvement measured by the Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology - IVR (QIDS-IVR).</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 4 &amp; week 8</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Multivariate logistic regression models of vocal acoustic properties optimized for sensitivity to treatment response and prediction of the response likelihood fitted to data obtained in NCT00407952.</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, week 4, week 8</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">125</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Young adults (18-25 years old)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Young adults (18-25 years old). Major Depressive - eligible subjects will meet a baseline depression severity score of 10 or greater on the QIDS-C &amp; QIDS-IVR, will have recently started treatment or about to start receiving treatment for MDD. Exclusion: subjects with suicidal ideation; subjects who have a history or current diagnosis of the following DSM-IV psychiatric illness: organic mental disorder, schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, delusional disorder, psychotic disorders not otherwise specified, bipolar disorder, patients with mood congruent or mood incongruent psychotic features, patients with substance dependence disorders, other than alcohol, active within the last 12 months; subjects with a history or current diagnosis of dementia or diagnosis or history of hypothyroidism.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Elderly (60-80 years old)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Elderly (60-80 years old). Major Depressive - eligible subjects will meet a baseline depression severity score of 10 or greater on the QIDS-C &amp; QIDS-IVR, will have recently started treatment or about to start receiving treatment for MDD. Exclusion: subjects with suicidal ideation; subjects who have a history or current diagnosis of the following DSM-IV psychiatric illness: organic mental disorder, schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, delusional disorder, psychotic disorders not otherwise specified, bipolar disorder, patients with mood congruent or mood incongruent psychotic features, patients with substance dependence disorders, other than alcohol, active within the last 12 months; subjects with a history or current diagnosis of dementia or diagnosis or history of hypothyroidism.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Chinese speakers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Chinese speakers (Mandarin or Cantonese). Major Depressive - eligible subjects will meet a baseline depression severity score of 10 or greater on the QIDS-C &amp; QIDS-IVR, will have recently started or about to start receiving treatment for MDD. Exclusion: subjects with suicidal ideation; subjects who have a history or current diagnosis of the following DSM-IV psychiatric illness: organic mental disorder, schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, delusional disorder, psychotic disorders not otherwise specified, bipolar disorder, patients with mood congruent or mood incongruent psychotic features, patients with substance dependence disorders, other than alcohol, active within the last 12 months; subjects with a history or current diagnosis of dementia or diagnosis or history of hypothyroidism.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        English speaking: Young Adults, age 18-25; Elderly, age 60-80. Chinese speaking (Mandarin
        or Cantonese): age 18-80.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18 - 80.

          2. Written informed consent.

          3. Current MDD according to the fourth version of the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual
             for Mental Disorders (DSM-IV)

          4. Recently started to receive or about to start receiving treatment for MDD

          5. Quick Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology - Clinician-Rated (QIDS-C) and QIDS-IVR
             scores equal or greater than 10 at baseline visit.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects with suicidal ideation where outpatient treatment is determined unsafe by the
             study clinician. These patients will be immediately referred to appropriate clinical
             treatment.

          2. History or current diagnosis of the following DSM-IV psychiatric illness: organic
             mental disorder, schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, delusional disorder,
             psychotic disorders not otherwise specified, bipolar disorder, patients with mood
             congruent or mood incongruent psychotic features, patients with substance dependence
             disorders, other than alcohol, active within the last 12 months.

          3. History or current diagnosis of dementia.

          4. Diagnosis or history of hypothyroidism.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James C Mundt, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Center for Psychological Research, Training and Consultation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>South Cove Community Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital Depression Clinical and Research Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 13, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 13, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 16, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 7, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

