<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00847964</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SYM-08-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00847964</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Feasibility of Algisyl-LVR™ as a Method of Left Ventricular Restoration in Patients With DCM Undergoing Open-heart Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>SYM-08-001: A Pilot Study to Evaluate the Safety and Feasibility of Algisyl-LVR™ as a Method of Left Ventricular Restoration in Patients With Dilated Cardiomyopathy Undergoing Open-heart Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>LoneStar Heart, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>LoneStar Heart, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot study to evaluate the feasibility and safety of the Algisyl-LVR™ device. The
      purpose of this study is to investigate Algisyl-LVR™ employed as a method of left ventricular
      restoration in patients with dilated cardiomyopathy who are scheduled to undergo routine open
      heart surgery. Algisyl-LVR™ will be injected into the myocardium under direct visualization
      during the surgical procedure. This clinical evaluation is intended to provide the initial
      evidence of the safety and feasibility of the device as well as the procedure used to deploy
      the device. The results of the initial trial will also help to establish the utility of
      various assessments in evaluating and following the effects of the device.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Heart Failure (HF) is a progressive condition that has diverse etiologies with only 50
      percent of patients presenting at diagnosis with a defined reason for developing the disease.
      However, estimates are that over half of all patients presenting with HF have coronary artery
      disease (CAD) as the primary etiology. The most common etiologies among HF patients without
      CAD have been reported to be systemic hypertension and valvular disease. Irrespective of the
      etiology, the majority of patients with HF have symptoms due to an impairment of left
      ventricular (LV) myocardial function. HF is a progressive condition that results from
      myocardial damage. This damage can be caused by predisposing conditions or an acute event
      that leads to cardiac remodeling. The principal manifestation of such progression and cardiac
      remodeling is a change in the geometry and structure of the left ventricle (LV), such that
      the chamber dilates and/or hypertrophies and becomes more spherical. The cardiac remodeling
      is maladaptive and its progression leads to worsening of the clinical symptoms of HF,
      characterized by limited exercise tolerance and edema. Despite optimal medical management, HF
      is progressive in nature and patients have a mortality rate of over 50 percent in 5 years.

      Structural heart abnormalities are known to play a central role in HF, and clinical evidence
      supports a strong causal relationship between cardiac chamber dilation and heart failure.
      Because dilation, and not contractile dysfunction, appears to be responsible for the severity
      of the disease, the mitigation or prevention of the deleterious dilation process appears to
      be an important therapeutic target for HF patients. Hence, a therapy that specifically
      targets progressive LV dilatation and remodeling by reshaping and reducing the LV chamber
      size may offer an important new alternative in the treatment of HF.

      Algisyl-LVR™ is a single use, multiple component device under development for the indication
      to prevent or reverse the progression of heart failure (HF) by providing implanted
      space-occupying material in the myocardium to affect LV shape and prevent or reverse LV
      enlargement. The intended clinical benefits of Algisyl-LVR™ are to improve the failing
      heart's structure and function with an associated improvement in the patient's clinical
      status and quality of life. Data from this current study will be used to evaluate the initial
      feasibility of this novel therapeutic device.

      The objective of this pilot study is to evaluate the feasibility and safety of the
      Algisyl-LVR™ device. No formal hypothesis testing will be performed. Descriptive statistics
      will be used to summarize operator (surgeon) experience and patient outcomes. The results of
      the study will be used to assess the design of the device and feasibility of the procedures
      to use the device. The study will also guide the design and sample size of future studies.

      This study will be conducted at a several centers in Europe. The surgeon's experience with
      the use of the device will be collected and evaluated. Measures of safety and tolerability of
      Algisyl-LVR™ will be evaluated through analysis of adverse experiences, clinical laboratory
      tests, electrocardiograms, physical examinations, echocardiographic measures and magnetic
      resonance imaging (MRI). Measurements at specified time intervals will be compared to
      baseline values obtained prior to treatment.

      Patients will be evaluated prior to the procedure, during the immediate post operative
      period, and then, return to the clinic at 8 days, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months, 18 months
      and 24 months after the procedure for follow-up evaluations.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Freedom from serious adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">11</enrollment>
  <condition>Dilated Cardiomyopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Algisyl-LVR implants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Algisyl-LVR implants to the left ventricular wall</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Algisyl-LVR</intervention_name>
    <description>method of left ventricular restoration in patients with dilated cardiomyopathy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Algisyl-LVR implants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          1. The patients must be able and willing to give written informed consent.

          2. The patients will be adult (age ≥ 18 years and &lt;/= 75 years) males or females who are
             scheduled to undergo open-chest coronary artery bypass grafting surgery and/or valve
             repair/replacement.

          3. The patients must be on stable, evidence-based therapy for heart failure.

          4. The patients will have an ejection fraction equal to or less than 40% and a left
             ventricular end diastolic dimension indexed to body surface area (LVEDDi) of 30 to
             40mm/m2 (LVEDD/BSA).

          5. Patients must have symptomatic heart failure with a New York Heart Association (NYHA)
             class of III or IV

          6. If female, the patients must be (a) post-menopausal, (b) surgically sterile, or (c)
             using adequate birth control and have a negative serum pregnancy test within 7 days
             prior to administration of study device.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Emergent open heart surgery or cardiogenic shock.

          2. Right-sided heart failure.

          3. Patients scheduled to undergo pulmonic or tricuspid valve replacements.

          4. Patients who have undergone a previous mid-sternotomy or thoracotomy surgical
             procedure

          5. Patients presenting with a restrictive cardiomyopathy such as due to amyloidosis,
             sarcoidosis, or hemochromatosis.

          6. Patient with a history of constrictive pericarditis.

          7. Patients with a Q wave myocardial infarction (MI) within the last 30 days.

          8. Patients with a recent history of stroke (within 60 days prior to the surgical
             procedure)

          9. A left ventricular (LV) wall thickness of the LV free-wall, at the mid-ventricular
             level, of less than 6 mm.

         10. Patients with a serum creatinine &gt; 2.0 mg/dL..

         11. Clinically significant liver enzyme abnormalities, i.e., AST or ALT more than two
             times the upper limit of normal and/or bilirubin more than 50% above the upper limit
             of normal.

         12. The patients will not be receiving concurrently an investigational Product in another
             clinical trial or have received an investigational Product in another clinical trial
             in the 30 days prior to enrollment.

         13. A life expectancy of less than 1 year or any other condition that, in the opinion of
             the clinical investigator, might compromise any aspect of the trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Klaus Matschke, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Heart Center Dresden University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Deutsche Herzzentrum München</name>
      <address>
        <city>München</city>
        <state>Bavaria</state>
        <zip>80636</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Heart Center of the Technical University of Dresden</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dresden</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>John Paul II Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cracow</city>
        <zip>31-202</zip>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 17, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 17, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 19, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 29, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 29, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 30, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Heart Failure</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathy, Dilated</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

