<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00843583</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCT00843583</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00843583</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Cross-sectional Study of the Occurrence and Effect of Obstructive Sleep Apnea in Subjects With Resistant Hypertension</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Cross-sectional Study of the Occurrence and Effect of Obstructive Sleep Apnea in Subjects With Resistant Hypertension</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to investigate the prevalence of obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) in subjects
      with resistant hypertension and to evaluate the relationship between parameters of OSA
      severity and blood pressure control
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is characterized by intermittent upper airway collapse during
      sleep, which results in hypoxia, arousals and surge in sympathetic activity. There is robust
      evidence to support a contributing role of OSA in hypertension (HT). The Sleep Heart Health
      Study (1), which recruited more than 6000 subjects having polysomnogram at home, found an
      independent association between OSA and HT. The adjusted odds ratio was 1.37 for subjects
      with and apnea-hypopnea index &gt;= 30/hour compared to those without apnea. The Wisconsin Sleep
      Cohort Study , which provided prospective longitudinal follow-up for OSA subjects over 4
      years, have shown dose dependency of the severity of OSA and the risk of development of HT.
      Current available data suggests that in hypertensive patients with severe OSA, there is a BP
      drop of about 10mmHg with CPAP treatment (2-5). The blood pressure (BP) lowering effect of
      CPAP treatment in the group with mild asymptomatic OSA is less consolidated.

      The relationship between BP and risk of cardiovascular events is continuous, consistent, and
      independent of other risk factors. A strict blood pressure control is imperative in subjects
      with diabetes mellitus or renal impairment. Resistant hypertension is defined as blood
      pressure that remains above goal in spite of concurrent use of 3 antihypertensive agents of
      different classes. (6) Resistant hypertension is defined in order to identify patients who
      are at risk of having secondary causes of hypertension, and who may benefit from specific
      diagnostic and therapeutic applications. Despite the fact that OSA is listed as one of the
      causes of resistant HT (6), paucity of works has demonstrated the scale of problems of
      untreated OSA in subjects with resistant HT. (7-9) There is so far one study demonstrating
      the beneficial effect of CPAP treatment in subjects with resistant HT, though no
      randomization was implemented and the sample size was limited (n=11). (10) We aim at
      conducting a cross-sectional study to explore the situation which would guide further
      clinical trial.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>ambulatory blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hour</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea</condition>
  <condition>Resistant Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>resistant hypertension subjects</arm_group_label>
    <description>subjects with resistant hypertension</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood test for glucose, lipid, vascular and metabolic markers
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Consecutive sampling of subjects who attend Hypertension clinic , Department of Medicine,
        Queen Mary Hospital, and who fulfill the inclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≧ 3 anti-HT drugs

          -  age 18-65

          -  mentally fit for signing an informed written consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  moderate renal impairment (glomerular filtration rate &lt;30 mL/min/m2 )

          -  endocrine/renal/cardiac causes of secondary HT

          -  congestive heart failure and clinically fluid overloaded

          -  On drugs that elevate BP e.g. alcohol, NSAID, steroid
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sau Man Mary Ip, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Medicine, The University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Medicine, The University of Hong Kong, Queen Mary Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <zip>852</zip>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nieto FJ, Young TB, Lind BK, Shahar E, Samet JM, Redline S, D'Agostino RB, Newman AB, Lebowitz MD, Pickering TG. Association of sleep-disordered breathing, sleep apnea, and hypertension in a large community-based study. Sleep Heart Health Study. JAMA. 2000 Apr 12;283(14):1829-36. Erratum in: JAMA 2002 Oct 23-30;288(16):1985.</citation>
    <PMID>10770144</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pepperell JC, Ramdassingh-Dow S, Crosthwaite N, Mullins R, Jenkinson C, Stradling JR, Davies RJ. Ambulatory blood pressure after therapeutic and subtherapeutic nasal continuous positive airway pressure for obstructive sleep apnoea: a randomised parallel trial. Lancet. 2002 Jan 19;359(9302):204-10.</citation>
    <PMID>11812555</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Becker HF, Jerrentrup A, Ploch T, Grote L, Penzel T, Sullivan CE, Peter JH. Effect of nasal continuous positive airway pressure treatment on blood pressure in patients with obstructive sleep apnea. Circulation. 2003 Jan 7;107(1):68-73.</citation>
    <PMID>12515745</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mills PJ, Kennedy BP, Loredo JS, Dimsdale JE, Ziegler MG. Effects of nasal continuous positive airway pressure and oxygen supplementation on norepinephrine kinetics and cardiovascular responses in obstructive sleep apnea. J Appl Physiol (1985). 2006 Jan;100(1):343-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16357087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Norman D, Loredo JS, Nelesen RA, Ancoli-Israel S, Mills PJ, Ziegler MG, Dimsdale JE. Effects of continuous positive airway pressure versus supplemental oxygen on 24-hour ambulatory blood pressure. Hypertension. 2006 May;47(5):840-5. Epub 2006 Apr 3.</citation>
    <PMID>16585412</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calhoun DA, Jones D, Textor S, Goff DC, Murphy TP, Toto RD, White A, Cushman WC, White W, Sica D, Ferdinand K, Giles TD, Falkner B, Carey RM. Resistant hypertension: diagnosis, evaluation, and treatment. A scientific statement from the American Heart Association Professional Education Committee of the Council for High Blood Pressure Research. Hypertension. 2008 Jun;51(6):1403-19. doi: 10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.108.189141. Epub 2008 Apr 7.</citation>
    <PMID>18391085</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Logan AG, Perlikowski SM, Mente A, Tisler A, Tkacova R, Niroumand M, Leung RS, Bradley TD. High prevalence of unrecognized sleep apnoea in drug-resistant hypertension. J Hypertens. 2001 Dec;19(12):2271-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11725173</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grote L, Hedner J, Peter JH. Sleep-related breathing disorder is an independent risk factor for uncontrolled hypertension. J Hypertens. 2000 Jun;18(6):679-85.</citation>
    <PMID>10872551</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lavie P, Hoffstein V. Sleep apnea syndrome: a possible contributing factor to resistant. Sleep. 2001 Sep 15;24(6):721-5.</citation>
    <PMID>11560187</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Logan AG, Tkacova R, Perlikowski SM, Leung RS, Tisler A, Floras JS, Bradley TD. Refractory hypertension and sleep apnoea: effect of CPAP on blood pressure and baroreflex. Eur Respir J. 2003 Feb;21(2):241-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12608436</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 12, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 12, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 13, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Professor Ip, Sau Man Mary</name_title>
    <organization>Department of Medicine, The University of Hong Kong, Queen Mary Hospital</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>prevalence</keyword>
  <keyword>obstructive sleep apnea</keyword>
  <keyword>resistant hypertension</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Apnea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

