<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03413969</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1090321</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03413969</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Building Physician Resiliency Through CREATION Health: A Research Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Building Physician Resiliency Through CREATION Health: A Research Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Florida Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Florida Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether a standardized application of a
      physician-oriented CREATION Health curriculum is associated with reductions in burnout and
      perceived stress and improvements in well-being and empathy
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, non-randomized study of a convenience sample of Centura Health
      physicians.This study will not include any drugs or devices. The physician-oriented
      intervention will consist of a two-day weekend retreat that focuses on the application of
      CREATION Health principles in order to reduce burnout and perceived stress and improve
      well-being and empathy. There will be one four-hour session about each of the following
      CREATION Health principles: Choice, Trust, Interpersonal Relationships, and Outlook.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maslach Burnout Inventory - Human Services Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The Emotional Exhaustion subscale scores range from 0 to 54. Higher scores indicate worse outcomes. The Depersonalization subscale scores range from 0 to 30. Higher scores indicate worst outcomes. The Personal Accomplishment subscale scores range from 0 to 48. Higher scores indicate better outcomes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Well-Being Item</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The following question will be asked to assess well-being: &quot;How satisfied are you with your life as a whole?&quot; The scores range from 0 to 10. Higher scores indicate better outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Stress Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The Perceived Stress Scale will be used to measure perceived stress. The scores range from 0 to 40. Higher scores indicate worse outcomes.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Jefferson Scale of Empathy</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>The Jefferson Scale of Empathy will be used to assess empathy. The scores range from 0 to 140. Higher scores indicate better outcomes.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Burnout</condition>
  <condition>Stress</condition>
  <condition>Well-being</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study subjects will be recruited for approximately six weeks prior to the projected start date. The participants will attend the two-day weekend retreat. Follow-up assessments will be administered three months and six months after the retreat. The investigators will analyze the data and complete the study one month after the final assessment is administered.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CREATION</intervention_name>
    <description>The physician-oriented intervention will consist of a two-day weekend retreat that focuses on the application of CREATION Health principles in order to reduce burnout and perceived stress and improve well-being and empathy. There will be one four-hour session about each of the following CREATION Health principles: Choice, Trust, Interpersonal Relationships, and Outlook.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Behavioral Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Physician employed by Centura Health or credentialed physician with privileges at
             Centura Health

          -  Adult ≥ 18 years old

          -  English language proficiency

          -  Able to provide informed consent

          -  Resides in the Denver, Colorado area

          -  Willing to commit to the timeline of the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Plans to reside outside of the Denver, Colorado area within the 8 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amanda Terry</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Center for CREATION Health Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amanda Terry</last_name>
    <phone>407-303-7128</phone>
    <email>amanda.terry@flhosp.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jasmine Jones</last_name>
    <email>jasmine.jones@flhosp.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Florida Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32804</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amanda Terry</last_name>
      <email>amanda.terry@flhosp.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jasmine Jones</last_name>
      <email>jasmine.jones@flhosp.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Amanda Terry</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shanafelt TD, Boone S, Tan L, Dyrbye LN, Sotile W, Satele D, West CP, Sloan J, Oreskovich MR. Burnout and satisfaction with work-life balance among US physicians relative to the general US population. Arch Intern Med. 2012 Oct 8;172(18):1377-85.</citation>
    <PMID>22911330</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maslach C, Jackson SE, Leiter MP. Maslach Burnout Inventory manual. 3rd ed. Palo Alto, CA: Consulting Psychologists Press; 1996.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shanafelt TD, Noseworthy JH. Executive Leadership and Physician Well-being: Nine Organizational Strategies to Promote Engagement and Reduce Burnout. Mayo Clin Proc. 2017 Jan;92(1):129-146. doi: 10.1016/j.mayocp.2016.10.004. Epub 2016 Nov 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27871627</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shanafelt TD, Sloan JA, Habermann TM. The well-being of physicians. Am J Med. 2003 Apr 15;114(6):513-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12727590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wallace JE, Lemaire JB, Ghali WA. Physician wellness: a missing quality indicator. Lancet. 2009 Nov 14;374(9702):1714-21. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(09)61424-0. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19914516</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Connor PG, Spickard A Jr. Physician impairment by substance abuse. Med Clin North Am. 1997 Jul;81(4):1037-52. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9222267</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spickard A Jr, Gabbe SG, Christensen JF. Mid-career burnout in generalist and specialist physicians. JAMA. 2002 Sep 25;288(12):1447-50.</citation>
    <PMID>12243624</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thomas NK. Resident burnout. JAMA. 2004 Dec 15;292(23):2880-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15598920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Crane M. Why burned-out doctors get sued more often. Med Econ. 1998 May 26;75(10):210-2, 215-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10179678</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haas JS, Cook EF, Puopolo AL, Burstin HR, Cleary PD, Brennan TA. Is the professional satisfaction of general internists associated with patient satisfaction? J Gen Intern Med. 2000 Feb;15(2):122-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10672116</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shanafelt TD, West C, Zhao X, Novotny P, Kolars J, Habermann T, Sloan J. Relationship between increased personal well-being and enhanced empathy among internal medicine residents. J Gen Intern Med. 2005 Jul;20(7):559-64.</citation>
    <PMID>16050855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shanafelt TD, Hasan O, Dyrbye LN, Sinsky C, Satele D, Sloan J, West CP. Changes in Burnout and Satisfaction With Work-Life Balance in Physicians and the General US Working Population Between 2011 and 2014. Mayo Clin Proc. 2015 Dec;90(12):1600-13. doi: 10.1016/j.mayocp.2015.08.023. Erratum in: Mayo Clin Proc. 2016 Feb;91(2):276.</citation>
    <PMID>26653297</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>West CP, Dyrbye LN, Erwin PJ, Shanafelt TD. Interventions to prevent and reduce physician burnout: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet. 2016 Nov 5;388(10057):2272-2281. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(16)31279-X. Epub 2016 Sep 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27692469</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fujimori M, Oba A, Koike M, Okamura M, Akizuki N, Kamiya M, Akechi T, Sakano Y, Uchitomi Y. Communication skills training for Japanese oncologists on how to break bad news. J Cancer Educ. 2003 Winter;18(4):194-201.</citation>
    <PMID>14766329</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fujimori M, Shirai Y, Asai M, Akizuki N, Katsumata N, Kubota K, Uchitomi Y. Development and preliminary evaluation of communication skills training program for oncologists based on patient preferences for communicating bad news. Palliat Support Care. 2014 Oct;12(5):379-86. doi: 10.1017/S147895151300031X. Epub 2013 Nov 4.</citation>
    <PMID>24182602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goodman MJ, Schorling JB. A mindfulness course decreases burnout and improves well-being among healthcare providers. Int J Psychiatry Med. 2012;43(2):119-28.</citation>
    <PMID>22849035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krasner MS, Epstein RM, Beckman H, Suchman AL, Chapman B, Mooney CJ, Quill TE. Association of an educational program in mindful communication with burnout, empathy, and attitudes among primary care physicians. JAMA. 2009 Sep 23;302(12):1284-93. doi: 10.1001/jama.2009.1384.</citation>
    <PMID>19773563</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ospina-Kammerer V, Figley CR. An evaluation of the Respiratory One Method (ROM) in reducing emotional exhaustion among family physician residents. Int J Emerg Ment Health. 2003 Winter;5(1):29-32.</citation>
    <PMID>12722487</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosdahl JA, Kingsolver KO. Mindfulness training to increase resilience and decrease stress and burnout in ophthalmology residents: A pilot study. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 2014;55(13):5579.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Winefield H, Farmer E, Denson L. Work stress management for women general practitioners: An evaluation. Psychol Health Med. 1998;3(2):163-170.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dunn PM, Arnetz BB, Christensen JF, Homer L. Meeting the imperative to improve physician well-being: assessment of an innovative program. J Gen Intern Med. 2007 Nov;22(11):1544-52. Epub 2007 Sep 22.</citation>
    <PMID>17891503</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>International Wellbeing Group. Personal Wellbeing Index: 5th edition. Melbourne: Australian Centre on Quality of Life, Deakin University; 2013.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen S, Kamarck T, Mermelstein R. A global measure of perceived stress. J Health Soc Behav. 1983 Dec;24(4):385-96.</citation>
    <PMID>6668417</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen S, Williamson G. Psychological stress in a probability sample of the United States. In: Spacapan S, Oskamp S, eds. The social psychology of health. Newbury Park, CA: Sage; 1988:31-67.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hojat M, Mangione S, Nasca T, et al. The Jefferson Scale of Physician Empathy: Development and Preliminary Psychometric Data. Educ Psychol Meas. 2001; 61(2):349-365.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

