<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03412188</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GPVI-ITP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03412188</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Eltrombopag on the Expression of Platelet Collagen Receptor GPVI in Pediatric ITP.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Effect of Eltrombopag on the Expression of Platelet Collagen Receptor Glycoprotein VI (GPVI) in Pediatric Patients With Chronic and Persistent Immune Thrombocytopenia.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nayera Hazaa Elsherif</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ain Shams University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Using eltronmobag as an alternative pathway, which depend on stimulation of thrombocyte
      synthesis, in chronic and persistent immune thrombocytopenia may be more promising treatment
      than the classic type, not only by increasing platelets count but also through enhancing of
      the platelets activation and upregulation of GPVI expression on platelet surface.

      This study will include 40 pediatric patients with chronic or persistent ITP, recruited from
      the Hematology clinic of pediatric hospital Ain Shams University, aiming to investigate the
      efficacy, &amp; the safety and tolerability of eltrombopag therapy for children as well as the
      ability of eltrombopag to enhance the platelet activation through the up-regulation of
      glycoprotein VI (GPVI) receptor expression in comparison with other lines of treatment.

      Patients will be divided into 2 groups : Group 1 on eltrombopag ; Group 2 : receiving other
      lines of therapy .

      All Patients will be subjected to :

        1. bleeding score assessment ( baseline &amp;every month ) and Health related quality of life
           based on Kids' ITP Tools (KIT) questionnaires( baseline and week 24 )

        2. Baseline and at week 24 bone marrow examination with reticulin stain

        3. clinical examination every 2 weeks and complete blood counts.

        4. Assessment of soluble form of glycoprotein VI using sandwich enzyme-linked immunosorbent
           assay (ELISA) as well as assessment of platelet activation by GPVI using flowcytometry
           (Gardiner, etal.,2010 ) at baseline and at the end of 6 months treatment period
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary immune thrombocytopenia (ITP) is an acquired immune-mediated disorder characterized
      by isolated thrombocytopenia, defined as a peripheral blood platelet count less than 100
      ×109/l and the absence of any obvious initiating and/ or underlying cause of the
      thrombocytopenia. (Buchanan, 1989).

      Novel thrombopoiesis-stimulating agents have been developed increasing platelet production by
      overdriving the system and thereby correcting the thrombocytopenia (Cines etal., 2002).
      Because these peptides bear no structural resemblance to thrombopoietin agonist(TPO) but
      still bind and activate the TPO receptor, these compounds are called TPO receptor agonists
      (TRAs). (Meletis etal.,2010).

      Newly formed young platelets are larger and express higher levels of glycoprotein Ibα
      (GPIbα), which decreases as platelets age. For the purpose of quantitative platelet analysis,
      GPIbα of the GPIb-IX-V complex and GPVI are of particular interest because these receptors
      are essentially platelet specific, are critical for initiation of thrombus formation at
      arterial shear rates, and are implicated in wider platelet functions beyond hemostasis and
      thrombosis, as well as platelet aging and clearance. (Gardiner etal., 2014).

      GP VI is thought to be the major signaling receptor involved in platelet activation on
      exposed collagen. Following GP VI interactions with collagen, platelets initiate strong
      activation and release the content of alpha and dense granules.( Yun etal.,2016) GPVI
      expression was upregulated in megakaryocytes after TPO stimulation (Holmes etal., 2002).
      Eltrombopag could upregulate GPVI expression in ITP patients, thereby enhancing their
      platelet adhesion capacity leading to reduce bleeding symptoms (Chiou etal.,2015).

      The Aim is to :

      To investigate the efficacy, &amp; the safety and tolerability of eltrombopag therapy for
      children with persistent and chronic immune thrombocytopenia as well as the ability of
      eltrombopag to enhance the platelet activation through the up-regulation of glycoprotein VI
      (GPVI) receptor expression in comparison with other lines of treatment.

      Study methods :

      This study will include 40 pediatric patients with chronic or persistent ITP, age ≥ 1 to ≤ 18
      years, recruited from the Hematology clinic of pediatric hospital Ain Shams University

        -  Baseline bleeding score assessment (ITP-BAT (v1.0) score) and Health related quality of
           life based on Kids' ITP Tools (KIT) questionnaires will be done.

        -  Patients will be divided into 2 groups:

             1. Group 1 (eltrombopag arm n=20 patients): Patients who showed no response (platelet
                count ≤ 20x109/L) initially for 3 months or relapse after 6 months after at least
                one prior ITP therapy. patients will receive a total daily dose of eltrombopag of
                (25-50mg/d). Dose adjustments may be made based on platelets count with an
                increment of 25mg once per day at 2 weeks intervals (Maximum dose: 75 mg orally
                once a day). If platelet counts reached more than 200 × 109 per L, the dose will be
                decreased by 25 mg once per day at 2 weeks intervals. If platelet counts increased
                to more than 400 × 109 per L, treatment will be interrupted until platelet counts
                decreases to less than 150 × 109 per L then the dose will be resumed at the next
                lower dose.

                Patients, who responded poorly to eltrombopag in 6 months or developed adverse
                effects, will be asked to discontinue the medication. Those who responded will be
                followed for further 6 month period.

             2. Group 2 (n=20 patients) Patients who are currently receiving other lines of
                treatment (steroids, IVIG, azathioprine, and rituximab).

        -  All patients will be followed clinically every 2 weeks throughout the period of the
           study for safety and efficacy, and complete blood counts.

        -  Baseline and at week 24 bone marrow examination with reticulin stain will be done

        -  Baseline and every 3 months liver and kidney function tests. Throughout the study
           periods, patients with increased serum alanine transaminase (ALT) ≥ 3 times upper limit
           normal (ULN) with a total bilirubin ≥2 times ULN or those with increased serum ALT ≥ 5
           times ULN will be withdrawn, as well as patients with increased serum creatinine above
           ULN.

        -  Adverse events, episodes of bleeding and bleeding score will be collected and evaluated
           every month throughout the study.

        -  Health related quality of life based on Kids' ITP Tools (KIT) questionnaires will be
           repeated at the end of study period.

        -  Assessment of soluble form of glycoprotein VI using sandwich enzyme-linked immunosorbent
           assay (ELISA) as well as assessment of platelet activation by GPVI using flowcytometry
           (Gardiner, etal.,2010 ) at baseline and at the end of 6 months treatment period

      Statistical Analysis : Analysis of data will be done using Statistical Program for Social
      Science version 21 (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patients will be divided into 2 groups:
Group 1 (eltrombopag arm n=20 patients): Patients who showed no response (platelet count ≤ 20x109/L) initially for 3 months or relapse after 6 months after at least one prior ITP therapy. patients will receive a total daily dose of eltrombopag of (25-50mg/d). Dose adjustments may be made based on platelets count.
Group 2 (n=20 patients) Patients who are currently receiving other lines of treatment (steroids, IVIG, azathioprine, and rituximab).</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete response or response</measure>
    <time_frame>at 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Percentages of patients achieving Complete response&quot; (CR) defined as any platelet count of 100x109/L at least once throughout the study period in the absence of rescue treatment and those achieving &quot;Response&quot; (R) is defined as any platelet count between 50 and 100x 109/L or doubling of the baseline count at least once throughout the study period</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Expression of glycoprotein VI collagen receptor</measure>
    <time_frame>at 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Percentages of patients achieving increased expression of glycoprotein VI collagen receptor</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>at 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Patients who will have adverse events.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maintenance of response</measure>
    <time_frame>at 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The maximum duration for which a patient continuously maintained a platelet count between 50 and 100x 10*9/L in the absence of rescue treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Idiopathic Thrombocytopenic Purpura</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group 1 Eltrombopag arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 1 (eltrombopag arm n=20 patients): Patients who showed no response (platelet count ≤ 20x109/L) initially for 3 months or relapse after 6 months after at least one prior ITP therapy. patients will receive a total daily dose of eltrombopag of (25-50mg/d). Dose adjustments may be made based on platelets count with an increment of 25mg once per day at 2 weeks intervals (Maximum dose: 75 mg orally once a day).
Patients, who responded poorly to eltrombopag in 6 months or developed adverse effects, were asked to discontinue the medication. Those who responded were followed for further 6 month period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>group 2 conventional Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group 2 (n=20 patients) Patients who are currently receiving other lines of treatment (steroids, IVIG, azathioprine, and rituximab).
patients will continue on the conventional line of treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Eltrombopag</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients who showed no response (platelet count ≤ 20x109/L) initially for 3 months or relapse after 6 months after at least one prior ITP therapy will receive a total daily dose of eltrombopag of (25-50mg/d)</description>
    <arm_group_label>group 1 Eltrombopag arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Revolade</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>conventional</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients who are currently receiving conventional lines of treatment (steroids, IVIG, azathioprine, and rituximab, Mycophenolate mofetil) will continue on the same line of treatment</description>
    <arm_group_label>group 2 conventional Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>solumedrol</other_name>
    <other_name>imuran</other_name>
    <other_name>cellcept</other_name>
    <other_name>mabthera</other_name>
    <other_name>gammaglobulin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 1 to ≤ 18 years at enrollment. Patient should be able to swallow tablet form.
             Weight should be ≥ 12kg.

          -  Diagnosis of persistent (3-&lt;12 months duration) or chronic cases (≥12 months duration)
             with day 1 platelet count ≤ 20x10^9.

          -  Patients have a bleeding score grade 3 for skin and/or grade 2 or higher for mucosal
             domains and/or higher than grade 1 for organ domain at the baseline visit or the worst
             bleeding incident episode in the patient's medical reports in the last 3 months prior
             screening, using ITP-BAT (v1.0) score.

          -  Normal Kidney function tests and liver function tests.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute thrombocytopenic purpura patients or Other causes of thrombocytopenia. Patients
             with Evans syndrome

          -  Hypertension, cardiovascular disease, diabetes, hepatitis C virus (HCV), HIV,
             hepatitis B surface antigen(HBsAg) seropositive status.

          -  Baseline bone marrow biopsy with evident fibrosis (reticulin stain grade 2 or more)

          -  Patients who have previously received eltrombopag.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Azza AG Tantawy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ain shams university, Faculty of medicine, Pediatric Hematology &amp;Oncology department</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>nayera elsherif, MD</last_name>
    <phone>01003322052</phone>
    <email>elsherif.nayera@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>fatma ebeid, MD</last_name>
    <phone>01095569596</phone>
    <email>dr.fatma_ebeid@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ainshams University , Faculty of medicine , Pediatric Hematology&amp;Oncology unit, children hospital.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cairo</city>
        <zip>11579</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Micheal morcos, M.Sc</last_name>
      <email>mekoo_828@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mahmoud Kenny, MD</last_name>
      <email>moudykenny@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Azza AG Tantawy, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nayera HK El Sherif, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Fatma S Ebeid, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eman AR Ismail, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mahmoud A Kenny, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael BE morcos, M.Sc</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mazzucconi MG, Fazi P, Bernasconi S, De Rossi G, Leone G, Gugliotta L, Vianelli N, Avvisati G, Rodeghiero F, Amendola A, Baronci C, Carbone C, Quattrin S, Fioritoni G, D'Alfonso G, Mandelli F; Gruppo Italiano Malattie EMatologiche dell'Adulto (GIMEMA) Thrombocytopenia Working Party. Therapy with high-dose dexamethasone (HD-DXM) in previously untreated patients affected by idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura: a GIMEMA experience. Blood. 2007 Feb 15;109(4):1401-7. Epub 2006 Oct 31.</citation>
    <PMID>17077333</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Buchanan GR. Overview of ITP treatment modalities in children. Blut. 1989 Jul;59(1):96-104. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2665875</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bussel JB, de Miguel PG, Despotovic JM, Grainger JD, Sevilla J, Blanchette VS, Krishnamurti L, Connor P, David M, Boayue KB, Matthews DC, Lambert MP, Marcello LM, Iyengar M, Chan GW, Chagin KD, Theodore D, Bailey CK, Bakshi KK. Eltrombopag for the treatment of children with persistent and chronic immune thrombocytopenia (PETIT): a randomised, multicentre, placebo-controlled study. Lancet Haematol. 2015 Aug;2(8):e315-25. doi: 10.1016/S2352-3026(15)00114-3. Epub 2015 Jul 28. Erratum in: Lancet Haematol. 2015 Oct;2(10):e407.</citation>
    <PMID>26688484</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chiou TJ, Chang YF, Wang MC, Kao CW, Lin HY, Chen TY, Hsueh EJ, Lan YJ, Sung YC, Lin SF, Bai LY, Chen CG. Eltrombopag enhances platelet adhesion by upregulating the expression of glycoprotein VI in patients with chronic immune thrombocytopenic purpura. Transl Res. 2015 Dec;166(6):750-761.e4. doi: 10.1016/j.trsl.2015.09.005. Epub 2015 Sep 30.</citation>
    <PMID>26477577</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Cines DB, Blanchette VS. Immune thrombocytopenic purpura. N Engl J Med. 2002 Mar 28;346(13):995-1008. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11919310</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ehrlich LA, Kwitkowski VE, Reaman G, Ko CW, Nie L, Pazdur R, Farrell AT. U.S. Food and Drug Administration approval summary: Eltrombopag for the treatment of pediatric patients with chronic immune (idiopathic) thrombocytopenia. Pediatr Blood Cancer. 2017 Dec;64(12). doi: 10.1002/pbc.26657. Epub 2017 Jun 19.</citation>
    <PMID>28627134</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gardiner EE, Andrews RK. Platelet receptor expression and shedding: glycoprotein Ib-IX-V and glycoprotein VI. Transfus Med Rev. 2014 Apr;28(2):56-60. doi: 10.1016/j.tmrv.2014.03.001. Epub 2014 Mar 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24674813</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gardiner EE, Thom JY, Al-Tamimi M, Hughes A, Berndt MC, Andrews RK, Baker RI. Restored platelet function after romiplostim treatment in a patient with immune thrombocytopenic purpura. Br J Haematol. 2010 May;149(4):625-8. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2141.2010.08092.x. Epub 2010 Feb 8.</citation>
    <PMID>20148887</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Grainger JD, Locatelli F, Chotsampancharoen T, Donyush E, Pongtanakul B, Komvilaisak P, Sosothikul D, Drelichman G, Sirachainan N, Holzhauer S, Lebedev V, Lemons R, Pospisilova D, Ramenghi U, Bussel JB, Bakshi KK, Iyengar M, Chan GW, Chagin KD, Theodore D, Marcello LM, Bailey CK. Eltrombopag for children with chronic immune thrombocytopenia (PETIT2): a randomised, multicentre, placebo-controlled trial. Lancet. 2015 Oct 24;386(10004):1649-58. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(15)61107-2. Epub 2015 Jul 28. Erratum in: Lancet. 2015 Oct 24;386(10004):1630.</citation>
    <PMID>26231455</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Holmes ML, Bartle N, Eisbacher M, Chong BH. Cloning and analysis of the thrombopoietin-induced megakaryocyte-specific glycoprotein VI promoter and its regulation by GATA-1, Fli-1, and Sp1. J Biol Chem. 2002 Dec 13;277(50):48333-41. Epub 2002 Sep 30.</citation>
    <PMID>12359731</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Klaassen RJ, Blanchette VS, Barnard D, Wakefield CD, Curtis C, Bradley CS, Neufeld EJ, Buchanan GR, Silva MP, Chan AK, Young NL. Validity, reliability, and responsiveness of a new measure of health-related quality of life in children with immune thrombocytopenic purpura: the Kids' ITP Tools. J Pediatr. 2007 May;150(5):510-5, 515.e1.</citation>
    <PMID>17452226</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rodeghiero F, Michel M, Gernsheimer T, Ruggeri M, Blanchette V, Bussel JB, Cines DB, Cooper N, Godeau B, Greinacher A, Imbach P, Khellaf M, Klaassen RJ, Kühne T, Liebman H, Mazzucconi MG, Newland A, Pabinger I, Tosetto A, Stasi R. Standardization of bleeding assessment in immune thrombocytopenia: report from the International Working Group. Blood. 2013 Apr 4;121(14):2596-606. doi: 10.1182/blood-2012-07-442392. Epub 2013 Jan 29.</citation>
    <PMID>23361904</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rodeghiero F, Stasi R, Gernsheimer T, Michel M, Provan D, Arnold DM, Bussel JB, Cines DB, Chong BH, Cooper N, Godeau B, Lechner K, Mazzucconi MG, McMillan R, Sanz MA, Imbach P, Blanchette V, Kühne T, Ruggeri M, George JN. Standardization of terminology, definitions and outcome criteria in immune thrombocytopenic purpura of adults and children: report from an international working group. Blood. 2009 Mar 12;113(11):2386-93. doi: 10.1182/blood-2008-07-162503. Epub 2008 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>19005182</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yun SH, Sim EH, Goh RY, Park JI, Han JY. Platelet Activation: The Mechanisms and Potential Biomarkers. Biomed Res Int. 2016;2016:9060143. doi: 10.1155/2016/9060143. Epub 2016 Jun 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27403440</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Meletis J, Katsandris A, Raptis SD, Mantzourani M. Successful treatment of Immune Thrombocytopenic Purpura (ITP) with the thrombopoietin-mimetic romiplostim. Med Sci Monit. 2010 Aug;16(8):CS100-2.</citation>
    <PMID>20671616</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 20, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 20, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ain Shams University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nayera Hazaa Elsherif</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>assistant professor of pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic ITP</keyword>
  <keyword>persistent ITP</keyword>
  <keyword>Eltrombopag</keyword>
  <keyword>GPVI receptor</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Purpura</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Purpura, Thrombocytopenic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Purpura, Thrombocytopenic, Idiopathic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Still investigators did not decide about sharing individual participants data</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

