<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03414762</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-0843</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03414762</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PICO Negative Pressure Wound Therapy in Obese Women Undergoing Elective Cesarean Delivery.</brief_title>
  <official_title>PICO Negative Pressure Wound Therapy in Obese Women Undergoing Elective Cesarean Delivery.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwell Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwell Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A randomized controlled, parallel group, superiority, open-label, single-institution, Phase 3
      interventional clinical trial to evaluate clinical outcomes in obese gravidas undergoing
      elective cesarean delivery whose wounds were dressed with the PICO Negative Pressure Wound
      Therapy (NPWT) versus the standard dressing. We hypothesize that the PICO NPWT will reduce
      the incidence of surgical site occurrences and interventions and postoperative readmissions
      in obese women. The study will compare surgical site occurrences and surgical incision
      intervention incidence within 42 +/- 10 days post cesarean delivery in obese women who have
      the current standard-of-care dressing versus the PICO NPWT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 5, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 12, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgical Site Occurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>42 days</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence of postoperative Surgical Site Occurrences (SSOs) up to Day 42 (+/- 10 Days) post Cesarean Section.The incidence of postoperative surgical site occurrences (SSOs) post Cesarean delivery. SSOs include:
Unanticipated local inflammatory response
Prolonged drainage
Fluid collection
Dehiscence
Surgical site infection (SSI)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgical Incision Intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>42 days</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence rate of surgical incision intervention (SII) post Cesarean delivery.
Interventions include:
- Antimicrobials for surgical site infection
- Surgical drainage of the incision
- Surgical incision packing
- Adjunctive negative pressure therapy
- Debridement
- Re-operation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Cesarean Section Complications</condition>
  <condition>Cesarean Wound; Dehiscence</condition>
  <condition>Cesarean Wound Disruption</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PICO Dressing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PICO Negative Pressure Wound Therapy (Smith and Nephew Healthcare, Hull, United Kingdom) is a non-significant-risk, FDA Class II, medical device commercially available in the USA. The PICO unit is a single patient use, battery-powered, disposable unit that can provide continuous 80 - 125 mmHg negative pressure over a 5 to 7-day therapy period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Dressing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The standard-of-care is consistent with the national standard for dressing Cesarean section incisions and includes, but not limited to, coverage of the sutured incision with sterile gauze and non-penetrable barrier (e.g., Tegaderm™). The non-penetrable barrier may be left in place for a minimum of 1 day and no longer than 2 days (± 4 hours) to promote epithelialization of the surgical incision edges. After the dressing is removed, the surgical site is left exposed to air to promote further healing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PICO Negative Pressure Wound Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>The PICO unit is a single patient use, battery-powered, disposable unit that can provide continuous 80 - 125 mmHg negative pressure over a 5 to 7-day therapy period.The dressing is applied to the wound and extra strips are placed over the outside edge to help hold the dressing in place. When the pump is turned on, air is pulled out of the dressing and excess fluid from the wound will start to enter the dressing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PICO Dressing</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PICO Dressing</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Dressing</intervention_name>
    <description>The standard-of-care is consistent with the national standard for dressing Cesarean section incisions and includes, but not limited to, coverage of the sutured incision with sterile gauze and non-penetrable barrier (e.g., Tegaderm™). The non-penetrable barrier may be left in place for a minimum of 1 day and no longer than 2 days (± 4 hours) to promote epithelialization of the surgical incision edges. After the dressing is removed, the surgical site is left exposed to air to promote further healing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Dressing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Provision of signed and dated informed consent form

          -  Stated willingness to comply with all study procedures and availability for the
             duration of the study; willing and able to return for all scheduled and required study
             visits

          -  Female, aged 18 - 55 years

          -  BMI ≥ 35 kg/m2 in the 42 days prior to surgery

          -  In good general health as evidenced by medical history with a 24 - 41 weeks
             gestational age pregnancy scheduled for cesarean delivery for any routine indication
             (repeat procedure, breech presentation, abnormal placentation, uterine anomaly,
             maternal medical condition, or elective)

          -  Surgical skin site preparation with chlorhexidine gluconate solution (ChloraPrep©)

          -  Received preoperative surgical prophylaxis antibiotics as per protocol

          -  Surgical incision that can be covered completely by the NPWT skin system

          -  Pre-operatively assessed to undergo a procedure with a CDC Wound Classification of:

             a. Class I (Clean): An uninfected operative wound in which no inflammation is
             encountered and the respiratory, alimentary, genital, or uninfected urinary tract is
             not entered

          -  OR - b. Class II (Clean Contaminated): An operative wound in which the respiratory,
             alimentary, genital, or uninfected urinary tract are entered under controlled
             conditions and without unusual contamination

          -  Wound hemostasis has been achieved

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cesarean delivery before fetal viability (24 0/7 weeks gestational age)

          -  Unplanned Cesarean delivery

          -  Intrauterine fetal demise

          -  Known allergic reactions to components of the PICO NPWT system

          -  Systemic bacterial or fungal infection at the time of surgery

          -  Diagnosis of systemic or remote-site skin infections at time of delivery

          -  Treatment with another investigational drug or other intervention within 7 days prior
             to cesarean delivery or 42 +/- 10 days after cesarean delivery

          -  Delivery for suspected intrauterine infection (defined as maternal fever plus one
             clinical criteria)

          -  Critical illness or immune-compromising disease (eg acquired immunodeficiency
             syndrome)

          -  Chronic steroid use

          -  Pre-operatively assessed to have a CDC Wound Classification of:

        Class III (Contaminated): Open, fresh, accidental wounds, and/or major breaks in sterile
        technique or gross spillage from the gastrointestinal tract

          -  OR - Class IV (Dirty-Infected): Old traumatic wounds with retained devitalized tissue
             and those that involve existing clinical infection or perforated viscera

          -  High-risk for anesthesia (American Society of Anesthesiologists [ASA] class P4 - P6)

          -  Intra-operative hemorrhage requiring blood transfusion, disseminated-intravascular
             coagulopathy (DIC) or any other medical or surgical condition during the Cesarean
             section deemed by the investigator to pose a prohibitively high risk for surgical
             re-exploration

          -  Unable to speak or understand English, with no interpreter available.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Study is being conducted on female postpartum patient.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gary Goldberg, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Long Island Jewish Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sarah Pachtman, MD</last_name>
    <phone>516-562-2892</phone>
    <email>spachtman@northwell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.smith-nephew.com/global/assets/pdf/products/wound/31447%20uk%20pico%20patient%20info%20leaflet.pdf</url>
    <description>Smith &amp; Nephew PICO Patient Information</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Acosta S, Björck M, Wanhainen A. Negative-pressure wound therapy for prevention and treatment of surgical-site infections after vascular surgery. Br J Surg. 2017 Jan;104(2):e75-e84. doi: 10.1002/bjs.10403. Epub 2016 Nov 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27901277</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists. ACOG Practice Bulletin No. 120: Use of prophylactic antibiotics in labor and delivery. Obstet Gynecol. 2011 Jun;117(6):1472-83. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0b013e3182238c31.</citation>
    <PMID>21606770</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bilgi A, Zumrut Biber Muftuler F, Akman L, Ilker Medine E, Tonbaklar Bilgi P, Kozgus Guldu O, Goksun Gokulu S, Tekin V, Cosan Terek M. Negative Pressure Wound Therapy for Patients With Complex Abdominal Wounds. Wounds. 2017 Jul;29(7):209-214.</citation>
    <PMID>28759428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Echebiri NC, McDoom MM, Aalto MM, Fauntleroy J, Nagappan N, Barnabei VM. Prophylactic use of negative pressure wound therapy after cesarean delivery. Obstet Gynecol. 2015 Feb;125(2):299-307. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0000000000000634. Erratum in: Obstet Gynecol. 2015 Oct;126(4):903.</citation>
    <PMID>25569006</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gillespie BM. Prophylactic Use of Negative Pressure Wound Therapy After Cesarean Delivery. Obstet Gynecol. 2015 Jul;126(1):214. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0000000000000937.</citation>
    <PMID>26241279</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grauhan O, Navasardyan A, Hofmann M, Müller P, Stein J, Hetzer R. Prevention of poststernotomy wound infections in obese patients by negative pressure wound therapy. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2013 May;145(5):1387-92. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2012.09.040. Epub 2012 Oct 27.</citation>
    <PMID>23111014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leth RA, Uldbjerg N, Nørgaard M, Møller JK, Thomsen RW. Obesity, diabetes, and the risk of infections diagnosed in hospital and post-discharge infections after cesarean section: a prospective cohort study. Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand. 2011 May;90(5):501-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-0412.2011.01090.x. Epub 2011 Mar 14.</citation>
    <PMID>21306347</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Olsen MA, Butler AM, Willers DM, Devkota P, Gross GA, Fraser VJ. Risk factors for surgical site infection after low transverse cesarean section. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol. 2008 Jun;29(6):477-84; discussion 485-6. doi: 10.1086/587810.</citation>
    <PMID>18510455</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Leary DP, Peirce C, Anglim B, Burton M, Concannon E, Carter M, Hickey K, Coffey JC. Prophylactic Negative Pressure Dressing Use in Closed Laparotomy Wounds Following Abdominal Operations: A Randomized, Controlled, Open-label Trial: The P.I.C.O. Trial. Ann Surg. 2017 Jun;265(6):1082-1086. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0000000000002098.</citation>
    <PMID>27926575</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Searle RJ, Myers D. A survey of caesarean section surgical site infections with PICO™ Single Use Negative Pressure Wound Therapy System in high-risk patients in England and Ireland. J Hosp Infect. 2017 Oct;97(2):122-124. doi: 10.1016/j.jhin.2017.02.023. Epub 2017 Aug 12.</citation>
    <PMID>28807639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smid MC, Dotters-Katz SK, Grace M, Wright ST, Villers MS, Hardy-Fairbanks A, Stamilio DM. Prophylactic Negative Pressure Wound Therapy for Obese Women After Cesarean Delivery: A Systematic Review and Meta-analysis. Obstet Gynecol. 2017 Nov;130(5):969-978. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0000000000002259. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>29016508</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strugala V, Martin R. Meta-Analysis of Comparative Trials Evaluating a Prophylactic Single-Use Negative Pressure Wound Therapy System for the Prevention of Surgical Site Complications. Surg Infect (Larchmt). 2017 Oct;18(7):810-819. doi: 10.1089/sur.2017.156. Epub 2017 Sep 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28885895</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yu L, Kronen RJ, Simon LE, Stoll CRT, Colditz GA, Tuuli MG. Prophylactic negative-pressure wound therapy after cesarean is associated with reduced risk of surgical site infection: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2018 Feb;218(2):200-210.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2017.09.017. Epub 2017 Sep 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28951263</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwell Health</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sarah Pachtman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Fellow, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Division of Maternal Fetal Medicine, Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cesarean section</keyword>
  <keyword>negative-pressure wound therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>surgical wound dehiscence</keyword>
  <keyword>hospital readmission</keyword>
  <keyword>surgical site infection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

