<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03414697</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FirstHospitalDalianMU004</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03414697</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transplantation of Umbilical Cord-derived Mesenchymal Stem Cells Via Different Routes</brief_title>
  <official_title>Transplantation of Umbilical Cord-derived Mesenchymal Stem Cells Via Different Routes for the Treatment of Cerebral Palsy in Children</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The First Affiliated Hospital of Dalian Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The First Affiliated Hospital of Dalian Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To preliminarily evaluate the efficacy and safety of umbilical cord-derived mesenchymal stem
      cells (UC-MSCs), and compare the efficacy of UC-MSCs administered through the intravenous,
      intrathecal, and intranasal routes, in the treatment of cerebral palsy in children.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cerebral palsy refers to a neurological disorder caused by a non-progressive brain injury or
      malformation that occurs in early childhood. It can result in central motor deficits,
      developmental retardation, abnormal posture, abnormal muscular strength, abnormal muscle tone
      and/or dysreflexia. It has a high disability rate. There is currently no effective treatment
      for cerebral palsy. Conventional treatments for cerebral palsy are often tiresome and
      expensive and have a slow onset of action. Stem cells have been recently used in the
      treatment of cerebral palsy. This provides a novel method for the treatment of cerebral
      palsy. According to the existing clinical studies, neural stem cells, bone marrow-derived
      mesenchymal stem cells, and umbilical cord-derived mesenchymal stem cells (UC-MSCs) are
      mainly used as the seed cells for the treatment of cerebral palsy. UC-MSCs are the most
      promising seed cells for the treatment of cerebral palsy because of the advantages including
      rich sources, ease of harvesting, short doubling time, low immunogenicity, long-time survival
      post-transplantation, and no ethical issues. UC-MSCs have been widely used to treat
      Parkinson's disease, rheumatoid arthritis, traumatic brain injury, aplastic anemia, and
      decompensated liver disease. However,only two studies, and performed only in China, are
      reported on the treatment of cerebral palsy with UC-MSCs. One from the Hospital 463 of PLA
      reported 51 patients with cerebral palsy whose symptoms had not been obviously improved after
      1 year of rehabilitative treatment. These patients received intrathecal injection of UC-MSCs
      for three times, once a week, followed by one injection of UC-MSCs via the peripheral vein in
      the fourth week. Four UC-MSCs injections, once per week, were considered as one course of
      treatment. Activities of daily living scale score was compared between before and after
      treatment to evaluate efficacy. Another study is a case report from China. In this report, a
      combined intravenous and intrathecal injection of UC-MSCs was used to treat cerebral palsy in
      a 5-year-old child. 28-month follow-up results revealed that the child's gross motor
      function, immune function, muscle strength, and language ability improved and adverse
      reactions were not obvious.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Gross Motor Function Measure (GMFM)-88 item score</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after 2 courses of treatment with UC-MSCs.</time_frame>
    <description>a 4-point scale that is divided into five categories including lying and rolling, sitting, crawling and kneeling, standing, walking, running, and jumping. A score of 0 indicates that the child does not initiate the task; 1 indicates that the child initiates the task (completes &lt; 10% of the activity); 2 indicates that the child partially completes the task (completes from 10 to 99% of the activity); 3 indicates that the child completes the task (100%). The sum of score of the five categories is used as the evaluation outcome.It is used to evaluate gross motor function.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fine Motor Function Measure scale (FMFM) score</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months after 2 courses of treatment with UC-MSCs.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate fine motor function.The scale is divided into 45 items covering visual tracing (7 items), upper extremity range of motion (8 items), grab ability (8 items), operational ability (10 items), and hand-eye coordination (12 items). The FMFM is a 4-point scale with the score range of 0-3. The original total score is 135. The summed score for evaluating fine motor function measure is 0-100.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Modified Ashworth scale (MAS) score</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months after 2 courses of treatment with UC-MSCs.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate muscle tone. The MAS score is divided into six grades: 0, 1, 1+, 2, 3 and 4. Passive full ranges of motion exercises are performed by moving the knee and ankle until the patient feel a slight resistance from hamstrings and plantar flexor muscles (soleus muscle and gastrocnemius muscle). The average score is calculated across three repeated measurements.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gesell Development Schedule score</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months after 2 courses of treatment with UC-MSCs.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate neurobehavioral development.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 9 and 12 months after 2 courses of treatment with UC-MSCs.</time_frame>
    <description>Liver and kidney dysfunction, fever, infection, vomiting.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Palsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Routine rehabilitation treatments</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intravenous UC-MSCs group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Injection of UC-MSCs via the peripheral vein.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intrathecal UC-MSCs group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Injection of UC-MSCs via the intrathecal route.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intranasal UC-MSCs group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Injection of UC-MSCs via the nasal route.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control group</intervention_name>
    <description>The control group received routine rehabilitation treatments including acupuncture, massage, Bobath therapy, and Vojat therapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>UC-MSCs</intervention_name>
    <description>Injection of umbilical cord-derived mesenchymal stem cells (UC-MSCs) (at least 1×10^7), once every 2 weeks, one course of treatment including two injections within 4 weeks, a total of two courses of treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intravenous UC-MSCs group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intrathecal UC-MSCs group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Intranasal UC-MSCs group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients diagnosed with hypoxic/ischemic cerebral palsy, primarily including birth
             asphyxia and premature children

          -  Patients with spastic quadriplegia

          -  Patients with moderate to severe cerebral palsy, GMFM scores of 2-3

          -  Age at 2-18 years

          -  Provision of signed informed consent by legal representatives of the child prior to
             start of the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Those with systemic diseases that likely interfere with the treatment or child's
             compliance

          -  Those complicated by life-threatening diseases of any organ

          -  Those with brain deformity

          -  Those with uncontrolled epilepsy

          -  Those with abnormal behavior or mood disorders

          -  Those with allergies especially those who are allergic to blood products

          -  Those are infected with infectious diseases

          -  Those who had underwent a craniocerebral surgery in other clinical trials
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jing Liu, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The First Affiliated Hospital of Dalian Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jing Liu, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>86041184394568</phone>
    <email>liujing.dlrmc@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The First Affiliated Hospital of Dalian Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dalian</city>
        <state>Liaoning</state>
        <zip>116011</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jing Liu, Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>86041184394568</phone>
      <email>liujing.dlrmc@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The First Affiliated Hospital of Dalian Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Liu Jing</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>umbilical cord-derived mesenchymal stem cells</keyword>
  <keyword>cerebral palsy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Palsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

