<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03413605</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>U01 Viet CRC</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01MD010627</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03413605</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>U01 CRC Project for Vietnamese Americans</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multilevel CBPR Intervention to Improve Colorectal Cancer Screening in Underserved Vietnamese Americans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Temple University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities (NIMHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Temple University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Colorectal cancer (CRC) is the second most commonly diagnosed cancer and the third highest
      cause of mortality in Vietnamese and Asian Americans. CRC incidence is rising rapidly in
      Vietnamese Americans, but they have among the lowest rates of CRC screening (14%) and are
      more likely to be diagnosed with advanced stage disease, which is highly preventable. Over
      85% of Vietnamese Americans in our region (PA, NJ and NYC) are foreign-born with limited
      English proficiency, have low SES, and live in economically disadvantaged neighborhoods. Many
      lack knowledge about CRC risks and screening benefits and have limited access to culturally
      appropriate preventive care. Center for Asian Health, Temple University will be working with
      Vietnamese CBOs to address their critical health disparities. The investigators will test the
      hypothesis that the proposed multilevel CRC intervention will yield higher CRC screening
      rates compared to the control at 12-month follow-up. This project represents the first
      large-scale community-based randomized controlled trial of a multilevel,
      culturally-appropriate intervention to increase CRC screening among underserved Vietnamese.
      If effective, this innovative CRC intervention can be used as a model program that has
      potential impact, generalizability and sustainability in Asian American and other underserved
      ethnic communities.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Colorectal cancer (CRC) is the second most commonly diagnosed cancer and the third highest
      cause of mortality in Vietnamese and Asian Americans. CRC incidence is rising rapidly in
      Vietnamese Americans, but they have among the lowest rates of CRC screening (14%) and are
      more likely to be diagnosed with advanced stage disease, which is highly preventable. Over
      85% of Vietnamese Americans in our region (PA, NJ, and NYC) are foreign-born with limited
      English proficiency, have low SES, and live in economically disadvantaged neighborhoods. Many
      lack knowledge about CRC risks and screening benefits and have limited access to culturally
      appropriate preventive care. Thus, a multilevel intervention is needed to address the
      multiple barriers to and determinants of CRC screening in this community. Vietnamese
      community organizations (VCOs) serve dynamic social functions and represent an important
      resource for addressing this critical health disparity priority by promoting CRC screening.
      This project builds on established partnerships and successful work of Center for Asian
      Health, Temple University with Vietnamese CBOs that address their overwhelming health
      disparities. CBPR principles will be applied to engage 20 VCOs in all phases of planning,
      implementing, evaluating, and disseminating a culturally appropriate, theory- and
      evidence-based multilevel CRC intervention. The proposed intervention will be guided by
      Social Ecological Model, which addresses sociocultural, behavioral and environmental
      determinants and intervention strategies at the individual, interpersonal, and community
      organizational levels. CDC's Clinical Preventive Services Guidelines for adults 50+ (CPS)
      recommend that cancer screenings and other preventive services should be promoted. The
      standard CPS will be provided to both intervention and control groups, and intervention group
      will receive CPS + multilevel CRC intervention. Specific Aim 1 is to test the hypothesis that
      CPS + multilevel CRC intervention will yield higher CRC screening rates compared to CPS
      control at 12-month follow up; Aim 2 is to examine whether CPS + multilevel CRC intervention
      (which includes CHW-led group education, automated and interactive text messaging and
      phone-based peer support) is more effective in changing screening determinants (e.g. KAB,
      self-efficacy, risk factors, lifestyles, social support, social norms, access barriers) than
      CPS control condition; and Aim 3 is to assess costs and cost-effectiveness of CPS +
      multilevel CRC intervention compared to CPS control condition in relation to CRC screening
      rates in order to inform future dissemination efforts. In sum, this project represents the
      first large-scale community-based randomized controlled trial of a multilevel,
      culturally-appropriate CBPR intervention to increase CRC screening among underserved
      Vietnamese. If effective, this innovative multilevel CRC intervention can be used as a model
      program that has potential generalizability and sustainability in Asian American and other
      underserved ethnic communities to impact preventive behaviors at the population level.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Colorectal Cancer Screening Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>percentage of subjects, who received colorectal screening at 12-month Follow Up</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">800</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>a multilevel CBPR intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention will be delivered in group-based education workshop format. The education session is a curriculum-based group education; each group will be having about 15-20 participants. We will allow 5-7 minutes for participants to get to know each other and to get comfortable talking to the group. Education will have two major topics.(a) CDC's standard Clinical Preventive Services Guidelines for adults 50+ (CPS). (b) culturally tailored CRC information discussion. This session is to increase knowledge, change cultural beliefs and attitudes on risks of CRC and benefits of screening by using interactive discussion approaches, visual aids, motivation video and print materials.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>the standard CDC's Clinical Preventive Services Guidelines for adults 50+ (CPS) will be provided to control groups.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>A Multilevel CBPR Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention will be implemented through a group-based education workshop. The education session is a curriculum-based group education; each group will be having about 15-20 participants. All group education sessions will take place at collaborating Viet community partners sites, and delivered in Vietnamese language, with offering of refreshment. We will allow 5-7 minutes for participants to get to know each other and to get comfortable talking to the group. Education will have two major topics--- (a) CDC's standard Clinical Preventive Services Guidelines for adults 50+ (CPS). (b) culturally tailored CRC information discussion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>a multilevel CBPR intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. self-identified Vietnamese ethnicity,

          2. age 50 and above,

          3. accessible by cell telephone,

          4. presence in the same geographic study area for a period of one year (to minimize
             participant attrition);

          5. not enrolled in any CRC intervention (to prevent a potential program impact),

          6. do not have the colorectal polyp, CRC cancer or a family history of CRC (first-degree
             relative),

          7. non-adherent to CRC screening guidelines (never had CRC screening or are overdue for
             screening).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. enrolled in any CRC intervention (to prevent a potential program impact)

          2. have the colorectal polyp, CRC cancer or a family history of CRC

          3. had CRC screening or adherent to CRC screening guidelines
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Grace X Ma, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Grace X Ma, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>215-707-6493</phone>
    <email>grace.ma@temple.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vietnamese community center of Atlantic city</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlantic City</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08401</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nga Vu</last_name>
      <phone>215-552-2155</phone>
      <email>ngavu@vietlead.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bo De Temple</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19147</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tam Tran</last_name>
      <phone>917-952-6396</phone>
      <email>tranquanniem@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 11, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 22, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

