<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03413800</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HMR003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03413800</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Len/Dex/DLI in Relapsed Multiple Myeloma After Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II, Open-label Study of Lenalidomide and Dexamethasone Followed by Donor Lymphocyte Infusions in Relapsed Multiple Myeloma Following Allogeneic Stem Cell Transplant</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ciusss de L'Est de l'Île de Montréal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celgene</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centre de Commercialisation en Immunothérapie du Cancer</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ciusss de L'Est de l'Île de Montréal</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multiple Myeloma (MM) is a morbid disease which can only be cured with an allogeneic
      hematopoietic stem cell transplant (HSCT). Approximately 50% of allotransplanted patients
      will relapse, with a median survival of 5 years. Better approaches to improve disease control
      at relapse, while decreasing toxicity, are urgently needed.

      Relapse after allogeneic transplant is a failure of the graft versus MM effect (GvMM). DLIs
      can be used to control disease following relapse, but the optimal dose, schedule of
      administration and drug association remain elusive, while the immunosuppression found in MM
      patients can compromise their effect. One reason for immunotherapy failure relates to the
      immunological environment: as much as myeloma cells depend on their microenvironment to
      survive and proliferate, the immunotherapeutic effect of allogeneic HSCT depends on both
      systemic and local immunological status to be efficacious. Immunomodulatory drugs such as
      Lenalidomide (Len) have been tried in various settings after allogeneic transplantation with
      the aim to reverse immunosuppression and stimulate the GvMM, but if and how Len influences a
      GvMM and thereby promotes an immunotherapeutic success remained uncharacterized. Therefore, a
      deeper understanding of the immunological environment in MM patients is needed in order to
      establish and / or restore a potent GvMM effect.

      This study proposes the powerful combination of the two following goals, one clinical and one
      biological :

        1. Clinical: The investigators propose a two-step treatment using first Len in association
           with Dexamethasone (Dex), followed by Donor Leukocytes Infusions (DLIs) to offer an
           optimal disease control strategy in relapsed patients. The cytoreductive and
           immunomodulatory effects of Len is expected to induce a permissive immunological
           environment for the immunotherapeutic activity of DLIs to develop, while the association
           with Dex will lessen the risk of graft-versus-host disease (GVHD). This treatment
           combination has the potential to further improve depth of myeloma response, delay
           myeloma progression and improve patient survival.

        2. Biological: In an attempt to gain knowledge on how the GvMM behaves in MM patients
           post-relapse after having received a combined treatment of Len/Dex/DLIs, the
           investigators propose to characterize the immune environment of their bone marrow (BM)
           using both minimal residual disease (MRD) assessement by flow cytometry and an unbiased
           analysis of the transcriptome at various time points.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Myeloma patients in first relapse after sibling or unrelated donor allogeneic transplant
      willing to participate in this study will be screened for eligibility.

        1. After baseline evaluation including BM aspirate for plasma cell count, minimal residual
           disease using 8-color multiparameter flow cytometry, transcriptome sequencing and a
           positron emission tomography (PET scan), patients will receive Len- Dex daily x 21 days
           with Dex 40 mg once weekly for a total of 6 cycles of 28 days each

        2. Patients will then be evaluated clinically for acute and chronic GVHD before each cycle
           and a PET scan will be performed at the end of Len/Dex treatment

        3. Sibling and unrelated donor transplant recipients will receive 3 DLIs

        4. Disease and immune evaluation using serum and urine electrophoresis/immunofixation in
           addition to measurement of serum-free light chains, BM aspirate for plasma cell count
           and minimal residual disease using 8-color multiparameter flow cytometry, transcriptome
           sequencing and a PET scan will be performed

             1. A BM aspirate will be performed before each DLI for plasma cell count, MRD
                evaluation by flow cytometry and transcriptome sequencing

             2. Patients will be followed with a BM aspirate every 3 months x 1 year, then yearly
                and at progression for plasma cell count and evaluation

             3. Transcriptome sequencing will be done on BM aspirates at time of relapse, after
                Len/Dex cycles, 6m, 12m, 18m and 24m after the last-DLI.

             4. A PET scan will be performed after the last DLI and at progression.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 12, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 29, 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 29, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of Len-Dex-DLI in patients with relapsed myeloma measured by progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the as efficacy of Len and Dex followed by DLIs, measured by progression-free survival at 2 years after the last DLI</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of grade ≥III non hematologic toxicity and incidence of grade ≥IV hematologic toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will be evaluated according to protocol and adverse events will be monitored continuously, documented and collected in database</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of acute GVHD</measure>
    <time_frame>1 years</time_frame>
    <description>GVHD will be evaluated according to protocol, documented and collected in database. Analysis will be done by cumulative incidence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of chronic GVHD</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>GVHD will be evaluated according to protocol, documented and collected in database. Analysis will be done by cumulative incidence.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum grades of acute and chronic GVHD</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>GVHD will be evaluated according to protocol, documented and collected in database</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response to treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) response after Len/Dex and after DLIs, best response achieved</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-relapse mortality after DLIs</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis by cumulative incidence</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival at 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Kaplan Meier analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of progression at 2 years</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Kaplan Meier analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease status assessment by flow cytometry</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>BM evaluation of minimal residual disease (MRD) by multiparametric flow cytometry (MFC) analysis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease status assessment by PET scan</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of extramedullary disease by positron emission tomography (PET) scan</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of quality of life (QoL) during treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>QoL questionnaire will be given to patients according to protocol</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the BM microenvironment by transcriptome analysis before and after treatments</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Both mononucleated celles and extracellular compartment will be analyzed by RNAseq</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Relapsed Hematologic Malignancy</condition>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide-Dexamethasone-DLI</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive Len (10 mg in the presence of ≤ grade I acute GVHD or absence of chronic GVHD; 5 mg in presence of controlled mild or moderate chronic GVHD) daily x 21 days with Dex 40 mg once weekly for a total of 6 cycles of 28 days each
For grade ≥III non hematologic or grade IV hematologic toxicity, Len can be reduced to 5 mg
In absence of these toxicities, acute GVHD (using Glucksberg modified criteria) or severe chronic GVHD (using NIH criteria), Len dose can be increased by 5 mg per cycle to a maximum of 25 mg
If eligibility is confirmed, sibling and unrelated donor transplant recipients will both receive 3 donor lymphocyte infusions (DLIs) at the following doses: 5 x 106 CD3+/kg; 1 x 107 CD3+/kg; 5 x 107 CD3+/kg
Patient will be followed for 5 years post relapse.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lenalidomide-Dexamethasone-DLI</intervention_name>
    <description>Lenalidomide (Len) and Dexamethasone (Dex) for 6 months followed by three donor lymphocyte infusions (DLIs)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide-Dexamethasone-DLI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18-65 years

          2. Myeloma patients in first relapse after a sibling or unrelated allogeneic stem cell
             transplantation

          3. Patients with measurable disease at time of relapse based on the IMWG criteria

          4. All study participants must comply with the Revlimid Pregnancy Prevention Plan.

          5. Females of reproductive potential must adhere to the scheduled pregnancy testing as
             required in the Revlimid Pregnancy Prevention Plan.

             Exclusion Criteria:

          6. Relapse occurred within 180 days post allograft

          7. Refractory to Len at any given time before allogeneic transplantation

          8. Presence of ≥ grade II or uncontrolled acute GVHD

          9. Presence of severe or uncontrolled chronic GVHD

         10. Karnofsky score &lt; 70%

         11. Bilirubin &gt; 50 μmol/L unless felt to be related to Gilbert's disease or hemolysis; AST
             and ALT &gt; 5 x upper limit of normal (ULN); alkaline phosphatase &gt; 5 x ULN

         12. Known hypersensitivity to Len or Dex

         13. Active infection with any of the following viruses: HIV, HTLV-1 or 2, hepatitis B
             (defined as HBsAg positivity) or hepatitis C (defined as anti-HCV positivity or
             HCV-RNA positivity)

         14. Presence of another malignancy with an expected survival estimated &lt; 75% at 5 years
             (complete resection of basal cell carcinoma or squamous cell carcinoma, complete
             resection of a ductal carcinoma in situ, presence of lobular carcinoma in situ,
             complete resection of carcinoma in situ of the cervix, or an in situ or low-risk
             prostate cancer after curative therapy are not exclusion criteria)

         15. Positive beta-human chorionic gonadotropin pregnancy test, to be performed in all
             women of childbearing potential at screening and baseline. Female study participants
             who are surgically sterile (hysterectomy) or who have been postmenopausal for at least
             12 consecutive months are automatically eligible for this criterion

         16. Females of child-bearing potential not agreeing to remain abstinent or to use 2
             simultaneous effective methods of contraception from at least 4 weeks before, to at
             least 4 weeks following discontinuation of Len. Males not agreeing to use a condom
             during any sexual contact with females of child-bearing potential from at least 4
             weeks before, to at least 4 weeks following discontinuation of Len

         17. Women who are lactating

         18. Female of child-bearing potential who are planning to become pregnant while enrolled
             in this study up to 4 weeks after the last Len dose

         19. Participation in a trial with an investigational agent within 30 days prior to entry
             in the study

         20. Inability to provide written informed consent prior to initiation of any study-related
             procedures, or inability, in the opinion of investigators, to comply with all
             requirements of the study

         21. Estimated probability to survive less than 6 months after initiation of Len and Dex

         22. Current history of drug and/or alcohol abuse

         23. Any abnormal condition or laboratory result that is considered by investigators
             capable of altering patient's condition, compliance or study outcome

         24. Any patient who, in the opinion of investigators, should not participate in this study

         25. Having received allogeneic stem cell transplantation in relapse after autologous
             transplant.

         26. Having received Len therapy after allogeneic transplant, before relapse

         27. Poor organ function defined as either: diffusing capacity of the lung for carbon
             monoxide corrected for hemoglobin using Dinakara method (DLCOc) &lt; 50%; forced
             expiratory volume in 1 second &lt; 50%; left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt; 40%
             evaluated by echocardiogram or multi-gated acquisition scan (MUGA); uncontrolled
             arrhythmia; symptomatic cardiac disease; creatinine clearance &lt; 30 mL/minute; liver
             cirrhosis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean Roy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ciusss de L'Est de l'Île de Montréal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jean Roy, MD</last_name>
    <phone>514-252-3400</phone>
    <email>jroy.hmr@ssss.gouv.qc.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Séverine Landais, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>514-252-3400</phone>
    <phone_ext>3609</phone_ext>
    <email>slandais.hmr@ssss.gouv.qc.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CIUSSS de l'Est-de-l'île-de-Montréal, Installation Hôpital Maisonneuve Rosemond</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H1T2M4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Séverine Landais, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>514-252-3400</phone>
      <phone_ext>3609</phone_ext>
      <email>slandais.hmr@ssss.gouv.qc.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jean Roy, MD</last_name>
      <phone>514-252-3400</phone>
      <email>jroy.hmr@ssss.gouv.qc.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ciusss de L'Est de l'Île de Montréal</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Severine Landais</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hematopoietic stem cell transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>lenalidomide</keyword>
  <keyword>DLI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

