<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03419156</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>28143</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03419156</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of a Short Message Service Intervention on Patients With Short Bowel Syndrome</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of a Short Message Service Intervention on Patients With Short Bowel Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Louis University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Epharmix, Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Louis University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will be using a text messaging intervention to identify potentially
      dangerous and re- admission causing symptoms in patients with Short Bowel Syndrome (SBS) on
      Total Parenteral Nutrition (TPN). Each consented patient will receive weekly text messages
      inquiring about potentially harmful symptoms identified by a team of physicians. If the
      patient screens positive via text message, an alert will be sent to the medical team. All
      patients with SBS on TPN will receive text messages. The investigators will be monitoring
      response rates to text messages screening for potentially harmful symptoms and compare the
      text- message response rate to historical rates of successful calls by nurses.

      All patients with SBS on TPN will receive text messages instead of weekly phone calls from a
      nurse. If the patient does not respond to the text messages or the text message responses
      suggest that the patient may be presenting with potentially harmful symptoms, the nurse will
      call the patient to inquire about more information.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Short Bowel Syndrome (SBS) is a condition that results from a host of different conditions,
      the most common of which is Necrotizing Enterocolitis. Patients who have SBS are often Total
      Parenteral Nutrition (TPN) dependent. TPN is a carefully formulated intravenous nutrition
      that is utilized either alone or in conjunction with gastrointestinal feeds in patients who
      fail to achieve adequate caloric intake enterally. According to the American Society of
      Parenteral and Enteral Nutrition, 360,000 hospital visits required usage of TPN in 2009.
      Short and long-term use of TPN is associated with catheter infections, cholestasis, liver
      failure, refeeding-syndrome, hyperglycemia, bone demineralization, and death (1). Thus
      careful and comprehensive monitoring of patients on TPN, especially after hospital discharge
      is essential (1-3). Some hospitals have introduced resource intensive support teams
      consisting of various health care professionals to manage these costly patients (1).

      Using a variety of definitions, the incidence of SBS has been estimated at approximately 0.02
      to 0.1 percent among all live births (4, 5), 0.5 to 2.0 percent among neonatal intensive care
      unit (NICU) admissions (4, 5), and 0.7 percent among very low birthweight infants (6).
      Approximately 80 percent of pediatric SBS cases develop during the neonatal period.

      The average cost of care in the US for a single pediatric patient with SBS is $550,250 +/-
      $248, 398 for the first year of care alone (7). These costs were attributable to prolonged
      requirements for intensive care resources, numerous surgical procedures, multiple
      readmissions, TPN and home care during the first year of diagnosis. Interestingly, Spencer et
      al. suggested that hospital-based costs steadily declined in subsequent years, but home-care
      services increased every year for the first 5 y of diagnosis (7). This increasing cost was
      attributable to increasing complications of TPN, especially infectious complications
      (something our application will specifically try to identify). The mean total cost of care
      per child over a 5-y period was US$1,619,851 +/- US$1,028,985 (7).

      At Cardinal Glenon, a significant amount of time (about 10 hours per week) is spent by nurses
      calling these patients. This automated system will allow nurses to spend a portion of these
      10 hours performing other activities, significantly reducing the costs attributed to SBS
      patients. Also, most of the mothers of patients who have SBS are between the ages of 15-30.
      This generation of millennials often have an aversion to phone calls and prefer texts [8].
      Text- messages can be answered at a convenient time for the parent while the parent must be
      present and available to answer a phone call. Multiple prior text message or application
      intervention studies have reported high response rates, high satisfaction, and improvement in
      outcomes (9-12). For example, Devitto et al. reported that the estimated odds of reporting
      critical care symptoms of application group was 8.9 times that of control and showed slightly
      higher adherence to the prescribed regimen (OR 1.64, 95% CI [1.01, 2.66]) (9). Martinez et
      al. reported that 16 patients would have returned to the hospital without photos of surgical
      sites prompting health care team intervention (12). Our automated texting system may improve
      response rates from these young parents.

      For this project, the investigators will be examining the effect of an Epharmix text
      messaging intervention on identifying potentially dangerous and re-admission causing symptoms
      with SBS patients on TPN.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 20, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 20, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 20, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>All patients with SBS on TPN at Cardinal Glennon will receive text messages inquiring about their symptoms instead of weekly phone calls from a nurse. There will be no randomization. All patients will be sent text-messages from the automated system for 6 months to assess response rates and the amount of time saved by the nurse staff. If the patient does not respond to the text messages or the text message responses suggest that the patient may be presenting with potentially harmful symptoms, the nurse will call the patient to inquire about more information.The text messages are designed to help target calls made by the nursing staff.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome for this study will be comparing response rates to automated text messages vs historical weekly nurse call success rates. The investigators will compare these values using a chi-square.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specificity and Sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Specificity and sensitivity of the alerts generated by the automated system</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost savings</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Cost saved in terms of nurse time required without automated text message intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinic visits</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of clinic visits by SBS patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Readmissions</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>30 day readmission of SBS patients</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Days spent in the hospital</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of days spent in the hospital</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">16</enrollment>
  <condition>Short Bowel Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Text Message Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the Text Message Arm will receive a weekly set of text messages inquiring about the patients' symptoms instead of a weekly phone call from the nurse team (standard of care). Potentially harmful symptoms identified by the automated system will generate an alert that will be sent to the medical team. The alert will be immediately sent via email to the nursing team. The nurse will be able to contact the patient to decide the best further treatment. The nurses will check patient response rates daily. If a patient does not respond to their weekly message, then the patient will be called.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Text Message Arm Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients in the Text Message Arm will receive a weekly set of text messages inquiring about the patients' symptoms instead of a weekly phone call from the nurse team (standard of care). Potentially harmful symptoms identified by the automated system will generate an alert that will be sent to the medical team. The alert will be immediately sent via email to the nursing team. The nurse will be able to contact the patient to decide the best further treatment. The nurses will check patient response rates daily. If a patient does not respond to their weekly message, then the patient will be called.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Text Message Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients under the age of 18

          -  Patients with a diagnosis of short bowel syndrome and who are treated with total
             parenteral nutrition

          -  Patients able to understand English or have a caregiver who understands English.

          -  Patients must have caregiver who has access to a phone (landline or cell phone)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who do not have access to a phone (landline or cell phone), and patients who
             are not mentally able to consent to the study.

          -  Patients who are not treated with total parenteral nutrition.

          -  Patients who do no have a short bowel syndrome diagnosis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Josef Greenspon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Louis University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Josef Greenspon, MD</last_name>
    <phone>314-882-9329</phone>
    <email>ygreensp@slu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nikolas E Marino, BA</last_name>
    <phone>8584142732</phone>
    <email>nikolas.marino@health.slu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cardinal Glennon Children's Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yosef Greenspon, MD</last_name>
      <phone>314-882-9329</phone>
      <email>ygreensp@slu.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hartl WH, Jauch KW, Parhofer K, Rittler P; Working group for developing the guidelines for parenteral nutrition of The German Association for Nutritional Medicine. Complications and monitoring - Guidelines on Parenteral Nutrition, Chapter 11. Ger Med Sci. 2009 Nov 18;7:Doc17. doi: 10.3205/000076. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20049074</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Duro D, Kamin D, Duggan C. Overview of pediatric short bowel syndrome. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr. 2008 Aug;47 Suppl 1:S33-6. doi: 10.1097/MPG.0b013e3181819007. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18667916</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uko V, Radhakrishnan K, Alkhouri N. Short bowel syndrome in children: current and potential therapies. Paediatr Drugs. 2012 Jun 1;14(3):179-88. doi: 10.2165/11594880-000000000-00000. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22452596</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Salvia G, Guarino A, Terrin G, Cascioli C, Paludetto R, Indrio F, Lega L, Fanaro S, Stronati M, Corvaglia L, Tagliabue P, De Curtis M; Working Group on Neonatal Gastroenterology of the Italian Society of Pediatric Gastroenterology, Hepatology and Nutrition. Neonatal onset intestinal failure: an Italian Multicenter Study. J Pediatr. 2008 Nov;153(5):674-6, 676.e1-2. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2008.05.017. Epub 2008 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>18589446</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wales PW, de Silva N, Kim J, Lecce L, To T, Moore A. Neonatal short bowel syndrome: population-based estimates of incidence and mortality rates. J Pediatr Surg. 2004 May;39(5):690-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15137001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cole CR, Hansen NI, Higgins RD, Ziegler TR, Stoll BJ; Eunice Kennedy Shriver NICHD Neonatal Research Network. Very low birth weight preterm infants with surgical short bowel syndrome: incidence, morbidity and mortality, and growth outcomes at 18 to 22 months. Pediatrics. 2008 Sep;122(3):e573-82. doi: 10.1542/peds.2007-3449.</citation>
    <PMID>18762491</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spencer AU, Kovacevich D, McKinney-Barnett M, Hair D, Canham J, Maksym C, Teitelbaum DH. Pediatric short-bowel syndrome: the cost of comprehensive care. Am J Clin Nutr. 2008 Dec;88(6):1552-9. doi: 10.3945/ajcn.2008.26007.</citation>
    <PMID>19064515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>https://www.forbes.com/sites/larryalton/2017/05/11/how-do-millennials-prefer-to- communicate/#58cc85d16d6f</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DeVito Dabbs A, Song MK, Myers BA, Li R, Hawkins RP, Pilewski JM, Bermudez CA, Aubrecht J, Begey A, Connolly M, Alrawashdeh M, Dew MA. A Randomized Controlled Trial of a Mobile Health Intervention to Promote Self-Management After Lung Transplantation. Am J Transplant. 2016 Jul;16(7):2172-80. doi: 10.1111/ajt.13701. Epub 2016 Mar 14.</citation>
    <PMID>26729617</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carrier G, Cotte E, Beyer-Berjot L, Faucheron JL, Joris J, Slim K; Groupe Francophone de Réhabilitation Améliorée après Chirurgie (GRACE). Post-discharge follow-up using text messaging within an enhanced recovery program after colorectal surgery. J Visc Surg. 2016 Aug;153(4):249-52. doi: 10.1016/j.jviscsurg.2016.05.016. Epub 2016 Aug 8.</citation>
    <PMID>27423211</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cleeland CS, Wang XS, Shi Q, Mendoza TR, Wright SL, Berry MD, Malveaux D, Shah PK, Gning I, Hofstetter WL, Putnam JB Jr, Vaporciyan AA. Automated symptom alerts reduce postoperative symptom severity after cancer surgery: a randomized controlled clinical trial. J Clin Oncol. 2011 Mar 10;29(8):994-1000. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2010.29.8315. Epub 2011 Jan 31.</citation>
    <PMID>21282546</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martínez-Ramos C, Cerdán MT, López RS. Mobile phone-based telemedicine system for the home follow-up of patients undergoing ambulatory surgery. Telemed J E Health. 2009 Jul-Aug;15(6):531-7. doi: 10.1089/tmj.2009.0003.</citation>
    <PMID>19566396</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">February 1, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>St. Louis University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Yosef Greenspon, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Surgery; Pediatric Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>text message</keyword>
  <keyword>telemedicine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Short Bowel Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

