<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03412604</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017P000648</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03412604</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Modulating Gamma Oscillations Using tACS</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Modulating Gamma Oscillations by Transcranial Alternating Current Stimulation on Brain Structure and Function in Humans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to implement an intervention based on multiple, individualized multifocal
      tACS stimulation sessions based on individual PET and MRI information in patients with
      amyloid-positive PET with the hope that this leads to microglia activation and decrease in
      cerebral amyloid and tau depositions in human patients with AD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will leverage all this accumulated knowledge by implementing an intervention based
      on multiple, individualized multifocal tACS stimulation sessions based on individual PET and
      MRI information in patients with amyloid-positive PET with the hope that this leads to
      microglia activation and decrease in cerebral amyloid and tau depositions in human patients
      with AD.This would have immense translational impact, as gamma tACS is an intervention that
      is portable, does not require expensive hardware, can be widely applied to large numbers of
      patients with AD, as well as, given its favorable side effect profile, even to patients at
      earlier stages of the disease who have cerebral amyloid/tau without clinical symptoms.

      The investigators aim to enroll 10 individuals with AD with evidence of increased cerebral
      amyloid burden on amyloid PET imaging. This would allow for a final sample size of 5-6 fully
      evaluable subjects. Each subject's participation in this study will consist of approximately
      31-35 visits: 1 day for consent and screening procedures, 5-7 days of baseline procedures
      (this includes the PET scans), 20 tACS study visits, and 5-7 days of follow-up assessments.
      Subjects will undergo baseline cognitive assessment, structural and functional MRI
      characterization, PET imaging to assess amyloid burden, tau deposition and level of microglia
      activation, and resting-state EEG measurement. Additionally, subjects will undergo a TMS-EEG
      and a tACS-EEG recording session to assess brain plasticity levels and identify markers of
      response to stimulation. All subjects will subsequently undergo 20 sessions of
      gamma-frequency (40 Hz) tACS. At the end of the 20 sessions, subjects will then repeat the
      baseline assessments over 5-7 visits, including repeat PET imaging to assess for changes in
      amyloid burden, tau deposition, and microglia activation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse Events as a result of tACS stimulation will be reported</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PET amyloid burden</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the amyloid load observed via PET imaging will be evaluated by comparing PET data acquired before and after the 20 tACS sessions</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PET tau deposition</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the tau deposition observed via PET imaging will be evaluated by comparing PET data acquired before and after the 20 tACS sessions</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PET Microglia activation</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in the microglia activation observed via PET imaging will be evaluated by comparing PET data acquired before and after the 20 tACS sessions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Alzheimer's Disease Assessment Scale -Cog Score</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Adas-Cog score will be reported, to document a potential clinical benefit of tACS. The scale ranges from a total score of 0-70 with higher score indicating greater cognitive impairment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>tACS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Transcranial alternating current stimulation (tACS) tuned at the frequency of 40Hz (gamma frequency) will be applied for 1 hour in 20 sessions on consecutive weekdays. The tACS intervention (20 sessions) will be preceded and followed by amyloid, microglia and tau PET imaging as well as a clinical/cognitive evaluation. The assessment of the effect of stimulation on microglia activation, amyloid deposition and tau deposition will constitute a primary outcome measure. Assessment of adverse effects will be also evaluated as a secondary outcome. The effect of brain stimulation on brain connectivity will be assessed by EEG and MRI and cognitive function.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Transcranial Alternating Current Stimulation (tACS)</intervention_name>
    <description>tACS will be applied at a frequency of 40Hz and targeting the area of maximal tracer uptake on amyloid PET imaging using an individualized multielectrode design to maximize the induced electrical current to the target region.</description>
    <arm_group_label>tACS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Non-invasive Brain Stimulation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical Diagnosis of mild to moderate AD*

          -  Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE) &gt; 18

          -  Mild AD ≥ 21

          -  Moderate AD 18-20

          -  Demonstration or history of memory impairments.

             * Confirmation of diagnosis will be made by the study MD based on a holistic
             consideration of the participant's cognitive evaluation and history.

          -  Amyloid positive PET imaging

          -  At least 45 years old

          -  On a stable dose of medications for memory loss including cholinesterase inhibitors
             (e.g. donepezil, rivastigmine or memantine) as defined as 6 consecutive weeks of
             treatment at an unchanging dose

          -  Minimum of completed 8th grade education

          -  IQ&gt; 85 as determined by the WTAR and no history of intellectual disability

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current history of poorly controlled migraines including chronic medication for
             migraine prevention

          -  Current or past history of any neurological disorder other than dementia, such as
             epilepsy, stroke, progressive neurologic disease (e.g. multiple sclerosis) or
             intracranial brain lesions; and history of previous neurosurgery or head trauma that
             resulted in residual neurologic impairment.

          -  Past or current history of major depression, bipolar disorder or psychotic disorders,
             or any other major psychiatric condition.

          -  Contraindication for undergoing MRI or receiving TMS or tACS,

          -  &gt;50 mSv of radiation exposure for research within the past year (PET imaging
             exclusion)

          -  Presence of the Thr/Thr polymorphism in the TSPO gene (rs6971) due to low affinity
             binding for the PBR 28 (microlgia) PET scan

          -  History of fainting spells of unknown or undetermined etiology that might constitute
             seizures.

          -  History of seizures, diagnosis of epilepsy, history of abnormal (epileptiform) EEG or
             immediate (1st degree relative) family history of epilepsy; with the exception of a
             single seizure of benign etiology (e.g. febrile seizure) in the judgment of the
             investigator.

          -  Chronic (particularly) uncontrolled medical conditions that may cause a medical
             emergency in case of a provoked seizure (cardiac malformation, cardiac dysrhythmia,
             asthma, etc.).

          -  Metal implants (excluding dental fillings) or devices such as pacemaker, medication
             pump, nerve stimulator, TENS unit, ventriculo-peritoneal shunt, cochlear implant,
             unless cleared by the study MD.

          -  Substance abuse or dependence within the past six months.

          -  Medications will be reviewed by the responsible MD and a decision about inclusion will
             be made based on the following: The patient's past medical history, drug dose, history
             of recent medication changes or duration of treatment, and combination of CNS active
             drugs.

          -  All female participants that are pre-menopausal will be required to have a pregnancy
             test; any participant who is pregnant or breastfeeding will not be enrolled in the
             study.

          -  Subjects who, in the investigator's opinion, might not be suitable for the study

          -  A hair style or head dress that prevents electrode contact with the scalp or would
             interfere with the stimulation (for example: thick braids, hair weave, afro, wig)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alvaro Pascual-Leone, MD</last_name>
    <phone>617-667-0203</phone>
    <email>apleone@bidmc.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rachel Paciorek, MA</last_name>
    <phone>617-667-9088</phone>
    <email>rpaciore@bidmc.harvard.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 22, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alvaro Pascual-Leone, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief, Division of Cognitive Neurology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alzheimer Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

