<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03411616</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CAAE - 10726313.3.0000.5149</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03411616</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Eating Behavior, Food Craving and Relation to Excessive Weight Gain in Patients Submitted to Liver Transplantation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Eating Behavior, Food Craving and Relation to Excessive Weight Gain in Patients Submitted to Liver Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Federal University of Minas Gerais</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Federal University of Minas Gerais</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Excessive weight gain, obesity and metabolic syndrome are highly prevalent in patients
      undergoing liver transplantation. Traditional methods of assessing dietary intake have failed
      to demonstrate an association between these problems and dietary intake. Patients with an
      indication for transplantation due to ethanolic cirrhosis, ex-smokers and those with a
      previous history of overweight were identified as being at greater risk for overweight and
      metabolic syndrome, and these factors may be related to the change in eating behavior after
      the operation. Objective: To evaluate the eating behavior, the occurrence of food craving and
      relation to weight gain, overweight and obesity after liver transplantation. Method: This is
      a cross-sectional study in which adult and elderly patients in follow-up at the Hepatic
      Transplant Outpatient Clinic of the Alpha Institute of Gastroenterology of the Federal
      University of Minas Gerais were evaluated for eating behavior and food craving. The
      evaluation of the eating behavior was performed with the help of the Three Factor Eating
      Questionnaire-R21 (TFEQ-R21), translated version and validated for Portuguese. Food Craving
      Questionnaires State (FCQ-S) and Trait (FCQ-T) and the Brazilian Inventory of Foods Related
      to Craving (FCI-Br) were used in the translated and validated versions for Portuguese.
      Demographic, lifestyle, clinical and anthropometric variables of the evaluated patients were
      obtained through electronic medical records. Weight gain was assessed by the difference
      between the current weight and the first post-transplant outpatient weight.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 23, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 23, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 23, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Eating behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>40 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The evaluation of the eating behavior was performed with the help of the Three Factor Eating Questionnaire-R21 (TFEQ-R21), translated version and validated for Portuguese. This is a self-report questionnaire composed of 21 items, with 4 response options for questions 1 to 20 and question 21 is evaluated on a likert 8-point scale. TFEQ-R21 evaluates 3 types of eating behavior: cognitive restriction (CR), emotional eating (EE) and uncontrolled eating (UE). The CR scale assesses the tendency to control food intake in order to influence body weight and body shape, with 6 items in scale. The EE scale measures the propensity to overeat in relation to negative mood states, e.g., when feeling lonely, anxious, or depressed, has 6 items. The UE scale assesses the tendency to lose control over eating when feeling hungry or when exposed to external stimuli, has 9 of items in scale. Each score ranges from 0 to 100, with higher score indicative of greater level in the eating behavior of interest.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food Craving Questionnaires State (FCQ-S)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The FCQ-State consists of 15 questions, grouped into five dimensions: An intense desire to eat (Desire); anticipation of positive reinforcement that may result from eating (Pos R); anticipation of relief from negative states and feelings as a result of eating (Neg R); thoughts of preoccupation with food and lack of control over eating (Lack Co); and craving as part of the sensation of hunger, a physiological state (Hunger). Participants must answer each question related to what they are feeling at the moment, using a Likert scale of five points, the extremes of which are &quot;(1) strongly disagree&quot; and &quot;(5) strongly agree&quot;. The full-scale score corresponds to the sum of the scores obtained in each dimension, which is calculated by simply adding them. Total scores can vary from 15 to 75.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Food Craving Questionnaires Trait (FCQ-T)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>consume food (Plan); environmental cues that may trigger food craving (Environ); thoughts or preoccupation with food (Thoughts); craving as a physiological state (Hunger); possible lack of control over eating if food is being eaten (Lack Co); emotions that may be experienced before or during food cravings or eating (Emotion); and guilt that may be experienced because of cravings and/or giving in to them (Guilt). The answers are recorded on a Likert scale, ranging from &quot;(1) never or not applicable&quot; to &quot;(6) Always,&quot; referring to the frequency with each statement applies to the participant. Full-scale and factor-scale totals are obtained by the sum of the corresponding item scores. Thus, the overall score can range from 39 to 234.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brazilian Inventory of Foods Related to Craving (FCI-Br)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The Brazilian Inventory of Foods Related to Craving (FCI-Br) begins with a short definition of food cravings behavior, followed by the question ''Over the past month, how often have you experienced a craving for the food listed below?''. Each of the foods listed was evaluated using a five point Likert scale ranging from: &quot;(1) never&quot; to &quot;(5) almost every day&quot;. The total score of each FCI-Br subscale was calculated by adding the scores obtained for each item that comprised it.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Demographic, lifestyle, clinical and anthropometric variables</measure>
    <time_frame>40 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Own Checklist - Demographic variables as well as habitual life style, clinical and anthropometric characteristics were assessed. Clinical variables encompassed indication for LTx, time since LTx and current immunossupressive drugs. Self reported current and past smoking and alcohol consumption were also collected. The patients' weight (kilograms) on the first outpatient visit after LTx was collected from their medical recorders, it is regularly measured with patients wearing light street clothing, no shoes, on a calibrated mechanical scale (Filizola®). Current height (meters) and weight (kilograms) of patients were measured on the day of the interview. Considering these weights, weight gain was assessed by the difference between the current weight and the first post-LTx outpatient weight. Nutritional status was defined according to body mass index (BMI) values as underweight, BMI &lt;18.5 kg/m²; normal weight, BMI 18.5-24.9 kg/m²; overweight, BMI 24.9-29.9 kg/m² and obese, BMI &gt;30 kg/m².</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">301</enrollment>
  <condition>Eating Behavior</condition>
  <condition>Liver Transplant</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who undergone liver transplantation at least 18 years of age, who were regularly
        followed up at the Bias Fortes outpatient clinic
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who undergone liver transplantation

          -  At least 18 years of age

          -  Patients regularly followed up at the Bias Fortes outpatient clinic

          -  Patients who agreed to participate in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who were unable to write and who did not have an accompanying person present
             as a literate person

          -  Pregnant or nursing women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital of Clinics of the University Federal of Minas Gerais</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belo Horizonte</city>
        <state>Minas Gerais</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 6, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 19, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 19, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 19, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Federal University of Minas Gerais</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Maria Isabel Toulson Davisson Correia</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Eating behavior</keyword>
  <keyword>Excessive weight</keyword>
  <keyword>Food craving</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver transplantation</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Weight gain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Weight Gain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

