<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03417050</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MEC-2016-716</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03417050</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Synergy Between PCI With TAXUS and Cardiac Surgery: SYNTAX Extended Survival</brief_title>
  <acronym>SYNTAXES</acronym>
  <official_title>Synergy Between PCI With TAXUS and Cardiac Surgery: SYNTAX Extended Survival</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Erasmus Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Erasmus Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      An investigator-driven, retrospective study to compare long-term survival-data (10-year
      follow-up) of patients with coronary artery disease (CAD), previously enrolled in the SYNTAX
      trial, who were randomized to percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) using a paclitaxel
      (TAXUS) drug-eluting-stent (DES) or coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Long-term survival status</measure>
    <time_frame>10-year</time_frame>
    <description>All-cause death</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cause of death</measure>
    <time_frame>10-year</time_frame>
    <description>Cause-specific death, separated in cardiovascular and non-cardiovascular death with specific causes for cardiovascular deaths.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2636</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Randomized CABG patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients which were randomized to undergo CABG.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Randomized PCI patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients which were randomized to undergo PCI.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Registry CABG</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients for whom only one treatment option was suitable were included into a parallel, nested registry: the CABG registry for PCI-ineligible patients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Registry PCI</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients for whom only one treatment option was suitable were included into a parallel, nested registry: the PCI registry for CABG-ineligible patients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No intervention will take place for this retrospective and observational study.</intervention_name>
    <description>No intervention will take place for this retrospective and observational study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Randomized CABG patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Randomized PCI patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Registry CABG</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Registry PCI</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients enrolled in the SYNTAX trial and registries had to be diagnosed with three-vessel
        (3VD) or left main (LM) coronary artery disease. The vessels (diameter ≥1.5 mm and
        significant stenosis &gt; 50%) deemed important to revascularize were determined by the Heart
        Team prior to randomization. The group of 3VD consists of patients with significant
        stenosis in vessels supplying all three major epicardial territories in absence of LM
        disease, as determined by the site investigators. The group of patients with LM disease
        consists of patients with a significant stenosis of the left main coronary artery,
        irrespective of additional vessel disease.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients which have previously been enrolled in the SYNTAX trial (randomized and registry
        patients)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>A. Pieter Kappetein, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Erasmus Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Friedrick W. Mohr, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>German Heart Center, Leipzig, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patrick W.J.C. Serruys, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Imperial College London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael J. Mack, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor Scott &amp; White Health, Plano, TX, United States</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David R. Holmes, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN, United States</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marie-Claude Morice, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>ICPS Ramsay-Generale de Sante, Massy, France</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Piroze M. Davierwala, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>German Heart Center, Leipzig, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stuart J. Head, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Erasmus Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel J.F.M. Thuijs, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Erasmus Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sianos G, Morel MA, Kappetein AP, Morice MC, Colombo A, Dawkins K, van den Brand M, Van Dyck N, Russell ME, Mohr FW, Serruys PW. The SYNTAX Score: an angiographic tool grading the complexity of coronary artery disease. EuroIntervention. 2005 Aug;1(2):219-27.</citation>
    <PMID>19758907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kappetein AP, Dawkins KD, Mohr FW, Morice MC, Mack MJ, Russell ME, Pomar J, Serruys PW. Current percutaneous coronary intervention and coronary artery bypass grafting practices for three-vessel and left main coronary artery disease. Insights from the SYNTAX run-in phase. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2006 Apr;29(4):486-91. Epub 2006 Feb 23.</citation>
    <PMID>16497510</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ong AT, Serruys PW, Mohr FW, Morice MC, Kappetein AP, Holmes DR Jr, Mack MJ, van den Brand M, Morel MA, van Es GA, Kleijne J, Koglin J, Russell ME. The SYNergy between percutaneous coronary intervention with TAXus and cardiac surgery (SYNTAX) study: design, rationale, and run-in phase. Am Heart J. 2006 Jun;151(6):1194-204.</citation>
    <PMID>16781219</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Serruys PW, Morice MC, Kappetein AP, Colombo A, Holmes DR, Mack MJ, Ståhle E, Feldman TE, van den Brand M, Bass EJ, Van Dyck N, Leadley K, Dawkins KD, Mohr FW; SYNTAX Investigators. Percutaneous coronary intervention versus coronary-artery bypass grafting for severe coronary artery disease. N Engl J Med. 2009 Mar 5;360(10):961-72. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0804626. Epub 2009 Feb 18. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2013 Feb 7;368(6):584.</citation>
    <PMID>19228612</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Serruys PW, Onuma Y, Garg S, Sarno G, van den Brand M, Kappetein AP, Van Dyck N, Mack M, Holmes D, Feldman T, Morice MC, Colombo A, Bass E, Leadley K, Dawkins KD, van Es GA, Morel MA, Mohr FW. Assessment of the SYNTAX score in the Syntax study. EuroIntervention. 2009 May;5(1):50-6.</citation>
    <PMID>19577983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Banning AP, Westaby S, Morice MC, Kappetein AP, Mohr FW, Berti S, Glauber M, Kellett MA, Kramer RS, Leadley K, Dawkins KD, Serruys PW. Diabetic and nondiabetic patients with left main and/or 3-vessel coronary artery disease: comparison of outcomes with cardiac surgery and paclitaxel-eluting stents. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2010 Mar 16;55(11):1067-75. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2009.09.057. Epub 2010 Jan 14.</citation>
    <PMID>20079596</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Girasis C, Serruys PW, Onuma Y, Colombo A, Holmes DR Jr, Feldman TE, Bass EJ, Leadley K, Dawkins KD, Morice MC. 3-Dimensional bifurcation angle analysis in patients with left main disease: a substudy of the SYNTAX trial (SYNergy Between Percutaneous Coronary Intervention with TAXus and Cardiac Surgery). JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2010 Jan;3(1):41-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2009.10.019.</citation>
    <PMID>20129567</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garg S, Girasis C, Sarno G, Goedhart D, Morel MA, Garcia-Garcia HM, Bressers M, van Es GA, Serruys PW; SYNTAX trial investigators. The SYNTAX score revisited: a reassessment of the SYNTAX score reproducibility. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2010 May 1;75(6):946-52. doi: 10.1002/ccd.22372.</citation>
    <PMID>20146321</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morice MC, Serruys PW, Kappetein AP, Feldman TE, Ståhle E, Colombo A, Mack MJ, Holmes DR, Torracca L, van Es GA, Leadley K, Dawkins KD, Mohr F. Outcomes in patients with de novo left main disease treated with either percutaneous coronary intervention using paclitaxel-eluting stents or coronary artery bypass graft treatment in the Synergy Between Percutaneous Coronary Intervention with TAXUS and Cardiac Surgery (SYNTAX) trial. Circulation. 2010 Jun 22;121(24):2645-53. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.109.899211. Epub 2010 Jun 7.</citation>
    <PMID>20530001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mohr FW, Rastan AJ, Serruys PW, Kappetein AP, Holmes DR, Pomar JL, Westaby S, Leadley K, Dawkins KD, Mack MJ. Complex coronary anatomy in coronary artery bypass graft surgery: impact of complex coronary anatomy in modern bypass surgery? Lessons learned from the SYNTAX trial after two years. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2011 Jan;141(1):130-40. doi: 10.1016/j.jtcvs.2010.07.094.</citation>
    <PMID>21168023</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen DJ, Lavelle TA, Van Hout B, Li H, Lei Y, Robertus K, Pinto D, Magnuson EA, Mcgarry TF, Lucas SK, Horwitz PA, Henry CA, Serruys PW, Mohr FW, Kappetein AP. Economic outcomes of percutaneous coronary intervention with drug-eluting stents versus bypass surgery for patients with left main or three-vessel coronary artery disease: one-year results from the SYNTAX trial. Catheter Cardiovasc Interv. 2012 Feb 1;79(2):198-209. doi: 10.1002/ccd.23147. Epub 2011 Sep 26.</citation>
    <PMID>21542113</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kappetein AP, Feldman TE, Mack MJ, Morice MC, Holmes DR, Ståhle E, Dawkins KD, Mohr FW, Serruys PW, Colombo A. Comparison of coronary bypass surgery with drug-eluting stenting for the treatment of left main and/or three-vessel disease: 3-year follow-up of the SYNTAX trial. Eur Heart J. 2011 Sep;32(17):2125-34. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehr213. Epub 2011 Jun 22.</citation>
    <PMID>21697170</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morice MC, Feldman TE, Mack MJ, Ståhle E, Holmes DR, Colombo A, Morel MA, van den Brand M, Serruys PW, Mohr F, Carrié D, Fournial G, James S, Leadley K, Dawkins KD, Kappetein AP. Angiographic outcomes following stenting or coronary artery bypass surgery of the left main coronary artery: fifteen-month outcomes from the synergy between PCI with TAXUS express and cardiac surgery left main angiographic substudy (SYNTAX-LE MANS). EuroIntervention. 2011 Oct 30;7(6):670-9. doi: 10.4244/EIJV7I6A109.</citation>
    <PMID>21959312</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mack MJ, Banning AP, Serruys PW, Morice MC, Taeymans Y, Van Nooten G, Possati G, Crea F, Hood KL, Leadley K, Dawkins KD, Kappetein AP. Bypass versus drug-eluting stents at three years in SYNTAX patients with diabetes mellitus or metabolic syndrome. Ann Thorac Surg. 2011 Dec;92(6):2140-6. doi: 10.1016/j.athoracsur.2011.06.028. Epub 2011 Oct 2.</citation>
    <PMID>21967819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Head SJ, Mack MJ, Holmes DR Jr, Mohr FW, Morice MC, Serruys PW, Kappetein AP. Incidence, predictors and outcomes of incomplete revascularization after percutaneous coronary intervention and coronary artery bypass grafting: a subgroup analysis of 3-year SYNTAX data. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2012 Mar;41(3):535-41. doi: 10.1093/ejcts/ezr105. Epub 2011 Dec 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22219412</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arnold SV, Magnuson EA, Wang K, Serruys PW, Kappetein AP, Mohr FW, Cohen DJ; SYNTAX Investigators. Do differences in repeat revascularization explain the antianginal benefits of bypass surgery versus percutaneous coronary intervention?: implications for future treatment comparisons. Circ Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes. 2012 May;5(3):267-75. doi: 10.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.111.964585. Epub 2012 Apr 10.</citation>
    <PMID>22496114</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Serruys PW, Farooq V, Vranckx P, Girasis C, Brugaletta S, Garcia-Garcia HM, Holmes DR Jr, Kappetein AP, Mack MJ, Feldman T, Morice MC, Ståhle E, James S, Colombo A, Pereda P, Huang J, Morel MA, Van Es GA, Dawkins KD, Mohr FW, Steyerberg EW. A global risk approach to identify patients with left main or 3-vessel disease who could safely and efficaciously be treated with percutaneous coronary intervention: the SYNTAX Trial at 3 years. JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2012 Jun;5(6):606-17. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2012.03.016.</citation>
    <PMID>22721655</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Head SJ, Holmes DR Jr, Mack MJ, Serruys PW, Mohr FW, Morice MC, Colombo A, Kappetein AP; SYNTAX Investigators. Risk profile and 3-year outcomes from the SYNTAX percutaneous coronary intervention and coronary artery bypass grafting nested registries. JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2012 Jun;5(6):618-25. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2012.02.013.</citation>
    <PMID>22721656</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farooq V, Vergouwe Y, Räber L, Vranckx P, Garcia-Garcia H, Diletti R, Kappetein AP, Morel MA, de Vries T, Swart M, Valgimigli M, Dawkins KD, Windecker S, Steyerberg EW, Serruys PW. Combined anatomical and clinical factors for the long-term risk stratification of patients undergoing percutaneous coronary intervention: the Logistic Clinical SYNTAX score. Eur Heart J. 2012 Dec;33(24):3098-104. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehs295. Epub 2012 Oct 9.</citation>
    <PMID>23048195</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farooq V, Serruys PW, Bourantas C, Vranckx P, Diletti R, Garcia Garcia HM, Holmes DR, Kappetein AP, Mack M, Feldman T, Morice MC, Colombo A, Morel MA, de Vries T, van Es GA, Steyerberg EW, Dawkins KD, Mohr FW, James S, Ståhle E. Incidence and multivariable correlates of long-term mortality in patients treated with surgical or percutaneous revascularization in the synergy between percutaneous coronary intervention with taxus and cardiac surgery (SYNTAX) trial. Eur Heart J. 2012 Dec;33(24):3105-13. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehs367. Epub 2012 Oct 26.</citation>
    <PMID>23103663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farooq V, Serruys PW, Garcia-Garcia HM, Zhang Y, Bourantas CV, Holmes DR, Mack M, Feldman T, Morice MC, Ståhle E, James S, Colombo A, Diletti R, Papafaklis MI, de Vries T, Morel MA, van Es GA, Mohr FW, Dawkins KD, Kappetein AP, Sianos G, Boersma E. The negative impact of incomplete angiographic revascularization on clinical outcomes and its association with total occlusions: the SYNTAX (Synergy Between Percutaneous Coronary Intervention with Taxus and Cardiac Surgery) trial. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2013 Jan 22;61(3):282-94. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2012.10.017. Epub 2012 Dec 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23265332</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kappetein AP, Head SJ, Morice MC, Banning AP, Serruys PW, Mohr FW, Dawkins KD, Mack MJ; SYNTAX Investigators. Treatment of complex coronary artery disease in patients with diabetes: 5-year results comparing outcomes of bypass surgery and percutaneous coronary intervention in the SYNTAX trial. Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2013 May;43(5):1006-13. doi: 10.1093/ejcts/ezt017. Epub 2013 Feb 14.</citation>
    <PMID>23413014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mohr FW, Morice MC, Kappetein AP, Feldman TE, Ståhle E, Colombo A, Mack MJ, Holmes DR Jr, Morel MA, Van Dyck N, Houle VM, Dawkins KD, Serruys PW. Coronary artery bypass graft surgery versus percutaneous coronary intervention in patients with three-vessel disease and left main coronary disease: 5-year follow-up of the randomised, clinical SYNTAX trial. Lancet. 2013 Feb 23;381(9867):629-38. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(13)60141-5.</citation>
    <PMID>23439102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farooq V, van Klaveren D, Steyerberg EW, Meliga E, Vergouwe Y, Chieffo A, Kappetein AP, Colombo A, Holmes DR Jr, Mack M, Feldman T, Morice MC, Ståhle E, Onuma Y, Morel MA, Garcia-Garcia HM, van Es GA, Dawkins KD, Mohr FW, Serruys PW. Anatomical and clinical characteristics to guide decision making between coronary artery bypass surgery and percutaneous coronary intervention for individual patients: development and validation of SYNTAX score II. Lancet. 2013 Feb 23;381(9867):639-50. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(13)60108-7.</citation>
    <PMID>23439103</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mack MJ, Head SJ, Holmes DR Jr, Ståhle E, Feldman TE, Colombo A, Morice MC, Unger F, Erglis A, Stoler R, Dawkins KD, Serruys PW, Mohr FW, Kappetein AP. Analysis of stroke occurring in the SYNTAX trial comparing coronary artery bypass surgery and percutaneous coronary intervention in the treatment of complex coronary artery disease. JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2013 Apr;6(4):344-54. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2012.11.010. Epub 2013 Mar 20.</citation>
    <PMID>23523456</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farooq V, Girasis C, Magro M, Onuma Y, Morel MA, Heo JH, Garcia-Garcia H, Kappetein AP, van den Brand M, Holmes DR, Mack M, Feldman T, Colombo A, Ståhle E, James S, Carrié D, Fournial G, van Es GA, Dawkins KD, Mohr FW, Morice MC, Serruys PW. The CABG SYNTAX Score - an angiographic tool to grade the complexity of coronary disease following coronary artery bypass graft surgery: from the SYNTAX Left Main Angiographic (SYNTAX-LE MANS) substudy. EuroIntervention. 2013 Mar;8(11):1277-85. doi: 10.4244/EIJV8I11A196.</citation>
    <PMID>23537954</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farooq V, Girasis C, Magro M, Onuma Y, Morel MA, Heo JH, Garcia-Garcia HM, Kappetein AP, van den Brand M, Holmes DR, Mack M, Feldman T, Colombo A, Ståhle E, James S, Carrié D, Fournial G, van Es GA, Dawkins KD, Mohr FW, Morice MC, Serruys PW. The coronary artery bypass graft SYNTAX Score: final five-year outcomes from the SYNTAX-LE MANS left main angiographic substudy. EuroIntervention. 2013 Dec;9(8):1009-10. doi: 10.4244/EIJV9I8A170.</citation>
    <PMID>23628520</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farooq V, Serruys PW, Bourantas CV, Zhang Y, Muramatsu T, Feldman T, Holmes DR, Mack M, Morice MC, Ståhle E, Colombo A, de Vries T, Morel MA, Dawkins KD, Kappetein AP, Mohr FW. Quantification of incomplete revascularization and its association with five-year mortality in the synergy between percutaneous coronary intervention with taxus and cardiac surgery (SYNTAX) trial validation of the residual SYNTAX score. Circulation. 2013 Jul 9;128(2):141-51. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.113.001803. Epub 2013 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>23766350</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farooq V, Serruys PW, Vranckx P, Bourantas CV, Girasis C, Holmes DR, Kappetein AP, Mack M, Feldman T, Morice MC, Colombo A, Morel MA, de Vries T, Dawkins KD, Mohr FW, James S, Ståhle E. Incidence, correlates, and significance of abnormal cardiac enzyme rises in patients treated with surgical or percutaneous based revascularisation: a substudy from the Synergy between Percutaneous Coronary Interventions with Taxus and Cardiac Surgery (SYNTAX) Trial. Int J Cardiol. 2013 Oct 15;168(6):5287-92. doi: 10.1016/j.ijcard.2013.08.013. Epub 2013 Aug 14.</citation>
    <PMID>23993326</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farooq V, Serruys PW, Zhang Y, Mack M, Ståhle E, Holmes DR, Feldman T, Morice MC, Colombo A, Bourantas CV, de Vries T, Morel MA, Dawkins KD, Kappetein AP, Mohr FW. Short-term and long-term clinical impact of stent thrombosis and graft occlusion in the SYNTAX trial at 5 years: Synergy Between Percutaneous Coronary Intervention with Taxus and Cardiac Surgery trial. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2013 Dec 24;62(25):2360-2369. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2013.07.106. Epub 2013 Oct 16.</citation>
    <PMID>24140677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Girasis C, Farooq V, Diletti R, Muramatsu T, Bourantas CV, Onuma Y, Holmes DR, Feldman TE, Morel MA, van Es GA, Dawkins KD, Morice MC, Serruys PW. Impact of 3-dimensional bifurcation angle on 5-year outcome of patients after percutaneous coronary intervention for left main coronary artery disease: a substudy of the SYNTAX trial (synergy between percutaneous coronary intervention with taxus and cardiac surgery). JACC Cardiovasc Interv. 2013 Dec;6(12):1250-60. doi: 10.1016/j.jcin.2013.08.009.</citation>
    <PMID>24355115</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morice MC, Serruys PW, Kappetein AP, Feldman TE, Ståhle E, Colombo A, Mack MJ, Holmes DR, Choi JW, Ruzyllo W, Religa G, Huang J, Roy K, Dawkins KD, Mohr F. Five-year outcomes in patients with left main disease treated with either percutaneous coronary intervention or coronary artery bypass grafting in the synergy between percutaneous coronary intervention with taxus and cardiac surgery trial. Circulation. 2014 Jun 10;129(23):2388-94. doi: 10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.113.006689. Epub 2014 Apr 3.</citation>
    <PMID>24700706</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Head SJ, Davierwala PM, Serruys PW, Redwood SR, Colombo A, Mack MJ, Morice MC, Holmes DR Jr, Feldman TE, Ståhle E, Underwood P, Dawkins KD, Kappetein AP, Mohr FW. Coronary artery bypass grafting vs. percutaneous coronary intervention for patients with three-vessel disease: final five-year follow-up of the SYNTAX trial. Eur Heart J. 2014 Oct 21;35(40):2821-30. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehu213. Epub 2014 May 21.</citation>
    <PMID>24849105</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 25, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Erasmus Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stuart Head</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD, Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>coronary artery bypass grafting</keyword>
  <keyword>percutaneous coronary intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>drug eluting stent</keyword>
  <keyword>survival status</keyword>
  <keyword>long-term follow-up</keyword>
  <keyword>complex coronary artery disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

