<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03415529</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CO2LUNGSAFE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03415529</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Arterial CO2 Tension on Management and Outcome in Patients With Acute Hypoxemic Respirator Failure and ARDS</brief_title>
  <acronym>CO2 LUNG SAFE</acronym>
  <official_title>Incidence of Hypercapnia and Impact of Arterial CO2 Tension on Management and Outcome in Patients With Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome (ARDS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>European Society of Intensive Care Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>European Society of Intensive Care Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There appears to be considerable variability in the approach physicians use to manage
      arterial carbon dioxide tensions, in patients in the early phases [first 48 hours] of ARDS
      (Acute hypoxemic respiratory failure and). A number of specific concerns exist, particularly
      the use of greater than needed inspired oxygen concentrations (potentially in 40% patients),
      and the proportion of hypocapnic patients in our cohort.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will address a number of specific concerns, including:

        1. the incidence of hypocapnia and hypercapnia;

        2. the factors (e.g. ventilatory mode) contributing to hypocapnia and hypercapnia;

        3. the impact of hypocapnia and hypercapnia on progression of ARDS, duration of
           ventilation, ICU stay, hospital stay and patient outcome;

        4. the impact of pH (respiratory versus metabolic cause) on outcome variables.

      LUNG SAFE was a prospective observational study. There was not patient intervention. The
      current analysis is a secondary analysis of this existing database.

      Data will be abstracted form the database on all patients meeting the inclusion criteria for
      ARDS (during the first 2 days from AHRF onset) for the following variables: Patient's
      demographic characteristics (age, sex) and chronic comorbidities, Arterial PCO2, pH in first
      48 hours, Data on P/F ratio over course of illness, Duration of ventilation, ICU stay,
      hospital survival in patients identified as being exposed to hypocapnia (pCO2 &lt; or = to
      30mmHg) and hypercapnia (PCO2 &gt; or = to 45mmHg); Main ventilatory variables: mode of
      ventilation, tidal volume, respiratory.

      Descriptive statistics will include proportions for categorical and mean (standard deviation)
      or median (interquartile range) for continuous variables, according the data distribution.
      The amount of missing data in the LUNG SAFE database is low so no assumptions will be made
      for missing data.

      In order to investigate the relationship between PaCO2 and management factors, the
      investigators will stratify study population according the presence or absence of hypercapnia
      and will evaluate differences in management factors, using appropriate statistical tests. In
      detail, proportions will be compared using chi-squared or Fisher exact tests and mean values
      were compared using T-test or Wilcoxon rank sum test, as appropriate. Shapiro-Wilks test will
      be used to assess normality in data distribution. Moreover, they will perform univariate and
      multivariable logistic regression models using hypercapnia as dependent variable. Stepwise
      regression approach with significance alpha levels of 0.05 (both for entry and retention)
      will be used to establish a set of independent predictors. Odds ratios (ORs) and 95%
      confidence intervals (CIs) will be reported as measure of association.

      They will assess the association of hypercapnia with different outcomes (ARDS progression,
      duration of mechanical ventilation, ICU and hospital stay and mortality) using generalized
      linear regression models (Poisson or Logistic regression models, according outcome
      distribution) and adjusting the relationship with all possible confounders identified with
      stepwise approach. Results will be reported as ORs, incidence rate ratios and corresponding
      95% CI.

      Particular attention will be given to the relationship and interaction between pH and PaCO2.

      Survival analysis (Kaplan-Meier approach) will be used to estimate the time of liberation
      from invasive mechanical ventilation, of ICU and hospital discharge, and of hospital
      mortality within 28 days of AHRF onset in patients with and without hypercapnia. Differences
      in survival time will be assess by Log-Rank test.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>LUNG SAFE was a prospective observational study. Patients were followed until hospital discharge or day 90, whichever came first</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence of hypercapnia [i.e. PaCO2 &gt; 45 mmHg] when ARDS arises</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity</measure>
    <time_frame>LUNG SAFE was a prospective observational study. Patients were followed until hospital discharge or day 90, whichever came first</time_frame>
    <description>The severity of hypercapnia [i.e. PaCO2 &gt; 45 mmHg] when ARDS arises ARDS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hypercapnia</measure>
    <time_frame>LUNG SAFE was a prospective observational study. Patients were followed until hospital discharge or day 90, whichever came first</time_frame>
    <description>Factors (e.g. ventilatory mode) contributing to hypercapnia in patients with ARDS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hypercapnia</measure>
    <time_frame>LUNG SAFE was a prospective observational study. Patients were followed until hospital discharge or day 90, whichever came first</time_frame>
    <description>The impact of hypercapnia on outcome on the progression of ARDS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pH ((potential of hydrogen)</measure>
    <time_frame>LUNG SAFE was a prospective observational study. Patients were followed until hospital discharge or day 90, whichever came first</time_frame>
    <description>The impact of pH (respiratory versus metabolic cause) on outcome variables</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4500</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Severe Respiratory Failure</condition>
  <condition>Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>4500 patients with ARDS</arm_group_label>
    <description>This is a secondary analysis of data from the LUNG SAFE database to determine the impact of alterations in arterial carbon dioxide tensions in patients with ARDS.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients over 18 years of age who fulfilled clinical criteria for ARDS and Acute Hypoxaemic
        respiratory failure were recruited into the LUNG SAFE trial (NCT02010073) that was
        published in JAMA, 2016 Jul 19;316(3):347).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients meeting criteria for ARDS. Fulfillment of criteria for Acute Hypoxaemic
             respiratory failure (AHRF) and fulfillment of Berlin criteria for ARDS during the
             first two days after AHRF onset.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt; 18
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John LAFFEY</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National University of Ireland, Galway</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Giacomo BELLANI</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Milano-Bicocca (Monza, Italy)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Guy M FRANCOIS</last_name>
    <phone>003225590353</phone>
    <email>research@esicm.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bellani G, Laffey JG, Pham T, Fan E, Brochard L, Esteban A, Gattinoni L, van Haren F, Larsson A, McAuley DF, Ranieri M, Rubenfeld G, Thompson BT, Wrigge H, Slutsky AS, Pesenti A; LUNG SAFE Investigators; ESICM Trials Group. Epidemiology, Patterns of Care, and Mortality for Patients With Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome in Intensive Care Units in 50 Countries. JAMA. 2016 Feb 23;315(8):788-800. doi: 10.1001/jama.2016.0291. Erratum in: JAMA. 2016 Jul 19;316(3):350. JAMA. 2016 Jul 19;316(3):350.</citation>
    <PMID>26903337</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laffey JG, Bellani G, Pham T, Fan E, Madotto F, Bajwa EK, Brochard L, Clarkson K, Esteban A, Gattinoni L, van Haren F, Heunks LM, Kurahashi K, Laake JH, Larsson A, McAuley DF, McNamee L, Nin N, Qiu H, Ranieri M, Rubenfeld GD, Thompson BT, Wrigge H, Slutsky AS, Pesenti A; LUNG SAFE Investigators; ESICM Trials Group. Correction to: Potentially modifiable factors contributing to outcome from acute respiratory distress syndrome: the LUNG SAFE study. Intensive Care Med. 2018 Jan;44(1):157-165. doi: 10.1007/s00134-017-4981-z.</citation>
    <PMID>29138899</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Prost N, Pham T, Carteaux G, Mekontso Dessap A, Brun-Buisson C, Fan E, Bellani G, Laffey J, Mercat A, Brochard L, Maître B; LUNG SAFE investigators; ESICM trials group; REVA network. Etiologies, diagnostic work-up and outcomes of acute respiratory distress syndrome with no common risk factor: a prospective multicenter study. Ann Intensive Care. 2017 Dec;7(1):69. doi: 10.1186/s13613-017-0281-6. Epub 2017 Jun 19.</citation>
    <PMID>28631088</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laffey JG, Madotto F, Bellani G, Pham T, Fan E, Brochard L, Amin P, Arabi Y, Bajwa EK, Bruhn A, Cerny V, Clarkson K, Heunks L, Kurahashi K, Laake JH, Lorente JA, McNamee L, Nin N, Palo JE, Piquilloud L, Qiu H, Jiménez JIS, Esteban A, McAuley DF, van Haren F, Ranieri M, Rubenfeld G, Wrigge H, Slutsky AS, Pesenti A; LUNG SAFE Investigators and the ESICM Trials Group. Geo-economic variations in epidemiology, patterns of care, and outcomes in patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome: insights from the LUNG SAFE prospective cohort study. Lancet Respir Med. 2017 Aug;5(8):627-638. doi: 10.1016/S2213-2600(17)30213-8. Epub 2017 Jun 15.</citation>
    <PMID>28624388</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dreyfuss D, Gaudry S, Madotto F, Laffey JG. Some remaining important questions after LUNG SAFE : Discussion of &quot;Potentially modifiable factors contributing to outcome from acute respiratory distress syndrome: the LUNG SAFE study&quot;. Intensive Care Med. 2017 Apr;43(4):598-599. doi: 10.1007/s00134-017-4706-3. Epub 2017 Feb 17.</citation>
    <PMID>28213623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laffey JG, Bellani G, Pham T, Fan E, Madotto F, Bajwa EK, Brochard L, Clarkson K, Esteban A, Gattinoni L, van Haren F, Heunks LM, Kurahashi K, Laake JH, Larsson A, McAuley DF, McNamee L, Nin N, Qiu H, Ranieri M, Rubenfeld GD, Thompson BT, Wrigge H, Slutsky AS, Pesenti A; LUNG SAFE Investigators and the ESICM Trials Group. Potentially modifiable factors contributing to outcome from acute respiratory distress syndrome: the LUNG SAFE study. Intensive Care Med. 2016 Dec;42(12):1865-1876. doi: 10.1007/s00134-016-4571-5. Epub 2016 Oct 18. Erratum in: Intensive Care Med. 2017 Nov 14;:.</citation>
    <PMID>27757516</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bellani G, Laffey JG, Pham T, Madotto F, Fan E, Brochard L, Esteban A, Gattinoni L, Bumbasirevic V, Piquilloud L, van Haren F, Larsson A, McAuley DF, Bauer PR, Arabi YM, Ranieri M, Antonelli M, Rubenfeld GD, Thompson BT, Wrigge H, Slutsky AS, Pesenti A; LUNG SAFE Investigators; ESICM Trials Group. Noninvasive Ventilation of Patients with Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome. Insights from the LUNG SAFE Study. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2017 Jan 1;195(1):67-77. doi: 10.1164/rccm.201606-1306OC.</citation>
    <PMID>27753501</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bellani G, Laffey JG, Pham T, Fan E; LUNG SAFE Investigators and the ESICM Trials Group. The LUNG SAFE study: a presentation of the prevalence of ARDS according to the Berlin Definition! Crit Care. 2016 Sep 9;20:268. doi: 10.1186/s13054-016-1443-x.</citation>
    <PMID>27608629</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bellani G, Pham T, Laffey J; LUNG-SAFE Investigators; ESICM Trials Group. Incidence of Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome--Reply. JAMA. 2016 Jul 19;316(3):347. doi: 10.1001/jama.2016.6471.</citation>
    <PMID>27434453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 17, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 30, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 31, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lung</keyword>
  <keyword>ARDS</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Respiratory Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Prognosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Outcome Research</keyword>
  <keyword>Respiratory infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Sepsis</keyword>
  <keyword>Organ failure</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypercapnia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Newborn</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Distress Syndrome, Adult</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Lung Injury</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

