<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01414439</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MMC-chf</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01414439</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Group Psychotherapy Among Congestive Heart Failure Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Group Psychotherapy Among Congestive Heart Failure Patients as a Way to Reduce Psychological Distress and Increase Psycho-social Adjustment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Meir Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Meir Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will examine the efficacy of group therapy utilizing the Existential Approach in
      heart failure patients when compared to a control group of patients who are waiting for the
      same group treatment. This comparison will be achieved by measuring changes in the variables
      studied namely, the levels of psychological distress and levels of psycho-social adjustment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Among all medical conditions, patients with heart failure report significantly poorer quality
      of life than do the other patients (1). The existing literature describes a wide range of
      negative emotions common among patients with heart failure; these include everything from
      depression, anxiety, submission and helplessness to a profound sense of &quot;discord and
      brokenness.&quot; The prevalence of depression, ranging from 11% to 25% among heart disease
      outpatients and 35% to 70% among those who are hospitalized (2). By comparison, the overall
      percentage of the population suffering from depression is about 6.6%. Psychological
      depression appears to be an important predictor of rehospitalization among persons who have
      been admitted with coronary artery disease (3). In addition, depression in patients with
      heart failure was found to be associated with the course of the disease and its prognosis.
      For example, it was found that in patients with heart failure, a diagnosis of Major
      Depression was correlated with a higher rate of mortality (4), and depressive symptoms
      predicted short-term worsening of heart failure symptoms (5). The reduction in quality of
      life that was also found to be common in patients with heart failure is also a prognostic
      factor for repeated hospitalizations and death (6).

      The high prevalence of distress among the population of patients with heart failure, along
      with the broad impact on the patient's quality of life, requires attention to detail and the
      implementation of interventions aimed at reducing levels of distress. Very few studies
      describe interventions aimed at alleviating distress in patients with heart failure.
      Cognitive Behavioral Therapy is reported to improve both the functional and emotional levels
      of these patients, resulting in the relief of their symptoms of depression. Using relaxation,
      Bio-Feedback devices have also achieved a reduction in depression of heart failure patients.
      Research testing the efficacy of psychological treatment using the interpersonal approach now
      is being performed; it is funded by the U.S. NIMH and is, at present, in the initial
      recruitment stages (National Institute of Mental Health, 2010). Studies examining the
      beneficial effects of group therapy are few in number and most of them utilize a Cognitive
      Behavioral approach. This therapeutic orientation has been found to be effective when the
      disease is moderate or the prognosis is favorable. However, outcomes tend to differ greatly
      when it comes to patients in advanced stages of the condition. These patients are also
      confronted with fundamental aspects of their own mortality. A large body of literature about
      psychological interventions for these patients exists. Many of these interventions are based
      on an Existential Approach aimed at facilitating responses to the unique distress of patients
      in an advanced stage of the disease (7).

      This study examines the contribution of a group therapy program based on the Existential
      Approach aimed at reducing distress in patients with heart failure.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>August 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptoms of Emotional Distress</measure>
    <time_frame>an expected average of 7 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Symptoms of Emotional Distress: The BSI questionnaire (The Brief Symptom Inventory), measuring levels of depression, anxiety and somatization of the subject, will be used.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patients' Psychosocial adjustment</measure>
    <time_frame>an expected average of 7 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Patients' Psychosocial adjustment: The PAIS-SR questionnaire (Psychological Adjustment to Illness Scale-Self Report), will be used. This questionnaire reflects the patient's adjustment in such areas as employment and leisure activities.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Congestive Heart Failure (CHF)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Congestive Heart Failure Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>40 patients diagnosed with heart failure at levels III and IV, according to the classification of the NYHA will participate in the research. The researchers will randomly allocate the patients to the treatment group or the control group. The subjects in the treatment group will participate in Existential Group Therapy, while the subjects in the control group will not participate in the treatment until after the completion of the study. Psychological data will be collected in the form of a self-reported questionnaire completed by all participants prior to the beginning of the research and again upon completion of the final group session.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Existential Group Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>The treatment will be given in two groups of eight to ten participants each one and will consist of one hour weekly sessions over a period of seven weeks. Dividing the subjects into small groups allows reference to all members of the group. The group facilitators will be two psychologists who work in co therapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Congestive Heart Failure Patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>group therapy</other_name>
    <other_name>Supportive-Expressive Group Therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        patients diagnosed with heart failure disorder at levels III and IV
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of heart failure at levels III and IV, according to the
             classification of the NYHA (New York Heart Association) for 3 months or more.

          -  Clinical diagnosis of LVEF less than 50% or were on diuretic therapy for more than
             three months with at least one previous hospitalization due to heart failure disease.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  uncertain prognosis for 12 months due to other conditions.

          -  acute coronary disease in recent months.

          -  existence of another life-threatening illness of the patient (such as active cancer,
             chronic kidney failure).

          -  severe neurological problem (Brain syndrome / orientation problem/ difficult
             peripheral neuropathy).

          -  severe mental illness (active psychosis / suicide risk / severe dementia).

          -  linguistic limitations (such as misunderstanding of the Hebrew language / stuttering /
             untreated audio impairment).

          -  a significant functional problem (such as unconsciousness / connection to respiration
             device / confined to a wheelchair or bed / severe walking disability / needs help with
             complete basic daily activities).

          -  objective limit that endangers liability for participation in the seven meetings (such
             as remote residential / tourist / convict / drug addict).

          -  subjects whose mother tongue is not Hebrew.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Morris Mosseri, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Cardiology, Meir Medical Center, Israel</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Morris Mosseri, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>972-9-7472587</phone>
    <email>Morris.Mosseri@clalit.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Noa Vilchinsky, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>: 972-3-531-8601</phone>
    <email>noav18@inter.net.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>: Department of Cardiology, Meir Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kefar Saba</city>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>: Morris : Mosseri, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>972-9-7472587</phone>
      <email>Morris.Mosseri@clalit.org.il</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Noa Vilchinsky, Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>972-3-531-8601</phone>
      <email>noav18@inter.net.il</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>: Morris Mosseri, : Professor</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Juenger J, Schellberg D, Kraemer S, Haunstetter A, Zugck C, Herzog W, Haass M. Health related quality of life in patients with congestive heart failure: comparison with other chronic diseases and relation to functional variables. Heart. 2002 Mar;87(3):235-41.</citation>
    <PMID>11847161</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>O'Connor CM, Joynt KE. Depression: are we ignoring an important comorbidity in heart failure? J Am Coll Cardiol. 2004 May 5;43(9):1550-2.</citation>
    <PMID>15120810</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Levine JB, Covino NA, Slack WV, Safran C, Safran DB, Boro JE, Davis RB, Buchanan GM, Gervino EV. Psychological predictors of subsequent medical care among patients hospitalized with cardiac disease. J Cardiopulm Rehabil. 1996 Mar-Apr;16(2):109-16.</citation>
    <PMID>8681155</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jiang W, Alexander J, Christopher E, Kuchibhatla M, Gaulden LH, Cuffe MS, Blazing MA, Davenport C, Califf RM, Krishnan RR, O'Connor CM. Relationship of depression to increased risk of mortality and rehospitalization in patients with congestive heart failure. Arch Intern Med. 2001 Aug 13-27;161(15):1849-56.</citation>
    <PMID>11493126</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rumsfeld JS, Havranek E, Masoudi FA, Peterson ED, Jones P, Tooley JF, Krumholz HM, Spertus JA; Cardiovascular Outcomes Research Consortium. Depressive symptoms are the strongest predictors of short-term declines in health status in patients with heart failure. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2003 Nov 19;42(10):1811-7.</citation>
    <PMID>14642693</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Konstam V, Salem D, Pouleur H, Kostis J, Gorkin L, Shumaker S, Mottard I, Woods P, Konstam MA, Yusuf S. Baseline quality of life as a predictor of mortality and hospitalization in 5,025 patients with congestive heart failure. SOLVD Investigations. Studies of Left Ventricular Dysfunction Investigators. Am J Cardiol. 1996 Oct 15;78(8):890-5.</citation>
    <PMID>8888661</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Spiegel D, Classen C. Group therapy for cancer patients. A research-based handbook of psychosocial care. New York: Basic, 2000.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 2, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 10, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 11, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 27, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 27, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 30, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

