<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01410968</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>101498</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01410968</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Feasibility and Safety Study of Vaccination With Poly-ICLC and Peptide-pulsed Dendritic Cells in Patients With Metastatic, Locally Advanced, Unresectable, or Recurrent Pancreatic Adenocarcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Feasibility and Safety Study of Vaccination With Poly-ICLC and Peptide-pulsed Dendritic Cells in Patients With Metastatic, Locally Advanced, Unresectable, or Recurrent Pancreatic Adenocarcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Carolyn Britten</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Oncovir, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of South Carolina</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to provide a safety and feasibility basis for future studies
      addressing the hypothesis that subcutaneous vaccination with dendritic cells loaded with
      multiple antigenic epitopes expressed by pancreatic tumor in combination with systemic
      administration of Poly-ICLC (Hiltonol) will induce anti-tumor immunity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objectives

        1. Assess the safety of this treatment by evaluating the qualitative and quantitative
           toxicities in this group of patients.

        2. Determine the feasibility of generating dendritic cells and administering these cells as
           a vaccine to patients.

      Secondary Objectives

        1. Assess anti-tumor activity after vaccination, measured by change in tumor burden and
           overall survival.

        2. Assess immunological responses after vaccination (antigen-specific T cell cytokine
           production, antigen-specific T cell frequencies by tetramer analysis, and DTH reactions)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Any protocol deviations will be described and the protocol schedule will be re-assessed to improve feasibility of implementation if necessary. The proportion of patients successfully completing the protocol (i.e., without deviations) will be reported with a one-sided 90% confidence interval. If the observed feasibility rate is &gt;0.80, the lower limit will be no lower than 0.60.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>2 Years</time_frame>
    <description>All toxicities will be reported by type and grade and tabulated. To provide a safety characterization of the treatment regimen, it is important that common toxicities be observed in this phase of study for planning the next phase of research.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Graphical displays of tumor size (as a percentage of baseline) over time. A subject's best response (i.e., complete response, partial response, stable disease or progressive disease) will be reported. Time to disease progression from baseline for each patient will be reported. Time to death will be reported in the same manner. These results will be summarized using proportions with confidence intervals and Kaplan-Meier curves, although the confidence limits are expected to be wide based on the small sample size.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunological Responses</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Antigen-specific T cell frequencies, antigen-specific T cell cytokine production and DTH reactions will be assessed.
For T cell-based functional analysis, each measurement will be performed with the three peptides telomerase, CEA, and survivin. Transformation of the continuous outcomes will be logged. Post measurements will be normalized by the baseline value (i.e. we will subtract the baseline value from each of the post vaccination measurements after the log transformations). Each of these measures will be displayed graphically over time for each patient to observe modulations in these measures. If appropriate based on the distribution of values over time, linear longitudinal regression will be used to model the change in these outcomes over time. Appropriateness will be based on the consistency of trends across patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vaccination</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>vaccination with investigational Poly-ICLC &amp; peptide-pulsed dendritic cells</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>vacc. w/ Poly-ICLC &amp; peptide-pulsed dendritic cells</intervention_name>
    <description>Intradermal injection of 1x107 peptide-pulsed dendritic cells followed by intramuscular injection of 30 micrograms per kilogram Poly-ICLC on days 0, 14, 28 and 42. Additional dose of 30 micrograms per kilogram Poly-ICLC on days 3, 17, 31 and 45. Treatment given via one 56-day cycle. Leukapheresis performed at baseline for dendritic cell generation.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vaccination</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Eligibility Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of pancreatic
             adenocarcinoma that is metastatic, locally advanced, unresectable, or recurrent.
             Patients with endocrine or neuroendocrine tumors, lymphoma of the pancreas, or
             ampullary cancer are not eligible. If the histologic diagnosis is based on a
             metastatic site, the histology must be compatible with pancreatic cancer.

          -  Patient must not have clinically significant ascites.

          -  Patients must be HLA-A2 positivity by serological testing.

          -  Prior surgery is allowed provided at least 14 days has elapsed between surgery and
             registration. Prior radiation/chemo is allowed provided that at least 28 days have
             elapsed since the last treatment.

          -  One or more tumors measurable on CT scan per RECIST 1.1. (Eisenhauer)

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status &lt; 2.

          -  Age &gt; 18 years.

          -  Patient must have an expected life expectancy greater than 3 months.

          -  Signed, written IRB-approved informed consent.

          -  A negative pregnancy test (if female).

          -  Acceptable organ function:

          -  Bilirubin &lt; 3 times upper limit of normal (CTCAE Grade 2 baseline)

          -  AST (SGOT), ALT (SGPT) &lt; 3 x ULN (CTCAE Grade 1 baseline)

          -  Serum creatinine &lt; 1.5 XULN (CTCAE Grade 1 baseline)

          -  Acceptable hematologic status:

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1000 cells/mm3,

          -  Platelet count &gt; 75,000 (plt/mm3), (CTCAE Grade 1 baseline)

          -  Hemoglobin &gt; 9 g/dL.

          -  Urinalysis: No clinically significant abnormalities.

          -  PT and PTT &lt; 1.5 X ULN after correction of nutritional deficiencies that may
             contribute to prolonged PT/PTT.

          -  No evidence of clinically significant, uncontrolled cardiovascular, endocrine, or
             infectious disease.

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Patients must not have any serious uncontrolled acute or chronic medical condition
             that would interfere with this treatment. An example would be an active acute or
             chronic infection requiring antibiotics

          -  Patients must not have significant ongoing cardiac problems, myocardial infarction
             within the last six months, uncontrolled hypertension, unstable angina, uncontrolled
             arrhythmia or congestive heart failure.

          -  Patients with known brain metastases are not eligible. However, brain-imaging studies
             are not required for eligibility if the patient has no neurologic signs or symptoms.
             If brain-imaging studies are performed, they must be negative for disease.

          -  Patients must have no plans to receive concurrent chemotherapy, hormonal therapy,
             radiotherapy, immunotherapy or any other type of therapy for treatment of cancer while
             on this protocol treatment.

          -  Due to the undetermined effect of this treatment regimen in patients with HIV-1
             infection and the potential for serious interaction with anti-HIV medications,
             patients known to be infected with HIV are not eligible for this study.

          -  Due to the possibility of harm to a fetus or nursing infant from this treatment
             regimen, patients must not be pregnant or nursing. Women and men of reproductive
             potential must have agreed to use an effective contraceptive method.

          -  No other prior malignancy is allowed except for the following: adequately treated
             basal cell or squamous cell skin cancer, in situ cervical cancer, adequately treated
             Stage I or II cancer from which the patient is currently in complete remission, or any
             other cancer from which the patient has been disease free for five years.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of South Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29425</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 4, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 4, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 5, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 8, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 8, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 9, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of South Carolina</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carolyn Britten</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief, Hematology/Oncology Division</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Poly ICLC</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Poly I-C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboxymethylcellulose Sodium</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

