<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01419522</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>110203</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11-CC-0203</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01419522</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treadmill Training at Constant or Different Speeds for People With Traumatic Brain Injury</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Time Varying Walking Velocity in Body-Weight Supported Treadmill Training</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Many people who have had a traumatic brain injury have difficulty walking. Training on a
      treadmill is often used to help people with walking difficulties. Supporting a person s body
      weight with a harness while using the treadmill can help improve walking skills in people
      with brain injury. Varying the rate at which people walk on the treadmill may also help more
      than walking at a constant rate. Treadmill training with body weight support or walking at
      different speeds may improve walking skills in people who have had a traumatic brain injury.
      More research is needed to see if one method is better than the other.

      Objectives:

      - To compare the effects of two types of treadmill training in people who have had a
      traumatic brain injury.

      Eligibility:

      - People at least 18 years of age who have had a mild or moderate traumatic brain injury at
      least 6 months ago and have mild or moderate walking difficulty.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a medical history and physical exam. They will also
           take a basic walking test (not on a treadmill).

        -  Participants will be divided into two groups. The first group will have treadmill
           training at a constant speed. The second group will have treadmill training at different
           speeds. All participants will wear a support harness while walking on the treadmill.

        -  At the first training visit, participants will have a gait assessment with different
           tests of walking. Then they will have a treadmill walking session.

        -  After the first visit, participants will return twice a week for 6 weeks for treadmill
           training sessions (visits 3 through 12). They will also have grip strength and walking
           tests.

        -  At the end of 6 weeks, participants will have a final treadmill training session, and
           will have a gait assessment exactly like the one in the first training visit.

        -  At 6 months after the final session, participants will have a followup visit with a
           final gait assessment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives: To test the effectiveness of using time varying walking velocity in Body-Weight
      Supported Treadmill Training (BWSTT) as compared to using constant velocity in subjects with
      Traumatic Brain Injury (TBI). We hypothesize that using time varying velocity will result in
      a greater improvement in ambulatory function.

      Study Population: 30 adult subjects with a clinical diagnosis of non-penetrating TBI and with
      functional deficits in gait will be enrolled. Subjects will be recruited from NIH, affiliated
      hospitals/clinics, and in the community.

      Design: This pilot study will use an instrumented treadmill (Bertec Co., Columbus, Ohio) and
      a force controlled harness system called ZeroG (Aretech LLC, Ashburn, Virginia). Subjects
      will be randomly assigned to one of two groups (12 subjects per group): the first group will
      receive BWSTT at a constant velocity (also known as standard treadmill training); and the
      second group will receive BWSTT at randomized time varying velocity. BWSTT at time varying
      velocity consists of two components: 1) subjects passively adjusting their walking speed to
      the continuously changing speed of the treadmill; and 2) subjects actively changing their
      walking speed by following the instructed walking speed displayed on a monitor screen while
      the treadmill is automatically adjusted to the subjects speed. Each group will receive 8 gait
      training sessions (30 minutes per session, twice per week) for four weeks. Gait performance
      will be tested before (pre-test) and after (post-test) the 8 session gait training program.

      Outcome Measures: The primary outcome measures are parameters representing gait performance:
      maximum walking speed, self-selected walking speed, cadence, stride length, percentage of
      swing, stance and double stance periods, gait symmetry, Time Up and Go (TUG), and Dynamic
      Gait Index (DGI) scores. The secondary outcome measure is physical and cognitive effort
      exerted during the training session as evaluated by grip-strength test and LNS (Letter-Number
      Sequencing) test.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 29, 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 6, 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 6, 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome measures are parameters representing gait performance such as maximum/self-selected walking speed, cadence, stride length, Time Up and Go test scores and Dynamic Gait Index scores.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The secondary outcome measures are physical and cognitive effort exerted during the training. Physical effort will be measured by grip strength. Cognitive effort will be estimated by Letter Number Sequence test.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <condition>Walking Impairment</condition>
  <condition>Gait Training</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gait Training Method</intervention_name>
    <description>Treadmill training at constant velocity</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects eligible for participation in this research study must meet the following
        inclusion criteria:

        Diagnosis of non-penetrating TBI, specifically functionally mild to moderate TBI (those
        individuals who demonstrate the ability or capacity to ambulate)

        Injury occurred at least 6 months prior to enrollment

        Age of 18 or older

        Able to stand and walk on a treadmill for 30 minutes (with some breaks in the middle)

        Have mild or moderate functional gait impairment (score 1 or 2 in the first two tests in
        DGI: 1. Gait Level Surface test and 2. Change in Gait Speed test)

        Able to provide informed consent

        Able to read 3 inch by 3 inch letters in the monitor located at 1 meter distance from the
        treadmill without affecting gait patterns on the treadmill.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Subjects are not eligible for participation in this research study if any of the following
        conditions exist:

        Taking medications that affect motor function such as baclofen, levodopa, benzodiazepams,
        tizanadine, or dantrolene sodium.

        Had surgery to either lower limb within the last year or requires surgery during the period
        of the study

        Had botulinum toxin injections in lower limbs within the last 4 months or willing to forego
        botulinum toxins in lower limbs for the duration of the study

        Are currently receiving any type of gait training or similar intervention outside of the
        study or unwilling to forego initiation of such an intervention during the period of this
        study

        Presence of severe pain in the lower limbs (VAS 5 or above)

        Medical or psychological instability such that the clinician judges that the subject is
        unsafe to enroll in the study or the subject cannot answer questions or follow instructions
        to fulfill the study

        Any known cardiac or pulmonary disease

        A woman with pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Diane L Damiano, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campbell M, Parry A. Balance disorder and traumatic brain injury: preliminary findings of a multi-factorial observational study. Brain Inj. 2005 Dec;19(13):1095-104.</citation>
    <PMID>16286323</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Katz-Leurer M, Rotem H, Lewitus H, Keren O, Meyer S. Relationship between balance abilities and gait characteristics in children with post-traumatic brain injury. Brain Inj. 2008 Feb;22(2):153-9. doi: 10.1080/02699050801895399.</citation>
    <PMID>18240044</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kerrigan DC, Bang MS, Burke DT. An algorithm to assess stiff-legged gait in traumatic brain injury. J Head Trauma Rehabil. 1999 Apr;14(2):136-45.</citation>
    <PMID>10191372</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 6, 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 17, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 17, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 18, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Traumatic Brain Injury</keyword>
  <keyword>Walking Impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>Gait Training</keyword>
  <keyword>TBI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

