<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01418001</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11-104</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01418001</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gemcitabine and Docetaxel in Combination With Pazopanib (Gem/Doce/Pzb) for the Neoadjuvant Treatment of Soft Tissue Sarcoma (STS)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase IB/II Study of Gemcitabine and Docetaxel in Combination With Pazopanib (Gem/Doce/Pzb) for the Neoadjuvant Treatment of Soft Tissue Sarcoma (STS)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Comprehensive Cancer Network</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to see the effects, good and/or bad, of the drug combination of
      gemcitabine, docetaxel and pazopanib on sarcoma. This is a phase Ib-phase II clinical trial.
      The goal of a phase Ib part of the clinical trial is to confirm a dose of the drugs that is
      safe. The investigators determine this by closely checking for side effects that the patient
      may experience.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Lack of accrual
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>August 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Objective Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Every 6 weeks up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Overall objective response measured using Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) version 1.1.Complete Response (CR): Disappearance of all target lesions. Any pathological lymph nodes (whether target or non-target) must have reduction in short axis to &lt;10 mm.
Partial Response (PR): At least a 30% decrease in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the baseline sum diameters.
Progressive Disease (PD): At least a 20% increase in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the smallest sum on study (this includes the baseline sum if that is the smallest on study). In addition to the relative increase of 20%, the sum must also demonstrate an absolute increase of at least 5 mm. (Note: the appearance of one or more new lesions is also considered progressions).
Stable Disease (SD): Neither sufficient shrinkage to qualify for PR nor sufficient increase to qualify for PD, taking as reference the smallest sum diameters while on study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathologic Response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>will be assessed by both MRI and by pathologic review after surgery. An estimate of each response rate and the 95% CI will be provided</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Leiomyosarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Peripheral Nerve Sheath Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Malignant Fibrous</condition>
  <condition>Histiocytoma/Undifferentiated Pleomorphic Sarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pazopanib 400 mg QD - Gemcitabine and Docetaxel in Combination</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This will be a multicenter single arm phase IB/II trial to evaluate the clinical safety and efficacy of gemcitabine/docetaxel and pazopanib in the neoadjuvant treatment of soft tissue sarcoma.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pazopanib 400 mg QD - Gemcitabine and Docetaxel in Combination</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients who meet the eligibility criteria above will be treated with the combination therapy of Gemcitabine, Docetaxel, and Pazopanib for two cycles and subsequently re-evaluated for treatment effect. If no progression of the tumor is seen, patients will continue with two more cycles of treatment (total four cycles). Those patients who have progression of disease will proceed directly to surgical resection.
Following completion of neoadjuvant treatment, all patients will have definitive surgical resection. Following recovery from surgery, patients will proceed with adjuvant radiation therapy. Patients will then be followed for 2 years or until January 1st 2015, whichever comes first .</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pazopanib 400 mg QD - Gemcitabine and Docetaxel in Combination</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed extremity only, ≥8 cm,
             high grade STS (MPNST, MFH/UPS, LMS) at MSKCC or locally for participating sites.

          -  Subjects must have only localized disease that is potentially amenable to definitive
             resection.

          -  The first 15 MSKCC patients on the Phase II portion of the protocol must undergo
             either an open incisional or core tumor biopsy prior to the initiation of therapy.

          -  Patients must have measurable disease by RECIST 1.1, defined as at least one lesion
             that can be accurately measured in at least one dimension (longest diameter to be
             recorded) as &gt;20 mm with conventional techniques or as &gt;10 mm with spiral CT scan. See
             Section 10 for the evaluation of measurable disease.

          -  Age &gt;18 years. ECOG performance status 0 or 1.

          -  Patients must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below (ULN indicates
             institutional upper limit of normal): Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1.5 X 109/L
             Hemoglobin ≥9 g/dL (5.6 mmol/L) Platelets ≥100 X 109/L International normalized ratio
             (INR) ≤1.2 X ULN Activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT)≤1.2 X ULN Total
             bilirubin ≤1.5 X ULN Alanine amino, transferase (ALT) and Aspartate aminotransferase
             (AST) ≤2.5 X ULN Serum creatinine ≤1.5 mg/dL (133 μmol/L) Or, if serum creatinine,
             &gt;1.5 mg/dL: Calculated creatinine clearance (ClCR)

             ≥30 mL/min to ≥50 mL/min Urine Protein to Creatinine Ratio (UPC; appropriate appendix)
             &lt;1 Or, 24-hour urine protein &lt;1g

          -  Patients must not have current evidence of another malignancy.

          -  Pazopanib, gemcitabine and docetaxel all carry category D (positive evidence of risk)
             pregnancy status. For this reason women of child-bearing potential and men must agree
             to use adequate contraception (hormonal or barrier method of birth control;
             abstinence) during therapy and for at least 8 weeks after completion of therapy and
             have pregnancy testing prior to study entry and after two cycles of treatment. Should
             a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while participating in this study,
             she must inform her treating physician immediately.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had major surgery 4 weeks prior to entering the study, or those who
             have not recovered from adverse events to ≤ NCI CTC AE Grade 1, associated with
             surgery. Excluded from such considerations are surgical changes not expected to
             improve, e.g. removal of muscle tissue.

          -  Patients must not have had been treated previously with radiation, chemotherapy or
             other anti-cancer agent for the current disease.

          -  History of allergic reactions or hypersensitivity reactions attributed to compounds of
             similar chemical or biologic composition to pazopanib, gemcitabine, docetaxel or other
             agents used in the study.

          -  Patients with a contraindication to MRIs.

          -  Patients who required concomitant treatment with medications that are known to be
             inhibitors or strong inducers of isoenzyme CYP3A4, CYP2C8, and CYP2D6 unless the drugs
             are medically necessary and no substitutes are available. If there are no acceptable
             substitutes, special precautions should be taken in these patients. Similarly,
             co-administration with CYP3A inhibitors (e.g. Ergot derivatives, Neuroleptics,
             Antiarrhythmics, Immune modulators and miscellaneous agents such quetiapine,
             risperidone, clozapine, atomoxetine, and inducers (e.g. Glucocorticoids,
             Anticonvulsants, HIV antivirals, Antibiotics, miscellaneous agents such as St. John's
             Wort, modafinil, pioglitazone, troglitazone, simvastatin, should also be avoided if
             possible, or otherwise subject to caution (e.g. increased frequency of safety
             monitoring). Strong CYP3A4 inhibitors are PROHIBITED within 14 days prior to the first
             dose of pazopanib including: Antibiotics, HIV protease inhibitors, Antifungals and
             Antidepressants

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, including HIV, active hepatitis B or C, symptomatic congestive heart
             failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, poorly controlled diabetes or
             psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with study
             requirements. Hepatitis B and C will be screened for in all patients prior to
             initiating treatment via hepatitis B serologic markers, that is, HBsAg, HBs Ab, HBc Ab
             and Hep C Antibody. If patients have positive serologic markers, viral load markers
             (HBV-DNA and Hepatitis C RNA-PCR) will be performed during screening to confirm
             disease as well as screening for hepatitis C via quantitative RNA-PCR.

          -  Pregnant women and women who are breast-feeding.

          -  HIV -positive patients on combination antiretroviral therapy due to the potential for
             pharmacokinetic interactions with pazopanib.

          -  Patients with significant respiratory compromise or an active and unexplained
             pneumonitis given that these patients would have an increased risk of pneumonitis from
             gemcitabine, and would also confuse the evaluation of pneumonitis on the trial

          -  Clinically significant gastrointestinal abnormalities that may increase the risk for
             gastrointestinal bleeding including, but not limited to:

        Active peptic ulcer disease

          -  Inflammatory bowel disease (e.g. ulcerative colitis, Crohn's disease), or other
             gastrointestinal conditions with increased risk of perforation

          -  History of abdominal fistula, gastrointestinal perforation, or intra-abdominal

          -  abscess within 28 days prior to beginning study treatment Active diarrhea of any grade

          -  Clinically significant gastrointestinal abnormalities that may affect absorption of
             investigational product including, but not limited to:

          -  Malabsorption syndrome

          -  Major resection of the stomach or small bowel

          -  History of any one or more of the following cardiovascular conditions within the past
             6 months:

        Cardiac angioplasty or stenting Myocardial infarction Unstable angina Coronary artery
        bypass graft surgery Symptomatic peripheral vascular disease

          -  History of cerebrovascular accident including transient ischemic attack (TIA),
             pulmonary embolism or untreated deep venous thrombosis (DVT) within the past 6 months.

          -  Note: Subjects with recent DVT who have been treated with therapeutic anticoagulating
             agents for at least 6 weeks are eligible

          -  Corrected QT interval (QTc) ≥ 450 msecs using Bazett's formula (append formula); for
             subjects with bundle branch block (BBB), QTc ≥480 msecs using Bazett's formula.)

          -  Poorly controlled hypertension, defined as systolic blood pressure (SBP) of ≥140 mmHg
             or diastolic blood pressure (DBP) of ≥ 90mmHg.

          -  Note: Initiation or adjustment of antihypertensive medication(s) is permitted prior to
             study entry.

        History of Class III or IV congestive heart failure, as defined by the New York Heart
        Association Classification of Congestive Heart Failure [see Appendix D for description]

          -  Evidence of active bleeding or bleeding diathesis

          -  Administration of any non-oncologic investigational drug within 30 days or 5 half
             lives whichever is longer prior to receiving the first dose of study treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William Tap, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Evanston</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60208</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org/mskcc/html/44.cfm</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 15, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 15, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 16, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>January 19, 2016</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>January 19, 2016</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">February 17, 2016</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GEMCITABINE</keyword>
  <keyword>GW786034 (PAZOPANIB)</keyword>
  <keyword>TAXOTERE (DOCETAXEL)</keyword>
  <keyword>11-104</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leiomyosarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nerve Sheath Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurofibroma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Histiocytoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurilemmoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neurofibrosarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Histiocytoma, Malignant Fibrous</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gemcitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Pazopanib 400 mg QD</title>
          <description>Pazopanib 400 mg QD - Gemcitabine and Docetaxel in Combination with Pazopanib</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="5"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="5"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Level 1: Pazopanib 400 mg QD Gemcitabine and Docetaxel in Com</title>
          <description>Level 1: Pazopanib 400 mg QD - Gemcitabine and Docetaxel in Combination with Pazopanib</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="5"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Overall Objective Response</title>
        <description>Overall objective response measured using Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) version 1.1.Complete Response (CR): Disappearance of all target lesions. Any pathological lymph nodes (whether target or non-target) must have reduction in short axis to &lt;10 mm.
Partial Response (PR): At least a 30% decrease in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the baseline sum diameters.
Progressive Disease (PD): At least a 20% increase in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the smallest sum on study (this includes the baseline sum if that is the smallest on study). In addition to the relative increase of 20%, the sum must also demonstrate an absolute increase of at least 5 mm. (Note: the appearance of one or more new lesions is also considered progressions).
Stable Disease (SD): Neither sufficient shrinkage to qualify for PR nor sufficient increase to qualify for PD, taking as reference the smallest sum diameters while on study.</description>
        <time_frame>Every 6 weeks up to 2 years</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Level 1: Pazopanib 400 mg QD</title>
            <description>Level 1: Pazopanib 400 mg QD - Gemcitabine and Docetaxel in Combination with Pazopanib</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Overall Objective Response</title>
          <description>Overall objective response measured using Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) version 1.1.Complete Response (CR): Disappearance of all target lesions. Any pathological lymph nodes (whether target or non-target) must have reduction in short axis to &lt;10 mm.
Partial Response (PR): At least a 30% decrease in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the baseline sum diameters.
Progressive Disease (PD): At least a 20% increase in the sum of the diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the smallest sum on study (this includes the baseline sum if that is the smallest on study). In addition to the relative increase of 20%, the sum must also demonstrate an absolute increase of at least 5 mm. (Note: the appearance of one or more new lesions is also considered progressions).
Stable Disease (SD): Neither sufficient shrinkage to qualify for PR nor sufficient increase to qualify for PD, taking as reference the smallest sum diameters while on study.</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="5"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Complete Response (CR)</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Stable Disease (SD)</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Pathologic Response</title>
        <description>will be assessed by both MRI and by pathologic review after surgery. An estimate of each response rate and the 95% CI will be provided</description>
        <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
        <population>No data is available because data was not collected due to lack of accrual.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Pazopanib 400 mg QD</title>
            <description>Pazopanib 400 mg QD - Gemcitabine and Docetaxel in Combination with Pazopanib</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Pathologic Response</title>
          <description>will be assessed by both MRI and by pathologic review after surgery. An estimate of each response rate and the 95% CI will be provided</description>
          <population>No data is available because data was not collected due to lack of accrual.</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Level 1: Pazopanib 400 mg QD</title>
          <description>Level 1: Pazopanib 400 mg QD - Gemcitabine and Docetaxel in Combination with Pazopanib</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_vocab>CTC-4.0</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Alanine aminotransferase increased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Fatigue</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Wound infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>CTC-4.0</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Alanine aminotransferase increased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Anemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Aspartate aminotransferase increased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Lymphocyte count decreased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Platelet count decreased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Cardiac disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypertension</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Diarrhea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nausea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Fatigue</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hoarseness</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Mucositis oral</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Metabolism and nutrition disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hyperglycemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypertriglyceridemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypoalbuminemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypocalcemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hyponatremia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="5"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. William Tap</name_or_title>
      <organization>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</organization>
      <phone>646-888-4163</phone>
      <email>tapw@mskcc.org</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

