<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01414621</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14547</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01414621</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Expression of Angiogenic Factors in Myocardial Tissue</brief_title>
  <official_title>IRB #14547: Expression of Angiogenic Factors in Myocardial Tissue in Diabetic and Non-diabetic Patients Undergoing Coronary Bypass Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Virginia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Virginia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate whether angiogenesis is decreased in diabetic
      patients with coronary artery disease compared to non-diabetics with coronary artery disease.
      The protein expression of angiogenic factors will be examined in atrial tissue prior to
      initiation of cardiopulmonary bypass in patients undergoing coronary bypass surgery.

      The goal of this project is to evaluate the tissue levels of HIF-1, VEGF and angiostatin in
      diabetic and non-diabetic patients coming for on-pump coronary artery bypass graft (CABG).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Coronary artery disease and its complications are the leading cause of death in the western
      world. Diabetes mellitus (DM) is one of the major risk factors to develop coronary artery
      disease, myocardial infarction and post-infarction complication1-3. Furthermore, mortality
      from myocardial infarction is almost doubled in diabetic patients compared to non-diabetics4.
      Despite significant amount of research, the basis for these differences in outcome still
      remains unclear. The survival of myocardial tissue subjected to ischemia can be increased by
      the ability to promote growth of new blood vessels into ischemic areas, thus limiting regions
      of impairment and ultimately preserving myocardial function. Hypoxia inducible factor (HIF)
      -1 is a transcription factor that promotes the expression of several genes that confer
      protection against hypoxia/ischemia through angiogenesis, erythropoiesis, vasodilation, and
      altered glucose metabolism5,6. Our hypothesis is that angiogenesis may be impaired in
      diabetes mainly via decreased protein expression and activation of HIF-1 and its main
      downstream target vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), as well as the inhibitor
      angiogenesis factor, angiostatin7, in the heart. Therefore the purpose of this study is to
      examine whether the angiogenic process during coronary ischemia is influenced by diabetes. To
      address these questions, HIF-1, VEGF and angiostatin protein expression will be evaluated in
      atrial tissue obtained from patients with and without diabetes who will undergo coronary
      bypass surgery. In addition comparison between emergency and elective procedure will be
      performed in regard to HIF-1 and VEGF protein levels and correlation with chronic statin
      therapy will be performed.

      During the cannulation process, prior to initiation of cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB) during
      heart surgery, a small piece of the right atrium is cut in order to insert a venous cannula
      into that chamber. The investigators intend to use this piece of tissue (that is routinely
      wasted) in our protein and histological analyses.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>tissue levels of HIF-1, VEGF and angiostatin</measure>
    <time_frame>initiation of CPB/ day 1</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will evaluate tissue levels of HIF-1, VEGF and angiostatin in diabetic and non-diabetic patients coming for on-pump CABG.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CABG patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>atrial tissue samples from CABG patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>atrial tissue sample</intervention_name>
    <description>atrial tissue sample from CABG patient</description>
    <arm_group_label>CABG patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      During the cannulation process before the initiation of CPB(cardiopulmonary bypass) a small
      piece of right atrial tissue is cut in order to insert venous drainage cannula to the right
      atrium. This small piece of tissue is discarded and is not sent for pathology.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        diabetic &amp; non-diabetic CABG patients
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. on-pump CABG

          2. 18 years of age &amp; older

          3. informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. active malignancy

          2. severe lung disease (requiring home O2 therapy)

          3. severe anemia&lt;8g/dl

          4. patient with moderate or severe renal dysfunction

          5. off- pump CABG
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jacob Raphael, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UVA Anesthesiology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Virginia Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlottesville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22908</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aguilar D, Solomon SD, Køber L, Rouleau JL, Skali H, McMurray JJ, Francis GS, Henis M, O'Connor CM, Diaz R, Belenkov YN, Varshavsky S, Leimberger JD, Velazquez EJ, Califf RM, Pfeffer MA. Newly diagnosed and previously known diabetes mellitus and 1-year outcomes of acute myocardial infarction: the VALsartan In Acute myocardial iNfarcTion (VALIANT) trial. Circulation. 2004 Sep 21;110(12):1572-8. Epub 2004 Sep 13.</citation>
    <PMID>15364810</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zairis MN, Lyras AG, Makrygiannis SS, Psarogianni PK, Adamopoulou EN, Handanis SM, Papantonakos A, Argyrakis SK, Prekates AA, Foussas SG. Type 2 diabetes and intravenous thrombolysis outcome in the setting of ST elevation myocardial infarction. Diabetes Care. 2004 Apr;27(4):967-71.</citation>
    <PMID>15047657</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Donahoe SM, Stewart GC, McCabe CH, Mohanavelu S, Murphy SA, Cannon CP, Antman EM. Diabetes and mortality following acute coronary syndromes. JAMA. 2007 Aug 15;298(7):765-75.</citation>
    <PMID>17699010</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abbott RD, Donahue RP, Kannel WB, Wilson PW. The impact of diabetes on survival following myocardial infarction in men vs women. The Framingham Study. JAMA. 1988 Dec 16;260(23):3456-60. Erratum in: JAMA 1989 Apr 7;261(13):1884.</citation>
    <PMID>2974889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Semenza GL. Hypoxia-inducible factor 1 and the molecular physiology of oxygen homeostasis. J Lab Clin Med. 1998 Mar;131(3):207-14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9523843</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Semenza GL, Roth PH, Fang HM, Wang GL. Transcriptional regulation of genes encoding glycolytic enzymes by hypoxia-inducible factor 1. J Biol Chem. 1994 Sep 23;269(38):23757-63.</citation>
    <PMID>8089148</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weihrauch D, Lohr NL, Mraovic B, Ludwig LM, Chilian WM, Pagel PS, Warltier DC, Kersten JR. Chronic hyperglycemia attenuates coronary collateral development and impairs proliferative properties of myocardial interstitial fluid by production of angiostatin. Circulation. 2004 May 18;109(19):2343-8. Epub 2004 May 10.</citation>
    <PMID>15136506</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 10, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 11, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 7, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 7, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 8, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Virginia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jacob Raphael</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Attending Anesthesiologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CABG</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Angiogenesis Inducing Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

