<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01413399</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MeckHypo2011</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01413399</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot Study of Intra-arrest Therapeutic Hypothermia in Patients Suffering Non-Traumatic Out of Hospital Cardiac Arrest</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of Intra-arrest Therapeutic Hypothermia in Patients Suffering Non-Traumatic Out of Hospital Cardiac Arrest</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Carolinas Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Carolinas Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study will be to assess the frequency of return of spontaneous
      circulation (ROSC), survival to admission, survival to discharge from the hospital, and
      neurologic function at time of discharge from the hospital among patients experiencing out of
      hospital cardiac arrest randomized to receive either intra-arrest induction of therapeutic
      hypothermia (IATH) or post-arrest therapeutic hypothermia (TH).

      Specific aims

        1. Develop and test methodologies for randomizing out-of-hospital cardiac arrest (OOHCA)
           patients to receive one of two therapeutic hypothermia treatments in the prehospital
           environment.

        2. Randomize patients experiencing OOHCA to receive either IATH or post-arrest TH and
           assess the frequency of ROSC, survival to admission, survival to discharge, and
           neurologic function.

        3. Estimate the most efficacious volume of chilled saline administered during the intra
           arrest period.

        4. Identify barriers and strategies for the successful implementation of this project as a
           multicenter randomized trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Therapeutic hypothermia improves mortality and functional neurologic outcomes in patients
      resuscitated from pulseless ventricular tachycardia and fibrillation (VT/VF), with several
      studies validating the safety of prehospital induction following successful (return of
      spontaneous circulation) ROSC by the rapid infusion of 2 liters of 4ยบC intravenous fluids.
      However, the optimal timing for inducing hypothermia remains uncertain. Early studies
      demonstrated the efficacy of therapeutic hypothermia despite delays of 4 to 8 hours from the
      time of ROSC to the initiation of cooling. The post-resuscitation reperfusion injury evolves
      quickly and was thought to be best attenuated by hypothermia induction immediately following
      return of spontaneous circulation (ROSC). This was supported by animal data which
      demonstrated that improved neurologic outcome was associated with reduced time to goal
      temperature following ROSC. More recently this hypothesis has been called into question by 2
      clinical trials which suggested that time to initiation of cooling was not associated with
      improved neurologic outcome at discharge.

      There may be another benefit to early therapeutic cooling. Animal data suggest that
      intra-arrest induction of therapeutic hypothermia (IATH) improves rates of ROSC from cardiac
      arrest. This is corroborated by a report describing an impressively high ROSC rate of 60.9%
      among patients receiving IATH. This was a higher frequency of ROSC than reported in similar
      patient groups. It has been demonstrated that mild hypothermia exerts a stabilizing effect on
      the myocardium, decreasing the rate of refibrillation following ROSC. Mild hypothermia has
      also been shown to prolong ventricular refractoriness and repolarization, possibly
      facilitating electrical defibrillation by slowing repolarization ion currents.

      Recently we conducted a retrospective observational study that demonstrated an association
      between the administration of IATH and ROSC.22 We found that the likelihood of ROSC with IATH
      was 2.4 (95% CI 1.41-4.24) time higher in the subset of patients who received &gt; 700ml of 4ยบ C
      normal saline compared to those who did not receive IATH. Our study lacked sufficient power
      to demonstrate a difference in survival to admission or discharge; however, we noted trends
      towards improved survival. Current intra-arrest treatments do not obtain ROSC rates greater
      than those seen in our study with IATH. These associations were noted in all rhythms,
      including asystole and pulseless electrical activity.

      Obtaining ROSC quickly with the resulting decrease in time spent in a low or no flow
      circulation would have obvious downstream effects on both hospital mortality and neurologic
      function, independent of the effect of mild hypothermia in the post-arrest inflammatory
      state. Surprisingly these associations were seen even with fluid volumes that were too low to
      change core body temperature suggesting that the benefits of therapeutic hypothermia on the
      myocardium may be possible even at relatively low fluid volumes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival to hospital discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>participants will be followed for the duration of hospital stay, an expected average of 5 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients who achieve prehospital return of spontaneous circulation</measure>
    <time_frame>Patients will be followed for the duration of their prehospital course of care expected to be an average of 1 hour</time_frame>
    <description>ROSC will be defined as return of sustained pulses during the prehospital cardiac arrest resuscitation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total volume of chilled saline infused</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at the end of prehospital care likely 30-90 min. after resuscitation was initiated</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">363</enrollment>
  <condition>Out-of-Hospital Cardiac Arrest</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intra-Arrest Therapeutic Hypothermia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Post-Arrest Therapeutic Hypothermia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>4 degree chilled saline</intervention_name>
    <description>4 degree chilled saline up to 2L in the prehospital setting</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intra-Arrest Therapeutic Hypothermia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Post-Arrest Therapeutic Hypothermia</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Cardiac arrest of presumed medical etiology in the out-of-hospital setting

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Traumatic Cardiac Arrests

          -  Cardiac Arrests Due to hemorrhage

          -  Cardiac arrests involving children or young adults

          -  Patients presumed to be pregnant

          -  Patients with a do not resuscitate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jonathan R Studnek, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Carolinas Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Carolinas Medical Center; Center for Prehospital MEdicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlotte</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garrett JS, Studnek JR, Blackwell T, Vandeventer S, Pearson DA, Heffner AC, Reades R. The association between intra-arrest therapeutic hypothermia and return of spontaneous circulation among individuals experiencing out of hospital cardiac arrest. Resuscitation. 2011 Jan;82(1):21-5. doi: 10.1016/j.resuscitation.2010.09.473. Epub 2010 Oct 30.</citation>
    <PMID>21036449</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 9, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 9, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 10, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 3, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 3, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 7, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Carolinas Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jonathan Studnek</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Prehospital Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Arrest</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypothermia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Out-of-Hospital Cardiac Arrest</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

