<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01412190</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>31GR0803</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01412190</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate Restylane Vital Light Using an Injector Device</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open, Randomized, Single-centre, Intra-individual Controlled, Explorative, Safety and Efficacy Study Comparing Restylane Vital White With no Treatment in the Face, Back of the Hands and décolletage, Using an Injector Device</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Q-Med AB</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Q-Med AB</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of Restylane Vital White
      administered with an injector device on aged skin in the face, hands and décolletage.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The objectives are to explore the safety and efficacy profile of Restylane Vital White
      administered with an injector device when one side of the face, one of the hands and one side
      of the décolletage is treated and the other side of the face, the other hand and the other
      side of the décolletage is left untreated. The face, the hands and the décolletage will be
      evaluated separately for both the efficacy and the safety parameters.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Elasticity</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4,8,12,20,28,36 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the change in elasticity from baseline for the treated and untreated side respectively.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>GEIS subject</measure>
    <time_frame>4,8,12,20,28,36 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate esthetic change from baseline as judged by the subjects using GEIS for the treated and untreated side respectively</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>GEIS blinded evaluator</measure>
    <time_frame>12,20,28,36 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate esthetic change from baseline as judged by the blinded evaluator using GEIS for the treated and untreated side respectively,</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Skin structure</measure>
    <time_frame>0,4,8,12,20,28,36 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the change in skin structure from baseline for the treated and untreated side respectively.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>0,12,20,28,36 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate subject satisfaction</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Best skin quality by blinded live evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>12,20,28,36 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate best skin quality of treated and untreated side judged by a blinded live evaluation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>0-36 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the safety of Restylane Vital White during the whole study by collecting Adverse Events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject diary</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks after each treatment</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the acute safety profile, i.e. treatment procedure reactions by direct questioning to subjects in a diary used daily for 2 weeks after each injection.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Aesthetics</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Untreated</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Restylane Vital Light</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Restylane Vital Light administered at 3 treatment sessions 4 weeks apart</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Restylane Vital Light</intervention_name>
    <description>Treatment of up to 4 ml for one side of the face, one hand and one side of the décolletage dispensed by 10ul doses 0.5-1 cm apart. 3 treatment sessions 4 weeks apart.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Restylane Vital Light</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Restylane skinbooster</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>One side of face, one hand and one side of the décolletage is left untreated as a control.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Untreated</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Signed informed consent obtained

          -  Female subjects 40-65 years of age, inclusive.

          -  Visible signs of skin aging in the face, hands and décolletage (e.g. reduced skin
             elasticity, reduced turgor, actinic elastosis, smaller and larger wrinkles) according
             to the Investigators opinion.

          -  Subjects must be cooperative and willing to comply with the instructions and
             procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Extensively photo damaged and aged skin according to the Investigators opinion.

          -  Active skin disease, inflammation or related conditions, such as infection, perioral
             dermatitis, seborrheic eczema and rosacea in the face, hands or décolletage.

          -  History of or active collagenosis (e.g. systemic lupus, erythematosis, Rheumatic
             arthritis, skin or systemic sclerosis)

          -  Previous hypersensitivity to hyaluronic acid.

          -  Concomitant therapy with thrombolytics or anticoagulants, or have taken inhibitors of
             platelet aggregation, within 2 weeks before the baseline visit.

          -  History of cancerous or pre-cancerous lesions in the face, hands and décolletage.

          -  Previous tissue augmenting therapy with non-permanent filler or treatment with
             botulinum toxin, aesthetic surgical therapy, laser treatment, mesotherapy, or any form
             of peeling in the face, hands or décolletage within 12 months prior to the baseline
             visit.

          -  Use of injectable revitalization preparations (e.g. Hyal System®, Restylane Vital)
             within 12 months prior to the baseline visit.

          -  Use of retinoic acid within 6 months prior to the baseline visit.

          -  Previous or concomitant treatment with chemotherapy, immunosuppressive agents or
             corticoids.

          -  History of treatment with permanent filling materials.

          -  Pregnancy or breast feeding woman or woman of childbearing potential not practicing
             adequate contraception.

          -  Participation in any other clinical study within 30 days prior to the baseline visit
             or plan to participate in another clinical study during this study period.

          -  Unrealistic expectation with regard to the esthetic results of the treatment.

          -  Planned or ongoing weight reduction program during the study.

          -  Known history of drug or alcohol abuse within 6 months prior to the baseline visit.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to one or more components of EMLA cream®.

          -  Any medical condition that in the opinion of the Investigator makes the subject
             unsuitable for inclusion (e.g. severe chronic disease, malignancy, bleeding disorder,
             skin diseases etc).

          -  Other condition preventing the subject to entering the study in the Investigator's
             opinion e.g. subjects anticipated to be unreliable, unable to return for the follow-up
             visits, not likely to avoid other prohibited treatments or procedures or incapable of
             understanding the information or instructions.

          -  Nicotine use during the study or stopped within 12 months before the baseline visit.

          -  Study staff or close relative of study staff (e.g. parents, children, siblings and
             spouse).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Martina Kerscher, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Hamburg, Prof. Dr. Martina Kerscher, Department Chemie, Martin-Luther-King Platz 6, 20146 Hamburg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Hamburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <zip>20146</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 30, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 8, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 9, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 22, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 22, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 27, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Skin rejuvenation</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hyaluronic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

