<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01419561</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>110220</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11-C-0220</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01419561</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>History of the KSHV Inflammatory Cytokine Syndrome (KICS)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Natural History Study of the KSHV Inflammatory Cytokine Syndrome (KICS) Incorporating Pilot Evaluation of KSHV Targeted Therapies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - KSHV inflammatory cytokine syndrome (KICS) is a newly recognized disease caused by Kaposi
      sarcoma-associated herpesvirus (KSHV). This virus can cause cancer. People with KICS can have
      severe symptoms. They include fever, weight loss, and fluid in the legs or abdomen. People
      with KICS may also be at risk of getting other cancers associated with KSHV. These cancers
      include Kaposi sarcoma and lymphoma. Because KICS is a newly identified disease, more
      information is needed on how the disease works and what can be done to treat it.

      Objectives:

      - To collect genetic and medical information from people with KSHV inflammatory cytokine
      syndrome.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age who have Kaposi sarcoma herpes virus and symptoms that
      resemble those caused by KICS.

      Design:

        -  Participants will have regular study visits. The schedule will be determined by the
           study researchers.

        -  Participants will provide a complete medical history and have a full physical exam.
           Blood and urine samples will be collected as well.

        -  People with KICS that requires treatment may get new experimental treatments. These
           treatments may include antiviral drugs and chemotherapy drugs, depending on the nature
           of the disease.

        -  Participants will have imaging studies, such as chest x-rays and computed tomography
           scans, to study the tumors.

        -  Bone marrow and lymph node biopsies may be done to collect tissue samples for study.

        -  Participants who have Kaposi sarcoma will have photographs taken of their lesions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND:

      KSHV inflammatory cytokine syndrome (KICS) is a newly recognized syndrome caused by Kaposi
      sarcoma-associated herpesvirus (KSHV). It is characterized by severe inflammatory symptoms
      including fevers, wasting, cytopenias, hypoalbuminemia, and hyponatremia, associated in some
      cases with lymphadenopathy or effusions, without pathological evidence of MCD. Patients with
      KICS exhibit elevated KSHV viral loads and cytokine dysregulation, with elevations of IL-6,
      IL-10, and a KSHV-encoded IL-6 homolog, viral IL-6.

      OBJECTIVE:

      The primary study objective is to enable intensive study and description of the natural
      history of KICS.

      ELIGIBILITY:

      Adults of any HIV status with:

        -  At least two symptoms, laboratory or radiographic abnormalities which are at least
           possibly attributable to KICS (including fever, fatigue, cachexia, edema, respiratory or
           gastrointestinal symptoms, hematologic cytopenias, hypoalbuminemia, hyponatremia,
           lymphadenopathy,organomegaly, effusions)

        -  C-reactive protein &gt;3mg/L.

        -  Evidence of KSHV infection or a risk exposure for KSHV infection

        -  No evidence of KSHV-associated multicentric Castleman disease

      Patients with these characteristics will be further evaluated to identify those whose
      clinical and laboratory features are consistent with the working KICS working case definition
      to be followed in the natural history phase of the study.

      DESIGN:

      This is a single center natural history cohort with an observation arm and two nested open
      label pilot treatment arms, and an accrual ceiling of 40 patients to the overall natural
      history arm. Natural history patients will undergo clinical, laboratory and correlative
      assessment every 3 months until sustained resolution. Patients with clinical and laboratory
      manifestations of KICS, elevated inflammatory markers and KSHV viral load will be eligible
      for therapy with high dose zidovudine/valganciclovir or, if they have intercurrent KS
      requiring cytotoxic therapy, rituximab/liposomal doxorubicin. Each treatment arm uses a two
      stage design, with interim analysis at 8 patients in each arm and potential accrual of 14 per
      arm.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 17, 2011</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of the natural history of KICS, including the spectrum of clinical, laboratory and radiographic abnormalities seen in affected patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>KSHV Inflammatory Cytokine Syndrome (KICS)</condition>
  <condition>KSHV</condition>
  <condition>HHV-8</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <description>Treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <description>Treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group C</arm_group_label>
    <description>Observation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Age greater than or equal to18 Years.

          -  Any HIV status.

          -  At least two manifestations drawn from at least two of the categories (clinical
             symptoms, laboratory abnormalities and radiographic abnormalities), which are at least
             possibly attributable to KICS and are not readily explicable from known medical
             conditions in the patient:

          -  Clinical symptoms (each at least grade 1 by CTCAE definitions)

          -  Fever (&gt;38 degrees C), chills or rigors

          -  Fatigue or lethargy

          -  Cachexia or edema

          -  Cough, dyspnea, airway hyperreactivity, or nasal inflammation

          -  Nausea, anorexia, abdominal pain or altered bowel habit

          -  Athralgia or myalgia

          -  Altered mental state

          -  Neuropathy with or without pain

          -  Laboratory abnormalities

          -  Anemia (hemoglobin&lt;12.0g/dL)

          -  Thrombocytopenia (platelets&lt;100,000 cells/microL)

          -  Leukopenia (white cell count&lt;4,000 cells/microL)

          -  Hypoalbuminemia (albumin&lt;3.5g/dL)

          -  Hyponatremia (sodium&lt;135mmol/L)

          -  Coagulopathy (PT or PTT &gt;1.5 times upper limit of normal)

          -  Pathologic lymphadenopathy (at least five discrete nodes each &gt;1cm in their longest
             dimension)

          -  Splenomegaly (&gt;12 cm in the longest dimension)

          -  Hepatomegaly (&gt;17cm in the longest dimension)

          -  Body cavity effusions not caused by primary effusion lymphoma nor chylous effusions
             directly related to lymphatic infiltration by KS

             -. C-reactive protein &gt;3mg/L.

          -  Exposure risk for KSHV infection (including being a first or second generation
             immigrant from an endemic area, or male-to-male sexual activity) or evidence of KSHV
             infection demonstrated by one of:

               -  Molecular evidence of KSHV in whole blood, confirmed by testing at Focus
                  Laboratories, CA (HHV-8 Quantitative PCR, Focus Unit Code 45700).

               -  Immunohistochemical evidence of KSHV in tissues (for example by staining for LANA
                  or vIL-6). Confirmed in the Laboratory of Pathology, CCR, NCI.

               -  Presence of KS or PEL (KSHV-associated malignancies), confirmed in the Laboratory
                  of Pathology, CCR, NCI.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Biopsy proven KSHV-associated MCD, confirmed in the Laboratory of Pathology, CCR, NCI.

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Any abnormality that would be scored as NCI CTC Grade 4 toxicity that is unrelated to
             HIV, its treatment, or to KICS that would preclude the use of all of the study
             treatments or the ability to monitor the natural history of KICS untreated.

          -  Any condition or set of circumstances that in the opinion of the investigators would
             make participation in this study unsafe or otherwise inappropriate for a given
             individual.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Yarchoan, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anaida Widell</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 451-3694</phone>
    <email>awidell@cc.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Robert Yarchoan, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(240) 760-6075</phone>
    <email>robert.yarchoan@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>(888) NCI-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2011-C-0220.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chang Y, Cesarman E, Pessin MS, Lee F, Culpepper J, Knowles DM, Moore PS. Identification of herpesvirus-like DNA sequences in AIDS-associated Kaposi's sarcoma. Science. 1994 Dec 16;266(5192):1865-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7997879</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moore PS, Gao SJ, Dominguez G, Cesarman E, Lungu O, Knowles DM, Garber R, Pellett PE, McGeoch DJ, Chang Y. Primary characterization of a herpesvirus agent associated with Kaposi's sarcomae. J Virol. 1996 Jan;70(1):549-58. Erratum in: J Virol 1996 Dec;70(12):9083.</citation>
    <PMID>8523568</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Viejo-Borbolla A, Schulz TF. Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus (KSHV/HHV8): key aspects of epidemiology and pathogenesis. AIDS Rev. 2003 Oct-Dec;5(4):222-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15012001</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 20, 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 17, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 17, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 18, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 25, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 25, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 28, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>KSHV</keyword>
  <keyword>KICS</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Cytokines</keyword>
  <keyword>HHV-8</keyword>
  <keyword>KSHV Inflammatory Cytokine Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Kaposi Sarcoma Heres Virus</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

