<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01418716</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FRSQ-22424</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01418716</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TRANSforming InTerprofessional Cardiovascular Prevention in Primary Care</brief_title>
  <acronym>TRANSIT</acronym>
  <official_title>A Program to TRANSform InTerprofessional Clinical Practices to Improve Cardiovascular Prevention in Primary Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fonds de la Recherche en Santé du Québec</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Université de Montréal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fonds de la Recherche en Santé du Québec</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The TRANSIT program is a program to TRANSform InTerprofessional clinical practices to improve
      cardiovascular prevention in primary care. It addresses priorities in primary care relevant
      to the Chronic Care Model (Wagner 2001): self-management support, delivery-system design, and
      management of clinical information.

      The program includes :

        -  a case manager to coordinate and provide care and follow up;

        -  clinical protocols and tools to support interprofessional and systematic follow up;

        -  training for clinicians;

        -  patient's personalized cardiovascular health booklet;

        -  tools to promote group sessions for patient education on cholesterol, hypertension, and
           diabetes.

      The general OBJECTIVE of this trial is to evaluate and compare two STRATEGIES for
      implementing the TRANSIT program in Family Medicine Groups (FMGs):

        1. facilitation, and

        2. passive diffusion.

      Passive diffusion is the usual strategy where clinicians implement an intervention program by
      themselves. Facilitation is a strategy whereby a facilitator provides support to a team of
      clinicians to help them introduce the changes required to implement the program into
      practice.

      The hypothesis is that facilitation will be more efficacious to implement the program than
      passive diffusion:

        -  it will enhance the provision of cardiovascular preventive care;

        -  it will enhance interprofessional collaboration;

        -  it will enable more efficaciously the implementation of new clinical processes;

        -  it will improve patient clinical outcomes;

        -  it will cost more in the short term, but will have positive economic impact in the long
           term;

        -  there will be less &quot;undesired effects&quot; of all types related to implementation.

      To test the hypothesis, we assess the efficacy of the implementation strategies to enhance
      interprofessional collaboration and better support patients in the management of their
      conditions. Impact on provision of care, interprofessional collaboration, clinical processes,
      and patient clinical outcomes (values, therapeutic targets, and lifestyle habits) will be
      evaluated. Moreover, the implementation cost related to each strategy will be estimated.

      We complement the trial with qualitative methods to document the perceptions of clinicians,
      facilitators, patients and members of the family regarding the TRANSIT program, the
      implementation strategies and the observed changes in the clinical practices and outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      STUDY DESIGN:

      Pragmatic cluster randomized clinical trial

      SETTING:

      Nine Family Medicine Groups (FMGs) take part in the study. FMGs are primary care clinics
      delivering family medicine services. They include physicians and nurses, and collaborate with
      other health professionals.

      Eligible FMGs meet the following criteria:

        1. 2 physicians, 1 nurse, 1 community pharmacist, 1 member of the medical administrative
           support, and 1 other health professional (nutritionist, kinesiologist, or psychologist)
           accept to participate by collaborating to the facilitation activities, if the FMG is
           assigned to the facilitation group;

        2. 1 physician, 1 nurse, 1 community pharmacist and 1 other health professional
           (nutritionist, psychologist, kinesiologist) accept to play a role in the internal
           facilitation team, if the FMG is assigned to the facilitation group;

        3. a room is available for the case manager nurse for the equivalent of one day/week over
           15 months;

        4. 100 eligible patients accept to participate in the study, with a minimum of 15 patients
           per physician participant.

      All FMGs in the TRANSIT study are given access to the TRANSIT program, to the supportive
      clinical tools cliniques, and to a case manager nurse. Training will be offered on the use of
      the electronic directory of health resources and on motivational interview.

      RANDOMIZATION:

      Prior to randomization, each clinician is assigned to one FMG only. Each FMG will be paired
      with 2 others of the same level of CVD preventive care (score &lt;6 or ≥6), as estimated with
      the questionnaire &quot;Assessment of Chronic Illness Care&quot; (ACIC). Usually, medical clinics
      report a score of 5 or less at baseline.

      Participating FMGs (n=9) will be randomly assigned to facilitation (n=6) and to passive
      diffusion (n=3). FMGs will be randomized simultaniously in blocs of 3. For each bloc, 2:1
      ratio (facilitation:passive diffusion) will be respected. Randomization will be stratified in
      fonction of the ACIC score (score &lt;6 or score ≥6). Because of the small number of
      participating FMGs, grouping GMFs in blocs of 3 according to the ACIC score will ensure
      complete blocs are found in each randomization stratum.

      ANALYSIS:

      For all variables, multivariable analysis models taking account the intracluster correlation
      (linear/SAS PROC MIXED) for continuous and categorical variables (logistic/PROC GENMOD) will
      be developed. Significative variables (p&lt;0.2) in bivariable model including the study group
      will be included in the multivariable model. We will then apply a backward selection
      procedure and include in the final model those variables that were statistically significant
      at p &lt; 0.1.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of the cardiovascular preventive care</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change in the composite score of the quality of the cardiovascular preventive care</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Organisational outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Impact of implementation strategy on:
clinicians' and patients' perception of health service delivery (questionnaires: ACIC and PACIC);
team work (questionnaire: TCI - short version);
clinicians' perception of achievement of change (questionnaires: Herscovitch and Meyer's Affective Engagement, Bandura's Self Efficacy, and clinician's perception of achievement of the TRANSIT program [after 12 months only]);
direct costs (clinician time and compensations for participation in facilitation activities, salary and training of the external facilitator).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change in the systolic/diastolic blood pressure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>c-LDL</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change in change in the c-LDL</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glycosylated hemoglobine (HgA1c)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change in the HgA1c</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Achieved therapeutic targets</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change in percentage of achieved therapeutic targets</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lifestyle habits</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change in lifestyle habits as measured using self-administered questionnaires to patients : Hopkin's food frequency questionnaire, International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ), smoking status</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of public programs</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months after randomization</time_frame>
    <description>Mean change in percentage of patients using the education programs and in mean frequency of use. Programs are education to patients on diabetes, cholesterol, hypertension, and healthy weight control</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">759</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Dyslipidemias</condition>
  <condition>Cholesterol, LDL</condition>
  <condition>Comorbitdity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Facilitation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Facilitation is a change management process. In the TRANSIT study, the change consist in implementing the TRANSIT program in primary care clinics. In the facilitation group, external facilitators accompany, support, and empower clinical teams so they quickly develop a sense of ownership regarding new clinical practices and sustainably implement them with lower costs. External facilitators offer counseling, coaching, and various tools to an internal facilitation team composed of clinicians of the clinical team to support their efforts in implementing change in their practices. Facilitation activities are structured in a cycle of 4 steps, the Plan-Do-Study-Act cycle (PDSA cycle).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Passive diffusion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Clinical teams in primary care clinics implement the TRANSIT program without the help of facilitators.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Facilitation</intervention_name>
    <description>Facilitation is a change management process. In the TRANSIT study, the change consist in implementing the TRANSIT program in primary care clinics. In the facilitation group, external facilitators accompany, support, and empower clinical teams so they quickly develop a sense of ownership regarding new clinical practices and sustainably implement them with lower costs. External facilitators offer counseling, coaching, and various tools to an internal facilitation team composed of clinicians of the clinical team to support their efforts in implementing change in their practices. Facilitation activities are structured in a cycle of 4 steps, the Plan-Do-Study-Act cycle (PDSA cycle).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Facilitation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Plan-Do-Study-Act cycles (PDSA cycles)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Passive diffusion</intervention_name>
    <description>Clinical teams in primary care clinics implement the TRANSIT program without the help of facilitators.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Passive diffusion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patient is registered in a Family Medicine Group;

          -  10-year Framingham risk score (FRS) moderate (11-19%) to high (≥ 20%);

          -  at least one of the following condition uncontrolled:

               -  Diabetes: HbA1C &gt; 7% OR fasting blood glucose &gt; 7 mmol/L OR 2-hour postprandial
                  blood glucose &gt; 10 mmol/L (OR &gt; 8 mmol/L if HbA1C target is not
                  acheived)(Canadian Diabetes Association Clinical Practice Guidelines Expert
                  Committee, Canadian Journal of Diabetes, 2008)

               -  Dyslipidemia: C-LDL ≥ 2 mmol/L in moderate to high risk patients OR less than 50%
                  reduction of C-LDL compared to initial value OR Apo-B ≥ 0,8 g/L (Genest,
                  McPherson et al. 2009)

               -  Hypertension: blood pressure ≥ 140/90 ou ≥ 130/80 in diabetic patients or with
                  chronic kidney disease (TFG &lt; 60mL/min/1,73m2; (Cloutier &amp; Poirier 2011)

          -  Patient with at least two chronic disease or chronic health problem other than type II
             diabetes, dyslipidemia, hypertension, or cardiovascular disease (e.g. : angina,
             previous history of myocard infarct, stroke, and intermittent claudication).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient followed for a cardiovascular disease in a specialized clinic in secondary
             care (ex.: cardiology, endocrinology etc).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lyne Lalonde, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre de santé et de services sociaux de Laval ; University of Montreal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Johanne Goudreau, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Université de Montréal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Céline Bareil, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>HEC Montréal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Éveline Hudon, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Université de Montréal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fabie Duhamel, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Université de Montréal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marie-Thérèse Lussier, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Université de Montréal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre de santé et de services sociaux de Laval</name>
      <address>
        <city>Laval</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H7M 3L9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.recherchepl.ca/autres-productions-scientifiques.php</url>
    <description>Protocole de suivi interprofessionnel TRANSIT et outils cliniques associés (in French only)</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wagner EH, Austin BT, Davis C, Hindmarsh M, Schaefer J, Bonomi A. Improving chronic illness care: translating evidence into action. Health Aff (Millwood). 2001 Nov-Dec;20(6):64-78.</citation>
    <PMID>11816692</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dogherty EJ, Harrison MB, Graham ID. Facilitation as a role and process in achieving evidence-based practice in nursing: a focused review of concept and meaning. Worldviews Evid Based Nurs. 2010 Jun 1;7(2):76-89. doi: 10.1111/j.1741-6787.2010.00186.x. Epub 2010 Feb 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20180826</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nagykaldi Z, Mold JW, Robinson A, Niebauer L, Ford A. Practice facilitators and practice-based research networks. J Am Board Fam Med. 2006 Sep-Oct;19(5):506-10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16951300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Genest J, McPherson R, Frohlich J, Anderson T, Campbell N, Carpentier A, Couture P, Dufour R, Fodor G, Francis GA, Grover S, Gupta M, Hegele RA, Lau DC, Leiter L, Lewis GF, Lonn E, Mancini GB, Ng D, Pearson GJ, Sniderman A, Stone JA, Ur E. 2009 Canadian Cardiovascular Society/Canadian guidelines for the diagnosis and treatment of dyslipidemia and prevention of cardiovascular disease in the adult - 2009 recommendations. Can J Cardiol. 2009 Oct;25(10):567-79. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19812802</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hackam DG, Khan NA, Hemmelgarn BR, Rabkin SW, Touyz RM, Campbell NR, Padwal R, Campbell TS, Lindsay MP, Hill MD, Quinn RR, Mahon JL, Herman RJ, Schiffrin EL, Ruzicka M, Larochelle P, Feldman RD, Lebel M, Poirier L, Arnold JM, Moe GW, Howlett JG, Trudeau L, Bacon SL, Petrella RJ, Milot A, Stone JA, Drouin D, Boulanger JM, Sharma M, Hamet P, Fodor G, Dresser GK, Carruthers SG, Pylypchuk G, Burgess ED, Burns KD, Vallée M, Prasad GV, Gilbert RE, Leiter LA, Jones C, Ogilvie RI, Woo V, McFarlane PA, Hegele RA, Tobe SW; Canadian Hypertension Education Program. The 2010 Canadian Hypertension Education Program recommendations for the management of hypertension: part 2 - therapy. Can J Cardiol. 2010 May;26(5):249-58. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20485689</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fortin M, Soubhi H, Hudon C, Bayliss EA, van den Akker M. Multimorbidity's many challenges. BMJ. 2007 May 19;334(7602):1016-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17510108</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lalonde L, Goudreau J, Hudon É, Lussier MT, Duhamel F, Bélanger D, Lévesque L, Martin É; Group for TRANSIT to Best Practices in Cardiovascular Disease Prevention in Primary Care. Priorities for action to improve cardiovascular preventive care of patients with multimorbid conditions in primary care--a participatory action research project. Fam Pract. 2012 Dec;29(6):733-41. doi: 10.1093/fampra/cms021. Epub 2012 Feb 29.</citation>
    <PMID>22379187</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lalonde L, Goudreau J, Hudon É, Lussier MT, Bareil C, Duhamel F, Lévesque L, Turcotte A, Lalonde G; Group for TRANSIT to Best Practices in Cardiovascular Disease Prevention in Primary Care. Development of an interprofessional program for cardiovascular prevention in primary care: A participatory research approach. SAGE Open Med. 2014 Feb 17;2:2050312114522788. doi: 10.1177/2050312114522788. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>26770705</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 16, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 16, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 17, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 15, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 15, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Fonds de la Recherche en Santé du Québec</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lyne Lalonde</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor (professeur agrégé)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Disease Management</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality Improvement</keyword>
  <keyword>Cooperative Behavior (collaboration)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dyslipidemias</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

