<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02148276</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1408</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R21DA036407</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02148276</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving Identification of Social Harm Among Substance Abusers in HIV Trials</brief_title>
  <official_title>Improving Identification of Social Harm Among Substance Abusers in HIV Trials</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Treatment Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Treatment Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This two-phased project will develop a comprehensive, audio computer assisted
      self-administered interview social harm questionnaire (ACASI-SHQ) that will allow researchers
      to more easily identify and monitor social harms experienced by substance abusers
      participating in HIV-related trials. The ACASI-SHQ will (1) reduce the likelihood of socially
      desirable responding, (2) include items with high levels of specificity to increase the
      likelihood of identifying social harms (construct validity), and (3) utilize a self-interview
      format that will increase the likelihood of its adoption by HIV researchers. The
      investigators will then evaluate its feasibility, acceptability, and preliminary utility and
      construct validity in an ongoing HIV-related trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Most clinical trials do not regularly monitor for negative social harms experienced by
      participants in any systematic way. Participation in HIV trials often places participants at
      a heightened risk of oppression, discrimination, and victimization. These risks may be
      compounded when participants are substance abusers. Although foreseen risks are generally
      outlined in the consent form and monitored throughout the study, many social harms are
      unforeseen and, consequently, are not discussed or monitored. Without systematic monitoring,
      the majority of social harms likely go undetected. Recognizing the high level of social harm
      that may arise as a result of participation in HIV vaccine trials, several National Institute
      of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)-sponsored groups began to incorporate general
      assessments to measure the social impact of research participation in HIV vaccine trials.
      Although this has provided a preliminary model for monitoring social harms in clinical
      research, the assessments have several shortcomings that limit their reliability, validity,
      and utility. In general, they are administered in an interview format that may be cumbersome
      to the research team. Furthermore, participants may feel uncomfortable or reluctant to report
      social harms directly to the interviewer, resulting in inaccuracies or underreporting of
      negative events. Interview items generally address large classes of behavior rather than
      specific behaviors, reducing the sensitivity and construct validity of the assessments, and
      questions used across agencies are not standardized. Finally, these assessments do not
      include harms specific to substance use, a major risk factor for HIV/AIDS transmission. The
      two-phased project aims to improve the collection of social harms among HIV trial
      participants by developing a comprehensive, audio computer assisted self-administered
      interview social harm questionnaire (ACASI-SHQ) that will allow researchers to more easily
      identify and monitor social harms experienced by substance abusers participating in HIV
      trials. The proposed study will proceed in two phases. In Phase 1, the investigators will
      develop the ACASI Social Harm Questionnaire (SHQ). In Phase 2, the investigators will conduct
      a controlled study to evaluate its acceptability, feasibility, and utility and construct
      validity.

      During Phase 1 the investigators will first conduct a systematic literature review to
      identify existing tools that researchers currently use to measure social harm or impact
      experienced by research participants. In addition, the investigators will survey 100
      researchers who are currently conducting National Institutes of Health (NIH)-funded
      HIV-related trials involving substance abusers. The sample will be randomly selected from a
      pool of researchers meeting this criterion identified through the NIH RePORTER database. The
      brief telephone survey will include questions about methods used to collect data on social
      harm including specific questions asked, mode of administration, frequency of assessment,
      perceived ease of data collection, and concerns related to the assessment. During this phase
      the investigators will also conduct a focus group with 10 former research participants to
      gather information about their experiences and perceptions of social harm in HIV-related
      research trials. The research team in collaboration with a multidisciplinary panel of experts
      will draft a beta-version of the SHQ content and format. The expert panel will also assist in
      identifying an optimal trial in which to test the finalized instrument in the second phase of
      the study. Finally, the investigators will conduct a protocol analysis of the beta-version
      through interviews with 20 individuals who are currently enrolled in an ongoing National
      Institute of Drug Abuse (NIDA)-funded HIV prevention trial being conducted by the
      investigators. This is intended to ensure that items are correctly and similarly understood
      by subjects, and to provide insight into better methods of phrasing or structuring questions
      and response options to properly convey their meaning. Upon completion of the protocol
      analysis, the revised instrument will be finalized by the investigators, programmed into the
      ACASI format, beta-tested by the research team, and critically reviewed by our expert panel
      before the final programming of the ACASI-SHQ is completed.

      During Phase 2, we will conduct a pilot study to evaluate the acceptability, feasibility, and
      utility and construct validity of the ACASI-SHQ. Individuals consenting to the host study
      will be offered the opportunity to participate in the pilot study, and they will receive a
      manualized written informed consent procedure. We will enroll a total of 80 individuals into
      the pilot study. All participants will complete two measures of social harm at monthly
      research appointments for a three month period. The social harms assessments will be (1) the
      ACASI-SHQ that was developed in Phase 1 and (2) the HIV Vaccine Trials Network (HVTN) Social
      Impact Assessment. At each appointment, the order in which the instruments are delivered will
      be counterbalanced to control for carryover effects. At the end of Phase 2, host study
      research team will complete the ACASI-SHQ Feasibility and Acceptability Questionnaire.
      Additionally, the PI and Co-I will conduct a focus group with the research team to collect
      qualitative data on the feasibility, acceptability, and perceived benefits of the ACASI-SHQ
      and information to guide its future implementation.

      The recruitment, study design, conditions, arms, interventions, and eligibility criteria
      sections of this record reflect the involvement of the 80 participants who will participate
      in Phase 2 pilot testing of the ACASI-SHQ.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 4, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 4, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Crossover</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability to participants</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the acceptability of the ACASI-SHQ to clients using a modified version of the well-validated Client Satisfaction Questionnaire.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility and acceptability to research staff</measure>
    <time_frame>22 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the host study research team's perceptions of the ACASI-SHQ's acceptability and feasibility using the the ACASI-SHQ Feasibility and Acceptability Questionnaire. We will also hold a focus group with the host study research team to collect qualitative data on the feasibility, acceptability, and perceived benefits of the ACASI-SHQ and information to guide its future implementation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Utility and construct validity</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the preliminary utility and construct validity of the ACASI-SHQ by comparing the number of social harms it identifies to the number identified using the HVTN social impact assessment. Improved construct validity would be demonstrated if more harms were identified using the ACASI-SHQ than the HVTN social impact assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">79</enrollment>
  <condition>Social Harms in Substance Users in HIV Trials</condition>
  <condition>Audio Computer Assisted Self-administered Questionnaire</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Research Participants</arm_group_label>
    <description>All participants will complete two measures of social harm at monthly research appointments for a three month period. The social harms assessments will be (1) the ACASI-SHQ that was developed in Phase 1 and (2) the HIV Vaccine Trials Network (HVTN) Social Impact Assessment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        We anticipate that the sample will be representative of the populations in our ongoing
        trials of clients with substance use disorders and of the substance abuse treatment
        population, which is approximately 70% male, 60% African-American, 35% Caucasian, and 30%
        Hispanic. This distribution is similar to the gender and racial distributions of publicly
        funded drug abuse treatment patients in Philadelphia and other large cities located in
        Mid-Atlantic States.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently participating in an HIV-related trial

          -  Current or former substance abusers

          -  18 years of age or older

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to give competent informed consent

          -  Involvement in the study would negatively affect the participant's health or safety
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David S Festinger, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Treatment Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Treatment Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.tresearch.org/</url>
    <description>Treatment Research Institute</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 23, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 27, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 12, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 12, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 16, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Social harm detection</keyword>
  <keyword>Instrument development</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV-related clinical trials</keyword>
  <keyword>Substance abuse</keyword>
  <keyword>Research participation</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

