<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02141451</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013LS081</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HM2013-24</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02141451</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ADAM17 Inhibitor/ Rituximab After Auto HCT for DLBCL</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study of the ADAM17 Inhibitor INCB7839 Combined With Rituximab After Autologous Hematopoietic Cell Transplantation (HCT) For Patients With Diffuse Large B Cell Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma (DLBCL)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Masonic Cancer Center, University of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Masonic Cancer Center, University of Minnesota</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single institution phase I/II study using an ADAM17 inhibitor (INCB7839) with
      rituximab as consolidation therapy after an autologous hematopoietic cell transplant (HCT)
      for patients with diffuse large B cell lymphoma (DLBCL). The study consists of two phases.
      The dose finding phase is a modified version of a phase I trial and the extended phase is a
      modified version of a phase II trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary goal of the dose finding phase is to determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD)
      of INCB7839. Up to three dose levels will be tested (100 mg bid, 200 mg bid, and 300 mg bid).
      As the 300 mg bid has been proven safe in the non-transplant setting, dose escalation follows
      a Fast-Track Design with 1 patient enrolled per dose level unless a grade 2 or greater
      treatment emergent event occurs within the 1st 14 days of INCB7839. At that point, dose
      escalation converts to a standard 3+3 design and two additional patients are enrolled at the
      current dose level. If dose level 3 is completed without dose limiting toxicity (DLT) in the
      1st 3 patients, an additional 3 patients will be enrolled at this level (without the
      staggering required by the DLT rules) prior to moving to the phase II component.

      Once the phase I dose escalation is completed, an additional 12 patients will be enrolled at
      the MTD (or dose level 3, if no DLT) to obtain a more detailed toxicity profile as well as a
      preliminary estimate of progression free survival at 6 months post-transplant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose of INCB7839</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The Phase I design will continue until the MTD is declared or until the first dose is declared to be above MTD. Phase I dose limiting toxicity (DLT) is defined as Grade 3-5 non-hematologic, non-infectious toxicity including thromboembolic complications and select hematologic events including: grade 4 neutropenia lasting for ≥ 7 days, febrile neutropenia, grade 4 thrombocytopenia lasting ≥ 7 days despite dose delay or grade 3 thrombocytopenia associated with bleeding.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>This Phase 2 primary end point will be estimated with Kaplan-Meier curves.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Serious Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To determine incidence of serious adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of disease free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate 1 year disease-free survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate 1 year overall survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean time to progression</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To determine mean time to relapse/progression</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">33</enrollment>
  <condition>Diffuse Large B Cell Non-Hodgkin Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Rituximab will be given after day +28 re-staging and again 1 and 7 weeks later, followed by INCB7839 at assigned dose twice daily for 90 days - begin the morning of the 2nd dose of rituximab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituximab</intervention_name>
    <description>Rituximab 375 mg/m2 IV after day +28 re-staging and again 1 and 7 weeks later</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rituxan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>INCB7839</intervention_name>
    <description>INCB7839 at assigned dose twice daily for 90 days - begin the morning of the 2nd dose of rituximab</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients 18 years or older who have undergone an autologous HCT for the treatment of
             DLBCL and are in a complete remission (CR), partial remission (PR) or have stable
             disease (SD) at the day 28 post-transplant reassessment

          -  Karnofsky Score of ≥ 70% (appendix II)

          -  Able to start the protocol therapy (1st dose of rituximab) between day 28-60
             post-transplant

          -  Adequate organ function defined as:

               -  Hematologic: platelets ≥ 50,000 x 109/L; ANC ≥ 1000 x 109/L unsupported by G-CSF
                  or GM-CSF for 3 days

               -  Renal: creatinine &lt; 1.5 mg/dl or glomerular filtration rate &gt; 50 ml/min

               -  Hepatic: Alanine transaminase (ALT, SGPT) and aspartate aminotransferase (SGOT,
                  AST) &lt; 3 x upper limit of institutional normal and total bilirubin &lt; 3.0 mg/dl
                  (if total bilirubin is ≥ 3.0 patient is eligible if direct bilirubin is within
                  normal limits)

               -  Pulmonary: clinically no evidence of pulmonary disease

               -  Cardiac: no symptoms of uncontrolled cardiac disease

          -  If post-transplant consolidation radiation therapy is given, the patient must be at
             least 14 days between last radiation treatment and 1st dose of rituximab

          -  Able to take daily aspirin (325 mg) for the duration of INCB7839 treatment and 1 week
             after the last dose to reduce the risk of thrombosis (not applicable if on other
             anti-coagulant therapy at time of study registration - see section 5.11)

          -  Females are either postmenopausal for at least 1 year, are surgically sterile for at
             least 3 months, or must agree to take appropriate precautions to avoid pregnancy (with
             at least 99% certainty) from screening through 12 months after the last dose of
             rituximab if of childbearing potential. (Note: Permitted methods that are at least 99%
             effective in preventing pregnancy should be communicated to the participants and their
             understanding confirmed).

          -  Males must agree to take appropriate precautions to avoid fathering a child (with at
             least 99% certainty) from screening through 12 months after the last dose of
             rituximab. (Note: Permitted methods that are at least 99% effective in preventing
             pregnancy should be communicated to the participants and their understanding
             confirmed).

          -  Voluntary written consent signed before performance of any study-related procedure not
             part of normal medical care

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or lactating - Studies to evaluate the potential for embryo toxicity and
             teratogenicity have not been performed for INCB7839. Until additional information is
             available, women of childbearing potential should use appropriate precautions to avoid
             becoming pregnant. Rituximab is Pregnancy Category C: There are no adequate and
             well-controlled studies of rituximab in pregnant women. Females of childbearing
             potential must have a negative urine or serum pregnancy test within 14 days of study
             treatment start

          -  Recent venous thrombosis within 4 weeks prior to study registration. Patients at high
             risk for thrombotic events due to inherited risk factors (i.e. factor V Leiden) or
             DVT/PE in the past 12 months should be on secondary prophylaxis with anti-coagulant
             therapy (i.e. warfarin or low molecular weight heparin) prior to enrollment

          -  Active uncontrolled infection

          -  Active CNS disease

          -  Previous severe or life-threatening allergic reaction with rituximab or known allergy
             to the compounds found in INCB7839

          -  Any gastrointestinal condition causing malabsorption or obstruction (eg, celiac sprue,
             gastric bypass surgery, strictures, adhesions, history of small bowel resection, blind
             loop syndrome)

          -  Unwilling or unable to swallow tablets BID

          -  Serologic or clinical evidence of current active hepatitis B or C infection, defined
             as elevated levels of Hep B antigen or Hep C antibody (unless active infection is
             ruled out by nucleic acid tests)

          -  Known HIV infection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Veronika Bachanova, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Minnesota Medical Center, Fairview</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Veronika Bachanova, MD</last_name>
    <phone>612-625-5469</phone>
    <email>bach0173@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota Medical Center, Fairview</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Veronika Bachanova, MD</last_name>
      <phone>612-625-5469</phone>
      <email>bach0173@umn.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Veronika Bachanova, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 15, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 19, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>DLBCL</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

