<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02140359</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R34DA034855</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02140359</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Enhancing Housing First Programs With a Social Network Substance Use Intervention</brief_title>
  <official_title>Enhancing Housing First Programs With a Social Network Substance Use Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>RAND</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>RAND</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Housing First programs are promising approaches to transitioning substance using chronically
      homeless adults to affordable housing. However, Housing First programs need to provide
      support to residents to adjust to their changing social environments. The proposed project
      fulfills a critical gap by developing an electronic tool for a social network intervention
      using motivational interviewing techniques as well as results of a pilot test of the tool.
      The hypothesis to be tested is that Housing First residents who are given the intervention
      will be significantly more motivated to change their drinking, drug use, sexual risk
      behaviors, and social networks compared to controls receiving usual care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We propose a 3-year study to develop and pilot test a social network substance use and
      HIV-risk intervention for permanent supportive housing program residents in the Skid Row area
      of Los Angeles. The intervention will be developed for residents at the Skid Row Housing
      Trust (SRHT), one of the largest Housing First providers in Los Angeles. Housing First
      residents are not required to abstain from alcohol and drugs as a requirement of their
      residency. There is some evidence that providing housing rapidly to chronically homeless
      persons--along with support--helps to reduce substance use and HIV risk behaviors in the
      short term because homelessness is the primary cause of high-risk behavior. However, the
      evidence thus far is limited. One aspect that has not received much research attention is the
      needs of Housing First residents for support to transition their social networks while
      transitioning out of homeless into residency in a Housing First program. New residents are
      exposed to a wide range of potentially negative social influences while also having greater
      potential to reconnect with lost positive ties. This project will develop a social network
      intervention to residents of SRHT in order to increase their knowledge about their social
      networks and enhance their motivation to make necessary changes to improve their ability to
      reduce or continue to abstain from high-risk behavior. The intervention sessions will enhance
      the weekly support meetings that SRHT case workers already conduct with new residents during
      their first 6 months of residency. Case workers will be trained to deliver the 30-minute
      intervention sessions using a motivational interviewing style. The intervention will be
      developed so that case managers can deliver it with the aid of an electronic tablet device.
      The tablet will guide them in collecting information about the residents' social networks and
      then display several diagrams highlighting various aspects of the residents' networks. They
      will then use motivational interviewing techniques to guide residents to think about how
      their network currently functions, how they would like it to function, and what steps they
      can take to make changes necessary to achieve goals related to reducing their substance use
      and sexual risk behaviors. The intervention will be delivered by case managers across four
      sessions (at baseline and at two-week intervals). We anticipate that residents who
      participate in this intervention will develop new strategies in their interactions with their
      social networks that will facilitate a reduction in their high-risk behavior.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Readiness to change alcohol and other drug use</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 13-14 weeks (post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with 12 item Readiness to Change Questionnaire (RTCQ) and a one item Contemplation Ladder</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Readiness to change risky sexual behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 13-14 weeks (post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>11 item Readiness to Change Risky Sexual Behavior (RTCQ-SB) scale a one item Contemplation Ladder</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self efficacy to change alcohol and other drug use</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 13-14 weeks (post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with two questionnaire items that assess the participant's importance and self-efficacy to stop alcohol and other drug use and 4 items from the Alcohol Abstinence Self-Efficacy Scale (AASE) which measure how confident participants feel in their ability to abstain from alcohol use when depressed, relaxed, craving substances, and offered alcohol.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self efficacy to change risky sexual behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 13-14 weeks (post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with 4 item Self-Efficacy to Use Condoms scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-efficacy to change social networks</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 13-14 weeks (post intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Two item ladder scale item measuring importance and self-efficacy to change social networks.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived Social Network support and approval/disapproval of alcohol, drug use, and risky sex.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 13-14 weeks (after intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Measures of Perceived Social Support and ratings of network members on emotional closeness, drinking, drug use, safe-sex behavior, and approval/disapproval of high-risk behavior of social network members based on the Important People Drug and Alcohol Interview. Raw network data to provide measures will result from a personal network interview in which participants will name 20 network member and answer questions about each of them and their relationships with each other.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Drug and Alcohol use</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 13-14 weeks (after intervention is completed)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed with a Timeline Followback calendar structured interview that measures alcohol and drug use through recall aided by a calendar. Participants will be asked quantity and intensity of drinking and drug use to calculate a quantity-frequency index for both drinking and drug use. Self-reports of non-use will be validated with a Oral Fluid Test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV risk behavior</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 13-14 weeks (after intervention completion)</time_frame>
    <description>Survey items asking if the participant engaged in unprotected sex and concurrent sexual relationships overall and with particular partners in the past 90 days.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in social network composition and structure</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 13-14 weeks (after intervention completion)</time_frame>
    <description>Measures of network composition and structure will be constructed from raw network data. Raw network data result from a personal network interview in which participants will name 20 network member and answer questions about each of them and their relationships with each other.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with Intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>13-14 weeks (after intervention)</time_frame>
    <description>Administration of the Client Satisfaction Questionnaire (CSQ-8), an 8-item Likert-type measure of client feedback regarding services provided in a treatment program.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcohol Drinking</condition>
  <condition>Drug Abuse</condition>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group: Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Residents of a housing first permanent supporting housing program will be randomly assigned to this arm after screening and baseline assessments. They will meet with case managers according to the usual procedures for new residents and will be given a standard case manager interaction.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Motivational Network Interview Recipients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Residents of a housing first permanent supporting housing program will be randomly assigned to this arm after screening and baseline assessments. They will meet roughly every two weeks with a case manager and answer questions about their social network, will be shown visual feedback about their networks, and will participate in a motivational interview conducted by the case managers. The questions and visualizations will be facilitated by an electronic tool for presenting screens with questions, capturing responses, processing and visualizing social network data.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Motivational Network Interview</intervention_name>
    <description>Residents of a housing first permanent supporting housing program will be randomly assigned to this arm after screening and baseline assessments. They will meet roughly every two weeks with a case manager and answer questions about their social network, will be shown visual feedback about their networks, and will participate in a motivational interview conducted by the case managers. The questions and visualizations will be facilitated by an electronic tool for presenting screens with questions, capturing responses, processing and visualizing social network data.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Motivational Network Interview Recipients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  New residents of Skid Row Housing Trust receiving permanent supportive housing

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age younger than 18

          -  Does not speak English

          -  Cognitively impaired either by identifying those having a diagnosis of dementia in the
             new resident intake interview or using the Short Blessed Scale Exam)

          -  Does not screen positive for past -year harmful AOD use using the AUDIT-C (a score &gt; 4
             for men and &gt; 3 for women) and DAST (a score greater than 2).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David P Kennedy, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>RAND</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Skid Row Housing Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>RAND Corporation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santa Monica</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90407</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 14, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 15, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 16, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 24, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>RAND</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Kennedy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Behavioral / Social Scientist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>homelessness</keyword>
  <keyword>housing first</keyword>
  <keyword>social networks</keyword>
  <keyword>drug abuse</keyword>
  <keyword>alcohol use</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcohol Drinking</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

