<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02140723</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PART1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02140723</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>p53 and Response to Preoperative Radiotherapy for T2 and T3</brief_title>
  <acronym>PART1</acronym>
  <official_title>PART1 - a Prospective Phase II Study to Evaluate the Impact of TP53 Gene Mutations in Patients With Preoperative Radiotherapy for T2 and T3 Rectal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of Vienna</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Vienna</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Meta-analyses of large randomized trials proved the superiority of preoperative short course
      radiation and surgery, as compared with surgery alone. Short course radiation results in a
      50% reduction in terms of local relapse in stage II and III rectal cancer patients. Patients
      with complete pathological remission additionally show a significant survival benefit.
      Complete pathological remission (pCR) occurs in 8% after preoperative radiation and in &gt;16%
      if the interval between radiation and surgery is at least 8 weeks.

      It is generally accepted that mutations in the TP53 gene represent a crucial defect in the
      apoptosis pathway. Radiation therapy is suggested to act via induction of apoptosis in
      irradiated cells. Therefore, it is expected that a defect in the TP53 gene has an effect on
      the success of radiation therapy.

      Currently available imaging tools are hardly able to diagnose response to radiation therapy
      correctly, as this does not essentially correlate with tumor size.

      Method:

      Aim of this prospective observation study is to strengthen the hypothesis that the TP53
      genotype is a promising marker to predict response to radiation therapy in rectal cancer
      patients. Consequently, the expected results will justify prospective, randomized
      intervention trials to obtain level of evidence I for the p53 marker hypothesis. Trial
      endpoint is downstaging and pCR rate. Tumor stage and pathological remission will be
      evaluated by MRT and pathohistology and correlated to the TP53 genotype of the diagnostic
      biopsy. Additionally, we will investigate the applicability of novel imaging modalities in
      magnet resonance tomography to monitor response to radiotherapy.

      The objective of this study is

        -  to evaluate the effect of a genetic tumor marker (TP53 genotype) on the response to
           preoperative short course radiation (in terms of downstaging and pCR rate)

        -  to evaluate the applicability of novel magnet resonance tomography imaging modalities to
           monitor response to preoperative short time radiation.

      Conclusion:

      The prospective evaluation of the potential predictive marker TP53 may bring us one-step
      closer to an individualized therapy regimen, which allows the restriction of preoperative
      radiation in rectal cancer to those patients who will benefit.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Interaction between the status of the biomarker TP53 and response to treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>weeks 12-16 after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Primary outcome measure is the interaction between the status of the biomarker TP53 and response to radiation.
The TP53 maker status is determined by standardized gene specific sequencing of the TP53 using DNA from formalin fixed paraffin embedded material from diagnostic biopsies.
Response to treatment is determined by &quot;down sizing&quot; - down sizing will be measured by comparison of pretreatment T stage with pathohistological post treatment T stage . Pretreatement T stage is assessed with MRI, and supported by endosonography. Posttreatment T stage will be assessed prior to operation with MRI and after resection in the pathohistological specimen. The postreatment MRI results will be compared pathohistology.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>pCR rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12-16 weeks after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>pCR - pathohistological complete resmission as assessed in surgical specimen</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>complete resection rate</measure>
    <time_frame>12-16 weeks after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Patholohistological assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>local and distant relapse</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>preoperative short course radiation</arm_group_label>
    <description>preoperative short course radiation with 8 weeks delay of surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>preoperative short course radiation</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>preoperative short course radiation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      whole blood diagnostic tumor biopsy
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Rectal cancer patients with clinical staging T2/T3 Nx M0
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Patients who are eligible for this observational study will be treated according to current
        standards with preoperative short course radiation (5x5 Gy) and a subsequent interval to
        surgery of at least 8 to maximum 16 weeks.

        According to standards of rectal cancer therapy, eligible patients will meet the following
        criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the rectum

          -  Tumor staging with MRI

          -  Inferior margin of the tumor located not farther than 15 cm from anal verge and below
             the level of S1-2

          -  Tumor stage T2 and T3

          -  No evidence of metastatic disease

          -  No prior tumor therapy for rectal or pelvic cancers (surgery, radio-, chemo-,
             immunotherapy, molecular target therapy, or any other type of tumor therapy)

          -  Medical fitness of the patient for treatment (decided by the involved physician)

          -  Patient compliance

          -  Signed informed consent from the patient or a legal representative, for the analysis
             of the tumor including genetic analyses of the tumor DNA.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients will be excluded from the study for any of the following reasons

          -  Clinical stage T1 (appropriate for local excision),

          -  Clinical stage T4 (Radio/Chemotherapy)

          -  Clinical stage M+ (distant metastases)

          -  No tumor staging with MRI

          -  Inoperability (technical or functional)

          -  Prior tumor therapy of the pelvis

          -  Concurrent administration of any other tumor therapy

          -  Second primary malignancy that is clinically detectable at the time of consideration
             for study enrollment

          -  Serious concomitant disorders or attitudes of the patient that would compromise the
             safety of the patient or his/her ability to complete the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniela Kandioler, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>MUW</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Daniela Kandioler, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+43 1 40400 56210</phone>
    <email>daniela.kandioler@meduniwien.ac.at</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of Vienna, Department of Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.p53.at</url>
    <description>Homepage of the p53-research group</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kandioler D, Zwrtek R, Ludwig C, Janschek E, Ploner M, Hofbauer F, Kührer I, Kappel S, Wrba F, Horvath M, Karner J, Renner K, Bergmann M, Karner-Hanusch J, Pötter R, Jakesz R, Teleky B, Herbst F. TP53 genotype but not p53 immunohistochemical result predicts response to preoperative short-term radiotherapy in rectal cancer. Ann Surg. 2002 Apr;235(4):493-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11923604</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 14, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 16, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of Vienna</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Daniela Kandioler</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Unif. Prof. Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>preoperative short course radiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>delay of surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>rectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>TP53</keyword>
  <keyword>predictive marker</keyword>
  <keyword>MRT imaging</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

