<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02141555</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140250</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02141555</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparing Buccal and Vaginal Misoprostol in Management of Early Pregnancy Loss</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparing Buccal and Vaginal Misoprostol in Management of Early Pregnancy Loss: a Pilot Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Diego</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Diego</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      First trimester miscarriages are common. When the failed pregnancy does not pass
      spontaneously on its own, it is called a missed abortion. There are several ways in which
      missed abortions are managed, one of which involves administering a medication called
      misoprostol which causes uterine contractions inducing expulsion of the failed pregnancy.
      Misoprostol can be administered in multiple ways but has been traditionally inserted
      vaginally when used for management of missed abortions. Some studies have shown that some
      women are not comfortable with vaginal insertion of misoprostol and prefer oral
      administration. Buccal misoprostol is a way of administering misoprostol by having the
      patients insert the tablets of misoprostol between their gum and cheek, letting it dissolve
      for 30 minutes, then swallowing the remaining remnants. Buccal misoprostol is used safely in
      medical abortion. In fact a study by Fjerstad et al (2009), found a decrease in infection
      rate for medical abortion when misoprostol administration was switched from vaginal to buccal
      route combined with routine administration of doxycycline. The efficacy of using buccal
      misoprostol to treat missed abortions has not been studied previously to the investigators'
      knowledge. In this pilot study, investigators aim to test the hypotheses that buccal
      misoprostol is equally effective as vaginal misoprostol in the medical management of early
      pregnancy loss. As secondary outcomes, investigators suspect that buccal misoprostol may be
      associated with higher rates of gastrointestinal side effect but that patient satisfaction
      will remain equally as high for buccal misoprostol as for vaginal misoprostol.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Randomization:

      Women who present to UCSD Medical Offices South clinic for evaluation and management of
      missed abortion will all be sent to the lab prior to the clinic visit for a type and screen
      and hemogram to determine blood type and hemoglobin level as is the current standard of care.
      Each woman will then be screened by a physician. The physician will notify a co-investigator
      of eligible patients who are interested in participating in the study. The co-investigator
      will consent the patient for the study. Once the written consent is obtained, patient will be
      asked to fill out an intake survey to obtain demographic information. Participants will be
      randomized into either the vaginal or buccal misoprostol group with a block size of four.
      Assignments will be concealed in sequentially numbered sealed opaque envelope. The envelope
      will be opened by the co-investigator who will reveal the route of misoprostol to the patient
      and review the written instructions on how to take the medication appropriately. Given the
      different routes of administration, neither the patient nor the provider will be blinded.
      Given that one of the secondary outcomes of interest was patient satisfaction based on the
      different route of administration, decision was made to not use placebo pills which could
      have been used to do a double-blinded study.

      Intervention:

      Dose of Misoprostol for both treatment groups: 800 micrograms administered as four tablets of
      200 micrograms.

      Currently, the standard of care is to prescribe vaginal misoprostol 800 mcg for women with an
      early pregnancy failure desiring medical management. The only &quot;intervention&quot; in this study is
      to change the route of administration from vaginal to buccal for the women randomized to this
      group. The dose of misoprostol, follow up plan (including ultrasound) and prescription for
      pain medications (described below) is unchanged from the current standard of care.
      Participants randomized to the vaginal misoprostol group will be instructed to insert four
      misoprostol tablets (total of 800 micrograms) deeply into the vagina with their fingers.
      Participants randomized to the buccal misoprostol group will be instructed to place two
      tablets of misoprostol between their gum and cheek on each side (total 800 micrograms), then
      swish and swallow the remnants after 30 minutes. If the patient is Rh negative, the patient
      will be given a dose of rhogam 300 mcg at the initial visit which is the current standard of
      care.

      Patients will be prescribed an additional dose of misoprostol 800 mcg that they can take at
      their own discretion in the absence of vaginal bleeding 48 hours from initial dose using the
      same route of administration as the first dose. All participants will be prescribed ibuprofen
      with instructions to take 600 mg every 6 hours as needed for pain and a narcotic medication
      for breakthrough pain. The cost of these medications will be fully covered by the
      participant's insurance with no additional cost to the participant.

      Follow up will be a clinic visit scheduled one week from the from the initial visit at UCSD
      Medical Offices South Clinic which time the participant will fill out a follow up survey
      assessing the participant's satisfaction and side effects experienced. The provider will also
      fill out a survey at this 1-week follow up visit assessing the success of the misoprostol in
      achieving a complete abortion. The participant's involvement in the study will conclude at
      this end of this one-week follow up visit.

      Participant Commitment:

      The research will require the following additional time commitment from participant in
      addition to the standard clinic visit:

        1. Initial Visit: An additional 20 minutes will be required to review the study consent,
           randomize to the vaginal or buccal misoprostol group, and have the patient fill out a
           short intake survey.

        2. Follow-up visit: The follow up visit will take one week from time of initial visit. An
           additional 10 minutes will be required to fill out the follow up survey. The
           participant's involvement in the study will conclude with this visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient enrollment</measure>
    <time_frame>One year</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of women who are offered enrollment and accept.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete abortion</measure>
    <time_frame>one week</time_frame>
    <description>Complete abortion without surgical intervention defined as no evidence of a gestational sac on transvaginal ultrasound at the follow up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>one week</time_frame>
    <description>Written surveys patients will fill out at follow up visit assessing patient's satisfaction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication side effects</measure>
    <time_frame>one week</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of medication side effects including: nausea, vomiting, headache, fever (&gt; 100.4 F), dizziness, diarrhea, bad taste, dry mouth</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Spontaneous Abortion in First Trimester</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vaginal misoprostol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will insert four misoprostol tablets (total of 800 micrograms) deeply into the vagina with their fingers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Buccal Misoprostol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will place two tablets of misoprostol between their gum and cheek on each side (total 800 micrograms), then swish and swallow the remnants after 30 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vaginal Misoprostol</intervention_name>
    <description>Misoprostol inserted into vagina</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vaginal misoprostol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vaginal Cytotec</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Buccal Misoprostol</intervention_name>
    <description>Misoprostol placed between the gum and cheek and allowed to dissolve for 30 minutes with the remnants swallowed after this time.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Buccal Misoprostol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Buccal Cytotec</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women ages 18-50 who are English or Spanish speaking

          -  First trimester pregnancy (less than 13 weeks and 0 days)

          -  Desires medical management of an early pregnancy loss with misoprostol

          -  Diagnosed with an early pregnancy failure by UCSD Radiology or diagnosed early
             pregnancy failure defined by any of the following criteria (Bourne 2013):

               -  Crown-rump length &gt; 7mm with no cardiac activity

               -  Mean gestational sac diameter of &gt; 25 mm and no embryo

               -  Absence of an embryo with heartbeat &gt; 2 weeks after a scan showing a gestational
                  sac without a yolk sac

               -  Absence of embryo with heartbeat &gt; 11 days after a scan showing a gestational sac
                  with a yolk sac

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Evidence of infection, acute hemorrhage, or hemodynamic instability

          -  Hemoglobin less than 9.5 including use of point of care Hgb testing

          -  Known allergy to misoprostol

          -  Underwent surgical or medical abortion during current pregnancy

          -  History of clotting disorder or on anticoagulant therapy (excluding aspirin)

          -  Unreliable for follow up
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janie Pak, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Diego</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sheila Mody, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Diego</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Janie Pak, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>8188134417</phone>
    <email>jop047@ucsd.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sheila Mody, MD</last_name>
    <phone>6195437878</phone>
    <email>smody@ucsd.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California San Diego Medical Offices South Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Janie Pak, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>818-813-4417</phone>
      <email>jop047@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sheila Mody, MD</last_name>
      <phone>6195437878</phone>
      <email>smody@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Janie Pak, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sheila Mody, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aronsson A, Fiala C, Stephansson O, Granath F, Watzer B, Schweer H, Gemzell-Danielsson K. Pharmacokinetic profiles up to 12 h after administration of vaginal, sublingual and slow-release oral misoprostol. Hum Reprod. 2007 Jul;22(7):1912-8. Epub 2007 May 8.</citation>
    <PMID>17488782</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Doubilet PM, Benson CB, Bourne T, Blaivas M; Society of Radiologists in Ultrasound Multispecialty Panel on Early First Trimester Diagnosis of Miscarriage and Exclusion of a Viable Intrauterine Pregnancy, Barnhart KT, Benacerraf BR, Brown DL, Filly RA, Fox JC, Goldstein SR, Kendall JL, Lyons EA, Porter MB, Pretorius DH, Timor-Tritsch IE. Diagnostic criteria for nonviable pregnancy early in the first trimester. N Engl J Med. 2013 Oct 10;369(15):1443-51. doi: 10.1056/NEJMra1302417. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24106937</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Danielsson KG, Marions L, Rodriguez A, Spur BW, Wong PY, Bygdeman M. Comparison between oral and vaginal administration of misoprostol on uterine contractility. Obstet Gynecol. 1999 Feb;93(2):275-80.</citation>
    <PMID>9932569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fjerstad M, Trussell J, Sivin I, Lichtenberg ES, Cullins V. Rates of serious infection after changes in regimens for medical abortion. N Engl J Med. 2009 Jul 9;361(2):145-51. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0809146.</citation>
    <PMID>19587339</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones RK, Kost K. Underreporting of induced and spontaneous abortion in the United States: an analysis of the 2002 National Survey of Family Growth. Stud Fam Plann. 2007 Sep;38(3):187-97.</citation>
    <PMID>17933292</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herting RL, Clay GA. Overview of clinical safety with misoprostol. Dig Dis Sci. 1985 Nov;30(11 Suppl):185S-193S.</citation>
    <PMID>3932053</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meckstroth KR, Whitaker AK, Bertisch S, Goldberg AB, Darney PD. Misoprostol administered by epithelial routes: Drug absorption and uterine response. Obstet Gynecol. 2006 Sep;108(3 Pt 1):582-90.</citation>
    <PMID>16946218</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Middleton T, Schaff E, Fielding SL, Scahill M, Shannon C, Westheimer E, Wilkinson T, Winikoff B. Randomized trial of mifepristone and buccal or vaginal misoprostol for abortion through 56 days of last menstrual period. Contraception. 2005 Nov;72(5):328-32. Epub 2005 Aug 9.</citation>
    <PMID>16246656</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tang OS, Gemzell-Danielsson K, Ho PC. Misoprostol: pharmacokinetic profiles, effects on the uterus and side-effects. Int J Gynaecol Obstet. 2007 Dec;99 Suppl 2:S160-7. Epub 2007 Oct 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17963768</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saraiya M, Berg CJ, Shulman H, Green CA, Atrash HK. Estimates of the annual number of clinically recognized pregnancies in the United States, 1981-1991. Am J Epidemiol. 1999 Jun 1;149(11):1025-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10355378</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schaff EA, DiCenzo R, Fielding SL. Comparison of misoprostol plasma concentrations following buccal and sublingual administration. Contraception. 2005 Jan;71(1):22-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15639067</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schaff EA, Fielding SL, Westhoff C. Randomized trial of oral versus vaginal misoprostol at one day after mifepristone for early medical abortion. Contraception. 2001 Aug;64(2):81-5.</citation>
    <PMID>11704083</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sedgh G, Henshaw S, Singh S, Ahman E, Shah IH. Induced abortion: estimated rates and trends worldwide. Lancet. 2007 Oct 13;370(9595):1338-45.</citation>
    <PMID>17933648</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilcox AJ, Weinberg CR, O'Connor JF, Baird DD, Schlatterer JP, Canfield RE, Armstrong EG, Nisula BC. Incidence of early loss of pregnancy. N Engl J Med. 1988 Jul 28;319(4):189-94.</citation>
    <PMID>3393170</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Winikoff B, Dzuba IG, Creinin MD, Crowden WA, Goldberg AB, Gonzales J, Howe M, Moskowitz J, Prine L, Shannon CS. Two distinct oral routes of misoprostol in mifepristone medical abortion: a randomized controlled trial. Obstet Gynecol. 2008 Dec;112(6):1303-10. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0b013e31818d8eb4.</citation>
    <PMID>19037040</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 10, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 14, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 19, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 14, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 14, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 19, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Diego</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sheila Mody</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Adjunct Professor, Section of Family Planning</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>misoprostol, early pregnancy loss, missed abortion</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Abortion, Spontaneous</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Misoprostol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

