<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02142699</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SE01047</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2014-001021-32</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02142699</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Heme Arginate in Cardiac Surgery Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>HACS</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Heme Arginate in Patients Planned for Cardiac Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Edinburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical Research Council</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>NHS Lothian</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Edinburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A recent analysis of over 4500 cardiac surgical patients at the Royal Infirmary of Edinburgh
      has confirmed that acute kidney injury (AKI) is not only a relatively common post-operative
      complication but is associated with prolonged hospital stay, and increased risk of death.
      There is currently no specific therapy available except supportive care.

      In laboratory studies, heme arginate (HA), a drug licensed for human use, has been shown to
      upregulate the anti-inflammatory enzyme hemeoxygenase-1 (HO-1) and protect aged mice from
      acute kidney injury.

      This study will bring this research into the human arena. It will aim to evaluate the minimum
      effective dose of HA and verify its safety in this specific group of patients. This will be
      the next step in investigating if HA could be a potential protective treatment for reducing
      AKI in patients about to have cardiac surgery.

      Patients who are due to have cardiac surgery and are aged 60 or above will be approached for
      inclusion in the study. If agreeable, they will be randomly assigned to receive either HA at
      a dose of 1mg/kg or 3mg/kg. There will be 10 patients in each group.

      Blood tests will be taken just before the study drug is given, at 6 hours, 24 hours and 7
      days post dose. These samples will be used to examine the effect of HA on HO-1 at different
      doses, and will verify drug safety. Any adverse effects of the drug will be evaluated,
      although HA has an excellent safety profile when used as it is currently licensed for acute
      porphyria. Urine samples will also be collected to assess inflammation and quantify urinary
      biomarkers of AKI. This will set the scene for a randomised clinical trial of HA in cardiac
      surgical patients at high risk of AKI.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      AKI is a common condition which carries significant morbidity and mortality and has no
      current treatment except supportive care.

      Cardiac surgery remains the standard of care for the revascularisation of the most severe
      coronary artery disease despite improvements in percutaneous coronary intervention. The
      nature of such surgery confers an ischaemic renal insult and it follows on that AKI is a
      relatively common complication. However, the reported incidence of AKI post cardiac surgery
      varies widely depending on the diagnostic criteria used. A recent retrospective analysis of
      4572 cardiac surgical patients at the Royal Infirmary of Edinburgh over a 5 year period
      showed that 12.4% developed AKI by AKIN criteria post operatively. This was associated with
      an increased risk of death and prolonged inpatient stay.

      Pre-clinical studies in murine models of ischaemia reperfusion injury (IRI) have demonstrated
      that the anti-inflammatory enzyme HO-1 is of interest as a potential target for therapeutic
      intervention. Heme arginate (HA) is a drug licensed for human use, as a treatment for acute
      porphyria. HA upregulates HO-1, and ameliorates IRI when given before injury in murine models
      of IRI. In Phase I clinical trials, HA has been shown to upregulate HO-1 and is well
      tolerated.

      This is a single-blinded randomised trial of Heme arginate (HA) in patients who are due to
      have cardiac surgery. The aim of the study is to investigate the efficacy of HA in HO-1
      upregulation and its safety in this patient cohort. This will inform a further clinical trial
      of HA as a preventative treatment for AKI in patients undergoing cardiac surgery.

      Methods

      Eligible patients will be those planned for elective cardiac surgery, identified at their
      Cardiothoracic outpatient clinic assessment, aged 60 or above.

      HA (3mg/kg) upregulates HO-1 mRNA up to 2-fold at 24 hours post dose in healthy young
      volunteers. Power calculations based on an 80% power (at p&lt;0.05) to detect at least 2 fold
      upregulation of HO-1 protein by western blot necessitate 2 groups of 10 (assuming standard
      deviation (SD) of ±1.5x). 20 patients will be recruited (10 per group).

      Patients who agree to participate will be invited up for a study visit to the Clinical
      Research Facility at the Royal Infirmary of Edinburgh (RIE). If consent is given,
      participants will be randomised to receive HA at a dose of either 1 or 3mg/kg (maximum
      250mg). Prior to the dose being given, routine observations (including blood pressure, pulse,
      respiratory rate, oxygen saturations and temperature) will be taken, and the trial team
      member will perform a routine examination of the cardiac and respiratory systems. An
      electrocardiogram (ecg) will be done for reference.

      Blood samples to assess HO-1 expression in circulating monocytes will be taken prior to the
      administration of the study drug, and at 24 hours post dose. Samples for routine blood tests
      including full blood count (FBC), urea and electrolytes (U&amp;E), C-reactive protein (CRP),
      liver function tests (LFT), and ferritin will be taken alongside those for monocyte
      isolation, with a further set on day 7. Serum (and urine) will be frozen for batch analysis
      and monocytes will be isolated by in-house protocols. Routine blood tests will be processed
      at the biochemistry and haematology laboratories at the RIE as per their usual methods.

      Urine samples will be collected before the study drug is given, and at 24 hours and 7 days
      post dose. Urinalysis will be performed, and microalbuminuria and urinary biomarkers of
      tubular injury neutrophil gelatinase associated lipocalin(NGAL), interleukin 18(IL-18) &amp;
      kidney injury molecule 1(KIM-1) will be quantified.

      Routine clinical observations will be carried out for 6 hours post dose, at which time the
      patient will be allowed home in the absence of any adverse events. A second study visit at
      the Clinical Research Facility will be scheduled for 24 hours post dose (day 1), with a third
      study visit on day 7.

      The second and third study visits will allow reporting of any adverse events, as well as an
      opportunity to perform routine observations and take further blood samples for HO-1 induction
      and in order to analyse safety.

      All patients will be genotyped for the short or long repeat HO-1 promoter polymorphism
      (either homozygous or heterozygous) though this has not been shown to affect HO-1 induction
      by HA in previous studies.

      The RIE cardiac surgery unit performs approximately 1000 cases per year, with just less than
      80% aged 60 or over from our analysis of 4572 patients. A conservative estimate for time to
      meet recruitment to the study is 3 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Upregulation of Heme oxygenase-1 protein expression in circulating monocytes</measure>
    <time_frame>within 3 months of study completion</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Upregulation of heme oxygenase-1 messenger ribonucleic acid (mRNA) in circulating monocytes</measure>
    <time_frame>within 3 months of completion</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary biomarkers of acute kidney injury</measure>
    <time_frame>within 3 months of completion of study</time_frame>
    <description>Samples will be collected pre dose and at 24 hrs and 7 days to determine the effect (if any) of Heme arginate on levels of urinary biomarkers of AKI in order to inform future interventional trials</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>at final study visit ie 7 days post dose (or at the resolution of any ongoing adverse event if this lasts longer than 7 days)</time_frame>
    <description>This will be a composite outcome measure consisting of multiple routine measures of safety including adverse event reporting, and the biochemical and haematological data collected (eg renal function, liver function tests, full blood count)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heme oxygenase-1 (HO-1) Genotype</measure>
    <time_frame>within 3 months of study completion</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will have their genotype for HO-1 gene recorded (for the long (L) or short (S) promoter region)- therefore they will be either LL, LS or SS. The study is not powered to detect any difference but will inform future studies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Kidney Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Heme arginate 1mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is the lower of the 2 doses of Heme arginate (HA). This will be given as a single dose of 1mg/kg on the first study visit.
This is given over 1 hour intravenously.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Heme arginate 3mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is the larger dose, Heme arginate 3mg/kg (up to a maximum dose of 250mg)
This will be given intravenously, as a single dose on the first study visit, over one hour.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Heme arginate</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Heme arginate 1mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Heme arginate 3mg/kg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Normosang (Orphan Europe)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Age ≥60

        Planned for elective cardiac surgical procedure:

          -  Aortic valve replacement

          -  CABG

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Inability to give informed consent Hypersensitivity to HA Enrolment in other clinical
        trials Renal replacement therapy Planned for elective cardiac surgical procedure other than
        CABG or AVR (including combined CABG and AVR) Less than 2 weeks until planned cardiac
        surgery at time of study drug administration Active infection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeremy Hughes, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Professor of Experimental Nephrology, University of Edinburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David C Kluth, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Reader in Nephrology, University of Edinburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vipin Zamvar, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Royal Infirmary of Edinburgh, NHS Lothian</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Fiona AI Duthie, MD</last_name>
    <phone>007764946050</phone>
    <email>fduthie@staffmail.ed.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Infirmary of Edinburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edinburgh</city>
        <state>Midlothian</state>
        <zip>EH16 4SA</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Fiona AI Duthie, MD</last_name>
      <phone>00447764946050</phone>
      <email>fduthie@staffmail.ed.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 9, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 15, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 20, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 20, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acute kidney injury</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Ischaemia reperfusion injury</keyword>
  <keyword>hemearginate</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acute Kidney Injury</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

