<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02146573</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB 14-010987</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02146573</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pediatric Continuity Care Intensivist</brief_title>
  <acronym>CCI</acronym>
  <official_title>Pediatric Continuity Care Intensivist: Role Implementation and Randomized Control Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will implement and evaluate the effects of a pediatric continuity care intensivist
      program. This study will determine the impact of an additional pediatric intensive care unit
      (PICU) intensivist on outcomes at the patient and family level. It will also evaluate the
      training program to prepare the continuity care intensivist (CCI).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This randomized controlled trial will implement and evaluate the effects of a pediatric
      continuity care intensivist (CCI) program. The study will evaluate how effective the modified
      communication training for providers is to perform this new role. The primary outcome for the
      study is whether a CCI will affect several patient level outcomes for patients who have been
      admitted to the PICU longer than 7 days. Patient length of stay, hospital acquired
      conditions, time to limitations of interventions and new medical technology will be assessed
      comparing the intervention and usual care arms. The study will also determine the impact of
      the CCI program on parent/family satisfaction with provider communication and decision-making
      for their child.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in patient length of stay in the PICU between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Length of stay as measured by the Virtual PICU system (VPS) in the PICU.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in number of new technological dependence patients acquire during hospitalization between usual care and intervention arms</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure new technology dependence like tracheostomy, gastrostomy tube, long term ventilation, bipap using VPS during the PICU hospitalization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in patient hospital-acquired conditions between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Using VPS, investigators will track hospital acquired infections like catheter associated urinary tract infections and ventilator associated pneumonias</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in patient length of time on sedation medicines between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will track the length of time on sedation medications used during intubations and when there is other medical equipment like chest tubes that it is not safe for patients to be moving. These medications include midazolam and fentanyl among others.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in patients' new or progressive multiple organ dysfunction syndrome between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will use the VPS designation of multiple organ dysfunction syndrome to characterize system failures like respiratory, renal, cardiac failure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in patient organ failure free days between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will use the VPS designation of organ failure for systems like renal, respiratory and cardiac.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in patient ventilator free days between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will use the VPS designation for days up to 90 that the patient remains off of mechanical ventilation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in change in parent preferences for shared decision-making from baseline to patient discharge between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>A decision-analysis method will be used to administer and measure parental preferences for shared decision-making. Validation of the measure is completed but not yet published by the principal investigator.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in change in parent preferences for control in decision-making from baseline to patient discharge between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>The Control Preferences Scale for Pediatrics (CPS-P), a validated tool, will be used to measure parent's preferences for control in decision-making.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Affects of Parent attachment style on communication preferences</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The Relationship Questionnaire, a validated measure, will be used to measure parent relationship style, which is based on attachment theory.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in change in parental levels of anxiety and depression from baseline to patient discharge between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Parental levels of hospital anxiety and depression will be measured using the Hospital Anxiety and Depression scale (HADS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in change in parental levels of positive and negative affect from baseline to patient discharge between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Parental levels of positive and negative affect will be measured using the Positive and Negative Affect Scale (PANAS), a validated tool.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in change in parental levels of anger from baseline to patient discharge between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Parent levels of anger will be measured using PROMIS bank v1.1- Anger scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in change in parental levels of hope from baseline to patient discharge between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Parental levels of hope will be measured using the Hope Scale, a validated tool.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in change in Parent/family satisfaction with decision-making from baseline to patient discharge between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Parent satisfaction with decision-making will measured through several question items designed to assess parent satisfaction with making decisions during their child's PICU visit. This measure was developed through extensive literature review and has been evaluated for face validity through cognitive interviewing and pilot testing with parents and families of children admitted to the ICU.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in parent/family satisfaction with communication with their child's PICU physicians between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>The Pediatric Family Satisfaction in the Intensive Care Unit (pFS-ICU), a validated tool, will be used to measure parent satisfaction with communication with their child's PICU physician.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in change in parent self-report of medical communication competence from baseline to patient discharge between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>The Medical Communication Competence Scale, a partially validated tool, will be used to measure parent self-reported competency with communication.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in change in parent assessment of physician communication competency from baseline to patient discharge between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>The Communication Assessment Tool (CAT), a validated tool, will be used to measure parent perceptions of physician competence in interpersonal and communication skills.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of physician burnout between intervention and control group from baseline up to 600 days</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>The Maslach Stress and Burnout Inventory, a validated tool, will be used to measure the three aspects of the burnout syndrome: emotional exhaustion, depersonalization, and lack of personal accomplishment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician satisfaction with the communication training and with the CCI experience.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Questions written for this study that have been written and piloted will assess the physicians' satisfaction and perceived usefulness of the communication training.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of CCI provider experience in role of CCI and its feasibility of larger implementation</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Both open ended survey questions and focus groups will be qualitatively analyzed to determine the benefits and burdens for providers of serving in the CCI role.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of physician comfort with end-of-life communication between intervention and control group from baseline up to 600 days</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Physician comfort with end-of-life communication will be measured through several question items developed to assess how physicians feel about engaging in end of life discussions. The measure was developed through extensive literature review and has been evaluated for face validity through cognitive interviewing and pilot testing with PICU physicians.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in timing of patient's limitations of interventions to death between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>As measured by a chart review of timing of limitations of interventions including do not resuscitate (DNR)/ do not intubate (DNI) and other limitations like no escalation of care will be described and the time to event of death will be compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of palliative care consultation between usual care and intervention arm</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Medical chart review to determine request for and consultation performed by Pediatric Advanced Care Team (palliative care consultation service) will be measured and compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physician competency in communication with families via objective structured clinical examination (OSCE) evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>CCI providers will be evaluated using a simulated patient and scored using a validated tool for communication skills including empathy in an encounter in the end-of-life setting.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of physician self-reported communication competency between intervention and control group</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>The Medical Communication Competence Scale, a partially validated measure will be used to assess physician self-reported competency.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between amount of CCI contact and parent and patient level outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, up to 600 days</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will categorize the extent of CCI contact and then determine if there is a correlation between amount of contact and parent and patient level outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">276</enrollment>
  <condition>Critical Illness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CCI Provider for Parent-patient dyad</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parents and patients are randomly assigned to a Continuity Care Intensivist (CCI) Provider who has received specialized communication training. The parent-patient dyad will receive standardized care from the CCI throughout their time in the PICU in addition to being assigned a rotating physician of record.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care for Parent-patient dyad</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients and parents randomly assigned to usual care in the PICU which includes the rotation of the physician of record approximately every 7 days. There is no standardized process by which patients may be assigned a primary attending who would follow them throughout their stay. In the usual care arm it may never happen that they are assigned a primary intensivist, regardless of the length of their hospitalization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Continuity Care Intensivist Communication Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Physicians enrolled in the intervention arm will complete a two to three part communication training. Survey measures of communication competency and burnout will be administered at baseline, after training, and at the end of the study. After the communication training, physicians will undergo an OSCE assessment with a simulated patient to evaluate communication skills. At the end of the study, CCI providers will receive surveys that assess the experience and challenges of the role, repeat surveys assessing competency with communication and frequency of engaging families in goals of care conversations, in addition to a follow-up focus group that will assess their experience with the intervention, the time required and the potential tradeoffs in other duties required by them to participate as a CCI.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CCI Provider for Parent-patient dyad</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CCI Communication Training</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Continuity Care Intensivist (CCI) Provider Program</intervention_name>
    <description>After undergoing CCI training, CCI providers will fulfill a standardized role with parent-patient dyads:
CCI will meet with families on a regular basis and at change of physician of record throughout their entire PICU hospitalization.
Help patients/families navigate decisions in concert with preferences and beliefs
Help patients/families and other care providers look at &quot;bigger picture&quot;; trajectory of illness, goals, and hopes for the patient.
Serve as point person for active intensivists on service and other specialists
Help resolve conflict when multiple providers have different opinions on course of action</description>
    <arm_group_label>CCI Provider for Parent-patient dyad</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CCI Provider</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        CCI Provider

        1. Pediatric Intensive Care Unit Attending Physician who volunteers to serve in the role of
        CCI.

        Usual Care (UC) Provider

        1. Any Pediatric Intensive Care Unit Attending Physician who is not enrolled as a CCI.

        Parent-Patient Dyads

          1. Parent/guardian of a child who has been admitted to the Children's Hospital of
             Philadelphia (CHOP) PICU for ≥7 days after onset of the study

          2. Parent/guardian ≥ 18 years old

          3. Parent/guardian is English-speaking

          4. Child &lt;18 years old at time of enrollment

          5. Child has been admitted to the PICU at CHOP for ≥7 days following onset of study

          6. Patients are also eligible if, at the time the study is initiated, they have been in
             the PICU for less than seven days

        Exclusion Criteria:

        CCI Provider

        1. Any medical care provider who is not an attending physician (e.g., Pediatric critical
        care residents, nurses, and fellows)

        UC Provider

          1. Any medical care provider who is not an attending physician (e.g., Pediatric critical
             care residents, nurses, and fellows)

          2. Attending physician who is enrolled in the study as a CCI

        Parent-Patient Dyads

          1. Parent or guardian who has previously participated in the CCI study in a previous
             hospitalization (in either usual care or intervention arm)

          2. Parent or guardian of a child who has already been hospitalized in the PICU &gt;7 days at
             the onset of the study.

          3. Child ≥18 years of age at time of enrollment

          4. Child is an emancipated minor.

          5. Child has previously participated in the CCI study in a previous PICU stay (in either
             usual care or intervention arm)

          6. Child has been hospitalized in the PICU &gt;7 days at the onset of the study

          7. Child already has a &quot;primary&quot; attending

          8. Child has a sibling that has already been enrolled in the study. This child will be
             ineligible for the study but will be assigned to the same care as the child who is or
             was enrolled in the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer K Walter, MD, PhD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Board R, Ryan-Wenger N. Long-term effects of pediatric intensive care unit hospitalization on families with young children. Heart Lung. 2002 Jan-Feb;31(1):53-66.</citation>
    <PMID>11805751</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Balluffi A, Kassam-Adams N, Kazak A, Tucker M, Dominguez T, Helfaer M. Traumatic stress in parents of children admitted to the pediatric intensive care unit. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2004 Nov;5(6):547-53.</citation>
    <PMID>15530191</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Needle JS, O'Riordan M, Smith PG. Parental anxiety and medical comprehension within 24 hrs of a child's admission to the pediatric intensive care unit*. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2009 Nov;10(6):668-74; quiz 674. doi: 10.1097/PCC.0b013e3181a706c9.</citation>
    <PMID>19451843</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pochard F, Darmon M, Fassier T, Bollaert PE, Cheval C, Coloigner M, Merouani A, Moulront S, Pigne E, Pingat J, Zahar JR, Schlemmer B, Azoulay E; French FAMIREA study group. Symptoms of anxiety and depression in family members of intensive care unit patients before discharge or death. A prospective multicenter study. J Crit Care. 2005 Mar;20(1):90-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16015522</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fauman KR, Pituch KJ, Han YY, Niedner MF, Reske J, LeVine AM. Predictors of depressive symptoms in parents of chronically ill children admitted to the pediatric intensive care unit. Am J Hosp Palliat Care. 2011 Dec;28(8):556-63. doi: 10.1177/1049909111403465. Epub 2011 Mar 30.</citation>
    <PMID>21454321</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nuss SL, Hinds PS, LaFond DA. Collaborative clinical research on end-of-life care in pediatric oncology. Semin Oncol Nurs. 2005 May;21(2):125-34; discussion 134-44. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15991662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Diaz-Caneja A, Gledhill J, Weaver T, Nadel S, Garralda E. A child's admission to hospital: a qualitative study examining the experiences of parents. Intensive Care Med. 2005 Sep;31(9):1248-54. Epub 2005 Jul 15.</citation>
    <PMID>16021417</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Colville G, Darkins J, Hesketh J, Bennett V, Alcock J, Noyes J. The impact on parents of a child's admission to intensive care: integration of qualitative findings from a cross-sectional study. Intensive Crit Care Nurs. 2009 Apr;25(2):72-9. doi: 10.1016/j.iccn.2008.10.002. Epub 2008 Nov 18.</citation>
    <PMID>19019677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Back AL, Arnold RM, Baile WF, Fryer-Edwards KA, Alexander SC, Barley GE, Gooley TA, Tulsky JA. Efficacy of communication skills training for giving bad news and discussing transitions to palliative care. Arch Intern Med. 2007 Mar 12;167(5):453-60.</citation>
    <PMID>17353492</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davidson JE, Powers K, Hedayat KM, Tieszen M, Kon AA, Shepard E, Spuhler V, Todres ID, Levy M, Barr J, Ghandi R, Hirsch G, Armstrong D; American College of Critical Care Medicine Task Force 2004-2005, Society of Critical Care Medicine. Clinical practice guidelines for support of the family in the patient-centered intensive care unit: American College of Critical Care Medicine Task Force 2004-2005. Crit Care Med. 2007 Feb;35(2):605-22.</citation>
    <PMID>17205007</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Namachivayam P, Shann F, Shekerdemian L, Taylor A, van Sloten I, Delzoppo C, Daffey C, Butt W. Three decades of pediatric intensive care: Who was admitted, what happened in intensive care, and what happened afterward. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2010 Sep;11(5):549-55. doi: 10.1097/PCC.0b013e3181ce7427.</citation>
    <PMID>20124947</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feudtner C, Christakis DA, Connell FA. Pediatric deaths attributable to complex chronic conditions: a population-based study of Washington State, 1980-1997. Pediatrics. 2000 Jul;106(1 Pt 2):205-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10888693</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Azoulay E, Pochard F, Chevret S, Lemaire F, Mokhtari M, Le Gall JR, Dhainaut JF, Schlemmer B; French FAMIREA Group. Meeting the needs of intensive care unit patient families: a multicenter study. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2001 Jan;163(1):135-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11208638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson D, Wilson M, Cavanaugh B, Bryden C, Gudmundson D, Moodley O. Measuring the ability to meet family needs in an intensive care unit. Crit Care Med. 1998 Feb;26(2):266-71.</citation>
    <PMID>9468163</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Curtis JR, Ciechanowski PS, Downey L, Gold J, Nielsen EL, Shannon SE, Treece PD, Young JP, Engelberg RA. Development and evaluation of an interprofessional communication intervention to improve family outcomes in the ICU. Contemp Clin Trials. 2012 Nov;33(6):1245-54. doi: 10.1016/j.cct.2012.06.010. Epub 2012 Jul 6.</citation>
    <PMID>22772089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schneiderman LJ. Ethics consultation in the intensive care unit. Curr Opin Crit Care. 2005 Dec;11(6):600-4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16292067</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schneiderman LJ. Effect of ethics consultations in the intensive care unit. Crit Care Med. 2006 Nov;34(11 Suppl):S359-63.</citation>
    <PMID>17057599</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schneiderman LJ, Gilmer T, Teetzel HD. Impact of ethics consultations in the intensive care setting: a randomized, controlled trial. Crit Care Med. 2000 Dec;28(12):3920-4.</citation>
    <PMID>11153636</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schneiderman LJ, Gilmer T, Teetzel HD, Dugan DO, Blustein J, Cranford R, Briggs KB, Komatsu GI, Goodman-Crews P, Cohn F, Young EW. Effect of ethics consultations on nonbeneficial life-sustaining treatments in the intensive care setting: a randomized controlled trial. JAMA. 2003 Sep 3;290(9):1166-72.</citation>
    <PMID>12952998</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gilmer T, Schneiderman LJ, Teetzel H, Blustein J, Briggs K, Cohn F, Cranford R, Dugan D, Kamatsu G, Young E. The costs of nonbeneficial treatment in the intensive care setting. Health Aff (Millwood). 2005 Jul-Aug;24(4):961-71.</citation>
    <PMID>16136635</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Temel JS, Greer JA, Admane S, Gallagher ER, Jackson VA, Lynch TJ, Lennes IT, Dahlin CM, Pirl WF. Longitudinal perceptions of prognosis and goals of therapy in patients with metastatic non-small-cell lung cancer: results of a randomized study of early palliative care. J Clin Oncol. 2011 Jun 10;29(17):2319-26. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2010.32.4459. Epub 2011 May 9.</citation>
    <PMID>21555700</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Contro N, Larson J, Scofield S, Sourkes B, Cohen H. Family perspectives on the quality of pediatric palliative care. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2002 Jan;156(1):14-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11772185</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leach MJ. Rapport: a key to treatment success. Complement Ther Clin Pract. 2005 Nov;11(4):262-5. Epub 2005 Jun 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16290897</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kimberlin C, Brushwood D, Allen W, Radson E, Wilson D. Cancer patient and caregiver experiences: communication and pain management issues. J Pain Symptom Manage. 2004 Dec;28(6):566-78.</citation>
    <PMID>15589081</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DeLemos D, Chen M, Romer A, Brydon K, Kastner K, Anthony B, Hoehn KS. Building trust through communication in the intensive care unit: HICCC. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2010 May;11(3):378-84. doi: 10.1097/PCC.0b013e3181b8088b.</citation>
    <PMID>19770787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meert KL, Eggly S, Pollack M, Anand KJ, Zimmerman J, Carcillo J, Newth CJ, Dean JM, Willson DF, Nicholson C; National Institute of Child Health and Human Development Collaborative Pediatric Critical Care Research Network. Parents' perspectives on physician-parent communication near the time of a child's death in the pediatric intensive care unit. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2008 Jan;9(1):2-7. doi: 10.1097/01.PCC.0000298644.13882.88.</citation>
    <PMID>18477906</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heyland DK, Rocker GM, Dodek PM, Kutsogiannis DJ, Konopad E, Cook DJ, Peters S, Tranmer JE, O'Callaghan CJ. Family satisfaction with care in the intensive care unit: results of a multiple center study. Crit Care Med. 2002 Jul;30(7):1413-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12130954</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mack JW, Wolfe J, Cook EF, Grier HE, Cleary PD, Weeks JC. Hope and prognostic disclosure. J Clin Oncol. 2007 Dec 10;25(35):5636-42.</citation>
    <PMID>18065734</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Epstein D, Unger JB, Ornelas B, Chang JC, Markovitz BP, Moromisato DY, Dodek PM, Heyland DK, Gold JI. Psychometric evaluation of a modified version of the family satisfaction in the ICU survey in parents/caregivers of critically ill children*. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2013 Oct;14(8):e350-6. doi: 10.1097/PCC.0b013e3182917705.</citation>
    <PMID>23863815</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zigmond AS, Snaith RP. The hospital anxiety and depression scale. Acta Psychiatr Scand. 1983 Jun;67(6):361-70.</citation>
    <PMID>6880820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pyke-Grimm KA, Degner L, Small A, Mueller B. Preferences for participation in treatment decision making and information needs of parents of children with cancer: a pilot study. J Pediatr Oncol Nurs. 1999 Jan;16(1):13-24.</citation>
    <PMID>9989013</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cegala DJ, Coleman MT, Turner JW. The development and partial assessment of the medical communication competence scale. Health Commun. 1998;10(3):261-88.</citation>
    <PMID>16370986</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Snyder CR, Harris C, Anderson JR, Holleran SA, Irving LM, Sigmon ST, Yoshinobu L, Gibb J, Langelle C, Harney P. The will and the ways: development and validation of an individual-differences measure of hope. J Pers Soc Psychol. 1991 Apr;60(4):570-85.</citation>
    <PMID>2037968</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Makoul G, Krupat E, Chang CH. Measuring patient views of physician communication skills: development and testing of the Communication Assessment Tool. Patient Educ Couns. 2007 Aug;67(3):333-42. Epub 2007 Jun 18.</citation>
    <PMID>17574367</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 19, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 21, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intensive Care Units, Pediatric</keyword>
  <keyword>Communication</keyword>
  <keyword>Health personnel</keyword>
  <keyword>Decision making</keyword>
  <keyword>Critical Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Length of Stay</keyword>
  <keyword>Iatrogenic Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

