<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01273155</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>110060</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11-C-0060</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01273155</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Belinostat for Solid Tumors and Lymphomas in Patients With Varying Degrees of Hepatic Dysfunction</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Pharmacokinetic Study of Belinostat for Solid Tumors and Lymphomas in Patients With Varying Degrees of Hepatic Dysfunction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Belinostat is an experimental cancer treatment drug that works by helping to turn on genes
      that limit cell growth and survival of the tumor that are switched off in cancer cells.
      Belinostat has been given to patients with different types of cancer to measure its safety
      and effectiveness, but it has not been given in a formal trial to cancer patients who have
      abnormal liver function. Because belinostat is processed by the liver, its safety and
      effectiveness needs to be established in individuals who have abnormal liver function.
      Researchers are interested in comparing the effects of belinostat as a cancer treatment drug
      in individuals with normal and abnormal liver function.

      Objectives:

        -  To test the safety and effectiveness of belinostat in individuals who have solid tumors
           and lymphomas and who also have abnormal liver function.

        -  To compare the results of belinostat treatment in individuals with normal and abnormal
           liver function.

      Eligibility:

        -  Individuals at least 18 years of age who have been diagnosed with solid tumors or
           lymphomas that have not responded to standard treatment.

        -  Individuals with normal liver function and varying degrees of abnormal liver function
           (mild, moderate, severe) are eligible.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a full medical history and physical examination, as
           well as blood and urine tests, and tumor imaging studies. Participants will then be
           divided into study groups based on their liver function.

        -  Participants will receive belinostat in cycles of treatment. Except for cycle 1, all
           cycles will last 21 days. Cycle 1 will last 28 days. For cycle 1 only, participants will
           receive a single dose of belinostat 1 week before the regular 21-day treatment cycle
           starts.

        -  In each cycle, participants will receive belinostat once a day for 5 days, and will be
           asked to keep a medication diary to record any side effects.

        -  Participants will have regular clinic visits with blood and urine samples and imaging
           studies to evaluate the cancer s response to treatment.

        -  Participants may continue to take belinostat for as long as the cancer responds to the
           treatment....
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Belinostat is a histone deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitor. HDACs are frequently deregulated
           in cancer cells, leading to an increase in deacetylation and the silencing of genes that
           normally control cell cycle arrest and apoptosis.

        -  Belinostat has growth inhibitory activity in several malignancies in vitro and in vivo,
           both as a single agent and in combination with chemotherapeutic agents. Several Phase I
           and II clinical trials have been conducted to date in patients with solid tumor and
           hematologic malignancies; belinostat has been generally well tolerated.

        -  Belinostat is metabolized in the liver and therefore, the safety and dosing of
           belinostat needs to be established in patients with varying degrees of hepatic
           dysfunction.

      Objectives:

        -  Establish the safety and tolerability of belinostat given on days 1 5 of 21-day cycles
           to patients with varying degrees of liver dysfunction.

        -  Define the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) and recommended dose of belinostat given on days
           1 5 of 21-day cycles to patients with varying degrees of liver dysfunction.

        -  Evaluate the pharmacokinetics (PK) of one dose of belinostat (400 mg/m(2)) in patients
           with varying degrees of liver dysfunction.

        -  Obtain preliminary evidence of anti-tumor activity at tolerable doses of belinostat in
           patients with varying degrees of liver dysfunction.

        -  Determine polymorphisms in the UGT1A1 28 allele and correlate these with the observed
           toxicities and the PK of belinostat in patients with varying degrees of liver
           dysfunction.

        -  Measure direct versus indirect bilirubin levels and correlate these with observed
           toxicities, PK.

      Eligibility:

      -Adults with solid tumors or lymphomas whose disease has progressed after standard therapy or
      who have no acceptable standard treatment options. Patients with normal and varying degrees
      of hepatic dysfunction (mild, moderate, and severe) are eligible.

      Study Design:

      -Patients will be divided into 4 cohorts based on their level of liver dysfunction.
      Belinostat will be administered IV over 30 minutes. On day -7 (Cycle 1 only), all patients
      will receive a single dose of 400 mg/m(2) belinostat. On days 1 5 of each cycle, patients
      will receive belinostat at a dose dependent on the level of hepatic dysfunction (see below).
      The total length of Cycle 1 will be 28 days; all other cycles will be 21 days. No more than
      12 patients with normal hepatic function will be accrued.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 10, 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 25, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 25, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the pharmacokinetics of one dose of belinostat (400 mg/m2) in patients with varying degrees of liver dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>Study day 7</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Lymphomas</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohorts1-4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Four cohorts: normal, mild, moderate, and severe hepatic dysfunction</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Belinostat</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients divided into 4 cohorts based on level of liver dysfunction. Belinostat administered IV over 30 minutes. On day -7 (Cycle 1 only), all patients receive a single dose of 400 mg/m2 belinostat. On days 1 5 of each cycle, patients receive belinostat at a dose dependent on the level of hepatic dysfunction (125-1000 mg/m2/day)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohorts1-4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Patients must have histologically or cytologically confirmed (at original diagnosis or
             subsequent recurrence or progression) solid tumor or lymphoma that is metastatic,
             unresectable, progressive, or recurrent, and for which standard curative or palliative
             measures do not exist or are no longer effective.

          -  No radiation, major surgery, chemotherapy or biologic therapy within 4 weeks prior to
             entering the study (6 weeks for nitrosoureas or mitomycin C); greater than or equal to
             2 weeks since any prior administration of study drug in an exploratory IND/Phase 0
             study. (also referred to as an &quot;early Phase I study&quot; or &quot;pre-Phase I study&quot; where a
             sub-therapeutic dose of drug is administered) at the PI's discretion. Patients must
             have recovered to at least eligibility levels due to adverse events and/or toxicity of
             prior chemotherapy or biologic therapy.

          -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years. Because no dosing or adverse event data are
             currently available on the use of belinostat in patients &lt; 18 years of age, children
             are excluded from this study but will be eligible for future pediatric Phase I
             single-agent trials.

          -  ECOG performance status less than or equal to 2 (Karnofsky greater than or equal to 60
             percent.

          -  Life expectancy of greater than 3 months.

          -  Patients must have acceptable renal and marrow function as defined below:

          -  -leukocytes greater than or equal to 3,000/mcL

          -  -absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1,500/mcL

          -  -platelets greater than or equal to 100,000/mcL

          -  -serum creatinine within normal institutional limits

        OR

          -  -creatinine clearance greater than or equal to 60 mL/min for patients with creatinine
             levels above institutional normal, as determined by a measured 24-hour creatinine
             clearance Baseline evaluations should be conducted within 7 days of treatment start
             date.

          -  Patients with abnormal liver function will be eligible. Patients with active hemolysis
             should be excluded. No distinction will be made between liver dysfunction due to
             metastases and liver dysfunction due to other causes.

          -  Patients with biliary obstruction for which a stent has been placed are eligible,
             provided the stent has been in place for at least 10 days prior to the first dose of
             belinostat and the liver function has stabilized. Two measurements at least 2 days
             apart that put the patient in the same hepatic dysfunction stratum will be accepted as
             evidence of stable hepatic function. There should be no evidence of biliary sepsis.

          -  Patients with gliomas or brain metastases who require corticosteroids or
             anticonvulsants must be on a stable dose of corticosteroids and seizure free for 1
             month prior to enrollment. Patients with known brain metastases should have had brain
             irradiation (whole brain or gamma knife) more than 4 weeks before starting the
             protocol. Note that patients should have had their steroids tapered to low dose (i.e.,
             &lt; 1.5 mg of dexamethasone/day).

          -  The effects of belinostat on the developing human fetus are unknown. For this reason
             and because HDAC inhibitors are known to be teratogenic, women of child-bearing
             potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception (hormonal or barrier method
             of birth control; abstinence) prior to study entry and for the duration of study
             participation. Should a woman become pregnant or suspect she is pregnant while
             participating in this study, she should inform her treating physician immediately.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Prior therapy with belinostat.

          -  Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents.

          -  Patients with history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar
             chemical or biologic composition to belinostat, including hydroxamate compounds or
             arginine.

          -  Patients should not have taken valproic acid, another HDAC inhibitor, for at least 2
             weeks prior to enrollment.

          -  Patients with uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to ongoing
             or active infection, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit
             compliance with study requirements.

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study because belinostat is an HDAC inhibitor
             with the potential for teratogenic or abortifacient effects. Because there is an
             unknown but potential risk for adverse events in nursing infants secondary to
             treatment of the mother with belinostat, breastfeeding should be discontinued if the
             mother is treated with belinostat.

          -  HIV positive patients who are not on retroviral therapy will not be excluded from
             cohort 1, the normal liver function cohort. HIV positive patients who are not on
             retroviral therapy will be excluded from cohorts 2-4 because of confounding effects
             from potential complications from HIV and opportunistic infections.

          -  HIV-positive patients on combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible because of
             the potential for the increased risk of liver dysfunction from the antiretroviral
             therapies themselves and because of potential PK interactions with belinostat.
             Appropriate studies will be undertaken in these groups of patients when indicated.

          -  Patients with significant cardiovascular disease (New York Heart Association Class III
             or IV cardiac disease), symptomatic congestive heart failure, myocardial infarction
             within the past 6 months, unstable angina, unstable arrhythmia or a need for
             anti-arrhythmic therapy (use of frequency adjusting medication for atrial fibrillation
             is allowed, if stable medication for at least last month prior to initiation of
             belinostat treatment and medication not listed as causing Torsades de Points), or
             evidence of acute ischemia on ECG. Marked baseline prolongation of QT/QTc interval,
             e.g., repeated demonstration of a QTc interval &gt; 450 msec; Long QT Syndrome; the
             required use of concomitant medication that may cause Torsades de Pointes.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>110 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alice P Chen, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, Davis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Davis</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95616</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope National Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>USC Norris Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322-1102</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karmanos Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Albert Einstein College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10461</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2011-C-0060.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Plumb JA, Finn PW, Williams RJ, Bandara MJ, Romero MR, Watkins CJ, La Thangue NB, Brown R. Pharmacodynamic response and inhibition of growth of human tumor xenografts by the novel histone deacetylase inhibitor PXD101. Mol Cancer Ther. 2003 Aug;2(8):721-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12939461</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gimsing P. Belinostat: a new broad acting antineoplastic histone deacetylase inhibitor. Expert Opin Investig Drugs. 2009 Apr;18(4):501-8. doi: 10.1517/13543780902852560 . Erratum in: Expert Opin Investig Drugs. 2009 Jun;18(6):873.</citation>
    <PMID>19335278</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marks PA, Richon VM, Rifkind RA. Histone deacetylase inhibitors: inducers of differentiation or apoptosis of transformed cells. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2000 Aug 2;92(15):1210-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10922406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 3, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 7, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 10, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Histone Deacetylase Inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver Dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>UGT1A1 Polymorphisms</keyword>
  <keyword>Solid Tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Belinostat</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Histone Deacetylase Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

