<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03517111</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ASU6797</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2U54MD002316-11</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03517111</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Impact of a Parenting Intervention on Latino Youth Health Behaviors</brief_title>
  <acronym>FPNG+</acronym>
  <official_title>Multi-level Effects of a Parenting Intervention for Enhancing Latino Youth Health Behaviors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Arizona State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities (NIMHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Arizona State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test if a parenting program can be used to prevent substance
      use among Latino youth and at the same time promote healthy eating. Pairs of 7th grade
      students and one of their parents will be enrolled in the study and randomly assigned to
      three groups: an existing parenting intervention focusing on substance use prevention (FPNG),
      the enhanced parenting intervention that also has nutrition content (FPNG+), and a comparison
      program focused on academic success. Only parents will attend intervention sessions. Data
      will be collected from the parent and their 7th grade student to see how these programs
      impacted substance use, nutrition, and parenting. The investigators hypothesize that families
      receiving the FPNG+ will have improved nutrition habits than the other conditions. Students
      in both FPNG and FPNG+ will have lower substance use rates as compared to the academic
      success program. In addition, the effects of parenting strategies and sociocultural factors
      on the FPNG and FPNG+ results will be studied.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Latino youth are a population at risk for chronic diseases because of their growing
      overweight and obesity rates, lack of adherence to nutrition and physical activity
      recommendations, and greater rates of tobacco, alcohol and other drugs use than youth of
      other ethnic groups. Parents are an important agent of change for youth due to their ability
      to create a home environment that promotes healthful behaviors (including substance use
      prevention and healthy nutrition), and parents' role as providers of resources to the family
      (including food). Parenting interventions are efficacious in preventing substance use among
      Latino youth, but few studies have used a family approach to promote healthy nutrition. Thus,
      the overall objective of the proposed project is to extend the scope of Families Preparing
      the New Generation (FPNG), an existing parenting program proven to help reduce substance use
      among Latino youth, to also promote healthy nutrition. The eco-developmental perspective will
      provide the theoretical foundation for the project for investigating risk and resiliency in
      Latino youth's drug use and nutrition behaviors. The main aims of the study are to (1) test
      the effects of a nutrition-enhanced parenting program (FPNG+) on substance use and nutrition
      among Latino youth, (2) explore how enhancing parenting skills impact the effects of the
      enhanced intervention, and (3) understand how social and cultural factors impact how the
      enhanced program works. The research team will first seek input from community members to
      create a nutrition-enhanced program that is acceptable to Latino parents of middle school
      students. The investigators will then collaborate with the American Dream Academy (ADA), an
      organization delivering an academic success program to families within middle schools
      throughout the Phoenix Area, to recruit 1,494 families who have a student in 7th grade to
      participate in the study. Parents from different schools will be offered one of three 10-week
      programs (assigned to each individual school): FPNG+ (substance use prevention and healthy
      nutrition), FPNG (substance use prevention only), and the ADA comparison program (focusing on
      academic success). Data will be collected from the 7th grade student and his/her
      participating parent before the start of the program, immediately after it ends, and 16 weeks
      later, to compare how the programs affect nutrition, substance use, and parenting. In a
      subgroup of 126 families (42 from each program), investigators will explore how the FPNG+
      program affects diabetes and cardiovascular risk factors and whether the program induces
      changes in the types of foods available at participants' homes. For this, investigators will
      collect capillary blood samples from participants to measure glycosylated hemoglobin (a
      marker of diabetes risk) and cholesterol (a marker of cardiovascular risk), and blood
      pressure, as well as a list of foods that participants have at home. The long-term goal is to
      design and disseminate programs that contribute to helping parents assist their adolescent
      children develop and maintain long-lasting positive lifestyle behaviors in order to prevent
      substance use and chronic diseases.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomization to treatment conditions (FPNG+, FPNG, or comparison [RAD]) will occur at the school level. From the 18 participating schools, 6 each will be randomized into one of the three conditions.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recent use of substances</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Survey questions: Changes in amount and frequency of alcohol, cigarettes, marijuana, and inhalants in the past 30 days. Scale ranges from 1 (no use of substance) to 7 (used 40 or more times). Higher score indicates more use.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Drug resistance strategies</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Survey questions: Change in youths' responses to substance use offers in the past 30 days and likely responses to hypothetical substance use offers. Scale ranges from 1 (never responded in this way) to 6 (responded this way more than 10 times).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Nutrition outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>NCI Dietary Screener: Change in intake of fruit, vegetables, and sugar-laden foods</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall family functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Survey questions (parents) measuring: Change in family support, family conflict, parental monitoring, extent of involvement, and familism.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parents' social support</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Social Support Questionnaire score. Scale from 1 (very dissatisfied with support) to 6 (very satisfied with support). Higher scores mean more social support.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acculturation</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Acculturation Rating Scale for Mexican Americans-II (ARSMA-II) asks participants to indicate on a five point likert scale (Not at all (1) and Extremely often or almost always (5)) the extent to which they engage in 17 Mexican oriented behaviors. The Anglo Orientation Subscale (AOS) consists of 13 items, which asks participants to indicate on a five point likert scale (Not at all (1) and Extremely often or almost always (5)) the extent to which they engage in Anglo oriented behaviors. Means for each subscale are calculated, higher score means higher Mexican orientation and higher Anglo orientation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Food Insecurity</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Assesses financially-based food insecurity and hunger in households.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Resilience</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Connor-Davidson Resilience Scale total score. Scale ranges from 0 (not true at all) to 4 (true nearly all the time). Total sum calculated, with higher score indicating more resilience.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-efficacy for Parenting Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>A measure of parental beliefs that he/she is capable of performing parental roles/responsibilities</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent self-agency</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Gauges the parent's sense of parenting competence and ability to positively influence the child's development</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent-child communication</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>includes questions from the National Longitudinal Study of Adolescent Health Parent Survey about how parents communicate with their children, including specific questions about substance use and risky behaviors</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child Feeding Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>assesses parental attitudes, beliefs and practices about feeding</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Multidimensional Acculturative Stress Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Measures how often a person experienced certain acculturation situations and how stressful they were.
Scale ranges from 0 (No, did not happen to me) to 5 (Extremely stressful). Mean score is created, where higher values indicate more acculturative stress.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Measured body weight for parents and youth.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Height</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Measured height for parents and youth.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body mass index</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated BMI for parents and youth estimated by dividing weight by height squared</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systolic blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Measured systolic blood pressure using an automated blood pressure monitor</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diastolic blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Measured diastolic blood pressure using an automated blood pressure monitor</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Total cholesterol measured via finger prick blood sample</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c)</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>HbA1c measured via finger prick blood sample</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diet of adolescents</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>2004 Block Food Frequency Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diet of the parents</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Southwestern Food Frequency Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Home food environment</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 0, Week 10-12, Week 24-26</time_frame>
    <description>Modified version of the validated Home Food Inventory with cultural adaptations including foods commonly consumed by Latinos.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2988</enrollment>
  <condition>Diet Modification</condition>
  <condition>Substance Use Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus Risk</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Risk Factor</condition>
  <condition>Lifestyle Risk Reduction</condition>
  <condition>Parenting</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nutrition/substance use prevention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parenting and nutrition curriculum targeting substance use prevention and diet improvement.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Substance use prevention only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parenting curriculum targeting substance use prevention only.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Academic success program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control program focused only on academic success.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nutrition/substance use prevention</intervention_name>
    <description>Parenting program focusing on diet improvement and substance use prevention</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nutrition/substance use prevention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FPNG+</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Substance use prevention only</intervention_name>
    <description>Parenting program focusing only on substance use prevention</description>
    <arm_group_label>Substance use prevention only</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FPNG</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Academic success program</intervention_name>
    <description>Program focusing on academic success and college acceptance</description>
    <arm_group_label>Academic success program</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RAD (Realizing the American Dream)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Youth: ages 12-14

          -  Youth: Enrolled in 7th grade at the time of recruitment from the American Dream
             Academy (ADA) programs

          -  Adults: Age 18 or older

          -  Adults: Parent/caregiver/guardian of an eligible youth

        Exclusion Criteria: None
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Flavio F Marsiglia, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Southwest Interdisciplinary Research Center, Arizona State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sonia Vega-López, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(602) 827-2268</phone>
    <email>Sonia.Vega.Lopez@asu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arizona State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85004</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 22, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Arizona State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sonia Vega-Lopez</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor, School of Nutrition and Health Promotion</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Substance-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

