<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03519399</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RJ115/N071</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03519399</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bile Acid Effects in Fetal Arrhythmia Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>BEATS</acronym>
  <official_title>Investigation of the Effect of Elevated Serum Bile Acids in Intrahepatic Cholestasis of Pregnancy (ICP) on the Fetal Cardiac Rhythm and on Myometrial Contractility: a Prospective Case-control Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Guy's and St Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>King's College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Guy's and St Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy (ICP) is a liver disorder of pregnancy that typically
      presents in late pregnancy with generalised itching. ICP is associated with an increased risk
      of pregnancy complications, including premature labour, fetal distress, and stillbirth.
      Models of the fetal heart (using cells from rodents) have shown that high bile acids levels
      cause an abnormal heart rhythm (arrhythmia), which may be the cause of stillbirth. High
      levels of bile acids also cause preterm labour in animal models.

      This pilot study aims to assess whether severe ICP, defined as maternal serum bile acid
      levels ≥40μmol/L, is associated with abnormal fetal heart rhythms and abnormal myometrial
      contractility, which may lead to preterm birth.

      Fetal heart rhythms and myometrial contractility will be recorded using a portable
      electrocardiogram (ECG) device, the Monica AN24. This monitors the fetal heart and myometrial
      activity via stickers applied to the mother's abdomen. It also records the maternal ECG. We
      will also study women with uncomplicated pregnancy, in order to make comparisons.

      The importance of maternal position during sleep has also more recently been established,
      with some studies demonstrating an association between the risk of stillbirth and the
      position the mother was sleeping in (Stacey et al,2011). Work by Stone et al published this
      year has shown that the maternal sleep position has a significant impact on the fetal sleep
      state and fetal heart rate, (in particular something called the fetal RMSSD value), (Stone et
      al,2017). We therefore wish to identify any potential correlation between fetal heart
      arrhythmia and maternal sleep position. To do this we will use a Zephyr BioPatchTM which
      provides a clear indication of whether the patient was in left lateral, right lateral or
      supine position.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy (ICP) also known as obstetric cholestasis (OC) is a
      liver disorder unique to pregnancy that affects 0.5-1% of women in the UK. It typically
      presents in the third trimester of pregnancy with pruritus that can affect any part of the
      body, but is most commonly experienced on the palms and soles. Biochemically, it is
      characterised by liver dysfunction with raised serum bile acids, and clinically, by a
      significantly increased incidence of fetal complications, including spontaneous preterm
      labour, fetal distress, meconium staining of the amniotic fluid and sudden fetal death
      (Geenes and Williamson 2009).

      The aetiology of ICP is complex and incompletely understood although the maternal disease is
      likely to be caused by interaction between sex hormone metabolites and bile acids in
      genetically susceptible women (Abu-Hayyeh et al., 2010). To date, genetic variation in
      several biliary transporters have been identified that predispose women to the disease (Dixon
      et al., 2000; Mullenbach et al., 2005; Pauli−Magnus et al., 2004; Van Mil et al, 2007; Dixon
      et al. 2009). The aetiology of the adverse perinatal outcomes is also not fully understood.

      ICP is associated with an increased risk of adverse perinatal outcomes, including spontaneous
      preterm delivery, meconium staining of the amniotic fluid, admission to the neonatal unit and
      sudden intrauterine death. As with the maternal disease, the aetiology for the perinatal
      complications is not fully understood, but evidence from animal and in vitro studies suggests
      a role for bile acids. This hypothesis is supported by the finding that the risk of adverse
      perinatal outcomes is directly associated with the level of maternal serum bile acids, and
      specifically with maternal serum bile acids exceeding 40 μmol /L, i.e. severe ICP (Glantz et
      al., 2004; Geenes et al., 2014).

      Of the adverse perinatal outcomes associated with ICP, the most severe is sudden intrauterine
      death, which is reported to affect between 2 and 4% of ICP pregnancies (Fisk et al., 1988;
      Geenes et al., 2014). The mechanism for fetal demise is unclear, but is appears to be a
      sudden event as there are several case reports of normal fetal movements and CTG recordings
      in the hours preceding fetal demise. Furthermore, at post-mortem there is typically no
      evidence of preceding uteroplacental insufficiency, and the babies are appropriately grown
      (Fisk et al, 1988). One possible explanation for the sudden intrauterine death is an acute
      cardiac arrhythmia leading to fetal cardiac arrest. This hypothesis is supported by evidence
      from in vitro studies of cultured neonatal rat cardiomyocytes which demonstrate the
      development of arrhythmias following the addition of bile acids to the culture (Williamson et
      al., 2001). Further studies have shown that this effect is dose dependent and reversed by the
      addition of ursodeoxycholic acid (UDCA), the drug commonly used to treat ICP (Miragoli et
      al., 2011). However, there are very few case reports in the literature of fetal heart
      abnormalities in women with ICP, but studies have reported bradycardias, tachycardias and
      atrial flutter (Laatkainen, 1975; Laatikainen et al., 1984; Al Inizi et al., 2006).
      Prolongation of the PR interval in the fetal echocardiogram has also been reported; this
      clinical feature has been known to predispose the heart to arrhythmias (Strehlow et al,
      2010). A recent study using the same technique has also reported fetal diastolic dysfunction
      in patients with severe ICP (Ataalla et al, 2016). Given the paucity of human clinical data
      regarding the fetal heart rhythm in ICP, we propose to undertake this study to investigate
      whether ICP is associated with fetal arrhythmias and the influence of bile acid levels on
      fetal heart rhythm. In parallel we will evaluate whether there is fetal ventricular
      dysfunction.

      Recent studies have shown that maternal lie has an association with stillbirth; an increased
      risk of stillbirth was observed when women slept in a supine or right lateral position
      (Stacey et al, 2011). Stone et al (2017) have published data from a study where the Monica
      AN24, a transabdominal fetal electrocardiogram (fECG) monitor, was used on mothers lying in
      supine, left and right lateral positions. They found that the fetal short-term heart rate
      variability (RMSSD) changed depending on the position the mother was lying in. Unpublished
      data also using the Monica AN24 has demonstrated an association between maternal lie and
      maternal RMSSD (Fifer et al, personal communication). As the RMSSD is one of the principal
      measures we will be using to detect arrhythmogenic activity, analysis will include the
      detection of maternal lie in order to accurately determine short-term heart rate variability.

      There is limited evidence that the maternal heart is affected by ICP to cause maternal rhythm
      disturbance, although there is one report of prolonged maternal QT interval (Kirbas et al
      2015). The fetal heart develops in an environment of relative hypoxia and this is associated
      with the transformation of human fetal cardiac fibroblasts into myofibroblasts, which
      subsequently disappear post-natally. Myofibroblasts may re-appear in the diseased adult heart
      during the process of remodelling following infarction, and have been shown to act as an
      arrhythmogenic focus in these circumstances. Interestingly, in vitro data have demonstrated
      that the myofibroblasts also act as the arrhythmogenic focus in bile acid induced arrhythmia
      in the neonatal heart. UDCA has also been demonstrated to protect against bile acid-induced
      arrhythmias in myofibroblasts (Schultz et al, 2016).

      ICP is also associated with an increased risk of spontaneous preterm labour (Geenes et al.,
      2014). Again, the reasons for this are unclear, but evidence from animal studies suggests
      that bile acids may be involved. Bile acid infusions cause spontaneous preterm labour in
      sheep (Campos et al., 1986), and in vitro studies have shown that they increase the
      sensitivity of the myometrium to the hormone oxytocin (Germain et al., 2003), which is
      central to the process of labour. Human data regarding myometrial contractility are lacking.
      As a secondary aim of this study, we also propose to investigate whether ICP is associated
      with abnormal myometrial contractility.

      Data regarding fetal cardiac rhythms and myometrial contractility collected from women with
      ICP will be compared to data collected from women with uncomplicated pregnancy. The inclusion
      of women with uncomplicated pregnancies will ensure that any variation identified in the
      fetal cardiac rhythms or myometrial contractility in women with ICP is attributable to the
      condition, rather than a variant of normal. The parallel recording of the maternal ECG in
      both women with ICP and women with uncomplicated pregnancy will enable us to ensure that any
      abnormal fetal cardiac rhythms are not due to an inherited arrhythmia.

      Fetal and maternal ECG, and myometrial contractility data will be collected using the Monica
      AN24 device. This is a small wearable monitor that continuously records maternal and fetal
      ECG's, and myometrial activity data via electrodes placed on the maternal abdomen. Maternal
      lie will be detected using the Zephyr BioPatchTM. This wearable monitor is much smaller than
      the Monica AN24 and also functions via adhesive electrodes. It is placed at the base of the
      breastbone of the participant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 27, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of the influence of maternal bile acids levels on fetal ECG</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 hours (overnight recording at home)</time_frame>
    <description>To investigate the influence of maternal serum bile acid levels on the fetal ECG in women with ICP and women with uncomplicated pregnancy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of the influence of fetal bile acids levels on fetal ECG</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 hours (overnight recording at home)</time_frame>
    <description>To investigate associations between fetal bile acid levels and the fetal ECG in women with ICP and women with uncomplicated pregnancy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measurement of the influence of maternal bile acids levels on myometrial contractility</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 hours (overnight recording at home)</time_frame>
    <description>To investigate associations between maternal serum bile acid levels and myometrial contractility in women with ICP and women with uncomplicated pregnancy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Cholestasis of Pregnancy</condition>
  <condition>Intrahepatic Cholestasis of Pregnancy</condition>
  <condition>Obstetric Cholestasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cases and Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Cases - Pregnant women with ICP defined as pruritus in pregnancy in association with raised serum bile acids (using hospital threshold for diagnosis), and in the absence of an alternative cause.
Controls - Pregnant women not affected by ICP, or other liver, cardiac or hypertensive disorders.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Monica AN24</intervention_name>
    <description>Monica AN24 will be used to record maternal and fetal ECGs. The Zephyr will be used to determine maternal lie.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cases and Controls</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zephyr</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Maternal sera samples collected at recruitment. Maternal sera and umbilical cord blood sera
      collected following the delivery of the fetus.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Eligible women will be identified via the antenatal services at participating hospitals,
        and via ICP support (www.icpsupport.org).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  CASES - Pregnant women with ICP defined as pruritus in pregnancy in association with
             raised serum bile acids (using hospital threshold for diagnosis), and in the absence
             of an alternative cause.

          -  CONTROLS - Pregnant women not affected by ICP, or other liver, cardiac or hypertensive
             disorders.

          -  Pregnant women who are willing and able to give consent.

          -  Pregnant women ≥ 18 years of age.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-pregnant women.

          -  Pregnant women with medical disorders that can cause liver impairment in pregnancy
             e.g. pre-eclampsia, acute fatty liver of pregnancy, diabetes mellitus.

          -  Pregnant women with a history of pre-existing liver or cardiac

          -  Pregnant women with current hypertensive disease (this would include women taking
             drugs such as methyldopa, labetolol, atenolol, bisoprolol, nifedipine, amlodipine)

          -  Pregnant women who are expecting more than one baby.

          -  Pregnant women with blood-borne viruses e.g. HIV and hepatitis.

          -  Women ≤ 18 years of age.

          -  Pregnant women expecting a baby with a structural heart abnormality identified

          -  Women unable or unwilling to give informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Catherine Williamson</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>King's College London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tharni Vavasan</last_name>
    <phone>0207 848 6202</phone>
    <email>tharni.vasavan@kcl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jenny Chambers</last_name>
    <phone>07843 660349</phone>
    <email>jenny.chambers@imperial.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Thomas' Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE1 7EH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tharni Vavasan</last_name>
      <phone>02078486202</phone>
      <email>tharni.vasavan@kcl.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Catherine Williamson</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Charlotte's &amp; Chelsea Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>W12 0NN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jenny Chambers</last_name>
      <phone>07843 660349</phone>
      <email>jenny.chambers@imperial.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Muna Noori</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 26, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bile Acids, Fetal ECG, Stillbirth,</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cholestasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cholestasis, Intrahepatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pregnancy Complications</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bile Acids and Salts</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

