<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03515733</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PF04995274 Study 2 RESTART</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03515733</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PF-04995274 and Emotional Processing in Treatment Resistant Depression</brief_title>
  <acronym>RESTART</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effects of PF-04995274 on Emotional Processing in Treatment-resistant, Medicated, Depressed Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will test whether seven days adjunctive administration of a serotonin receptor
      subtype 4 (5HT4) agonist called PF-04995274 has positive effects on emotional processing and
      neural activity in medicated, treatment-resistant depressed patients compared to placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study uses a double-blind, placebo-controlled, randomised between-groups design to test
      if adjunctive administration of a serotonin receptor subtype 4 (5HT4) agonist called
      PF-04995274 has positive effects on emotional processing and neural activity in medicated
      treatment-resistant depressed patients. Participants are patients who fulfill criteria for
      current episode of Major Depressive Disorder (MDD) and have shown lack of response to
      antidepressant treatment, and they will be randomised to receive 7 days treatment with either
      PF-04995274 (15 mg daily) or a matched placebo. Participants will come for a Screening Visit,
      a First Dose Visit, and a Research Visit (including measures of emotional processing and
      non-emotion cognition).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be randomly allocated to one of two groups (PF-04995264 or placebo) and receive their allocated study medication for 7 days.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Facial Expression Recognition Task (FERT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Completed on Day 7</time_frame>
    <description>Facial expressions of basic emotions (happiness, fear, anger, disgust, sadness, surprise) are displayed on the screen and participants are asked to correctly classify them. Each emotion is presented at different intensity levels. Responses are made via a button-press and accuracy and reaction time are recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression, Unipolar</condition>
  <condition>Treatment Resistant Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PF-04995274</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PF-04995274, three x 5mg tablet (15mg total), once daily for 7-9 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>3 placebo tablets, once daily for 7-9 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PF-04995274</intervention_name>
    <description>PF-04995274 tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>PF-04995274</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Oral Tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo tablet, identical appearance to experimental tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female;

          -  Aged 18-65 years;

          -  Willing and able to give informed consent for participation in the study;

          -  Sufficiently fluent English to understand and complete the tasks;

          -  Registered with a GP and consents to GP being informed of participation in study;

          -  Participants need to meet a number of concurrent clinical criteria:

          -  Current criteria for Major Depressive Disorder [as determined by the Structured
             Clinical interview for DSM-V (SCID)];

          -  Failure within the current depressive episode to respond clinically to at least one
             course of antidepressant therapy, each given at a therapeutic dose for at least four
             weeks [as determined by use of the MGH Antidepressant Treatment Response Questionnaire
             (ATRQ)];

          -  Currently taking an antidepressant, which must be either a Selective Serotonin
             Reuptake Inhibitor (SSRI) - with the exception of fluoxetine, paroxetine or
             fluvoxamine - or a Serotonin-norepinephrine reuptake inhibitor (SNRI) ; Participants
             currently taking excluded medications can be switched to sertraline or citalopram;

          -  Participants engaging in sex with a risk of pregnancy must agree to use a highly
             effective method of contraception from Screening Visit until 30 days after receiving
             study medication treatment, and male participants must not donate sperm.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of or current DSM-V bipolar disorder, schizophrenia or eating disorders.
             Participants who fulfil current criteria for other comorbid disorders may still be
             entered into the study, if, in the opinion of the Investigator, the psychiatric
             diagnosis will not compromise safety or affect data quality;

          -  First-degree relative with a diagnosis of Bipolar Disorder type 1;

          -  Participants currently taking strong cytochrome P450 (CYPs) enzymes inhibitors, such
             as fluoxetine, paroxetine or fluvoxamine (in order to avoid drug-drug interactions);

          -  Participants currently taking psychotropic medications which in the opinion of the
             investigator may interfere with the safety of the participant or the scientific
             integrity of the study;

          -  Participants who have previously failed a combination/augmentation therapy (i.e.,
             therapy with the combination of two or more pharmacological agents) for the treatment
             of depression, which in the opinion of the Investigator may reduce the likelihood of
             responding;

          -  Electroconvulsive therapy for the treatment of the current episode of depression;

          -  Participants undergoing any form of face-to-face structured psychological treatment
             during the study;

          -  Clinically significant abnormal values for liver function tests, clinical chemistry,
             urine drug screen, blood pressure measurement and ECG. A participant with a clinical
             abnormality or parameters outside the reference range for the population being studied
             may be included only if the Investigator considers that the finding is unlikely to
             introduce additional risk factors and will not interfere with the study procedures;

          -  History of stimulant abuse (lifetime; e.g. amphetamine, cocaine), or of alcohol abuse
             within one year or of alcohol dependence within the lifetime;

          -  History of, or current medical conditions which in the opinion of the investigator may
             interfere with the safety of the participant or the scientific integrity of the study,
             including epilepsy/seizures, brain injury, severe hepatic or renal disease, severe
             gastro-intestinal problems, Central Nervous System (CNS) tumors, severe neurological
             problems (like Parkinson's Disease; blackouts requiring hospitalisation);

          -  Clinically significant risk of suicide;

          -  Current pregnancy (as determined by urine pregnancy test taken during Screening and
             First Dose Visits), breastfeeding or planning a pregnancy during the course of the
             study;

          -  Participant not willing to use a suitable method of contraception for 30 days after
             receiving study medication treatment;

          -  Participants with Body Mass Index (BMI - kg/m2) outside the 18 - 36 range at the
             Screening Visit;

          -  Night-shift working or recent travel involving significant change of timezones;

          -  Excessive caffeine consumption, i.e., consumption higher than 8 cups of standard
             caffeinated drinks (tea, instant coffee) or higher than 6 cups of stronger coffee or
             other drinks containing methylxanthines such as coca cola or Red Bull per day;

          -  Participation in a psychological or medical study involving the use of medication
             within the last 3 months;

          -  Previous participation in a study using the same, or similar, emotional processing
             tasks;

          -  Smoker &gt; 10 cigarettes per day or similar levels of tobacco consumption in other
             forms.

          -  Participant received prescribed medication within 28 days prior to First Dose Visit
             (apart from their prescribed antidepressant and the contraceptive pill). Participants
             who have taken prescription medication may still be entered into the study, if, in the
             opinion of the Investigator, the medication received will not interfere with the study
             procedures or compromise safety;

          -  Participant received non-prescription medication, including supplements such as
             vitamins and herbal supplements within 48 hours prior to First Dose Visit (apart from
             paracetamol). Participants who have taken non-prescription medication may still be
             entered into the study, if, in the opinion of the Investigator, the medication
             received will not interfere with the study procedures or compromise safety;

          -  Participant with a known hypersensitivity to PF-04995274 or any other serotonergic
             agents;

          -  Participant with planned medical treatment within the study period that might
             interfere with the study procedures;

          -  Participant who is unlikely to comply with the clinical study protocol or is
             unsuitable for any other reason, in the opinion of the Investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Catherine Harmer</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amy Gillespie</last_name>
    <phone>01865 618324</phone>
    <email>amy.gillespie@psych.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Wendy Howard</last_name>
    <phone>01865 618286</phone>
    <email>wendy.howard@psych.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Oxford</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <state>Oxfordshire</state>
        <zip>OX3 7JX</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Amy Gillespie</last_name>
      <email>amy.gillespie@psych.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Catherine Harmer, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Philip Cowen, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 23, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Treatment-Resistant</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

