<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03517878</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N14/03/019</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03517878</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of a Home-based Community Health Worker Program in Rural Eastern Cape, South Africa</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Non-randomized Comparative Cohort Study Evaluating a Home-based Community Health Worker Program in the Rural Eastern Cape Province of South Africa</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The ELMA Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Stellenbosch</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Philani Maternal Child Health and Nutrition Project</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this early Phase 2 comparison trial is to evaluate the impact of community
      health worker (CHW) home visitors on pregnant women and their children in a rural setting in
      the rural Eastern Cape of South Africa. The intervention provided by the CHWs targets
      underweight children, mothers living with HIV (MLH), mothers using alcohol, and depressed
      mothers with the goal of supporting pregnant women to improve birth outcomes, decrease the
      number of children born with a low birthweight, and develop child caretaking skills over
      time. UCLA has identified and matched four areas surrounding primary health care clinics: two
      intervention areas in which this CHW program has been running for one year, and two control
      areas without the program. Mothers in the research area are followed for one year after
      giving birth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Inequalities in the quality and accessibility of healthcare between urban centers and rural
      areas is a global challenge that is particularly stark for low and middle-income countries
      (LMIC). Maternal and child health (MCH) in rural South Africa is negatively impacted by large
      distances, poor infrastructure, and a shortage of healthcare workers at clinics and
      hospitals.

      Home visiting has been repeatedly demonstrated efficacious in addressing some of these
      challenges and improving MCH outcomes, including when delivered by CHW in LMIC. However,
      there is limited research on the effectiveness of implementing these types of programs in
      rural areas.

      The investigators have shown that with training, supervision, and accountability, CHW home
      visits are effective in improving MCH over the first five years of life. These results were
      observed in a successful randomized controlled trial conducted in peri-urban townships in
      Cape Town, South Africa. CHW were trained to address HIV, alcohol, and malnutrition among all
      pregnant women in a neighborhood, to avoid stigma, and to address multiple health challenges
      concurrently. The visits significantly improved MCH outcomes over five years. Based on these
      results, this comprehensive CHW home visiting program served as one model for re-engineering
      primary health care to include 65,000 paraprofessionals providing home-based care in South
      Africa.

      This early phase two comparison trial examines whether the same comprehensive CHW home
      visiting program can be effectively implemented in a deeply rural area of the Eastern Cape in
      South Africa. Two matched cohorts of women and their children, one in areas where the
      comprehensive CHW program has been active for one year and one in areas without the program,
      will be followed from pregnancy through the first 12 months after giving birth. Stellenbosch
      University interviewers will independently assess outcomes of each mother at pregnancy, and
      of the mothers and infants within two weeks of post-birth, 6 months, and 12 months later. The
      primary outcomes are a combined measures of maternal and child health including maternal HIV
      testing, depression, and alcohol use, as well as the child's nutrition, physical growth,
      development, and healthcare and a measure of how MLH comply with tasks for PMTCT.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 11, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite outcome: Number of significantly improved child and maternal outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Out of 11 variables, we run 1000 simulations on the distribution of 0 and 1. The investigators total number of outcomes (each scored as 0=not present or 1=present) and determine if the Comprehensive CHW Cohort sum is significantly greater than expected based on the Control Cohort.
For Mothers:
Breastfeeding
No alcohol in pregnancy
Not depressed
Adhere to medical regimens
For all mothers:
-4 antenatal care visits
For HIV+ mothers:
Test for HIV
Take ARV
Give infant NVP and bactrim
infant PCR
exclusive breastfeeding
For Children:
Not low birth weight
Growth in height
Growth in weight
Hospitalizations
Developmental milestones
Vaccinations
Child support grant
Harwood JM, Weiss RE, Comulada WS. Beyond the Primary Endpoint Paradigm: A Test of Intervention Effect in HIV Behavioral Intervention Trials with Numerous Correlated Outcomes. Prevention Science. 2017 Jul 1;18(5):526-33.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breastfeed for three months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mothers are asked at the 6 month and 12 month follow up &quot;How long after your baby's birth did you stop breastfeeding your baby completely?&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breastfeed for six months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mothers are asked at the 6 month and 12 month follow up &quot;How long after your baby's birth did you stop breastfeeding your baby completely?&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>No alcohol after learning that the participant was pregnant</measure>
    <time_frame>Birth</time_frame>
    <description>At the birth interview mothers are asked &quot;Have you ever used alcohol during this pregnancy?&quot; and follows up with &quot;Did you continue to drink alcohol after you knew you were pregnant?&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Attend 4 antenatal care visits</measure>
    <time_frame>Birth</time_frame>
    <description>At the birth interview antenatal care cards are inspected and mothers are asked &quot;How many antenatal care visits did you attend?&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Not depressed, EPDS below 13</measure>
    <time_frame>Birth, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>EPDS is asked after birth, 6 months after birth, and at 12 months after birth.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant was not low birth weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Birth</time_frame>
    <description>Birth weight is recorded from child's road to health card and baby is weighed by data collector shortly after birth (this value is used when road to health card is not available).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Growth in height-for-age (above -2SD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Birth, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Child height/length is recorded shortly after birth, at 6 months, and at 12 months. Values are compared to WHO norms and turned into a Z score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Growth in weight-for-age (above -2SD)</measure>
    <time_frame>Birth, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Child weight is recorded shortly after birth, at 6 months, and at 12 months. Values are compared to WHO norms and turned into a Z score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>At 6 months and 12 months after birth mothers are asked &quot;During the past 3 months, have you taken the child to the hospital for any reason?&quot; and &quot;How many times have you taken the child to the hospital?&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>WHO developmental scale measures at 50th percentile</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>WHO measures of child development are used and children are compared to the mean level of achievement for their age. Fussy or sleepy children may be unable to be evaluated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vaccinations up to date</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Data collectors examine the child's road to health card to determine if all immunizations are up to date and which ones are missing. A photo is taken of this page for confirmation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Has Child Support Grant</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mothers are asked &quot;Does the child get a child support grant?&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mothers test for HIV during pregnancy</measure>
    <time_frame>Birth</time_frame>
    <description>Data collectors look for any evidence on the antenatal card of an HIV test during pregnancy. If not, or if card is unavailable, check with the mother if she has previously tested positive for HIV or ask &quot;Did you have a test for HIV during this pregnancy?&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MLH take ARV during pregnancy</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mothers are asked &quot;When did you start taking ARVs?&quot; and antenatal cards and health cards are examined for evidence of ARV prescription and start date.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Give infant NVP and Bactrim</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mothers are asked &quot;Did you get Nevarapine syrup for your baby around the time of birth?&quot;; &quot;Are you currently using nevirapine syrup for the baby?&quot; and &quot;Are you currently still giving your child bactrim?&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PCR testing at 6 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mothers are asked &quot;Has you child been tested for HIV yet?&quot; and &quot;Do you know what the result of your child's HIV test (PCR) is?&quot; Data collectors independently confirm this information on the child's road to health card to determine how many times (if at all) the child has been tested for HIV?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6 months exclusive breastfeeding</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mothers are asked &quot;How soon after birth did you give your child something else in addition to breastmilk?&quot; In addition, mothers are asked to provide a 24 hour, 1 months, and 3 month dietary recall.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1300</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <condition>HIV/AIDS</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Depressive Symptoms</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol Use Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol Drinking</condition>
  <condition>Stunting</condition>
  <condition>Alcohol; Harmful Use</condition>
  <condition>Child Development</condition>
  <condition>Child Malnutrition</condition>
  <condition>Child Nutrition Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Birth Weight Less Than 10Th Percentile</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Comprehensive CHW Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>Pregnant women who become mothers and their infants living in areas served by the comprehensive CHW program. These are areas around two primary health care clinics and matched to the Control Cohort clinic areas.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>Pregnant women who become mothers and their infants living in areas that are not served by the comprehensive CHW program. These are areas around two primary health care clinics and matched to the Comprehensive CHW Cohort clinic areas.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Comprehensive CHW Program</intervention_name>
    <description>The comprehensive CHW Cohort will receive home visits from CHWs recruited, trained, and supervised by the Philani organization. Philani has a 30-year history of non-stigmatizing home-based support for women and children in Cape Town. The organization has been operating their comprehensive CHW program in the rural Eastern Cape since 2010; however, in the research areas, CHWs have only been active for one year prior to initiation of the study. Philani recruits CHWs that are &quot;positive peer deviants&quot; to serve as role models in the community. The CHWs then receive training, materials, and skills to address major community health challenges of HIV, TB, malnutrition, alcohol use, and depression. The CHWs also receive ongoing monitoring and supervision as well as support for difficult cases.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Comprehensive CHW Cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Cohorts include all women meeting inclusion criteria from the catchment areas surrounding
        four clinics in the rural Eastern Cape.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women who are or become mothers living in the catchment area at the time of
             recruitment

          -  Women not identified as psychotic or delusional based on the interviewer's judgment

          -  Women able to provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to give informed consent

          -  Inability to converse with the interviewer or the CHW

          -  Miscarriage or stillbirth

          -  Death of the infant

          -  Death of the mother
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Tomlinson, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Stellenbosch</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karl W le Roux, MB ChB</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Zithulele Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ingrid le Roux, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Philani Maternal Child Health and Nutrition Project</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Zithulele Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mqanduli</city>
        <state>Eastern Cape</state>
        <zip>5080</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stellenbosch University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stellenbosch</city>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>South Africa</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.philani.org.za/</url>
    <description>Philani Website</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.zithuleleresearch.org/</url>
    <description>Zithuele Research Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 14, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mary Jane Rotheram-Borus</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Community Health Worker</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast Feeding</keyword>
  <keyword>Child Development</keyword>
  <keyword>Home Visits</keyword>
  <keyword>Infants</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Malnutrition</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Birth Weight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alcohol Drinking</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nutrition Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Child Nutrition Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

