<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03519685</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A125604</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03519685</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>UCSF College Health Study on Contraceptive Training and Education at Community Colleges</brief_title>
  <official_title>UCSF College Health Study: A Cluster Randomized Trial on Contraceptive Training and Education at Community Colleges</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to measure whether a training and education intervention for
      clinic staff and young women aged 18-25 on contraceptive methods, including intrauterine
      devices (IUDs) and the implant, will result in greater contraceptive knowledge and access
      among students in community colleges.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the US, young women aged 18-25 years experience high rates of unintended pregnancy and
      have limited knowledge of contraception or their pregnancy risks. They have little
      familiarity with the full range of contraceptives, particularly long-acting reversible
      contraception (LARC) including the IUD and implant. This campus-level, multiple component
      intervention provides evidence-based contraceptive training and education to clinic staff and
      students in this age group attending community colleges in California.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 9, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in student knowledge of full range of contraceptive methods (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediate post educational intervention session</time_frame>
    <description>The outcome is measure by whether student knows these reversible methods including male condom, female condom, oral contraceptive pill, transdermal patch, vaginal ring, Depo-provera injectable, intrauterine device, subdermal implant, and emergency contraception.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in student access to contraceptive services over 12 months, measured as whether student knows of or visited health services for contraceptives (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in willingness to use long-acting reversible contraception (LARC) (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediate post educational intervention session</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in LARC use over 12 months (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dual condom use at last sex, measured by student report of condom use together with another method of birth control at last vaginal sex (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Unintended pregnancy incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The researchers will measure pregnancy through questionnaires and urine pregnancy tests.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Certificate or degree completion (ordinal outcome including categories for on-time progression for graduation, delayed progression or dropout), measured by student report (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in receipt of public assistance (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Likelihood of finding good job after college measured by questionnaire item asking student if she thinks she will find a good job after college (measured with Likert scale: very likely, likely, unlikely, very unlikely)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in provider LARC practices (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sub-analyses for change in student knowledge of full range of contraceptive methods (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediate post educational intervention session, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The outcome is measure by whether student knows these reversible methods including male condom, female condom, oral contraceptive pill, transdermal patch, vaginal ring, Depo-provera injectable, intrauterine device, subdermal implant, and emergency contraception. The researchers will assess the outcome of student contraceptive knowledge by sociodemographic factors (age, race/ethnicity, parental education, health insurance, receipt of public assistance) and reproductive characteristics (parity, pregnancy intentions, male partner, prior contraceptive use).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sub-analyses for change in student access to contraceptive services over 12 months, measured as whether student knew of or visited health services for contraceptives (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The researchers will assess the outcome of contraceptive access by sociodemographic factors (age, race/ethnicity, parental education, health insurance, receipt of public assistance) and reproductive characteristics (parity, pregnancy intentions, male partner, prior contraceptive use). The researchers will also test interaction of the intervention with race/ethnicity, parental education, and health insurance.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sub-analyses for changes in LARC use over 12 months, measured by whether student is using an IUD or implant (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The researchers will assess the outcome of LARC use over 12 months by sociodemographic factors (age, race/ethnicity, health insurance), reproductive characteristics (parity, pregnancy intentions, prior contraceptive use) and women's autonomy in contraceptive decision-making including perceptions of bias in education and counseling.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sub-analyses for unintended pregnancy</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The researchers will assess the outcome of unintended pregnancy by sociodemographic factors (age, race/ethnicity, parental education, health insurance, receipt of public assistance) and reproductive characteristics (parity, pregnancy intentions, male partner, prior contraceptive use).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Sub-analyses for certificate or degree completion (ordinal outcome including categories for on-time progression for graduation, delayed progression or dropout), measured by student report (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The researchers will assess the ordinal educational outcome variable by age, race/ethnicity, parental education, and poverty. The researchers will also test interaction of the intervention with race/ethnicity, parental education, and poverty.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1480</enrollment>
  <condition>Contraception</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Contraceptive Training and Education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Colleges assigned to this arm receive a one-day UCSF Continuing Medical Education (CME # MMC18087) accredited training on contraceptives and technical assistance. The training is for staff at the student health center and local health centers where they refer for contraceptive services. Students attending colleges assigned to this arm receive education about contraceptive methods and how to access services.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Nutrition Education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Students attending colleges assigned to this arm receive nutrition education about the impacts of sugar on health.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Contraceptive Training and Education</intervention_name>
    <description>Staff at the student health center and local health centers where they refer for contraceptive services will receive a CME-accredited education and training session and technical assistance. The one-day session emphasizes evidence-based and patient-centered contraceptive counseling and provision. Students attending colleges assigned to the intervention arm will receive materials and resources designed to educate young people about contraceptive methods and where to access services.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Contraceptive Training and Education</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Nutrition Education</intervention_name>
    <description>Students attending colleges assigned to the nutrition education arm will receive materials and resources designed to educate young people about the impacts of sugar on health.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Nutrition Education</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        This study involves two groups of human subjects: students at 20 community colleges and
        staff at the student health center and referral clinics.

        Students must be:

          -  Female;

          -  Age 18-25;

          -  Speaks English;

          -  Sexually active (vaginal sex with a male partner) in the last year;

          -  Not currently pregnant;

          -  Does not want to become pregnant in the next 12 months;

          -  At risk of pregnancy (including not sterilized);

          -  Enrolled in the current term at the participating community college;

          -  First-time college students, meaning no college enrollment prior to the current
             academic year; and

          -  Willing to be contacted by email and telephone over the next 12 months.

        Clinic staff must:

          -  Be employed by a participating clinic; and

          -  Offer clinical care, counseling or education for contraception at the clinic.

        For colleges to be eligible to be study sites, they must:

          -  Be an accredited community college;

          -  Not share health center staff with a participating college site;

          -  Have no active LARC intervention; and

          -  Enroll students ages 18-25 years.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Students and clinic staff will be excluded if they do not meet the inclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Cynthia Harper, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>415-502-4092</phone>
    <email>cynthia.harper@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94118</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stanwood NL, Bradley KA. Young pregnant women's knowledge of modern intrauterine devices. Obstet Gynecol. 2006 Dec;108(6):1417-22.</citation>
    <PMID>17138775</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frost JJ, Lindberg LD, Finer LB. Young adults' contraceptive knowledge, norms and attitudes: associations with risk of unintended pregnancy. Perspect Sex Reprod Health. 2012 Jun;44(2):107-16. doi: 10.1363/4410712. Epub 2012 May 8.</citation>
    <PMID>22681426</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Finer LB, Zolna MR. Shifts in intended and unintended pregnancies in the United States, 2001-2008. Am J Public Health. 2014 Feb;104 Suppl 1:S43-8. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.2013.301416. Epub 2013 Dec 19.</citation>
    <PMID>24354819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trieu SL, Bratton S, Hopp Marshak H. Sexual and reproductive health behaviors of California community college students. J Am Coll Health. 2011;59(8):744-50. doi: 10.1080/07448481.2010.540764.</citation>
    <PMID>21950256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harper CC, Rocca CH, Thompson KM, Morfesis J, Goodman S, Darney PD, Westhoff CL, Speidel JJ. Reductions in pregnancy rates in the USA with long-acting reversible contraception: a cluster randomised trial. Lancet. 2015 Aug 8;386(9993):562-8. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(14)62460-0. Epub 2015 Jun 16.</citation>
    <PMID>26091743</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sundstrom B, Baker-Whitcomb A, DeMaria AL. A qualitative analysis of long-acting reversible contraception. Matern Child Health J. 2015 Jul;19(7):1507-14. doi: 10.1007/s10995-014-1655-0.</citation>
    <PMID>25424456</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thompson KM, Rocca CH, Kohn JE, Goodman S, Stern L, Blum M, Speidel JJ, Darney PD, Harper CC. Public Funding for Contraception, Provider Training, and Use of Highly Effective Contraceptives: A Cluster Randomized Trial. Am J Public Health. 2016 Mar;106(3):541-6. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.2015.303001. Epub 2016 Jan 21.</citation>
    <PMID>26794168</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Landry DJ, Wei J, Frost JJ. Public and private providers' involvement in improving their patients' contraceptive use. Contraception. 2008 Jul;78(1):42-51. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2008.03.009. Epub 2008 May 29.</citation>
    <PMID>18555817</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gibbs SE, Rocca CH, Bednarek P, Thompson KMJ, Darney PD, Harper CC. Long-Acting Reversible Contraception Counseling and Use for Older Adolescents and Nulliparous Women. J Adolesc Health. 2016 Dec;59(6):703-709. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2016.07.018. Epub 2016 Sep 21. Erratum in: J Adolesc Health. 2018 Jan;62(1):121.</citation>
    <PMID>27665153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>El Ayadi AM, Rocca CH, Kohn JE, Velazquez D, Blum M, Newmann SJ, Harper CC. The impact of an IUD and implant intervention on dual method use among young women: Results from a cluster randomized trial. Prev Med. 2017 Jan;94:1-6. doi: 10.1016/j.ypmed.2016.10.015. Epub 2016 Oct 20.</citation>
    <PMID>27773708</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rocca CH, Thompson KM, Goodman S, Westhoff CL, Harper CC. Funding policies and postabortion long-acting reversible contraception: results from a cluster randomized trial. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2016 Jun;214(6):716.e1-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2015.12.009. Epub 2015 Dec 12.</citation>
    <PMID>26692178</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harper CC, Henderson JT, Raine TR, Goodman S, Darney PD, Thompson KM, Dehlendorf C, Speidel JJ. Evidence-based IUD practice: family physicians and obstetrician-gynecologists. Fam Med. 2012 Oct;44(9):637-45.</citation>
    <PMID>23027156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kost K, Singh S, Vaughan B, Trussell J, Bankole A. Estimates of contraceptive failure from the 2002 National Survey of Family Growth. Contraception. 2008 Jan;77(1):10-21. Epub 2007 Dec 3.</citation>
    <PMID>18082661</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rocca CH, Harper CC. Do racial and ethnic differences in contraceptive attitudes and knowledge explain disparities in method use? Perspect Sex Reprod Health. 2012 Sep;44(3):150-8. doi: 10.1363/4415012. Epub 2012 Jun 26.</citation>
    <PMID>22958659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Finer LB, Zolna MR. Declines in Unintended Pregnancy in the United States, 2008-2011. N Engl J Med. 2016 Mar 3;374(9):843-52. doi: 10.1056/NEJMsa1506575.</citation>
    <PMID>26962904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thompson KM, Stern L, Gelt M, Speidel JJ, Harper CC. Counseling for IUDs and implants: are health educators and clinicians on the same page? Perspect Sex Reprod Health. 2013 Dec;45(4):191-5. doi: 10.1363/4519113. Epub 2013 Oct 28.</citation>
    <PMID>24325290</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harper CC, Stratton L, Raine TR, Thompson K, Henderson JT, Blum M, Postlethwaite D, Speidel JJ. Counseling and provision of long-acting reversible contraception in the US: national survey of nurse practitioners. Prev Med. 2013 Dec;57(6):883-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ypmed.2013.10.005. Epub 2013 Oct 12.</citation>
    <PMID>24128950</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rocca CH, Goodman S, Grossman D, Cadwallader K, Thompson KMJ, Talmont E, Speidel JJ, Harper CC. Contraception after medication abortion in the United States: results from a cluster randomized trial. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2018 Jan;218(1):107.e1-107.e8. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2017.09.020. Epub 2017 Oct 3.</citation>
    <PMID>28986072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kavanaugh ML, Jerman J, Finer LB. Changes in Use of Long-Acting Reversible Contraceptive Methods Among U.S. Women, 2009-2012. Obstet Gynecol. 2015 Nov;126(5):917-27. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0000000000001094.</citation>
    <PMID>26444110</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moore PJ, Adler NE, Kegeles SM. Adolescents and the contraceptive pill: the impact of beliefs on intentions and use. Obstet Gynecol. 1996 Sep;88(3 Suppl):48S-56S.</citation>
    <PMID>8752228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trussell J. Contraceptive efficacy. In: Hatcher R, Trussell J, Nelson A, Cates W, Kowal D, Policar M, eds. Contraceptive technology, 20th edn. New York: Ardent Media, 2011: 779-863.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Whitaker AK, Johnson LM, Harwood B, Chiappetta L, Creinin MD, Gold MA. Adolescent and young adult women's knowledge of and attitudes toward the intrauterine device. Contraception. 2008 Sep;78(3):211-7. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2008.04.119. Epub 2008 Jul 3.</citation>
    <PMID>18692611</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Golden SD, Earp JA. Social ecological approaches to individuals and their contexts: twenty years of health education &amp; behavior health promotion interventions. Health Educ Behav. 2012 Jun;39(3):364-72. doi: 10.1177/1090198111418634. Epub 2012 Jan 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22267868</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Foster DG, Biggs MA, Ralph L, Gerdts C, Roberts S, Glymour MM. Socioeconomic Outcomes of Women Who Receive and Women Who Are Denied Wanted Abortions in the United States. Am J Public Health. 2018 Mar;108(3):407-413. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.2017.304247. Epub 2018 Jan 18.</citation>
    <PMID>29345993</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dehlendorf C, Henderson JT, Vittinghoff E, Steinauer J, Hessler D. Development of a patient-reported measure of the interpersonal quality of family planning care. Contraception. 2018 Jan;97(1):34-40. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2017.09.005. Epub 2017 Sep 18.</citation>
    <PMID>28935217</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 21, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cynthia Harper</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, Department of Obstetrics, Gynecology &amp; Reproductive Sciences</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Contraception</keyword>
  <keyword>Hormonal contraception</keyword>
  <keyword>Long-acting reversible contraception</keyword>
  <keyword>Condoms</keyword>
  <keyword>Emergency contraception</keyword>
  <keyword>Family planning services</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Contraceptive Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

