<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03517761</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RSI2017-RCT01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03517761</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Use of Bone Marrow Concentrate for Treatment of Alar, Accessory, and Transverse Ligament Injuries</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-Blinded, Randomized Controlled Trial Evaluating the Use of Bone Marrow Concentrate for the Treatment of Alar, Accessory, and Transverse Ligament Injuries</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Regenerative Sciences, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Regenerative Sciences, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effectiveness of using anterior approach through
      the posterior oropharynx for treating alar and transverse ligament injuries with bone marrow
      concentrate for patients with craniocervical junction (CCJ) instability.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will be a single-center, prospective, single-blinded, randomized, controlled study
      of patients with CCJ instability that are randomized to either bone marrow concentrate (BMC)
      treatment or a sham procedure to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of using an anterior
      approach through the posterior oropharynx for treating alar and transverse ligament injuries.
      Patients will undergo a bone marrow aspiration of approximately 30-60 cc from the posterior
      superior iliac crest. Platelet rich plasma (PRP) and platelet lysate (PL) will be derived
      from the bone marrow aspirate and later mixed with the bone marrow nucleated cell layer for
      those in the treatment group. While under unconscious TIVA anesthesia, the injectate is then
      injected under fluoroscopy into the area in need of treatment using an anterior approach
      through the posterior oropharynx with direct visualization of the injection site via
      endoscopy. Patients assigned to the sham control condition will also undergo a bone marrow
      aspiration of 30-60 cc to maintain blinding. Control subjects will receive a sham procedure
      of a small skin puncture to the posterior oropharynx guided under fluoroscopy while under
      anesthesia. In this group, the BMC will be donated for research purposes and not used
      clinically. Study patients will be evaluated at 6 and 12 months using patient reported
      clinical outcome questionnaires and digital motion x-ray. Control patients can crossover to
      the treatment group after being unblinded at 6-months post-procedure.

      As an alternative to invasive surgery, ligament injections of proliferant agents
      (prolotherapy) have been proposed to treat cervical instability. Our group has used a blinded
      flexion-extension radiography to demonstrate that injections of cervical proliferant agents
      (hypertonic dextrose) into the supraspinous and interspinous ligaments can objectively reduce
      excessive cervical translation in flexion (Centeno et al. 2005). More recently we have
      published on the use of bone marrow concentrate to demonstrate MRI evidence of robust ACL
      ligament signal changes consistent with healing and repair (Centeno et al. 2015).

      One of the challenges of treating the upper cervical ligaments through injection is that they
      can't be accessed from the posterior due to obstruction from the cervical spinal cord.Our
      group has developed an injection technique using an anterior approach through the posterior
      oropharynx, which allows direct access to the ligaments for injection. The goal of this study
      is to evaluate the effectiveness of this procedure in carefully selected CCJ instability
      patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 23, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2025</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Single-center, prospective, single-blinded, randomized, controlled study to include 80 subjects total, 40 treated with Bone Marrow Concentrate and 40 subjects treated with a Sham Procedure with cross-over from the sham to active group at 6 months</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
    <masking_description>Participants are blind to treatment condition until 6 months post-procedure. Participants in sham control group can crossover to treatment group at that time.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Headache Impact Test score change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from Baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The difference between treatment groups in the within patient mean change from baseline to 6 months in Headache Impact Test scores.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neck Disability Index score change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between groups in changes scores for Neck Disability Index scores from baseline and 6 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neck Disability Index score change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between groups in changes scores for Neck Disability Index scores from baseline and 12 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short Form Health Survey change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between groups in changes scores for Short Form Health Survey scores from baseline and 6 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short Form Health Survey change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between groups in changes scores for Short Form Health Survey scores from baseline and 12 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Numeric Pain Scale change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between groups in changes scores for numeric pain scores from baseline and 6 months, where 0=no pain and 10=worst possible pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Numeric Pain Scale change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between groups in changes scores for numeric pain scores from baseline and 12 months, where 0=no pain and 10=worst possible pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Single Assessment Numeric Evaluation improvement rating -modified</measure>
    <time_frame>mean at 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between groups for mean improvement scores at 6 months, where -100=100% worse from baseline and 100=100% better or improved from baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Single Assessment Numeric Evaluation improvement rating -modified</measure>
    <time_frame>mean at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Difference between groups for mean improvement scores at 12 months, where -100=100% worse from baseline and 100=100% better or improved from baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Thru 12 month post procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Any complication of adverse event</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>C1-C2 overhang</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post procedure</time_frame>
    <description>Post-op DMX studies will also be used to quantify any reduction in C1-C2 overhang or ADI.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Craniocervical Injuries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bone Marrow Concentrate treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bone marrow concentrate subjects will undergo a bone marrow aspiration of approximately 30-60 cc. Platelet rich plasma (PRP) and platelet lysate (PL) will be derived from the bone marrow aspirate and later mixed with the bone marrow nucleated cell layer. Injectate will then be used to treat the ligaments in the CCJ.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control subjects will also undergo a bone marrow aspiration of 30-60 cc to maintain blinding. Control subjects will receive a sham procedure of a small skin puncture to the posterior oropharynx guided under fluoroscopy while under anesthesia.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bone Marrow Concentrate treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>While under unconscious TIVA anesthesia, the injectate is then injected under fluoroscopy into the area in need of treatment using an anterior approach through the posterior oropharynx with direct visualization of the injection site via endoscopy. The alar, transverse, and accessory ligaments are the target areas to be treated with the bone marrow concentrate injectate.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bone Marrow Concentrate treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sham Control</intervention_name>
    <description>Control subjects will receive a sham procedure of a small skin puncture to the posterior oropharynx guided under fluoroscopy while under anesthesia.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sham Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1) Voluntary signature of the IRB approved Informed Consent, 2) Skeletally mature Male
             or Female ages 18 to 65 3) Disabling symptoms of headache, dizziness, neck pain, or
             other neuro-musculoskeletal symptoms, that based on physical exam or diagnostic blocks
             is attributable to the upper cervical spine, for &gt;12 months 4) Symptoms exacerbated by
             activity and relieved by rest 5) Failed all conservative care 6) Hasn't responded
             long-term to:

               1. C0-C3 facet injections

               2. Upper cervical prolotherapy or PRP into the posterior stabilizing ligaments
                  (nuchal, supraspinous, interspinous ligaments) 7) Considered a likely cervical
                  fusion candidate 8) Imaging (one of the three)

               1. Upper cervical MRI showing decreased signal in alar, transverse, PAOM, AAOM, or
                  Tectorial membrane

               2. DMX showing 2 mm or greater lateral overhang of C1 on C2 in lateral bending open
                  mouth view or a V shaped ADI in flexion of increased ADI in flexion

               3. Upper cervical rotatory CT that shows excessive C0-C1 rotation 9) Exam is c/w
                  upper cervical injury (ie. tenderness along upper cervical facet joints and/or
                  musculature/skull base, good anesthetic block response (&gt;50% pain relief) to
                  C0-C3 intra-articular facet injections, proprioceptive difficulties) 10) Is
                  independent, ambulatory, and can comply with all post-operative evaluations and
                  visits 11) Patient states strong desire to avoid surgery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Unable to tolerate injections due to central sensitization (i.e. significant
             intolerance to manual therapy such as massage, activity such as physical therapy, or
             an exaggerated pain response to prior injection therapy)

          2. Previous neck surgery that has caused chronic neck pain or radiculopathy

          3. Prior epidural or other milligram dose steroid injection in any area or other neck
             injection therapy within the past 6 months

          4. Physical infirmity that is incompatible with the procedure and/or anesthesia required
             for same

          5. Unable to tolerate the injection position

          6. Abnormal anatomy seen on MRI imaging that would make the procedure higher risk (e.g.
             congenital atlanto-axial fusion, atlas assimilation, upper cervical fracture or
             surgical fusion)

          7. Inflammatory or auto-immune based pathology (e.g., rheumatoid arthritis, systemic
             lupus erythematosus, psoriatic arthritis, polymyalgia, polymyositis, gout, pseudo
             gout)

          8. Quinolone or Statin induced myopathy/tendinopathy

          9. Severe neurogenic inflammation of the cutaneous nerves

         10. Condition represents a worker's compensation case

         11. Currently involved in a health-related litigation procedure

         12. Is pregnant

         13. Bleeding disorders

         14. Currently taking anticoagulant or immunosuppressive medication

         15. Allergy or intolerance to study medication

         16. Use of and significant physical dependence on a chronic opioid (&gt;20 mg oxycodone
             equivalent per day)

         17. Documented history of drug abuse within six months of treatment

         18. Any other condition, that in the opinion of the investigator, that would preclude the
             patient from enrollment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ehren R Dodson, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>720-287-7199</phone>
    <email>edodson@regenexx.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ehren Dodson</name>
      <address>
        <city>Broomfield</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ehren Dodson, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>720-287-7199</phone>
      <email>edodson@regenexx.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Neven Steinmetz, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>3034296448</phone>
      <phone_ext>141</phone_ext>
      <email>nsteinmetz@regenexx.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christopher Centeno, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Schultz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John Pitts, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jason Markle, DO</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Centeno CJ, Elliott J, Elkins WL, Freeman M. Fluoroscopically guided cervical prolotherapy for instability with blinded pre and post radiographic reading. Pain Physician. 2005 Jan;8(1):67-72.</citation>
    <PMID>16850045</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Panjabi MM, Crisco JJ 3rd, Lydon C, Dvorak J. The mechanical properties of human alar and transverse ligaments at slow and fast extension rates. Clin Biomech (Bristol, Avon). 1998 Mar;13(2):112-120.</citation>
    <PMID>11415778</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rajwanshi A, Rohilla M, Singh P. Trans-oral fine needle aspiration cytology in cervical (C1 and C2) vertebral lesions: a novel diagnostic approach. Cytopathology. 2017 Feb;28(1):31-34. doi: 10.1111/cyt.12361. Epub 2016 Aug 3.</citation>
    <PMID>27489015</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Centeno CJ, Pitts J, Al-Sayegh H, Freeman MD. Anterior cruciate ligament tears treated with percutaneous injection of autologous bone marrow nucleated cells: a case series. J Pain Res. 2015 Jul 31;8:437-47. doi: 10.2147/JPR.S86244. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26261424</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 23, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 24, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CCJ</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone Marrow Concentrate</keyword>
  <keyword>Stem Cell Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Alar Ligament</keyword>
  <keyword>Transverse Ligament</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trauma, Nervous System</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

