<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03511131</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5U01MD011281</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>5U01MD011281</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03511131</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pragmatic Trial of An Adaptive eHealth HIV Prevention Program for Diverse Adolescent MSM</brief_title>
  <acronym>SMART</acronym>
  <official_title>A Pragmatic Trial of An Adaptive eHealth HIV Prevention Program for Diverse Adolescent MSM</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities (NIMHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pragmatic trial of an HIV prevention program focuses on HIV risk-reduction in men who
      have sex with men (MSM) ages 13-18. The design is a three-tiered, internet-based HIV
      prevention intervention series that uses a sequential multiple assignment randomized trial
      (SMART) to track adolescent MSM reporting varying degree of sexual risk.The program package
      includes: (1-low risk) a universally-delivered, brief, online sexual health education program
      designed for sexual and gender minority youth regardless of whether they are sexually active
      (Queer Sex Ed); (2-middle risk) a more intensive online intervention designed for diverse
      AMSM engaging in HIV transmission risk behaviors (Keep It Up!), and (3-high risk) the most
      intensive is a motivational interviewing (MI) intervention that will be delivered by MI
      therapists via online videochat (Young Men's Health Project).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Adolescent (ages 13-18) men who have sex with men (AMSM) experience a dramatic health
      disparity as they represent 2% of young people but account for almost 80% of HIV diagnoses in
      youth. Despite this disproportionate burden, current evidence-based HIV prevention programs
      focus primarily on adults and heterosexual youth. Because issues affecting sexual health
      decisions among AMSM are unique, interventions need to be designed to ensure appropriate
      content that resonates with AMSM. Prevention programs must also be responsive to minority
      AMSM that experience disparities in incidence or lack of access to prevention services. For
      example, Hispanics represent 27% of HIV infections among MSM, but Spanish speaking MSM face
      significant language barriers to accessing HIV services.

      Implementation issues are particularly critical as traditional HIV prevention delivery
      channels have significant limitations for AMSM: few adolescents attend LGBT youth oriented
      programs, schools place many restrictions on discussions of MSM sexual health, and major
      questions remain as to the feasibility of enrolling parents of AMSM into HIV prevention
      programs. With 92% of adolescents (across all races and income levels) going online every
      day, eHealth interventions represent a critical modality for delivering AMSM- specific
      intervention material where youth &quot;are.&quot; Combining online recruitment with intervention
      delivery across a range of devices can overcome many access barriers to engagement of AMSM in
      HIV prevention.

      Unfortunately, there will be no single magic solution that will work for all AMSM and public
      health programmers should not continue to deliver the same fixed intervention when a
      participant is not responding. Alternatively, stepped-care strategies increase in intensity
      to meet the needs of those who do not respond to a less intense intervention. Using a
      Sequential Multiple Assignment Randomized Trial (SMART) design, the investigators will
      evaluate the impact of a package of increasingly intensive interventions that have already
      shown evidence of efficacy with diverse adolescent and young adult MSM. The SMART methodology
      is an ideal approach because SMART designs mimic treatment decisions as they are made in
      real-world clinical settings, components of traditional RCTs are embedded within the design,
      and participant data can be used post-hoc to inform decision rules in order to optimize
      implementation. Collectively the investigators brand this package of eHealth interventions as
      the SMART Program (Sexual Minority Adolescent Risk Taking). The SMART Program package
      includes: (1) a universally-delivered, brief, online sexual health education program designed
      for sexual and gender minority youth regardless of whether they are sexually active (&quot;Queer
      Sex Ed&quot;) (2) a more intensive online intervention designed for diverse AMSM engaging in HIV
      transmission risk behaviors (&quot;Keep It Up!&quot;); and (3) a more intensive motivational
      interviewing (MI) intervention that will be delivered by MI therapists via online videochat
      (&quot;Young Men's Health Project&quot;). The investigators will evaluate the impact of the SMART
      Program and carefully document implementation context to inform scale out with the following
      aims:

      Aim 1: Evaluate the impact of the SMART Program and its constituent components at reducing
      HIV risk among AMSM. To do this, the investigators will:

        1. Involve diverse AMSM (e.g., Youth Advisory Council) in developmentally adapting existing
           SMART Program components for AMSM ages 13-18 using the ADAPT-ITT framework.

        2. Culturally and linguistically adapt the SMART Program for Spanish speaking Latino AMSM
           in the US.

        3. Embed the SMART Program content into an eHealth platform that will allow access on a
           range of devices and accommodate updates. Perform alpha and beta testing.

        4. Enroll a national sample of 1,938 AMSM who are diverse in terms of race/ethnicity, age,
           geographic region, socioeconomic status, and sexual experience history.

        5. Test the effectiveness of the SMART Program at reducing HIV risk taking behaviors,
           increasing HIV testing, and improving prevention intentions. Consistent with a SMART
           design, the investigators operationalize and power the primary test of effectiveness as
           the first point of randomization, which tests the effectiveness of &quot;Keep It Up!&quot;.
           Additional comparisons will allow the investigators to establish the response rate for
           &quot;Queer Sex Ed&quot;, examine whether the more intensive &quot;Young Men's Health Project&quot;
           outperforms the less intensive &quot;Keep It Up!&quot; among non-responders to &quot;Queer Sex Ed,&quot; and
           determine whether &quot;Young Men's Health Project&quot; provides added benefit to AMSM who did
           not respond to &quot;Keep it Up!&quot;.

      Aim 2: Test if the SMART Program has differential efficacy across important sub-groups of
      AMSM. Consistent with the RFA, the investigators will test intervention effects within each
      of the NIH designated health disparity populations (racial/ethnicity minorities, rural, low
      SES), and by age and language (Spanish).

      Aim 3: Evaluate the delivery of the SMART Program nationally to inform scale out and
      determine cost-effectiveness. To reduce the science-practice gap, the investigators will
      utilize mixed methods to identify facilitators and barriers to the implementation of the
      SMART Program using a Hybrid Type 1 Effectiveness-Implementation trial design. The
      investigators will assess process metrics and indicators of its acceptability among AMSM and
      key national stakeholders, scale out feasibility, sustainability potential, and conduct a
      cost analysis to estimate the cost of program implementation compare to monetized benefits.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 18, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Condomless anal sex</measure>
    <time_frame>12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in condomless anal sex acts from baseline to 12-months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Condom Use Intentions Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12-months</time_frame>
    <description>This is a multi-item scale which asks participants about their plans and abilities to use condoms in the future. It has two subscales. The first subscale (Condom Use) asks about participants' likelihood to use condoms with partners. An example item for Condom Use is: &quot;How likely is it that you will use a condom every time you have sex?&quot; The 11-items for this subscale are measured from very unlikely (1) to very likely (4) [averaged min value 1, averaged max value 4]. High values mean a better outcome, or likely condom use with partners. The second subscale (Self-Efficacy) asks participants' ability to use condoms. An example item for Self-Efficacy is: &quot;How confident are you that you would be able to be sure you had condoms with you?&quot; The 5-items for this subscale are measured from not at all confident (1) to extremely confident (7) [averaged min value 1, averaged max value 7]. High values mean a better outcome, or more confidence at using condoms. The two subscales are not combined.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV Testing</measure>
    <time_frame>12-months</time_frame>
    <description>Participants are asked to self-reported their history of actual getting HIV tested.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV Knowledge</measure>
    <time_frame>Months: 0, 3, 6, 9, 12</time_frame>
    <description>The brief HIV/AIDS Knowledge questionnaire assesses knowledge of transmission and prevention of HIV. Example items that are dichotomously measured as true/false, include: &quot;A person can get HIV by sharing a glass of water with someone who has HIV,&quot; &quot;There is a vaccine that can stop people (or adults) from getting HIV,&quot; &quot;Using a latex condom or rubber can lower a person's chance of getting HIV,&quot; etc.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV/AIDS Motivation and Behavioral Skills</measure>
    <time_frame>Months: 0, 3, 6, 9, 12</time_frame>
    <description>Motivation (e.g. perceived threat of HIV/STI infection, motivation to become safer), social norms (e.g., partners/friends/family members opinions about condom use), and behavioral skills (e.g., negotiating condom use) will be assessed. An example of motivation-based measures would be: &quot;True or False: You really only need to use condoms during one night stands.&quot; An example of social norm-based measures would be: &quot;How likely/unlikely is it that you will have sex without a condom because you are afraid of what a partner might do to you if you ask to use condoms?&quot; An example of skills-based measures would be: &quot;How hard would it be for you to discuss safer sex with a partner in a non-sexual setting, such as while riding in your car?&quot; More specific behavioral skills are also measured within the The Health Protective Communication Scale. An example of this would be, &quot;In the past 12 months, have you asked a new sex partner about the number of past sex partners (he/she) had?&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Condom Errors</measure>
    <time_frame>Months: 0, 3, 6, 9, 12</time_frame>
    <description>An adaptation of the Condom Errors Questionnaire will be asked, which has been found to be predictive of condom breakage and slippage, and STI contraction. An example item from this questionnaire is: &quot;When you used condoms during the LAST 6 MONTHS, how often was the condom package checked for visible damage before having sex?&quot;</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>PrEP Knowledge/Experience</measure>
    <time_frame>Months: 0, 3, 6, 9, 12</time_frame>
    <description>The Knowledge of and Experience with Pre-Exposure Prophylaxis (PrEP) scale (for adolescents) will be used. This is a validated scale that asks questions such as: (Agree/Disagree) &quot;Taking pre-exposure prophylaxis (a pill, also known as PrEP or Truvada) regularly can reduce the risk of contracting HIV from an HIV-positive sex partner.&quot;</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>8</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1878</enrollment>
  <condition>Hiv</condition>
  <condition>Adolescent Behavior</condition>
  <condition>Sex, Safe</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Resp (Only follow)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants enter Queer Sex Ed (QSE) and are measured at 0, 3, 6, 9, and 12-months. This arm is comprised of participants who responded to QSE, were randomized at month-6 to no additional treatment, and then followed for the rest of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Resp (KIU at 6-month)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants enter Queer Sex Ed (QSE) and are measured at 0, 3, 6, 9, and 12-months. This arm is comprised of participants who responded to QSE, were randomized at month-6 to receive Keep It Up (KIU), and then followed for the rest of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU-Control Resp</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants enter Queer Sex Ed (QSE) and are measured at 0, 3, 6, 9, and 12-months. This arm is comprised of participants who did not respond to QSE, were randomized at month-3 to receive Keep It Up-Control (KIU-Control), responded to KIU-Control at month-6, and then were followed for the rest of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU-Control Non-Resp, KIU</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants enter Queer Sex Ed (QSE) and are measured at 0, 3, 6, 9, and 12-months. This arm is comprised of participants who did not respond to QSE, were randomized at month-3 to receive Keep It Up-Control (KIU-Control), did not respond to KIU-Control at month-6, and so were randomized into Keep It Up (KIU). After KIU, they were followed for the rest of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU Control Non-Resp, YMHP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants enter Queer Sex Ed (QSE) and are measured at 0, 3, 6, 9, and 12-months. This arm is comprised of participants who did not respond to QSE, were randomized at month-3 to receive Keep It Up-Control (KIU-Control), did not respond to KIU-Control at month-6, and so were randomized into Young Men's Health Project (YMHP). After YMHP, they were followed for the rest of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU Resp</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants enter Queer Sex Ed (QSE) and are measured at 0, 3, 6, 9, and 12-months. This arm is comprised of participants who did not respond to QSE, were randomized at month-3 to receive Keep It Up (KIU), responded to KIU at month-6, and then were followed for the rest of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU Non-Resp</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants enter Queer Sex Ed (QSE) and are measured at 0, 3, 6, 9, and 12-months. This arm is comprised of participants who did not respond to QSE, were randomized at month-3 to receive Keep It Up (KIU), did not respond to KIU at month-6, and then were randomized into no treatment/just follow for the rest of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU Non-Resp, YMHP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants enter Queer Sex Ed (QSE) and are measured at 0, 3, 6, 9, and 12-months. This arm is comprised of participants who did not respond to QSE, were randomized at month-3 to receive Keep It Up (KIU), did not respond to KIU at month-6, and then were randomized into Young Men's Health Project. After YMHP, they were followed for the rest of the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Queer Sex Ed</intervention_name>
    <description>Comprehensive sexual health education program condition (Informational)</description>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Resp (Only follow)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Resp (KIU at 6-month)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU-Control Resp</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU-Control Non-Resp, KIU</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU Control Non-Resp, YMHP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU Resp</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU Non-Resp</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU Non-Resp, YMHP</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>QSE, SMART Sex Ed</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Keep It Up</intervention_name>
    <description>Culturally/situation-relevant HIV-prevention experimental condition (Motivational/behavioral)</description>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Resp (KIU at 6-month)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU-Control Non-Resp, KIU</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU Resp</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU Non-Resp</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU Non-Resp, YMHP</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>KIU, SMART Squad</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Keep It Up-Control</intervention_name>
    <description>HIV knowledge control condition, attention-matched to KIU (Informational)</description>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU-Control Resp</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU-Control Non-Resp, KIU</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU Control Non-Resp, YMHP</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>KIU-Control, SMART Sex Ed 2.0</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Young Men's Health Project</intervention_name>
    <description>Motivational enhancement video interviewing condition (Motivational/behavioral)</description>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU Control Non-Resp, YMHP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>QSE Non-Resp, KIU Non-Resp, YMHP</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>YMHP, SMART Sessions</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  identifying as male-assigned at birth

          -  reporting attraction to men;

          -  13-18 years old

          -  self-reported HIV-negative at the beginning of the study (or have never been HIV
             tested/do not know their HIV status)

          -  able to read English or Spanish,

          -  has a usable e-mail address, textable phone number, and access to the internet or
             smart-phone/-device

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  identifying as female-assigned at birth

          -  reporting no attraction men

          -  identifying as under 13 years of age

          -  identifying as 19 years old or older

          -  self-reported HIV-positive

          -  unable to read English or Spanish

          -  unable to have access to or use email, text messaging, voice calling

          -  unable to have access to the internet or a smart-phone/-device
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Male-assigned at birth</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Brian Mustanski, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Moskowitz, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Brian Mustanski, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>312-503-5421</phone>
    <email>brian@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>David Moskowitz, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>312-503-0055</phone>
    <email>david.moskowitz@northwestern.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Moskowitz, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>312-503-0055</phone>
      <email>david.moskowitz@northwestern.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 29, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 17, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 27, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 14, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 14, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwestern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Brian Mustanski</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, Medical Social Sciences</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescent risk-taking behaviors</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

