<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03515174</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017/2949</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03515174</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial Comparing Active Intervention At Diagnosis With Usual Care to Improve Psycho-social Care in AYAO</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial Comparing Active Intervention at Diagnosis With Usual Care to Improve the Psycho-social Care in the Adolescent and Young Adult Oncology (AYAO) Population</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Centre, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Centre, Singapore</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Adolescents and young adults (AYA) patients experience significant distress in specific areas
      at diagnosis. The investigators hypothesize that providing developmentally-appropriate
      AYA-specific psychosocial care, with an individualized multi-disciplinary program will
      alleviate this distress, as well as improve health-related quality of life (HRQOL).

      The investigators' primary aim is to evaluate the impact of psychosocial interventions on
      HRQOL. The secondary aims are to firstly identify the types of psychosocial distress
      experienced and secondly, to assess the feasibility of implementing a psychosocial screening
      and intervention program amongst AYA patients newly diagnosed with cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 16, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Extent of symptom burden measured using Rotterdam Symptom Checklist (RSCL)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post recruitment</time_frame>
    <description>The Rotterdam Symptom Checklist (RSCL) is a self-report measure to assess the quality of life of cancer patients. It uses a 4-point Likert-type scales (not at all, a little, quite a bit, very much) to measure four domains, namely the physical symptom distress (23 items), psychological distress (7 items) activity level (8 items) overall valuation of life (1 item). The higher the score, the higher the level of burden or impairment. Standardized scores of scales can also be obtained when comparing different scales by transforming raw scores into scores on a 100-point scale using the formula [(raw scale score - minimum raw score) / (maximum - minimum score)] x 100 = transformed score.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life using PedsQL 4.0 Generic Core Scales</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post recruitment</time_frame>
    <description>Pediatrics Quality of Life Inventory (PedsQL) is a model used to measure health-related quality of life (HRQOL) in adolescents and young adults by generating a physical health summary score and psychosocial health summary score both ranging from 0-100, whereby a higher score suggests a better HRQOL. It encompasses physical, mental, and social health, the core dimensions of health defined by the World Health Organization, as well as is school functioning to generate pediatric HRQOL.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patients' distress levels using the National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) Distress Thermometer</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post recruitment</time_frame>
    <description>NCCN Distress Thermometer is a screening tool that measures distress on a 0 to 10 scale, whereby 0 indicates &quot;No distress&quot; and 10 indicates &quot;Extreme distress&quot;. The Distress Thermometer also includes a problem checklist to identify problems that contribute to the score. These include practical problems, family problems, emotional problems, spiritual/religious concerns and physical problems that cancer patients may have.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>At 3 months from baseline</time_frame>
    <description>The satisfaction questionnaire is adapted from a client satisfaction questionnaire incorporating questions about communication with healthcare providers. Patients rate their satisfaction of the info-education sessions - the way it is conducted and content and if their needs have been met on a Likert Scale. This ranges from 1 to 5: with 1 being strongly disagree and, 2 being disagree, 3 being neutral, 4 being agree and 5 being strongly agree. The total score of each individual item is summed up, with higher scores indicating a favourable response to the info-educational sessions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will participate in a structured supportive care program.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in the control group will receive usual care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Supportive Care Program</intervention_name>
    <description>This program takes place within one month post-diagnosis of cancer. It will include three info-educational session. After that, recommendations for further consultation with specific healthcare professionals will be made based on the concerns and needs of patients at baseline. Patient will also be given usual care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be provided with an information booklet by the study team on self-management of cancer- and treatment-related symptoms, which is routinely provided by the National Cancer Centre of Singapore (NCCS) after cancer diagnosis. Usual general advice is provided by the medical oncologists during the routine consultations.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interventional Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  16 to 39 years old

          -  Newly diagnosed with any form of cancers

          -  Capable of giving informed consent (by patients or parents, whichever applicable)

          -  Ability to understand and willingness to sign a written informed consent document

          -  Able to speak and understand English

          -  Able to commit to attending the 3 info-educational sessions as well as
             patient-directed additional visits

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with uncontrolled brain metastasis.

          -  Patients who are unable to commit to attend all 3 info-educational sessions

          -  Patients who are unable to communicate in English.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>39 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eileen YL Poon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Centre, Singapore</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eileen YL Poon, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+65 6436 8000</phone>
    <email>eileen.poon.y.l@singhealth.com.sg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alexandre Chan, PharmD</last_name>
    <email>alexandre.chan@nccs.com.sg</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Centre Singapore</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>169610</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eileen YL Poon, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zebrack B, Isaacson S. Psychosocial care of adolescent and young adult patients with cancer and survivors. J Clin Oncol. 2012 Apr 10;30(11):1221-6. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2011.39.5467. Epub 2012 Mar 12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22412147</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>National Cancer Institute, LIVESTRONG Young Adult Alliance. Closing the Gap: Research and Care Imperatives for Adolescents and Young Adults with Cancer (Report of the Adolescent and Young Adult Oncology Progress Review Group).; 2006. https://www.livestrong.org/content/closing-gap-research-and-care-imperatives-adolescents-and-young-adults-cancer.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richter D, Koehler M, Friedrich M, Hilgendorf I, Mehnert A, Weißflog G. Psychosocial interventions for adolescents and young adult cancer patients: A systematic review and meta-analysis. Crit Rev Oncol Hematol. 2015 Sep;95(3):370-86. doi: 10.1016/j.critrevonc.2015.04.003. Epub 2015 Apr 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25922217</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chan A, Gan YX, Oh SK, Ng T, Shwe M, Chan R, Ng R, Goh B, Tan YP, Fan G. A culturally adapted survivorship programme for Asian early stage breast cancer patients in Singapore: A randomized, controlled trial. Psychooncology. 2017 Oct;26(10):1654-1659. doi: 10.1002/pon.4357. Epub 2017 Jan 25.</citation>
    <PMID>28024163</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lim HA, Mahendran R, Chua J, Peh CX, Lim SE, Kua EH. The Distress Thermometer as an ultra-short screening tool: a first validation study for mixed-cancer outpatients in Singapore. Compr Psychiatry. 2014 May;55(4):1055-62. doi: 10.1016/j.comppsych.2014.01.008. Epub 2014 Jan 18.</citation>
    <PMID>24556515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mahendran R, Lim HA, Chua J, Lim SE, Kua EH. Psychosocial concerns of cancer patients in Singapore. Asia Pac J Clin Oncol. 2017 Apr;13(2):e96-e103. doi: 10.1111/ajco.12344. Epub 2015 Apr 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25856735</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Watson M, Law M, Maguire B, et al. Further development of a quality of life measure for cancer patients; the Rotterdam Symptom Checklist (revised). Psychooncology. 1992;1:35-44.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ewing JE, King MT, Smith NF. Validation of modified forms of the PedsQL generic core scales and cancer module scales for adolescents and young adults (AYA) with cancer or a blood disorder. Qual Life Res. 2009 Mar;18(2):231-44. doi: 10.1007/s11136-008-9424-4. Epub 2009 Jan 23.</citation>
    <PMID>19165624</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larsen DL, Attkisson CC, Hargreaves WA, Nguyen TD. Assessment of client/patient satisfaction: development of a general scale. Eval Program Plann. 1979;2(3):197-207.</citation>
    <PMID>10245370</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mitchell AJ. Short screening tools for cancer-related distress: a review and diagnostic validity meta-analysis. J Natl Compr Canc Netw. 2010 Apr;8(4):487-94. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20410338</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 28, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Adolescent and Young Adult Oncology</keyword>
  <keyword>Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Sarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

