<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03518866</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-MK-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03518866</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patient Recovery After Knee Replacement Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Feasibility Study to Monitor Post Discharge Activity of Patient Recovery After Knee Replacement Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bev Hoddell</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Open University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Milton Keynes University Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This main objective of this feasibility study is to begin to quantify the relationship
      between patient activity levels following knee replacement surgery and outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This main objective of this feasibility study is to begin to quantify the relationship
      between patient activity levels following knee replacement surgery and outcomes.

      Primary Aims The primary objective of this study is to compare step count and activity levels
      with key outcome measures - including pain scores and painkiller usage - to determine whether
      more active people have better recovery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 21, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in mean weekly step count between pre surgery and 6 weeks post surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>7 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Daily activity level of participant as measured by step count automatically on commercial step counter at one minute granularity from up to one week before surgery up to 6 weeks post surgery. Step count data for days which are deemed non compliant (not wearing device long enough) will be ignored. Total average daily step count (for compliant days) each week will be reported.
The outcome measure we plan to use will be the mean daily step count from the 6th week post op. The baseline will be the mean step count from the 1 week prior to surgery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Daily Pain Score over 6 weeks following surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked to record their NRS-11 (Numeric Rating Scale) pain level in the morning, afternoon and evening daily in a paper diary for six weeks after surgery. NRS-11 is an integer scale from 0-10 with 0 representing no pain and 10 representing worst pain possible.
The outcome measure will be the mean pain score from the 6 week post op period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean weekly Oxford Knee Score for 6 weeks following surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>For the 6 weeks following surgery, at the end of each week patients will be asked to fill in the 12 question Oxford Knee Score (OKS) questionnaire which will result in an integer score from 0-48 for each week.
The outcome measure will be the mean OKS over the 6 week post op period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The OKS (Oxford Knee Score) at 6 months post surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Routine physiotherapy review appointment 6 months post surgery. OKS is collected and uploaded to standard hospital outcomes database.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The OKS (Oxford Knee Score) at 12 months post surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Routine physiotherapy review appointment 12 months post surgery. OKS is collected and uploaded to standard hospital outcomes database.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Pain score at 6 months post surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Routine physiotherapy review appointment 6 months post surgery. Pain score is collected and uploaded to standard hospital outcomes database.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Pain score at 12 months post surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Routine physiotherapy review appointment 12 months post surgery. Pain score is collected and uploaded to standard hospital outcomes database.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">46</enrollment>
  <condition>Total Knee Replacement</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Adults undergoing elective single total knee replacement surgery at Milton Keynes
        University Hospital under the care of the principal investigator with no other relevant
        co-morbidities.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        * Adult

          -  Must be able to converse and understand English

          -  The participants must be selected for for single full knee replacement surgery at
             Milton Keynes University Hospital

          -  The participant must have access to a computer at home or be willing to plug a
             synchronization box into their broadband router

          -  The participants must have access to a valid email address or be able to create one
             for the purpose of this study (this may belong to a spouse, partner, friend or
             relative) or have access to a mobile phone able to receive SMS (text) messages

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Insufficient language skills to understand the study procedures

          -  Cognitive impairment

          -  Medical conditions (e.g., severe neurological disorder, acute cancer, psychiatric
             disorder, acute infections) that prevent participation in the study

          -  Wheelchair user

          -  Significant lower limb arthritic joints

          -  Severe mobility limitation due to central or peripheral respiratory dysfunction

          -  Severe mobility limitation due to central or peripheral nervous system disorders

          -  Severe mobility limitation due to spinal condition

          -  Severe mobility limitation due to musculoskeletal disabilities

          -  Rheumatoid arthritis due to joint pain in both upper and lower limbs

          -  Amputee

          -  Dementia
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Blaine Price</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Open University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Milton Keynes University Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milton Keynes</city>
        <state>Bucks</state>
        <zip>MK6 5LD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 11, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 25, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Milton Keynes University Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bev Hoddell</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Academic Research Coordinator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Anonymised raw participant data for basic demographics, surgery date, daily step count, pain scores, Oxford Knee scores will be shared on the institutional open data archive.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

