<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03511833</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TASMC-18-PH-0459-17-CTIL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03511833</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of Treatment by IN Ketamine to IV Morphine in Acute Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of Treatment by IN Ketamine to IV Morphine in Acute Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical Corps, Israel Defense Force</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients who present with acute traumatic injuries in the pre-hospital setting or to the
      emergency department (ED) are treated with opioids, the current gold standard for severe
      acute pain therapy. Treatment with opioids has many disadvantages: the need of skilled
      manpower to administer the medication IV, numerous side effects- mainly cardiorespiratory
      depression- which necessitates post medication administration continuous monitoring of
      patients. IV administration may be difficult or impossible to provide in a number of extreme
      circumstances. For these reasons, there is a constant search for alternate treatment options
      for pain in acute traumatic injuries. IN ketamine has only recently been studied favorably in
      our department in adults, in an open, prospective study (Shimonovich at al 2016), and
      warrants further investigation in the setting of acute traumatic pain. Ketamine is a safe and
      efficacious analgesic and is overall well received both by patients and physicians. Side
      effects include: hallucinations and dissociation. As opposed to opioids, ketamine does not
      alter patients' respiratory and hemodynamic stability giving ketamine great therapeutic
      potential for pain reduction in trauma patients, pre-hospital patients, and battlefield
      injuries. The study we are conducting is designed to test and analyze the safety and efficacy
      of IN Ketamine compared to IV morphine in a setting of acute traumatic pain in the ED, when
      both medications are administered by the protocol as is customary for treatment of pain in
      the Emergency Medicine department, and will be a prospective, randomized, double blind,
      controlled study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The procedure:

        1. Eligible patients will be identified by the ED personnel. They will make sure to inquire
           about and also visually inspect the patient's nares regarding nasal congestion, deviated
           septum, obstruction or injury.

        2. Research physician will address the patient, explain about the trial and ask the patient
           to sign a consent form.

        3. The patient will be randomized and assigned to a trial group: &quot;A&quot; or &quot;B&quot; and it will be
           noted in the Data sheet.

        4. According to physician order (IV amount and IN amount) and patient group assignment, the
           nurse will prepare two blinded syringes that will be marked &quot;A&quot; or &quot;B&quot; (the assigned
           group) and &quot;IN&quot; or &quot;IV&quot; and note in the data sheet the time of syringe preparation.

        5. The IV syringe will contain either Morphine or Normal Saline (up to 10 ml), and the IN
           syringe will contain either Ketamine or Normal saline (up to 2 ml).

        6. The amount in the syringes will be calculated based on the patients' weight:

           IV-0.1 mg/kg: Morphine vial contains 10 mg/10 ml = 1mg/ml ----&gt; 0.1 ml/kg IN-1 mg/kg:
           Ketamine vial contains 100 mg/2 ml = 50mg/ml ---&gt; 0.02ml/kg

        7. Administration of the medication is limited to one hour from preparation in the syringe.

        8. The nurse will hand the syringes to the researcher (blinded and coded) and note in the
           data sheet the time of administration and the amount to administer IN and IV.

        9. Prior to administering medication to the patient the researcher will measure vital signs
           (blood pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate, and O2 saturation) as well as pain level
           on a 100 mm VAS (visual analogue scale) questionnaire.

       10. After administration of medications the researcher will measure vital signs (blood
           pressure, heart rate, respiratory rate, and O2 saturation) as well as pain level on a
           100 mm VAS questionnaire every 5 minutes for the first 30 minutes and then every 15
           minutes after that at 30, 45, 60, and 90 minutes.

           Saturation &gt;95% on room air; if lower than 90%, the patient will be placed on 40% oxygen
           mask.

       11. Measurement of vital signs will not interfere with any other treatment that the patients
           receives for their injury in the ED.

       12. If the patient will be moved to another department from the ED, they will be withdrawn
           from the study.

       13. Cardiorespiratory follow-up (as per bullet point number 8 above), will be concluded at
           1.5 hours post-intervention, and clinical follow-up will continue as long as the patient
           remains in the ED.

       14. 90 minutes after drug administration, if pain had not subsided sufficiently according to
           treating physician's clinical assessment, patient will receive further analgesic
           medications by physician order, as per ED protocol. The protocol takes into account
           concurrent medications (in this case either morphine or ketamine. Neither morphine nor
           ketamine will be used in these patients after test drug administration.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 28, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Eligible patients will be randomized according to a blocked randomization scheme using www.sealedenvelope.com (site accessed Sep 10, 2017), which permits assignment of the participant to either group &quot;A&quot; or &quot;group B&quot; (the IN ketamine or IV morphine group). Only the pharmacy will have knowledge of which group is Ketamine and which group is Morphine. Eligible patients will be divided in equal proportions (58 in group A and 58 in group B). Both medications will be prepared by the pharmacy as coded kits, and will be stored in the ER safe with clear signage: &quot;For ketamine/morphine clinical trial only&quot;. Shelf life of the kits is 6 months. Each vial in a kit will be marked by the group name either &quot;A&quot; or &quot;B&quot; and by either &quot;IN&quot; or &quot;IV&quot;. The &quot;IV&quot; vials will either contain: morphine (10 mg of morphine in 10 ml saline) or 10 ml saline for IV administration, and the &quot;IN&quot; vials will either contain ketamine (100 mg in 2ml saline) or 2 ml saline for nasal administration.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness of intranasal ketamine in decreasing pain intensity [patient assessed - VAS pain score] [ Time Frame: 2 hour post administration</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Time to achieve a clinically meaningful pain reduction was defined as the first time-point at which the patient reported 15mm of pain reduction or more. Maximal pain reduction was defined as the lowest VAS score reported by the patient over the course of follow-up. Time to maximal pain reduction was defined as the time at which the patient has the lowest VAS score over the course of the 2 hours follow-up.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>• adverse effects [Opiate Related Symptom Distress Scale] [ Time Frame: 2 hour post administration ]</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse effects were recorded at the end of two hours using the 'Opiate Related Symptom Distress Scale' and included measurements of the presence, frequency, intensity and disruptiveness of 12 common opiate side-effects. Among these were nausea, vomiting, urinary retention, constipation, difficulty concentrating, dizziness, confusion, and others.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>• patient satisfaction [Interview] [ Time Frame: 2 hours post administration ]</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours post administration</time_frame>
    <description>patients were asked to provide subjective comments</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Traumatic Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Morphine group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Morphine group will receive IV medication and IN saline.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ketamine group will receive IV saline and IN medication.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Morphine</intervention_name>
    <description>IV morphine -0.1 mg/kg: Morphine vial contains 10 mg/10 ml = 1mg/ml ----&gt; 0.1 ml/kg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Morphine group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>no other Intervention name</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ketamine</intervention_name>
    <description>IN ketamine: 1 mg/kg: Ketamine vial contains 100 mg/2 ml = 50mg/ml ---&gt; 0.02ml/kg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ketamine group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>no other Intervention name</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  be 18-70 years old

          -  self-report pain greater than or equal to 7/10 on a numerical-verbal scale

          -  weigh 50-100 kg

          -  have an ASA (American Society of Anaesthesiologists' classification) score of 1-2

          -  have systolic blood pressure of 90-160 mmHg

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  have had opioid analgesia administered within 2 hours of the study

          -  are chronic analgesia users (of opioid or others)

          -  have known allergies to morphine or ketamine

          -  have had a large meal within an hour prior to trauma

          -  are pregnant

          -  have a psychiatric history

          -  have nasal congestion, nasal trauma, epistaxis, or a deviated nasal septum

          -  have suffered any head or face trauma: any trauma that is manifested by an external
             mark in the face or skull.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pinchas Halpern, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+97236973829</phone>
    <email>DR_HALPERIN@tlvmc.gov.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Daniel Trotzky, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+972507308675</phone>
    <email>danieltro@tlvmc.gov.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tel Aviv Sourasky Medical Center, department of Emergency Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tel Aviv</city>
        <zip>6423906</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Pinchas Halpern, MD</last_name>
      <phone>972-3-6973829</phone>
      <email>dr_halperin@tasmc.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Daniel Trotzky, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+972507308675</phone>
      <email>danieltro@tlvmc.gov.il</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pinchas Halpern, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 5, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 18, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 30, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>michal roll</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, R&amp;D Department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Intra nasal ketamine</keyword>
  <keyword>IV morphine</keyword>
  <keyword>acute traumatic pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acute Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Morphine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ketamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>a table summering pain assessing questioners will be available from corresponding author on reasonable request.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

