<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01680965</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCC-17071</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01680965</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ofatumumab as Primary Therapy of Chronic Graft Versus Host Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Ofatumumab in Combination With Glucocorticoids for Primary Therapy of Chronic Graft Versus Host Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To study the safety and side effects of Ofatumumab in the treatment of chronic
      graft-versus-host disease (GvHD). This study will also evaluate effectiveness of Ofatumumab
      when added to standard steroid treatment for chronic graft-versus-host disease
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase I-II trial to examine the safety and efficacy of prednisone and escalating
      dose of ofatumumab for the primary therapy of chronic GVHD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 14, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of Dose Limiting Toxicities</measure>
    <time_frame>within 28 days of initiation</time_frame>
    <description>The dose limiting toxicity (DLT) will be Common Toxicity Criteria for Adverse Effects (CTCAE) version 4.0 defined grade 4 adverse events attributable to the study agent ofatumumab</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participants Response Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months following initiation of Ofatumumab</time_frame>
    <description>Overall response rate (ORR) at 6 months following initiation of therapy represents the composite outcome of complete and partial response</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Graft Versus Host Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ofatumumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Phase I:
Escalating dose of ofatumumab
Phase II:
Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of Ofatumumab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ofatumumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase I: test an escalating dose of ofatumumab at cohorts of 300 mg, 700 mg, and 1000 mg given on day 0 and 14 of study.
Phase II: Ofatumumab MTD on day 0 and 14; patients will be followed for total of 24 months (months 1, 3, 6, 12 after therapy, then at 18 and 24 months following therapy)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ofatumumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Hematopoietic cell transplantation (HCT) recipients newly requiring systemic
             glucocorticoid therapy (at ≥ 1mg/kg/day prednisone or equivalent) for chronic GVHD

          -  Participants can be enrolled and begin study therapy with ofatumumab within 14 days
             from initiation of 1 mg/kg/day prednisone for therapy of chronic GVHD.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Relapse of primary hematologic malignancy that served as indication for HCT.

          -  Previous systemic glucocorticoid therapy (at ≥ 1mg/kg/day prednisone or equivalent)
             for chronic GVHD

          -  Prior systemic glucocorticoid therapy for acute GVHD is permitted

          -  Prior or ongoing systemic immune suppressive agents (including, but not limited to
             common examples such as calcineurin inhibitors, sirolimus, mycophenolate mofetil)
             provided for either prevention or treatment of acute GVHD are permitted and part of
             routine standard of care

          -  Current active hepatic or biliary disease (with exception of liver disease secondary
             to chronic GVHD, or patients with Gilbert's syndrome, asymptomatic gallstones, or
             stable chronic liver disease per investigator assessment).

          -  Patients with abnormal liver function tests due to chronic GVHD are specifically not
             excluded from the study. This is a common manifestation of chronic GVHD, and thus a
             major target for the study therapy.

          -  Treatment with experimental non-FDA approved therapy within 5 terminal half lives or 4
             weeks prior to enrollment, whichever is longer

          -  Other past or current solid tumor malignancy

          -  Have been free of malignancy for at least 5 years, or have a history of completely
             resected non-melanoma skin cancer, or successfully treated in situ carcinoma are
             eligible.

          -  Prior treatment with anti-CD20 monoclonal antibody or alemtuzumab within 3 months
             prior to start of therapy.

          -  Uncontrolled infectious complications not responsive to appropriate antimicrobial
             therapy.

          -  History of significant cerebrovascular disease (i.e. stroke or TIA) in the past 6
             months or ongoing event with active symptoms or sequelae

          -  HIV positivity

          -  Uncontrolled, current significant cardiac disease including unstable angina, acute
             myocardial infarction within six months prior to randomization, congestive heart
             failure (NYHA III-IV), and arrhythmia unless controlled by therapy, with the exception
             of extra systoles or minor conduction abnormalities.

          -  A history of cardiac disease, such as coronary disease, arrhythmia or congestive heart
             failure that are on appropriate medical therapy and without evidence of current
             decompensation are eligible.

          -  Significant concurrent, uncontrolled medical condition including, but not limited to,
             renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal, endocrine, pulmonary, neurological, cerebral or
             psychiatric disease which in the opinion of the investigator may represent a risk for
             the patient.

          -  Those patients with medical conditions that are controlled with medical therapy are
             eligible.

          -  Clinically active Hepatitis B defined as positive HBsAg; or positive HBcAb with
             detectable hepatitis B virus (HBV) DNA viral load. Patients who are HBcAb with
             undetectable HBV DNA viremia are eligible.

          -  Positive serology for hepatitis C (HC) defined as a positive test for HCAb and
             confirmed by HC RIBA or hepatitis C virus (HCV) RNA viral load

          -  Screening laboratory value exclusion criteria: platelets &lt; 50 x 10^9/L (patients with
             platelet counts &gt; 50 x 10^9/L supported by platelet transfusion are eligible);
             neutrophils &lt; 1.0 x 10^9/L (patients with an absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1.0 x 10^9/L
             supported by growth factors are eligible); creatinine &gt; 2.0 times upper normal limit;
             total bilirubin &gt;1.5 times upper normal limit (unless due to chronic GVHD); alanine
             transaminase (ALT) &gt; 2.0 times upper normal limit (unless due to chronic GVHD);
             alkaline phosphatase &gt; 2.5 times upper normal limit (unless due to chronic GVHD).

          -  Women who are pregnant or lactating. Women of childbearing potential must have a
             negative pregnancy test at screening.

          -  Women of child bearing potential must undergo pregnancy testing within 7 days of the
             first dose of study therapy. Women must also undergo pregnancy test at 6 months after
             the last dose.

          -  Women of childbearing potential, including women whose last menstrual period was less
             than one year prior to screening, unable or unwilling to use adequate contraception
             from study start to one year after the last dose of protocol therapy. Adequate
             contraception is defined as hormonal birth control, intrauterine device, double
             barrier method or total abstinence.

          -  Males unable or unwilling to use adequate contraception methods from study start to
             one year after the last dose of protocol therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph Pidala, MD, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>H. Lee Moffitt Cancer Center and Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85054</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>H.Lee Moffitt Cancer Center &amp; Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.moffitt.org/</url>
    <description>H.Lee Moffitt Cancer Center &amp; Research Institute</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 4, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 6, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 7, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Graft vs. Host Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>GVHD</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic graft versus host disease (cGVHD)</keyword>
  <keyword>Allogeneic Transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Ofatumumab</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Graft vs Host Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ofatumumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

