<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01685138</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CLDK378A2203</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-003474-36</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01685138</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>LDK378 in Crizotinib naïve Adult Patients With ALK-activated Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II, Multicenter, Single-arm Study of Oral LDK378 in Crizotinib naïve Adult Patients With ALK-activated Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Novartis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A single-arm, open-label, two-stage multicenter, phase II study. Patients will be
      pre-screened for ALK positive status. Treatment with LDK378 at 750 mg qd will continue until
      the patient experiences unacceptable toxicity that precludes further treatment, discontinues
      treatment at the discretion of the investigator or patient, starts a new anticancer therapy
      and/or dies. LDK378 may be continued beyond RECIST defined PD as assessed by the
      investigator, if in the judgment of the investigator, there is evidence of clinical benefit.
      Patients who discontinue the study medication in the absence of progression will continue to
      be followed for tumor assessment until the time of PD as assessed by the investigator. Male
      and female patients aged 18 or over with ALK-rearranged NSCLC will be screened for
      eligibility. Patients must have received no prior crizotinib, and must be chemotherapy-naïve
      or have been pretreated with cytotoxic chemotherapy (up to three prior lines)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-arm, open-label, two-stage, multicenter, phase II study in which the
      efficacy and safety of LDK378 will be evaluated in patients with stage IIIB or IV NSCLC
      harboring a confirmed ALK rearrangement, defined as 15% or more positive tumor cells as
      assessed by the FDA-approved FISH test (Abbott Molecular Inc.) using Vysis breakapart probes.

      Patients will be pre-screened to test for ALK positivity. The test to confirm ALK
      rearrangement must be performed either using archival tissue or, preferably, using a fresh
      biopsy prior to study entry according to the above criteria, i.e. with an FDA-approved assay.
      The test will be performed at a Novartis designated central laboratory.

      After confirmation of ALK positivity, the study begins with a screening period to assess
      eligibility, up to and including 28 days prior to the first dose of LDK378.

      Patients must not have received prior crizotinib. Patients must be chemotherapy-naïve or have
      been pretreated with cytotoxic chemotherapy (up to three prior lines)

      The study will use a Simon's optimal two-stage design. Stage 1 will consist of 43 patients
      and their data up to 6 cycles of treatment unless a patient has discontinued treatment
      earlier or a confirmed response to treatment has been observed prior to completing 6 cycles.
      The trial will be stopped at Stage 1 for futility if 16 or fewer responses are observed. If
      at the time that the last patient is enrolled to Stage 1 a minimum of 17 responses have not
      yet been observed, accrual may be temporarily suspended during the analysis of Stage 1. The
      Data Monitoring Committee will periodically review response data and will make the
      appropriate recommendation regarding transition into Stage 2 or stopping enrollment. Stage 2
      will include an additional 62 patients. The primary analysis will occur when all 105 patients
      have completed 6 cycles of treatment or discontinued treatment earlier.

      The treatment period begins on Day 1 of Cycle 1. All patients will be treated with LDK378,
      administered orally, at a starting dose of 750 mg. A total of approximately 105 patients will
      be enrolled in the study. Patients will take LDK378 once daily, at approximately the same
      time each day. On days when a PK sample is obtained, the patient will take LDK378 during the
      clinic visit as instructed by the study staff. Treatment with LDK378 will continue until the
      patient experiences unacceptable toxicity that precludes further treatment, discontinues
      treatment at the discretion of the patient or investigator, starts a new anti-cancer therapy
      or dies. If the patient experiences RECIST-defined progressive disease (PD) on LDK378 as
      assessed by the investigator, treatment with the study drug may be continued if, in the
      judgment of the investigator, there is still evidence of clinical benefit. These patients
      will be counted as PD for ORR, DOR, DCR and PFS calculations.

      Assessments of tumor response and progression will be performed every 8 weeks (i.e. every 2
      cycles), starting from the first day of treatment with LDK378. This schedule of tumor
      assessment every 8 weeks must continue regardless of dose interruptions. Tumor assessment
      should continue until:

        -  For patients who experience PD as assessed by the investigator, tumor assessments should
           continue every 8 weeks until LDK378 is permanently discontinued (i.e. if the patient
           continues treatment with LDK378 after PD, tumor assessments should continue until LDK378
           is permanently discontinued).

        -  For patients who discontinue treatment in the absence of PD, tumor assessments should
           continue every 8 weeks from the EOT visit until PD is assessed by the investigator.

      Tumor evaluations will always cease if the patient starts a new anti-cancer therapy,
      withdraws consent (unless the patient agrees to continue efficacy assessments in absence of
      dosing with LDK378, or dies.

      All tumor imaging assessments will be submitted for independent radiological assessment of
      response by a Blinded Independent Review Committee (BIRC).

      Clinical and laboratory assessments will be performed.

      When the patient discontinues from study treatment an End of Treatment (EOT) visit must be
      performed as soon as possible and within 7 days of the last dose of LDK378. Patients will be
      contacted for the safety follow-up 30 days after their last dose of LDK378 to determine if
      they have experienced any new AEs and/or to follow resolution of ongoing AEs.

      Following the end of tumor assessments, the Study Phase Completion Disposition eCRF must be
      completed. Patients will be contacted every 3 months to obtain information pertaining to
      survival status until death, loss to follow-up, withdrawal of consent to survival follow-up,
      or the end of the study. Patients do not need to visit the clinic during the survival
      follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 20, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 29, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 29, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate (ORR) to LDK378 by investigator assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 cycles of 28 days up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>ORR per RECIST 1.1 calculated as the proportion of patients with a best overall response (OR) defined as complete response (CR) or partial response (PR) as assessed by investigator.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response (DOR)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 cycles of 28 days up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>DOR, calculated as the time from the date of the first documented CR or PR to the first documented progression or death due to underlying cancer, by investigator and BIRC (Blinded Independent Review Committee) assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate (DCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 cycles of 28 days up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>DCR, calculated as the proportion of patients with best overall response of CR, PR, or SD, by investigator and BIRC assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Response (TTR)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 cycles of 28 days up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>TTR, calculated as the time from first dose of LDK378 to first documented response (CR+PR), by investigator and BIRC assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ORR by BIRC assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>6 cycles of 28 days up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>ORR (CR+PR) per RECIST 1.1 as assessed by BIRC</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety profile</measure>
    <time_frame>6 cycles of 28 days up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events and laboratory abnormalities</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 cycles of 28 days up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>PFS, defined as time from first dose of LDK378 to progression or death due to any cause, as assessed by BIRC and investigator assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 cycles of 28 days up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>OS, defined as time from first dose of LDK378 to death due to any cause</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall intracranial response rate (OIRR)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 cycles of 28 days up to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>OIRR calculated as the ORR (CR+PR) of lesions in the brain for patients who have measureable disease in the brain at baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">126</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LDK378</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral LDK378 750 mg once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LDK378</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral LDK378 750 mg once daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>LDK378</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of stage IIIB or IV NSCLC that
             carries an ALK rearrangement, as per the FDA-approved Vysis ALK break-apart FISH assay
             (Abbott Molecular Inc.)

          -  Age 18 years or older at the time of informed consent.

          -  Patients must have NSCLC that has progressed during or after the last chemotherapy
             regimen received prior to the first dose of LDK378, if chemotherapy was received

          -  Patients must be chemotherapy-naive or have received 1-3 lines of cytotoxic
             chemotherapy to treat their locally advanced or metastatic NSCLC

          -  Patients must have a tumor tissue sample available, collected either at the time of
             diagnosis of NSCLC or any time since.

          -  Patients must have recovered from all toxicities related to prior anticancer therapies
             to grade ≤ 2, except for patients with grade 2 nausea/vomiting and/or grade 2 diarrhea
             despite optimal supportive therapy who will not be allowed to participate in the
             study.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Prior treatment with crizotinib, or any other ALK inhibitor investigational agent, for
             NSCLC

          -  Patients with known hypersensitivity to any of the excipients of LDK378.

          -  Patients with symptomatic central nervous system (CNS) metastases who are
             neurologically unstable or have required increasing doses of steroids within the 2
             weeks prior to study entry to manage CNS symptoms.

          -  History of carcinomatous meningitis.

          -  Presence or history of a malignant disease other than NSCLC that has been diagnosed
             and/or required therapy within the past 3 years.

          -  Clinically significant, uncontrolled heart disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Novartis Pharmaceuticals</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital Mass Gen 5</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>U of TX Southwestern Medical Center - SimmonsCompCancerCtr Clinical Research Office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Leonards</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2065</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Franston</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3199</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Auckland</city>
        <zip>1142</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Genk</city>
        <zip>3600</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 2M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saskatoon</city>
        <state>Saskatchewan</state>
        <zip>S7N 4H4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Herblain cedex</city>
        <zip>44805</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Avellino</city>
        <state>AV</state>
        <zip>83100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Genova</city>
        <state>GE</state>
        <zip>16132</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milano</city>
        <state>MI</state>
        <zip>20141</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rozzano</city>
        <state>MI</state>
        <zip>20089</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orbassano</city>
        <state>TO</state>
        <zip>10043</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nagoya</city>
        <state>Aichi</state>
        <zip>464-8681</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kashiwa</city>
        <state>Chiba</state>
        <zip>277-8577</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Akashi</city>
        <state>Hyogo</state>
        <zip>673-8558</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>OsakaSayama</city>
        <state>Osaka</state>
        <zip>589-8511</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sunto-gun</city>
        <state>Shizuoka</state>
        <zip>411-8777</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chuo-ku</city>
        <state>Tokyo</state>
        <zip>104-0045</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Koto</city>
        <state>Tokyo</state>
        <zip>135-8550</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fukuoka</city>
        <zip>811-1395</zip>
        <country>Japan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <state>Korea</state>
        <zip>03080</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <state>Korea</state>
        <zip>05505</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <state>Korea</state>
        <zip>06351</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>03722</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oslo</city>
        <zip>NO-0424</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chelyabinsk</city>
        <zip>454087</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Moscow</city>
        <zip>115478</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>St-Petersburg</city>
        <zip>197022</zip>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>169610</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Malaga</city>
        <state>Andalucia</state>
        <zip>29010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Badalona</city>
        <state>Catalunya</state>
        <zip>08916</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <state>Catalunya</state>
        <zip>08035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28046</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28050</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <zip>SE-171 76</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Uppsala</city>
        <zip>SE-751 85</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tainan</city>
        <state>Taiwan ROC</state>
        <zip>70421</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <state>Taiwan, ROC</state>
        <zip>11217</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taichung</city>
        <zip>407</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <zip>10002</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <zip>10330</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <zip>10400</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <zip>10700</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Songkla</city>
        <zip>90110</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Colchester</city>
        <zip>CO3 3NB</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Novartis Investigative Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE1 9RT</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Japan</country>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
    <country>Norway</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Singapore</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Sweden</country>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
    <country>Thailand</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>New Zealand</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 4, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 13, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 14, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 19, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 19, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer, ALK, LDK378</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Crizotinib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ceritinib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

