<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01684020</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ART-RHI-12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01684020</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study Evaluating the Efficacy and Safety of ARTISS Human Fibrin Sealant as Used in External Rhinoplasty</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Double-Blinded, Randomized Study Evaluating the Efficacy and Safety of ARTISS Human Fibrin Sealant as Used in External Rhinoplasty</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>DeNova Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Baxter Healthcare Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>DeNova Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rhinoplasty (nasal reconstruction i.e. &quot;a nose job&quot;) is a surgical procedure performed on the
      nose to correct a medical problem or change the appearance of the nose. During the healing
      process, swelling and/or bruising is likely to occur. A drug called ARTISS Fibrin Sealant may
      or may not lessen these effects. This study is looking to see the effects of ARTISS on
      adhering tissue and improving wound healing in an external rhinoplasty. The purpose of this
      study is to evaluate the safety and effectiveness of rhinoplasty using ARTISS compared to
      rhinoplasty without using ARTISS in patients undergoing rhinoplasty performed through an
      external approach.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy will be determined by a live assessment of edema at 4 weeks using a four-point categorical scale [(none, mild, moderate, severe)].</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary safety endpoint is the incidence of AEs.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Safety will be assessed by the incidence of AEs throughout the study period as documented by clinician observations at study visits and in a 30-day subject diary.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of Edema</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day, 1 week, 4 weeks and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Edema will be determined by a live assessment at 1 day, 1 week, 4 weeks and 6 months following surgery using a four-point categorical edema scale [none, mild, moderate, severe)].</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blinded-assessment of satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months post surgery</time_frame>
    <description>A non-treating blinded evaluator will assess satisfaction with a four-point categorical satisfaction scale [unsatisfied, satisfied, very satisfied, highly satisfied)] of subject's grafts using photographs from baseline, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, and 12 months and will consist of a blinded evaluation in which the physician is aware of the type of graft, but unaware of plating status or the specific grafting site.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Ecchymosis Evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day, 1 week, 4 weeks and 6 months following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>The surface area and color of ecchymosis will be evaluated using Mirror Software and Vectra 3D photography at 1 day, 1 week, 4 weeks and 6 months following surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective Ecchymosis Evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day, 1 week, 4 weeks and 6 months following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Ecchymosis will be determined by a live assessment at 1 day, 1 week, 4 weeks and 6 months following surgery using a six-point categorical edema scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 30</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will complete a 30-day diary documenting adverse events such as erythema, pain, tenderness, firmness, swelling, lumps/bumps, bruising, itching and numbness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subject Downtime Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day, 1 week, 4 weeks and 6 months following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Subject downtime will be determined using a questionnaire at 1 day, 1 week, 4 weeks and 6 months following surgery. Responders are defined as those subjects experiencing little to no downtime.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HPSS Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week, 4 weeks and 6 months following surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in subject self-esteem will be determined by subject completion of the Heatherton &amp; Polivy State Self-Esteem (HPSS) Scale at 1 week, 4 weeks and 6 months following surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ease of Use</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately Post Surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Ease of use will be determined by the treating investigator using a 10 cm Visual Analog Scale (VAS) to demonstrate technical ease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Rhinoplasty</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ARTISS Human Fibrin Sealant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Prior to fixation of the external rhinoplasty skin flap, a thin layer of ARTISS human fibrin sealant will be applied over the nasal tissue and fixated to the skin flap for at least 3 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fixation of the skin flap created during external rhinoplasty will use the standard of care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ARTISS human fibrin sealant</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>ARTISS Human Fibrin Sealant</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Males and females between 18 and 65 years of age.

          2. Subjects requesting primary rhinoplasty and requiring an external approach.

          3. Subjects willing to undergo treatment with fibrin sealant.

          4. Willingness and ability to comply with protocol requirements, including returning for
             follow-up visits and abstaining from exclusionary procedures for the duration of the
             study.

          5. Willingness and ability to comply with the PI's standard preoperative and
             postoperative rhinoplasty instructions.

          6. Subjects of childbearing potential must have a negative urine pregnancy test result at
             Visit 1 and be willing able to use an acceptable method of birth control (e.g.,
             barrier methods used with a spermicidal agent, hormonal methods, IUD, surgical
             sterilization, abstinence) during the study. Women will not be considered of
             childbearing potential if one of the following is documented on the medical history:

               -  postmenopausal for at least 12 months prior to study drug administration

               -  without a uterus and/or both ovaries

               -  has had a bilateral tubal ligation for at least 6 months prior to study drug
                  administration.

               -  absence of an other physical condition according to the PI's discretion

          7. Willingness and ability to provide written photo consent and adherence to photography
             procedures (i.e., removal of jewelry and makeup).

          8. Willingness and ability to provide written informed consent prior to performance of
             any study related procedure.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects who are pregnant, nursing, planning to become pregnant, and/or not using a
             reliable form of birth control.

          2. Subjects who are planning a concurrent facial surgery during the operation (eg
             forehead plasty, blepharoplasty, rhinoplasty, buccal fat removal, any filler
             injections including fat injections, lip augmentation, skin resurfacing procedures
             etc.).

          3. Subjects with a previous history of rhinoplasty.

          4. Subjects with a current history of smoking.

          5. Subjects with a previous history of a bleeding or coagulation disorder .

          6. Subject with a previous history of a vascular disorder, cardiovascular disease, and/or
             uncontrolled hypertension.

          7. Subjects a previous history of diabetes mellitus with glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c)
             &gt; 7.

          8. Subjects undergoing active treatment for a malignancy.

          9. Subjects with a previous history of has a connective tissue disorder.

         10. Subjects with active or chronic skin disorder.

         11. Subjects with a previous history of Bell's palsy.

         12. Subjects with a previous history of pathologically or pharmacologically induced immune
             deficiency.

         13. Subjects who have received chronic treatment with immunosuppressive drugs, systemic
             corticosteroids, or other chronic treatments within 30 days prior to the surgery.

         14. Subjects with a known sensitivity to components of FS VH S/D 4 s-apr.

         15. Subjects with a previous history of healing complications following previous surgeries
             (eg, hypertrophic scarring).

         16. Subjects with a significant systemic illness or illness localized to the areas of
             treatment.

         17. Subjects with previous history of nasal implants.

         18. Subjects with previous or current history of nasal infections.

         19. Subjects who have history of blood thinners (aspirin, ibuprofen, naprosyn, herbal
             supplements, Vitamin E) within the two weeks prior to surgery.

         20. Subjects who have smoked within the two weeks prior to surgery.

         21. Subjects who have had alcohol or illicit drugs one week prior to surgery.

         22. Subjects who have eaten or drank anything after midnight the night prior to surgery.

         23. Subjects with current history of chronic drug or alcohol abuse.

         24. Concurrent therapy that, in the investigator's opinion, would interfere with the
             evaluation of the safety or efficacy of the study medication.

         25. Subjects who anticipate the need for surgery, other than the study procedure, or
             overnight hospitalization during the study.

         26. Subjects who, in the Investigator's opinion, have a history of poor cooperation, non
             compliance with medical treatment or unreliability.

         27. Subject has participated in another clinical study involving an investigational
             product/device within 30 days prior to enrollment or is scheduled to participate in
             another clinical study involving an investigational product/device during the course
             of this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven H Dayan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>DeNova Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Katherine Cho, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>312.335.2070</phone>
    <email>katherine@denovaresearch.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Selika Gutierrez- Borst, MS, RN</last_name>
    <phone>312.335.2070</phone>
    <email>selika@denovaresearch.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>DeNova Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Katherine Cho, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>312-335-2070</phone>
      <email>katherine@denovaresearch.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven H Dayan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.denovaresearch.com</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 7, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 10, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 12, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 12, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 12, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 15, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>DeNova Research</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Steven H. Dayan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>rhinoplasty</keyword>
  <keyword>external rhinoplasty</keyword>
  <keyword>open rhinoplasty</keyword>
  <keyword>nose job</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibrin Tissue Adhesive</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

