<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01515930</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>3M's Diabetes Study</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R21DK089238</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01515930</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Computerized Intervention of Parental Involvement in Diabetes Care of Their Child</brief_title>
  <official_title>Computer-Delivered Motivational Intervention to Improve Teen Diabetes Management</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wayne State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wayne State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to develop an intervention to increase parental motivation for
      supervision and monitoring youth diabetes care behavior. The intervention will be tested in
      three brief session in conjunction with regularly scheduled diabetes clinic visits and
      delivered through a computer program based in the principles of Motivational Interviewing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study includes a development phase (Phase 1: development of the intervention followed by
      feasibility testing with 10 youth and 10 parents) and a pilot validation phase [Phase 2:
      pilot randomized clinical trial (RCT)] using a sample of 90 African American youth
      transitioning to independent diabetes care and their parents. In this phase, families will be
      randomly assigned to one of three study arms: parent motivation for monitoring and youth
      motivation for diabetes care (arm 1), parent motivation for monitoring and youth information
      (arm 2) or parent and youth information (arm 3). In phase 1 (development), youth and their
      caregivers will complete a one-time research visit where they use the program and provide
      feedback via a semi-structured interview regarding the usefulness of the content, its
      user-friendliness and make suggestions for changes to enhance acceptability. In phase 2 (
      RCT), families will complete three intervention plus data collection visits and one
      additional data collection only visit. Research visits will be scheduled to coincide with
      appointments in the diabetes clinic to maximize convenience for families.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 9, 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 3, 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diabetes Management Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Each of 3 intervention session, 3-4 month apart</time_frame>
    <description>The Diabetes Management Scale (DMS) (Frey, Ellis, Naar-King et al., 2004) is a self-report questionnaire used to measure a broad range of diabetes management behaviors, such as insulin management, dietary management, blood glucose monitoring, symptom response, and parent assistance/supervision.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Regulation Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Each of 3 intervention session, 3-4 month apart</time_frame>
    <description>Parental motivation to monitor the youth is measured by the Treatment Self-Regulation Questionnaire (TSRQ; Ryan &amp; Connell (1989). The TSRQ evaluates why people engage in a health-relevant behavior and assesses the degree to which one's motivation for a particular behavior or set of behaviors is relatively autonomous or self-determined as compared to derived from external pressures or constraints.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Readiness Ruler</measure>
    <time_frame>Each of 3 intervention session, 3-4 month apart</time_frame>
    <description>Parent motivation to monitor the youth is also measured by the Readiness Ruler (Stott, Rollnick, &amp; Pill, 1995). Since readiness to change behaviors is behavior specific, the items will be tailored to assess the behaviors most critical to parental monitoring of diabetes management. The response format is a visual analog scale (VAS) 10 mm in length. Written cues anchor the ends and middle of the scale. Respondents mark their &quot;readiness&quot; on the scale and the position on the line is measured in millimeters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HbA1C Blood Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Each of 3 intervention session, 3-4 month apart</time_frame>
    <description>Metabolic control will be measured via hemoglobin A1c (HbA1c). HbA1c is an indirect and retrospective measure of average blood glucose levels over the previous two to three month period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parental Monitoring of Diabetes Care</measure>
    <time_frame>Each of 3 intervention session, 3-4 month apart</time_frame>
    <description>The Parental Monitoring of Diabetes Care scale (PMDC) is an 18 item, investigator-developed questionnaire that measures the frequency of parental monitoring and direct supervision of diabetes care tasks such as insulin administration, blood glucose testing, and dietary management.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Twenty-four Hour Recall Interview</measure>
    <time_frame>Each of 3 intervention session, 3-4 month apart</time_frame>
    <description>The Twenty-four Hour Recall Interview, developed by Johnson and colleagues (Freund, Johnson, Silverstein et al., 1991), has been used extensively in pediatric diabetes research for the assessment of illness management.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood Glucose Testing Frequency</measure>
    <time_frame>Each of 3 intervention session, 3-4 month apart</time_frame>
    <description>Objective data on mean daily frequency of blood glucose testing during the 14-day period prior to data collection will be obtained directly from blood glucose meters.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">145</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active Caregiver and Active Child</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parent &amp; Child Computer-Delivered Motivational Intervention will be delivered to participants. A brief computer delivered behavior change counseling intervention for parents of children with diabetes to improve monitoring of diabetes care and a brief computer delivered behavior change counseling intervention for children with diabetes to improve completion of daily diabetes care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active Caregiver and Child Education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Parent Computer-Delivered Motivational Intervention will be delivered to the parents only. A brief computer delivered behavior change counseling intervention for parents of children with diabetes to improve monitoring of diabetes care and a brief computer delivered informational session about diabetes related topics for their child with diabetes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Education Caregiver/Education Child</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive computer-delivered information. A brief computer delivered information session about diabetes related topics for both the caregiver and the child with diabetes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Parent Computer-Delivered Motivational Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Motivational Interviewing (MI) is a client-centered, directive method for enhancing intrinsic motivation to change by exploring &amp; resolving ambivalence, with a strong evidence for improving adolescent &amp; adult health behaviors. Three motivational sessions will be provided by an animated character who delivers the intervention with high fidelity to MI principles. Small amounts of psychoeducation about potential improvements illness management that can result from parental monitoring of diabetes care will be integrated with more purely motivational elements. Mailings will be sent to participants to remind them of the reasons they gave as motivation &amp; goals they set regarding monitoring diabetes care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active Caregiver and Child Education</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Parent &amp; Child Computer-Delivered Motivational Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Motivational Interviewing (MI) is a client-centered, directive method for enhancing intrinsic motivation to change by exploring &amp; resolving ambivalence, with a strong evidence for improving adolescent &amp; adult health behaviors. Three motivational sessions will be provided by an animated character who delivers the intervention with high fidelity to MI principles. Small amounts of psychoeducation about potential improvements illness management that can result from monitoring/completing diabetes care will be integrated with more purely motivational elements. Mailings will be sent to participants to remind them of the reasons they gave as motivation &amp; goals they set regarding diabetes care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active Caregiver and Active Child</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Computer-Delivered Information</intervention_name>
    <description>Computer-Delivered Information about issues related to living with diabetes that do not directly impact completing diabetes care.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Education Caregiver/Education Child</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  African American race/ethnicity

          -  Age: 10 years 0 months - 12 years, 11 months

          -  Type 1 diabetes mellitus

          -  Diagnosed at least 6 months

          -  Patient of Children's Hospital of Michigan Diabetes Clinics

          -  English fluency, both verbal and written

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Psychiatry/psychological diagnoses including cognitive impairment that would prevent
             the participant from understanding the data collection measures, (i.e. moderate or
             severe mental retardation) or the following psychiatric diagnoses: autism and
             schizophrenia. Youth with current suicidal intent are not enrolled until
             psychiatrically stable.

          -  Medical diagnoses that would result in atypical diabetes management i.e. cystic
             fibrosis. Other medical conditions that would not affect diabetes management, such as
             asthma, do not exclude the participant from study participation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>13 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Deborah A Ellis, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wayne State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wayne State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Detroit</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 24, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Wayne State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Deborah Ellis, Ph.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Parenting</keyword>
  <keyword>Parental Monitoring</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

