<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01515137</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>05-045</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01515137</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of TARCEVA (Erlotinib) as Adjuvant Treatment for Locally Advanced Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of TARCEVA (Erlotinib) as Adjuvant Treatment for Locally Advanced Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma With Evaluation of Neoadjuvant Biomarker Modulation With TARCEVA vs. TARCEVA Plus Sulindac</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>OSI Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This trial was originally designed and powered to compare biomarker modulation in the
      neo-adjuvant setting (erlotinib versus erlotinib plus sulindac versus placebo) with clinical
      response to erlotinib in the adjuvant setting. Since implementing the trial in late 2005, The
      investigators have encountered significant obstacles to implementing the adjuvant therapy
      phase of the trial.

        -  Barriers included:

             1. disease recurrence

             2. patient refusal to take the agent

             3. patient refusal to travel to Pittsburgh for clinical evaluations.

      Given the institutional challenges to implement and complete the adjuvant portion, the
      investigators have decided to change the primary endpoint to a biomarker modulation endpoint.
      To achieve this goal, the investigators determined that they needed 39 paired tissue
      specimens (see statistical justification below).

      The central hypothesis to be tested in this study is that persistent activation of parallel
      and/or downstream pathways contributes to tumor progression in the setting of EGFR blockade.
      While not all head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC) patients will respond to EGFR
      targeting, the optimal strategy to identify those subjects whose tumors are sensitive to EGFR
      inhibition remains unknown.

      The primary objective is centered around the concept of tumor biomarkers which may be
      modulated by EGFR and Cox-2 inhibitors and may serve as future therapeutic targets for
      therapy. To this end patients on this trial will be randomly assigned to one of three arms to
      receive either Tarceva, Tarceva plus sulindac, or a placebo in the 2 week pre-operative
      period. A panel of biomarkers will be obtained by biopsy prior to pre-operative therapy and
      again at surgery. Biomarkers will be examined for modulation in the 2-week pre-operative
      period, for group differences, for treatment effects and for further understanding of protein
      signaling pathways.

      Sample size for the primary objective

      Modification of Statistical Design:

      The primary endpoint is the difference between pre (biopsy) and post (surgery). There are 3
      hypotheses of interest: (1) placebo vs erlotinib alone, (2) placebo versus erlotinib plus
      sulindac, and (3) erlotinib vs erlotinib + sulindac. With a randomization in a 3:5:5 ratio,
      we have 88% power, alpha = .01 for an omnibus test to show between-group differences of 1 log
      exist. This requires 39 patients. Basically, 39 patients will provide the ability to detect a
      one log difference between any 2 of the 3 groups in pre-post change.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSCC) constitutes 3 percent of all malignancies and
      is the sixth most common malignancy worldwide. There will be an estimated 38,000 new cases
      and 11,000 deaths in the United States in 2004 and approximately 500,000 cases worldwide
      yearly [1]. Squamous cell carcinoma accounts for at least 95 percent of all head and neck
      cancers. Surgical treatment remains the standard of therapy for patients with resectable
      HNSCC. For patients with high risk of local or distant relapse, radiation therapy (RT) alone,
      or in combination with chemotherapy, is given after surgery to improve loco-regional control
      and overall survival.

      Neoadjuvant chemotherapy for patients with respectable HNSCC remains an experimental option
      for these patients. A two-week delay in definitive surgical resection in patients with
      operable HNSCC is not thought to impact the clinical outcome of these patients and in many
      cases may be needed to complete all of the preoperative work-up. As a result, a study design
      involving a two-week preoperative course of therapy in patients with operable HNSCC should
      not be a concern.

      EGFR as a therapeutic target in HNSCC

      Epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) is a 170-Kda transmembrane protein that is thought to
      be important in the proliferation and survival of cancer cells [2]. Overexpression of EGFR
      has been found in several malignancies, including head and neck, lung, breast, prostate,
      bladder, and pancreatic cancer [3-7]. In HNSCC, EGFR and its ligand TGF are overexpressed in
      80-90% of tumors compared to normal mucosa; [8] the coexpression of receptor and ligand
      implicates an autocrine regulatory pathway in HNSCC carcinogenesis. The clinical relevance of
      EGFR overexpression as an independent prognostic factor in HNSCC has been well demonstrated.
      High tumor EGFR levels are correlated with advanced stage,[9] increased tumor size, [9]
      decreased survival,[10-13] increased recurrence,[10] and decreased sensitivity to radiation
      treatment [14]. A recent study suggests that high serum EGFR levels may even correlate with
      higher head and neck tumor grade [15]. The overexpression of EGFR and ligand in partially and
      fully transformed HNSCC tissue, its correlation with poor clinical outcome, and the aberrant
      function of the EGFR network in HNSCC provide compelling evidence of a relationship between
      EGFR and the development and progression of HNSCC, and suggest a role for EGFR as a target
      for cancer therapy.

      EGFR has been targeted at the extracellular domain by blocking ligand binding, at the
      intracellular domain by inhibiting tyrosine kinase activity, and at the genetic level by
      targeting production of the receptor itself. EGFR-specific monoclonal antibodies interfere
      with ligand binding, while conjugation of an EGFR ligand or antibody to a bacterially derived
      toxin enables the delivery of a cytotoxic agent to the cell surface. Many of the
      EGFR-targeting agents are undergoing clinical evaluation in HNSCC. In general, clinical
      responses in HNSCC patients with advanced disease have only been observed when these agents
      have been combined with cytotoxic chemotherapy or radiation therapy. Clinical trials using
      EGFR inhibitors as adjuvant therapy for HNSCC are currently underway.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Phase II Study of TARCEVA (Erlotinib) as Adjuvant Treatment for Locally Advanced Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma with Evaluation of Neoadjuvant Biomarker Modulation with TARCEVA vs. TARCEVA Plus Sulindac</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>Primary objective centered around concept of tumor biomarkers which may be modulated by EGFR &amp; Cox-2 inhibitors &amp; may serve as future therapeutic targets for therapy. Patients on this trial to be randomly assigned to 1 of 3 arms in the 2 week pre-operative period. A panel of biomarkers will be obtained by biopsy prior to pre-operative therapy and again at surgery. Biomarkers will be examined for modulation in the 2-week pre-operative period, for group differences, for treatment effects and for further understanding of protein signaling pathways.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">47</enrollment>
  <condition>Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A erlotinib plus sulindac</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>erlotinib (150 mg PO QD) plus sulindac (150 mg PO BID) (Arm A),</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B erlotinib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>erlotinib (150 mg PO QD) (Arm B)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>placebo (for Erlotinib) QD (Arm C).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Erlotinib</intervention_name>
    <description>Erlotinib (150 mg PO QD) plus sulindac (150 mg PO BID) (Arm A), Erlotinib (150 mg PO QD) (Arm B) or placebo (for Erlotinib) QD (Arm C).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B erlotinib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tarceva</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Erlotinib plus sulindac</intervention_name>
    <description>Erlotinib (150 mg PO QD) plus sulindac (150 mg PO BID) (Arm A), Erlotinib (150 mg PO QD) (Arm B) or placebo (for Erlotinib) QD (Arm C).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A erlotinib plus sulindac</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tarceva</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Erlotinib (150 mg PO QD) plus sulindac (150 mg PO BID) (Arm A), Erlotinib (150 mg PO QD) (Arm B) or placebo (for Erlotinib) QD (Arm C).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm C</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tarceva</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed, previously untreated HNSCC.

          -  Clinical stage II, III or IVA disease without distant metastasis, as defined by the
             American Joint Committee on Cancer Staging System, Sixth edition (See Appendix I).

          -  Primary tumors of the oral cavity, oropharynx, hypopharynx, or larynx will be
             included. Primary tumors of the sinuses, paranasal sinuses, or nasopharynx, or unknown
             primary tumors are NOT allowed.

          -  Macroscopic complete resection of the primary tumor must be planned.

          -  Patients will be willing to receive postoperative therapy with platinum and radiation
             if qualified based on criteria listed in treatment plan.

          -  Age 18 years.

          -  ECOG performance status 0-1 (See Appendix II).

          -  Adequate hematologic, renal and hepatic function, as defined by:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) greater than 1,500/ul, platelets greater than
                  100,000/ul.

               -  Creatinine less than 1.5 x institutional upper limit of normal (ULN).

               -  Bilirubin less than 1.5 x ULN, AST or ALT 2.5 x ULN.

          -  Have signed written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects who fail to meet the above criteria.

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding. Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must practice
             acceptable methods of birth control to prevent pregnancy.

          -  Subjects with a ECOG performance status of 2 or worse.

          -  Evidence of distant metastasis.

          -  Any other malignancy active within 5 years except for non-melanoma skin cancer or
             carcinoma in situ of the cervix, DCIS or LCIS of the breast.

          -  Prior history of HNSCC.

          -  Prior therapy targeting the EGFR pathway.

          -  Known severe hypersensitivity to sulindac or other non-steroidal anti-inflammatory
             drugs (NSAIDs), including aspirin.

          -  Any unresolved chronic toxicity greater than grade 2 from previous anticancer therapy
             (except alopecia), according to Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events v3.0
             (CTCAE).

          -  Incomplete healing from previous major surgery.

          -  Acute hepatitis, known HIV, or active uncontrolled infection.

          -  History of uncontrolled cardiac disease; i.e., uncontrolled hypertension, unstable
             angina, myocardial infarction within prior 6 months, untreated known coronary artery
             disease, uncontrolled congestive heart failure, and cardiomyopathy with decreased
             ejection fraction.

          -  Any preexisting active interstitial lung disease (patients with chronic stable
             radiographic changes who are asymptomatic are NOT excluded).

          -  Treatment with anticoagulants, except when used to maintain the patency of a central
             venous line.

          -  Uncontrolled peptic or gastric ulcer disease, or gastrointestinal bleeding within
             prior 6 months.

          -  Active alcohol abuse or other illness that carries a likelihood of inability to comply
             with study treatment and follow-up.

          -  Treatment with a non-approved or investigational drug within 30 days prior to Day 1 of
             study treatment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer Grandis, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 12, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 20, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 23, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 28, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 28, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 29, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Head and Neck</keyword>
  <keyword>Locally Advanced Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Erlotinib Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sulindac</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

