<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00690846</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>00002156</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>32410</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00690846</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Determine the Safety and Efficacy of Adalimumab in the Treatment of Pyoderma Gangrenosum</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multi-Center, Open Label Pilot Study to Determine the Safety and Efficacy of Adalimumab in the Treatment of Pyoderma Gangrenosum (HUM 04-37)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to see if Humira (adalimumab) is effective and safe in
      the treatment of pyoderma gangrenosum.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to obtain preliminary data on the safety and efficacy
      of adalimumab for the treatment of PG. A secondary objective is to study gene expression in
      PG.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Dr. Jorizzo has decided to withdraw from this study due to the time it is taking to get the
    study started.
  </why_stopped>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean change in the number of ulcers.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Pyoderma Gangrenosum</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>40 mg weekly subcutaneous injection of adalimumab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>adalimumab</intervention_name>
    <description>40 mg weekly adalimumab injection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Humira</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is willing and able to give informed consent.

          -  Subject is willing and able to participate in the study as an outpatient and is
             willing to comply with study requirements.

          -  Subject is 18 years of age or older.

          -  Subject has a diagnosis of pyoderma gangrenosum that involves total area of 3 cm2 or
             greater and is of sufficient severity to warrant systemic agents.

          -  If female of childbearing potential, subject will have a negative urine pregnancy test
             at Screening and Week 0.

          -  If female, subject will be either post-menopausal for &gt; 1 year, surgically sterile
             (hysterectomy or bilateral tubal ligation), or practicing one form of birth control
             (abstinence, oral contraceptive, estrogen patch, implant contraception, injectable
             contraception, IUD, diaphragm, condom, sponge, spermicides, or vasectomy of partner).
             Female subjects will continue to use contraception for 6 months following the last
             injection.

          -  Screening laboratory results are within the following parameters:

          -  Subject has been on a stable dose of antibiotics, oral corticosteroids or other
             immunosuppressives, such cyclosporine, tacrolimus, azathioprine, methotrexate, or
             mycophenolate mofetil over the previous 4 weeks

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has evidence of a clinically significant, unstable or poorly controlled
             medical condition.

          -  Subject has a chest X-ray consistent with an active infection or previous exposure to
             TB and/or a positive purified protein derivative test at screening (&gt;5 mm). (Subjects
             may participate if they are being actively treated in accordance with CDC guidelines.)

          -  Subject has a serious, active or recurrent bacterial, viral, or fungal infection. This
             includes hepatitis B and C, and HIV.

          -  Subject has been hospitalized for infection or received IV antibiotics within the
             previous 2 months prior to baseline.

          -  Subject has clinical evidence as determined by the investigator of acutely infected
             pyoderma gangrenosum or subject is receiving systemic antibiotics for the treatment of
             acute infection. Subjects receiving minocycline, tetracycline, dapsone, or other
             antibiotics for anti-inflammatory purposes are permitted.

          -  Subject has a history of tuberculosis without documented adequate therapy.

          -  Subject has a history of a central nervous system disorder/demyelinating disease or
             symptoms suggestive of multiple sclerosis or optic neuritis.

          -  Subject has current signs or symptoms or history of systemic lupus erythematosus.

          -  Subject has been diagnosed with a malignancy within the past 5 years except for
             successfully treated non-melanoma skin cancer.

          -  Subject has signs or symptoms suggestive of a possible lymphoproliferative disease.

          -  Subject has a diagnosis of severe congestive heart failure (Class III or IV NYHA).

          -  Subject has had a substance abuse problem within the previous 3 years.

          -  Subject has been treated with an anti-TNF biologic immune response modifier, such as
             infliximab, adalimumab, or etanercept within the past 8 weeks.

          -  Subject has any dermatologic disease in the target site that may be exacerbated by
             treatment or interfere with examination.

          -  Subject has been administered an investigational drug in another clinical study within
             30 days prior to baseline (or 5 half-lives, whichever is longer).

          -  Subject has a known allergy to adalimumab.

          -  Subject is female and is pregnant, is considering becoming pregnant during the study
             and for 6 months afterwards, or is nursing.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph Jorizzo, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wake Forest University Health Sciences Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27157</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 2, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 4, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 5, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 14, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 14, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 15, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Joseph Jorizzo, MD</name_title>
    <organization>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pyoderma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pyoderma Gangrenosum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adalimumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

