<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00693940</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>586</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01HL088589-01</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>HL088589-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00693940</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of Group Walking Sessions for Increasing Activity in People With Peripheral Arterial Disease (The Group Oriented Arterial Leg Study [GOALS])</brief_title>
  <official_title>Increasing Activity in Peripheral Arterial Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Lower extremity peripheral arterial disease (PAD) is a disease in which fatty build-up, or
      plaque, accumulates in the arteries of the legs. People with lower extremity PAD often
      experience leg pain while walking, which is caused by reduced blood flow to the legs. Regular
      walking has significant benefits for people with blood flow problems in their legs, but
      previous studies have shown that most men and women with PAD do not walk for exercise on a
      regular basis. A group home-based walking program may help people with PAD to walk more often
      and improve their lower extremity functioning. This study will evaluate the effectiveness of
      a home-based group mediated cognitive behavioral (GMCB) exercise program in helping people
      with lower extremity PAD to increase their walking frequency and improve their lower leg
      functioning.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lower extremity PAD affects between 10% and 15% of people over the age of 65. A person's risk
      for PAD increases with age but can also be raised by smoking or having diabetes, high blood
      pressure, high cholesterol, or heart disease. PAD symptoms may include leg pain, foot or toe
      wounds, and a noticeably lower temperature in the lower legs than in the rest of the body.
      The specific functional impairments caused by PAD symptoms are associated with increased
      risks of disability, nursing home placement, mobility loss, hospitalization, and mortality.
      Supervised exercise rehabilitation programs have been shown to improve walking ability in
      people with PAD. However, few people with PAD have access to supervised exercise
      rehabilitation programs because of costs and difficulty traveling to the exercise facility.
      Home-based exercise programs may be more beneficial than supervised programs in improving
      lower extremity functioning in people with PAD, but more information is needed to support the
      effectiveness of at-home rehabilitation. This study will compare the effectiveness of a
      home-based GMCB exercise program versus general health education sessions in helping people
      with lower extremity PAD to increase their walking frequency and improve their lower leg
      functioning.

      Participation in this study will last 12 months. The primary outcome will be measured at 6
      month follow-up. All participants will undergo a baseline 6-minute walk test on a treadmill
      and an electrocardiogram (ECG). They will also provide information on their physical activity
      levels. Participants will then be assigned randomly to receive GMCB sessions or health
      education sessions. Both groups will attend weekly sessions of their assigned treatment for a
      6 month period. During the GMCB sessions, participants will be asked to exercise by walking
      around a track. There will also be a group discussion, led by a facilitator, who will help
      participants find ways to increase the frequency of their walking exercise at home. Each GMCB
      session will last approximately 60 to 75 minutes. Health education sessions will last 60
      minutes and will cover health-related topics.

      After completing approximately 6 months of treatment, participants in both groups will be
      telephoned regularly by a study coordinator: they will receive telephone calls every other
      week during Months 6 to 9 of follow-up and monthly during Months 9 to 12 of follow-up.
      Participants will be asked to return for follow-up testing at Month 6 and Month 12; outcomes
      measured at Month 6 are highest priority.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>6-minute walk test at 6 month follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline and Month 6 follow-up</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treadmill walking performance</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline and Month 6 follow-up</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-related quality of life measures</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline, Month 6, and Month 12 follow-up</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical activity levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline, Month 6, and Month 12 follow-up</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6-minute walk test at Month 12 follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at Month 12 follow-up</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">194</enrollment>
  <condition>Peripheral Vascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive treatment with group mediated cognitive behavioral sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive treatment with health education sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Group mediated cognitive behavioral (GMCB) sessions</intervention_name>
    <description>GMCB will include weekly group exercise sessions, lasting approximately 60 to 75 minutes each for a 6 month period. During these sessions, participants will be asked to exercise by walking around a track. There will also be a group discussion, led by a facilitator, who will help participants find ways to increase the frequency of their walking exercise at home. After completing the GMCB sessions, which will last about 6 months, participants will be telephoned regularly by a study coordinator for another 6 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health education sessions</intervention_name>
    <description>Health education will include weekly educational sessions on a health-related topic, lasting approximately 60 minutes each. After completing the health education sessions, which will last about 6 months, participants will be telephoned regularly by a study coordinator for another 6 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Have PAD

          -  Potential participants with a resting ABI greater than or equal to 0.91 and less than
             or equal to 1.00 at their baseline visit will be eligible if their ABI drops by at
             least 20% after the heel-rise test. Potential participants with a resting baseline ABI
             greater than 0.91 who do not meet criteria for inclusion based on the heel-rise test
             can be eligible if they have data from a certified non-invasive vascular laboratory
             that demonstrates presence of lower extremity ischemia. However, more evidence than an
             abnormal PVR from the non-invasive vascular laboratory is required (for example, a toe
             brachial index pressure less than 0.60). Finally, potential participants who do not
             meet the above criteria for inclusion will be eligible if they have an angiogram
             demonstrating greater than 50% stenosis on one or more lower extremity arterial
             vessels.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Below or above knee amputation

          -  Wheelchair confinement

          -  Uses a walking aid other than a cane (e.g., walker)

          -  Unable to return to the medical center at the required visit frequency

          -  Greater than Class II New York Heart Association heart failure or angina (symptoms at
             rest or with minimal exertion)

          -  Any increase in angina pectoris symptoms during the 6 months before study entry or
             angina at rest

          -  Presence of a foot ulcer

          -  Lower extremity revascularization or major orthopedic surgery during the 3 months
             before study entry

          -  Heart attack or coronary artery bypass grafting during the 3 months before study entry

          -  Major medical illnesses, including treatment for cancer (except non-melanoma skin
             cancer) during the 12 months before study entry

          -  Planned lower extremity revascularization within the 12 months after study entry

          -  Current participation in another clinical trial

          -  Walking for exercise at a level comparable to that targeted in the study's
             intervention

          -  Completion of a cardiac rehabilitation program within 3 months before study entry

          -  Coronary ischemia during exercise, defined as ST segment depression greater than 1 mm
             during the baseline exercise treadmill test, with or without associated chest
             discomfort

          -  Left-bundle branch block or significant ST-T wave changes on the baseline ECG without
             a perfusion stress test, demonstrating no reversible ischemia within the 3 months
             before study entry

          -  Stopping during the treadmill exercise stress test because of chest pain, shortness of
             breath, hip or knee arthritis. These individuals will be interviewed by the principal
             investigator and will be excluded only if it is determined that their walking
             performance (based in part on the treadmill test) is limited by a comorbidity other
             than leg ischemia.

          -  Unable to walk at least 50 feet without stopping during the 6-minute walk test

          -  Stopping during the 6-minute walk test for symptoms other than ischemic leg symptoms

          -  Mini-Mental Status Examination (MMSE) score of less than 23 or psychiatric illness

          -  Failure to complete a study run-in period

          -  Parkinson's disease

          -  Requires oxygen with exertion.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mary M. McDermott, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 5, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 9, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 27, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 27, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 29, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwestern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mary McDermott</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine and Preventive Medicine at Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Peripheral Arterial Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>PAD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Arterial Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

