<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00693121</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MethodistRC Project 1</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NIDRR grant #: H133A020514</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00693121</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Amantadine for Treatment of Symptoms of the Post-Traumatic Confusional State</brief_title>
  <official_title>Amantadine Hydrochloride for Treatment of Symptoms of the Post-Traumatic Confusional State Among Neurorehabilitation Admissions With TBI: A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Methodist Rehabilitation Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>U.S. Department of Education</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Methodist Rehabilitation Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with traumatic brain injury often experience a period of acute confusion that may
      include agitation as they recover from their injuries. While this confusion generally
      resolves with time, patients may pose increased risk of injury to themselves or others during
      this period. Their behavior may also increase stress for family members and interfere with
      their ability to benefit from rehabilitation therapies. A number of different medications
      have been used to treat confusion to decrease agitation, decrease risk of injury, and improve
      participation in rehabilitation therapies. To this point, there has not been a research or
      scientific basis for knowing which medication is the best for a specific patient. The overall
      goal of this study is to conduct a scientific investigation to help determine which
      medication works best to treat confusion.

      Study hypothesis: Amantadine will reduce the severity and number of symptoms of acute
      confusion after traumatic brain injury.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with TBI who require inpatient rehabilitation are frequently confused at the time of
      admission for rehabilitation. Our investigations of confusion conducted as part of the TBIMSM
      have clarified the nature of confusion in early recovery after TBI. Early confusion (PTCS)
      has been found to be a complex syndrome characterized by disorientation, cognitive
      impairment, restlessness, decreased level of daytime arousal, sleep disturbance, fluctuation
      of symptoms, and psychotic-type symptoms. PTCS complicates early management of patients with
      TBI, and may contribute to increased risk of injury to patients and hospital staff, increased
      stress among family members and staff, decreased participation in therapies, increased cost
      of care, and an increased likelihood of being discharged to psychiatric or long-term care
      settings. These facts indicate the need for effective management of PTCS. Consensus regarding
      optimal treatment of the cognitive and behavioral symptoms encountered among patients with
      PTCS does not exist currently. While many agents have been tried to address such symptoms in
      TBI, few have been investigated systematically. These circumstances indicate the need for
      appropriate clinical trials to provide guidance to clinicians for medical treatment of PTCS.
      In response, the NIDRR-Traumatic Brain Injury Model System of Mississippi proposed a
      randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled, parallel group trial for the pharmacological
      treatment of PTCS. The agent selected for this clinical trial is amantadine, an NMDA and
      indirect dopamine agonist. This agent will be compared to placebo on response measures of
      efficacy and safety.

      Study hypothesis: Amantadine will reduce the severity and number of symptoms of PTCS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Confusion Assessment Protocol (number of symptoms)</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>number of participants withdrawn from study due to fulfillment of &quot;escape criteria&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>14 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to reach &quot;non-confused&quot; Confusion Assessment Protocol score</measure>
    <time_frame>&lt;14 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">79</enrollment>
  <condition>Traumatic Brain Injury</condition>
  <condition>Posttraumatic Confusional State</condition>
  <condition>Delirium</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Identical capsule to amantadine hydrochloride active intervention, administered twice daily x 14 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Amantadine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Amantadine hydrochloride 100mg capsule administered twice daily x 14 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Amantadine hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>100mg administered orally twice daily x 14 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Amantadine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>capsule, identical to amantadine hydrochloride capsule, administered twice daily x 14 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute Traumatic Brain Injury (≤90 days postinjury)

          -  Responsive (not fulfilling criteria for Minimally Conscious State)

          -  Meet PTCS criteria on 2 consecutive examinations (as determined by the Confusion
             Assessment Protocol)

          -  Initial neurorehabilitation hospital admission

          -  Anticipated ≥2 week length-of-stay after meeting PTCS criteria

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Preexisting seizure disorder

          -  Prior history of hospitalization for psychiatric condition
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stuart A Yablon, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brain Injury Program, Methodist Rehabilitation Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Sherer, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Research, Memorial Hermann/TIRR, Houston, TX</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Risa N Richardson, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Polytrauma Program, James A. Haley Veterans Hospital, Tampa, FL</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Methodist Rehabilitation Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jackson</city>
        <state>Mississippi</state>
        <zip>39216</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sherer M, Yablon SA, Nakase-Richardson R, Nick TG. Effect of severity of post-traumatic confusion and its constituent symptoms on outcome after traumatic brain injury. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2008 Jan;89(1):42-7. doi: 10.1016/j.apmr.2007.08.128.</citation>
    <PMID>18164329</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nakase-Richardson R, Yablon SA, Sherer M. Prospective comparison of acute confusion severity with duration of post-traumatic amnesia in predicting employment outcome after traumatic brain injury. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2007 Aug;78(8):872-6. Epub 2006 Dec 18.</citation>
    <PMID>17178822</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sherer M, Nakase-Thompson R, Yablon SA, Gontkovsky ST. Multidimensional assessment of acute confusion after traumatic brain injury. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 2005 May;86(5):896-904.</citation>
    <PMID>15895334</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nakase-Thompson R, Sherer M, Yablon SA, Nick TG, Trzepacz PT. Acute confusion following traumatic brain injury. Brain Inj. 2004 Feb;18(2):131-42.</citation>
    <PMID>14660226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 4, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 6, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 5, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 5, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 6, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Theresa San Augustin</name_title>
    <organization>National Institute for Disability and Rehabilitation Research</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Traumatic Brain Injury</keyword>
  <keyword>Posttraumatic Confusional State</keyword>
  <keyword>Delirium</keyword>
  <keyword>Amantadine</keyword>
  <keyword>Clinical trial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Delirium</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Confusion</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Amantadine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

