<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00691366</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>00002115</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00691366</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comprehensive Investigation of Heart Rate Variability as a Measure of the Autonomic Nervous System in Atopic Dermatitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Autonomic Nervous System Physiology and Chronic Pruritus: A Comprehensive Investigation of Heart Rate Variability as a Measure of the Autonomic Nervous System in Atopic Dermatitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wake Forest University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research is to study heart rate patterns in people with moderate to
      severe atopic dermatitis and how itching affects those patterns.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To comprehensively evaluate the autonomic nervous system through heart rate variability (HRV)
      measurements in patients with moderate to severe atopic dermatitis suffering from pruritus.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Atopic Dermatitis</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Wake Forest University Health Sciences Dermatology Clinic population and from appropriate
        IRB-approved advertising in the community.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult men and women who are between 18 and 50 years of age.

          -  Diagnosis of moderate to severe atopic dermatitis confirmed by published consensus
             diagnostic criteria26 (except for healthy control subjects). Severity will be based on
             an investigator's global assessment score and will have to be moderate or severe (IGA)
             (see Appendix 1).

          -  Subjects must be in general good health with no other skin disease, disease state or
             physical condition which would impair evaluation of their skin or which would increase
             their health risk by study participation as determined by the investigators.

          -  Women of child bearing potential will be required to have a negative pregnancy test in
             order to enroll in the study and will be required to maintain adequate birth control
             throughout the study. Reliable methods of birth control are: abstinence, oral
             contraceptives, intrauterine device (IUD), DepoProvera, Norplant, tubal ligation, or
             vasectomy of the partner (with confirmed negative sperm counts) in a monogamous
             relationship. An acceptable, although less reliable, method involves the careful use
             of condoms and spermicidal foam or gel and/or a cervical cap or sponge.

          -  Subjects must cease using topical agents on the forearm where experimental data is
             going to be collected at least 1 week prior. Topical agents can be used on all other
             parts of the body.

          -  Subjects will be required to cease use of oral antihistamines for a period of one week
             prior to and during the study visit.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults over age 50.

          -  Children less than 18 years of age.

          -  Unable to complete the required measures.

          -  Diagnosis with other diseases that would affect the measurement of heart rate
             variability as determined by the investigators such as cardiovascular disease,
             hypertension, bradycardia (&lt;60 beats per minute) and tachycardia (&gt;100 beats per
             minute) amongst others.

          -  Diagnosis with other skin diseases that would affect the measurement of transepidermal
             water loss (TEWL) and skin hydration as determined by the investigators.

          -  Currently enrolled in any investigational study in which the subject is receiving any
             type of drug, biologic, or non-drug therapy and subjects undergoing treatment with
             another investigational drug or approved therapy for investigational use within 28
             days prior to study participation.

          -  Consistent consumption of more than 4 caffeinated beverages per day.

          -  Current treatment with oral lipophilic beta blockers, antihistamines, opioids,
             glucocorticoids, theophylline, anticholinergic medication or inhaled beta-agonists or
             anticholinergics or other medications known to interfere autonomic nervous system
             physiology.

          -  Asthma/Chronic Obstructive Airways Disease or other respiratory disease.

          -  Neuropathy causing diseases such as uremia.

          -  Uncontrolled thyroid disease.

          -  Diabetes mellitus.

          -  Use of illicit drugs.

          -  Current diagnosis of a psychiatric disorder27;28.

          -  History of chronic urticaria.

          -  History of anaphylactic shock.

          -  Allergy to histamine.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gil Yosipovitch, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Wake Forest University Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Facility: Wake Forest University Health Sciences Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27295</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 2, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 2, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 5, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 16, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis, Atopic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eczema</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

