<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00692991</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>566</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>K23HL004444-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00692991</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using Magnetic Resonance Imaging to Evaluate Heart Vessel Function After Angioplasty or Stent Placement Procedures</brief_title>
  <official_title>Microvascular Obstruction by Contrast-enhanced MRI Following Percutaneous Coronary Interventions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Coronary artery disease (CAD) is caused by a narrowing of the blood vessels that supply blood
      and oxygen to the heart. Balloon angioplasty and stent placement are two treatment options
      for people with reduced heart function caused by CAD. This study will use magnetic resonance
      imaging (MRI) procedures to evaluate heart function over time in people with CAD who have
      undergone a balloon angioplasty or stent placement procedure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      CAD is the most common type of heart disease in the United States. It occurs when the
      arteries that supply blood to the heart become hardened and narrowed because of a build-up of
      cholesterol and plaque on the inner walls of the arteries. Over time, less blood is able to
      flow through the arteries, depriving the heart of the blood and oxygen it needs. If left
      untreated, CAD can lead to heart failure, heart attack, and arrhythmias. Someone with plaque
      build-up may undergo a percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) to unblock the narrowed
      arteries and increase blood flow. PCI encompasses a variety of procedures, including balloon
      angioplasty and stent placement. In balloon angioplasty, a small balloon is inserted into the
      heart artery and then inflated. This pushes the plaque against the artery walls and widens
      the artery. Stents are wire mesh tubes that are permanently implanted in the artery to keep
      it propped open. Although balloon angioplasty and stent placement procedures open up
      blockages in the large vessels of the heart, the tiny vessels of the heart may become blocked
      after these procedures, which may affect how the heart heals. This study will use MRI to
      examine heart function in people who have undergone PCI procedures. Study researchers will
      attempt to define how often blockages of the tiny vessels occur after PCI procedures, the
      factors that lead to the blockages, and how often blockages affect healing of the heart.

      This study will enroll people who are undergoing a PCI procedure. Participants will undergo
      an MRI scan of the heart before and after the PCI procedure. During the 72 hours after the
      procedure, electrocardiogram (EKG) will be used to monitor heart electrical activity. At a
      study visit 10 days after the PCI procedure and at a follow-up visit 6 to 12 months later,
      participants will undergo an MRI, EKG, and blood collection. Study staff will call
      participants every 6 months for 5 years to collect medical information.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of microvascular obstruction by MRI in participants who may or may not have had an acute heart attack; coronary angiographic correlates of MRI microvascular obstruction</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured during participant's initial and follow-up MRIs</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Relation of presence and extent of microvascular obstruction to clinical outcomes over 5 years</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured every 6 months for 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">144</enrollment>
  <condition>Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <condition>Angina, Unstable</condition>
  <condition>Cardiomyopathy, Hypertrophic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <description>People undergoing percutaneous coronary interventions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients listed on the cardiac catheterization schedule who are undergoing percutaneous
        coronary interventions.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Undergoing diagnostic coronary angiography

          -  Undergoing percutaneous coronary intervention

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinically unstable (i.e., demonstrates unstable cardiac rhythm or hemodynamics,
             supported on vasopressors or an intra-aortic balloon pump, and/or is actively
             ischemic) at the time of the MRI procedure

          -  Unable to undergo MRI procedure (e.g., has non-MRI compatible implanted metallic
             objects, including cardiac pacemakers or cerebral aneurysm clips that are not MRI
             compatible)

          -  Current glomerular filtration rate of less than 60mL/min/1.73m2

          -  Pregnant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathy Wu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins Medical Institution</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins Medical Institution</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fernandes VR, Wu KC, Rosen BD, Schmidt A, Lardo AC, Osman N, Halperin HR, Tomaselli G, Berger R, Bluemke DA, Marbán E, Lima JA. Enhanced infarct border zone function and altered mechanical activation predict inducibility of monomorphic ventricular tachycardia in patients with ischemic cardiomyopathy. Radiology. 2007 Dec;245(3):712-9. Epub 2007 Oct 2.</citation>
    <PMID>17911537</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rettmann DW, Saranathan M, Wu KC, Azevedo CF, Bluemke DA, Foo TK. High temporal resolution breathheld 3D FIESTA CINE imaging: validation of ventricular function in patients with chronic myocardial infarction. J Magn Reson Imaging. 2007 Jun;25(6):1141-6.</citation>
    <PMID>17520725</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murthy VL, Wu KC. Advances in cardiac MRI: The multi-ethnic study of atherosclerosis. Curr Cardiol Rep. 2007 Mar;9(1):43-4.</citation>
    <PMID>17436456</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murthy VL, Wu KC. Advances in cardiac MRI: The Dallas Heart Study. Curr Cardiol Rep. 2007 Mar;9(1):43.</citation>
    <PMID>17436455</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmidt A, Azevedo CF, Cheng A, Gupta SN, Bluemke DA, Foo TK, Gerstenblith G, Weiss RG, Marbán E, Tomaselli GF, Lima JA, Wu KC. Infarct tissue heterogeneity by magnetic resonance imaging identifies enhanced cardiac arrhythmia susceptibility in patients with left ventricular dysfunction. Circulation. 2007 Apr 17;115(15):2006-14. Epub 2007 Mar 26.</citation>
    <PMID>17389270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Azevedo CF, Amado LC, Kraitchman DL, Gerber BL, Edvardsen T, Osman NF, Rochitte CE, Wu KC, Lima JA. The effect of intra-aortic balloon counterpulsation on left ventricular functional recovery early after acute myocardial infarction: a randomized experimental magnetic resonance imaging study. Eur Heart J. 2005 Jun;26(12):1235-41. Epub 2005 Feb 16.</citation>
    <PMID>15716282</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kumbasar B, Wu KC, Kamel IR, Lima JA, Bluemke DA. Left ventricular true aneurysm: diagnosis of myocardial viability shown on MR imaging. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2002 Aug;179(2):472-4.</citation>
    <PMID>12130455</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Heldman AW, Wu KC, Abraham TP, Cameron DE. Myectomy or alcohol septal ablation surgery and percutaneous intervention go another round. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2007 Jan 23;49(3):358-60. Epub 2007 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>17239718</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Luo AK, Wu KC. Imaging microvascular obstruction and its clinical significance following acute myocardial infarction. Heart Fail Rev. 2006 Dec;11(4):305-12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17131076</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Vogel-Claussen J, Rochitte CE, Wu KC, Kamel IR, Foo TK, Lima JA, Bluemke DA. Delayed enhancement MR imaging: utility in myocardial assessment. Radiographics. 2006 May-Jun;26(3):795-810. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16702455</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Schmidt A, Wu KC. MRI assessment of myocardial viability. Semin Ultrasound CT MR. 2006 Feb;27(1):11-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16562568</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wu KC. Assessment of non-st-segment elevation acute coronary syndromes with cardiac MRI. Curr Cardiol Rep. 2006 Feb;8(1):42-3.</citation>
    <PMID>16507235</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wu KC. Utility of cardiac MRI in the diagnosis of hypertrophic cardiomyopathy. Curr Cardiol Rep. 2006 Feb;8(1):41.</citation>
    <PMID>16507234</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lardo AC, Cordeiro MA, Silva C, Amado LC, George RT, Saliaris AP, Schuleri KH, Fernandes VR, Zviman M, Nazarian S, Halperin HR, Wu KC, Hare JM, Lima JA. Contrast-enhanced multidetector computed tomography viability imaging after myocardial infarction: characterization of myocyte death, microvascular obstruction, and chronic scar. Circulation. 2006 Jan 24;113(3):394-404.</citation>
    <PMID>16432071</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Foo TK, Ho VB, Saranathan M, Cheng LQ, Sakuma H, Kraitchman DL, Wu KC, Bluemke DA. Feasibility of integrating high-spatial-resolution 3D breath-hold coronary MR angiography with myocardial perfusion and viability examinations. Radiology. 2005 Jun;235(3):1025-30.</citation>
    <PMID>15914483</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Foo TK, Stanley DW, Castillo E, Rochitte CE, Wang Y, Lima JA, Bluemke DA, Wu KC. Myocardial viability: breath-hold 3D MR imaging of delayed hyperenhancement with variable sampling in time. Radiology. 2004 Mar;230(3):845-51.</citation>
    <PMID>14990846</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wu KC, Lima JA. Noninvasive imaging of myocardial viability: current techniques and future developments. Circ Res. 2003 Dec 12;93(12):1146-58. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14670830</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wu KC. Myocardial perfusion imaging by magnetic resonance imaging. Curr Cardiol Rep. 2003 Jan;5(1):63-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12493162</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gerber BL, Garot J, Bluemke DA, Wu KC, Lima JA. Accuracy of contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging in predicting improvement of regional myocardial function in patients after acute myocardial infarction. Circulation. 2002 Aug 27;106(9):1083-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12196333</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 4, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 4, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 6, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 22, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 22, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 23, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Johns Hopkins University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Katherine C. Wu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Microvascular Obstruction</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Alcohol Ablation</keyword>
  <keyword>Diagnostic PCI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertrophy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Angina, Unstable</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiomyopathy, Hypertrophic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

