<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00696566</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STH14468</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>BHF Grant: PG/05/095</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00696566</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Healthy Volunteer Study of Clopidogrel and Rifampicin</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study of the Potentiation of the Effects of Clopidogrel by Rifampicin in Healthy Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>British Heart Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Sheffield</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sheffield Teaching Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The principal research question is: Can platelet P2Y12 receptor blockade by the
      antithrombotic drug clopidogrel be significantly enhanced by coadministration of the
      antibiotic rifampicin?

      Clopidogrel is an antithrombotic drug in clinical use that reduces the risk of heart attack
      and coronary stent thrombosis. However some patients respond poorly to clopidogrel, at least
      partly because they fail to convert it effectively to its active form, and consequently are
      at higher risk of arterial thrombosis. Preliminary evidence indicates that the antibiotic
      rifampicin enhances the effectiveness of clopidogrel by increasing its conversion to its
      active form by the liver. We wish to study further the extent of rifampicin's effect on
      clopidogrel to see whether this might be useful in clinical practice.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Clopidogrel is an antithrombotic drug that is licensed for the treatment and prevention of
      arterial thrombosis, such as in people admitted to hospital with heart attacks. However, some
      people fail to achieve a substantial antithrombotic effect from the drug and one important
      reason for this is that their livers do not convert clopidogrel to its active form
      effectively. Current evidence suggests that these people are less protected by clopidogrel
      and have a higher risk of arterial thrombosis than those who respond well to clopidogrel.
      Rifampicin is an antibiotic that increases the activity of liver enzymes that convert
      clopidogrel to its active form and preliminary evidence indicates that it increases the
      effectiveness of clopidogrel. This raises the possibility that rifampicin might be used with
      clopidogrel to increase its clinical effectiveness. We wish to study this interaction
      further.

      12 healthy volunteers will be recruited for this study after giving informed consent.
      Following Screening, the study will run over 28 days. Lab safety (clinical chemistry,
      haematology and urinalysis) will be undertaken on days 7, 22 and 28 in addition to screening.
      During the first visit, an intravenous cannula will be inserted into a forearm vein. Subjects
      will perform an erythromycin breath test. Subsequently, venous blood will be obtained via the
      intravenous cannula and platelet function studies will be performed and a plasma sample will
      be stored for baseline metabolite analysis. Subsequently the subjects will be administered a
      600 mg loading dose of clopidogrel (Plavix, Sanofi Pharma Bristol−Myers Squibb) and further
      blood samples will be taken over 4 hours for clopidogrel metabolite analysis and platelet
      function studies. Subjects will then take clopidogrel 75 mg daily for a further 6 days and, 4
      hours after the last dose, a further blood sample will be taken using venepuncture for
      platelet function studies and a plasma sample. After a washout period of 7 days, subjects
      will then start rifampicin 300 mg twice daily for 14 days (Rifadin, Aventis Pharma). On the
      8th day of taking rifampicin, a further intravenous cannula will be inserted, the
      erythromycin breath test will be repeated, as above, and the same regimen of clopidogrel
      administration and blood testing will be repeated, this time with co−administration of
      rifampicin.

      The data obtained will allow the following assessments: (i) comparison of the early effects
      of a 600 mg clopidogrel loading dose and late effects of clopidogrel after 7 days on platelet
      aggregation and receptor blockade; (ii) assessment of the effects of rifampicin on
      clopidogrel's action on platelet aggregation and receptor blockade following a loading dose
      and after prolonged administration of clopidogrel.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Can platelet P2Y12 receptor blockade by the antithrombotic drug clopidogrel be significantly enhanced by coadministration of the antibiotic rifampicin?</measure>
    <time_frame>All year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects will receive Clopidogrel and Rifampicin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clopidogrel and Rifampicin</intervention_name>
    <description>Clopidogrel: loading dose of 600 mg, then 75 mg o.d. for up to 28 days
Rifampicin: 300 mg b.d. for up to 28 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Clopidorel = Plavix</other_name>
    <other_name>Rifampicin = Rifadin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy male subjects, or female subjects not of childbearing potential (either
             surgically sterile or post menopausal).

          -  Age between 18 and 65 years inclusive.

          -  Non smokers.

          -  Body mass index (BMI) between 18 and 28 kg/m2 inclusive, with a body weight between 60
             - 100 kg.

          -  Subjects are to be in good health as determined by a medical history, physical
             examination including vital signs, and clinical laboratory test results including
             liver function and full blood count.

          -  Subjects have given their signed informed consent before any trial−related activity.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  In the opinion of the investigator, subjects with, or a history of, cancer, diabetes
             or clinically significant cardiovascular, respiratory, metabolic, renal, hepatic,
             gastrointestinal, haematological, dermatological, neurological, psychiatric or other
             major disorders.

          -  Subjects with a history of significant multiple drug allergies or with a known allergy
             to the study drugs or any medicine chemically related to the trial product.

          -  Subjects who have a clinically significant allergic disease (including hay fever).

          -  Subjects who have had a clinically significant illness within 4 weeks of dosing.

          -  Subjects taking regular medication including NSAID's, antibiotics, aspirin or
             anticoagulant therapy.

          -  Any clinically significant abnormal laboratory test results at screening.

          -  Subjects who have a supine blood pressure at screening, after resting for 5 min higher
             than 150/90 mmHg or lower than 100/50 mmHg.

          -  Subjects who have a supine heart rate at screening, after resting for 5 minutes
             outside the range of 40 - 90 beats/min.

          -  Subjects who have received any prescribed systemic or topical medication within two
             weeks prior to screening (although occasional use of paracetamol is permitted at the
             discretion of the investigator).

          -  Subjects who have received an investigational medicinal product within the previous
             four months (new chemical entity) or three months (licensed product) or subjects who
             have received a vaccine within three months preceding the start of dosing.

          -  Subjects who have donated any blood or plasma in the past month or in excess of 500 ml
             within twelve weeks preceding screening.

          -  Subjects who have a history of alcohol or drug abuse (consume greater than 28 units
             per week [one unit of alcohol equals 250 ml of beer or lager or one glass of wine or
             20 ml of spirits]).

          -  Subjects with mental incapacity or language barriers which preclude adequate
             understanding.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert F Storey</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Sheffield</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sheffield Clinical Research Facility, Royal Hallamshire Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sheffield</city>
        <state>S. Yorkshire</state>
        <zip>S10 2JF</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 4, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 11, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 12, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 11, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 11, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 12, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Dr Robert Storey / Senior Lecturer &amp; Honorary Consultant in Cardiology</name_title>
    <organization>University of Sheffield</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Thrombosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Platelet aggregation inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood platelets</keyword>
  <keyword>P2 receptor</keyword>
  <keyword>Cytochrome P450</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Clopidogrel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ticlopidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Platelet Aggregation Inhibitors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rifampin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

