<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00695682</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>101606</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00695682</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intravitreal Infliximab for Diabetic Macular Edema (DME) and Choroidal Neovascularization (CNV)</brief_title>
  <acronym>ITVR</acronym>
  <official_title>The Safety and Tolerability of Intravitreal Infliximab (Remicade) in Patients With Refractory Diabetic Macular Edema or Choroidal Neovascularization Secondary to Age Related Macular Degeneration- A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Retina Research Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Retina Research Foundation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Injections of medicine into the middle of the eye (intravitreal injections) are commonly used
      in a multitude of retinal diseases. We are looking for new treatments that may be beneficial
      in treating retinal disease and improving patients' vision.

      Infliximab (Remicade) is a genetically engineered antibody against a molecule in the body
      called TNF-α. It neutralizes the effects of TNF-α by binding to it. Intravenous Infliximab
      has been used for inflammatory arthritic conditions and Crohn's disease since 1998. We do not
      know if infliximab injections into the eye are safe. We are performing this pilot study to
      determine if they can be safe.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Intravenous Infliximab is currently used for the treatment of systemic inflammatory
      conditions and inflammatory disease of the eye with a relatively favorable safety profile.
      However, systemic administration carries the risk of systemic side effects, which in the case
      of infliximab can be severe, such as increased risk of infection, reactivation of
      tuberculosis or Hepatosplenic T-cell Lymphoma.

      Direct intravitreal administration of medication is the preferred method of treatment for
      retinal vascular disorders. The eye is a self contained organ relatively isolated from the
      systemic circulation by the tight blood retinal barrier. Effective intraocular drug levels
      can be achieved with a much smaller amount of medication if injected intravitreally and this
      also results in minimal systemic exposure to the patient. Preliminary studies have shown that
      Infliximab may have a positive role in the management of retinal vascular disorders in humans
      when administered intravenously, and can be an effective treatment intravitreally in animal
      models. No data has been published yet on intravitreal use of infliximab in human subjects.

      We plan to study the safety and tolerability of intravitreal injections of infliximab in
      human subjects with refractory diabetic macular edema or choroidal neovascularization. Our
      infliximab dose will be 0.5mg/0.5ml, as it follows the reconstitution instructions in the
      Product Insert. This dosing will fall within the therapeutic dosing found within the animal
      study as it leads to the same vitreous concentration as the7.5 µg dose in group B rat eye
      study. (4)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>June 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>This is a pilot study to study the safety and tolerability of intravitreal Infliximab in patients with refractory diabetic macular edema and choroidal neovascularization (CNV)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 m</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>(BCVA)</measure>
    <time_frame>3m</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Standard Electroretinogram</measure>
    <time_frame>3m</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OCT</measure>
    <time_frame>3m</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fluorescein angiography</measure>
    <time_frame>3m</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nidek Microperimetry</measure>
    <time_frame>3m</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence and severity of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>3m</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetic Retinopathy</condition>
  <condition>Macular Degeneration</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>intravitreal injection of infliximab</intervention_name>
    <description>All subjects will receive 0.5 mg/ 0.05 mL of infliximab by intravitreal injection at their first treatment visit or the 6 weeks visit if eligible for a repeat injection.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ability to provide written informed consent and comply with study assessments for the
             full duration of the study

          -  Age &gt; 21 years

          -  Patients with active CNV secondary to AMD in the study eye which did not improve with
             conventional therapy

          -  Patients with refractory diabetic macular edema in the study eye which did not improve
             with conventional therapy

          -  BCVA 20/70 or less as measured on an ETDRS chart.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Are participating in another clinical study requiring follow up examinations

          -  Have received any other experimental drug within 12 weeks prior to enrollment

          -  Are unwilling or unable to follow or comply with all study-related procedures

          -  Inability to obtain photographs, fluorescein angiography, or optical coherence
             tomography to document CNV, e.g. due to media opacity, allergy to fluorescein dye or
             lack of venous access

          -  Aphakia or pseudophakia with the absence of posterior capsule (unless it resulted from
             a yttrium aluminum garner [YAG]) posterior capsulotomy)

          -  Within two months prior to screening, have had intraocular surgery (including cataract
             surgery) in the study eye

          -  Within 1 month prior to screening had YAG laser in the study eye

          -  Have had intravitreal anti VEGF or intravitreal steroids in the last 6 weeks

          -  Have had previous pars plana vitrectomy in the study eye

          -  Are pregnant or are trying to become pregnant

          -  Any other condition that the investigator believes would pose a significant hazard to
             the subject if the investigational therapy were initiated

          -  Have a history of allergies to murine monoclonal antibodies, mice or mouse products.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul M Beer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Retina Research Foundation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Retina Consultants</name>
      <address>
        <city>SLingerlands</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>12159</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul Beer, MD</last_name>
      <phone>518-533-6550</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul M Beer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://retinaconsultants.org</url>
    <description>Retina Consultants</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 10, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 11, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 12, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 11, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 11, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 12, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Paul Beer, MD</name_title>
    <organization>Retina Research Foundation</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Remicade</keyword>
  <keyword>Infliximab</keyword>
  <keyword>CSME</keyword>
  <keyword>BDR</keyword>
  <keyword>CNV</keyword>
  <keyword>AMD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Macular Degeneration</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Macular Edema</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Retinopathy</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neovascularization, Pathologic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Choroidal Neovascularization</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infliximab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>July 28, 2011</submitted>
    <returned>August 25, 2011</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

