<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00692861</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>080153</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>08-N-0153</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00692861</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Autoimmunity in Neurologic Complications of Celiac Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Role of Autoimmunity in Neurologic Complications of Celiac Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study, done in collaboration with Cornell University in New York, will explore the
      potential role of the body s immune response to gluten in ataxia. Celiac disease is an
      autoimmune disorder that is triggered by the ingestion of wheat gluten and related proteins
      in genetically susceptible individuals. Some people with celiac disease also develop ataxia,
      which is a loss of muscle coordination, leading to imbalance. The cause of the associated
      ataxia is not well understood, but it is suspected to be related to the immune response
      towards gluten in these patients. Preliminary results indicate that antibodies in people with
      celiac disease can react with brain proteins, which might have a role in the associated
      neurologic deficits. The aim of this study is to characterize the immune response in the
      ataxia that is associated with celiac disease.

      People 18 years of age and older with 1) ataxia and no celiac disease, 2) ataxia plus celiac
      disease and 3) matched healthy control subjects will be enrolled at the NIH. People with
      celiac disease only will be enrolled at Cornell University.

      All participants have a blood sample drawn for various tests of immune function as well as
      genetic tests. Healthy volunteers also have a history and physical examination if they have
      not had one done at NIH in the past year. Some patients may require additional clinical
      evaluations for clinical or diagnostic reasons.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective: To understand the role of the immune system in the neurologic complications of
      celiac disease (CD) or gluten sensitivity (GS).

      Study population: We plan to study 15 patients with CD and ataxia, 15 patients with
      hereditary ataxia, and 30 healthy matched controls.

      Design: Four groups of patients will be enrolled into the study. The first group will consist
      of patients with CD and ataxia, the second group will consist of CD patients without
      neurological manifestations, the third group will consist of patients with hereditary
      cerebellar ataxia without CD, and the final group will consist of healthy 30 race matched
      volunteers. The second group will not be recruited at the NIH. Standardized enzyme-linked
      immunosorbent assay (ELISA) techniques will used to assess the presence of synapsin I in the
      groups of patients. Using affinity assays, cross-reactivity of antibodies to gliadin and
      synapsin 1 will be evaluated. Antibody epitope mapping will be performed on those antibodies
      that cross-react with synapsin 1 and gliadin. HLA class II genotypic and phenotypic
      frequencies will be assessed and compared with the matched volunteers as an exploratory
      measure to look for genetic risk and protective factors in this group of patients.

      Outcome measures: our outcome measures are as follows:

      A. To determine whether there is an association between antibody reactivity to synapsin I and
      neurological deficits of CD/GS.

      B. To characterize the cross-reactive antibodies in patients by determining subclass and
      affinity

      C. To map the epitope(s) of synapsin I that are targeted in patients with cross-reactive
      antibodies

      D. To explore HLA association in the subset of patients with CD and ataxia
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2, 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date>January 3, 2014</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Antibodies to synapsin I.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antibody characterization and HLA association</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Ataxia</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        We plan to evaluate serum and blood from patients with gluten sensitivity (including both
        biopsy-proven CD, and biopsy-negative cases with high anti-gliadin antibody titer)
        accompanied by cerebellar ataxia. Serum samples will be acquired prior to initiation of a
        gluten-free diet. Therefore, several inclusion criteria exist based on the study group:

        INCLUSION CRITERIA FOR PATIENTS WITH CD PLUS CEREBELLAR ATAXIA:

          -  The patient meets criteria for CD based on the modified ESPGAN criteria

          -  The patient has ataxia with or without neuropathy based on clinical evaluation

          -  The patient is free from other neurological and psychiatric deficits

          -  All other known causes for ataxia have been ruled out through routine clinical
             evaluations

          -  The patient is at least 18 years old and is willing to participate in the protocol

          -  The patient is not taking medications that are commonly known to have immune
             modulating effects.

          -  The patient is not on a gluten free diet

        INCLUSION CRITERIA FOR PATIENTS WITH HEREDITARY CEREBELLAR ATAXIA WITHOUT CD:

          -  The patient tested negative for serologic markers of CD (i.e. antigliadin,
             antireticulin, and antiendomysial antibody testing as performed under protocol
             93-N-0202)

          -  The patient has ataxia on routine clinical examination and no other neurological or
             psychiatric problems

          -  The patient has a known autosomal dominant ataxia (i.e., SCA, DRPLA, Friedreich s
             ataxia, and etc).

        INCLUSION CRITERIA FOR MATCHED-CONTROLS:

          -  They should not have CD and or ataxia based on clinical evaluation and history

          -  Serologic testing for antigliadin, antireticulin, and antiendomysial antibodies should
             reveal negative results

          -  They should be race and age-matched with patients with CD and the ataxia group.

          -  They should have no neurological or psychiatric conditions based on clinical
             evaluation and history

          -  They should not have any rheumatological or autoimmune conditions in them or in their
             first degree relatives.

          -  They should be at least 18 years of age and be able to provide consent for
             participation

          -  They should not be on any immune modulating medications.

        Final diagnosis of CD will strictly follow the modified criteria of the European Society
        for Pediatric Gastroenterology and Nutrition (ESPGAN) and recommendations of the recently
        held National Institutes of Health Consensus Development Conference on Celiac Disease.
        Assessment and diagnosis of cerebellar ataxia will be made by magnetic resonance imaging of
        the brain, clinical examination and genetic testing for spinocerebellar ataxias and
        Friedreich s ataxia. Additional routine testing will be done if necessary to exclude other
        causes.

        Healthy and disease control groups will be evaluated for CD and for neurological deficits.
        Only symptom-free, antibody-negative individuals will be recruited into these control
        groups. Exclusion of neurological deficits and psychiatric illness in healthy and disease
        control subjects will be by history and neurological examination.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        For all groups, if other neurological and psychiatric diagnoses are present, the individual
        will not qualify to participate in this study.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA FOR ALL GROUPS:

          -  Subject is already on a gluten-restricted diet.

          -  Is taking known immune modulating therapy

          -  Have other neurological condition (except for neuropathy) or psychiatric condition

          -  Not willing to have blood drawn

          -  Is known to have immune dysfunction

          -  Being pregnant leads to numerous physiological changes. It is unclear if antibody
             characteristics are influenced by these changes.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Hallett, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cornell University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021-4872</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alaedini A, Green PH. Narrative review: celiac disease: understanding a complex autoimmune disorder. Ann Intern Med. 2005 Feb 15;142(4):289-98. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15710962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fasano A, Berti I, Gerarduzzi T, Not T, Colletti RB, Drago S, Elitsur Y, Green PH, Guandalini S, Hill ID, Pietzak M, Ventura A, Thorpe M, Kryszak D, Fornaroli F, Wasserman SS, Murray JA, Horvath K. Prevalence of celiac disease in at-risk and not-at-risk groups in the United States: a large multicenter study. Arch Intern Med. 2003 Feb 10;163(3):286-92.</citation>
    <PMID>12578508</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tommasini A, Not T, Kiren V, Baldas V, Santon D, Trevisiol C, Berti I, Neri E, Gerarduzzi T, Bruno I, Lenhardt A, Zamuner E, Spanò A, Crovella S, Martellossi S, Torre G, Sblattero D, Marzari R, Bradbury A, Tamburlini G, Ventura A. Mass screening for coeliac disease using antihuman transglutaminase antibody assay. Arch Dis Child. 2004 Jun;89(6):512-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15155392</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 3, 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 5, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 5, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 6, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Celiac Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Ataxia</keyword>
  <keyword>Adults</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>HV</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ataxia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Celiac Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autoimmune Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

