<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00691678</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAC8748</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00691678</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Glucosamine and Chondroitin for Aromatase Inhibitor Induced Joint Symptoms in Women With Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pase II Study of Glucosamine With Chondroitin on Joint Symptoms Induced By Aromatase Inhibitors in Breast Cancer Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dawn L. Hershman</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Investigators are hoping to learn if glucosamine with chondroitin can help relieve joint
      pain/stiffness associated with aromatase inhibitors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Due to early detection and improved treatments, women with breast cancer are living longer.
      The increase in breast cancer survival is largely due to the benefits of hormonal therapy,
      such as tamoxifen and aromatase inhibitors (AIs), for the treatment of hormone-sensitive
      breast cancer. Recent clinical trials have demonstrated that AIs are more effective than
      tamoxifen at reducing breast cancer recurrences. However, breast cancer patients receiving
      AIs have a higher incidence of osteoporosis, bone fractures and musculoskeletal symptoms,
      particularly joint pain and stiffness. Musculoskeletal pain, which occurs in up to 50% of
      patients treated with AIs, often does not respond to conventional pain medications, may lead
      to noncompliance, may cause major disability, and may interfere with quality of life. Many
      women are unable to tolerate these life-saving drugs because of severe joint pain, therefore,
      safe and effective treatments that alleviate these symptoms are needed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of reduced knee and/or joint pain and/or stiffness</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Using the Outcome Measures in Rheumatology Clinical Trials and Osteoarthritis Research Society International (OMERACT-OARSI) criteria, which provides a combined assessment of changes in pain, function, and the patient's global assessment of disease status.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">53</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Joint Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>chondroitin and glucosamine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Postmenopausal breast cancer patients that have joint symptoms induced by aromatase inhibitors and are receiving chondroitin and glucosamine.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chondroitin</intervention_name>
    <description>400mg chondroitin TID for twenty-four weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>chondroitin and glucosamine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Chondroitin sulfate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glucosamine</intervention_name>
    <description>500mg glucosamine TID for twenty-four weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>chondroitin and glucosamine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Glucosamine sulfate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &gt;21 years.

          -  Postmenopausal status defined as cessation of menses for &gt;1 year or FSH &gt;20 mIU/mL or
             bilateral oophorectomy.

          -  History of stage I, II or III hormone receptor-positive breast cancer, without
             metastatic disease.

          -  Currently taking a third-generation aromatase inhibitor for at least 3 months.

          -  Clinical symptoms of knee and/or hand joint pain and/or stiffness for at least 3
             months prior to study entry.

          -  Ongoing musculoskeletal pain/stiffness in hand and/or knee joints (50 or higher on the
             100 point global assessment VAS) that started or increased since initiating aromatase
             inhibitor therapy, and has been present for at least 3 months.

          -  Patients must agree to refrain from use of glucosamine and chondroitin from sources
             outside of this study.

          -  If taking bisphosphonates, on a stable dose for at least 3 months and tolerating the
             dose. Patients must agree to refrain from initiating bisphosphonate use during the
             course of the study, therefore it is recommended that routine bone density testing be
             performed prior to enrollment or after completing trial.

          -  ECOG performance status 0-2.

          -  Hemoglobin A1c &lt;8 within the last year.

          -  Signed informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of glucosamine or chondroitin within the past three (3) months.

          -  Concurrent medical/arthritic disease that could confound or interfere with evaluation
             of pain or efficacy.

          -  History of significant collateral ligament, anterior cruciate ligament or meniscal
             injury of the index joint requiring surgery or non-weight bearing (requiring use of
             crutches or cane) for more than 3 weeks (minor ligamentous injury prior to 6 months is
             not an exclusion).

          -  History of bone fracture or surgery of the afflicted knees and/or hands within 6
             months prior to study entry.

          -  Uncontrolled diabetes mellitus, defined as Hemoglobin A1c level of &gt; 8%.

          -  History of any illness that, in the opinion of the investigator, might confound the
             results of the study or pose additional risk to the patient.

          -  Allergy to, or history of significant clinical or laboratory adverse experience
             associated with acetaminophen, glucosamine or chondroitin sulfate.

          -  Allergy to shellfish.

          -  Inability to understand and complete study questionnaires including questions
             requiring a visual analog scale (VAS) response.

          -  Inability to understand the study procedures and/or give written informed consent.

          -  Alcohol use in excess of 3 mixed drinks/day.

          -  Corticosteroid treatment was used or administered.

          -  Aspirin (up to 325 mg/day) for cardiovascular reasons may be continued.

          -  Intra-articular injection of hyaluronic acid or congeners into the study joint within
             12 months.

          -  Topical analgesics (e.g., capsaicin preparations) to the study joint, or any oral
             analgesics (e.g., opiates, tramadol; with the exception of ibuprofen and
             acetaminophen) within 2 weeks of baseline visit or during the study.

          -  Implementation of any other medical therapy for arthritis within one month prior to
             entry.

          -  Other medications, unrelated to the patient's joint pain/stiffness must have been used
             at a stable dosage for at least 1 month. In addition, it should be anticipated that
             the dose of the concomitant medication will be stable during the entire treatment
             period.

          -  Participation in another clinical study with an investigational agent within the last
             4 weeks.

          -  Exposure to glucosamine within 3 months or chondroitin sulfate within 3 months of
             Baseline Visit.

          -  Initiation of physical therapy or muscle conditioning program within 2 months prior to
             study entry.

          -  Concurrent use of the following medications and dietary supplements.

               -  Chronic therapy with tetracycline or tetracycline derivatives.

               -  Other new complementary or alternative regimens for the treatment of
                  osteoarthritis, including, but not limited to, acupuncture, topical creams, oral
                  agents, and magnets.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dawn Hershman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 3, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 4, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 5, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 15, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 15, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dawn L. Hershman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine &amp; Epidemiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>aromatase inhibitor</keyword>
  <keyword>supportive care</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthralgia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aromatase Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

