<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01859845</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU00077615</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01859845</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Melanoma Simulation Model With Smartphone Devices: Training Physicians for Early Detection of Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Melanoma Simulation Model With Smartphone Devices: Training Physicians to Perform Opportunistic Surveillance for Early Detection of Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The specific aim of this study is to determine if interactive touchscreen-based learning with
      deliberate practice modules can enhance the retention of life-saving medical skills when
      incorporated into medical training curricula. We will analyze the retention and confidence of
      screening skills by comparing outcomes on pretest and posttest in each arm.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Age-adjusted melanoma incidence among Caucasians has risen from 7.5 to 21.9 cases per 100,000
      representing an increase of nearly 200% over 30 years. In contrast to other cancers (i.e.
      colorectal, prostate, cervical), melanoma is detected by intentional visual skin inspection.
      Intentional screening is the deliberate visual inspection of all cutaneous surfaces. However,
      fewer than 30% of primary care physicians (PCPs) reported training in skin cancer during
      their medical education. Early detection of melanoma by PCPs cannot be expected to improve
      without addressing both the PCPs' lack of training and their low confidence in examination
      skills pertaining to pigmented lesion exams. A focused intervention is required to improve
      PCPs' early detection of melanoma and mitigate the near-term consequences of an aging US
      population.

      Opportunistic surveillance requires skills in both unaided visual inspection of the skin and
      in dermoscopy of lesions. Dermoscopy—a hand-held magnifying device that assists with
      diagnosis—reduces the number of unnecessary biopsies and improves the clinical sensitivity of
      diagnosing melanoma. Studies show that Australian PCPs trained to use a &quot;three-point
      checklist of dermoscopy,&quot; developed biopsy ratios of benign to malignant lesions of 8:1 in
      the general population, which is comparable to dermatologists using dermoscopy. In 2009, the
      American Academy of Family Physicians held their first dermoscopy course at their Annual
      Scientific Meeting, and there is continuing demand for similar courses. By making dermoscopy
      customary for PCPs, PCPs will be able to detect melanomas opportunistically and render care
      to the at-risk population of elderly for whom they provide care. Smart-touchscreen
      technologies can potentially provide a safe environment for medical trainees to learn
      procedural and screening skills that are rarely available opportunities in the clinic. As
      such, these technologies may lead to better health outcomes in future populations.

      In this study, eighty 3rd year medical and thirty 1st year physician's assistant students
      participate in a visual screening and dermoscopy curriculum aimed at improving the retention
      rate of the learned clinical skills. After a didactic lecture on melanoma screening,
      participants are randomized to either a control or an experimental study arm for the clinical
      skills workshop. The control arm represents our previously published clinical skills training
      workshop (IRB STU 0002705) in which participants interact with a simulated patient model
      presenting with pigment lesions and review dermoscopy images on a projector screen. In the
      experimental arm, the projector-based learning approach is replaced with a handheld
      touchscreen device (smartphone) preloaded with interactive melanoma screening tutorial. The
      smartphone provides instant feedback and remediation of improper clinical management
      decisions. Across both groups, all learning content remains similar. Further deliberate
      practice questions provided to the control arm are standardized while the experimental arm's
      questions are individualized based on weaknesses determined in the smartphone software.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of medical student's abilities to select pigmented lesions for review with dermoscopy on pre-didactic lecture test, pre-skills workshop test, and post-educational intervention test</measure>
    <time_frame>Two weeks post initial didactic education</time_frame>
    <description>Retention will be measured using the percent of correctly identified benign nevi, clinically suspicious lesions, and melanomas identified by unaided visual inspection and the percent of correctly identified &quot;benign&quot; or &quot;refer&quot; lesions on dermoscopy images. The biopsy ratio of benign to malignant lesions will be also be assessed to determine the sensitivity and specificity outcomes of both study arms. Other outcomes measured are the confidence with identifying melanoma, attitudes toward melanoma screening, and recall of screening rules by participants. The rates of retention in both study arms will be compared on pre-workshop test and the post-test to determine if simulation learning modules positively impact learning and retention of skin screening.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">63</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Study Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control participants will first interact with the simulated melanoma back model to learn clinical unaided visual inspection skills and then view a passive image projected onto a screen for dermoscopy learning. Remediation of inappropriate clinical decisions will be carried out by the research coordinator and is based on predefined feedback consistent across both arms of the study. Along with the projected images, the coordinator will provide each control participant with worksheets for the clinical Asymmetry, Border, Color, Diameter (ABCD) and Dermoscopy 3-point check list. A copy of the completed worksheet will be made at the end of the workshop.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>smartphone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each participant in the educational intervention arm will have access to a smartphone with a preloaded android software package. The smartphone software allows the participant to visualize a dermoscopic image of the pigmented lesion at the surface of the simulated melanoma model. Participants are given the freedom to navigate through the program via the smartphone to learn at their own pace with reinforcement of correct clinical management decisions and correction of weaknesses. The software content is limited to the dermoscopy information available to the positive control arm through the coordinator and the dermoscopic images projected onto the screen, thus a comparison of retention rates across both arms is possible.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Smartphone</intervention_name>
    <description>Our team of dermatologists and biomechanical engineers led by the PI developed a simulation skills training prototype device using a smartphone. Software was developed to teach dermoscopic evaluation of pigmented lesions using the &quot;three-poin checklist of dermoscopy&quot;. The software used in the smartphone presentation of the educational intervention also provides a decision tree of clinical management options and best-practices feedback. No patients are involved in this research.</description>
    <arm_group_label>smartphone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>educational intervention</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria for Evaluation of the smartphone-based dermoscopy prototype device:

          -  Thirty 4th year medical students and 2nd year physician assistant (PA) students with
             previous experience with the Melanoma Simulation Model of the back (IRB STU00025072)

        Inclusion Criteria for teaching and testing sessions with medical students and physician
        assistant students:

          -  Eighty third-year medical students and thirty PA students

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Those not meeting the above inclusion criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>June K Robinson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University Department of Dermatology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University Department of Dermatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 20, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 20, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 22, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 30, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 30, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 1, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwestern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>June Robinson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Professor of Dermatology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Opportunistic surveillance</keyword>
  <keyword>Melanoma simulation model</keyword>
  <keyword>Smartphone devices</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

