<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01855620</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAK6606</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01855620</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Body Mass Index on Etonogestrel Hormone Levels in Women Using the Single-rod Contraceptive Implant</brief_title>
  <acronym>Eto BMI</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effect of Body Mass Index on Etonogestrel Levels in Women Using the Single-rod Contraceptive Implant</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Two-thirds of young women in the United States are overweight or obese. This excess weight
      may affect how their body metabolizes drugs such as different birth control methods. There is
      a not a lot of research about how excess weight could affect the hormone levels of the
      contraceptive implant. Methods like the implant contain only progesterone, which is a hormone
      that does not increase a woman's risk of blood clot. These methods would be preferred for
      overweight and obese women because excess weight also increases a woman's risk of blood clot.

      The investigators propose a study comparing blood hormone levels of women using the implant
      for at least twelve months and in all weight categories. The investigators hope to show that
      all women, regardless of weight, will have hormone levels high enough to prevent pregnancy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Two-thirds of reproductive-age women in the United States are either overweight or obese.
      Body composition may affect contraceptive hormone metabolism and possibly efficacy. Phase III
      studies to date included few women weighing more than 70 kilograms (134 of 923, 14.5%); there
      were no reported pregnancies in that group. Data about pregnancy rates for women in higher
      body mass index (BMI) categories using the etonogestrel implant exists, but we know little
      about how weight affects the serum etonogestrel levels. Progestin-only methods, such as the
      etonogestrel implant, may be preferred over combined methods including estrogens because
      obesity increases thrombosis risk.

      The investigators propose a prospective study to compare serum etonogestrel levels in the
      second and third years of implant use between women across body mass index categories.

      Based on previous studies, the investigators expect a difference in etonogestrel levels based
      on body weight; however, the investigators hypothesize that etonogestrel levels will remain
      above the threshold for ovulation suppression through three years of implant use for women
      across BMI categories.

      The investigators will measure the serum levels of etonogestrel in normal weight (BMI &lt;
      25kg/m2), overweight (BMI ≥ 25kg/m2 and &lt; 30kg/m2), and obese women (BMI ≥ 30kg/m2) using the
      single-rod contraceptive implant for at least twelve months. Their primary objective is to
      compare the three groups and to evaluate whether etonogestrel levels fall below the critical
      level for contraceptive efficacy (90 pg/mL) (Díaz 1991) in any group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Etonogestrel Level</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will measure the serum levels of etonogestrel in normal weight (BMI &lt; 25kg/m2), overweight (BMI ≥ 25kg/m2 and &lt; 30kg/m2), and obese women (BMI ≥ 30kg/m2) using the single-rod contraceptive implant for at least twelve months. The primary objective is to compare the three groups and to evaluate whether etonogestrel levels fall below the critical level for contraceptive efficacy (90 pg/mL) (Díaz 1991) in any group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">52</enrollment>
  <condition>Contraception</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal weight women</arm_group_label>
    <description>Women with implant for more than twelve months who have BMI &lt;25.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Overweight women</arm_group_label>
    <description>Women with implant for more than twelve months who have BMI &gt; or = 25 and &lt;30.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Obese women</arm_group_label>
    <description>Women with implant for more than twelve months who have BMI &gt; or = 30.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Whole blood
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population is English or Spanish-speaking women ages 15-45 years old at the New
        York Presbyterian Hospital's Title X Family Planning Clinic and the Columbia University
        Medical Center's Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology Family Planning Practice who have
        been using the etonogestrel contraceptive implant for at least the six months prior to
        their visit.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Woman using contraceptive implant for more than 12 months

          -  English or Spanish-speaking

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathleen M Morrell, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.merck.com/product/usa/pi_circulars/n/nexplanon/nexplanon_pi.pdf</url>
    <description>Nexplanon Prescribing information</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jacobson JC, Aikins Murphy P. United States medical eligibility criteria for contraceptive use 2010: a review of changes. J Midwifery Womens Health. 2011 Nov-Dec;56(6):598-607. doi: 10.1111/j.1542-2011.2011.00093.x. Epub 2011 Oct 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22060220</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ciangura C, Corigliano N, Basdevant A, Mouly S, Declèves X, Touraine P, Lloret-Linares C. Etonorgestrel concentrations in morbidly obese women following Roux-en-Y gastric bypass surgery: three case reports. Contraception. 2011 Dec;84(6):649-51. doi: 10.1016/j.contraception.2011.03.015. Epub 2011 May 8.</citation>
    <PMID>22078197</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davies GC, Feng LX, Newton JR, Van Beek A, Coelingh-Bennink HJ. Release characteristics, ovarian activity and menstrual bleeding pattern with a single contraceptive implant releasing 3-ketodesogestrel. Contraception. 1993 Mar;47(3):251-61.</citation>
    <PMID>8462316</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Díaz S, Pavez M, Moo-Young AJ, Bardin CW, Croxatto HB. Clinical trial with 3-keto-desogestrel subdermal implants. Contraception. 1991 Oct;44(4):393-408.</citation>
    <PMID>1756627</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Graesslin O, Korver T. The contraceptive efficacy of Implanon: a review of clinical trials and marketing experience. Eur J Contracept Reprod Health Care. 2008 Jun;13 Suppl 1:4-12. doi: 10.1080/13625180801942754. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18330813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flegal KM, Carroll MD, Kit BK, Ogden CL. Prevalence of obesity and trends in the distribution of body mass index among US adults, 1999-2010. JAMA. 2012 Feb 1;307(5):491-7. doi: 10.1001/jama.2012.39. Epub 2012 Jan 17.</citation>
    <PMID>22253363</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huber J, Wenzl R. Pharmacokinetics of Implanon. An integrated analysis. Contraception. 1998 Dec;58(6 Suppl):85S-90S. Erratum in: Contraception 1999 Feb;59(2):145. Retraction in: Rekers H, Affandi B. Contraception. 2004 Nov;70(5):433.</citation>
    <PMID>10095978</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mornar S, Chan LN, Mistretta S, Neustadt A, Martins S, Gilliam M. Pharmacokinetics of the etonogestrel contraceptive implant in obese women. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2012 Aug;207(2):110.e1-6. doi: 10.1016/j.ajog.2012.05.002. Epub 2012 May 8.</citation>
    <PMID>22717269</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schnabel P, Merki-Feld GS, Malvy A, Duijkers I, Mommers E, van den Heuvel MW. Bioequivalence and x-ray visibility of a radiopaque etonogestrel implant versus a non-radiopaque implant: a 3-year, randomized, double-blind study. Clin Drug Investig. 2012 Jun 1;32(6):413-22. doi: 10.2165/11631930-000000000-00000.</citation>
    <PMID>22540269</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sivin I, Wan L, Ranta S, Alvarez F, Brache V, Mishell DR Jr, Darney P, Biswas A, Diaz S, Kiriwat O, Anant MP, Klaisle C, Pavez M, Schechter J. Levonorgestrel concentrations during 7 years of continuous use of Jadelle contraceptive implants. Contraception. 2001 Jul;64(1):43-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11535213</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Xu H, Wade JA, Peipert JF, Zhao Q, Madden T, Secura GM. Contraceptive failure rates of etonogestrel subdermal implants in overweight and obese women. Obstet Gynecol. 2012 Jul;120(1):21-6. doi: 10.1097/AOG.0b013e318259565a.</citation>
    <PMID>22678035</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 14, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 14, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 16, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 11, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 11, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kathleen M. Morrell</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Clinical Obgyn</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Contraception</keyword>
  <keyword>Implant</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Contraceptive Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etonogestrel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

