<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01851213</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FMI-001-NGS-500</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01851213</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>FoundationOne™ Test Registry Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>FMI Registry</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective Observational Study to Examine, in Routine Clinical Practice in the US, Practice Patterns and Impact on Clinical Decision Making Associated With the FoundationOne™ Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) Test</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Foundation Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Quintiles, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Foundation Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a prospective, multicenter, observational study to characterize utilization
      patterns of the FoundationOne™ test by oncologists under conditions of routine clinical
      practice in the US. The study will also examine impact of test results on subsequent clinical
      decisions regarding choice of therapy. The planned duration of the study is at least 2 years
      with 1 year for patient recruitment and a minimum 1-year follow-up period for each patient.
      Any patient for whom the treating physician has ordered a FoundationOne™ test and a report is
      delivered is eligible for participation on the study. Eligible patients from participating
      sites will be enrolled sequentially during the 1-year enrollment period. Sites will be
      required to maintain an enrollment log of all patients for whom the FoundationOne™ test has
      been ordered and document patient disposition and reasons for non-participation. All
      treatment decisions and clinical assessment will be made at the discretion of the treating
      physician per usual care and are not mandated by study design or protocol. Informed consent
      will be obtained from eligible patients prior to study entry.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Molecular testing of tumors, using techniques such as next-generation sequencing (NGS),
      facilitates an individualized approach to cancer treatment by sub-classifying diseases on an
      individual basis. Physicians can utilize an in depth understanding of disease at a molecular
      level to optimize therapy by selecting the most appropriate drugs and therapeutic targets.
      Genomic profiling has identified multiple genomic aberrations that are predictive markers for
      treatment response with targeted therapeutics.

      FoundationOne™ is a commercially available molecular diagnostics test, for all solid tumor
      types, that analyzes routine clinical specimens for somatic alterations in relevant
      cancer-related genes. This validated in vitro diagnostic test, is performed in a single
      Clinical Laboratory Improvement Amendments (CLIA) certified and College of American
      Pathologists (CAP) approved laboratory at Foundation Medicine, Inc. It provides
      individualized, potentially actionable information regarding a patient's molecular cancer
      subtype that can be used by physicians to tailor treatment options.

      With the recent commercial availability of the FoundationOne™ test, knowledge gaps exist
      regarding practice patterns associated with the use of this test in routine clinical practice
      and the impact of this test on clinical decision making. There is limited information
      regarding physician and patient characteristics that determine which patients receive the
      test, rationale for patient selection, and how physicians interpret and use the test results.
      Findings from this study will help to optimize patient selection and maximize the clinical
      impact of the test in terms of guiding therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>1 Year</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite characterization of current real-world practice patterns in the use of the FoundationOne™ test and the effect of the FoundationOne™ test on clinical decision making across the US</measure>
    <time_frame>Minimum 1 year follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Characterization of practice patterns for the use of the test described by:
Provider and site characteristics of patients receiving the FoundationOne test
Socio-demographic and clinical characteristics of patients receiving the FoundationOne test
Examination of the effect of the test on clinical decision making by describing:
Subsequent treatment patterns for patients after receipt of test results
Clinician report outcomes regarding how test results guided clinical decision making</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory endpoints describing clinical outcomes in the study population</measure>
    <time_frame>Minimum 1 year follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival
1-year survival
Overall progression-free survival (PFS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">510</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Neoplasm Metastasis</condition>
  <condition>Tumor</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FoundationOne™ Test Ordered</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients for whom a FoundationOne™ test was ordered and a report is delivered.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        This Pilot Study will aim to enroll approximately 500 patients from a total of 40 oncology
        centers in the US over a 1-year time period. Any patient for whom the treating physician
        has ordered the FoundationOne test is eligible for inclusion in the study. In order to
        capture real-world treatment patterns, site recruitment will aim to include approximately
        80% of sites (and 80% of patients) from the community oncology setting. Enrollment will be
        competitive and each site will be capped at a maximum of 15 patients.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        The FoundationOne test was ordered by the treating physician under routine clinical
        practice

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  Patient willing and able to provide informed consent

          -  Informed consent date is at least one day prior to the FoundationOne test report date

        Exclusion Criteria:

        There are no exclusion criteria for this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gary Palmer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sr VP Medical Afairs</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Evergreen Hematology/Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spokane</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>99218</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 6, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 8, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 10, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 8, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 8, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 9, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>genomics</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>registry</keyword>
  <keyword>neoplasm metastasis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

