<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01855659</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-HAL-EL-36</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01855659</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Single-center Study to Assess Peak Inspiratory Flow (PIF) in Different Stages' COPD Patients by Using the In-check Method.</brief_title>
  <acronym>INSPIRE</acronym>
  <official_title>A Single-center Study to Assess Peak Inspiratory Flow (PIF) in Different Stages' COPD Patients by Using the In-check Method.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Elpen Pharmaceutical Co. Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Elpen Pharmaceutical Co. Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Peak Inspiratory Flow Rate (PIFR) is defined by the fastest flow rate noted during the
      inspiratory cycle.

      Inhaled medication plays an important role in the treatment of chronic obstructive pulmonary
      disease (COPD), with dry powder inhalers (DPIs) increasingly replacing metered dose inhalers
      (MDIs). DPIs are interesting as they do not require the need for coordinate actuation of the
      MDI device with inhalation or the use of a large spacer device 1-3. Several DPIs are
      available for the administration of inhaled corticosteroids, as well as bronchodilators, with
      each of them corresponding to a different type of inhaler (e.g. Diskus®, Turbuhaler®,
      Aeroliser®, etc.). During the inspiratory effort the patient generates a pressure drop with a
      consequent airflow across the DPI. This inspiratory flow has to be high enough to
      disaggregate and adequately disperse the drug powder into an aerosol cloud of drug particles
      and to guarantee an optimal deposition of the medication in the lung. Such peak inspiratory
      flows (PIFs) are not only dependent on a patient's inhalation effort but also on the internal
      resistance of the device.

      It has been shown that optimal deposition of medication with DPIs is not achieved in some
      patients with low inspiratory flow rates, such as children or patients with COPD, especially
      during acute exacerbations. In such conditions the use of a DPI with low internal resistance
      has been suggested, ensuring an optimal deposition despite the lower flow rate. In addition,
      many clinicians are nowadays confronted with an important number of COPD patients who are
      aged &gt;70 yrs
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will assess the inspiratory flow rates at high levels of resistance in different
      stages of COPD patients. PIF will be measured by in-check method.

      Commonly used for Asthma patients, the In-Check Oral Inspiratory Flow Meter is a portable
      hand-held inspiratory flow meter that provides an assessment of the speed of inhalation. The
      In-Check Oral measures inspiratory flow between 30 and 370 L/min, inspiratory flow is thought
      of by physicians as a sensitive marker for Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)
      screening. The In-Check Oral works when a patient inhales through the mouth, this will cause
      air to be drawn through the meter and a cursor moves along the scale to indicate the speed of
      inhalation. The flow rate achieved can be noted by checking the position of the cursor
      against the calibrated scale. The Standard In-Check Oral inspiratory flow meter can measure
      inspiratory flow rates in the range 30 to 370 l/min, with an accuracy of +/- 10% or 10 l/min
      (whichever is the greater). (A Low Range In-Check Oral Inspiratory flow meter is available by
      special request, measuring between 15 and 120 l/min).

      All In-Check Oral meters are calibrated using an ATS pulmonary waveform generator, and the
      product complies with the Australian and New Zealand standards for back pressure in flow
      meters. As with any inhalation device checking for loose foreign objects is important. The
      transparent body of the In-Check Oral meter is designed to allow a visual inspection before
      use. The meter is manufactured from medical grade components, and is suitable for multiple
      patient uses when cleaned appropriately between patients. The expected life of the In-Check
      Oral, in normal use, is two years.

      Commonly used for Asthma patients, the In-Check Oral Inspiratory Flow Meter is a portable
      hand-held inspiratory flow meter that provides an assessment of the speed of inhalation. The
      In-Check Oral measures inspiratory flow between 30 and 370 L/min, inspiratory flow is thought
      of by physicians as a sensitive marker for Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)
      screening. The In-Check Oral works when a patient inhales through the mouth, this will cause
      air to be drawn through the meter and a cursor moves along the scale to indicate the speed of
      inhalation. The flow rate achieved can be noted by checking the position of the cursor
      against the calibrated scale. The Standard In-Check Oral inspiratory flow meter can measure
      inspiratory flow rates in the range 30 to 370 l/min, with an accuracy of +/- 10% or 10 l/min
      (whichever is the greater). (A Low Range In-Check Oral Inspiratory flow meter is available by
      special request, measuring between 15 and 120 l/min).

      All In-Check Oral meters are calibrated using an ATS pulmonary waveform generator, and the
      product complies with the Australian and New Zealand standards for back pressure in flow
      meters. As with any inhalation device checking for loose foreign objects is important. The
      transparent body of the In-Check Oral meter is designed to allow a visual inspection before
      use. The meter is manufactured from medical grade components, and is suitable for multiple
      patient use when cleaned appropriately between patients. The expected life of the In-Check
      Oral, in normal use, is two years.

      Commonly used for Asthma patients, the In-Check Oral Inspiratory Flow Meter is a portable
      hand-held inspiratory flow meter that provides an assessment of the speed of inhalation. The
      In-Check Oral measures inspiratory flow between 30 and 370 L/min, inspiratory flow is thought
      of by physicians as a sensitive marker for Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD)
      screening. The In-Check Oral works when a patient inhales through the mouth, this will cause
      air to be drawn through the meter and a cursor moves along the scale to indicate the speed of
      inhalation. The flow rate achieved can be noted by checking the position of the cursor
      against the calibrated scale. The Standard In-Check Oral inspiratory flow meter can measure
      inspiratory flow rates in the range 30 to 370 l/min, with an accuracy of +/- 10% or 10 l/min
      (whichever is the greater). (A Low Range In-Check Oral Inspiratory flow meter is available by
      special request, measuring between 15 and 120 l/min).

        -  All In-Check Oral meters are calibrated using an ATS pulmonary waveform generator, and
           the product complies with the Australian and New Zealand standards for back pressure in
           flow meters. As with any inhalation device checking for loose foreign objects is
           important. The transparent body of the In-Check Oral meter is designed to allow a visual
           inspection before use. The meter is manufactured from medical grade components, and is
           suitable for multiple patient use when cleaned appropriately between patients. The
           expected life of the In-Check Oral, in normal use, is two Accurately measures oral
           inspiratory flow rate (peak and sub-maximal) in order to assess suitability for inhaled
           medication

        -  Measures nasal inspiratory flow for assessing nasal airway patency

        -  Assesses response to nasal provocation

        -  Allows home monitoring of Peak Nasal Inspiratory Flow (PNIF)

        -  Easy to use, clean and reset, the In-Check helps patients maintain their respiratory
           health.

        -  High-quality medical-grade stainless steel and plastic construction

        -  Sterilizable plastic mouthpiece accepts different mask sizes

        -  Simple enough for home patient use, rugged enough for routine clinic use.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PIF measurements in COPD</measure>
    <time_frame>0 (baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>Values of PIF measurement in COPD stages' subgroups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PIF measurement in COPD per age and gender</measure>
    <time_frame>0 (baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>Values of PIF measurement in COPD patients per age and gender</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">210</enrollment>
  <condition>Pulmonary Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>COPD patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who are stratified in the subgroups of COPD based on the severity: stages II, III, IV</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        COPD patients belonging in Stages II, II, IV
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  COPD patients (Global Initiative of Chronic Lung Disease (GOLD) definition

          -  COPD stage II, III, IV

          -  Patients who are followed in Outpatients' Unit

          -  Patients &gt;50 years of age

          -  Patients who accept PIF to be measured using the In-Check Inhaler

          -  Patients who have signed the Informed Consent

          -  Patients who will comply with study demands and procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  COPD stage I patients

          -  Patients who are hospitalized

          -  Patients &lt;50 years of age

          -  Patients who do not accept PIF to be measured using the In-Check Inhaler

          -  Patients who have not signed the Informed Consent

          -  Patients who face problems in order to comply with study demands and procedures
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eleftherios Zervas, M.D</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Coordinator of Asthma Working Group of Hellenic Thoracic Society</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>7th Pulmonary Dept, Athens Chest Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Athens</city>
        <state>Mesogion Ave. 152</state>
        <zip>Athens 11527</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Greece</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Melissinos CG, Mead J. Maximum expiratory flow changes induced by longitudinal tension on trachea in normal subjects. J Appl Physiol Respir Environ Exerc Physiol. 1977 Sep;43(3):537-44.</citation>
    <PMID>914724</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malik SK, Jindal SK, Jindal V, Bansal S. Peak expiratory flow rate in healthy adults. Indian J Chest Dis. 1975 Oct;17(4):166-71.</citation>
    <PMID>1218939</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Potter WA, Olafsson S, Hyatt RE. Ventilatory mechanics and expiratory flow limitation during exercise in patients with obstructive lung disease. J Clin Invest. 1971 Apr;50(4):910-9.</citation>
    <PMID>5547281</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwela D. Air pollution and health in urban areas. Rev Environ Health. 2000 Jan-Jun;15(1-2):13-42. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10939084</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Singh V, Khandelwal R, Gupta AB. Effect of air pollution on peak expiratory flow rate variability. J Asthma. 2003 Feb;40(1):81-6.</citation>
    <PMID>12699215</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Njoku CH, Anah CO. Reference values for peak expiratory flow rate in adults of African descent. Trop Doct. 2004 Jul;34(3):135-40.</citation>
    <PMID>15267038</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Quanjer PH, Lebowitz MD, Gregg I, Miller MR, Pedersen OF. Peak expiratory flow: conclusions and recommendations of a Working Party of the European Respiratory Society. Eur Respir J Suppl. 1997 Feb;24:2S-8S. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9098701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elebute EA, Femi-Pearse D. Peak flow rate in Nigeria: anthropometric determinants and usefulness in assessment of ventilatory function. Thorax. 1971 Sep;26(5):597-601.</citation>
    <PMID>5134061</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Onadeko BO, Iyun AO, Sofowora EO, Adamu SO. Peak expiratory flow rate in normal Nigerian children. Afr J Med Med Sci. 1984 Mar-Jun;13(1-2):25-32.</citation>
    <PMID>6087636</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 14, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 15, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 16, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 2, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 2, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 3, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lung diseases,</keyword>
  <keyword>Obstructive,</keyword>
  <keyword>Peak Inspiratory Flow</keyword>
  <keyword>[C08.381.495.389]</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Aspiration</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

