<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01859559</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PIV-RCT-ED</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01859559</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluate Initial Success Rate of Ultrasound Guided Versus Landmark Approach For Peripheral Intravenous Access</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial To Compare The Initial Success Rate of Ultrasound Guided Versus Landmark Approach For Placement of Peripheral Intravenous Access Lines in Emergency Department Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>George Washington University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>George Washington University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this randomized controlled trial (RCT) is to compare the success
      rate of obtaining peripheral vascular access with ultrasound guidance versus the traditional,
      landmark approach among patients with varying degrees of intravenous access difficulty. In
      addition to comparing overall initial success rates of the two methods, we will also compare
      the success rates by degree of intravenous access difficulty (3 main subject subgroups) and
      by operator experience (approximately 20 emergency department technicians).

      The main hypothesis is that the initial success rate will be significantly higher (5% or
      greater) for ultrasound guided peripheral intravenous access compared to landmark approach
      among patients who are judged to have difficult intravenous access but no significant
      difference (i.e. &lt; 5%) among patients judged to have easy intravenous access.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized controlled trial with a two group parallel design that will compare the
      initial success rate of peripheral intravenous line (PIV) placement between the traditional,
      landmark approach versus ultrasound guided. Emergency department (ED) patients who are in a
      treatment room and require a PIV line are eligible for the study. For those who are eligible,
      the ED technician and an ED nurse will each complete a clinical data sheet that documents the
      degree of IV access difficulty.

      For those who enroll, the research assistant (RA) will randomize the subject to one of two
      treatment groups: (1) ultrasound guided or; (2) landmark approach. The ED technician will
      perform the PIV placement based on the treatment group assigned through the randomization
      process. The RA will be present during the PIV placement and will ask the patient prior to
      the procedure about factors that may influence IV access (i.e. self-reported weight and
      height, presence of chronic conditions). The RA will also document the ED outcomes of the
      procedure (i.e. duration of procedure, success or failure, complications of procedure) and
      query the patient on the extent of discomfort associated with the procedure. Finally, for
      those subjects who are admitted to the hospital, a RA will conduct follow-up on the PIV line
      to determine how long it is used on the ward and the reason for taking it out (i.e. no longer
      needed, infection, infiltration, fell out, etc). It is hospital policy that PIV lines be
      changed every 72 hours to prevent infection so we anticipate that the maximum follow-up of
      each ED PIV line placed will be 72 hours.

      There are two treatment groups, the ultrasound guided treatment group and the traditional,
      landmark group. For both treatment groups, a tourniquet will be placed above the upper
      extremity vein chosen for cannulation. For the landmark approach, the ED technician will use
      standard anatomical landmarks and palpation to puncture the skin and insert the IV line. If
      the patient is randomized to the ultrasound group, the operator will use ultrasound to help
      visualize the vein and direct line placement. When using ultrasound, the ED technicians will
      employ a one-person technique. For both treatment groups, if the first attempt fails, we will
      randomize the subject again to one of the two treatment arms. We are randomizing a second
      time because failure at first attempt is a good marker of the difficulty of the procedure. By
      randomizing a second time, we will be able to determine whether either method is superior
      after one failed attempt. After the second failed attempt, the ED technician can use whatever
      method he/she chooses to place the line.

      Because of the nature of the intervention, this RCT is unblinded.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Initial success rate</measure>
    <time_frame>immediatetely after first attempt, average attempt takes 15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>A successful cannulation (blood return or ability to infuse intravenous fluid without infiltration) on initial percutaneous needle puncture.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Any complications associated with the PIV line</measure>
    <time_frame>within ED visit, average ED length of stay is 6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of infiltration, arterial puncture, or nerve puncture</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Numeric Rating of Pain Associated with insertion of PIV line</measure>
    <time_frame>within 5 minutes of final PIV placement, average placement take &lt; 30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Patient-reported measure of pain associated with the insertion of the PIV line using the Numeric Rating Scale.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1189</enrollment>
  <condition>Patients With Peripheral Intravenous Access Lines</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Easy Access</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will included emergency department patients that are judged to have easy intravenous access in at least one of the upper extremities by the ED technician.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Difficult Access By Clinician Judgment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will include patients that at least one vein is visible or palpable in one of the upper extremities but either the ED technician and/or ED nurse judges the patient to have difficult intravenous access.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non visible and Non palpable</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This arm will include patients for whom neither the ED technician nor an ED nurse can identify a visible or palpable vein that is suitable for an intravenous access line in either upper extremity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ultrasound-guided peripheral intravenous access line placement</intervention_name>
    <description>The ED technician will use an ultrasound machine with a vascular probe to visualize the vein and guide the PIV line using a one-operator dynamic technique.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Easy Access</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Difficult Access By Clinician Judgment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non visible and Non palpable</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Landmark Approach to peripheral intravenous access line placement</intervention_name>
    <description>ED technician will use standard anatomical landmarks and palpation to puncture the skin and insert the peripheral intravenous access line in the upper extremity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Easy Access</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Difficult Access By Clinician Judgment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Non visible and Non palpable</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  peripheral venous (PIV) access line ordered by a physician during their emergency
             department visit.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-English or non-spanish speaking

          -  already enrolled in a different study during the ED visit

          -  too sick, patient requires intravenous access quickly and can not take the time to
             enroll in study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Melissa L McCarthy, ScD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>George Washington University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hamid Shokoohi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>George Washington University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>George Washington University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heinrichs J, Fritze Z, Vandermeer B, Klassen T, Curtis S. Ultrasonographically guided peripheral intravenous cannulation of children and adults: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Ann Emerg Med. 2013 Apr;61(4):444-454.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.annemergmed.2012.11.014. Epub 2013 Feb 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23415740</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 16, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 20, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 22, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 11, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 11, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 13, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>George Washington University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Melissa McCarthy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>peripheral intravenous access</keyword>
  <keyword>operator experience</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

