<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01856712</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012-0702</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01856712</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Oral vs. Injectable Naltrexone for Hospitalized Veterans With Alcohol Dependence</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pharmacotherapeutic Intervention to Improve Treatment Engagement Among Alcohol-dependent Veterans After Hospital Discharge</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin, Madison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Wisconsin, Madison</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The over-arching goal of the proposed project is to understand the impact of medication
      adherence upon engagement in behavioral treatment for alcohol use disorders. The proposed
      project is a pilot feasibility study of inpatient veterans with problem alcohol use at the
      William S. Middleton VA Hospital (Madison, WI). Participants will be randomized to one of two
      parallel study conditions: (1) an initial 50 mg oral dose of naltrexone prior to hospital
      discharge plus a 30-day prescription for oral naltrexone, or (2) a single 380 mg
      intramuscular injection of naltrexone administered prior to discharge and a second injection
      one month later. The central hypothesis is that hospital-administered injectable naltrexone,
      when compared to daily oral naltrexone taken at home, will reduce alcohol use in the days
      immediately following hospitalization. Injectable naltrexone has been efficacious vs. placebo
      in addition to behavioral treatment in several studies. However, it has yet to be examined in
      head-to-head comparison with oral naltrexone, or in the hospital setting as an intervention
      that might facilitate behavioral treatment follow up after discharge.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The proposed project is a pilot feasibility study of inpatient veterans with problem alcohol
      use at the William S. Middleton VA Hospital. The over-arching goal is to understand the
      impact of medication adherence upon engagement in behavioral treatment for alcohol use
      disorders. Participants will be randomized to one of two parallel study conditions: (1) an
      initial 50 mg oral dose of naltrexone prior to hospital discharge plus a 30-day prescription
      for oral naltrexone, or (2) a single 380 mg intramuscular injection of naltrexone (duration
      of action = 30 days) administered prior to discharge followed by a second injection one month
      later. The central hypothesis is that hospital-administered, long-acting injectable
      naltrexone, when compared to daily oral naltrexone, will reduce alcohol use in the days
      immediately following hospitalization. This reduced consumption, we hypothesize, will be
      followed by improved engagement in substance abuse treatment.

      Primary Aim: Demonstrate the feasibility of the proposed recruitment methods and study
      design. This aim comprises two measures with corresponding goals: (1)
      Recruitment/enrollment—with a recruitment goal of 50 eligible and consenting subjects in an 8
      month time period, and (2) Follow-up data collection with a goal of post-hospitalization
      follow-up data on no less than 70% of enrolled subjects.

      Secondary Aims: As a pilot feasibility study, we may not anticipate sufficient power to
      attain statistical significance on patient-oriented outcome measures. However, it will be
      important for us to consider and to evaluate pertinent outcomes and potential moderators in
      order to (1) develop and fine-tune study design, and (2) determine effect sizes for primary
      outcomes so that we may calculate appropriate sample sizes for future larger study. As such,
      the secondary aims for the current study are:

        1. To compare injectable naltrexone study to oral naltrexone in terms of attendance to
           recommended outpatient substance abuse treatment. We hypothesize that injectable
           naltrexone will be associated with improved likelihood of attending initial visits for
           substance abuse treatment.

        2. To compare treatment attendance in adherent vs. non-adherent patients in the oral
           naltrexone condition. Adherence will be defined as taking ≥ 80% of daily naltrexone
           doses determined via pill counts. We hypothesize that, while controlling for addiction
           severity, mental illness measures, and motivation to change, adherence to daily oral
           naltrexone will predict treatment engagement following hospital discharge.

        3. To compare study arms in terms of ongoing alcohol consumption. We hypothesize that (1)
           improved medication adherence in the oral naltrexone arm and (2) assignment to
           injectable naltrexone will be associated with reduced alcohol consumption (number of
           heavy drinking days in the past 14 days) following hospital discharge.

      Exploratory Aims will involve the examination of the relationships between study outcomes and
      (1) disorders prevalent in the veteran population (post-traumatic stress disorder, anxiety,
      depression, and traumatic brain injury) and (2) stigma related to alcohol dependence.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Demonstrate the feasibility of the proposed recruitment methods and study design. This aim comprises two measures with corresponding goals: (1) Recruitment/enrollment—with a recruitment goal of 50 eligible and consenting subjects in an 8 month time period, and (2) Follow-up data collection with a goal of post-hospitalization follow-up data on no less than 70% of enrolled subjects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Outpatient treatment attendance</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare injectable naltrexone study to oral naltrexone in terms of attendance to recommended outpatient substance abuse treatment. We hypothesize that injectable naltrexone will be associated with improved likelihood of attending initial visits for substance abuse treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication adherence</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare treatment attendance in adherent vs. non-adherent patients in the oral naltrexone condition. Adherence will be defined as taking ≥ 80% of daily naltrexone doses determined via pill counts. We hypothesize that, while controlling for addiction severity, mental illness measures, and motivation to change, adherence to daily oral naltrexone will predict treatment engagement following hospital discharge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ongoing alcohol consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare study arms in terms of ongoing alcohol consumption. We hypothesize that (1) improved medication adherence in the oral naltrexone arm and (2) assignment to injectable naltrexone will be associated with reduced alcohol consumption (number of heavy drinking days in the past 14 days) following hospital discharge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Alcohol Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>oral naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>an initial 50 mg oral dose of naltrexone prior to hospital discharge plus a 30-day prescription for oral naltrexone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>injectable naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>a single 380 mg intramuscular injection of naltrexone (duration of action = 30 days)prior to hospital discharge followed by a second injection one month later.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Naltrexone</intervention_name>
    <description>Naltexone was chosen for this study because naltrexone is the only medication available in both oral daily and injectable monthly formulations, which will allow the study to examine issues around medication adherence.</description>
    <arm_group_label>oral naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>injectable naltrexone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Revia, Vivitrol</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years or older

          -  diagnostic criteria for alcohol dependence or abuse

          -  women of childbearing potential who have a negative screening urine pregnancy test and
             are willing to use reliable birth control methods throughout the duration of the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  active or recently active (less than 1 year) opioid dependence or daily use of opioid
             analgesics

          -  acute hepatitis or liver failure

          -  pregnancy

          -  women who are currently breastfeeding

          -  active suicidality

          -  inability to provide written informed consent as determined by study comprehension
             questions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Randall T Brown, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Madison</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin - Department of Family Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53715</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 14, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 14, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 17, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 5, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>alcohol</keyword>
  <keyword>veterans</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alcoholism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ethanol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Naltrexone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>May 14, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

