<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01855451</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TROG 12.01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ACTRN12613000279729</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01855451</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Weekly Cetuximab/RT Versus Weekly Cisplatin/RT in HPV-Associated Oropharyngeal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>HPVOropharynx</acronym>
  <official_title>TROG12.01 A Randomised Trial of Weekly Cetuximab and Radiation Versus Weekly Cisplatin and Radiation in Good Prognosis Locoregionally Advanced HPV-Associated Oropharyngeal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Trans-Tasman Radiation Oncology Group (TROG)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Trans-Tasman Radiation Oncology Group (TROG)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A standard treatment for patients with head and neck cancer is radiation given with high
      doses of a chemotherapy drug called cisplatin, given every 3 weeks during the radiation. This
      treatment is effective but can significantly increase side effects such as difficulty with
      swallowing, a sore mouth, fatigue, hearing loss, ringing in the ears and kidney failure. In
      Australia, a commonly used treatment HPV-Associated Oropharyngeal Squamous Cell Carcinoma is
      a lower dose of cisplatin given weekly during the radiation. The high dose and low dose
      schedules result in a similar total dose of cisplatin being given during the radiation, but
      it is thought that the weekly schedule results in fewer side effects while maintaining
      effectiveness.

      Another approach widely used around the world for patients with head and neck cancer, is to
      administer the antibody, cetuximab, weekly during radiation. Cetuximab has a very different
      side effect profile to cisplatin, and has been reported to result in less exacerbation of
      radiation related side effects. Both cetuximab and cisplatin can reduce the growth of a
      cancer and increase the effectiveness of radiation. Both cisplatin and cetuximab appear to be
      effective treatments in combination with radiation, but have not been directly compared.

      The purpose of this study is to compare the treatment related side effects (both acute and
      longer term) between the cisplatin and cetuximab regimens. Both treatments would be given
      with the same dose of radiation therapy over 7 weeks. The results of this trial will help
      determine the optimal treatment for patients with HPV-Associated Oropharyngeal Squamous Cell
      Carcinoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Human Papilloma Virus (HPV)-associated oropharyngeal squamous cell carcinoma (OPSCC) is
      increasing in incidence and has an improved prognosis compared to other head and neck
      malignancies when treated with standard combination chemoradiation.

      The current standard regimen of high dose cisplatin and Radiation Therapy (RT) for head and
      neck cancer patients results in significant toxicity and is at the limits of tolerance. The
      excellent prognosis of patients with HPV-positive OPSCC raises concerns about overtreatment
      with the current standard of care, resulting in unnecessary acute and late morbidity.

      Therefore, investigation of chemo-sparing or chemo-modified regimens with RT for
      HPV-associated OPSCC that do not compromise efficacy is warranted. A number of regimens less
      intensive than high dose cisplatin are being used in clinical practice for patients with good
      prognosis HPV OPSCC, but no comparative trials have been performed in this population. The
      trial population will be restricted to low risk HPV-associated OPSCC.

      Trial Arms:

      A- RT (70 Gy in 35 fractions, 5 days a week over 7 weeks) with weekly Cetuximab (400 mg/m2
      loading dose IV prior to radiation, followed by weekly cetuximab 250 mg/m2 for the duration
      of the radiotherapy) B- RT(70 Gy in 35 fractions, 5 days a week over 7 weeks) with weekly
      Cisplatin (40 mg/m2 IV for the duration of the radiotherapy)

      Hypothesis: In patients with locally advanced HPV-associated OPSCC, those treated with weekly
      cetuximab and conventionally fractionated radiotherapy will experience less acute symptom
      severity than patients receiving weekly cisplatin and conventionally fractionated
      radiotherapy.

      Patients will be followed weekly during treatment, then at 1, 3, 5, 9, 13 weeks
      post-treatment and at months 6, 9, 12, 15, 18, 21, 24, 28, 32, 36, 42, 48, 54, and 60
      post-completion of treatment. Follow-up for the trial will cease when the last patient
      accrued has a minimum of 2 years follow-up i.e. has attended the 24 months post-treatment
      review.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 3, 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom Severity</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The area under curve of symptom severity between weekly cisplatin and Radiotherapy Therapy (RT) versus weekly cetuximab and RT from baseline to week 20 (13 weeks post-completion of radiotherapy) as measured by M.D. Anderson Symptom Inventory - Head and Neck Module (MDASI-HN).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptom severity</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Symptom severity measured by MDASI-HN (Symptom Interference Score, Symptom Score, Symptom Clusters and individual item scores at individual time points)and by Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy - Head and Neck (FACT-HN).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Interference of symptoms with daily life</measure>
    <time_frame>24 mths</time_frame>
    <description>To compare interference of symptoms with daily life using the MDASI-HN Symptom Interference Score and Quality adjusted life years (QALYs) using the EQ-5D-5L</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychological distress</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare psychological distress measured by FACT-HN domain scores and depression and anxiety scales of Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact on Health Related Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Swallowing dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare swallowing dysfunction by Functional swallowing outcome (video fluoroscopy), CTCAE (v4.0) dysphagia, MDASI and FACT questionnaires, enteral feeding rates.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Speech and dietary function</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare speech and dietary function as measured by the Performance Status Scale for Head &amp; Neck Cancer Patients (PSS-HN)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinician-assessed acute and late toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>60 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare clinician-assessed acute and late toxicity using toxicity grading (CTCAE v4.0) - reported as worst toxicity and as overall acute toxicity burden (T-score)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of enteral feeding</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare rate of enteral feeding at 12 months following treatment using Barnard's exact test for the comparison of two proportions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hearing impairment</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare hearing impairment, as measured by total score of the Hearing Handicap Inventory for adults, screening version (HHIA-S) and audiometry (results will be evaluated according to CTCAE 3 and 4 criteria, Brock criteria, Chang criteria and SIOP Boston Ototoxicity Scale).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to locoregional failure</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare time to locoregional failure primarily determined by evidence of progression or recurrence clinically or radiologically</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Failure-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare failure-free survival by clinical and radioloigical assessments</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>60 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare overall survival by clinical assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pattern of disease failure</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Pattern of disease failure (locoregional [recurrence at primary tumour site and/or regional nodes], distant, both) as assessed radiologically.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>20 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To compare FDG-PET-CT complete response rate at week 20</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost of health resource utilisation</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare cost of health resource utilisation via questionnaires EQ-5D-5L and RTOG return to work questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Work status and time to return to work</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>To compare work status and time to return to work by RTOG questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Potential prognostic markers</measure>
    <time_frame>60 months</time_frame>
    <description>To correlate several potential prognostic markers (including but not limited to EGFR protein level, EGFR copy number, ERCC1, plasma hepatocyte growth factor level, and plasma IL-8) with failure-free survival, overall survival and time to locoregional failure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>HPV Positive Oropharyngeal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Radiation Therapy + Cetuximab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>RT (70 Gy in 35 fractions, 5 days a week over 7 weeks) with weekly Cetuximab (400 mg/m2 loading dose IV prior to radiation, followed by weekly cetuximab 250 mg/m2 for the duration of the radiotherapy)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Radiation Therapy + Cisplatin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>RT(70 Gy in 35 fractions, 5 days a week over 7 weeks) with weekly Cisplatin (40 mg/m2 IV for the duration of the radiotherapy)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cetuximab</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Radiation Therapy + Cetuximab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RT (70 Gy in 35 fractions)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Radiation Therapy + Cetuximab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Radiation Therapy + Cisplatin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Radiation Therapy + Cisplatin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Aged 18 years or older

          2. Has provided written Informed Consent for participation in this trial

          3. Histologically confirmed squamous cell carcinoma of the oropharynx with p16 positive
             status confirmed locally by immunohistochemistry

          4. Stage III (excluding T1-2N1) or stage IV (excluding T4, N3, and distant metastasis) if
             smoking history of &lt; /=10 pack years. If &gt; 10 pack years nodal disease must be N0 -
             N2a.

          5. If an excisional biopsy has been performed, patients remain eligible for the study
             provided there is clinically measurable disease prior to commencing RT. The residual
             disease should still meet the stage criteria required for the trial e.g. excisional
             biopsy of a node with residual T3 primary, or tonsillectomy for T1 primary with
             residual &gt; N2a nodes.

          6. No prior treatment for oropharyngeal cancer

          7. Adequate haematological, renal, and hepatic function as defined by,

               1. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC, segs + bands) &gt; /= 1.5 x 109/L

               2. Platelet count &gt; /= 100 x 109/L

               3. Total bilirubin &lt; /= 1.5 x upper normal limit

               4. ALT &lt; /= 2.5 x upper normal limit

               5. Calculated creatinine clearance (Cockcroft-Gault formula) or isotopic GFR &gt;
                  55ml/min

          8. ECOG performance status score of 0-1

          9. Participants capable of childbearing are using adequate contraception and intend to
             continue use of contraception for at least 6 months following completion of treatment

         10. Negative pregnancy test within 72 hours prior to randomisation of women who are of
             childbearing potential

         11. Suitable for follow-up for at least 24 months as per trial protocol.

         12. Sufficient proficiency in English, cognitive capacity and willingness to complete
             questionnaires

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of unknown primary of the head and neck

          2. T4, N3 or distant metastases

          3. Smoking history &gt;10 pack years with N2b or c nodal status

          4. Women who are pregnant or lactating.

          5. Previous radiotherapy to the area to be treated (excluding superficial radiotherapy
             for a cutaneous malignancy)

          6. Previous cisplatin or carboplatin chemotherapy

          7. Prior EGFR targeted therapy of any kind

          8. Primary surgery to the affected area (excisional biopsy allowed)

          9. Peripheral neuropathy &gt; /= grade 2 (CTCAE v4.0)

         10. Sensori-neural hearing impairment &gt;= grade 2 (CTCAE v4.0, hearing impaired, not
             enrolled on a monitoring program) which may be exacerbated by cisplatin (Audiometric
             abnormalities without corresponding clinical deafness will not be grounds for
             exclusion)

         11. Tinnitus &gt; /= grade 2 (CTCAE v4.0)

         12. History of interstitial lung disease or evidence of interstitial lung disease on
             pre-registration CT

         13. History of myocardial infarction within 12 months prior to study entry, uncontrolled
             congestive heart failure, unstable angina, active cardiomyopathy, unstable arrhythmia,
             uncontrolled psychotic disorders, active serious infections, active peptic ulcer
             disease, immunosuppression due to post-organ transplantation or use of
             immunosuppressants for autoimmune disorders

         14. Patients known to be HIV positive

         15. Other cancer that was diagnosed:

               1. more than 5 years prior to current diagnosis with (i) subsequent evidence of
                  disease recurrence or (ii) clinical expectation of recurrence is greater than 10%
                  or

               2. within 5 years of the current diagnosis, with the exception of successfully
                  treated basal cell or squamous cell skin carcinoma, in situ melanoma, or
                  carcinoma in situ of the cervix
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>D Rischin, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>TROG and Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Anetta Matera</last_name>
    <phone>+61 3 9656 3661</phone>
    <email>ania.matera@petermac.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Canberra Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Canberra</city>
        <state>Australian Capital Territory</state>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrew Lee</last_name>
      <email>drandrewlee@me.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew Lee</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chris O'Brien Lifehouse</name>
      <address>
        <city>Camperdown</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2050</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mo Mo Tin</last_name>
      <email>MoMo.Tin@lh.org.au</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mo Mo Tin</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Liverpool Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2170</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dion Forstner</last_name>
      <email>Dion.Forstner@sswahs.nsw.gov.au</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dion Forstner</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St George Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>St George</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2217</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peter Graham</last_name>
      <email>Peter.Graham@SESIAHS.HEALTH.NSW.GOV.AU</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Peter Graham</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Riverina Cancer Care Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wagga Wagga</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anupam Chaudhuri</last_name>
      <email>chaudhurianupam@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Anupam Chaudhuri</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Calvary Mater Newcastle</name>
      <address>
        <city>Waratah</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chris Wratten</last_name>
      <email>chris.wratten@calvarymater.org.au</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chris Wratten</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Westmead Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Westmead</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2145</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lakmalie Perera</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lakmalie Perera</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Brisbane and Womens Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Herston</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4006</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Liz Kenny</last_name>
      <email>lizkenny@bigpond.net.au</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Liz Kenny</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Townsville Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Townsville</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4810</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Collins</last_name>
      <email>mkcset@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Collins</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Princess Alexandra Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Woolloongabba</city>
        <state>Queensland</state>
        <zip>4102</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sandro Porceddu</last_name>
      <email>sandro.porceddu@health.qld.gov.au</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sandro Porceddu</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Flinders Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bedford Park</city>
        <state>South Australia</state>
        <zip>5042</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shawgi Sukumaran</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Shawgi Sukumaran</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>East Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3002</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Danny Rischin</last_name>
      <email>danny.rischin@petermac.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Danny Rischin</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Austin Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelburg</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3084</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Morikatsu Wada</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Morikatsu Wada</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sir Charles Gairdner</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nedlands</city>
        <state>Western Australia</state>
        <zip>6009</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Colin Tang</last_name>
      <email>colin.tang@health.wa.gov.au</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Colin Tang</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Auckland City Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Auckland</city>
        <zip>1344</zip>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Andrew Macann</last_name>
      <email>amacann@adhb.govt.nz</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Andrew Macann</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Palmerston North Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palmerston</city>
        <zip>4442</zip>
        <country>New Zealand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nikolay Nedev</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nikolay Nedev</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>New Zealand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 13, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 15, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 16, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Human Papilloma Virus</keyword>
  <keyword>HPV</keyword>
  <keyword>Oropharyngeal</keyword>
  <keyword>Squamous Cell</keyword>
  <keyword>Carcinoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cetuximab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

