<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01859767</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MNI-672-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01859767</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety of MNI-672 SPECT for Detection/Exclusion of Cerebral B-amyloid in AD Subjects Compared to HVs.</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Exploratory, Open-label, Non-randomized Phase 1 Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of MNI-672 SPECT for Detection/Exclusion of Cerebral B-amyloid in Patients With Alzheimer's Disease Compared to Healthy Volunteers.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Molecular NeuroImaging</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Molecular NeuroImaging</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 1, single center, open-label, non-randomized, clinical study in probable AD
      patients and HVs to evaluate the efficacy, safety and tolerability of a single dose of
      MNI-672. The underlying goal of this study is to assess MNI-672 SPECT imaging as a tool to
      detect ß amyloid deposition in the brain of AD research participants and young healthy male
      subjects. All study procedures will be conducted at Molecular NeuroImaging (MNI) in New
      Haven, CT. Approximately 3 patients with AD and 3 young male HVs will be recruited to
      participate in this study. HVs will be screened to ensure that there is no evidence of
      cognitive decline or significant neurological deficit.

      All eligible subjects will be required to visit the study center on at least 2 occasions:

        1. for one or more screening visits which should include a history and physical
           examination, laboratory and extensive neuro-psychological testing and MRI brain
           scanning. AD subjects will also undergo Amyvid PET imaging as part of the Screening
           Visit.

        2. on one day for baseline examinations and MNI-672 administration and subsequent SPECT
           scanning- followed by safety measures
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To determine diagnostic efficacy of the MNI-672 SPECT scans in differentiating between
      patients with probable AD and HVs on the basis of neocortical tracer binding pattern, the
      SPECT scans will be visually assessed by a nuclear physician experienced in the field of
      neuro-imaging. SPECT scan findings will be classified either as abnormal (i.e., significant
      neocortical uptake in predefined regions) or as normal (i.e. no significant neocortical
      uptake in predefined regions). The visual analysis of the MNI SPECT images will be compared
      to the clinical diagnosis and Amyvid PET imaging results to determine the efficacy of MNI-672
      as an agent to detect B-amyloid. The nuclear physician evaluating the SPECT images will be
      unaware of the clinical diagnosis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Safety will be assessed by the number of participants with adverse events.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinically significant changes in vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Safety will also be assessed by any clinically significant changes in vital signs, ECG parameters, physical examination findings, clinical laboratory findings, and injection site monitoring.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total I-123 radioactivity in plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The plasma concentrations will be expressed in %ID/mL. The I-123 radioactivity will be derived from the concentration -time profile.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Standard uptake values (SUV)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Standard uptake values (SUV) for the target areas including the frontal cortex, temporal cortex, parietal cortex, posterior cingulate cortex and anterior cingulate cortex, and the cerebellum as the reference region will be calculated. Standard uptake values regional (SUVR) for cortical target areas relative to cerebellum will also be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The imaging diagnosis will be compared to the clinical diagnosis and Amyvid PET interpretation to determine the efficacy of MNI-672 as a diagnostic tool for AD.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>[123I]MNI-672 SPECT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>[123I]MNI-672 single photon emission tomography (SPECT)imaging</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>[123I]MNI-672 SPECT</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be dosed by intravenous injection to a target dose of 5 mCi and not to exceed 5.5 (not &gt;10% of 5 mCi limit) I-123 MNI-672 prior to the SPECT scan.</description>
    <arm_group_label>[123I]MNI-672 SPECT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MNI-672</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Healthy Volunteer Inclusion Criteria:

          -  is male and is 20-30 years of age (inclusive)

          -  has no evidence of cognitive impairment as indicated by a clinical dementia rating
             (CDR, [Hughes et al. 1993]) score of 0 (zero) and a score of ≥ 28 in the Mini-Mental
             Status Examination (MMSE, [Folstein et al. 1975])

          -  has MRI brain scan that has been judged as &quot;normal (age- appropriate)&quot; including ARWMC
             scale [Wahlund et al. 2001] scores supporting the lack of cerebrovascular disease
             (e.g., a white matter lesion score of 0 or 1 or 2 and a basal ganglia score of 0 or 1)

          -  has no family history of AD defined by more than 1 first-degree relative

        Alzheimer disease subject inclusion criteria:

          -  is male or female and is ≥ 50 of age, whereby females must be without childbearing
             potential (confirmed by either: age ≥ 60; or history of surgical sterilization or of
             hysterectomy, or last spontaneous bleeding at least 2 years prior to the study start)

          -  presents with positive assessment for dementia of Alzheimer's type in accordance with
             the DSM-IV-TR and probable AD according to the NINCDS-ADRDA criteria and fulfils none
             of the exclusion criteria of either

          -  does not fulfill the ICC criteria for probable DLB, the NINDS-AIREN for probable
             Vascular dementia, or the Neary [Neary et al. 1998] criteria for FTD

          -  has a CDR [Hughes et al. 1993] score of 0.5, 1 or 2

          -  MRI brain scan findings that do not reveal changes indicative of stroke and/or
             generalized cerebrovascular disease (e.g., the ARWMC scale) changes limited to: a
             white matter lesion score of 0 or 1 or 2 and a basal ganglia score of 0 or 1)

          -  has an Amyvid PET scan with moderate to frequent amyloid neuritic plaques based on
             visual interpretation

          -  has a caregiver who is willing and able to attend study visits and perform the
             psychometric tests requiring the presence of a caregiver

        Exclusion Criteria for all subjects:

          -  has any contraindication to MRI examination, e.g. metal implants or phobia

          -  is scheduled for surgery and/or another invasive procedure within the time period of
             up to 7 days following MNI-672 application

          -  is medically unstable and whose clinical course during the observation period is
             unpredictable, e.g. patients / volunteers within 14 days of myocardial infarction or
             stroke, unstable patients / volunteers with previous surgery (within 7 days), patients
             with advanced heart insufficiency (NYHA stage IV), or with acute renal failure

          -  has a history of exposure to any radiation &gt;15 mSv/year (e.g. occupational or
             radiation therapy)

          -  is receiving drug therapy or other treatment that is known to lead to greatly
             fluctuating values of the hematological or chemical laboratory parameters or to severe
             side effects (e.g. chemotherapy)

          -  has received anti-amyloid drug therapy

          -  has been previously enrolled in this study or participated in a clinical study
             involving an investigational pharmaceutical product within 30 days prior to screening,
             and/or any radiopharmaceutical within 10 radioactive half-lives prior to MNI-672
             administration

          -  has a brain tumor or other intracranial lesion, a disturbance of CSF circulation
             (e.g., normal pressure hydrocephalus) and/or a history of serious head trauma or brain
             surgery

          -  has a history, physical, laboratory or imaging findings indicative of a significant
             neurological or psychiatric illness (for patients - other than AD)

          -  has another disease that can cause disturbance of brain function (e.g. vitamin B12 or
             folic acid deficiency, disturbed thyroid function)

          -  has a history of alcohol or drug abuse
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Danna Jennings, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Molecular NeuroImaging, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Molecular NeuroImaging, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06510</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mnimaging.com</url>
    <description>Molecular NeuroImaging, LLC</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Neary D, Snowden JS, Gustafson L, Passant U, Stuss D, Black S, Freedman M, Kertesz A, Robert PH, Albert M, Boone K, Miller BL, Cummings J, Benson DF. Frontotemporal lobar degeneration: a consensus on clinical diagnostic criteria. Neurology. 1998 Dec;51(6):1546-54. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9855500</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hughes CP et al: A new clinical scale for staging of dementia. British Journal of Psychiatry 1982; 140: 566-572. Updated by Morris J: The CDR: current version and scoring rules. Neurology 1993; 43: 2412-2413</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wahlund LO, Barkhof F, Fazekas F, Bronge L, Augustin M, Sjögren M, Wallin A, Ader H, Leys D, Pantoni L, Pasquier F, Erkinjuntti T, Scheltens P; European Task Force on Age-Related White Matter Changes. A new rating scale for age-related white matter changes applicable to MRI and CT. Stroke. 2001 Jun;32(6):1318-22.</citation>
    <PMID>11387493</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 20, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 22, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 15, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 15, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 16, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Molecular NeuroImaging</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Danna Jennings</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>SPECT</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

