<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01858337</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL28886.081.09</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01858337</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mum Can I Have Vegetables Again? Development of Vegetable Preferences</brief_title>
  <acronym>VaVo</acronym>
  <official_title>Mum Can I Have Vegetables Again? Development of Vegetable Preferences.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Wageningen University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Wageningen University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      -  Rationale: Despite the health benefits, children's consumption of vegetables is below
           the recommendations. Most human food preferences are learned through mere exposure,
           imitation, and conditioning principles. During the last years, it has become clear that
           the development of food preferences starts very early in life. Furthermore, preferences
           that are learned early in life, are relatively stable and may track into adulthood.
           However, it is unclear how vegetable preferences develop from infancy until young
           childhood. In order to influence vegetable consumption, it is essential to study the
           opportunities to develop a preference for vegetable products early in childhood.

        -  Objective: The aim of this study is to investigate the effect of repeated exposure to
           vegetables compared to repeated exposure to fruit during weaning on short and long term
           vegetable and fruit intake. Furthermore, the stability of the learned fruit or vegetable
           preferences and the later food preferences are measured (i.e. vegetable, fruits,
           sweets).

        -  Study design:

      In this longitudinal study we will measure the development of preferences for a particular
      vegetable or fruit type within 4 to 6 months old subjects, during a 19 day exposure period to
      fruit or vegetables (of which 9 days exposure to the target fruit or vegetable) and 6 months
      after this exposure period. In addition, we compare the food preferences (fruit, vegetable,
      sweet foods in general), after 6 months, between infants who were weaned with a variety of
      fruits and infants who were weaned with a variety of vegetables.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Vegetable and fruit intake</measure>
    <time_frame>At the first 19 days of weaning (4-6 months of age)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in Vegetable and fruit intake from before to after the repeated exposure to it. Measured at day 1 and 2 and day 17 and 18 at the intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intake of the target Vegetables and fruits at 12 months of age.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after the intervention. Mean age 12 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Vegetable and fruit intake at 12 months of age. Measured in the lab. Fruit group received apple, plum and green beans at 3 different days</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Green beans and Apple intake at 23 months of age.</measure>
    <time_frame>when infants are 23 months of age</time_frame>
    <description>Green beans and Apple intake at 23 months of age.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vegetable and in fruit intake after the repeated exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>After the repeated exposure period during the first 19 days of weaning</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in vegetable intake between vegetable and fruit groups and in fruit intake between the vegetable and fruit groups. Vegetable intake is measured on day 17 and 18 in the vegetable groups and in the fruit groups at day 19 (when fruit groups gets the first vegetable.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">101</enrollment>
  <condition>Vegetable Intake After Weaning With Vegetables or Fruits</condition>
  <condition>Fruit Intake After Weaning With Vegetables or Fruits</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>green beans group,</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>1 of the 2 vegetable groups. The infants were weaned only with vegetables. With green beans every other day and another vegetable on the days in between.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Artichoke group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>1 of the 2 vegetable groups. The infants were weaned only with vegetables. With Artichoke every other day and another vegetable on the days in between</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Apple group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>1 of the 2 fruit groups. The infants were weaned only with fruits. With Apple every other day and other fruits on the days in between</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Plums group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>1 of the 2 fruit groups. The infants were weaned only with vegetables. With Plums every other day and other fruits on the days in between</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>green beans group</intervention_name>
    <description>Infants were weaned with vegetable purees for the first 18 days of weaning. One vegetable type per day. With green beans every other day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>green beans group,</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Artichoke group</intervention_name>
    <description>Infants were weaned with vegetable purees for the first 18 days of weaning. One vegetable type per day. With artichoke every other day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Artichoke group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Apple group</intervention_name>
    <description>Infants were weaned with fruit purees for the first 18 days of weaning. One fruit type per day. With apple every other day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Apple group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Plums group</intervention_name>
    <description>Infants were weaned with fruit purees for the first 18 days of weaning. One fruit type per day. With Plums every other day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Plums group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Infants between 4 and 6 months of age that are apparently healthy are invited to
             participate in the study. The parents have to give permission for themselves and for
             their infant to participate by signing an informed consent. By signing the informed
             consent the parents also agree to participate in the study for 2 years.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The parents will not sign the informed consent

          -  The parents have already started weaning their child

          -  The infant has a food allergy or intolerance

          -  The child has medical problems that influences with eating or food digestion. (e.g.
             schisis, problems with the bowls)

          -  The child has a known cognitive or physical developmental problem, which influences
             how the child's reaction or facial expressions.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cees de Graaf, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Wageningen University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wageningen University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wageningen</city>
        <state>Gelderland</state>
        <zip>6703 HD</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Barends, C.d.V., J; Mojet, J &amp; de Graaf, C, Effects of repeated exposure to either vegetables or fruits on infant's vegetable and fruit acceptance at the beginning of weaning. Food quality and preference, 29 , 157-165, 2013</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 16, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 21, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 16, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 16, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 21, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>weaning</keyword>
  <keyword>infants</keyword>
  <keyword>vegetables</keyword>
  <keyword>repeated-exposure</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

