<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02747927</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DEN-301</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1166-8401</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>PHRR150522-001010</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02747927</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy, Safety and Immunogenicity of Takeda's Tetravalent Dengue Vaccine (TDV) in Healthy Children</brief_title>
  <acronym>TIDES</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase III, Double-Blind, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled Trial to Investigate the Efficacy, Safety and Immunogenicity of a Tetravalent Dengue Vaccine (TDV) Administered Subcutaneously in Healthy Children Aged 4 - 16 Years Old</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of 2 doses of Tetravalent Dengue
      Vaccine Candidate (TDV) in preventing symptomatic dengue fever of any severity and due to any
      of the four dengue virus serotypes in 4 to 16 year old participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The vaccine being tested in this study is Takeda's Tetravalent Dengue Vaccine Candidate
      (TDV). TDV is being tested to protect people against dengue fever and to look at long-term
      safety results. This study will look at the success rate of TDV in preventing dengue fever
      (vaccine efficacy) and long-term side effects of the vaccine.

      The study will be conducted in 3 parts. Part 1 will evaluate vaccine efficacy (VE) and will
      last a minimum of 15 months. Part 2 will be for an additional 6 months to evaluate VE. Part 3
      will evaluate long-term safety by following participants for side effects and will last an
      additional 3 years. Participants may be enrolled into a dry-run to commence and test febrile
      surveillance methodology; this dry-run part may be upto 10 months prior to receiving study
      injection, however, will not be applicable to all trials sites or participants.

      Approximately 20,100 participants will be enrolled into the study and randomly assigned (by
      chance) to one of the two treatment groups—which will remain undisclosed to the participants
      and study doctors during the study (unless there is an urgent medical need):

        -  TDV 0.5 mL subcutaneous injection

        -  Placebo (dummy inactive subcutaneous injection) - this is a solution that looks like the
           study drug but has no active ingredient

      All participants will receive a single injection on Day 1 and Day 90. A subset of
      participants will be asked to record any local symptoms at the injection site (Pain, Erythema
      and Swelling) in a diary card for 7 days after each injection. The same subset of
      participants will also be asked to record any systemic symptoms (child &lt;6 years: fever,
      irritability/fussiness, drowsiness, loss of appetite and child ≥6 years: fever, headache,
      asthenia, malaise and myalgia) in a diary card for 14 days after each injection.

      This multi-center trial will be conducted worldwide. The overall time to participate in this
      study is approximately 4.75 years excluding the dry-run. Participants will make multiple
      visits to the clinic and will be contacted at least every week for the entire study duration.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 7, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 27, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 29, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vaccine Efficacy (VE) of Two Doses of Tetravalent Dengue Vaccine Candidate (TDV) in Preventing Virologically-Confirmed Dengue Fever Induced by Any Dengue Serotype</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days post-second vaccination (Day 120) until the end of Part 1 (120 cases of dengue fever are confirmed and minimum duration of subject follow-up of 12 months post-second vaccination)</time_frame>
    <description>VE defined as 1 - (λv/λc), where λv and λc denote the hazard rates for the TDV and placebo arms, respectively.
A virologically-confirmed dengue case is defined as febrile illness (defined as temperature ≥38°C on any 2 of 3 consecutive days) or illness clinically suspected to be dengue by the Investigator with a positive serotype-specific reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VE of Two Doses of TDV in Preventing Virologically-Confirmed Dengue Fever Induced by Each Dengue Serotype</measure>
    <time_frame>From 30 days post-second vaccination (Day 120) until the end of Part 2 (up to 21 months)</time_frame>
    <description>VE is defined as 1 - (λv/λc), where λv and λc denote the hazard rates for the TDV and placebo arms, respectively.
A virologically-confirmed dengue case is defined as febrile illness (defined as temperature ≥38°C on any 2 of 3 consecutive days) or illness clinically suspected to be dengue by the Investigator with a positive serotype-specific reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VE of Two Doses of TDV in Preventing Virologically-Confirmed Dengue Fever Induced by Any Dengue Serotype in Participants Dengue Seronegative at Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>From 30 days post-second vaccination (Day 120) until the end of Part 2 (up to 21 months)</time_frame>
    <description>VE is defined as 1 - (λv/λc), where λv and λc denote the hazard rates for the TDV and placebo arms, respectively.
A virologically-confirmed dengue case is defined as febrile illness (defined as temperature ≥38°C on any 2 of 3 consecutive days) or illness clinically suspected to be dengue by the Investigator with a positive serotype-specific reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VE of Two Doses of TDV in Preventing Virologically-Confirmed Dengue Fever Induced by Any Dengue Serotype in Participants Dengue Seropositive at Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>From 30 days post-second vaccination (Day 120) until the end of Part 2 (up to 21 months)</time_frame>
    <description>VE is defined as 1 - (λv/λC), where λv and λc denote the hazard rates for the TDV and placebo arms, respectively.
A virologically-confirmed dengue case is defined as febrile illness (defined as temperature ≥38°C on any 2 of 3 consecutive days) or illness clinically suspected to be dengue by the Investigator with a positive serotype-specific reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VE of Two Doses of TDV in Preventing Hospitalization due to Virologically-Confirmed Dengue Fever Induced by Any Dengue Serotype</measure>
    <time_frame>From 30 days post-second vaccination (Day 120) until the end of Part 2 (up to 21 months)</time_frame>
    <description>VE is defined as 1 - (λv/λc), where λv and λc denote the hazard rates for the TDV and placebo arms, respectively.
A virologically-confirmed dengue case is defined as febrile illness (defined as temperature ≥38°C on any 2 of 3 consecutive days) or illness clinically suspected to be dengue by the Investigator with a positive serotype-specific reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VE of Two Doses of TDV in Preventing Virologically-Confirmed Severe Dengue Fever Induced by Any Dengue Serotype</measure>
    <time_frame>From 30 days post-second vaccination (Day 120) until the end of Part 2 (up to 21 months)</time_frame>
    <description>VE is defined as 1 - (λv/λc), where λv and λc denote the hazard rates for the TDV and placebo arms, respectively.
A virologically-confirmed dengue case is defined as febrile illness (defined as temperature ≥38°C on any 2 of 3 consecutive days) or illness clinically suspected to be dengue by the Investigator with a positive serotype-specific reverse transcriptase polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Solicited Local Injection Site Adverse Events (AEs) in the Safety Subset</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 through 7 after each vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Solicited local AEs at injection site are defined as pain, erythema and swelling that occurred within 7 days after each vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of Solicited Local Injection Site Adverse Events (AEs) in the Safety Subset</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 through 7 after each vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Solicited local AEs at injection site are defined as pain, erythema and swelling that occurred within 7 days after each vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Solicited Systemic Adverse Events (AEs) in the Safety Subset</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 through 14 after each vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Solicited systemic AEs in children (&lt; 6 years) are defined as fever, irritability/fussiness, drowsiness and loss of appetite that occurred within 14 days after each vaccination. Solicited systemic AEs in children (≥ 6 years) are defined as fever, headache, asthenia, malaise and myalgia that occurred within 14 days after each vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of Solicited Systemic Adverse Events (AEs) in the Safety Subset</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 through 14 after each vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Solicited systemic AEs in children (&lt; 6 years) are defined as fever, irritability/fussiness, drowsiness and loss of appetite that occurred within 14 days after each vaccination. Solicited systemic AEs in children (≥ 6 years) are defined as fever, headache, asthenia, malaise and myalgia that occurred within 14 days after each vaccination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Any Unsolicited Adverse Events (AEs) in the Safety Subset</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 through 28 after each vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Unsolicited AEs are any AEs that are not solicited local or systemic AEs, as defined by this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Serious Adverse Events (SAEs) During Parts 1 and 2</measure>
    <time_frame>From Day 1 until the end of Parts 1 and 2 (approximately 21 months)</time_frame>
    <description>A serious adverse event (SAE) is any untoward medical occurrence or effect that at any dose results in death, is life-threatening, requires inpatient hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization, results in persistent or significant disability / incapacity, is a congenital anomaly / birth defect or is medically important due to other reasons than the above mentioned criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with Fatal SAEs and SAEs Related to Study Drug During the First and Second Half of Part 3</measure>
    <time_frame>For 3 years (18 month halves) beginning at the end of Part 2 (approximately 21 months after the first vaccination)</time_frame>
    <description>A serious adverse event (SAE) is any untoward medical occurrence or effect that at any dose results in death, is life-threatening, requires inpatient hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization, results in persistent or significant disability / incapacity, is a congenital anomaly / birth defect or is medically important due to other reasons than the above mentioned criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with a Seropositive Response for Each of the Four Dengue Serotypes in the Immunogenicity Subset</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Months 1, 3, 4, 9, 15 and then annually (up to 3 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Seropositive response is defined as a reciprocal neutralizing titer ≥ 10. The four DENV serotypes are DEN-1, DEN-2, DEN-3 and DEN-4.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants with a Seropositive Response for Multiple Dengue Serotypes in the Immunogenicity Subset</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Months 1, 3, 4, 9, 15 and then annually (up to 3 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Seropositive response is defined as a reciprocal neutralizing titer ≥ 10. The four DENV serotypes are DEN-1, DEN-2, DEN-3 and DEN-4.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Geometric Mean Titers (GMTs) of Neutralizing Antibodies for Each of the Four Dengue Serotypes in the Immunogenicity Subset</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 and Months 1, 3, 4, 9, 15 and then annually (up to 3 years)</time_frame>
    <description>GMTs of neutralizing antibodies will be measured via microneutralization test (MNT). The four DENV serotypes are DEN-1, DEN-2, DEN-3 and DEN-4.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20100</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tetravalent Dengue Vaccine Candidate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Takeda's Tetravalent Dengue Vaccine Candidate (TDV) 0.5 mL, subcutaneous injection on Day 1 and Day 90.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo-matching TDV, 0.5 mL, subcutaneous injection on Day 1 and Day 90.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Takeda's Tetravalent Dengue Vaccine Candidate</intervention_name>
    <description>TDV subcutaneous injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tetravalent Dengue Vaccine Candidate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TDV Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Takeda's TDV placebo-matching vaccine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Is aged 4 to 16 years, inclusive, at the time of randomization.

          2. Is in good health at the time of entry into the trial as determined by medical
             history, physical examination (including vital signs) and clinical judgment of the
             Investigator.

          3. The participant and/or the participant's parent/guardian signs and dates an
             assent/written informed consent form where applicable, and any required privacy
             authorization prior to the initiation of any trial procedures, after the nature of the
             trial has been explained according to local regulatory requirements.

          4. Can comply with trial procedures and are available for the duration of follow-up.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has febrile illness (temperature ≥38°C) or moderate or severe acute illness or
             infection at the time of randomization.

          2. Has history of or any illness that, in the opinion of the Investigator, might
             interfere with the results of the trial or pose an additional risk to the participant
             due to participation in the trial.

          3. Has received any other vaccine within 14 days (for inactivated vaccines) or 28 days
             (for live vaccines) prior to Day 1 (Month 0) or planning to receive any vaccine within
             28 days after Day 1 (Month 0).

          4. Has participated in any clinical trial with another investigational product 30 days
             prior to Day 1 (Month 0) or intent to participate in another clinical trial at any
             time during the conduct of this trial.

          5. Has previously participated in any clinical trial of a dengue candidate vaccine, or
             previous receipt of a dengue vaccine.

          6. Is first degree relative of individuals involved in trial conduct.

          7. Females of childbearing potential who are sexually active, and who have not used any
             of the acceptable contraceptive methods for at least 2 months prior to Day 1 (Month
             0).

          8. Females of childbearing potential who are sexually active, and who refuse to use an
             acceptable contraceptive method up to 6 weeks post-second vaccination.

          9. Deprived of freedom by administrative or court order, or in an emergency setting, or
             hospitalized involuntarily.

         10. Current alcohol abuse or drug addiction that may interfere with the participant's
             ability to comply with trial procedures.

         11. Identified as an employee of the Investigator or trial center, with direct involvement
             in the proposed trial or other trials under the direction of that Investigator or
             trial center.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>16 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director Clinical Science</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universidade Federal Do Espirito Santo Hospital Universitario Cassiano Antonio de Moraes HUCAM</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vitoria</city>
        <state>Espirito Santo</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universidade Federal de Mato Grosso do Sul</name>
      <address>
        <city>Campo Grande</city>
        <state>Mato Grosso Do Sul</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Associacao Obras Sociais Irma Dulce Hospital Santo Antonio</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bahia</city>
        <state>Salvador</state>
        <zip>40420-000</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital infantil Varela Santiago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Natal</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro de Atencion e Investigacion Medica (CAIMED) Aguazul</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aguazul</city>
        <state>Casanare</state>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro de Atencion e Investigacion Medica (CAIMED) Yopal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yopal</city>
        <state>Casanare</state>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro de Atencion e Investigacion Medica (CAIMED) Acacias</name>
      <address>
        <city>Acacias</city>
        <state>Meta</state>
        <zip>507001</zip>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro de Estudios em Infectologia Pediatrica SAS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cali</city>
        <country>Colombia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Maternidad Nuestra Senora de la Altagracia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santo Domingo</city>
        <zip>10205</zip>
        <country>Dominican Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro de Atencion E Investigacion Medica (CAIMED)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santo Domingo</city>
        <country>Dominican Republic</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universidad Nacional Autonoma de Nicaragua (UNAN) Leon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leon</city>
        <country>Nicaragua</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro De Vacunacion Internacional, S.A.(Cevaxin) - La Chorrera</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ciudad de Panama</city>
        <country>Panama</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro De Vacunacion Internacional, S.A.(Cevaxin) - Plaza Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ciudad de Panama</city>
        <country>Panama</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro De Vacunacion Internacional, S.A.(CEVAXIN)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Panama City</city>
        <zip>10662</zip>
        <country>Panama</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro De Vacunacion Internacional, S.A.(Cevaxin) - 24 de Diciembre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tocumen</city>
        <country>Panama</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dela Salle Health Sciences Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cavite</city>
        <zip>4114</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Philippines AFRIMS Virology Research Unit (PAVRU)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cebu City</city>
        <zip>6000</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Las Pinas Health Center A</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Pinas</city>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Las Pinas Health Center D</name>
      <address>
        <city>Las Pinas</city>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health, University of the Philippines Manila</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manila</city>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Institute for Tropical Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Muntinlupa City</city>
        <zip>1781</zip>
        <country>Philippines</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Colombo South Teaching Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gangodawila</city>
        <state>Nugegoda</state>
        <zip>10250</zip>
        <country>Sri Lanka</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lady Ridgeway Hospital for Children</name>
      <address>
        <city>Colombo</city>
        <zip>00800</zip>
        <country>Sri Lanka</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Negombo General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Negombo</city>
        <zip>11500</zip>
        <country>Sri Lanka</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Colombo North Teaching Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ragama</city>
        <zip>11010</zip>
        <country>Sri Lanka</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Faculty of Tropical Medicine, Mahidol University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <zip>10400</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Phramongkutklao Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <zip>10400</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Srinagarind Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Khon Kaen</city>
        <zip>40002</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
    <country>Colombia</country>
    <country>Dominican Republic</country>
    <country>Nicaragua</country>
    <country>Panama</country>
    <country>Philippines</country>
    <country>Sri Lanka</country>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Peru</country>
    <country>Vietnam</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 14, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 19, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug therapy</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

