<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02743910</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TBCRC040</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>TBCRC 040</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>IRB00093688</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02743910</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Monitoring Plasma Tumor DNA in Early-Stage Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Plasma Tumor DNA and Pathologic Complete Response in Early-Stage, High-Risk Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Translational Breast Cancer Research Consortium (TBCRC)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is being done to see if it is possible to use blood samples to predict response to
      treatment in breast cancer patients receiving preoperative (or neoadjuvant) therapy. Research
      has shown that most breast cancers release tumor-specific DNA into the blood (that is, DNA
      that is specific to the tumor cells or cancer). This DNA can be detected in blood testing
      known as plasma tumor-DNA or &quot;ptDNA.&quot; This DNA is separate from that found in the blood and
      tissue samples which serve as the &quot;instruction book&quot; or &quot;genetic code&quot; for the cells that
      make-up the human body. The changes in ptDNA before and after treatment, as well as after
      surgery, may also help investigators to understand more about a patient's risk of cancer
      returning and long-term outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospectively designed study. Up to 229 newly diagnosed invasive HER2-positive or
      triple-negative breast cancer patients planning neoadjuvant therapy (NAT) will be enrolled.
      Blood samples will be collected pre-operatively at the time of diagnosis/prior to NAT,
      post-cycle 1/pre-cycle 2 of NAT, after all NAT/immediately before surgery, and
      post-operatively at 6, 12, 24, and 36 months, and annually thereafter if funding allows.
      Researchers will also collect representative tissue samples from the diagnostic biopsy (in
      all participants) and definitive surgery (if available). Additionally, to look at feasibility
      of tumor DNA analyses in urine samples, urine samples will be collected along with blood
      samples (urine tumor DNA or utDNA).

      Next generation sequencing will be performed on core biopsies of all enrolled patients for
      tumor-specific mutations (TSM) discovery. Based on those findings, droplet digital PCR
      (ddPCR) on plasma DNA samples will also be performed to confirm the presence of the TSM in
      the plasma on diagnosis, and one TSM will be chosen to track as the plasma tumor DNA (ptDNA)
      mutation of interest. Investigators will perform ddPCR on pre-operative plasma DNA samples
      and will assess for the presence of ptDNA. Pathologists will assess surgical specimens for
      pathologic response (such as complete response/pCR and residual cancer burden/RCB). As
      primary endpoint, investigators will assess the number of patients with and without
      preoperative ptDNA who have pCR versus residual disease. As exploratory endpoints, the
      following will also be performed: (a) quantitative multiplex methylation-specific PCR
      (QM-MSP) in diagnostic biopsy and definitive residual surgery specimen; and, (b) the
      circulating methylated tumor DNA (cMethDNA) assay in plasma specimens (baseline and after
      NAT), and evaluate associations with pathologic response.

      Additional endpoints include the association between plasma and tissue markers at baseline,
      after NAT, and (if available) during surveillance with long-term prognosis (invasive
      disease-free survival/IDFS and distant disease-free survival/DDFS).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of absence of plasma tumor DNA (ptDNA) with pathologic complete response (pCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>To estimate the negative predictive value (NPV) of the absence of plasma tumor DNA (ptDNA) Tumor Specific Mutations (TSMs) after neoadjuvant therapy (NAT) for the absence of residual disease as defined by pathologic complete response (pCR) in stage II-III HER2-positive or triple negative breast cancer (TNBC)
NPV = True Negative/True Negative + False Negative (probability that the disease is not present when the test is negative)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prognostic value of ptDNA for invasive disease-free survival and distant disease-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>To estimate the prognostic value of ptDNA for 5-year invasive disease-free survival (IDFS) and distant disease-free survival (DDFS) in TNBC patients following completion of loco-regional and systemic therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of absence of ptDNA with residual cancer burden (RCB)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>To estimate the NPV of the absence of ptDNA TSMs after NAT for the absence of residual disease as defined by residual cancer burden (RCB) 0 or 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">229</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stage II-III breast cancer</arm_group_label>
    <description>Up to 229 newly diagnosed stage II-III invasive HER2-positive or triple-negative breast cancer patients planning neoadjuvant therapy (NAT) will be enrolled. ptDNA blood samples as well as a representative tumor tissue sample from both the diagnostic and surgical procedure (if available) will be collected.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ptDNA</intervention_name>
    <description>Pre-operative blood samples for ptDNA will be collected at the time of diagnosis/prior to NAT, post-cycle 1/pre-cycle 2 of NAT, after all NAT/immediately before surgery, and post-operatively at 6, 12, 24, and 36 months, and annually thereafter if funding allows.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stage II-III breast cancer</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Blood sample</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tissue sample</intervention_name>
    <description>Representative tissue sample will be collected from the diagnostic biopsy (in all participants) and definitive surgery (if available)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stage II-III breast cancer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood and tissue samples
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Newly diagnosed invasive HER2-positive or triple-negative breast cancer patients planning
        neoadjuvant therapy (NAT)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Newly diagnosed, histologically confirmed invasive breast cancer that is triple
             negative (estrogen receptor [ER], progesterone receptor [PR], and HER2-neu negative)
             or HER2-positive (any ER/PR status)

          -  Unresected, untreated breast cancer that is T2, T3, or T4a-c; any N (nodal status);
             and M0 (not metastatic)

          -  ECOG Performance Status of 0 or 1

          -  Planning to receive a neoadjuvant chemotherapy regimen containing a taxane ± an
             anthracycline for at least 4 cycles. Patients with HER2-positive disease must also be
             planning to receive HER2-targeted therapy.

          -  Diagnostic tumor material must be available for correlative analyses

          -  Patients must have the ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written
             informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No prior treatment for the current breast cancer, though prior use of selective
             estrogen receptor modulators (SERMs) or aromatase inhibitors (AIs) for the prevention
             of breast cancer is acceptable.

          -  Women who are pregnant or nursing are excluded.

          -  No history of another primary malignancy in the last 5 years prior to registration.
             Patients with prior history of in situ cancer or basal or localized squamous cell skin
             cancer are eligible.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ben Ho Park, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hopkins Breast Trials</last_name>
    <phone>410-614-1361</phone>
    <email>HopkinsBreastTrials@jhmi.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hopkins Breast Trials</last_name>
      <phone>410-955-8804</phone>
      <email>HopkinsBreastTrials@jhmi.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ben Ho Park, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 15, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 15, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 19, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>preoperative</keyword>
  <keyword>neoadjuvant</keyword>
  <keyword>plasma tumor DNA</keyword>
  <keyword>ptDNA</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

