<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02748525</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HSC-MS-16-0015</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02748525</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Gallbladder Contractility Using Both CCK and Milk Consecutively</brief_title>
  <acronym>Milk</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Gallbladder Contractility Using Both CCK and Milk Consecutively</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to combine the use of IV CCK administration followed by oral milk during a
      HIDA scan to further stimulate the gallbladder contractility and decrease the number of false
      abnormal HIDA scans and unnecessary cholecystectomies in some patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hepatobiliary imaging (HIDA) has an important role in the evaluation of the function and
      dynamics of the hepatobiliary system and the flow of bile to the gastrointestinal system.
      Contractility of the gallbladder is one of the functions that are uniquely evaluated using a
      HIDA scan. Poor contractility of the gallbladder can be the source of pain in many patients.
      Anatomic imaging studies like ultrasound, CT and/or MRI are usually normal in these patients.

      Contractility of the gallbladder is evaluated during a HIDA scan by intravenous injection of
      cholecystokinin (CCK) a physiologic peptide enzyme produced in the duodenum in response to
      the presence of fatty meal which causes the gallbladder to contract and the sphincter of Oddi
      to relax, thus allowing the flow of bile from the gallbladder to the duodenum. CCK is usually
      administered during a HIDA scan intravenously after filling of the gallbladder with
      radioactive tracer to simulate the action of the endogenous CCK in contracting the
      gallbladder and relaxation of the sphincter of Oddi. Gallbladder ejection fraction (GBEF) in
      response to CCK injection is calculated using special computer software program. A normal
      gallbladder ejection fraction is equal to or greater than 35%. Alternative to CCK injection,
      the patient may be administered milk as a fatty drink that should stimulate a normal
      gallbladder to contract when it reaches the duodenum approximately 15-20 minutes after oral
      administration. Thus, gallbladder contractility may be evaluated during a HIDA scan either by
      injecting CCK intravenously or oral administration of milk. Poor contractility of the
      gallbladder may result in abdominal pain usually triggered by meals. However, in many
      patients with abdominal pain and a decreased gallbladder contractility as evaluated by IV CCK
      or milk may continue to suffer from pain even after surgical removal of the gallbladder .
      This suggests that abnormally decreased GBEF after CCK or milk stimulation may represent
      false abnormal finding resulting in unnecessary cholecystectomies in some of the patients.
      There are no reports in the literature that have used both intravenous CCK stimulation and
      oral milk administration together in the same patient.

      This study aims to combine the use of IV CCK administration followed by oral milk during a
      HIDA scan to further stimulate the gallbladder contractility and decrease the number of false
      abnormal HIDA scans and unnecessary cholecystectomies in some patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in ejection fraction from original</measure>
    <time_frame>45 minutes after CCK administration, 45 minutes after milk administration</time_frame>
    <description>Patient will receive CCK, be scanned, and the ejection fraction will be measured. Then milk will be administered, repeat scan and ejection fraction will be measured.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who reported abdominal pain at 6 months</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients who received cholecystectomy</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Abdominal Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CCK then Milk</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CCK administered and HIDA scan performed. Results analyzed, if ejection fraction is low, patient is given milk to drink, and HIDA scan performed again. Results are analyzed to determine if ejection fraction is still low.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Milk</intervention_name>
    <description>Milk, in the form of 8 oz. half and half, administered after CCK scan, and patient is rescanned and ejection fraction measured to determine if ejection fraction is low.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CCK then Milk</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CCK</intervention_name>
    <description>CCK is standard of care, used in HIDA scans for gallbladder function evaluation. It is given intravenously to cause the gallbladder to contract. The usual dose of CCK is 0.02mg/kg slowly over 3 minutes as per standard.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CCK then Milk</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cholecystokinin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients referred to a HIDA scan for evaluation of gallbladder function.

          -  No evidence of gallbladder stones on any prior anatomic imaging studies.

          -  Patients who are able to lie flat on the imaging table for an additional 30 min. of
             imaging after the standard of care 1.5 hour HIDA scan.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who are under 18 years of age.

          -  Patients with evidence of gallbladder stones on other imaging modalities.

          -  Patient allergic to milk or dairy products.

          -  HIDA scan ordered to evaluate for acute cholecystitis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Isis W Gayed, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Texas Healtlh Science Center at Houston</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Isis W Gayed, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-704-1787</phone>
    <email>isis.w.gayed@uth.tmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Karen P Swaby, BSN</last_name>
    <phone>713-704-2842</phone>
    <email>karen.p.swaby@uth.tmc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Health Science Center Houston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen P. Swaby, BSN</last_name>
      <phone>713-704-2842</phone>
      <email>karen.p.swaby@uth.tmc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Usha Joseph, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Wan, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edwards MA, Mullenbach B, Chamberlain SM. Pain provocation and low gallbladder ejection fraction with CCK cholescintigraphy are not predictive of chronic acalculous gallbladder disease symptom relief after cholecystectomy. Dig Dis Sci. 2014 Nov;59(11):2773-8. doi: 10.1007/s10620-014-3213-4. Epub 2014 May 23.</citation>
    <PMID>24852884</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DiBaise JK, Oleynikov D. Does gallbladder ejection fraction predict outcome after cholecystectomy for suspected chronic acalculous gallbladder dysfunction? A systematic review. Am J Gastroenterol. 2003 Dec;98(12):2605-11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14687804</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hadigan C, Fishman SJ, Connolly LP, Treves ST, Nurko S. Stimulation with fatty meal (Lipomul) to assess gallbladder emptying in children with chronic acalculous cholecystitis. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr. 2003 Aug;37(2):178-82.</citation>
    <PMID>12883305</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Al-Muqbel KM, Bani Hani MN, Elheis MA, Al-Omari MH. Reproducibility of gallbladder ejection fraction measured by Fatty meal cholescintigraphy. Nucl Med Mol Imaging. 2010 Dec;44(4):246-51. doi: 10.1007/s13139-010-0046-8. Epub 2010 Oct 13.</citation>
    <PMID>24899960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Al-Muqbel KM. Gallbladder ejection fraction measured by fatty meal cholescintigraphy: is it affected by extended gallbladder emptying data acquisition time? Ann Nucl Med. 2010 Jan;24(1):29-34. doi: 10.1007/s12149-009-0324-7. Epub 2009 Nov 25.</citation>
    <PMID>19937405</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Delgado-Aros S, Cremonini F, Bredenoord AJ, Camilleri M. Systematic review and meta-analysis: does gall-bladder ejection fraction on cholecystokinin cholescintigraphy predict outcome after cholecystectomy in suspected functional biliary pain? Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2003 Jul 15;18(2):167-74. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12869076</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 4, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 19, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Texas Health Science Center, Houston</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Isis W Gayed</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Radiology - Clinical</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Abdominal Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cholecystokinin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Patient data will be collected, deidentified, and collated into aggregate. Descriptive statistics will be used to describe outcome.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

