<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02747433</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015P002107</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02747433</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Robot-Assisted Therapy and Motor Learning: An Active Learning Program for Stroke</brief_title>
  <acronym>ALPS</acronym>
  <official_title>Infusing Robot-Assisted Therapy With Motor Learning Principles: An Active Learning Program for Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Spaulding Rehabilitation Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Spaulding Rehabilitation Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Stroke is the leading cause of long-term disability in older adults in the United States. At
      six months after stroke, up to 65% of the more than 795,000 persons who experience a stroke
      each year continue to have motor impairments that inhibit functional use of the weaker arm
      during daily activities and negatively impact quality of life. Rehabilitation robots provide
      clinicians with new treatment options to improve movement and arm function after stroke. The
      purpose of this pilot study is to develop and test a therapy called the &quot;Active Learning
      Program for Stroke&quot; (ALPS). We are combining this therapy program with robot-assisted therapy
      and a home program for the stroke-affected arm and hand.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Little is known about how individuals learn to utilize robot-trained movements during upper
      extremity (UE) activities in the home and community and whether specific instruction can
      enhance motor learning and carry-over.. Systematic reviews of robot-assisted therapy for the
      paretic UE confirm gains in motor capacity as measured by clinical assessments, but provide
      little evidence of improved UE performance during daily tasks and occupations. These findings
      may be attributed to the limited availability of rehabilitation robots to train the paretic
      hand and a primary focus on intensity of practice with little regard for other principles of
      motor learning and experience-dependent neuroplasticity. These principles, including the
      salience of training tasks, transfer of acquired skills to similar activities, and active
      engagement and problem solving, are key to task-oriented training paradigms in stroke (e.g.
      constraint-induced movement therapy) but have not been well integrated into robot-assisted
      therapy protocols. The transfer of robot-trained movements to UE activities within the home
      and community needs further exploration before widespread use in rehabilitation practice is
      expected.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fugl-Meyer Assessment (FMA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediately after 6-week intervention; 1-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>The FMA will examine changes in motor function, pain and sensation in the paretic UE between baseline, post-intervention and 1-month follow-up assessments.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Wolf Motor Function Test (WMFT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediately after 6-week intervention; 1-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>The WMFT will examine changes in ability to complete timed, functionally-based activities with the paretic UE between baseline, post-intervention and 1-month follow-up assessments.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Confidence in Arm and Hand Movement (CAHM) scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediately after 6-week intervention; 1-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>The CAHM is a self-report assessment in which participants are asked to rate their confidence (0-100%) in successfully using their paretic UE for a variety of everyday activities. Change in confidence ratings between baseline, post-intervention and 1-month follow up assessments will be examined.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Motor Activity Log (MAL)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediately after 6-week intervention; 1-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>The MAL has been widely used in stroke rehabilitation studies to measure self-reported amount and quality of paretic arm use during daily activities. Change in MAL ratings between baseline, post-intervention and 1-month follow up assessments will be examined.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Home Based Accelerometry - Wearable Sensors</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediately after 6-week intervention; 1-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>GeneActiv (http://www.geneactiv.org) is a multi-directional, waterproof sensor used to quantitatively measure UE activity during everyday living situations. Sensors will be worn on both wrists during 72-hour periods at each assessment point to allow comparisons between paretic and intact UE activity in the home/community.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Kinematic data will be collected via 3-D motion capture (Vicon Motion Systems Ltd. UK)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediately after 6-week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Participants will be asked to perform reach and grasp movements directed toward targets positioned in front of the subject to elicit functional movements, including forward reach, shoulder abduction, wrist extension, and finger flexion/extension. Reflective markers will be attached to locations on the trunk and paretic arm to allow recording of motions by the Vicon system for off-line analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Surface EMG (SEMG)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediately after 6-week intervention</time_frame>
    <description>SEMG data may be gathered during the kinematic testing protocol above to study the characteristics of muscle activation patterns in stroke survivors during the performance of arm reaching movements. Data will be collected using Cometa WavePlus wireless surface electrodes with 16 channels (www.cometasystems.com).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Ashworth Scale (MAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediately after 6-week intervention; 1-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>The MAS will examine changes in muscle tone in the paretic UE between baseline, post-intervention and 1-month follow-up assessments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke Impact Scale (SIS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, immediately after 6-week intervention; 1-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>The SIS will measure changes in activity and participation due to stroke between baseline, post-intervention and 1-month follow-up assessments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Robot-Assisted Therapy (RT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Armeo and Amadeo robot-assisted intensive upper extremity therapy 1 hr sessions 3x week for 6 weeks plus ALPS training</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Robot &amp; Task-Oriented Training (RT-TOT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Armeo and Amadeo robot-assisted intensive upper extremity therapy 30 mins, 3x week for 6 weeks plus ALPS training. Task oriented training will be provided for remaining 30 min of each treatment session</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Robot-Assisted Therapy (RT)</intervention_name>
    <description>Highly repetitive robot-assisted therapy for paretic arm with Armeo (1 hr sessions, 3x week for 3 weeks) followed by robot-assisted therapy for hand motions with Amadeo (3x week for 3 weeks). Robot training to be accompanied with ALPS motor learning program directed toward UE self management and transfer of training to daily activities in home &amp; community.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Robot-Assisted Therapy (RT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Robot &amp; Task-Oriented Training (RT-TOT)</intervention_name>
    <description>Highly repetitive robot-assisted therapy for paretic arm with Armeo (30 min sessions, 3x week for 3 weeks) followed by robot-assisted therapy for hand motions with Amadeo (3x week for 3 weeks). Task oriented training will be delivered for remaining 30 mins of each treatment session. Robot and task oriented training to be accompanied with ALPS motor learning program directed toward UE self management and transfer of training to daily activities in home &amp; community.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Robot &amp; Task-Oriented Training (RT-TOT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Moderate UE hemiparesis (i.e. some ability to move shoulder, elbow &amp; hand and initial
             score on the Fugl-Meyer Assessment (FMA) between 21-50/66))

          -  Intact cognitive function to understand and actively engage in the ALPS robotic
             therapy procedures (Montreal Cognitive Assessment Score &gt;/=26/30)12 during initial
             evaluation visit

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No more than moderate impairments in paretic UE sensation, passive range of motion,
             and pain that would limit ability to engage in therapy

          -  Increased muscle tone as indicated by score of &gt;/= 3 on the Modified Ashworth Scale;

          -  Hemispatial neglect or visual field loss measured by the symbol cancellation subtest
             on the Cognitive Linguistic Quick Test 13

          -  Aphasia sufficient to limit comprehension and completion of the treatment protocol

          -  Currently enrolled or has plans to enroll in other upper limb therapy/research during
             the study period

          -  Contraindications for robot-assisted therapy including recent fracture or skin lesion
             of paretic UE
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Susan E Fasoli, ScD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>MGH Institute of Health Professions &amp; Spaulding Rehabilitation Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paolo Bonato, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Spaulding Rehabilitation Hospital &amp; Harvard Medical School</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Susan E Fasoli, ScD</last_name>
    <phone>617-643-4777</phone>
    <email>sfasoli@mghihp.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Catherine Adans-Dester</last_name>
    <phone>617-952-6321</phone>
    <email>cadans-dester@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Spaulding Rehabilitation Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02129</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan E. Fasoli, ScD</last_name>
      <phone>617-643-4777</phone>
      <email>sfasoli@mghihp.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Catherine Adans-Dester</last_name>
      <phone>617-952-6321</phone>
      <email>cadans-dester@partners.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Susan E. Fasoli, ScD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paolo Bonato, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 18, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 18, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 21, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 5, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Spaulding Rehabilitation Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Susan Fasoli, ScD OTR/L</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor, MGH Institute of Health Professions</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>robot-assisted therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>task-oriented training</keyword>
  <keyword>motor learning</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

