<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02745938</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-16023953</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02745938</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>GDF-15 as a Biomarker for Mitochondrial Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>GDF-15</acronym>
  <official_title>GDF-15 as a Biomarker for Mitochondrial Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Mitochondrial disorders are a group of inherited disorders causing malfunctional
      mitochondria. Mitochondria are found in every cell of the body, and the disorders therefore
      give symptoms from every tissue, especially those with high energy needs as the brain, heart
      and muscles. The symptoms are often unspecific in terms of muscle weakness and fatigue, which
      delays the first contact to the doctor and further delays the diagnosis.

      The aim of this study is to investigate if it is possible to use GDF-15 (Growth and
      Differentiation Factor 15) as a biomarker for mitochondrial disease and compare the results
      with that of healthy controls, metabolic myopathies and muscular dystrophies. The
      concentration relative to exercise will further be investigated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND

      Energy insufficiency:

      Mitochondrial and metabolic myopathies are inherited diseases compromising cellular energy
      metabolism, which especially affects skeletal muscle because of its high energy needs.
      Chemical energy is stored in the body as adenosine triphosphate (ATP), which is derived from
      different sources including breakdown of carbohydrates, lipids and purine nucleotides. In the
      respiratory chain in the inner mitochondrial membrane, ATP is released through oxidative
      phosphorylation.

      Any genetic disorder affecting any step in the production of energy, from storage and
      breakdown of glycogen and lipids to transport and conversion of substrates, can manifest as
      energy insufficiency in the affected tissues.

      Mutations in genes encoding enzymes of the lipid or carbohydrate metabolism result in
      metabolic myopathies and mutations in the enzyme complexes of the respiratory chain result in
      mitochondrial disorders.

      Mitochondrial disorders:

      Mitochondrial disorders are caused by mutations in either mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) or
      nuclear DNA (nDNA) which lead to impaired function of the respiratory chain and reduced
      energy generation. The disorders derived from mtDNA mutations are maternally inherited, while
      the nDNA mutations are autosomal recessively or dominantly inherited.

      Mitochondrial disorders present with a wide range of symptoms and syndromes depending on the
      mutation and mutation load in tissues. Symptoms usually arise from the brain, nerves,
      skeletal and cardiac muscle, as these tissues have a high energy demand. The patients may
      suffer from muscle weakness, exercise intolerance, impaired balance and coordination,
      seizures, learning deficits, impaired vision, hearing loss and heart defects. Age at disease
      onset varies and the disease can debut throughout life.

      The prevalence is in general 6.2/100.000 births.

      Metabolic myopathies:

      Metabolic myopathies are either inherited autosomal recessively, dominantly, X-linked or
      occur spontaneously. Metabolic myopathies can be caused by defective enzymes of the lipid
      metabolism (Fatty Acid Oxidation Disorders), and glycogen and glucose metabolism
      (Glycogenoses) with common features of compromised energy generation in the affected tissues,
      especially in muscle.

      Symptoms vary, but patients can suffer from exercise intolerance, muscle contractures,
      progressive muscle weakness and heart- and respiratory failure. If the symptoms start in
      childhood, the disease is often more severe and may present with acute metabolic
      decompensation, hypoketotic hypoglycemia, encephalopathy and risk of coma and death.

      The prevalence and incidence are uncertain, since there might be many patients who have not
      been diagnosed. With an increased awareness and newborn screening programs, more patients are
      now being diagnosed and survive metabolic decompensation.

      Growth Differentiation Factor 15 as a diagnostic tool:

      Since the symptoms of mitochondrial disorders and metabolic myopathies are very unspecific,
      they can easily be mistaken for i.e. cardiopulmonary disease and diagnosis can be difficult.
      Therefore, it would be useful to have a biomarker that could easily distinguish both
      disorders from others. A recent study showed that Growth Differentiation Factor 15 (GDF-15)
      was significantly elevated in blood from patients affected by mitochondrial disorders as
      compared to healthy individuals, but it is unknown whether this increase is specific for
      mitochondrial disease. Thus it is unknown how GDF-15 levels are in patients with other muscle
      disease, including metabolic myopathies in which an energy deficiency, as in mitochondrial
      diseases, is also present. GDF-15 belongs to the transforming growth factor beta super family
      of growth factors that regulates inflammation and apoptosis in injured tissue. It is not
      known why GDF-15 is elevated, but it has been suggested that the oxidative stress, which is a
      part of the pathophysiology in mitochondrial disorders, increases GDF-15 through activation
      of P53. Oxidative stress also plays a role in the pathophysiology of some metabolic
      myopathies [8], and GDF-15 may therefore be elevated in these patients too. To make sure that
      the GDF-15 is not elevated due to muscle involvement, it will also be measured in a subgroup
      of muscular dystrophies.

      AIM

      In this study, we wish to further investigate:

        1. if measurement of GDF-15 can be used as a biomarker for mitochondrial myopathy and
           distinguish these patients from healthy persons.

        2. if elevated GDF-15 is also a sign of either metabolic myopathy or muscle dystrophy and
           not exclusively detects mitochondrial disease.

        3. if the GDF-15 concentration in these mitochondrial and metabolic myopathy varies when
           metabolic demand is increased with exercise.

        4. if the GDF-15 concentration correlates with oxidative capacity (VO2max) in patients with
           mitochondrial myopathy.

      We will investigate the concentration of GDF-15 in blood samples in patients affected by
      mitochondrial disorders and compare it to the concentrations in patients affected by
      metabolic myopathies, muscular dystrophies and to a group of healthy controls. If there is a
      significant difference, GDF-15 may be a sensitive biomarker for mitochondrial disorders. We
      will further investigate the maximal oxidative capacity and the maximal workload capacity to
      study if and how this relates to the concentration of GDF-15.

      METHODS:

      30 subjects with mitochondrial disorders, 25 with metabolic myopathy, 25 with muscular
      dystrophy and 25 healthy controls will be recruited. A blood sample will be taken, and GDF-15
      and other muscle markers will be measured. 10-15 subjects with mitochondrial disorders, 10-15
      with metabolic myopathy and 10-15 healthy individuals will further be investigated with an
      exercise test, and blood samples will be taken afterwards.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>GDF-15 concentration in plasma sample at rest.</measure>
    <time_frame>One blood sample per subject will be analysed. It takes 5 minutes.</time_frame>
    <description>The blood sample will be analysed with a Luminex analyser to determine the concentration of GDF-15.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GDF-15 concentration in plasma after exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>The exercise test takes half an hour. Blood samples will be taken 1, 2, 3, 24 and 48 hours after the exercise test.</time_frame>
    <description>The subjects perform an incremental exercise test until exhaustion on a cycle ergometer. The concentration of GDF-15 is measured afterwards with a Luminex analyser.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other biomarkers of energy metabolism disorders at rest and after exercise test.</measure>
    <time_frame>If the blood samples are only taken at rest, the test takes 5 minutes. If an exercise test is done, it takes 48 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>Lactate is a muscle marker, that is measured in this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other biomarkers of energy metabolism disorders at rest and after exercise test.</measure>
    <time_frame>If the blood samples are only taken at rest, the test takes 5 minutes. If an exercise test is done, it takes 48 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>Pyruvate is a muscle marker, that is measured in this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other biomarkers of energy metabolism disorders at rest and after exercise test.</measure>
    <time_frame>If the blood samples are only taken at rest, the test takes 5 minutes. If an exercise test is done, it takes 48 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>Creatin kinase is a muscle marker, that is measured in this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Other biomarkers of energy metabolism disorders at rest and after exercise test.</measure>
    <time_frame>If the blood samples are only taken at rest, the test takes 5 minutes. If an exercise test is done, it takes 48 hours.</time_frame>
    <description>FGF-21 (Fibroblast Growth Factor 21) is a muscle marker that is measured in this study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximal oxidative capacity (VO2max)</measure>
    <time_frame>The test takes half an hour per subject.</time_frame>
    <description>During the exercise test, the subjects will breath through a mask, that is connected to a machine. The machine is able to calculate the VO2max.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximal workload capacity (Wmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>The test takes half an hour per subject.</time_frame>
    <description>The Wmax will be calculated during the exercise test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">97</enrollment>
  <condition>Mitochondrial Disease</condition>
  <condition>Metabolic Myopathy</condition>
  <condition>Muscular Dystrophy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mitochondrial disease</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with mitochondrial disease, investigated by blood samples and exercise test.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Metabolic myopathy</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with metabolic myopathy, investigated by blood samples and exercise test.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Muscular dystrophy</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with muscular dystrophy, investigated by blood samples and exercise test.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthy controls, investigated by blood samples and exercise test.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood samples
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Four groups are studied:

          1. Patients with mitochondrial disease.

          2. Patients with metabolic myopathy.

          3. Patients with muscular dystrophy.

          4. Healthy controls.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Criteria for subjects with mitochondrial disease, metabolic myopathy or muscle dystrophy:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Verified mitochondrial disease, metabolic myopathy or muscular dystrophy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Other muscle disorders.

          -  Heart failure or significantly reduced kidney or lung function.

          -  Contraindications for exercise test, e.g. serious heart and lung disease. The
             investigator will decide whether or not it is possible for the subject to participate
             (Only for the subjects doing an exercise test.).

        Criteria for healthy individuals:

        Inclusion Criteria:

        None (except age &gt; 15 years).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any muscle disorder

          -  Heart failure

          -  Contraindications for exercise test, e.g. serious heart and lung disease. The
             investigator will decide whether or not it is possible for the subject to participate
             (Only when participating in the exercise test).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nanna S. Nielsen, B.Sc.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Copenhagen Neuromuscular Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rigshospitalet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <state>Copenhagen East.</state>
        <zip>2100</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sharp LJ, Haller RG. Metabolic and mitochondrial myopathies. Neurol Clin. 2014 Aug;32(3):777-99, ix. doi: 10.1016/j.ncl.2014.05.001. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25037090</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lightowlers RN, Taylor RW, Turnbull DM. Mutations causing mitochondrial disease: What is new and what challenges remain? Science. 2015 Sep 25;349(6255):1494-9. doi: 10.1126/science.aac7516. Epub 2015 Sep 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26404827</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yatsuga S, Fujita Y, Ishii A, Fukumoto Y, Arahata H, Kakuma T, Kojima T, Ito M, Tanaka M, Saiki R, Koga Y. Growth differentiation factor 15 as a useful biomarker for mitochondrial disorders. Ann Neurol. 2015 Nov;78(5):814-23. doi: 10.1002/ana.24506. Epub 2015 Oct 14.</citation>
    <PMID>26463265</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalko SG, Paco S, Jou C, Rodríguez MA, Meznaric M, Rogac M, Jekovec-Vrhovsek M, Sciacco M, Moggio M, Fagiolari G, De Paepe B, De Meirleir L, Ferrer I, Roig-Quilis M, Munell F, Montoya J, López-Gallardo E, Ruiz-Pesini E, Artuch R, Montero R, Torner F, Nascimento A, Ortez C, Colomer J, Jimenez-Mallebrera C. Transcriptomic profiling of TK2 deficient human skeletal muscle suggests a role for the p53 signalling pathway and identifies growth and differentiation factor-15 as a potential novel biomarker for mitochondrial myopathies. BMC Genomics. 2014 Feb 1;15:91. doi: 10.1186/1471-2164-15-91.</citation>
    <PMID>24484525</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kitaoka Y, Ogborn DI, Nilsson MI, Mocellin NJ, MacNeil LG, Tarnopolsky MA. Oxidative stress and Nrf2 signaling in McArdle disease. Mol Genet Metab. 2013 Nov;110(3):297-302. doi: 10.1016/j.ymgme.2013.06.022. Epub 2013 Jul 6.</citation>
    <PMID>23906480</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Suomalainen A, Elo JM, Pietiläinen KH, Hakonen AH, Sevastianova K, Korpela M, Isohanni P, Marjavaara SK, Tyni T, Kiuru-Enari S, Pihko H, Darin N, Õunap K, Kluijtmans LA, Paetau A, Buzkova J, Bindoff LA, Annunen-Rasila J, Uusimaa J, Rissanen A, Yki-Järvinen H, Hirano M, Tulinius M, Smeitink J, Tyynismaa H. FGF-21 as a biomarker for muscle-manifesting mitochondrial respiratory chain deficiencies: a diagnostic study. Lancet Neurol. 2011 Sep;10(9):806-18. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(11)70155-7. Epub 2011 Aug 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21820356</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 17, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 20, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nanna Scharff Nielsen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Student researcher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Exercise test</keyword>
  <keyword>GDF-15</keyword>
  <keyword>Growth and Differentiation Factor 15</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscular Dystrophies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mitochondrial Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No plan</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

