<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02749461</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SNF 320030_159573</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02749461</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Validation of the Bernese Pain Scale for Neonates</brief_title>
  <acronym>BERN-PAIN</acronym>
  <official_title>Validation of the Bernese Pain Scale for Neonates With Consideration for Contextual Factors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bern University of Applied Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital Inselspital, Berne</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Zurich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Children's Hospital Basel</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bern University of Applied Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aims of this validation study are the testing of the Bernese Pain Scale for Neonates'
      (BPSN) psychometric properties. The variability of pain reactions related to behavioral and
      physiological patterns across time will also be examined. Furthermore, the influence of
      contextual factors on the variability of pain reactions across gestational age groups will be
      explored. The results will be used for modifications of the BPSN to account for contextual
      factors in future clinical pain assessment in neonates.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Preterm birth rates are rising worldwide, including in Europe. In 2014, Switzerland's rate of
      premature births reached 7.2%. Still, while significant progress in neonatal care has
      increased the long-term survival of preterm infants, other long-term outcomes remain
      problematic. As a result, affected infants commonly undergo exceedingly high numbers of
      painful procedures on a daily basis. For many, these treatment interventions take place at a
      crucial period in the development of the nociceptive and central nervous systems, i.e., at a
      developmental stage when repeated painful stimulus may induce both structural and functional
      reorganization of the nervous system and an altered pain response.

      As infants are unable to communicate verbally, clinical pain assessment in neonates,
      particularly those delivered preterm, is highly challenging. Therefore, pain responses have
      to be observed according to physiological and behavioral indicators which might vary across
      preterm infants depending on their physiological and neurological development stages.

      The Bernese Pain Scale for Neonates (BPSN) is a multidimensional pain assessment tool which
      is already widely used in clinical settings in the German speaking areas of Europe. Recent
      findings suggest that pain reaction is influenced by more than noxious stimulation alone: it
      is assumed that contextual factors, e.g., gestational age (GA) or gender, might also impact
      pain reactivity.

      The aims of this validation study are:

        -  to undertake the psychometric testing of the BPSN regarding its concurrent validity with
           the Premature Infant Pain Profile-Revised (PIPP-R), construct validity, interrater and
           intrarater reliability, specificity and sensitivity;

        -  to examine the variability of pain reactions related to behavioural and physiological
           patterns across time;

        -  to assess the influence of contextual factors on the variability of pain reactions
           across GA groups; and

        -  to examine the relationship between behavioural and physiological indicators across
           time.

      This multisite psychometric measurement study of the BPSN will use repeated measures design.
      The study will take place in three tertiary care hospitals (Bern, Zurich and Basel) in
      Switzerland. To examine the impact of GA on pain reaction and its variability, the infants
      will be stratified into six GA groups ranging from 24 0/7 to 42 0/7. Among preterm infants
      with GAs up to 36 6/7 weeks, five consecutive heel sticks within the first 14 days of life
      will be documented. Among healthy-term infants two heel sticks within the first days after
      birth will be documented. For each heel stick, measurements will be recorded for each of
      three phases: baseline, heel stick, and recovery. All phases will be videotaped and the
      child's pain reaction later rated according to the BPSN by five independent raters blinded to
      the measurement phase. Individual contextual factors of interest for this study are
      documented in a standardised way in all three participating Neonatal Intensive Care Units
      (NICUs), and can be extracted from patient charts.

      This diagnostic study is intended to validate the BPSN with consideration for contextual
      factors influencing neonatal pain responses. Understanding and embedding the influences of
      contextual factors into a final version of the BPSN-Context will help clinicians more
      accurately assess pain in the clinical setting, and will eventually help them minimize the
      pain endured by neonates, particularly preterm neonates in NICUs. For preterm infants
      requiring intensive care, adequate and efficient pain management is an important factor in
      later motor and cognitive development. The investigators hope this study will contribute to
      the prevention of negative long-term outcomes in this patient population.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain response across time</measure>
    <time_frame>2-5 timepoints within the first 14 days of life</time_frame>
    <description>Change and variability of pain response across different time points will be measured with the BPSN</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of individual contextual factors on pain response across time</measure>
    <time_frame>2-5 within the first 14 days of life</time_frame>
    <description>Time points of contextual factors documentation are determined by the clinical need for routine heel stick procedures within the first 14 days of life. These time points are not fixed before hand but are based on ongoing clinical judgement during the first 14 days of life. For each clinically determined time point for a heel stick appropriate contextual factors being relevant the day of the determined heel stick date will be extracted from patient chart.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychometric testing of the BPSN</measure>
    <time_frame>2-5 timepoints within the first 14 days of life</time_frame>
    <description>Psychometric testing will be done across all the five time points for baseline, heel stick and recovery phases</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">156</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain Assessment</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>heel stick</intervention_name>
    <description>Consecutive routine blood sampling heel sticks</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study includes preterm infants born between 24 0/7 and 36 6/7 weeks of gestation and
        term infants born between 37 0/7 and 42 0/7 weeks of gestation if they are hospitalised in
        a NICU in the University Hospitals in Basel, Bern and Zurich (Switzerland).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Preterm infants born between 24 0/7 and 36 6/7 weeks of gestation will be included if
             they are expected to undergo 5 routine heel capillary blood samples during the first
             14 days of life; if they are ventilated or not ventilated; and if their parents give
             informed consent.

          -  Term infants born between 37 0/7 and 42 0/7 weeks of gestation will be included if
             they are expected to have at least 2 routine heel capillary blood samples during the
             first days of life and if their parents give informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Grade III oder IV intraventricular haemorrhaging

          -  Severe life-threatening malformation or suffer from any condition involving partial or
             total loss of sensitivity

          -  pHa &lt; 7.15 (umbilical cord)

          -  Surgery for any reason

          -  Congenital malformation affecting brain circulation and cardiovascular system
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>24 Weeks</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>41 Weeks</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eva Cignacco, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Bern University of Applied Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lawrence S. Bloomberg Faculty of Nursing and Faculties of Medicine and Dentistry, University of Toronto</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Neonatology, University Children's Hospital of Basel (UKBB)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basel</city>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Neonatology, Children's Hospital, University Hospital of Bern</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bern</city>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Neonatology, University Hospital of Zurich</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zurich</city>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://p3.snf.ch/project-159573</url>
    <description>Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF), grant database</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://projektdatenbank.bfh.ch/search/pdbwebview.aspx</url>
    <description>Bern University of Applied Sciences, project database</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 22, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 25, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 3, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Bern University of Applied Sciences</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Eva Cignacco</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>preterm infants</keyword>
  <keyword>pain</keyword>
  <keyword>assessment</keyword>
  <keyword>contextual factors</keyword>
  <keyword>diagnostic accuracy</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

