<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02748369</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-000085</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U24DK100469</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02748369</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>In Vivo Assessment of Cellular Metabolism in Humans</brief_title>
  <official_title>In Vivo Assessment of the Tricarboxylic Acid Cycle Flux in the Muscle and Splanchnic Bed of Humans: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>K. Sreekumaran Nair</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot study to establish an arterial venous methodology to measure the activity of
      the TCA cycle or flux directly in tissues of human beings. It will also perform correlative
      studies to study the proteome, metabolome, oxygen consumption, carbon dioxide production and
      exosomes derived from the arterial venous supply of tissues with correlation to the TCA cycle
      activity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The tricarboxylic (TCA) or Krebs cycle is the &quot;central hub of cellular metabolism&quot; that takes
      place within the mitochondria. It is a series of sequential chemical reactions that generate
      cellular energy in the form of ATP. In addition, the cycle provides intermediate metabolites
      that are utilized in the biosynthesis of amino acids and fatty acids as well as reducing
      agents such as nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NADH) and flavin adenine dinucleotide
      (FADH2) that are used in numerous biochemical reactions. The dysfunction of the TCA cycle is
      recognized for its association in neurodegenerative and cardiovascular diseases, metabolic
      syndromes, tumorigenesis and aging. Hence, being able to measure the activity or flux of the
      TCA cycle either in vitro or in vivo holds significant clinical significance. Almost all
      studies are based on in vitro approaches except NMRS based studies that involve multiple
      non-validated assumptions.

      Various stable isotope labeling studies have been used to estimate the TCA cycle flux by
      measuring one or more labelled intermediate metabolites within the cycle. Unfortunately,
      these labelled intermediates are often present through only partial segments of the cycle due
      to exchange, anaplerosis (entrance into the cycle), cataplerosis (export out of the cycle) or
      incomplete cycling. Though these previous isotope labeling studies of the TCA cycle flux were
      qualitatively informative, many were quantitatively inaccurate due to unexpected dilutions of
      the TCA cycle intermediates arising from unlabeled precursors.

      This is a pilot study to establish a novel methodology using mass-isotopomer flux analysis
      after infusions of 2-13C-Acetate, 2-15N-Glutamine and D5-phenylalanine to measure the in vivo
      TCA cycle flux in tissues of human beings. This study will simultaneously determine the
      validity of measuring the TCA cycle flux in tissue indirectly through dynamic differences in
      enrichment of labelled TCA cycle intermediates between arterial and venous blood supplies of
      that particular tissue bed (i.e. arteriovenous model or A-V balance technique). We propose to
      measure the rates of the different metabolic reactions within the TCA cycle by tracing the
      position-specific 13C and 15N transfer between the intermediate metabolites in order to
      characterize the oxidative, anaplerotic, cataplerotic and exchange rates across the TCA
      cycle. The use of 2-15N-Glutamine will specifically allow us to determine the rate of
      glutamine entry into the cycle via its conversion to glutamate, thus providing a more
      accurate quantification of the TCA flux.

      This methodology will be validated in the setting of controlled physiologic perturbations in
      human study participants such as low endogenous insulin levels alone or in combination with
      high glucagon levels.

      Finally, correlative studies evaluating the mitochondrial activity in the skeletal muscle
      tissue, the oxygen consumption in the skeletal and splanchnic tissue beds, the role of
      circulating exosomes derived from the arteriovenous circulation of the skeletal and
      splanchnic tissue beds and the changes in the whole body metabolome will also be performed:

        -  First, mitochondrial respiration will be measured by high resolution respirometry
           (Oxygraph, Oroboros Instruments, Innsbruck, Austria) using a stepwise protocol to
           evaluate various components of the electron transport system. Protein content of the
           mitochondrial suspension will be measured using a colorimetric assay (Pierce 660-nm
           Protein Assay). Oxygen flux rates will be expressed per tissue-wet weight and per
           milligram of mitochondrial protein.

        -  Secondly, reactive oxygen species (ROS) emissions will also be evaluated on all skeletal
           muscle tissue samples. Briefly, a Fluorolog 3 (Horiba Jobin Yvon) spectrofluorometer
           with temperature control and continuous stirring will be used to monitor Amplex Red
           (Invitrogen) oxidation in freshly isolated mitochondrial suspensions obtained from the
           skeletal muscle biopsies. Amplex Red oxidation will be measured in the presence of
           glutamate (10 mmol/L), malate (2 mmol/L), and succinate (10 mmol/L). The fluorescent
           signal will be corrected for background auto-oxidation and calibrated to a standard
           curve. The H2O2 production rates will be expressed relative to mitochondrial protein.

        -  Third, simultaneous assessments of the oxygen consumption and carbon dioxide production
           will be determined through blood gas measurements from the arteriovenous samples
           obtained from the splanchnic and skeletal muscle tissue beds. These assessments will be
           performed at all three time points of blood sample assessments and correlated with the
           measured TCA cycle flux in their respective tissue beds.

        -  Circulating exosomes will also be derived from the arteriovenous samples of the
           splanchnic and skeletal muscle tissue beds to determine its intra-exosome proteome and
           metabolome and its relationship with the TCA cycle flux in their respective tissue beds.
           Incorporation of D5-phenylalanine will help trace the protein formation in the exosomes.

        -  Finally, changes in the whole body metabolome and proteome determined via the
           arteriovenous samples obtained from the splanchnic and skeletal muscle tissue beds will
           also be performed and correlated with the TCA cycle flux in their respective tissue
           beds.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>In Vivo TCA cycle flux in skeletal muscle and splanchnic tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>12 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Normal healthy study participants will receive an initial priming dose followed by a continuous infusion of 2-13C-Acetate, 2-15N-Glutamine and D5-Phenylalanine in order to achieve steady state enrichment of 13C and 15N in their system. Serial arteriovenous blood samples will be obtained from the femoral artery, femoral vein and hepatic vein and serial skeletal muscle tissue biopsies will be obtained from the vastus lateralis. These samples will be analyzed by GC-MS and NMR spectroscopy to quantify the isotopomer intermediates of the TCA cycle and measure the corresponding TCA cycle flux. The flux estimations from the arteriovenous blood samples will be compared to that obtained directly from the skeletal muscle tissue. This methodology will be validated in the setting of low insulin levels alone or in combination with high glucagon concentrations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the protein and metabolite contents within circulating exosomes derived from the arterial-venous blood supply of the skeletal muscle and splanchnic tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>12 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the metabolome derived from the arterial-venous blood supply of the skeletal muscle and splanchnic tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>12 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the proteome derived from the arterial-venous blood supply of the skeletal muscle and splanchnic tissue in response to hormonal manipulation.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Oxygen consumption in skeletal muscle and splanchnic tissue in response to hormonal manipulation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mitochondrial respiration in skeletal muscle tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>12 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reactive oxygen species emissions in skeletal muscle tissue</measure>
    <time_frame>12 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">17</enrollment>
  <condition>Normal Cellular Metabolism</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No somatostatin and glucagon infusions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Somatostatin and glucagon infusions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Somatostatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Somatostatin infusion to create a low insulin state.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>growth hormone-inhibiting hormone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glucagon</intervention_name>
    <description>Glucagon infusion in the setting of ongoing somatostatin.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Glucagen</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Ages 18-45

          -  Able to provide written consent

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Diabetes mellitus or impaired fasting glucose levels (fasting blood glucose
             &gt;110mg/dl).

          -  Renal Failure

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Steroid use

          -  Muscle Disease

          -  Liver Disease

          -  Major Depression

          -  Anemia

          -  H/O alcohol use

          -  Medications other than OCPs

          -  BMI of 30 or greater
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>K Sreekumaran Nair</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akram M. Citric acid cycle and role of its intermediates in metabolism. Cell Biochem Biophys. 2014 Apr;68(3):475-8. doi: 10.1007/s12013-013-9750-1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24068518</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Befroy DE, Perry RJ, Jain N, Dufour S, Cline GW, Trimmer JK, Brosnan J, Rothman DL, Petersen KF, Shulman GI. Direct assessment of hepatic mitochondrial oxidative and anaplerotic fluxes in humans using dynamic 13C magnetic resonance spectroscopy. Nat Med. 2014 Jan;20(1):98-102. doi: 10.1038/nm.3415. Epub 2013 Dec 8.</citation>
    <PMID>24317120</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sunny NE, Parks EJ, Browning JD, Burgess SC. Excessive hepatic mitochondrial TCA cycle and gluconeogenesis in humans with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. Cell Metab. 2011 Dec 7;14(6):804-10. doi: 10.1016/j.cmet.2011.11.004.</citation>
    <PMID>22152305</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schumann WC, Magnusson I, Chandramouli V, Kumaran K, Wahren J, Landau BR. Metabolism of [2-14C]acetate and its use in assessing hepatic Krebs cycle activity and gluconeogenesis. J Biol Chem. 1991 Apr 15;266(11):6985-90.</citation>
    <PMID>2016310</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alves TC, Pongratz RL, Zhao X, Yarborough O, Sereda S, Shirihai O, Cline GW, Mason G, Kibbey RG. Integrated, Step-Wise, Mass-Isotopomeric Flux Analysis of the TCA Cycle. Cell Metab. 2015 Nov 3;22(5):936-47. doi: 10.1016/j.cmet.2015.08.021. Epub 2015 Sep 24.</citation>
    <PMID>26411341</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones JG, Solomon MA, Cole SM, Sherry AD, Malloy CR. An integrated (2)H and (13)C NMR study of gluconeogenesis and TCA cycle flux in humans. Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab. 2001 Oct;281(4):E848-56.</citation>
    <PMID>11551863</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 19, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>K. Sreekumaran Nair</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>M.D., P.h.D. ; Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TCA cycle flux</keyword>
  <keyword>in vivo measurements</keyword>
  <keyword>Stable isotopes</keyword>
  <keyword>Arteriovenous balance</keyword>
  <keyword>Metabolome</keyword>
  <keyword>Proteome</keyword>
  <keyword>Exosomes</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glucagon</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucagon-Like Peptide 1</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Somatostatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

