<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02743403</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Carboxytherapy,TENS and pain</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02743403</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of TENS in Pain During Application of Carboxytherapy in Patients With Gynoid Lipodystrophy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Transcutaneous Electric Nerve Stimulation in Pain During Application of Carboxytherapy in Patients With Gynoid Lipodystrophy: Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidade Cidade de Sao Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade Cidade de Sao Paulo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The project aims to compare the use of carboxiterapia ( therapeutic administration of carbon
      dioxide) with the use of active TENS and placebo TENS using the VAS scale as a parameter. The
      therapy used was started in the 30s , with carbonated water baths, and , lately, is involved
      in the therapeutic arsenal of numerous diseases , Both for treatment of diseases when for
      aesthetic treatments , especially for the gynoid lipodystrophy. However, the therapy presents
      CO2 in clinical practice, limiting factors for its use , such as pain at the injection site ,
      small bruises or welts due to several punctures and feeling of crepitus. To try to combat
      these &quot; side effects &quot; that can last up to 30 minutes, the TENS was used in order to
      determine whether the use of this electric current helps at improvement of discomfort.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The assessment and intervention will be carried out only by the researcher, which has
      physical therapy training and expertise in dermato-functional physiotherapy with clinical
      experience in 11 years, as well as fulfilling all the prerequisites required for the
      management of carboxytherapy, according the judgment 293 of 16 June 2012 the Federal Council
      of Physical Therapy and Occupational Therapy (COFFITO). Patients will be submitted for
      assessment and intervention once.

      Assessments should contain demographic information of the participants by asking questions
      such as age, marital status, education and contact, lifestyle, gynecological history,
      surgical history, anthropometric measurements and physical inspection examination (Annex 3).
      Patients are advised not to make use of any medication for pain relief such as painkillers
      and anti-inflammatories, within 4 hours before the physiotherapy session. For physical
      examination, evaluations will be conducted in the standing position, with bathing suit,
      keeping the gluteal region with maximum visibility. The appraiser will inspect the bilateral
      gluteal region, to confirm the moderate degree of severity of the gynoid lipodystrophy,
      defined by the gynoid lipodystrophy severity scale, with the number of skin depressions (ND)
      in moderate amount, ND≥ 5-9 depressions, according CSS classification.

      For the study, three groups will be divided: group A (active TENS + active Carboxytherapy), Y
      group (TENS placebo + active Carboxytherapy) and S (active - control Carboxytherapy). Group A
      (active TENS + active Carboxytherapy) will be submitted to the application of TENS during the
      application of Carboxytherapy, both linked. The Y group (TENS placebo + active
      Carboxytherapy) will be submitted to the application of Carboxytherapy and TENS with low-dose
      therapy. The group S (active - control Carboxytherapy) will be submitted to the application
      of Carboxytherapy and off TENS. Prior to the beginning of the study, both devices will be
      calibrated. The gluteal that receive the intervention will be defined by lot.

      After drawing the group and laterality of the gluteal region that receive the intervention,
      will be marked by white pencil, the depressions of the skin with cellulite and the
      delimitation of the area, from the following lines: lateral line will have as midpoint the
      greater trochanter, where a vertical line will be drawn from the iliac crest to the lateral
      edge of the gluteal groove; top line will be drawn a horizontal line parallel to the gluteal
      groove, 4 cm below the posterior superior iliac spine to the vertical line drawn previously
      from the greater trochanter bottom line will be drawn a horizontal line delimiting the
      gluteal groove; the medial end of the gluteal groove to the vertical line drawn previously
      from the greater trochanter; medial line is delimited by anatomically intergluteal slot.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mesure and denouement</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>It will be used to assess pain intensity of the participants. This scale has 11 points, ranging from 0 to 10, where 0 is &quot;no pain&quot; and 10 &quot;worst pain imaginable&quot;. Pain intensity will be measured in three groups: Group A, Group B and Group C, where the patient will quantify their pain viewing a rule containing a scale of 0 to 10. The assessment of this parameter will be made verbally, in which the patient should report the intensity of your pain when you are getting each prick of carboxytherapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">84</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neurodyn Portable TENS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this study arm will receive active treatment. The active TENS device will be Neurodyn Portable TENS the IBRAMED® and application of carboxytherapy device will be Carboxyderm S20-1C equipment, Tone Derm® brand.
The subject receives both devices at the same time. The parameters of the active TENS are: frequency (f) of 100 Hertz (Hz) oscillator every 0.5 seconds pulse duration (T) 200 microseconds (microsiemens) and the amplitude (I) will be adjusted at the time of application the carboxiterapia.
The application of Carboxytherapy is realized by a carboxy Derm S20-1C equipment Derm® mark, which uses carbon dioxide (CO2) medical and non-toxic.
Each prick with a needle carboxiterapia will 100ml / min and will last 1 minute long.
Before each puncture will be adjusted to the intensity of TENS as sensitivity of the subject.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo TENS- Neurodyn Portable TENS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this study arm will receive placebo treatment. The placebo TENS device will be Neurodyn Portable TENS the IBRAMED® and application of carboxytherapy device will be Carboxyderm S20-1C equipment, Tone Derm® brand.
The application of placebo TENS will be made by the same unit of active TENS; however, it is used a device specially developed for this study. The device remains active only during the first 30 seconds of application. After this time, the current amplitude will gradually decrease over the next 15 seconds until it reaches zero, thereby interrupting the emission of electrical power to the remainder of the application time. The display of placebo TENS device shows a light on all the time of application, indicating the patient that the device is active.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects in this study arm only receive the application carboxiterapia through Carboxyderm S20-1C equipment, Tone Derm® brand.
The group (active - control Carboxytherapy) will be submitted to the application of Carboxytherapy and off TENS.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neurodyn Portable activeTENS, IBRAMED®</intervention_name>
    <description>Randomization and secret Allocation active TENS (GI / n = 27)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neurodyn Portable TENS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo TENS- Neurodyn Portable TENS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Carboxyderm S20-1C</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neurodyn Portable placeboTENS, IBRAMED®</intervention_name>
    <description>Randomization and secret Allocation placebo TENS (GII / n = 27)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neurodyn Portable TENS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo TENS- Neurodyn Portable TENS</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Carboxyderm S20-1C</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carboxyderm S20-1C</intervention_name>
    <description>Randomization and secret Allocation control group (CG / n = 27).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neurodyn Portable TENS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo TENS- Neurodyn Portable TENS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Body mass index &lt; 18,5 a 29,9 kg/m²

          -  with regular menstrual cycle

          -  without prior experience with carboxytherapy and TENS

          -  with the presence of moderate gynoid lipodystrophy at gluteal region as classification
             Hexsel Dal'Forno &amp; Hexsel (CSS )

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  pregnant women;

          -  nursing mothers;

          -  women with metabolic disorders and autoimmune diseases;

          -  which are suffering from skin lesions in the gluteal region and who have undergone
             surgical procedures in gluteus;

          -  the presence of malignant or benign tumor;

          -  with metal or silicone implants;

          -  heart disease and / or use of pacemakers, hypoesthesia or anesthesia in the gluteal
             region;

          -  women who have the risk of presenting epilepsy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>44 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard E Liebano, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universidade Cidade de São Paulo</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Paulo</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 28, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 13, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 19, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidade Cidade de Sao Paulo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Adria Yared Sadala</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Researcher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lipodystrophy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

