<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02744248</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CEECTTA20100721</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>IOP-CT-001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02744248</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase I , MTD, Pharmacokinetic, Safety/Tolerability, Efficacy of IOP Injection for MRI in Healthy Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study to Determine the MTD and to Evaluate Pharmacokinetic, Safety/Tolerability, and Efficacy Profiles of IOP Injection for MRI Contrast Agent in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>MegaPro Biomedical Co. Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>MegaPro Biomedical Co. Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study Objectives Primary: To determine MTD and dose limiting toxicities (DLTs) of IOP
      magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) contrast agent in healthy subjects.

      Secondary:

        1. To characterize the pharmacokinetic profiles of IOP MRI contrast agent in healthy
           subjects.

        2. To evaluate safety/tolerability profiles of IOP MRI contrast agent in healthy subjects.

        3. To explore efficacy profiles of IOP MRI contrast agent for liver organ in healthy
           subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Iron Oxide Nano Particle m-PEG-silane (IOP) Injection belongs to Superparamagnetic iron oxide
      (SPIO) can shorten the T2 relaxation time very effectively and reduces signal intensity in
      normal tissues. The mechanism of action increases after the particles have been phagocytosed
      by cells of the RES. Tissues with decreased RES function (e.g., metastases, primary liver
      cancer, cysts and various benign tumors, adenomas, and hyperplasia) retain their native
      signal intensity. In this study, investigators will characterize the PK profile, iron
      metabolism and preliminary efficacy of IOP Injection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose limiting toxicities (DLTs) of IOP</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days post-IOP injection</time_frame>
    <description>DLT is defined as any grade 2 or above toxicity by NCI-CTCAE version 4.03, as determined by the investigator and sponsor, to be at least possibly related in causality to the administered investigational product IOP</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of IOP</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days post-IOP injection</time_frame>
    <description>MTD is defined as the prior dose level below the dose level at which 2/6 subjects suffer dose limiting toxicities</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters-Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 days post-IOP injection</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax: the observed maximum drug concentration in plasma after dosing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters-Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 days post-IOP injection</time_frame>
    <description>Tmax: the time at which Cmax was reached</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters-AUC0-t</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 days post-IOP injection</time_frame>
    <description>the truncated area under the plasma concentration-time curve from the beginning of dosing to time t</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters-AUC0-inf</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 days post-IOP injection</time_frame>
    <description>the area under the plasma concentration-time curve from the beginning of dosing to time t (AUC0-t) extrapolated to time infinity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic parameters-T1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 days post-IOP injection</time_frame>
    <description>terminal elimination half-life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in laboratory safety tests (hematology, biochemistry, urinalysis, bleeding time) from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days post-IOP injection</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphatic Metastasis</condition>
  <condition>Liver Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IOP Injection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 1 injection of the IOP at Days 1,once time.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>0.9% normal saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 1 injection of 0.9% normal saline at Days 1,once time.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IOP Injection</intervention_name>
    <description>IOP Injection 20 mg Fe/ml, intravenous injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>IOP Injection</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Iron oxide nano particle m-PEG-silane</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>0.9% normal saline</intervention_name>
    <description>0.9% normal saline 10 ml, intravenous injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>0.9% normal saline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sodium Chloride</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male, age ≥ 20 ~40 years old with BMI between 18 and 27.

          2. Subject must be in good general health condition (i.e., full physical examinations,
             medical history, vital signs, ECG, and clinical laboratory tests performed at
             screening) as determined by the investigator. Normal ECG is defined as normal cardiac
             conduction parameters including resting heart rate between 50 and 100 bpm,
             Fridericia-corrected QT interval (QTcF) ≤ 450 milliseconds, and QRS interval &lt; 120
             milliseconds.

          3. Subject shows normal biochemistry test results (within normal range or considered
             clinically normal by the clinical investigator) at screening including items as listed
             below:

               -  Blood urea nitrogen (BUN), creatinine, and uric acid.

               -  Albumin and total protein.

               -  Alkaline phosphatase, ALT,AST, and total bilirubin.

               -  Serum iron, total iron-binding capacity, serum ferritin,percent transferrin
                  saturation (TSAT), and transferrin.

               -  Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), Antibody
                  HBsAg (anti-HBs),and antibodies against HCV (anti-HCV).

          4. Subject shows normal complete blood count (CBC) test results (within normal range or
             considered clinically normal by the clinical investigator) at screening including
             items as listed below:

               -  Red blood cell (RBC) count and reticulocyte count.

               -  White blood cell (WBC) count with differential.

               -  Hemoglobin and hematocrit.

               -  Platelet count.

          5. Subject shows normal urinalysis test results (within normal range or considered
             clinically normal by the clinical investigator) at screening including items as listed
             below:

               -  pH, color, appearance, and gravity

               -  Erythrocyte, leukocyte, glucose, protein, ketones, and nitrite

               -  Drug and alcohol abuse screening test including morphine, 3,4
                  methylenedioxymethamphetamine(MDMA), 3,4-methylenedioxyamphetamine
                  (MDA),ketamine, codeine and alcohol.

          6. Subject shows normal bleeding time test results (within normal range or considered
             clinically normal by the clinical investigator) at screening including prothrombin
             (PT) and activated partial thromboplastin time (APTT).

          7. Male subjects must take reliable contraceptive method(s) during and after the study
             for a period of 14 days.

          8. No screening of drug or alcohol abuse within one year prior to study enrollment.

          9. Subjects are willing to comply with the protocol and sign informed consent form.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects have serious allergic history or known allergy to similar ingredients of the
             study contrast agent (i.e.,Gd-based and SPIO particles contrast agents).

          2. Subjects have been diagnosed of Hepatitis B or C, venereal disease laboratory screens
             or have been determined of positive result of human immunodeficiency virus test.

          3. Imaging and/or functional abnormalities of liver and/or spleen. That is,

               -  Subjects have been diagnosed of abnormal liver function and appearances through
                  medical histories, clinical laboratory tests, and imaging test including mild
                  fatty liver, iron deposition or any acute/chronic liver change.

               -  Subjects have signs of splenomegaly, enlargement of the spleen, or clinical
                  laboratory tests showing signs of spleen functional abnormalities.

          4. Subjects have been performed with any examinations with contrast agents applied within
             28 days before study.

          5. Subjects have alcohol or caffeine consumption within 48 hours prior to the
             administration of study contrast agent.

          6. Subjects are unable to undergo an MRI scan.

          7. Subjects have electronically, magnetically and mechanically activated implanted
             devices, including but not limited to automatic cardioverter defibrillators, cardiac
             pacemakers,insulin pumps, metallic splinters in the eye, ferromagnetic haemostatic
             clips in central nervous systems or vascular vessels.

          8. Subjects have participated in other investigational trials within 28 days prior to
             study enrollment.

          9. Subjects with active systemic infections, active and clinically significant cardiac
             diseases, active gastrointestinal ulcers, or medical conditions that may significantly
             affect action,adequate absorption and elimination of investigational contrast agent.

         10. Subjects have taken any food 6 hours prior to administration.

         11. Subject with conditions judged by the investigator as unsuitable for the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rheun-Chuan Lee</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Taipei Veterans General Hospital, Taiwan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Taipei Veterans General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei City</city>
        <zip>112</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 24, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 15, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 20, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 9, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 9, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 10, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphatic Metastasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

