<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02745847</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ChangH Hosp</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02745847</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Re-irradiation With Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy for Relapsed Pancreatic Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Safety and Efficacy of Re-irradiation With Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy for Relapsed Pancreatic Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Changhai Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Changhai Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The safety and efficacy of re-irradiation with stereotactic body radiotherapy for relapsed
      pancreatic cancer will be evaluated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pancreatic cancer is one of the most lethal malignant tumors, probably attributable to local
      recurrence deemed as a predominant factor influencing patients' prognosis and quality of
      life. Only 15%-20% patients are suitable for surgeries among those first diagnosed with
      pancreatic cancer and the 5-year survival rate of those patients with R0 resection is still
      less than 20%. Therefore, radiotherapy is becoming a promising method to improve survival.
      However, due to adjacent organs at risk, conventional external beam radiotherapy, besides
      long courses, sometimes results in severe radiation-induced toxicity, delaying the initial of
      thereafter treatment, such as chemotherapy, which reduces clinical benefits.

      A single-fraction dose in the gross tumor volume could be increased stereotactic body
      radiotherapy (SBRT). Furthermore, doses of organs at risk could also be reduced, thus
      effectively improving local control rates and reducing radiation related toxicity. Compared
      with conventional external beam radiotherapy, SBRT is proved to provide longer progression
      free survival and safe with combination of chemotherapy. Moreover, owing to short courses and
      low toxicity of SBRT, quality of life is largely improved.

      However, it was reported that progression usually occurred 2 years after the initial
      treatment. The most common failure pattern was local recurrence. Chemotherapy and supportive
      treatment were commonly used in relapsed pancreatic cancer but with unfavored outcomes.
      Palliative surgeries are performed in patients with recurrent pancreatic cancer in some
      studies. Nevertheless, because of bad medical conditions and high complication rates, many
      patients could not endure surgeries. Therefore, whether patients previously treated with SBRT
      could be re-irradiated is another challenge in the treatment of pancreatic cancer.

      Some studies have confirmed that improved quality of life and longer survival could be
      available with re-irradiation via SBRT in patients with relapsed pancreatic cancer. Real-time
      guiding and synchronous tracing of SBRT increase the doses of tumor volumes but decrease
      doses of organs at risk and toxicity, rendering SBRT as an alternative treatment for relapsed
      pancreatic cancer. Chris et al. demonstrated that 1-year local control rate was 70% after
      re-irradiation with SBRT in 14 patients and the toxicity was mild. Nergiz Dagoglu et al.
      showed that the median overall survival was 14 months and no grade 3, 4 and 5 toxicities
      occurred.

      From 2013-2015, we retrospectively reviewed medical records of 14 patients with relapsed
      pancreatic cancer re-irradiated with SBRT. All of their tumor markers and pain scores
      decreased and quality of life improved 3 months after re-irradiation. Hence, based on our
      experience, we attempt to prospectively evaluate the safety and efficacy of re-irradiation
      with SBRT for relapsed pancreatic cancer.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The median survival time will be determined.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The acute toxicities following SBRT will be determined by RTOG/EORTC Late Radiation Morbidity Scoring Criteria.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The acute toxicities are determined by RTOG Acute Radiation Morbidity Scoring Criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The late toxicities following SBRT will be determined by RTOG/EORTC Late Radiation Morbidity Scoring Criteria.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The late toxicities are determined by RTOG/EORTC Late Radiation Morbidity Scoring Criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The progression free survival time will be determined.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The objective response rates will be determined.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The rate is the ratio of the number of patients with complete remission and partial remission to the total number of enrolled patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The quality of life will be analyzed.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The analysis of quality of life is based on QLQ-C30.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The local recurrence free survival time will be analyzed.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The quality of life will be analyzed.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>The analysis of quality of life is based on QLQ-PAN26.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Re-irradiation with SBRT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with relapsed pancreatic cancer meeting all inclusion criteria will receive re-irradiation with SBRT.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Re-irradiation with SBRT</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients previously treated with SBRT with relapsed pancreatic cancer will be re-irradiated with SBRT.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Re-irradiation with SBRT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients were previously treated with five-fraction SBRT in our hospital

          2. The time from the end of first SBRT to local recurrence is more than 6 months

          3. Local recurrence of pancreatic cancer confirmed by imaging studies

          4. KPS≥70

          5. Age of 18-75 years old

          6. Blood routine examination: Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 ×109 cells/L,
             leukocyte count≥ 3.5 ×109 cells/L, platelets ≥ 70×109 cells/L, hemoglobin ≥ 8.0 g/dl

          7. Liver and kidney function tests: Albumin &gt; 2.5 g/dL, total bilirubin &lt; 3 mg/dL,
             creatinine &lt; 2.0 mg/dL, AST&lt;2.5 × ULN(Upper Limit of Normal)(0-64U/L), ALT&lt;2.5 ×
             ULN(0-64U/L)

          8. INR &lt; 2 (0.9-1.1)

          9. Ability of the research subject or authorized legal representative to understand and
             the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior surgery, chemotherapy or radiation for the relapsed pancreatic cancer

          2. Evidences of metastatic disease such as invasion of the stomach or duodenum confirmed
             by imaging studies

          3. The time from the end of first SBRT to local recurrence is less than 6 months

          4. KPS&lt;70

          5. Age&lt;18 or &gt;75

          6. Abnormal results of blood routine examinations and liver and kidney tests

          7. Patients with active inflammatory bowel diseases or peptic ulcer

          8. Gastrointestinal bleeding or perforation within 6 months

          9. Heart failure: NYHA III-IV

         10. Women who are pregnant

         11. Participation in another clinical treatment trial while on study

         12. Inability of the research subject or authorized legal representative to understand and
             the willingness to sign a written informed consent document
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Huo Jun Zhang, MD., PH.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Changhai Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yu Xin Shen, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+8615800523983</phone>
    <email>syx2005@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen W, Zheng R, Baade PD, Zhang S, Zeng H, Bray F, Jemal A, Yu XQ, He J. Cancer statistics in China, 2015. CA Cancer J Clin. 2016 Mar-Apr;66(2):115-32. doi: 10.3322/caac.21338. Epub 2016 Jan 25.</citation>
    <PMID>26808342</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tseng JF, Raut CP, Lee JE, Pisters PW, Vauthey JN, Abdalla EK, Gomez HF, Sun CC, Crane CH, Wolff RA, Evans DB. Pancreaticoduodenectomy with vascular resection: margin status and survival duration. J Gastrointest Surg. 2004 Dec;8(8):935-49; discussion 949-50.</citation>
    <PMID>15585381</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sener SF, Fremgen A, Menck HR, Winchester DP. Pancreatic cancer: a report of treatment and survival trends for 100,313 patients diagnosed from 1985-1995, using the National Cancer Database. J Am Coll Surg. 1999 Jul;189(1):1-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10401733</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>HUGUET F H P V D. Impact of chemoradiation on local control and time without treatment in patients with locally advanced pancreatic cancer included in the international phase III LAP 07 study. Journal of Clinical Oncology 5s(32): 4001, 2014.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moningi S, Marciscano AE, Rosati LM, Ng SK, Teboh Forbang R, Jackson J, Chang DT, Koong AC, Herman JM. Stereotactic body radiation therapy in pancreatic cancer: the new frontier. Expert Rev Anticancer Ther. 2014 Dec;14(12):1461-75. doi: 10.1586/14737140.2014.952286. Epub 2014 Sep 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25183386</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berber B, Sanabria JR, Braun K, Yao M, Ellis RJ, Kunos CA, Sohn J, Machtay M, Teh BS, Huang Z, Mayr NA, Lo SS. Emerging role of stereotactic body radiotherapy in the treatment of pancreatic cancer. Expert Rev Anticancer Ther. 2013 Apr;13(4):481-7. doi: 10.1586/era.13.19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23560842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yechieli RL, Robbins JR, Mahan M, Siddiqui F, Ajlouni M. Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy for Elderly Patients With Medically Inoperable Pancreatic Cancer. Am J Clin Oncol. 2017 Feb;40(1):22-26. doi: 10.1097/COC.0000000000000090.</citation>
    <PMID>24879474</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim CH, Ling DC, Wegner RE, Flickinger JC, Heron DE, Zeh H, Moser AJ, Burton SA. Stereotactic body radiotherapy in the treatment of pancreatic adenocarcinoma in elderly patients. Radiat Oncol. 2013 Oct 16;8:240. doi: 10.1186/1748-717X-8-240.</citation>
    <PMID>24131503</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rwigema JC, Parikh SD, Heron DE, Howell M, Zeh H, Moser AJ, Bahary N, Quinn A, Burton SA. Stereotactic body radiotherapy in the treatment of advanced adenocarcinoma of the pancreas. Am J Clin Oncol. 2011 Feb;34(1):63-9. doi: 10.1097/COC.0b013e3181d270b4.</citation>
    <PMID>20308870</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gurka MK, Collins SP, Slack R, Tse G, Charabaty A, Ley L, Berzcel L, Lei S, Suy S, Haddad N, Jha R, Johnson CD, Jackson P, Marshall JL, Pishvaian MJ. Stereotactic body radiation therapy with concurrent full-dose gemcitabine for locally advanced pancreatic cancer: a pilot trial demonstrating safety. Radiat Oncol. 2013 Mar 1;8:44. doi: 10.1186/1748-717X-8-44.</citation>
    <PMID>23452509</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mahadevan A, Miksad R, Goldstein M, Sullivan R, Bullock A, Buchbinder E, Pleskow D, Sawhney M, Kent T, Vollmer C, Callery M. Induction gemcitabine and stereotactic body radiotherapy for locally advanced nonmetastatic pancreas cancer. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2011 Nov 15;81(4):e615-22. doi: 10.1016/j.ijrobp.2011.04.045. Epub 2011 Jun 12.</citation>
    <PMID>21658854</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mukherjee S, Hurt CN, Bridgewater J, Falk S, Cummins S, Wasan H, Crosby T, Jephcott C, Roy R, Radhakrishna G, McDonald A, Ray R, Joseph G, Staffurth J, Abrams RA, Griffiths G, Maughan T. Gemcitabine-based or capecitabine-based chemoradiotherapy for locally advanced pancreatic cancer (SCALOP): a multicentre, randomised, phase 2 trial. Lancet Oncol. 2013 Apr;14(4):317-26. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(13)70021-4. Epub 2013 Mar 6.</citation>
    <PMID>23474363</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taniguchi CM, Murphy JD, Eclov N, Atwood TF, Kielar KN, Christman-Skieller C, Mok E, Xing L, Koong AC, Chang DT. Dosimetric analysis of organs at risk during expiratory gating in stereotactic body radiation therapy for pancreatic cancer. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2013 Mar 15;85(4):1090-5. doi: 10.1016/j.ijrobp.2012.07.2366. Epub 2012 Dec 27.</citation>
    <PMID>23273994</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sperti C, Moletta L, Merigliano S. Multimodality treatment of recurrent pancreatic cancer: Mith or reality? World J Gastrointest Oncol. 2015 Dec 15;7(12):375-82. doi: 10.4251/wjgo.v7.i12.375.</citation>
    <PMID>26689800</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miyazaki M, Yoshitomi H, Shimizu H, Ohtsuka M, Yoshidome H, Furukawa K, Takayasiki T, Kuboki S, Okamura D, Suzuki D, Nakajima M. Repeat pancreatectomy for pancreatic ductal cancer recurrence in the remnant pancreas after initial pancreatectomy: is it worthwhile? Surgery. 2014 Jan;155(1):58-66. doi: 10.1016/j.surg.2013.06.050. Epub 2013 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>24238124</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lominska CE, Unger K, Nasr NM, Haddad N, Gagnon G. Stereotactic body radiation therapy for reirradiation of localized adenocarcinoma of the pancreas. Radiat Oncol. 2012 May 18;7:74. doi: 10.1186/1748-717X-7-74.</citation>
    <PMID>22607687</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dagoglu N, Callery M, Moser J, Tseng J, Kent T, Bullock A, Miksad R, Mancias JD, Mahadevan A. Stereotactic Body Radiotherapy (SBRT) Reirradiation for Recurrent Pancreas Cancer. J Cancer. 2016 Jan 10;7(3):283-8. doi: 10.7150/jca.13295. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>26918041</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grimm J, LaCouture T, Croce R, Yeo I, Zhu Y, Xue J. Dose tolerance limits and dose volume histogram evaluation for stereotactic body radiotherapy. J Appl Clin Med Phys. 2011 Feb 8;12(2):3368. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21587185</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aaronson NK, Ahmedzai S, Bergman B, Bullinger M, Cull A, Duez NJ, Filiberti A, Flechtner H, Fleishman SB, de Haes JC, et al. The European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer QLQ-C30: a quality-of-life instrument for use in international clinical trials in oncology. J Natl Cancer Inst. 1993 Mar 3;85(5):365-76.</citation>
    <PMID>8433390</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fitzsimmons D, Johnson CD, George S, Payne S, Sandberg AA, Bassi C, Beger HG, Birk D, Büchler MW, Dervenis C, Fernandez Cruz L, Friess H, Grahm AL, Jeekel J, Laugier R, Meyer D, Singer MW, Tihanyi T. Development of a disease specific quality of life (QoL) questionnaire module to supplement the EORTC core cancer QoL questionnaire, the QLQ-C30 in patients with pancreatic cancer. EORTC Study Group on Quality of Life. Eur J Cancer. 1999 Jun;35(6):939-41.</citation>
    <PMID>10533475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 15, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 18, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 20, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 20, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Changhai Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Zhang Huo Jun</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Radiation Oncology Department</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

