<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01668940</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1000031589</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01668940</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Freezie Remedy to Alleviate Morning Sickness</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness of a Natural Non-medicinal Freezie Remedy to Alleviate Morning Sickness</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Hospital for Sick Children</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Hospital for Sick Children</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to assess the effectiveness of Lillipops in the
      improvement of morning sickness symptoms. Secondary objectives are to assess if there are any
      changes to concurrent symptoms that may intensify NVP, such as metallic taste or
      gastrointestinal issues (e.g. heartburn, acid reflux, indigestion and gas), as well as
      preference for freezie flavours.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Nausea and vomiting of pregnancy (NVP) is the most common medical condition of pregnancy,
      also known as morning sickness which affects up to 80% of pregnant women. Lillipops Iced
      Soothies are naturally flavoured freezies developed in the United Kingdom for women with
      morning sickness. They are available in 5 different flavours: grapefruit and tangerine, lemon
      and mint, chamomile and orange, lime and vanilla, and ginger. The flavours are derived from
      steam distillation of the peels (grapefruit, tangerine, lemon, orange, lime), mint leaves,
      and chamomile flowers to release and collect their essential oils. Vanilla pods and ginger
      are macerated and their resin is used. These flavours are chosen because they may provide
      relief of symptoms as they are either traditional remedies for NVP, such as ginger, or
      soothing and refreshing flavours, such as chamomile, vanilla and citrus.

      This study hypothesizes that using Lillipops Iced Soothies will reduce the severity of NVP
      symptoms according to the PUQE-24 (pregnancy-unique quantification of emesis and nausea)
      scoring system for nausea and vomiting of pregnancy. In addition, we hypothesize concurrent
      symptoms that may intensify NVP, such as metallic taste or gastrointestinal disorders (e.g.
      heartburn, acid reflux, indigestion and gas), will be alleviated. We hypothesize that
      improvements to NVP and concurrent symptoms will be greater with Lillipop freezies compared
      to another commercially available freezie.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study Lapsed in July 2014
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of Nausea and Vomiting of Pregnancy (NVP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, +1, +3, +5, +7 days</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the effectiveness of Lillipops in the improvement of NVP symptoms. The primary endpoint of interest is the severity of NVP as compared between the 4 groups, defined according to the PUQE-24 (pregnancy-unique quantification of emesis and nausea) scoring system for nausea and vomiting of pregnancy that was developed and validated by Motherisk.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concurrent Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, +1, +3, +5, +7 days</time_frame>
    <description>To assess if there are any changes to concurrent symptoms that may intensify NVP, such as metallic taste or gastrointestinal issues (e.g. heartburn, acid reflux, indigestion and gas). The secondary endpoint of interest is the effect of the 4 groups on the status of concurrent symptoms that may intensify NVP, such as metallic taste or gastroesophageal reflux disease, as well as preference for freezie flavours, according to the PUQE-24 (pregnancy-unique quantification of emesis and nausea) scoring system for nausea and vomiting of pregnancy that was developed and validated by Motherisk.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Freezie Flavour Preference</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, +1, +3, +5, +7 days</time_frame>
    <description>To assess preference for freezie flavours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">53</enrollment>
  <condition>Morning Sickness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lillipops Iced Soothies (4 flavours)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Initially, women will be given 1 multiflavour box of Lillipop samples minus the ginger flavour (4 flavours). Each box contains 24 freezies (20 mL each), 6 of each flavor. They will be told to eat the freezies as needed to alleviate symptoms, up to a maximum of 12 per day, and to not have any other popsicles, freezies or any ginger products throughout the duration of the study (7 days). They can request an additional multiflavour box of freezies at each follow-up, as needed.
All participants will initially receive counselling and advice by the Motherisk NVP Counsellor about symptom management. This includes advice about dietary, non-medicinal and medical treatments as per the Motherisk NVP protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lillipop Iced Soothies (Ginger flavour)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Initially, women will be given 1 Ginger flavor box of Lillipop samples. Each box contains 24 freezies (20 mL each). Each 20ml contains 80mg of dried ginger root. They will be told to eat the freezies as needed to alleviate symptoms, up to a maximum of 12 a day and to not have any other popsicles, freezies or other ginger products throughout the duration of the study (7 days). Due ginger's antiemetic property, a maximum daily dose is up to 1000mg/day of dried ginger root powder in pregnancy.They can request an additional box of freezies at each follow-up, as needed.All participants will initially receive counselling and advice by the Motherisk NVP Counsellor about symptom management. This includes advice about dietary, non-medicinal and medical treatments as per the Motherisk NVP protocol.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mr. Freeze Freezies (4 flavours)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Initially, women will be given 1 multiflavour box of Mr. Freeze samples. Each box contains 24 freezies (20 mL each), 6 of each flavor. They will be told to eat the freezies as needed to alleviate symptoms, up to a maximum of 12 per day, and to not have any other popsicles, freezies or any ginger products throughout the duration of the study (7 days). They can request an additional multiflavour box of freezies at each follow-up, as needed.
All participants will initially receive counselling and advice by the Motherisk NVP Counsellor about symptom management. This includes advice about dietary, non-medicinal and medical treatments as per the Motherisk NVP protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Natural Course Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Women will not receive any freezies and will be asked to not have any other popsicles, freezies or any ginger products throughout the duration of the study (7 days).
All participants will initially receive counselling and advice by the Motherisk NVP Counsellor about symptom management. This includes advice about dietary, non-medicinal and medical treatments as per the Motherisk NVP protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lillipops Iced Soothies (4 flavours)</intervention_name>
    <description>Lillipops Iced Soothies are naturally flavoured freezies developed in the United Kingdom for women with morning sickness. They are available in 5 different flavours: grapefruit and tangerine, lemon and mint, chamomile and orange, lime and vanilla, and ginger. The flavours are derived from steam distillation of the peels (grapefruit, tangerine, lemon, orange, lime), mint leaves, and chamomile flowers to release and collect their essential oils. Vanilla pods and ginger are macerated and their resin is used. These flavours were chosen because they may provide relief of symptoms as they are either traditional remedies for NVP, such as ginger, or soothing and refreshing flavours, such as chamomile, vanilla and citrus.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lillipops Iced Soothies (4 flavours)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mr. Freeze Freezies</intervention_name>
    <description>There are other commercially available freezies, such as Mr. Freeze. Mr. Freeze freezies contain simulated flavours of watermelon, cherry, blue raspberry and cream soda. However, there have been no reports, studies or claims that they are effective as a remedy for the treatment of NVP.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mr. Freeze Freezies (4 flavours)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lillipop Iced Soothies (Ginger flavour)</intervention_name>
    <description>Lillipops Iced Soothies are naturally flavoured freezies developed in the United Kingdom for women with morning sickness. They are available in 5 different flavours: grapefruit and tangerine, lemon and mint, chamomile and orange, lime and vanilla, and ginger.The flavours are derived from steam distillation of the peels (grapefruit, tangerine, lemon, orange, lime), mint leaves, and chamomile flowers to release and collect their essential oils. Vanilla pods and ginger are macerated and their resin is used. These flavours were chosen because they may provide relief of symptoms as they are either traditional remedies for NVP, such as ginger, or soothing and refreshing flavours, such as chamomile, vanilla and citrus.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lillipop Iced Soothies (Ginger flavour)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy between 4 and 12 weeks gestation.

          -  Pregnant women with NVP, regardless of treatment (if any) for their NVP.

          -  Provide the signed informed consent form prior to initial interview.

          -  Able to come in person to Sick Kids or meet at an agreed location.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Gestational age beyond 12 weeks of pregnancy.

          -  Pregnant women less than 18 years of age.

          -  Women who are not proficient in the English language.

          -  Unable to consume any of the ingredients listed in Lillipops or Mr. Freeze freezies
             due to allergies, medication interactions or other reasons.

          -  Women refusing to avoid sources of ginger products for the duration of the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shinya Ito, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Hospital for Sick Children</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Hospital for Sick Children</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5G 1X8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 16, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 16, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 20, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 22, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Hospital for Sick Children</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Shinya Ito</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Division Head, Clinical Pharmacology and Toxicology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Morning Sickness</keyword>
  <keyword>Lillipops Iced Soothies</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Obstetrics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Morning Sickness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>April 18, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

