<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01660087</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SERC/1121480001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01660087</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Diagnosis of Lung Cancer From Exhaled Breath With Silicon Biophotonic Device</brief_title>
  <official_title>Diagnosis of Lung Cancer From Exhaled Breath With Silicon Biophotonic Device.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National University Hospital, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National University Hospital, Singapore</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall objective of this proposal is to develop a non-invasive, inexpensive and accurate
      device that detects VOCs in exhaled breath for lung cancer screening. Toward this goal, the
      team will design and fabricate a biophotonic platform consists of arrays of silicon
      micro-ring resonator sensors coated with polymers with different organic functionalities, in
      which each sensor is widely responsive to a variety of VOCs for the detection of lung cancer
      by means of breath testing. The team will identify signature VOCs as lung cancer biomarkers
      by comparison VOC contents between alveolar gas that directly sampled from the nodule or mass
      and exhaled breath using gas chromatography/ mass spectrometry.

      The specific aims of this proposal are as followings:

      Aim 1: To develop a biophotonic platform for the detection of VOCs

      Aim 2: To achieve multiplex detection of VOCs with high sensitivity and specificity using a
      novel biophotonic device.

      Aim 3: To evaluate the device as a lung cancer screening tool by testing both healthy and
      lung cancer breath samples
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lung cancer is the leading cause of cancer deaths throughout the world and accounts for more
      than 1.2M new cases worldwide annually, making lung cancer one of the most serious public
      health problems in industrialized countries. Up to date there is no valid screening method
      for lung cancer. Thus it is often diagnosed at an advance stage when treatment is less
      effective, which consequantly leads to high mortality rate. However, with early diagnosis and
      treatment, the 5-year survival rate improves dramatically from 1% in stage 4, 20% in stage 3
      to 70% in stage 1 disease. Therefore early diagnosis plays a pivotal role in improving
      survival for this otherwise uniformly fatal disease. In recently studies, it was found that
      some of the products of metabolism, called volatile organic comounds (VOCs), are carried in
      the breath and can serve as biomarkers. Cancer cells produce different types of VOCs than
      normal cells do. More importantly, these VOC markers can be found in exhaled breath for
      cancer stages 1 through 4.

      Combining the strength of IME's in the biophotonics, the research groups at NUS in basic
      science and the NUH clinician's knowledge and expertise in lung cancer, this proposal is
      aiming to tackle the challenge of lung cancer screening by developing a non-invasive,
      inexpensive, and accurate sensor platform to detect VOCs in exhaled breath. The device will
      consists of arrays of silicon micro-ring resonator sensors coated with polymers with
      different organic functionalities, in which each sensor is widely responsive to a variety of
      VOCs. In this proposal, we plan to build a prototype device and test for the detection of
      VOCs in exhaled breath from healthy controls and lung cancer patients. The successful outcome
      of this proposal would have an immense impact on lung cancer management by enabling an early
      stage cancer screening.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 30, 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 30, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Identification of signature VOCs as ling cancer biomarkers by comparing VOC contents between alveolar gas from lung nodules and exhaled gas.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biophotonic platform for VOC detection</intervention_name>
    <description>Multiplex detection of VOCs with high sensitivity and specificity using a novel biophotonic device.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients aged above 21 years, capable of giving consent and suspected of lung
             cancer with radiological lung nodules and masses.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with contra-indications to bronchoscopy and CT-TTNA that include active
             myocardial ischemia, uncorrected coagulopathy, severe respiratory distress,
             uncontrollable cough, and pregnancy will be excluded. Before females in the
             reproductive age are recruited, urine pregnancy test will be performed and confirmed
             negative.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pyng Lee, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National University Hospital, Singapore</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mi Kyoung Park, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Institute of Microelectronics</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Microelectronics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>117685</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National University Hospital/ National University of Singapore</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>119074</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jemal A, Siegel R, Xu J, Ward E. Cancer statistics, 2010. CA Cancer J Clin. 2010 Sep-Oct;60(5):277-300. doi: 10.3322/caac.20073. Epub 2010 Jul 7. Erratum in: CA Cancer J Clin. 2011 Mar-Apr;61(2):133-4.</citation>
    <PMID>20610543</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>International Early Lung Cancer Action Program Investigators, Henschke CI, Yankelevitz DF, Libby DM, Pasmantier MW, Smith JP, Miettinen OS. Survival of patients with stage I lung cancer detected on CT screening. N Engl J Med. 2006 Oct 26;355(17):1763-71. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2008 Apr 24;358(17):1875. N Engl J Med. 2008 Apr 24;358(17):1862. N Engl J Med. 2008 Aug 21;359(8):877.</citation>
    <PMID>17065637</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sit AK, Sihoe AD, Suen WS, Cheng LC. Positron-emission tomography for lung cancer in a tuberculosis-endemic region. Asian Cardiovasc Thorac Ann. 2010 Feb;18(1):33-8. doi: 10.1177/0218492309352119.</citation>
    <PMID>20124294</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mahadevia PJ, Fleisher LA, Frick KD, Eng J, Goodman SN, Powe NR. Lung cancer screening with helical computed tomography in older adult smokers: a decision and cost-effectiveness analysis. JAMA. 2003 Jan 15;289(3):313-22.</citation>
    <PMID>12525232</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phillips M, Gleeson K, Hughes JM, Greenberg J, Cataneo RN, Baker L, McVay WP. Volatile organic compounds in breath as markers of lung cancer: a cross-sectional study. Lancet. 1999 Jun 5;353(9168):1930-3.</citation>
    <PMID>10371572</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phillips M, Cataneo RN, Cummin AR, Gagliardi AJ, Gleeson K, Greenberg J, Maxfield RA, Rom WN. Detection of lung cancer with volatile markers in the breath. Chest. 2003 Jun;123(6):2115-23.</citation>
    <PMID>12796197</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mazzone PJ. Analysis of volatile organic compounds in the exhaled breath for the diagnosis of lung cancer. J Thorac Oncol. 2008 Jul;3(7):774-80. doi: 10.1097/JTO.0b013e31817c7439. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18594325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Filipiak W, Sponring A, Mikoviny T, Ager C, Schubert J, Miekisch W, Amann A, Troppmair J. Release of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) from the lung cancer cell line CALU-1 in vitro. Cancer Cell Int. 2008 Nov 24;8:17. doi: 10.1186/1475-2867-8-17.</citation>
    <PMID>19025629</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phillips M, Altorki N, Austin JH, Cameron RB, Cataneo RN, Greenberg J, Kloss R, Maxfield RA, Munawar MI, Pass HI, Rashid A, Rom WN, Schmitt P. Prediction of lung cancer using volatile biomarkers in breath. Cancer Biomark. 2007;3(2):95-109.</citation>
    <PMID>17522431</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Di Natale C, Macagnano A, Martinelli E, Paolesse R, D'Arcangelo G, Roscioni C, Finazzi-Agrò A, D'Amico A. Lung cancer identification by the analysis of breath by means of an array of non-selective gas sensors. Biosens Bioelectron. 2003 Sep;18(10):1209-18.</citation>
    <PMID>12835038</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mazzone PJ, Hammel J, Dweik R, Na J, Czich C, Laskowski D, Mekhail T. Diagnosis of lung cancer by the analysis of exhaled breath with a colorimetric sensor array. Thorax. 2007 Jul;62(7):565-8. Epub 2007 Feb 27.</citation>
    <PMID>17327260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peng G, Trock E, Haick H. Detecting simulated patterns of lung cancer biomarkers by random network of single-walled carbon nanotubes coated with nonpolymeric organic materials. Nano Lett. 2008 Nov;8(11):3631-5. doi: 10.1021/nl801577u. Epub 2008 Oct 8.</citation>
    <PMID>18839997</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Machado RF, Laskowski D, Deffenderfer O, Burch T, Zheng S, Mazzone PJ, Mekhail T, Jennings C, Stoller JK, Pyle J, Duncan J, Dweik RA, Erzurum SC. Detection of lung cancer by sensor array analyses of exhaled breath. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2005 Jun 1;171(11):1286-91. Epub 2005 Mar 4.</citation>
    <PMID>15750044</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peng G, Tisch U, Adams O, Hakim M, Shehada N, Broza YY, Billan S, Abdah-Bortnyak R, Kuten A, Haick H. Diagnosing lung cancer in exhaled breath using gold nanoparticles. Nat Nanotechnol. 2009 Oct;4(10):669-73. doi: 10.1038/nnano.2009.235. Epub 2009 Aug 30.</citation>
    <PMID>19809459</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carlborg CF, Gylfason KB, Kaźmierczak A, Dortu F, Bañuls Polo MJ, Maquieira Catala A, Kresbach GM, Sohlström H, Moh T, Vivien L, Popplewell J, Ronan G, Barrios CA, Stemme G, van der Wijngaart W. A packaged optical slot-waveguide ring resonator sensor array for multiplex label-free assays in labs-on-chips. Lab Chip. 2010 Feb 7;10(3):281-90. doi: 10.1039/b914183a. Epub 2009 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>20090999</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 6, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 6, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 8, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Exhaled breath condensate (EBC) method</keyword>
  <keyword>Volatile Organic Compounds (VOCs)</keyword>
  <keyword>Endobronchial Ultrasound (EBUS)</keyword>
  <keyword>Confocal Endoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Exhaled alveolar gas</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Silicon</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

