<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03375125</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CSUB0138</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03375125</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>L. Reuteri ATCC PTA 5289 + L. Reuteri DSM 17938 in Pregnant Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety and Efficacy of L. Reuteri ATCC PTA 5289 &amp; L. Reuteri DSM 17938 in Pregnant Women to Improve Oral Health and Reduce the Risk for Prematurity or Intrauterine Growth Retardation (IUGR)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Innovacion y Desarrollo de Estrategias en Salud</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Bari</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>BioGaia AB</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Innovacion y Desarrollo de Estrategias en Salud</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Randomized controlled tril to evaluate the safety and efficacy for the combination of L.
      reuteri ATCC PTA 5289 &amp; L. reuteri DSM 17938 in pregnant women with periodontitis and/or
      gingivits to improve oral health and at the same time reduce the risk for prematurity or
      intrauterine growth retardation (IUGR).

      Women in this study wil receive L. reuteri Prodentis (L. reuteri DSM 17938 &amp; L. reuteri ATCC
      PTA 5289 ) at a dose of 2x10^8 Colony Forming Units (CFU). One lozenges is to be taken twice
      per day (one in the morning and one in the afternoon) giving a total daily dose of at least
      4x108 CFU/day since randomization until delivery. The control group will receive placebo
      lozenges which contains identical ingredients except for lacking the bacteria. One lozenges
      is to be taken twice per day (one in the morning and one in the afternoon. The study product
      will be kept refrigerated (+20 - +80 C)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale. Gingivitis and periodontitis represent highly prevalent oral pathologies in
      pregnant women. The physiological, immunological and endocrine changes imposed by pregnancy
      are associated with a greater predisposition for the development of gingivitis. Considering
      the potential association between the presence of gingivitis and the development of
      complications during pregnancy and the time of delivery (preeclampsia, preterm, IUGRs), it is
      important to evaluate the impact of early administration of a mixture of lactobacillus on
      improved health oral status, and at the same time assessing the effect on risk reduction of
      prematurity and/or IUGRs.

      For primary outcome the investigators will evaluate the changes along the study in the oral
      health status evaluated through a composite of Modified Gingival Index (Lobene) + Plaque
      Index (Silnes and Loe) + Gingival Bleeding Index + Probing pocket depth (PPD) and Clinical
      attachment level (CAL).

      For secondary outcomes the investigators will evaluate rate of prematurity and or
      Intrauterine growth retardation; changes in mother salivary markers of systemic inflammation;
      profile of inflammosome in placenta and new born cord blood; lactobacilli, bifidobacteria and
      streptococcus profile in vagina by RT-PCR (specific primers); changes during the study for
      oral microbiome Intervention group wil receive L. reuteri Prodentis (L. reuteri DSM 17938 &amp;
      L. reuteri ATCC PTA 5289 ) at a dose of 2x10^8 Colony Forming Units (CFU). One lozenges is to
      be taken twice per day (one in the morning and one in the afternoon) giving a total daily
      dose of at least 4x108 CFU/day since randomization until delivery.

      The control group will receive placebo lozenges which contains identical ingredients except
      for lacking the bacteria. One lozenges is to be taken twice per day (one in the morning and
      one in the afternoon. The study product will be kept refrigerated (+20 - +80 C)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">December 20, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized controlled trial, double blind allocation concealment, parallel assignment</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Randomization list will by assembled by independient organization not related with participant, care provider, investigators or sponsors. eCRF will include randomization selection</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of periodontal disease</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes along the study in periodontal disease evaluated through Modified Gingival Index</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prematurity risk reduction</measure>
    <time_frame>At delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of prematurity at moment of delivery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mother Inflammosome profile</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes in salivary biomarkers of inflammation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Placental Inflammosome</measure>
    <time_frame>At delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Profile of cytokines measured in placenta at delivery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in vaginal microbiome</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of vaginal lactobacilli, bifidobacteria and streptococcus microbiome by RT-PCR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intrauterine growth retardation (IUGR) risj reduction</measure>
    <time_frame>At delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of Intrauterine growth retardation (IUGR) at delivery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Newborn cord blood inflammosome</measure>
    <time_frame>At delivery</time_frame>
    <description>Profile of cytokines measured in new-born cord blood at delivery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Periodontitis and Pregnancy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Probiotic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>L. reuteri DSM 17938 + L. reuteri ATCC PTA 5289), dose of 2x10^8 Colony Forming Units (CFU). One lozenges will be taken twice per day (one in the morning and one in the afternoon) giving a total daily dose of at least 4x108 CFU/day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo will have identical appearance, taste, and flavor, except for lacking the bacteria. One lozenges will be taken twice per day (one in the morning and one in the afternoon)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Probiotic</intervention_name>
    <description>L. reuteri DSM 17938 &amp; L. reuteri ATCC PTA 5289 ) will be given at a dose of 2x10^8 Colony Forming Units (CFU). One lozenges is to be taken twice per day (one in the morning and one in the afternoon) giving a total daily dose of at least 4x108 CFU/day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Probiotic</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo will have identical appearance, taste, and flavor, except for lacking the bacteria. One lozenges will be taken twice per day (one in the morning and one in the afternoon)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy pregnant women

          -  Age (Italy: 18-40 years; Mexico: 15-40 years)

          -  Gestational week (Mexico: &gt;8 weeks and 16 weeks; Italy: &gt;8 weeks and 12 weeks)

          -  Mild to Severe Gingival and Periodontal disease verified by dentist using Lobene
             Modified Gingival Index, Plaque Index, Gingival Bleeding Index, probing pocket depth
             (PPD) and clinical attachment level (CAL)

          -  Signed Informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pathologic pregnancy (except for preeclampsia and/or bacteriuria)

          -  Severe obesity (Body Mass Index&gt;35)

          -  Use of any product containing probiotics 2 weeks before randomization

          -  Use of any product containing chlorhexidine 2 weeks before randomization

          -  Antibiotic therapy within 2 weeks before randomization

          -  Known allergies towards the ingredients of the experimental product

          -  Inability to comprehend to the study protocol

          -  Systemic diseases differnt that periodontal disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Pediatric. Università di Bari; Ospedale Pediatrico Giovanni XXIII</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bari</city>
        <zip>70121</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Flavia Indrio, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+393292938421</phone>
      <email>f.indrio@alice.it</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Guisseppe Loverro, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+393292938421</phone>
      <email>giuseppe.loverro@uniba.it</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Dr. Manuel Gea Gonzalez</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mexico city</city>
        <state>Tlalpan</state>
        <zip>14080</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Krasse P, Carlsson B, Dahl C, Paulsson A, Nilsson A, Sinkiewicz G. Decreased gum bleeding and reduced gingivitis by the probiotic Lactobacillus reuteri. Swed Dent J. 2006;30(2):55-60.</citation>
    <PMID>16878680</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Staab B, Eick S, Knöfler G, Jentsch H. The influence of a probiotic milk drink on the development of gingivitis: a pilot study. J Clin Periodontol. 2009 Oct;36(10):850-6. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-051X.2009.01459.x. Epub 2009 Aug 12.</citation>
    <PMID>19682173</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Harini PM, Anegundi RT. Efficacy of a probiotic and chlorhexidine mouth rinses: a short-term clinical study. J Indian Soc Pedod Prev Dent. 2010 Jul-Sep;28(3):179-82. doi: 10.4103/0970-4388.73799.</citation>
    <PMID>21157050</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Slawik S, Staufenbiel I, Schilke R, Nicksch S, Weinspach K, Stiesch M, Eberhard J. Probiotics affect the clinical inflammatory parameters of experimental gingivitis in humans. Eur J Clin Nutr. 2011 Jul;65(7):857-63. doi: 10.1038/ejcn.2011.45. Epub 2011 Mar 30.</citation>
    <PMID>21448219</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Iniesta M, Herrera D, Montero E, Zurbriggen M, Matos AR, Marín MJ, Sánchez-Beltrán MC, Llama-Palacio A, Sanz M. Probiotic effects of orally administered Lactobacillus reuteri-containing tablets on the subgingival and salivary microbiota in patients with gingivitis. A randomized clinical trial. J Clin Periodontol. 2012 Aug;39(8):736-44. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-051X.2012.01914.x. Epub 2012 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>22694350</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Stensson M, Koch G, Coric S, Abrahamsson TR, Jenmalm MC, Birkhed D, Wendt LK. Oral administration of Lactobacillus reuteri during the first year of life reduces caries prevalence in the primary dentition at 9 years of age. Caries Res. 2014;48(2):111-7. doi: 10.1159/000354412. Epub 2013 Nov 29.</citation>
    <PMID>24296746</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Toiviainen A, Jalasvuori H, Lahti E, Gursoy U, Salminen S, Fontana M, Flannagan S, Eckert G, Kokaras A, Paster B, Söderling E. Impact of orally administered lozenges with Lactobacillus rhamnosus GG and Bifidobacterium animalis subsp. lactis BB-12 on the number of salivary mutans streptococci, amount of plaque, gingival inflammation and the oral microbiome in healthy adults. Clin Oral Investig. 2015 Jan;19(1):77-83. doi: 10.1007/s00784-014-1221-6. Epub 2014 Mar 18.</citation>
    <PMID>24638207</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 29, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 12, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 15, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 12, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 12, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 15, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Innovacion y Desarrollo de Estrategias en Salud</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Pedro Gutierrez Castrellon</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of Research on Translational Research Center on Mother-Child Health</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Periodontitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fetal Growth Retardation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

