<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03373292</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Stenting2018-IJVS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03373292</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Endovascular Stenting Treatment for Patients With Internal Jugular Vein Stenosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Feasibility, Safety and Efficacy of Venous Stenting for Internal Jugular Vein Stenosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Capital Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Capital Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, randomized, single-center clinical study aiming to explore the safety
      and efficacy of venous stenting for patients with internal jugular vein stenosis (IJVS).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The role of isolated non-thrombotic IJVS in idiopathic intracranial hypertension has recently
      gained a vested interest. Compared with venous sinus stenosis, isolated IJVS at extracranial
      segments is more concealed and likely to be neglected, leading to misdiagnosis or treatment
      delay and subsequent exacerbation of clinical outcomes. Stenting seems to hold a potential of
      addressing the intracranial pressure elevation-associated clinical issues from etiological
      level, especially after medical therapy failure. The complications of stenting such as
      ipsilateral headache, restenosis, intra-stent thrombosis and hemorrhage have beem
      demonstrated in the settings of intracranial sinus obstruction and osseous
      impingement-associated IJVS, particularly bony structures between the styloid process and
      lateral mass of C1 that constrain the IJV. Nevertheless, so far, to the best of our
      knowledge, few or no stenting related adverse events have been found in isolated IJVS
      patients with venous stent implantation.

      In this study, 60 patients satisfied with the inclusion criteria will be enrolled and
      randomly allocated into two groups. The safety and efficacy of stenting in patients with
      non-osseous impingement-mediated IJVS will be analyzed. Other medical interventions will be
      guaranteed according to the best medical judgment from clinical practitioners.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correction of internal jugular vein stenosis (IJVS) and abnormal collateral veins</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 1, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The status of internal jugular vein blood flow and collateral veins will be evaluated by imaging modalities, mainly including: Jugular Vein Doppler Ultrasound, Magnetic Resonance Venography (MRV), Computed Tomography Venography (CTV) and Digital Subtraction Angiography (DSA).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The evaluation of cerebral spinal fluid (CSF) pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, immediately post-stenting, within 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>CSF pressure will be assessed by lumbar puncture.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The evaluation of headache</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, within 1, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The intensity of headache will be assessed with the Headache Impact Test-6 (HIT-6).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The evaluation of tinnitus</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, within 1, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The severity of tinnitus will be assessed by the Tinnitus Handicap Inventory Questionnaire (THIQ).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The evaluation of the severity of papilledema and other ophthalmological conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, within 1, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The severity of papilledema will be assessed based on Frisén papilledema grade (FPG) criteria; the assessment of other ophthalmological conditions including visual acuity, visual ﬁeld, and fundus etc. will be based on visual acuity chart, visual fields picture, and optical coherence tomography (OCT) etc.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in cerebral white matter (WM)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, within 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The characteristics of WM will be evaluated by Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The evaluation of cognitive function</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, within 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Cognitive function will be assessed with the Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE), the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA) and/or the Modified Telephone Interview for Cognitive Status (TICS-M).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The evaluation of mental status</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, within 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mental status will be assessed with the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS). The HADS score ranges between 0 and 21 for either anxiety or depression. A cut-off point of 8/21 is indicated for anxiety or depression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The evaluation of sleeping status</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, within 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Sleeping status will be assessed with the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI) and/or the Athens Insomnia Scale (AIS). The PSQI score provides an overall score ranging from 0 to 21, where a cut-off score of ≤5 denotes a healthier sleep quality. The AIS score provides an overall score ranging from 0 to 24, where a cut-off score of &lt;6 denotes a healthier sleep quality.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The extent of disability or dependence in the daily activities</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, within 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The extent of disability will be assessed by the modified Rankin Scale (mRS). (Score 0-no symptoms; score 1-no significant disability; score 2-slight disability; score 3-moderate disability; score 4-moderately severe disability; score 5-severe disability; score 6-dead.)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants with abnormal lab values</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, within 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Lab examinations such as hepatic and renal function, blood and urine routine will be recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants with procedure-related and/or stenting-related complications</measure>
    <time_frame>within 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The incidence of all cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>within 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Death secondary to any reasons</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Stent Stenosis</condition>
  <condition>Intracranial Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Headache</condition>
  <condition>Tinnitus</condition>
  <condition>Papilledema</condition>
  <condition>Visual Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Venous stenting (Group-1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this group will undergo venous stenting treatment at once after enrollment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stenting one-month after routine medical treatment (Group-2)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this group will undergo routine medical treatment for one month, followed by venous stenting intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Venous stenting for internal jugular vein stenosis</intervention_name>
    <description>After confirming the diagnosis of IJVS by Jugular Vein Doppler Ultrasound, Magnetic Resonance Venography (MRV) and/or Computed Tomography Venography (CTV), and excluding external compression-induced stenosis as well as other causes of intracranial pressure elevation, patients will be divided into two groups randomly (30 for each group: group-1 and group-2).
Patients in Group-1 will receive Digital Subtraction Angiography (DSA) immediately after enrollment, and trans-stenotic pressures (∆MPGs) will be measured, balloon angioplasty bridging venous stenting will be performed when their ∆MPGs of jugular veins are equal to or greater than 5.44 cmH₂O (4 mmHg).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Venous stenting (Group-1)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>One-month routine medical treatment followed by venous stenting for internal jugular vein stenosis</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients in Group-2 will receive routine medical treatment for one month. Afterwards, they will undergo DSA (the procedure is the same as that in Group-1).
Notably, patients in Group-2 with medical uncontrolled intracranial hypertension will be provided stenting of their jugular veins at any time during the one-month routine medical treatment, in attempt to reduce their intracranial pressure and ameliorate visual damages in time.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Stenting one-month after routine medical treatment (Group-2)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ranging from 18 to 80 years of age, both genders.

          2. Patients diagnosed with IJVS surrounded by abnormally and tortuous collateral veins
             verified by MRV, CTV and/or DSA.

          3. Pressure gradient across the stenotic segments is equal to or greater than 4 mmHg.

          4. Intracranial hypertension associated manifestations cannot be satisfactorily
             controlled by conservative or non-surgical therapies.

          5. Informed consent obtained from the patient or his/her health care proxy, able to
             cooperate follow-up visits.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. External osseous impingement associated IJVS.

          2. Contraindication to iodinated contrasts.

          3. Contraindication to general anesthesia.

          4. Contraindication to standard medical therapy such as Aspirin, Clopidogrel or
             anticoagulants.

          5. Intracranial abnormalities such as tumor, abscess, vascular malformation, cerebral
             venous sinus stenosis or thrombosis.

          6. Previous history of major surgeries within 30 days prior to inclusion, or scheduled
             for any of the procedures within 12 months after inclusion.

          7. Severe hematological, hepatic or renal dysfunctions.

          8. Current or having a history of chronic physical diseases or mental disorders.

          9. Pregnant or lactating women.

         10. Life expectancy &lt; 1 year due to concomitant life-threatening illness.

         11. Patients unlikely to be compliant with intervention or return for follow-up visits.

         12. No signed consent from the patient or available legally authorized representatives.

         13. Patients recruited to other clinical trials with medications or devices, which may
             affect the outcome of this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Xuming Ji, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Xuanwu Hosptial, Capital Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ran Meng, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Xuanwu Hosptial, Capital Medical University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ran Meng, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+86-10-83198952</phone>
    <email>Ranmeng2011@pku.org.cn</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Da Zhou, MD, PhD Candidate</last_name>
    <phone>+86-10-83198952</phone>
    <email>popdoctor@foxmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhou D, Meng R, Zhang X, Guo L, Li S, Wu W, Duan J, Song H, Ding Y, Ji X. Intracranial hypertension induced by internal jugular vein stenosis can be resolved by stenting. Eur J Neurol. 2018 Feb;25(2):365-e13. doi: 10.1111/ene.13512. Epub 2017 Dec 7.</citation>
    <PMID>29114973</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Higgins JN, Garnett MR, Pickard JD, Axon PR. An Evaluation of Styloidectomy as an Adjunct or Alternative to Jugular Stenting in Idiopathic Intracranial Hypertension and Disturbances of Cranial Venous Outflow. J Neurol Surg B Skull Base. 2017 Apr;78(2):158-163. doi: 10.1055/s-0036-1594238. Epub 2016 Nov 23.</citation>
    <PMID>28321380</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spitze A, Malik A, Lee AG. Surgical and endovascular interventions in idiopathic intracranial hypertension. Curr Opin Neurol. 2014 Feb;27(1):69-74. doi: 10.1097/WCO.0000000000000049. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24296639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 3, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 8, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 14, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Capital Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ji Xunming</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Vice President, Professor, Xuanwu Hospital</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stenting</keyword>
  <keyword>Jugular vein stenosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Intracranial hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>Headache</keyword>
  <keyword>Tinnitus</keyword>
  <keyword>Papilledema</keyword>
  <keyword>Visual impairment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Constriction, Pathologic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Headache</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tinnitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vision Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vision, Low</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Intracranial Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Papilledema</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

