<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03371147</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>JWCI-17-1001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03371147</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CancerLife: Patient-Driven Solution in Cancer Care</brief_title>
  <official_title>Patient-Driven Solution in Cancer Care: Improving Outcomes Using a Digital Information and Communication Platform</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>John Wayne Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CancerLife</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>John Wayne Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this study is to evaluate the use of a digital information and
      communication platform (DICP) in improving outcomes in patients with cancer and their
      caregivers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a nonblinded, randomized, controlled trial of a digital information and communication
      platform (DICP) in self-reporting and monitoring of cancer and cancer-treatment related
      symptoms compared with usual care

      Patients initiating and/or receiving systemic treatment for cancer will be enrolled in a
      nonblinded, randomized, controlled trial of a DICP in self-reporting and monitoring of cancer
      and cancer-treatment related symptoms compared with usual care. The study will require one
      (1) study encounter for consenting purposes.

      All participants entering their information on the registration page will be contacted by a
      study team member for informed consent. Eligible subjects who agree to participate in the
      study and sign the consent form will be will be screened for eligibility. Participants will
      be randomized 1:1 to two arms:

      Arm A will be asked to download a mobile application called CancerLife. CancerLife is a
      patient facing messaging app that gives cancer survivors and caregivers the ability to update
      family and friends of their health status through their existing social networks and at the
      same collect psychosocial and symptom reports that can be shared with the patients care team.
      Participants will be provided with online or printed instructions on the use of CancerLife
      and receive a user guide that they can refer on demand. CancerLife is a stand-alone
      application that is NOT integrated into the patient's electronic health record and will NOT
      trigger symptom alerts to the treatment team. Participants will be instructed to use the
      after-visit instructions provided to them by their treatment team for any symptoms or
      conditions that will require an evaluation by a healthcare provider.

      Arm B will receive usual care provided for in the clinics. Usual care may vary between
      institutions, practices, and providers. Usual care may consist of but is not limited to any
      combination of the following: history and physical examination, review of systems, distress
      screening, symptom assessment measures, and/or interval quality of life measures.

      Participants in Arm A will be asked to register on CancerLife to start using the broadcasting
      feature of the app. In addition, they will be asked to complete a series of questions through
      CancerLife at baseline and every 3 months for up to 2 years. Participants in Arm A will also
      be asked to complete FACT-G, GAD-7, DST, and QQPPI at those timepoints.

      Participants in Arm B will receive usual care provided for in the clinics. They will also be
      asked to complete the FACT-G, GAD-7, DST, and QQPPI at baseline and every 3 months for up to
      2 years..
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Reported Symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in severity and occurrence of symptoms</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-General (FACT-G): subscale scores are added to derive total FACT-G score (0-108). The higher the score, the better the QOL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Generalized Anxiety Disorder 7-item (GAD-7) scale: score is calculated by assigning scores of 0, 1, 2, and 3, to the response categories of 'not at all', 'several days', 'more than half the days', and 'nearly every day', respectively, and adding together the scores for the seven questions. Scores of 5, 10, and 15 are taken as the cut-off points for mild, moderate and severe anxiety, respectively. When used as a screening tool, further evaluation is recommended when the score is 10 or greater.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Depression Screening Tool (DST): score ranges from 0-6, patient with scores of &gt;3 should be further evaluated with other diagnostic instruments.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Emotional state</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Tone analyzer and sentiment analysis using IBM Watson</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Physician-Patient Interaction</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire on the Quality of Physician-Patient Interaction (QQPPI): 14 items with each item ranging from 1-5, higher scores indicating more favorable ratings</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Emergency department visits/hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of emergency department visits/hospitalizations</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">254</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CancerLife</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm A will be asked to download a mobile application called CancerLife. CancerLife is a stand-alone application that is NOT integrated into the patient's electronic health record and will NOT trigger symptom alerts to the treatment team. Participants will be instructed to use the after-visit instructions provided to them by their treatment team for any symptoms or conditions that will require an evaluation by a healthcare provider.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Arm B will receive usual care provided for in the clinics. Usual care may vary between institutions, practices, and providers. Usual care may consist of but is not limited to any combination of the following: history and physical examination, review of systems, distress screening, symptom assessment measures, and/or interval quality of life measures.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CancerLife</intervention_name>
    <description>CancerLife is a patient facing messaging app that gives cancer survivors and caregivers the ability to update family and friends of their health status through their existing social networks and at the same collect psychosocial and symptom reports that can be shared with the patients care team.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CancerLife</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &gt; 18 years

          -  Diagnosis of cancer

          -  Receiving systemic treatment (chemotherapy, biotherapy/immunotherapy, hormonal
             therapy) that is expected to continue for at least 3 treatment sessions (approximately
             9 weeks) from the time of enrollment

          -  Karnofsky Index ≥50%

          -  Able to understand and sign informed consent

          -  Owns and able to use an electronic communication device (smart phone, tablet, laptop,
             desktop) and answer simple self-report questionnaires on their own

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Relevant cognitive impairment

          -  Participating in a therapeutic clinical trial

          -  Unable to read and comprehend English language text
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Santosh Kesari, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>John Wayne Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marlon G Saria, PhD, RN</last_name>
    <phone>3105827340</phone>
    <email>familycaregivers@providence.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 7, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 7, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 13, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

