<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03482128</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STZ-Dendrite11-15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03482128</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Blood Transfusion and Postoperative Outcome Before and After Implementing a Coagulation Management Algorithm</brief_title>
  <acronym>SONALG</acronym>
  <official_title>Allogeneic Blood Transfusion and Postoperative Outcome Before and After Implementing a SONOCLOT Based Coagulation Management Algorithm in Cardiac Surgery: A Quality Control Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Triemli Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Zurich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Triemli Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Implementing coagulation management algorithms based on Point-of-care (POC) testing devices
      such as thromboelastography (TEG) or rotational thromboelastometry (ROTEM) have been shown to
      reduce transfusion rates and the occurrence of adverse patient outcomes. Apart from the TEG
      and ROTEM, another viscoelastic POC measurement technique, the SONOCLOT, can be easily used
      at the bedsite. However Information regarding a SONOCLOT based coagulation management
      algorithm however is lacking.

      Transfusion rates of allogeneic blood products (Red blood cells = RBC, Fresh frozen plasma =
      FFP, Platelet concentrates = PLT) and patient adverse outcomes in two cohorts before and
      after the implementation of a SONOCLOT based coagulation management algorithm were evaluated
      on an observational basis in 1754 patients undergoing different types of cardiac surgery. The
      effect of the cohort and 19 predictors on transfusion was assessed by relative R2-values
      obtained by bootstrapping and a hurdle regression model, comprising a binomial and a Poisson
      count component. Association of predictors with post-operative outcomes was assessed with a
      logistic regression model.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patient data and all relevant procedure related data of cardiac surgery procedures at the
      Triemli City Hospital, Switzerland are recorded in a dedicated database with the approval of
      the institutional research ethics board and patient informed consent. Data analysis focusing
      on coagulation management using a dedicated algorithm in the present quality control study is
      done for 1754 out of 2199 consecutive patients undergoing cardiac surgery comprising the
      initial cohort from 2009 to 2011 (before implementation of the algorithm) and the subsequent
      cohort from 2013 to 2015 (after implementation of the algorithm).

      In the time period analyzed for this study anesthesia and intensive care were performed
      according to standardized protocols. Fluid management was done with lactated Ringer's
      solution and synthetic colloids. Different blood conservation strategies were used and
      included consistently cell salvage, standardized application of tranexamic acid and
      retrograde autologous cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB) priming. Anticoagulant medication was
      suspended at least 5 days prior to surgery for all elective procedures. Hematocrit
      measurements were performed using a standard POC blood gas analyzer available in the OR.
      Indication for red blood cells (RBC) transfusion were a hematocrit (HCT) level below 21%
      during CPB, below 25% for patients with preserved left ventricular function and 28% for
      patients with a left ventricular function ≤ 30% and patients undergoing emergency procedures.
      Standard laboratory tests (blood count, international normalized ratio (INR) / prothrombin
      time (PT), activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) fibrinogen concentration (FIB) were
      routinely available for guiding transfusion of coagulation blood products. Coagulation
      management before the implementation of the algorithm was performed based on institutional
      guidelines in accordance with published recommendations. Kaolin activated clotting time (ACT)
      measurements were used to guide heparin and protamine management. After heparin reversal and
      ongoing bleeding prothrombin complex concentrate was applied at a PT ≤ 70% / INR threshold of
      1.5 and in selected cases with ongoing major bleeding fresh frozen plasma (FFP) was used to
      normalize PT/INR. Moreover, fibrinogen concentrate was given below a fibrinogen level of 1
      g/l. Platelet concentrates (PLT) were transfused when platelet count was ≤ 100 x 109/lit. PLT
      were also given in suspected platelet dysfunction. When severe bleeding occurred at the end
      of the surgical procedure coagulation management was started on an empirical basis by the
      anesthesiologist in charge.

      The SONOCLOT coagulation management algorithm is based on existing literature on this subject
      and the experience of the authors with the specific POC technique: It considers standard
      coagulation lab results and platelet function tests and includes the use of the MULTIPLATE
      analyzer. SONOCLOT measurements consist basically of three dedicated tests:

        1. A kaolin ACT that is being applied for heparin and protamine administration.

        2. A glass-bead ACT providing information about the initiation of the clotting process, the
           propagation of the coagulation and platelet function.

        3. A glass-bead ACT with heparinase in case the measurement has to be performed under
           heparin.

      First coagulation measurements in each patient undergoing cardiac surgery are executed in the
      pre-intervention period. The established baseline values trigger the preparation of
      coagulation blood products that will be applied in the post-interventional period. At the end
      of the surgical procedure, heparin reversal is performed according to the Bulls protocol.
      After initial antagonisation with protamine kaolin ACT and glass-bead ACT as well as a
      heparinase glass-bead ACT are done to primarily detect any residual heparin. For any
      registered serum heparin the treatment and measurement loop is repeated. In case of an
      ongoing bleeding after heparin reversal a surgery-related cause has to be excluded and then
      another treatment and management loop based on glass-bead ACT is initiated and repeated until
      coagulation has been restored. As soon as results of the standard lab test are available in
      the postoperative period these are included in the decision making process.

      Primary outcome parameters were transfusion rates during the operation and the treatment in
      the ICU. Secondary outcome parameters included morbidity: an mortality in the postoperative
      period during the hospital stay.

      Statistical analysis will be performed with the software package R. To compare
      patient-related demographic and perioperative data prior and post algorithm implementation
      and univariable analysis are performed. Based on the data format and distribution, either
      Fisher's exact test, t-tests or Wilcoxon rank sum test were applied. For the assessment of
      the difference of transfusion in the two cohorts and controlling potential influence of other
      factors two approaches have been chosen. First, after a continuity-corrected
      log-transformation of the units of RBC given, a sequence of preoperative and procedure
      related predictors were included in the analysis. To check for multi-colinearity, variance
      inflation factors are assessed with the R package. Furthermore, to assess the association
      between potential risk factors and the incidence of postoperative infections a generalized
      linear model with a binomial link and logit function was chosen and performed with the R
      package.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 31, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Transfusion requirement</measure>
    <time_frame>Postoperative hospital stay; on average 8 days</time_frame>
    <description>RBC-Red Blood Cells (units), FFP-Fresh Frozen Plasma (units), PLT-Platelets (units)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Postoperative hospital stay; on average 8 days</time_frame>
    <description>Infections, myocardial infarction, cerebrovascular insult, acute renal failure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>Postoperative hospital stay; on average 8 days</time_frame>
    <description>Death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1754</enrollment>
  <condition>Coagulation Disorder, Blood</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>preAlgorithm</arm_group_label>
    <description>Standard coagulation management of patients undergoing cardiac surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>postAlgorithm</arm_group_label>
    <description>Coagulation management guided by SONOCLOT of patients undergoing cardiac surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Coagulation management guided by SONOCLOT</intervention_name>
    <description>Application of blood products guided by SONOCLOT measurements</description>
    <arm_group_label>postAlgorithm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard coagulation management</intervention_name>
    <description>Application of blood products based on clinical experience of the anesthesiologist in charge</description>
    <arm_group_label>preAlgorithm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients undergoing cardiac surgery at the Triemli City Hospital
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion

          -  Patients undergoing cardiac surgery at the Triemli City Hospital

          -  Coronary artery bypass grafting

          -  Valve intervention (Aortic/Mitral/Tricuspid)

          -  Aortic surgery

          -  Time period before implementation of a coagulation management guided by SONOCLOT

          -  Time period after implementation of a coagulation management guided by SONOCLOT

        Exclusion

          -  Time period during implementation of a coagulation management guided by SONOCLOT

          -  Missing data in data base
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michele Genoni, MD, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Triemli City Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Triemli City Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zurich</city>
        <zip>8063</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Serraino GF, Murphy GJ. Routine use of viscoelastic blood tests for diagnosis and treatment of coagulopathic bleeding in cardiac surgery: updated systematic review and meta-analysis. Br J Anaesth. 2017 Jun 1;118(6):823-833. doi: 10.1093/bja/aex100.</citation>
    <PMID>28475665</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deppe AC, Weber C, Zimmermann J, Kuhn EW, Slottosch I, Liakopoulos OJ, Choi YH, Wahlers T. Point-of-care thromboelastography/thromboelastometry-based coagulation management in cardiac surgery: a meta-analysis of 8332 patients. J Surg Res. 2016 Jun 15;203(2):424-33. doi: 10.1016/j.jss.2016.03.008. Epub 2016 Mar 26.</citation>
    <PMID>27363652</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Whiting P, Al M, Westwood M, Ramos IC, Ryder S, Armstrong N, Misso K, Ross J, Severens J, Kleijnen J. Viscoelastic point-of-care testing to assist with the diagnosis, management and monitoring of haemostasis: a systematic review and cost-effectiveness analysis. Health Technol Assess. 2015 Jul;19(58):1-228, v-vi. doi: 10.3310/hta19580. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26215747</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 22, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Triemli Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Christoph K Hofer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. Dr. med</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>transfusion</keyword>
  <keyword>coagulation</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiac surgery</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Blood Coagulation Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemostatic Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

