<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03485521</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RC31/17/0156</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2017-A01609-44</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03485521</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Interest of Simulation as Part of the Procedure Tracheobronchial Aspiration</brief_title>
  <acronym>SIMREAL</acronym>
  <official_title>Interest of High Fidelity Simulation Training Beginning as Part of the Procedure Tracheobronchial Aspiration</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Toulouse</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Toulouse</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to compare a control group (Practical Work Group) with a High
      fidelity Stimulation group about competences and reasoning clinic.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Health simulation is in full development on the national territory (France). The medical
      profession and nurses use this mode of learning in initial training to improve the students
      skills The report of Pr Granry allowed an inventory of the simulation in France with as
      Leitmotiv &quot;never the first time for the patient&quot;. It has also put in place priorities for the
      coming years, one of which is to develop simulation in initial and in-service training. This
      learning technique is interesting according to several parameters. First,is the safety of
      care. A novice who has already practiced on a mannequin or in the context of the simulation
      will be able to better understand the situation of care in the clinical field. The quality of
      care is also improved by the practice of simulation including communication skills,
      psychomotor skills, respect for procedures and theoretical knowledge. This more or less
      faithful reproduction is all the more necessary as the duration of clinical placements is
      decreasing. Simulation is a way to mitigate this lack is allows a faithful immersion in the
      care environment. Despite all these positive points, physiotherapy is not yet very affected
      by the simulation as shown in the literature Gordon's review (2015). Initial training,
      continuing education has not to this day largely developed this teaching method . Some timid
      uses have taken place and for the most part in Anglo-Saxon countries with various modes of
      simulation. In France, certainly linked to the specificity of the profession, its
      implementation is delicate, even complicated. It remains anecdotal to this day.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 13, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 13, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 13, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>It is a pilot study, monocentric with randomization of para-medical personnel The randomization list is established by the researcher before the search begins. The strengths of the 3 treatment groups are balanced (15 per group). A document describing the randomization procedure is kept confidential.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Care Provider)</masking>
    <masking_description>The randomization list is established by the researcher before the search begins.
A document describing the randomization procedure is kept confidential.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the acquisition of the skills of a tracheobronchial aspiration procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>Two hours</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the acquisition of the skills of a tracheobronchial aspiration procedure by an audit grid learning according to two different groups (Stimulation group and Practical Work group), on a learner population in initial formation of Institut physiotherapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compare the components of clinical reasoning : self-confrontation and simulation</measure>
    <time_frame>Two hours</time_frame>
    <description>Compare the components of clinical reasoning in different training typologies : practical work by using simple self-confrontation and simulation The simulation is filmed to watch the action of the learner after with him and bring out the implicit part of the student's clinical reasoning during the performance of the act (self-confrontation).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Tracheobronchial Anomalies</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Practical Work</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>15 students who participate in a practical work lasting two hours about the procedures of the tracheobronchial aspiration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Stimulation Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group with competences and reasoning clinic 15 students Simulation with a procedural practice of tracheobronchial suction as part of a simulation sequence after reading the procedures of the tracheobronchial aspiration</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>The tracheobronchial aspiration</intervention_name>
    <description>Reading of the procedures of the tracheobronchial aspiration (legislative framework, rules of hygiene, procedures, undesirable effects) The Practical Group participates in a practical work lasting two hours and the Stimulation Group is in simulation with a procedural practice of tracheobronchial suction as part of a simulation sequence. This group benefits from the methodology of the simulation with a part of briefing, a part simulated session and to finish the debriefing.
The experiment finished with a real activity on patients with tracheotomy with in this environment the reproduction of the procedure</description>
    <arm_group_label>Practical Work</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Stimulation Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Learners: All second year students enrolled in initial training of the Institute of
             kinesitherapy of Toulouse during the year 2017-2018. In total 45 students.

          -  Patients :All adult patients with tracheotomy, and able to communicate. Patients
             hospitalized in the University Hospital de Toulouse

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Learners: Students absent on the day of the reading of the procedures

          -  Patients:Adolescent patients, child patients, Patients with a communication deficit,
             Patients under respirators
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Didier Alain, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Toulouse</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Toulouse</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toulouse</city>
        <zip>31059</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 30, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>High Fidelity Simulation Training</keyword>
  <keyword>physiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>tracheobronchial aspiration.</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

