<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03481907</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>26552436</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03481907</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Topical Collagen Powder for Healing of Acute Full-thickness Wounds</brief_title>
  <official_title>Topical Collagen Powder as a Wound Healing Adjuvant for Acute Full-thickness Punch Biopsy-induced Human Wounds: a Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Adam Friedman</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CPN Biosciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>George Washington University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We have designed a pilot study to investigate the effect and potential utility of topical
      NuvagenTM (collagen powder) on the rate and quality of wound healing in healthy volunteers
      using the punch biopsy method. After inducing an acute full-thickness wound, the rate of
      complete healing of a wound treated with topical NuvagenTM (collagen powder) will be compared
      to the rate of complete healing of a wound treated with primary closure with sutures, the
      current gold standard. Qualification and semi-quantification of histologic and
      immunohistochemical markers will be used to assess the maturity and structural stability of
      the wound bed. Positive findings would suggest that NuvagenTM (collagen powder) may be
      capable of stimulating the healing of acute wounds in a similar or even superior manner to
      primary closure, suggesting collagen powder may be used in place of sutures, and encouraging
      further studies to characterize its therapeutic potential in dermatologic surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 15, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>This is a self-controlled trial in which subjects will receive punch biopsies at sites on each leg, and will receive a different treatment on each of the 2 sites.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Wound Measurements.</measure>
    <time_frame>Photographs will be obtained on weeks 0, 1, 2, 4, 6, and 12.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in wound measurements will be assessed digitally from photographs of the wounds obtained at several distinct time points, both at the time of wounding and afterwards.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Tissue Sample Histopathology Staining.</measure>
    <time_frame>Skin biopsy samples will be obtained at weeks 0 and 4.</time_frame>
    <description>Skin biopsy samples obtained from patients will be stained using Masson's trichrome and CD31 antibody stains to assess change in collagen deposition and angiogenesis, respectively, at 2 time points.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Patient Overall Assessment Scale and responses to assess wound healing improvement.</measure>
    <time_frame>Patient Overall Assessment Scale scores and responses will be obtained at weeks 1, 2, 4, 6, and 12.</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will assess the change in overall improvement of their wounds using a 4-point scale, where 1 = excellent improvement, 2 = good / moderate improvement, 3 = no change, 4 = worsening. Improvement will be indicated by a decrease by ≥ 1 point compared to the previous assessment. Worsening will be indicated by an increase in this scale by ≥ 1 point compared to the previous assessment. Patients will also be asked preference between the collagen powder and primary closure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Pruritus Numerical Rating Scale to assess patient itch symptoms.</measure>
    <time_frame>Pruritus Numerical Rating Scale scores will be obtained at weeks 1, 2, 4, 6, and 12.</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will also score change in itch symptoms on the Pruritus Numerical Rating Scale, which ranges from 0-10, where 0 = no itch and 10 = worst itch imaginable. Improvement will be indicated by a decrease by ≥ 2 points compared to the previous assessment. Worsening will be indicated by an increase in this scale by ≥ 2 points compared to the previous assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8</enrollment>
  <condition>Wound of Skin</condition>
  <condition>Wound Heal</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Internalized Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive 2 punch biopsy created wounds, one on each thigh, which will be addressed with primary closure with sutures or will be treated with Nuvagen collagen powder at time of wounding and daily thereafter. Suture(s) will be removed in 2 weeks. At week four, the wounded site will be biopsied again for tissue collection/evaluation, and treated with primary closure again. Suture(s) will be removed within to weeks. For those using collagen powder, the biopsy site will be biopsied again at week 4, and wound care will again be with NuvagenTM collagen powder until closure.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Nuvagen Collagen Powder</intervention_name>
    <description>Daily application of Nuvagen collagen powder for 2 to 4 weeks following wounding</description>
    <arm_group_label>Internalized Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Outpatient, male or female subjects of any race, 18-75 years of age

          -  Able to understand the requirements of the study and understand and sign Informed
             Consent/HIPAA Authorization forms

          -  Patients willing to refrain from using topical medications to punch biopsy sites

          -  Patients who are willing to follow protocol instructions and return for follow-up
             visits

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients that have any medical or skin condition that could impair wound healing

          -  Patients that have used systemic medications that suppress the immune system within 5
             half-lives (if known), or 2 months of enrollment (i.e. corticosteroids)

          -  Patients that have applied topical steroids to the thigh(s) in the 2 weeks prior to
             enrollment

          -  Patients that are currently participating in an investigational study of a drug or
             device or have participated within 4 weeks of enrollment

          -  Patients that in the opinion of the investigator demonstrate evidence of unwillingness
             or inability to follow instructions or to complete the study

          -  Patients currently using systemic antimicrobials

          -  Patients with a history of diabetes mellitus

          -  Patients with a history of bleeding disorders or concomitant treatment with aspirin or
             anticoagulants (including heparin, low molecular weight heparin, warfarin,
             fondaparinux, or rivaroxaban)

          -  Patients with a history of keloids or hypertrophic scars

          -  Patients with other conditions considered by the investigator to be reasons for
             disqualification that may jeopardize subject safety or interfere with the objectives
             of the trial (e.g., acute illness or exacerbation of chronic illness)

          -  Patients with a known allergy or sensitivity to any component of the test medication
             (including bovine and/or collagen products) or local anesthetic agent used

          -  Current or previous users of tobacco products

          -  Recent alcohol or drug abuse is evident

          -  Pregnant females or nursing mothers. Eligible women of reproductive age will be
             required to have a negative urine pregnancy test at screening. They will also be
             required to be on at least 1 reliable form of effective birth control [examples:
             barrier method (condoms, diaphragm), oral, injectable, implant birth control or
             abstinence] during the course of this study and 30 days following the last treatment
             period.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Adam Friedman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>GW School of Medicine and Health Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Monica Rengifo Pardo</last_name>
    <phone>202-677-6160</phone>
    <email>mrengifopardo@gwu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>George Washington Medical Faculty Associates</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20037</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Azam A. Qureshi</last_name>
      <phone>202-741-3547</phone>
      <email>aqureshi@mfa.gwu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Monica Rengifo Pardo</last_name>
      <phone>202-677-6160</phone>
      <email>mrengifopardo@gwu.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Adam J. Friedman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 22, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>George Washington University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Adam Friedman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>collagen powder</keyword>
  <keyword>punch biopsy wound</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

