<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03484182</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HP-00077863</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03484182</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of an Interactive Web-Based Home Therapy Program After Stroke</brief_title>
  <acronym>STRONG</acronym>
  <official_title>Efficacy of an Interactive Web-Based Home Therapy Program in the Recovery of Arm and Hand Function Following Stroke: A Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Maryland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Maryland Rehabilitation and Orthopedics Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Maryland Medical Center Midtown Campus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Maryland Upper Chesapeake Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of South Hampton</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Maryland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Stroke is the leading cause of disability worldwide. Of the annual incidence of stroke
      (~750,000) in the USA about 60% fail to recover arm and hand use contributing to reduced
      quality of life for survivors and caregivers. How can therapists facilitate the
      rehabilitation of individuals with arm movement deficits and increase their quality of life
      over a long time period? It is known that principles of treatment including repetition,
      feedback, challenge and progression are important for producing recovery. The ability for
      patients to train at home and manage their own rehabilitation duration, intensity and
      progression, via effective self-management strategies, is vital. What is needed is an
      effective, easy to use, low cost system that self-motivates patients to intensively practice
      their therapy exercises at home while maintaining elements of repetition, feedback, challenge
      and progression. In this proposal the investigators intend to adapt just such a &quot;web-based
      system&quot; originally designed in the UK. The first version of the system has shown preliminary
      efficacy and feasibility in a small pilot study in UK. The investigators will adapt the
      system for use in the USA, with the assistance of consultants from the UK.

      The purpose of this study is to investigate the efficacy and feasibility of using a free,
      easy to use, interactive web-based upper extremity stroke rehab program on individuals with
      stroke who have recently been discharged from outpatient rehabilitation. The goal is to
      compare the home use of the web-based stroke rehab program with that of written exercises in
      a randomized controlled trial. The aims/objectives are to (1) adapt the existing system for
      use in America including adding bilateral activities and then to assess (2) motor function
      immediately before and after six weeks intervention and after twenty weeks follow up in order
      to support the efficacy of using this web-based intervention; (3) behavioral changes in
      motivation and self-efficacy at the same time points to understand the relationship between
      behavioral and motor function changes; (4) perceptions of patients and caregivers of the
      web-based program to understand feasibility and barriers to home use; and (5) perceptions of
      therapists to understand feasibility and barriers to clinic use.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective 1, Development of the expanded STROKE web program applicable to individuals with
      stroke in the USA.

      This is a necessary objective to achieve before the investigators can start the trial; but it
      has no associated hypothesis. One rationale is to expand the target population in terms of
      impairment severity based both on feedback from therapists and on the need to add more
      bilateral activities that are important for everyday use. The second rationale is to check
      that material is readable and applicable to individuals with stroke in the USA.

      Objective 2: To determine the immediate and durable motor function changes from a six-week
      web-based stroke rehab program vs. usual written exercise care in individuals discharged from
      outpatient therapy after a stroke.

      H1: Six weeks of web-based stroke training compared to six weeks of a written home upper limb
      exercise program will result in clinically meaningful and statistically significant
      improvement in upper extremity function immediately after the intervention and 4.5 months
      later.

      This primary hypothesis is justified based on the combination of two theoretical constructs
      as described earlier. First, there is evidence that web-based programs, based on Self
      Determination Theory principles, will show an increase in motivation to exercise vs. a
      control with no intervention in non-disabled individuals. Second, since the web-based program
      is also based on neuroplasticity and motor learning principles known to improve functional
      recovery, and not just physiological improvements, our participants should also improve their
      functional recovery rather than merely gain physical activity benefits while maintaining or
      even losing their functional level. Third, the pilot feasibility study supports this
      hypothesis for the immediate effect and, after the power analysis, for the follow up testing.

      Objective 3: To determine the immediate and durable behavioral benefits of a six-week
      web-based stroke program vs. standard care in individuals discharged from outpatient therapy
      after a stroke.

      H2: Six weeks of web-based stroke training compared to six weeks of a written home upper limb
      exercise program will result in statistically significant gains in motivation to exercise,
      self-efficacy and amount of practice time immediately after the intervention and 4.5 months
      later.

      This secondary hypothesis explores whether the STRONG program will improve the patients
      motivation to exercise and their self-efficacy, while the written exercise program has the
      opposite effect, by the end of the intervention. There is evidence from the non-disabled
      population that behavioral improvements such as increasing exercise time will occur when
      individuals are intrinsically motivated but this has not been shown in the stroke population
      using a LifeGuide platform web-based system27. Conceptually, we predict that individuals with
      stroke will also become intrinsically motivated, because the program incorporates design
      details that enhance feelings of autonomy, competence and relatedness. Therefore, based on
      SDT, participants will not only have a better functional level but an increase in
      self-efficacy, motivation and independence. Specifically, during the 4.5 months after
      training, participants in the STRONG web program will demonstrate this by maintaining an
      increased amount of practice even though the investigators will have withdrawn our external
      support from the therapist (but not the participants ability to communicate with friends).

      Embedded Qualitative Component. Qualitative work is based on inductive reasoning and is
      hypothesis generating rather than hypothesis testing 49. Therefore, the investigators do not
      offer specific hypotheses but outline some of the questions that will be asked to give
      meaning and a context to the use of the web-based program.

      Objective 4: To determine the perceptions of patients/caregivers to the use of a web-based
      stroke training program.

      Qualitative methods will be used to explore patient and caregiver experiences and perceptions
      of using the Web-based system as part of stroke recovery to answer questions such as - In
      what ways did the STRONG web program help or hinder their rehabilitation? What did
      participants like and dislike about it? How did participants use it and why? What
      difficulties did participants have with using it? How could it be better? What did
      participants perceive to be the 'added value' of using the STRONG web program over routine
      practice alone?

      Objective 5: To determine the perceptions of therapists to the use of a web-based stroke
      training program.

      Qualitative methods will be used to explore therapists' experiences and perceptions of the
      STRONG web program in order to answer questions such as - What are the most important/useful
      aspects of the STRONG web program. What are the most difficult/problematic aspects of the
      STRONG? When would therapists use it and why? Who is it most successful for and why? What
      does it add to routine practice? In what ways does it detract from or complicate routine
      practice?
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Wolf Motor Function Test Short Battery</measure>
    <time_frame>Change after 6 weeks training and 4.5 months after training</time_frame>
    <description>Upper extremity function measure- 6 timed tasks - Up to 2 mins per task permitted. Shorter time indicates better outcome</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fugl Meyer Upper Extremity Motor Performance</measure>
    <time_frame>Change after 6 weeks training and 4.5 months after training</time_frame>
    <description>Upper extremity impairment measure- 0- 66 higher score indicates better outcome</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of Life Habits</measure>
    <time_frame>Change after 6 weeks training and 4.5 months after training</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire for quality of life/ social participation- Assess 77 life habits across 12 domains- one scale indicates difficulty with tasks 0-9 score 9 indicating better function, and a level of assist scale 1- 5 with 5 indicating a higher level of satisfaction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke Self-Efficacy Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Change after 6 weeks training and 4.5 months after training</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire for self-efficacy 13 items rated on 0-10 Likert scale - higher score better</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stroke Rehabilitation Motivation Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Change after 6 weeks training adn 4.5 months after training</time_frame>
    <description>Motivational Questionnaire - 28 item scale higher scores indicated higher levels of motivation - 7 sets of questions rated on a 5 point Likert scale with 1 completely disagree and 5 completely agree - range 7 - 35</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Amount of Practice</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured throughout - Change in total time after 6 weeks training and 4.5 months training</time_frame>
    <description>time completing home exercises</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative comments on impressions of exercise from those in Experimental Group</measure>
    <time_frame>Change after 6 weeks training adn 4.5 months training</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of web-based program</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">134</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Home Exercise Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Web-based Home Exercise Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Web-based Home Exercise Program</intervention_name>
    <description>Home exercises that are guided by a web-based program</description>
    <arm_group_label>Web-based Home Exercise Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Home Exercise Program</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard paper-based home exercise program</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard Home Exercise Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inclusion:

               1. Individuals over 40 years who have Ischemic or Hemorrhagic stroke &lt;20 weeks prior
                  to recruitment: Controlling for age and type of stroke is less relevant for a
                  pragmatic trial. We chose &lt;20 weeks to allow the maximum time to enroll
                  participants and still ensure that after a 6-week intervention they will not be
                  beyond the 6 month time period typically used to demark the beginning of the
                  chronic time period.

               2. Discharged from outpatient rehabilitation (within a week): We chose this marker
                  to reduce confounds from continuing therapy services or from time spent without
                  opportunity to practice.

               3. Impaired upper limb function: Participants must have recognizable (observable)
                  dysfunction. They should also have the ability to move their hand forward by at
                  least 3 inches without trunk compensation and demonstrating anti-gravity
                  movement.

               4. Able to use or willing to learn how to use a computer/tablet based on
                  patient/caregiver self-report and judgment of patient's therapist: This is
                  necessary to access the web-based intervention.

               5. Able to provide informed consent based on judgment of patient's therapist:
                  Participants need to have enough cognitive and communication function to
                  understand instructions from the web-based program. This will be a preliminary
                  screen to reduce the numbers of failed screening at consent time.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  program. This will be a preliminary screen to reduce the numbers of failed screening
             at consent time.

        Exclusion:

          1. Co-morbidities such as neurological, orthopaedic and cardiovascular complications that
             compromise safety and participation: Based on the discharge orders from the hospital,
             if the patient is recommended to discontinue exercising their paretic arm, they will
             be excluded.

          2. Severe cognitive and communication problems indicated by failure to respond to
             two-step commands: Participants must be able to interact with the web-based
             intervention.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sandy A McCombe Waller, PhD, PT</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Maryland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jill Whitall, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Maryland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sandy A McCombe Waller, PhD, PT</last_name>
    <phone>410-706-0787</phone>
    <email>smccombewaller@som.umaryland.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Janice Abarro, BS</last_name>
    <phone>410-706-0856</phone>
    <email>jabarro@som.umaryland.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 15, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 29, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Maryland</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sandy McCombe Waller</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor, Director of Educational Affairs</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Upper extremity</keyword>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Web-based program</keyword>
  <keyword>Home exercise training</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

