<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03480581</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18-001-FB</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03480581</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Reverse vs. Forward ICARE Training Interventions</brief_title>
  <official_title>Impact of Reverse vs. Forward ICARE Training Interventions on Walking and Fitness of Individuals With Walking Disorders Arising From Neurologic Injuries or Illnesses</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Madonna Rehabilitation Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Madonna Rehabilitation Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to determine if training in both the forward and reverse modes on
      the ICARE (motor-assisted elliptical) contributes to improvements in gait and
      cardiorespiratory fitness.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A growing number of facilities are using the robotic ICARE, a motor-assisted elliptical, to
      improve walking and fitness in individuals with physical disabilities. The device promotes
      movements emulating the joint motions and muscle demands of normal gait and integrates design
      features that improve accessibility and usability (e.g., motor assistance, partial BWS,
      electronic height-adjustable seat, steps, ramp, wheelchair platform) compared to traditional
      ellipticals. A motor assists those with strength and/or endurance limitations to train
      (forward/reverse directions) at speeds up to 65 cycles per minute (CPM), thus creating
      opportunities for the mass repetition of a gait-like movement pattern that is often advocated
      as critical for behavioral and neurologic recovery. Individuals can over-ride the motor's
      assistance simply by training faster than the set speed. Documented improvements in walking
      and cardiorespiratory fitness in individuals with neurologic injuries and illnesses following
      an ICARE training program in the forward direction are promising.

      Reverse walking is one method clinicians have used to improve forward walking performance in
      patients with various neurological disorders. Although the ICARE allows for reverse training,
      and this feature has been used clinically, no studies to date have compared changes in
      walking and cardiorespiratory fitness arising from an ICARE training intervention performed
      in the reverse direction to those arising from an ICARE intervention performed in the forward
      direction. Thus, the purpose of this exploratory study is to compare gait and
      cardiorespiratory improvements arising from blocks (12-sessions) of forward vs. reverse ICARE
      training in participants with walking dysfunction. For this exploratory study, the
      investigators hypothesize that both forward and reverse training will contribute to
      improvements in gait and cardiorespiratory fitness. In addition, the investigators seek to
      understand whether the magnitude of change will differ between each form of training (i.e.,
      forward vs. reverse) and whether the order of training will impact the magnitude of change
      (i.e. block of 12-sessions forward followed by block of 12-sessions reverse vs. block of
      12-sessions reverse followed by block of 12-sessions forward). Measurements will be recorded
      immediately prior to intervention initiation (T0), following completion of the first training
      block (T1), immediately following completion of the second training block (T2), and 3 months
      following completion of the second training block (T3)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>10 Meter Walk Test Speed</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Average walking speed while traversing 10 meters</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak Oxygen Consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>This test of aerobic capacity quantifies the peak oxygen consumed while walking on a treadmill or rotating a crank ergometer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6 Minute Walk Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 minute explanation followed by 6 minute formal walk test</time_frame>
    <description>This sub-maximal exercise test measures the maximum distance walked during 6 minutes. It is used to assess aerobic capacity and endurance. Protocol includes 2 minute explanation followed by 6 Minute Walk Test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Energy Cost of Treadmill Walking</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>This metabolic test of walking efficiency measures oxygen consumed during treadmill walking and divides it by the treadmill's walking speed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiorespiratory Response During Treadmill Walking</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Ratings of perceived effort during graded exercise test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiorespiratory Response During ICARE Training</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 50 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Ratings of perceived effort while training on the ICARE</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Spatiotemporal Gait Measures</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Stride characteristics (e.g., cadence, stride length, single limb support time) recorded while traversing instrumented walkway</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timed Up and Go (TUG) Test</measure>
    <time_frame>8 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Time required to completed standardized TUG test, a measure used to assess a person's mobility that requires both static and dynamic balance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Neurological Injury</condition>
  <condition>Neurological Diseases or Conditions</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Reverse First ICARE Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will engage in 12-sessions in the reverse direction followed by 12-sessions in the forward direction.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Forward First ICARE Training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will engage in 12-sessions in the forward direction followed by 12-sessions in the reverse direction.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Forward First ICARE Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will engage in 12-sessions in forward direction, followed by 12-sessions in the reverse direction. Sessions will be scheduled 3 times/week with training parameters adjusted to progressively increase challenge as tolerated.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Forward First ICARE Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Reverse First ICARE Training</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will engage in 12-sessions in reverse direction, followed by 12-sessions in the forward direction. Sessions will be scheduled 3 times/week with training parameters adjusted to progressively increase challenge as tolerated.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Reverse First ICARE Training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Walking dysfunction from a neurologic injury or illness (e.g. stroke, brain injury,
             incomplete spinal cord injury, multiple sclerosis, Parkinson's disease, cerebral
             palsy);

          -  Able to stand (with or without a standing frame) for at least 5 minutes at a time;

          -  Able to follow simple commands; and

          -  Possess adequate judgment or communication skills to safely use the ICARE trainer.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Currently enrolled in an existing physical or occupational therapy program or an
             exercise program for their legs;

          -  Orthopedic conditions (such as bone fractures/breaks) that haven't healed;

          -  Unstable cardiac or respiratory conditions that would prohibit safe exercise;

          -  Pregnant or think they may be pregnant, given unknown but potential risk of vigorous
             exercise to the mother and/or the unborn fetus; and/or

          -  Experience self-reported pain that inhibits walking/exercise ability.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Judith M. Burnfield, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Madonna Rehabilitation Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Judith M. Burnfield, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>402-413-4505</phone>
    <email>jburnfield@madonna.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Guilherme M. Cesar, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>402-413-4503</phone>
    <email>gcesar@madonna.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Madonna Rehabilitation Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lincoln</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68506</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Judith M. Burnfield, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>402-413-4505</phone>
      <email>jburnfield@madonna.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Katie Graf, B.A.</last_name>
      <phone>402-413-4781</phone>
      <email>kgraf@madonna.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burnfield JM, Shu Y, Buster TW, Taylor AP, Nelson CA. Impact of elliptical trainer ergonomic modifications on perceptions of safety, comfort, workout, and usability for people with physical disabilities and chronic conditions. Phys Ther. 2011 Nov;91(11):1604-17. doi: 10.2522/ptj.20100332. Epub 2011 Sep 1.</citation>
    <PMID>21885449</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burnfield JM, Shu Y, Buster T, Taylor A. Similarity of joint kinematics and muscle demands between elliptical training and walking: implications for practice. Phys Ther. 2010 Feb;90(2):289-305. doi: 10.2522/ptj.20090033. Epub 2009 Dec 18.</citation>
    <PMID>20022994</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burnfield JM, Cesar GM, Buster TW, Irons SL, Nelson CA. Kinematic and muscle demand similarities between motor-assisted elliptical training and walking: Implications for pediatric gait rehabilitation. Gait Posture. 2017 Jan;51:194-200. doi: 10.1016/j.gaitpost.2016.10.018. Epub 2016 Oct 24.</citation>
    <PMID>27810692</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burnfield JM, Irons SL, Buster TW, Taylor AP, Hildner GA, Shu Y. Comparative analysis of speed's impact on muscle demands during partial body weight support motor-assisted elliptical training. Gait Posture. 2014;39(1):314-20. doi: 10.1016/j.gaitpost.2013.07.120. Epub 2013 Aug 3.</citation>
    <PMID>23973354</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buster T, Burnfield J, Taylor AP, Stergiou N. Lower extremity kinematics during walking and elliptical training in individuals with and without traumatic brain injury. J Neurol Phys Ther. 2013 Dec;37(4):176-86. doi: 10.1097/NPT.0000000000000022.</citation>
    <PMID>24189335</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim SG, Ryu YU, Je HD, Jeong JH, Kim HD. Backward walking treadmill therapy can improve walking ability in children with spastic cerebral palsy: a pilot study. Int J Rehabil Res. 2013 Sep;36(3):246-52. doi: 10.1097/MRR.0b013e32835dd620.</citation>
    <PMID>23370765</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yang YR, Yen JG, Wang RY, Yen LL, Lieu FK. Gait outcomes after additional backward walking training in patients with stroke: a randomized controlled trial. Clin Rehabil. 2005 May;19(3):264-73.</citation>
    <PMID>15859527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irons, S.L., et al., Novel motor-assisted elliptical training intervention improves Six-Minute Walk Test and oxygen cost for an individual with progressive supranuclear palsy. Cardiopulmonary Physical Therapy Journal, 2015. 26(2): p. 36-41.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nelson, C.A., et al., Modified elliptical machine motor-drive design for assistive gait rehabilitation. Journal of Medical Devices, 2011. 5(June): p. 021001.1-7.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nelson, C.A., et al., Modification of the Intelligently Controlled Assistive Rehabilitation Elliptical (ICARE) system for pediatric therapy. Published online, ASME Journal of Medical Devices. DOI: 10.1115/1.4030276., 2015.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irons, S.L., et al., Individuals with multiple sclerosis improved walking endurance and decreased fatigue following motor-assisted elliptical training intervention [Abstract]. Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, 2016. 97(10): p. e34.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burnfield, J.M., et al., Pedi-ICARE training improves walking and endurance of child with cerebral palsy. Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation, 2016. 97(12): p. E19-E20.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cesar, G.M., et al., Child with traumatic brain injury improved gait abilities following intervention with pediatric motor-assisted elliptical training: A case report. Journal of Neurologic Physical Therapy, 2017. 41(1): p. 84.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Madonna Rehabilitation Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Judith M. Burnfield, PhD, PT</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Institute for Rehabilitation Science and Engineering</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neurological</keyword>
  <keyword>Gait</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiorespiratory fitness</keyword>
  <keyword>Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Walking</keyword>
  <keyword>Locomotor training</keyword>
  <keyword>Robotics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nervous System Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trauma, Nervous System</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is no plan for sharing IPD.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

