<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03486106</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HM20010566</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03486106</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Music Distraction and Its Influence on Anesthetic Requirements During Elective Knee Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Music Distraction and Its Influence on Anesthetic Requirements During Elective Knee Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Virginia Commonwealth University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Virginia Commonwealth University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the effect of music and its influence on anesthetic requirements during
      total knee replacement surgery. Half of the participants will receive noise-cancelling
      headphones in the operating room, and the other half of participants will receive
      noise-cancelling headphones with music playing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Prior to surgery, patient participants will receive a combined spinal-epidural per VCU total
      joint protocol; the following steps are considered standard of care and not considered study
      procedures. The combined spinal-epidural procedure creates complete numbness below the
      abdomen down to the feet, which negates the need for general anesthesia. For patient comfort
      during the combined-spinal epidural procedure, a one-time dose of 2 milligrams of intravenous
      midazolam will be given; this dose is adequate for reducing anxiety while allowing the
      patient to maintain conversation with health care providers if necessary. The standard
      intrathecal dose for total knee replacement at our institution is 15 mg bupivacaine and 0.2
      mg preservative-free morphine; this dose will provide complete numbness to the lower
      extremities for approximately 3-6 hours. After this dose is administered, the patient will
      then be positioned appropriately in the operating room and vital signs will monitored per
      standard protocol.

      Each patient participant will be randomized to one of two groups. Participants in the control
      group will receive noise-cancelling wireless headphones that will not play any noise
      throughout the procedure. Participants in the experimental group will receive the same
      noise-cancelling wireless headphones but will be permitted to listen to the music of their
      choice while in the operating room. Music will be provided via Spotify, which is an Internet
      streaming music service, and will be played through headphones; this way, no other individual
      in the operating room will be distracted or influenced by the patient's music selection.
      Participants will not be able to change the Spotify channel. We will be using the paid
      Spotify service with no commercials. If participants opt to have the music stopped, we will
      withdraw them from the study and continue standard of care. The participants will have the
      music playing for about two hours. If the participant has no music preference, the music will
      be chosen for them and it will be the same for all participants that have no preference. The
      volume will be adjusted in the operating room until the participant approves of the volume by
      saying &quot;yes, the volume is good&quot; or giving another verbal cue of approval.The music will
      continue playing until the surgical procedure is complete and the patient has reached the
      post-anesthesia recovery unit.

      As stated previously, spinal anesthesia provides numbness that negates the need for general
      anesthesia, but patients often times need additional sedation, which will be defined as
      anesthesia medication that is used to treat patient anxiety and discomfort in the operating
      room. Patient participants in both groups will receive sedation via the same protocol, which
      is outlined below.

      Sedation will only be given as needed per patient request; the patient will be given a
      noise-making device (such as a rubber duckie that makes sound when squeezed) that will inform
      the anesthesia provider that the patient is uncomfortable and needs some sedation. A weight
      based dose of 0.3 micrograms per kilogram of intravenous propofol will be given for each
      patient request. This dose is expected to provide amnesia or light sleep for a few minutes.
      For patient safety, if the patient requests sedation more than once within a two minute
      window, the anesthesia provider will not administer any more medication during this two
      minute period. Additionally, the anesthesia provider may withhold sedation if he or she
      determines with physical exam and hemodynamic monitors that the patient is already
      over-sedated.

      After five propofol boluses have been given to a patient, a propofol continuous infusion will
      be initiated at 25mcg/kg/min. The patient may still request additional sedation with the
      request instrument if he or she is still conscious enough to do so. If the anesthesia
      provider has given more than five boluses even with the baseline propofol infusion, the
      infusion will be increased to 50mcg/kg/min. In the highly unlikely scenario that five
      additional boluses are required with a propofol infusion rate of 50 mcg/kg/min, the
      anesthesia providers and investigators will make a clinical decision as to what is the safest
      next step.

      There may be scenarios that warrant conversion to general anesthesia. These scenarios
      include, but are not limited to, hemodynamic instability, regurgitation of gastric content,
      obtundation, excessive agitation, and inadequate spinal anesthesia. The decision to convert
      to the general anesthesia will be made by the anesthesiologist and anesthesia provider in the
      operating room; implementation of this study should not prevent or delay this decision if it
      is necessary.

      Documentation will be completed by the anesthesia provider per standard protocol for
      electronic anesthesia charting at VCU. This will allow for data acquisition by the
      investigators through the anesthesiology printed record in Cerner.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraoperative propofol requirement</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The amount of propofol given in the operating room divided by duration of operating room time</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain score</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The study will collect the numerical pain scores during each four hour interval for a 24 hour time period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction score</measure>
    <time_frame>72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction will be determined through a hospital survey that is completed by the patient at the end of their hospital stay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Anesthesia; Functional</condition>
  <condition>Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Headphones without music</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the control group will receive noise-cancelling wireless headphones that will not play any noise throughout the procedure. They will also receive propofol for sedation as needed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Headphones with music</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the experimental group will receive the same noise-cancelling wireless headphones but will be permitted to listen to the music of their choice while in the operating room. They will also receive propofol for sedation as needed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Music</intervention_name>
    <description>Music will be provided via Spotify, which is an Internet streaming music service, and will be played through headphones; this way, no other individual in the operating room will be distracted or influenced by the patient's music selection.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Headphones with music</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Headphones</intervention_name>
    <description>All participants will receive noise-cancelling wireless headphones that they will wear in the operating room during the procedure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Headphones without music</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Headphones with music</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Propofol</intervention_name>
    <description>All participants will receive intravenous doses of propofol; the timing and frequency of the doses will be given when the patient indicates (by squeezing a rubber duckie) that he/she wants sedation medication.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Headphones without music</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Headphones with music</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. undergoing a primary elective total knee replacement by Dr. Gregory Golladay (VCU
             surgeon and co-investigator for this research study)

          2. 18 years of age or older

          3. eligible for spinal anesthesia (which will be determined by the health care providers
             during the standard pre-surgery clinic visits)

          4. mentally capable of understanding instructions on how to request anesthesia medication

          5. mentally capable of understanding instructions on how to rate pain scores, anxiety
             level, and patient satisfaction

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. identified as a member of a regulated vulnerable population (one exception: limited
             English proficiency does not preclude them from this study; translation documents are
             available)

          2. ineligibility for spinal anesthesia (which will be determined by the health care
             providers during the standard pre-surgery clinic visits)

          3. morbid obesity, BMI greater than 40

          4. allergy to propofol, midazolam, or morphine

          5. pre-operative daily opioid consumption of more than 10 mg oxycodone every 6 hours

          6. hearing impaired individuals
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bryant Tran, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Virginia Commonwealth University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bryant Tran, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(804) 663-3589</phone>
    <email>Bryant.Tran@vcuhealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Commonwealth University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23298</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu PY, Huang ML, Lee WP, Wang C, Shih WM. Effects of music listening on anxiety and physiological responses in patients undergoing awake craniotomy. Complement Ther Med. 2017 Jun;32:56-60. doi: 10.1016/j.ctim.2017.03.007. Epub 2017 Mar 31.</citation>
    <PMID>28619305</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kahloul M, Mhamdi S, Nakhli MS, Sfeyhi AN, Azzaza M, Chaouch A, Naija W. Effects of music therapy under general anesthesia in patients undergoing abdominal surgery. Libyan J Med. 2017 Dec;12(1):1260886. doi: 10.1080/19932820.2017.1260886.</citation>
    <PMID>28452603</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li J, Zhou L, Wang Y. The effects of music intervention on burn patients during treatment procedures: a systematic review and meta-analysis of randomized controlled trials. BMC Complement Altern Med. 2017 Mar 17;17(1):158. doi: 10.1186/s12906-017-1669-4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28302117</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alam M, Roongpisuthipong W, Kim NA, Goyal A, Swary JH, Brindise RT, Iyengar S, Pace N, West DP, Polavarapu M, Yoo S. Utility of recorded guided imagery and relaxing music in reducing patient pain and anxiety, and surgeon anxiety, during cutaneous surgical procedures: A single-blinded randomized controlled trial. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2016 Sep;75(3):585-589. doi: 10.1016/j.jaad.2016.02.1143. Epub 2016 Apr 25.</citation>
    <PMID>27125531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang Y, Tang H, Guo Q, Liu J, Liu X, Luo J, Yang W. Effects of Intravenous Patient-Controlled Sufentanil Analgesia and Music Therapy on Pain and Hemodynamics After Surgery for Lung Cancer: A Randomized Parallel Study. J Altern Complement Med. 2015 Nov;21(11):667-72. doi: 10.1089/acm.2014.0310. Epub 2015 Sep 2.</citation>
    <PMID>26331434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 20, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 26, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 3, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Propofol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

