<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03487042</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BSNUFCO2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03487042</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bimatoprost 0.03% Solution With NB-UVB Versus Their Use With Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser in Treatment of Generalized Vitiligo</brief_title>
  <official_title>Bimatoprost 0.03% Solution, NB-UVB and Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser in Treatment of Generalized Vitiligo</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Vitiligo is a chronic disorder of pigmentation characterized by the development of white
      macules on the skin due to loss of epidermal melanocytes. It affects approximately 0.5%-2% of
      general population world-wide, without predilection for sex or race.Vitiligo can be
      classified into segmental or non-segmental. Non-segmental or generalized vitiligo is the most
      common clinical presentation and often involves the face and acral regions.

      Multiple monotherapy modalities are established to treat vitiligo but the response is
      variable, unsatisfactory, and requiring a prolonged course. This problem is exaggerated by
      the multifactorial and polygenic nature of the pathomechanism of the disease. These facts
      pave the way to combination therapy that showed better and safe repigmentation response than
      monotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Bimatoprost 0.03% ophthalmic solution is a synthetic prostaglandin F2 alpha analog that is
      approved for the treatment of glaucoma and eyelashes hypotrichosis (Lee et al, 2017).
      Cutaneous hyperpigmentation of the treated sites has been reported as a side effect with this
      agent. Phototherapy (narrow band ultraviolet B (NB-UVB)) of wavelength 308 nm, is considered
      as a successful method of treatment of vitiligo. The cytotoxic T-cells accountable for the
      destruction of melanocytes and disappearance of melanin are eliminated by phototherapy
      through apoptosis (diffuse repigmentation) and UVB does stimulate melanocytic proliferation
      and their migration to the epidermis from nearby follicular units (follicular repigmentation)
      and perilesional active melanocytes (marginal repigmentation).

      In recent years, fractional carbon dioxide laser has been introduced as an add-on treatment
      for vitiligo. It represents a new modality for skin resurfacing based on the theory of
      fractional photothermolysis. The beneficial effect of fractional carbon dioxide laser on
      vitiligo is the release of cytokines and growth factors that act as mitogens for
      melanogenesis. It also alters the skin barrier, which results in increased penetration of
      topical drugs and ultraviolet (UV) radiation, so it can be used in combination therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Repigmentation of skin lesions</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will be followed up by two blind dermatologists after 3 months to detect:
The percent of repigmentation: that will be subjectively rated with a previously reported scoring system:
&lt; 25% repigmentation (poor).
25-50% repigmentation (fair).
50-75% repigmentation (good). -&gt; 75% repigmentation (excellent).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency and types of side effects</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency and types of side effects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vitiligo area scoring index score</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Vitiligo area scoring index score percent change will be calculated by subtracting the pre- procedure vitiligo area scoring index score from the post-procedure vitiligo area scoring index score and dividing by the pre-procedure vitiligo area scoring index score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The patient overall satisfaction will be assessed after 6 months according to Wong Overall satisfaction:
dissatisfied
neutral
somewhat satisfied
moderately satisfied
very satisfied</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Generalized Vitiligo</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Generalized vitiligo patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each patient with generalized vitiligo will be subjected to the following:
One side will be treated by narrow band ultraviolet rays sessions twice weekly for 3 months + topical bimatoprost 0.03% ophthalmic solution solution twice daily ( 1 drop for each 2 cm2 ) and the other side will be treated by topical bimatoprost 0.03% ophthalmic solution twice daily ( 1 drop for each 2 cm2 ) + narrow band ultraviolet rays sessions twice weekly for 3 months + 10.600-nm fractional carbon dioxide laser sessions twice monthly for 3 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bimatoprost 0.03% ophthalmic solution</intervention_name>
    <description>Each patient will be subjected to the following:
One side will be treated by narrow band ultraviolet rays B sessions twice weekly for 3 months + topical bimatoprost 0.03% solution twice daily ( 1 drop for each 2 cm2 ) and the other side will be treated by topical bimatoprost 0.03% twice daily ( 1 drop for each 2 cm2 ) + narrow band ultraviolet rays B sessions twice weekly for 3 months + 10.600-nm fractional carbon dioxide laser sessions twice monthly for 3 months.
Patients' Evaluation:
The recruited patients will be subjected to:
A) Full history taking. B) General clinical examination. C) Dermatological examination of the skin lesions. D) Vitiligo area scoring index score will be calculated for each patient E) Clinical photographs will be taken at baseline, after each month during treatment and after the end of treatment by 3 months.
F) A skin biopsy from the treated lesions for histochemical examination. F) Dermoscopic evaluation of the treated sites every 2 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Generalized vitiligo patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Narrow band ultraviolet rays B</other_name>
    <other_name>Fractional carbon dioxide laser</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients older than 12.

          2. Patients with non-segmental vitiligo.

          3. Lesions stable for at least one year.

          4. Patients who were unresponsive to medical treatment or photo therapy for at least 3
             months.

          5. No sex or site predilection.

          6. Bilateral and symmetrical lesions with maximum size of 10×10 cm.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients with active infection.

          2. Patients with sensitivity to bimatoprost or photosensitivity.

          3. Patients with history or active skin cancer.

          4. Pregnant or lactating females.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amira Abdel-Motaleb</last_name>
    <phone>01005263721</phone>
    <email>Amiraali21@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yasmin Tawfik</last_name>
    <phone>01006033331</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ezzedine K, Eleftheriadou V, Whitton M, van Geel N. Vitiligo. Lancet. 2015 Jul 4;386(9988):74-84. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(14)60763-7. Epub 2015 Jan 15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25596811</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alikhan A, Felsten LM, Daly M, Petronic-Rosic V. Vitiligo: a comprehensive overview Part I. Introduction, epidemiology, quality of life, diagnosis, differential diagnosis, associations, histopathology, etiology, and work-up. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2011 Sep;65(3):473-91. doi: 10.1016/j.jaad.2010.11.061. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21839315</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abdelghani R, Ahmed NA, Darwish HM. Combined treatment with fractional carbon dioxide laser, autologous platelet-rich plasma, and narrow band ultraviolet B for vitiligo in different body sites: A prospective, randomized comparative trial. J Cosmet Dermatol. 2017 Aug 20. doi: 10.1111/jocd.12397. [Epub ahead of print]</citation>
    <PMID>28834191</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee D, Mantravadi AV, Myers JS. Patient considerations in ocular hypertension: role of bimatoprost ophthalmic solution. Clin Ophthalmol. 2017 Jul 10;11:1273-1280. doi: 10.2147/OPTH.S118689. eCollection 2017. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28744094</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bagherani N, Smoller BR. Efficacy of bimatoprost in the treatment of non-facial vitiligo. Dermatol Ther. 2017 Mar;30(2). doi: 10.1111/dth.12409. Epub 2016 Aug 23.</citation>
    <PMID>27550870</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Salah Eldin MM, Sami NA, Aly DG, Hanafy NS. Comparison Between (311-312 nm) Narrow Band Ultraviolet-B Phototherapy and (308 nm) Monochromatic Excimer Light Phototherapy in Treatment of Vitiligo: A Histopathological Study. J Lasers Med Sci. 2017 Summer;8(3):123-127. doi: 10.15171/jlms.2017.22. Epub 2017 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>29123631</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Omi T, Numano K. The Role of the CO2 Laser and Fractional CO2 Laser in Dermatology. Laser Ther. 2014 Mar 27;23(1):49-60. doi: 10.5978/islsm.14-RE-01. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24771971</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim HJ, Hong ES, Cho SH, Lee JD, Kim HS. Fractional Carbon Dioxide Laser as an &quot;Add-on&quot; Treatment for Vitiligo: A Meta-analysis with Systematic Review. Acta Derm Venereol. 2018 Feb 7;98(2):180-184. doi: 10.2340/00015555-2836.</citation>
    <PMID>29110015</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wong L, Vasconez HC. Patient satisfaction after Nd:YAG laser-assisted lipolysis. Ann Plast Surg. 2011 May;66(5):561-3. doi: 10.1097/SAP.0b013e31820b3d1e.</citation>
    <PMID>21451378</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 11, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 3, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 3, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Aml Hassan Ali</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitiligo</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pharmaceutical Solutions</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ophthalmic Solutions</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bimatoprost</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

