<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03480971</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MBI-04-05</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03480971</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Radiation and Cisplatin Induced Toxicities With Tempol</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double Blind, Placebo Controlled Dose Range Finding Study to Assess the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, and Efficacy of Tempol for the Reduction of Severe Mucositis in Head and Neck Cancer Patients Undergoing Combined Radio- and Chemotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Matrix Biomed, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Maryland</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Matrix Biomed, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A 10 week trial to assess the ability of Tempol to prevent and/or reduce toxicities
      associated with cisplatin and radiation treatment in head and neck cancer patients. Over the
      course of the 10 week trial, mucositis, nephrotoxicity, and ototoxicity will be monitored and
      assessed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      One hundred and twenty (120) participants with head and neck cancer are scheduled to undergo
      combined radio- and chemotherapy (n = 120).

      Nearly all (90% to 97%) participants receiving radiotherapy in the head and neck will develop
      some degree of mucositis. Of these participants treated with radiotherapy with or without
      chemotherapy, 34% to 43% will present severe mucositis. As a result, the participant's
      quality of life is affected, hospital admittance rates are higher, the use of total
      parenteral nutrition is increased and interruption of treatment is more frequent, all of
      which compromise tumor control. Mucositis causes 9% to 19% of chemotherapy and radiotherapy
      interruption.

      A common chemotherapeutic agent used in head and neck cancer is Cisplatin. Cisplatin (cis-
      diamminedichloroplatinum(II), CDDP) is an antineoplastic drug used in the treatment of many
      cancers including testicular cancer, ovarian cancer, bladder cancer, head and neck cancer,
      esophageal cancer, small and non-small cell lung cancer, breast cancer, cervical cancer,
      stomach cancer, prostate cancer, brain tumors, neuroblastoma, sarcomas, multiple myeloma,
      melanoma, mesothelioma, Hodgkin's lymphoma, non-Hodgkin's lymphoma, pancreatic cancer, and
      thyroid cancer. While toxicities include ototoxicity, gastrotoxicity, myelosuppression, and
      allergic reactions, the main dose-limiting side effect of cisplatin is nephrotoxicity
      followed by ototoxicity.

      Tempol is a piperidine nitroxide. Nitroxides are a class of stable free radical compounds
      that have anti-oxidant activity protecting mammalian cells against numerous toxic agents
      including hydrogen peroxide, superoxide, and t-butyl hydroperoxide cytotoxicity. This
      anti-oxidant activity of Tempol has led to its investigation as a potential radioprotector
      and chemoprotectant. In radiation and chemotherapy, Tempol protects normal cells from
      radiation and cisplatin-induced damage; however, in cancerous or tumor cells, Tempol is
      reduced to its hydroxylamine form that does not and cannot protect the cells from radiation
      and cisplatin induced damage. This distinction is of particular importance in the setting of
      cancer treatment, in which both normal and tumor tissue is exposed to radiation and
      chemotherapy. Without using Tempol, both normal cells and cancer cells suffer from toxicity.
      Tempol is the only known compound to possess this functional duality. Because of Tempol's
      free-radical scavenging ability, this compound is able to prevent many of the toxicities
      associated with cisplatin and radiation treatment including the prevention of mucositis,
      nephrotoxicity, and ototoxicity.

      The first group 60 participants will be randomized 1:1 to either Tempol 600 mg daily or
      placebo. Assuming that treatment is well tolerated but ≥20% of the participants in the active
      arm have grade 3 or 4 mucositis, a second group of 60 participants may be enrolled, and
      randomized 1:1 to receive either Tempol 1000 mg daily or placebo.

      Throughout the treatment period, participants will take study medication twice daily on both
      chemo/radiation days and cancer treatment free days. On radiation/chemo days, participants
      will be instructed to take study medication 10 minutes before each proton therapy or
      radiation treatment (400 or 600 mg) and again in the evening (200 or 400 mg) no less than 6
      hours following the first dose. Participants will begin to take study medication two (2) days
      before their scheduled cancer treatment. When proton therapy or radiation is not
      administered, participants will take the medication twice daily, 400 mg or 600 mg in the
      morning and 200 mg or 400 mg in the evening. On the day of radiation therapy, study
      medication will be administered within 10 minutes prior to each course of radiotherapy.
      Participants will be instructed to hold the solution in their mouth swishing for
      approximately 30 seconds and then swallow.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mucositis</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the efficacy of Tempol in reducing the incidence severe mucositis defined as grade 3 or 4 on the World Health Organization (WHO) scale.
The incidence will measure the number of patients who experience grade 3 or 4 mucositis according to the World Health Organization (WHO) scale. A reduction in the number of patients who receive grade 3 or 4 mucositis over the course of the treatment is considered a positive change in incidence.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mucositis</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the efficacy of Tempol in reducing the duration severe mucositis defined as grade 3 or 4 on the World Health Organization (WHO) scale.
This duration will be measured by total number of days number a patient experiences grade 3 or 4 mucositis according to the World Health Organization (WHO) scale. A reduction in the total number of days a patient receives grade 3 or 4 mucositis over the course of the treatment is considered a positive change in duration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nephrotoxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in Serum Creatinine levels in active arm versus placebo arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nephrotoxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in Blood Urea Nitrogen levels in active arm versus placebo arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Ototoxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Maintenance of participant performance levels as measured on the Distortion-product otoacoustic emissions (DPOAE) scale prior to and following cancer treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mucositis</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the efficacy of Tempol in reducing the time to onset of grades 1-4 mucositis on the World Health Organization (WHO) scale.
This time to onset will measure the number of days after exposure to cisplatin before a patient experiences grade 1 through 4 mucositis according to the World Health Organization (WHO) scale. An increase in the total number of days before a patient receives grade 1 through 4 mucositis after cisplatin exposure is considered a positive change in time to onset.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Mucositis</condition>
  <condition>Nephrotoxicity</condition>
  <condition>Ototoxicity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active 600 mg Tempol Solution</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will take 600 mg of Tempol a day for the duration of radiation treatment (6-8 weeks)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Solution</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will take placebo solution everyday for the duration of radiation treatment (6-8 weeks)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tempol</intervention_name>
    <description>Investigational product is Tempol (4-hydroxy-2,2,6,6-tetramethylpiperidine-1-oxyl) oral solution. Tempol solution is an orange-colored, aqueous solution containing 7% Tempol along with xanthan gum, xylitol, aspartame, acesulfame potassium, sodium saccharin, alcohol, peppermint and wintergreen oils.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active 600 mg Tempol Solution</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>4-hydroxy-2,2,6,6-tetramethylpiperidine-1-oxyl</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Solution</intervention_name>
    <description>The placebo contains the same excipients as the active product plus FD&amp;C Yellow #6 for color matching.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo Solution</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Be ≥18 years of age with medically diagnosed squamous cell cancer of the head and neck
             (SCCHN);

          2. Be scheduled to receive definitive radiotherapy or proton therapy administered with a
             curative intent;

          3. If female and of child bearing potential, be using an effective birth-control method
             with a history of reliability for the individual participant;

          4. If male and of child bearing potential, adequate methods of contraception must be
             employed including use of condoms with spermicide. No sperm donation for 90 days until
             after the conclusion of the study;

          5. Must be receiving cisplatin for chemotherapy;

          6. Be properly informed of the nature and risks of the clinical investigation, comply
             with all clinical investigation-related procedures, and sign an Informed Consent Form
             prior to entering the clinical investigation;

          7. Must have a score 2 or less on the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG)
             performance status;

          8. Participant life expectancy ≥ 6 months; and

          9. Adequate baseline organ function (hematologic, liver, renal, nutritional and
             metabolic):

        Haematology:

        Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1.5 Hemoglobin ≥ 10 g/dL Platelets ≥ 100,000 per
        microliter of blood

        Hepatic:

        Total bilirubin ≤ 2 X (Upper limit normal) ULN Alanine amino transferase (ALT) and
        Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≤5 x ULN

        Renal:

        Serum creatinine ≤ ULN or, if &gt; ULN calculated creatinine clearance (CrCl) ≥ 60 mL/min.

        Nutritional and metabolic:

        Urine Albumin &gt; 3.0 mg/dl

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Prior radiotherapy of the head and neck;

          2. Have a clinically significant infection defined as any acute viral, bacterial or
             fungal infection, which requires specific therapy. Anti-infectious therapy must have
             been completed within 14 days of starting study treatment;

          3. Be taking any non-approved therapy for oral mucositis, including β-carotene,
             tocopherol, laser irradiation, brushing the oral mucosa with silver-nitrate
             prophylactically, systemic TGF-β (transforming growth factor beta), or systemic KGF
             (keratinocyte growth factor) during or within 14 days of starting treatment;

          4. Be taking mugard;

          5. Be taking prostaglandins, pentoxifylline or leucovorin during or within 14 days of
             starting treatment;

          6. Be rinsing with allopurinol, hydrogen peroxide, sucralfate, or chlorhexidine
             mouthwashes during or within 14 days of starting treatment;

          7. Have had a recent, serious, non-malignant medical complication that, in the opinion of
             the investigator, makes the individual unsuitable for study participation;

          8. Have used an investigational drug within 28 days of the initiation of study treatment;

          9. Have a history of a positive blood test for HIV;

         10. At the time of screening, having a significant active medical illness which, in the
             opinion of the investigator, would preclude completion of the study;

         11. Participants with a treatment plan consisting of chemoradiation followed by further
             chemotherapy;

         12. Participants with body weight less than 35 kg, 77 lbs;

         13. Women who are pregnant or who are breastfeeding;

         14. Participants with known hearing loss;

         15. Participants with known intolerance to platin drugs;

         16. History of insulin-dependent Diabetes Mellitus; and

         17. Participants with Hepatitis B/C.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Malyapa, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Maryland</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Benjamin J Crane</last_name>
    <phone>6264376506</phone>
    <email>bjcrane@matrixbiomed.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Maryland School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Robert Malyapa, MD</last_name>
      <phone>410-328-6080</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Robert Malyapa, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arany I, Safirstein RL. Cisplatin nephrotoxicity. Semin Nephrol. 2003 Sep;23(5):460-4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>13680535</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahmed LA, Shehata NI, Abdelkader NF, Khattab MM. Tempol, a superoxide dismutase mimetic agent, ameliorates cisplatin-induced nephrotoxicity through alleviation of mitochondrial dysfunction in mice. PLoS One. 2014 Oct 1;9(10):e108889. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0108889. eCollection 2014. Erratum in: PLoS One. 2014;9(12):e115983.</citation>
    <PMID>25271439</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scully C, Sonis S, Diz PD. Oral mucositis. Oral Dis. 2006 May;12(3):229-41. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16700732</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hartmann JT, Lipp HP. Toxicity of platinum compounds. Expert Opin Pharmacother. 2003 Jun;4(6):889-901. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12783586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sastry J, Kellie SJ. Severe neurotoxicity, ototoxicity and nephrotoxicity following high-dose cisplatin and amifostine. Pediatr Hematol Oncol. 2005 Jul-Aug;22(5):441-5.</citation>
    <PMID>16020136</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Samuni A, Winkelsberg D, Pinson A, Hahn SM, Mitchell JB, Russo A. Nitroxide stable radicals protect beating cardiomyocytes against oxidative damage. J Clin Invest. 1991 May;87(5):1526-30.</citation>
    <PMID>1850756</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Samuni A, Mitchell JB, DeGraff W, Krishna CM, Samuni U, Russo A. Nitroxide SOD-mimics: modes of action. Free Radic Res Commun. 1991;12-13 Pt 1:187-94.</citation>
    <PMID>1649088</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Samuni A, Krishna CM, Mitchell JB, Collins CR, Russo A. Superoxide reaction with nitroxides. Free Radic Res Commun. 1990;9(3-6):241-9.</citation>
    <PMID>2167262</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mitchell JB, Anver MR, Sowers AL, Rosenberg PS, Figueroa M, Thetford A, Krishna MC, Albert PS, Cook JA. The antioxidant tempol reduces carcinogenesis and enhances survival in mice when administered after nonlethal total body radiation. Cancer Res. 2012 Sep 15;72(18):4846-55. doi: 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-12-1879. Epub 2012 Jul 17.</citation>
    <PMID>22805306</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 8, 2018</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cisplatin toxicity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mucositis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pharmaceutical Solutions</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tempol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>TEMPO</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

