<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00505310</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ID00-168</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-02100</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00505310</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Biobehavioral Effects of Emotional Expression in Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Biobehavioral Effects of Emotional Expression in Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study will assess the psychological and physiological benefits of an emotional
      expression intervention in patients with renal cancer. Patients will be randomly assigned to
      an emotional expression writing group or to a neutral writing group. This study will also
      evaluate the extent to which psychosocial factors mediate the intervention program and
      predict patients' recovery and adjustment to treatment. Potential mediators include level of
      cognitive processing, social networks/interactions, and sense of coherence and ability to
      find meaning in the illness experience.

      Specific objectives of the proposed research are:

        -  To evaluate an emotional expression intervention in patients with renal cancer.
           Researchers will determine the extent to which an emotional expression writing-based
           intervention enhances adjustment during the first 12 months following diagnosis and
           treatment. Dimensions of adjustment will be assessed by examining indices of QOL, mental
           health, and stress (subjective symptoms of distress, perceived stress, and mood).

        -  To determine the effects of an emotional expression writing-based intervention on immune
           function. The immune measures assessed in this study will include both general and
           autologous tumor-specific immune responses including cytotoxicity to K562 target cells;
           cytotoxicity to autologous tumor target cells; and functional assessment of type-1 and
           type-2 cytokines using autologous tumor and polyclonal stimulants.

        -  To identify the psychosocial processes underlying the efficacy of the intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients in this study will already be scheduled for surgery/ablation, or for chemotherapy
      and/or radiation treatment. Patients undergoing surgery/ablation will complete some
      questionnaires about their mood and quality of life. These questionnaires will happen about 6
      weeks after their procedure, during their scheduled visit to M.D. Anderson to follow-up after
      their surgery. Patients scheduled to receive chemotherapy and/or radiation treatment will
      complete the same questionnaires around the time of their new patient consult visit at M.D.
      Anderson. They should take about 60 minutes to complete. About 8 teaspoons of blood will be
      drawn to measure immune function.

      Patients will then be randomly picked (as in the toss of a coin) to be in one of two groups.
      One group will be the emotional expression writing group. The other group will be the neutral
      writing group.

      Patients in both groups will be asked to write for 20 minutes on different topics at four
      different times. They will be asked to complete all assignments in their home. They will
      choose four separate times when they would like to do the writing assignments and a research
      assistant will prompt them with a phone call at those times. During these phone calls,
      patients will complete a brief mood evaluation before the start of the writing session. After
      20 minutes, patients will receive another phone call to signal that they should stop writing.
      A second mood assessment will also be given at this time. Patients will be provided with a
      pre-addressed, stamped envelope for mailing each writing sample back to M. D. Anderson the
      day after it is completed.

      Patients will complete some questionnaires about their mood and quality of life approximately
      1 month, 4 months, and 10 months after their last writing assignment. They should take about
      60 minutes to complete. About 8 teaspoons of blood will then be taken each time to measure
      immune function.

      This is an investigational study. As many as 710 patients will be enrolled in this study. All
      will be enrolled at M. D. Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To measure the psychological and physiological benefits of an emotional expression program in patients with kidney cancer.</measure>
    <time_frame>8 Years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To learn how the expression of emotions affects quality of life, stress, and immune function.</measure>
    <time_frame>8 Years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">710</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Emotional Expression Writing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 minutes of writing on different topics at four different times. Questionnaires about mood and quality of life completed 1 month, 4 months, and 10 months after the last writing assignment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neutral Writing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 minutes of writing on different topics at four different times. Questionnaires about mood and quality of life completed 1 month, 4 months, and 10 months after the last writing assignment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Writing</intervention_name>
    <description>20 minutes of writing on different topics at four different times.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Emotional Expression Writing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Neutral Writing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>Questionnaires about mood and quality of life completed 1 month, 4 months, and 10 months after the last writing assignment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Emotional Expression Writing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Neutral Writing</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Survey</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        1) Men or woman older than 18 years with stage I-IV renal cell carcinoma 2) Zubrod
        performance status of less than or equal to 2 3) have no serious intercurrent medical
        illness 4) read and speak English

        Exclusion Criteria:

        1) Score of 23 or below on the Mini-mental 2) History of primary or secondary
        immunodeficiency 3) Taking immunosuppressive drugs such as systemic corticosteroid 4)
        Patients who are undergoing a surgical procedure and do not sign the general tissue consent
        form 5) Patients with major psychiatric diagnoses or currently seeking psychological
        counseling.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lorenzo Cohen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 19, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 20, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 23, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Kidney Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Renal Cell Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Emotional Expression</keyword>
  <keyword>Writing</keyword>
  <keyword>Questionnaire</keyword>
  <keyword>Survey</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

