<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00505466</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BS99-038</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00505466</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Transition From Research to Disclosure in Human Genetics</brief_title>
  <official_title>Transition From Research to Disclosure in Human Genetics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to design a means of providing research families, from diverse
      geographical locations, the chance to receive genetic testing after having been educated by
      video, and meetings or telephone conversations with a genetic counselor/study professional.

      This is an investigational study. About 800 people will be offered genetic testing. This
      study is being performed only at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants will receive pre-test genetic counseling in one of three ways: (1) in person at
      MD Anderson; (2) by telephone with an MD Anderson Genetic Counselor/study professional; (3)
      with a local Genetic Counselor in conference with the MD Anderson Genetic Counselor/study
      professional. After receiving pre-test genetic counseling, participants will be given the
      opportunity to schedule a submission of a small sample of blood (about 6 tablespoons) for
      genetic testing for p53. You may have this blood test repeated if there are any problems in
      the lab. The study doctor will discuss this with you.

      Participants who submit a sample may choose to see a genetic counselor/study professional in
      person or schedule a phone conversation to receive the results of the genetic test. Genetic
      counseling may take place at MD Anderson at no cost. Participants may wish to have counseling
      close to their home, though they then are responsible for the cost of the counseling. If,
      after talking to the counselor/study professional, the participant wants to know the results
      of the test, he or she will be told. A participant will be given more counseling and advice
      on what other care might be needed and what other actions they should take.

      The test results will be kept private. Names will not be used in computer records.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 6, 1999</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Received Pre-test Genetic Counseling</measure>
    <time_frame>10 Years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants completing genetic testing for p53</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to time of follow-up (2 weeks, 6, and 12 months)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">800</enrollment>
  <condition>Education</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-Test Genetic Counseling + Genetic Sample</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Genetic Counseling</intervention_name>
    <description>Genetic counseling conducted in person, by telephone with an M. D. Anderson Genetic Counselor, or with a local Genetic Counselor in conference with the M. D. Anderson Genetic Counselor.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-Test Genetic Counseling + Genetic Sample</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Optional small sample of blood (about 6 tablespoons) for genetic testing for p53 following
      pre-test genetic counseling.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patient diagnosed with cancer or a participant with a family member who has had cancer.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        2.0 Genetic testing

        Members of families who have participated in the p53 project through Dr. Strong's lab are
        eligible, via protocol P90-001. There are at least 145 kindreds including at least 800
        participants living who may be at risk of carrying a p53 germline mutation. The
        participants must provide an informed consent and be 18 years or older. We will include
        English and non-English speaking participants. For non-English speaking participants to be
        recruited, the consent documents has been translated into the language of the target
        population in accordance with the IRB procedures.

        2.1 Parents Attitudes toward testing children at risk for TP53 mutations

        For the survey portion of this study, we will invite individuals who 1) are already
        enrolled in the P90-001 study), 2) have been known to carry a germline p53 mutation, and 3)
        have children who are less than 27 years old. Patients who agree to enroll in the survey
        portion of the study will be presented with a consent statement and a printed copy of the
        survey along with a postage-paid envelope which they can return (either by mail or in
        person) at their convenience.

        2.2 Psychosocial impact of participating in LFS screening

          1. Adults who have undergone genetic testing and have a confirmed p53 mutation

          2. Adults participating in LFS screening program

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Louise C. Strong, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Louise C. Strong, MD</last_name>
    <phone>713-792-7555</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Louise C. Strong, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 19, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 20, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 23, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 15, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Human Genetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetic Counseling</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetic Testing</keyword>
  <keyword>p53 Mutation</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetics</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

