<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00503087</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TASMC 07- TL -268 CTIL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00503087</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Pain Reduction in the Administration of Saline Injections by the Usage of Pneumatic Skin Flattening</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Pain Reduction in the Administration of Saline Injections by the Usage of Pneumatic Skin Flattening (PSF)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PalJect Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PalJect Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Each participant will be administered 2 injections of saline - the first in the right gluteal
      area and the second in the left gluteal area. Both injections will be administered
      intra-muscularly by the same clinician. One injection will be given with vacuum (Pneumatic
      Skin Flattening or PSF Machine) and the other without vacuum. The order of the injections
      will be randomly assigned. Each subject will serve as a control for himself. Between
      injections a 30 min pause will be given to minimize pain sensation bias of the previous
      injection. Immediately after each injection the pain level will be assessed by the VAS scale.
      The researcher assessing the pain will be blinded for the type of injection given. The
      evaluation of the pain reduction will be made by comparison of the pain level with and
      without the application of the PSF.

      Hypothesis: PSF Technique will reduce the pain associated with saline injections.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Injections are currently the gold-standard for administrating various medications
      parenterally. The most significant side-effect related to injections is the accompanying
      pain. Injection pain is related to the penetration of the skin by the needle and to the
      mechanical and chemical effects of the drug during and after its injection. This pain remains
      a major obstacle in medication administration in children as well as in other populations
      subject to needle-phobia because of the pain experience. The associated pain may thus prevent
      optimized medical care for these patients.

      Current methods to alleviate immediate pain include the utilization of topical anesthesia
      whereas some patients do not utilize any form of pain relief and simply endure the pain of
      the injection. Other methods for pain reduction are taking advantage of the applying pressure
      or vibration to alleviate pain. These methods have resulted in a number of pain relieving
      devices currently on the market. Such predicate devices primarily involve vibration devices
      commonly used to alleviate the injection pain. Published data suggests possible use of
      pressure application mechanism in pain alleviation related to injections.

      We suggest here, for the first time, the use of the Pneumatic Skin Flattening (PSF)
      technology for alleviation of pain associated with injections. The PSF technology is
      currently used worldwide in the FDA cleared Serenity device (Serenity, Inolase Ltd.) for pain
      reduction in hair removal. The device generates contact and compression between a transparent
      sapphire window and the skin. The compression creatures pressure signal which, based on the
      gate theory, is though to depress the pain associated with the hair removal treatment. We
      assume the same mechanism would apply for the reduction of pain associated with injections.

      Comparison: Intra-Subject pain level change of injection with PSF and without PSF
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>August 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2008</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>VAS pain scaling differences between saline injection with PSF and without PSF</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately after each injection</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline Injection</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pneumatic Skin Flattening (PSF)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients 18 years old or older

          -  Healthy

          -  Patient informed consent must be obtained

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or nursing women

          -  Patients unable to understand or sign the informed consent form

          -  Anticoagulant or aspirin treatment

          -  Subjects with a history of vaso-vagal reactions to injections

          -  Coagulopathies

          -  Skin disease

          -  Chronic usage of medication
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pinchas Halpern, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Pinchas Halpern, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+972-3-697-3829</phone>
    <email>dr_halperin@tasmc.health.gov.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emergency Department- Tel-Aviv Sourasky Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tel-Aviv</city>
        <zip>64239</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tatiana Levit, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pinchas Halpern, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>MELZACK R, WALL PD. On the nature of cutaneous sensory mechanisms. Brain. 1962 Jun;85:331-56.</citation>
    <PMID>14472486</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Melzack R, Wall PD. Pain mechanisms: a new theory. Science. 1965 Nov 19;150(3699):971-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>5320816</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lask G, Friedman D, Elman M, Fournier N, Shavit R, Slatkine M. Pneumatic skin flattening (PSF): a novel technology for marked pain reduction in hair removal with high energy density lasers and IPLs. J Cosmet Laser Ther. 2006 Jun;8(2):76-81.</citation>
    <PMID>16766485</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 17, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 17, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 18, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 7, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 7, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 8, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Injections</keyword>
  <keyword>Vacuum</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Pneumatic Skin Flattening</keyword>
  <keyword>PSF</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

