<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00500669</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H0011</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00500669</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Randomised Study to Assess Betadine in the Groin Wound of Patients Undergoing Primary Varicose Vein Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomised, Blinded Study to Assess the Effect of Betadine in the Groin Wound of Patients Undergoing Primary Varicose Vein Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Royal Hobart Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Royal Hobart Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To investigate whether Betadine can reduce infection rates and recurrence rates following
      varicose veins surgery in a randomized double blind placebo controlled study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction. Varicose vein surgery is common. Worldwide, the commonest indication for this
      type of surgery is cosmesis. However, there are also some medical indications, including
      venous eczema, lipodermatosclerosis and venous ulceration. The surgery is usually straight
      forward and can in most instances be done as a day case. Patient and medical practitioner
      expectations are therefore high. Surgery in the groin is notorious for its risk of wound
      infection. In primary varicose vein surgery, the groin wound infection can rate can be as
      high as 20% 1. A more realistic figure might be approximately 10% (Sains PS, Reddy KM, Jones
      HJS and Derodra JK. Audit of varicose vein surgery: the patients perspective. Phlebology 2005
      20(4) 179 - 182.)

      A small prospective study has been conducted at the Royal Hobart Hospital to establish the
      wound infection rate in this hospital. All procedures were performed under the care of a
      single surgeon who routinely soaks the groin wound in Betadine. Patients were followed up on
      a weekly basis for six weeks and had wound inspections by an independent nurse consultant. Of
      the 11 patients (five female, mean age 50.3years, range 31 - 74 years, mean weight 92kg,
      range 60 - 130kg, mean body mass index 41) who have now completed six weeks of follow up,
      there were a total of 17 groin wounds. Only one of these (6%) has had an infection.
      Unfortunately, this study was terminated prematurely as the independent nurse who was
      performing the wound assessments has been replaced and there was a lag interval of at least 6
      weeks before her replacement was due to start.

      One of the major problems with varicose vein surgery is the risk of recurrence. Recurrent
      varicose veins are more difficult to deal with than primary varicose veins and thus every
      effort must be made at the time of the primary surgery to perform an operation with the
      lowest recurrence rate. Despite adequate surgery, recurrence can develop via
      neovascularisation in the groin. This may be part of the normal wound healing process. If
      neovascularisation can be prevented, this may reduce the recurrence rate. However, this
      should not be at the detriment of healing of the groin wound.

      Previous in vitro studies have looked at the effect of povidone-iodine on some of the
      components of wound healing. It can be toxic to granulocytes, monocytes and keratinocytes 2,
      3 . Dilute Povidone-Iodine solutions are also known to inhibit human skin fibroblast growth
      in vitro 4, 5. In vivo studies, however, have failed to show any clinically significant delay
      in wound healing when wounds are irrigated with povidine iodine 4.

      Povidine-iodine has bacteriocidal effects 6. Could it be that those groin wounds which
      develop an infection develop neovascularisation as part of the inflammatory response? Topical
      antimicrobial agents are commonly used in wound management. This is based on the premise that
      reduction of bacterial contamination aids wound healing. Sindelar showed that the incidence
      of superficial infections of surgical wounds irrigated with povidone-iodine solution prior to
      closure was less than wounds irrigated with saline (2.9% vs. 15.1%) 7 .

      No toxicity has been reported with povidone-iodine used as a brief rinse or soak, as planned
      for this study.

      In order to assess the effect of Betadine (10% povidone-iodine) in the groin wound on
      infection rates and recurrence rates in patients undergoing primary varicose vein surgery we
      will conduct a prospective, randomized study.

      Following injury and haemostasis, hypoxia, high lactate levels and acidosis stimulate
      angiogenesis. Under the influence of factors such as bFGF and VEGF, endothelial cells
      proliferate and form capillary buds. These cells secrete matrix metalloproteases which allow
      vascular buds to dissect through the wound matrix while EGF and PDGF recruit pericytes which
      stabilise the new vessel formation (Betsholtz C, Lindblom P, Gerhardt H. Role of pericytes in
      vascular morphogenesis. EXS9422005; 115 - 125

      Investigators. Mr. S. R. Walker - Staff Specialist, Vascular Surgery. Prof. Sinha - Associate
      Professor of Surgery Mr. David Cottier - Visiting Medical Officer - Vascular Surgery.

      Protocol. Inclusion criteria - Patients undergoing primary saphenofemoral ligation for
      varicose veins (can be combined with short saphenous surgery).

      Exclusion criteria - Allergy to iodine Redo groin dissections Patients having multiple
      avulsions only or saphenopopliteal ligation only Patients unable to return to outpatients for
      6 weeks to undergo assessment with the wound care nurse

      Patients admitted under the care of Prof. Sinha or Mr. S. R. Walker are to be included.

      Patients suitable for the study will be recruited from the outpatient department. If the
      patient agrees to be included in the study, they should undergo a pre-operative venous duplex
      scan. This may alter the operative plan. If patients have had a duplex scan prior to a
      decision on surgery, this scan does not need to be repeated.

      On admission for surgery the patient should undergo the usual pre-operative work up,
      including weight and height. Their past medical history should be recorded.

      All patients should receive a pre-operative dose of low molecular weight heparin (Clexane
      20mg) as thromboembolic prophylaxis. The groin area is shaved immediately before the
      operation. The groin and legs are prepared for surgery in the usual way using aqueous
      Betadine. No prophylactic antibiotics are to be given. The surgical procedure in the groin is
      then performed in a standard manner to expose the saphenofemoral junction. The junction and
      all tributaries are ligated. In all cases the long saphenous vein should be pin stripped to
      the level of the knee.

      At this point, patients are randomized via a sealed envelope to either a saline soaked gauze
      or a Betadine soaked gauze placed in the groin wound. This is left in place for a minimum of
      one minute. Some surgeons may then chose to close the groin wound before proceeding to the
      avulsions while others may choose to leave the soaked swab in place while any avulsions are
      dealt with. The length of time the swab is left in the groin wound should be recorded.

      The groin wound is then closed with vicral to the fascia and monocryl to the skin. The groin
      wound is dressed with a non occlusive dressing.

      Post operative protocol - Patients will be booked to see the wound care consultant on a
      weekly basis for 6 weeks. The patients will be booked into Prof. Sinha and Mr. Walker's
      outpatient clinic on Thursday morning. The wound care consultant will attend these clinics to
      assess the wounds. The wound care consultant will be blinded as to whether saline or Betadine
      was used in the groin. The wounds will be classified as:

        1. - normal post operative wound, no signs of infection

        2. - erythema of the wound not extending for more than 5mm from wound edge

        3. - erythema more than 5mm but no wound discharge

        4. - discharge of pus from wound

        5. - wound dehiscence with infection, presence of pus and necrotic tissue.

      At the six week follow up, the patient should undergo a venous duplex scan. This scan is
      performed to ensure an adequate surgical procedure has been performed.

      One year following the surgical procedure, patients undergo a final venous duplex scan to
      assess for signs or recurrence, and in particular, a recurrence in the groin.

      Both post operative duplex request forms should be completed at the time of the original
      operation with dates on the request forms for the scans.

      End points. Primary end point - groin wound infection Secondary end point - groin recurrence
      of varicose veins

      Statistics. If use of Betadine can reduce the infection rate (from 20%) and recurrence rate
      by 50%, for a study with 90% power, we would require at least 100 patients in each group.
      This number could be more readily recruited in a multicentre study.

      It is envisaged that approximate
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Recruitement too slow
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>June 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>groin wound infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 weeks post operative</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>- groin recurrence of varicose veins</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to one year post operatively</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Varicose Veins</condition>
  <condition>Wound Infection</condition>
  <condition>Recurrence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Betadine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Betadine</intervention_name>
    <description>Topically</description>
    <arm_group_label>Betadine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Saline</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients undergoing primary saphenofemoral ligation for varicose veins (can be
             combined with short saphenous surgery).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Allergy to iodine

          -  Redo groin dissections

          -  Patients having multiple avulsions only or saphenopopliteal ligation only

          -  Patients unable to return to outpatients for 6 weeks to undergo assessment with the
             wound care nurse
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stuart Walker, MBBS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Royal Hobart Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Hobart Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hobart</city>
        <state>Tasmania</state>
        <zip>7001</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 12, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 13, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 10, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 10, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 12, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Royal Hobart Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stuart Walker</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Staff Specialist vascular Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Varicose veins</keyword>
  <keyword>wound infection</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrence</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Recurrence</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wound Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Varicose Veins</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Povidone-Iodine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

