<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02889640</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SBS IRB16-0346</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02889640</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Increasing the Reach of Promising Dropout Prevention Programs: Examining the Trade-offs Between Scale and Effectiveness</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Chicago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>SAGA Innovations</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Chicago Public Schools</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Abdul Latif Jameel Poverty Action Lab (J-PAL)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>William T. Grant Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Chicago Beyond</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>New York City Department of Education</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Chicago</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The inability to consistently deliver at large scale promising education interventions is one
      of the most important contributing causes to inequality in the U.S. The research team applies
      insights from price theory and field-based randomized controlled trials to examine the effect
      of implementing a promising academic skills development program at large scale before
      implementing at scale. The project is designed to provide evidence of direct scientific and
      policy value for attempts to scale up a specific intervention, but also stimulate much more
      investigation of social policy scale-up challenges by refining these methods and
      demonstrating their feasibility and value.

      The research team examines the challenge of program scale up for a promising intervention
      studied in Chicago at medium scale in the past - &quot;SAGA tutoring&quot;. Past work has demonstrated
      that SAGA's intensive individualized, during-the-school-day math tutoring can generate very
      large gains in academic outcomes in a short period, even among students who are many years
      behind grade level. This study will explicitly explore the extent to which there is a
      trade-off between effectiveness and scale for this intervention. By taking advantage of the
      power of random sampling, this study will also allow for observation of the program's
      effectiveness as if it were running at three-and-a-half times the proposed scale in a subset
      of the study population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The University of Chicago Education Lab and Crime Lab New York research teams are carrying
      out a randomized controlled trial during the 2016-17 and 2017-18 academic years to build on
      previous collaborations with the Chicago Public Schools (CPS), the New York City Department
      of Education (DOE), and SAGA Innovations that have found that SAGA's intensive,
      individualized, during-the-school-day tutoring can generate very large gains in academic
      outcomes in a short period of time, even among students who are many years behind grade
      level. This research suggests the promise of this approach for improving the academic skills
      and educational attainment of disadvantaged youth, even once they have reached adolescence,
      both in Chicago and in distressed urban districts across the country. However, to truly
      affect outcomes at the local and national level, SAGA would have to be rolled out on a much
      greater scale than researchers have been able to study in Chicago. Yet little is known about
      how to take promising interventions to scale. This study seeks to build the science of
      scale-up, by examining the extent to which this individualized tutoring program can be
      implemented at an even greater scale and by explicitly exploring the trade-offs between
      effectiveness and scale.

      The SAGA Innovations program expands on the nationally recognized innovation of high-dosage,
      in-school-day tutoring developed in Match Education's charter school in Boston. The tutoring
      program meets as a scheduled course, Math Lab, once a day during the normal school day, and
      is provided in addition to a student's regular math class. Students work two-on-one (two
      students with one tutor) with the same full-time, professional tutor for the entirety of the
      school year. The content of the tutoring sessions is aligned with what students are learning
      in their regular math courses, but is also targeted to address individual gaps in math
      knowledge. Also following the original model developed by Match Education, SAGA tutors use
      frequent internal formative assessments of student progress to individualize instruction.

      A previous randomized controlled trial conducted by the University of Chicago research team
      found that one year of this intervention, delivered in academic year (AY) 2013-14 in the
      Chicago Public Schools, generated between one and two extra years of academic growth in math,
      over and above what the normal U.S. high school student learns in one year (Cook et al.,
      2015; Reardon 2011). The estimated effects for math achievement are on the order of 0.19 to
      0.30 standard deviations, depending on the exact test and norming used. The intervention also
      improved student grades in math by 0.58 points on a 1-4 grade point scale, compared to a
      control mean of 1.77. These gains are particularly important because of the growing evidence
      on the importance of math specifically for short- and medium-term success in school, and for
      long-term life outcomes such as employment and earnings (Duncan et al., 2007).

      This study aims to build upon the investigators' previous evaluations of the program, and
      will provide insight into the ability of this program to serve youth at a much larger scale.
      Specifically, this study aims to answer the following research questions:

        1. What is the effect of implementing an evidence-based individualized tutoring program at
           larger scale?

        2. What is the relationship between the effect of the program and the scale at which the
           program is implemented?

      Implementation sites are divided into two sets: sites in Chicago at which students are
      randomized to receive tutoring (hereby referred to as &quot;scale-up&quot; schools), and sites in
      Chicago and New York City where principals have primary discretion to choose which students
      receive tutoring (hereby referred to as &quot;returning schools&quot;).

      In order to study research question #1, investigators will take advantage of the power of
      random sampling to study scale-up of this program without actually having to implement the
      program at a much larger scale. The first research question seeks to measure the average
      quality of the scaled up program in Chicago, in which researchers will utilize data from the
      scale-up schools. Students in both scale up and returning schools are both randomly assigned
      to tutors. However, students in the scale-up schools have two additional randomizations - (1)
      tutor applicant randomization and (2) treatment assignment randomization. For the first
      feature, the research team is having SAGA over-recruit tutors as though they were
      implementing at larger than the intended scale in the scale up schools. Investigators then
      randomly select one in three-and-a-half tutor applicants to continue through SAGA's standard
      hiring process, and positions at the scale-up schools are only filled by these randomly
      selected tutors. As students are randomly assigned to treatment in these scale-up schools,
      investigators will be able to measure program effects at about three-and-a-half times the
      scale at which the program is being implemented at these schools.

      To measure treatment effects, the research team will estimate both intent to treat (ITT) and
      treatment on the treated (TOT) impacts. Researchers will estimate the ITT effect as follows:

      Y = a + bT + cX + Z

      where Y is the outcome of interest, T indicates students that are randomly assigned to be
      offered the chance to participate in the tutoring program, X is a set of baseline controls
      (which specifically includes randomization block, treatment assignment, gender, age, learning
      disability, free/reduced lunch status, race, baseline grade level, GPA, number of As/Bs/Cs/Ds
      in the prior year, days absent from school, and disciplinary incidents including suspensions
      and arrests), Z is a random error term, and a, b, c are parameters to be estimated. The
      random assignment of T assures that under standard assumptions, Ordinary Least Squares (OLS)
      estimation yields an unbiased estimate of the ITT as the estimate of b, or the effect of
      being offered participation in the SAGA tutoring program. As all students who were randomized
      into the program were paired with tutors that were randomized via the process described
      above, our ITT (and subsequently, TOT) effect will specifically measure the effect of the
      program when administered at three-and-a-half times the scale as it is currently being
      administered.

      The ITT measures the effect of being offered the chance to participate. As students assigned
      to treatment are not required to participate in the program, the ITT may not measure the
      effect of participation. The research team will measure the effect of participation using
      random assignment of T as an instrument for participation. If all participants were randomly
      selected (i.e. if there are no control students who are allowed to participate in the
      tutoring program) this method calculates the effect of the treatment on the treated (TOT), or
      the effect of participating for the group of students who choose to participate.

      To gain insight into research question #2 above, which seeks to determine the relationship
      between program scale and effects, tutors at all sites are ranked by SAGA leadership based on
      relative expected quality. The research team will then randomize student pairs to tutors in
      an effort to eventually identify a tutor's effect on student outcomes. Using this
      methodology, researchers can study whether tutor ranking predicts the size of the program
      effects. As the research team assumes that the program would hire tutors in the order of
      their ranking depending on the number of tutor slots they needed to fill, this analysis will
      shed light on the relationship between scale and effectiveness.

      To analyze the impacts of being assigned to a tutor of a particular ranking (i.e. the ITT
      estimate of research question #2), investigators will run regression models that regress
      academic outcomes—such as math course grades, grade point average (GPA), and math
      standardized test scores—on tutor rank. Researchers will model tutor rank as a continuous
      variable and also as quartiles and deciles. Investigators will also test impacts by using
      individual ranks as fixed effects (i.e. measuring the coefficient on each ranking as a dummy
      variable) to look for outliers and general trends that might not be captured in the rankings
      on a continuous scale. Each regression will include classroom fixed effects, as this is how
      students were randomly assigned to tutors. Other covariates in the model include: grade, math
      GPA from the previous three school years, grades from previous school years, and attendance
      and demographic indicators from previous school years.

      As students switch tutors for a variety of reasons, researchers will also need to calculate
      the TOT estimate to look at the impact of being assigned to and actually working with a tutor
      of a particular ranking. To do so, investigators will use the rank of the randomly assigned
      tutor as an instrument for the weighted average tutor rank, where the weight placed on each
      tutor's rank is equal to the proportion of time (measured in days) the student spent with
      that tutor. Investigators will use daily attendance data to create this weighted average.
      This method will help investigators understand whether working with a higher-ranked tutor
      means that a student actually receives better quality instruction, or whether an additional
      relationship between tutor rank and actual quality exists.

      At the end of AY2016-17 and AY2017-18, researchers will answer the research questions by
      looking at various academic and behavioral outcome accessed through administrative data from
      the Chicago Public Schools, New York City Department of Education, and Chicago Police
      Department. These outcomes include GPA, credits attempted, credits earned, and standardized
      test scores in Chicago and New York City, and crime involvement in Chicago. Researchers will
      also have access to data on tutor characteristics, which includes demographic information and
      information on math and teacher training, to assess the variation in the effectiveness of
      tutors and to examine the degree to which tutor characteristics correspond to different
      student outcomes. Lastly, researchers will receive programmatic attendance data from SAGA,
      which includes information on how often students were present and which tutors they worked
      with each day. From this attendance data, we will be able to compute an &quot;average tutor
      ranking&quot;, which will be a weighted average of tutor ranking and how many days a student
      worked with a tutor of that ranking.

      Researchers believe the proposed project will provide valuable insights into how to scale up
      what may turn out to be an extremely cost-effective way to improve educational outcomes for
      low-income youth. But perhaps more importantly, the hope is that this work will contribute to
      a broader understanding of how program scale affects program quality and how to
      systematically study this relationship. The investigators hope this project will create a
      &quot;roadmap&quot; for a growing body of research on the science of scale-up, guiding efforts of
      future researchers to understand the implications of scale up for interventions with scarce
      inputs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2016</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in math achievement</measure>
    <time_frame>1-year, 2-years, 3-years</time_frame>
    <description>Performance on math standardized achievement tests</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in math course grades</measure>
    <time_frame>1-year, 2-years</time_frame>
    <description>Math course grades, obtained from Chicago Public Schools and New York City Department of Education administrative database</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in absentee rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1-year, 2-years, 3-years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of school absences, obtained from Chicago Public Schools and New York City Department of Education administrative database</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in index of schooling outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>1-year, 2-years, 3-years</time_frame>
    <description>Index of standardized (in Z-score form) outcomes for school persistence, absences, and course grades, obtained from Chicago Public Schools and New York City Department of Education administrative data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in student misconduct</measure>
    <time_frame>1-year, 2-years, 3-years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of school misconduct infractions, obtained from Chicago Public Schools and New York City Department of Education administrative database</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in total courses failed</measure>
    <time_frame>1-year, 2-years, 3-years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of total school courses failed, obtained from Chicago Public Schools and New York City Department of Education administrative database</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in math courses failed</measure>
    <time_frame>1-year, 2-years, 3-years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of math courses failed, obtained from Chicago Public Schools and New York City Department of Education administrative database</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in non-math courses grades</measure>
    <time_frame>1-year, 2-years, 3-years</time_frame>
    <description>Non-math course grades, obtained from Chicago Public Schools and New York City Department of Education administrative database</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in non-math courses failures</measure>
    <time_frame>1-year, 2-years, 3-years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of non-math courses failed, obtained from Chicago Public Schools and New York City Department of Education administrative database</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in school persistence</measure>
    <time_frame>1-year, 2-years, 3-years</time_frame>
    <description>Measure from CPS and NYC DOE student records of school persistence (enrollment or graduation status by end of academic year)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in violent crime arrests</measure>
    <time_frame>1-year, 2-years, 3-years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of violent crime arrests, obtained from Chicago Police Department and Illinois State Police, New York City Police Department and New York State Police administrative databases (if available)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in other arrests (property, drug, and other crimes)</measure>
    <time_frame>1-year, 2-years, 3-years</time_frame>
    <description>Number of non-violent crime arrests, including property crimes, drug crimes, and other crimes, obtained from Chicago Police Department and Illinois State Police, New York City Police Department and New York State Police administrative databases (if available)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in standardized test score achievement</measure>
    <time_frame>1-year, 2-years, 3-years</time_frame>
    <description>Performance on additional sections of standardized tests (i.e. reading)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in high school graduation rate</measure>
    <time_frame>2-years, 3-years, 4-years</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in four-year and five-year high school graduation rates, obtained from Chicago Public Schools and New York City Department of Education administrative data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in college enrollment rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3-years, 4-years, 5-years, 6-years, 7-years, 8-years</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in college enrollment data, obtained from Chicago Public Schools and New York City Department of Education administrative data</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6600</enrollment>
  <condition>Educational Achievement</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>These youth will receive standard mathematics instruction and support (including possibly other tutoring interventions), but not the daily, intensive, during-the-school-day math tutoring provided by SAGA.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Scale-up SAGA math tutoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>These youth will receive intensive, daily mathematics tutoring, and students will be paired with scale-up tutors. Tutors will be hired using the randomization process, and will be randomly assigned to youth.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard SAGA math tutoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>These youth will receive intensive, daily mathematics tutoring, and students will be paired with tutors hired via SAGA's standard process, which does not involve randomization. Tutors will be randomly assigned to youth.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SAGA Innovations</intervention_name>
    <description>An intensive math tutoring program</description>
    <arm_group_label>Scale-up SAGA math tutoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard SAGA math tutoring</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Scale-up tutors</intervention_name>
    <description>Tutors who have been selected for hire via the one in three-and-a-half randomization process</description>
    <arm_group_label>Scale-up SAGA math tutoring</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Tutors</intervention_name>
    <description>Tutors who have been selected for hire via SAGA's standard hiring process, which does not entail randomization</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard SAGA math tutoring</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Chicago Public School and New York City Department of Education high schools students
             attending schools in low-income communities. Schools in the study are chosen in
             collaboration with the Chicago Public Schools and New York City Department of
             Education based on criteria such as dropout rate, test scores, scores on academic
             rating scale, etc.

          -  School administrators are enthusiastic about the program and agree to terms and
             conditions of the experimental design

          -  Male and female youth within these schools who are rising 9th and 10th graders in
             academic year (AY) 2016-17 and 2017-18

          -  Applicants who apply to be a tutor for SAGA Innovations

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  In Chicago (where the randomized controlled trial is being run), youth who have missed
             &gt;60% of days during AY2015-16 or AY2016-17 (through March), and so would not be
             expected to show up in school enough during intervention years (AY2016-17 and
             AY2017-2018) to benefit from school-based programming

          -  In Chicago, youth who have failed &gt;75% of classes during AY2015-16 and AY2016-17
             (through March)

          -  In Chicago, youth who have designations for autism, &quot;educable mentally handicapped,&quot;
             and/or traumatic brain injury
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jonathan Guryan, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kelly Hallberg, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Chicago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jens Ludwig, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Chicago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cook P, Dodge K, Farkas G, Fryer RG, Guryan J, Ludwig J, Mayer S, Pollack H, Steinberg L. Not Too Late: Improving Academic Outcomes for Disadvantaged Youth. Northwestern Institute for Policy Research Working Paper, February 2015.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cook P, Dodge K, Farkas G, Fryer RG, Guryan J, Ludwig J, Mayer S, Pollack H, Steinberg L. The (Surprising) Efficacy of Academic and Behavioral Intervention with Disadvantaged Youth: Results from a Randomized Experiment in Chicago. Cambridge, MA: National Bureau of Economic Research, Working Paper No. 19862, 2014.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fryer RG. Injecting Charter School Best Practices into Traditional Public Schools: Evidence from Field Experiments. The Quarterly Journal of Economics 129(3): 1355-1407, 2014.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 31, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 31, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 5, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Educational Achievement</keyword>
  <keyword>Individualized Tutoring</keyword>
  <keyword>Mathematics</keyword>
  <keyword>Academic Mismatch</keyword>
  <keyword>Achievement Gap</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

