<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02888665</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>9624</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2016-01286</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>9624</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015704</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02888665</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pembrolizumab and Doxorubicin Hydrochloride in Treating Patients With Sarcoma That is Metastatic or Cannot Be Removed by Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Trial of Pembrolizumab in Combination With Doxorubicin as Treatment for Patients With Advanced Sarcomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I/II trial studies the side effects and best dose of doxorubicin hydrochloride
      when given together with pembrolizumab and to see how well they work in treating patients
      with sarcoma that have spread to other parts of the body or that cannot be removed by
      surgery. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as doxorubicin hydrochloride, work in different
      ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells, by stopping them from
      dividing, or by stopping them from spreading. Monoclonal antibodies, such as pembrolizumab,
      may interfere with the ability of tumor cells to grow and spread. Giving doxorubicin
      hydrochloride together with pembrolizumab may work better in treating patients with sarcoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the safety and tolerability of the combination of pembrolizumab and doxorubicin
      hydrochloride (doxorubicin) in patients with advanced soft tissue sarcoma (STS).

      II. To assess the clinical response rate of advanced soft tissue sarcoma (STS) patients
      receiving the combination of pembrolizumab and doxorubicin.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To explore the clinical activity of pembrolizumab in subjects with advanced STS with
      respect to time to response.

      II. To explore the clinical activity of pembrolizumab in subjects with advanced STS with
      respect to duration of response.

      III. To explore the clinical activity of pembrolizumab in subjects with advanced STS with
      respect to progression-free survival (PFS).

      IV. To explore the clinical activity of pembrolizumab in subjects with advanced STS with
      respect to overall survival.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To compare response rates between patients with high levels of PD-L1 expression with those
      who have PD-L1 absent.

      OUTLINE: This is a phase I, dose-escalation study of doxorubicin hydrochloride followed by a
      phase II study.

      Patients receive pembrolizumab intravenously (IV) over 30 minutes on day 1 and doxorubicin
      hydrochloride IV over 1-3 hours on day 1 of courses 2-7 only. Treatment repeats every 21 days
      for up to 35 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 30 days and then every 12
      weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 5, 2016</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose of doxorubicin hydrochloride together with pembrolizumab according to the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0 (Phase I)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 42 days (6 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as a dose limiting toxicity in less than 2 of 6 patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR) (Phase II)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Will compare ORR with historical rates.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events, according to NCI CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The Kaplan-Meier method will be used to estimate median PFS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The Kaplan-Meier method will be used to estimate median OS.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Expression of PD-L1</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the association between PD-L1 expression and clinical outcome.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">47</enrollment>
  <condition>Sarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pembrolizumab, doxorubicin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive pembrolizumab IV over 30 minutes on day 1 and doxorubicin hydrochloride IV over 1-3 hours on day 1 of courses 2-7 only. Treatment repeats every 21 days for up to 35 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Doxorubicin Hydrochloride</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pembrolizumab, doxorubicin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>5,12-Naphthacenedione, 10-[(3-amino-2,3,6-trideoxy-alpha-L-lyxo-hexopyranosyl)oxy]-7,8, 9,10-tetrahydro-6,8,11-trihydroxy-8-(hydroxyacetyl)-1-methoxy-, hydrochloride, (8S-cis)- (9CI)</other_name>
    <other_name>ADM</other_name>
    <other_name>Adriacin</other_name>
    <other_name>Adriamycin</other_name>
    <other_name>Adriamycin Hydrochloride</other_name>
    <other_name>Adriamycin PFS</other_name>
    <other_name>Adriamycin RDF</other_name>
    <other_name>ADRIAMYCIN, HYDROCHLORIDE</other_name>
    <other_name>Adriamycine</other_name>
    <other_name>Adriblastina</other_name>
    <other_name>Adriblastine</other_name>
    <other_name>Adrimedac</other_name>
    <other_name>Chloridrato de Doxorrubicina</other_name>
    <other_name>DOX</other_name>
    <other_name>DOXO-CELL</other_name>
    <other_name>Doxolem</other_name>
    <other_name>Doxorubicin.HCl</other_name>
    <other_name>Doxorubin</other_name>
    <other_name>Farmiblastina</other_name>
    <other_name>FI 106</other_name>
    <other_name>FI-106</other_name>
    <other_name>hydroxydaunorubicin</other_name>
    <other_name>Rubex</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pembrolizumab, doxorubicin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (pembrolizumab, doxorubicin hydrochloride)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Keytruda</other_name>
    <other_name>Lambrolizumab</other_name>
    <other_name>MK-3475</other_name>
    <other_name>SCH 900475</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Be willing and able to provide written informed consent/assent for the trial

          -  Have measurable disease based on Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST)
             1.1

          -  Have metastatic or unresectable sarcoma

          -  Have a performance status of 0 to 1 on the Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG)
             performance scale

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1,500/mcL

          -  Platelets &gt;= 100,000/mcL

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9 g/dL or &gt;= 5.6 mmol/L without transfusion or erythropoietin (EPO)
             dependency (within 7 days of assessment)

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 1.5 X upper limit of normal (ULN) OR measured or calculated
             creatinine clearance (glomerular filtration rate [GFR] can also be used in place of
             creatinine or creatinine clearance [CrCl]) &gt;= 60 mL/min for subject with creatinine
             levels &gt; 1.5 X institutional ULN

          -  Serum total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 X ULN OR direct bilirubin =&lt; ULN for subjects with total
             bilirubin levels &gt; 1.5 ULN

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) (serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase [SGOT]) and
             alanine aminotransferase (ALT) (serum glutamate pyruvate transaminase [SGPT]) =&lt; 2.5 X
             ULN OR =&lt; 5 X ULN for subjects with liver metastases

          -  Albumin &gt;= 2.5 mg/dL

          -  International normalized ratio (INR) or prothrombin time (PT) =&lt; 1.5 X ULN unless
             subject is receiving anticoagulant therapy as long as PT or partial thromboplastin
             time (PTT) is within therapeutic range of intended use of anticoagulants

          -  Activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) =&lt; 1.5 X ULN unless subject is receiving
             anticoagulant therapy as long as PT or PTT is within therapeutic range of intended use
             of anticoagulants

          -  Female subject of childbearing potential should have a negative urine or serum
             pregnancy within 72 hours prior to receiving the first dose of study medication; if
             the urine test is positive or cannot be confirmed as negative, a serum pregnancy test
             will be required

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential should be willing to use 2 methods of birth
             control or be surgically sterile, or abstain from heterosexual activity for the course
             of the study through 120 days after the last dose of study medication; subjects of
             childbearing potential are those who have not been surgically sterilized or have not
             been free from menses for &gt; 1 year

          -  Male subjects should agree to use an adequate method of contraception starting with
             the first dose of study therapy through 120 days after the last dose of study therapy

          -  Ejection fraction &gt; 45% by either multi-gated acquisition scan (MUGA) scan or
             echocardiogram

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Has prior treatment using an anthracycline

          -  Has one of the following sarcoma subtypes where combining anthracyclines with other
             chemotherapies is established as the standard of care: osteosarcoma, Ewings sarcoma,
             embryonal rhabdomyosarcoma, alveolar rhabdomyosarcoma

          -  Is currently participating and receiving study therapy or has participated in a study
             of an investigational agent and received study therapy or used an investigational
             device within 4 weeks of the first dose of treatment

          -  Has a diagnosis of immunodeficiency or is receiving systemic steroid therapy or any
             other form of immunosuppressive therapy within 7 days prior to the first dose of trial
             treatment

          -  Has a known history of active TB (bacillus tuberculosis)

          -  Hypersensitivity to pembrolizumab or any of its excipients

          -  Has had a prior anti-cancer monoclonal antibody (mAb) within 4 weeks prior to study
             day 1 or who has not recovered (i.e., =&lt; grade 1 or at baseline) from adverse events
             due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier

          -  Has had prior chemotherapy, targeted small molecule therapy, or radiation therapy
             within 2 weeks prior to study day 1 or who has not recovered (i.e., =&lt; grade 1 or at
             baseline) from adverse events due to a previously administered agent

               -  Note: Subjects with =&lt; grade 2 neuropathy are an exception to this criterion and
                  may qualify for the study

               -  Note: If subject received major surgery, they must have recovered adequately from
                  the toxicity and/or complications from the intervention prior to starting therapy

          -  Has a known additional malignancy that is progressing or requires active treatment;
             exceptions include basal cell carcinoma of the skin or squamous cell carcinoma of the
             skin that has undergone potentially curative therapy or in situ cervical cancer

          -  Has known active central nervous system (CNS) metastases and/or carcinomatous
             meningitis; subjects with previously treated brain metastases may participate provided
             they are stable (without evidence of progression by imaging for at least four weeks
             prior to the first dose of trial treatment and any neurologic symptoms have returned
             to baseline), have no evidence of new or enlarging brain metastases, and are not using
             steroids for at least 7 days prior to trial treatment; this exception does not include
             carcinomatous meningitis which is excluded regardless of clinical stability

          -  Has active autoimmune disease that has required systemic treatment in the past 2 years
             (i.e. with use of disease modifying agents, corticosteroids or immunosuppressive
             drugs); replacement therapy (e.g., thyroxine, insulin, or physiologic corticosteroid
             replacement therapy for adrenal or pituitary insufficiency, etc.) is not considered a
             form of systemic treatment

          -  Has known history of, or any evidence of active, non-infectious pneumonitis

          -  Has an active infection requiring systemic therapy

          -  Has a history or current evidence of any condition, therapy, or laboratory abnormality
             that might confound the results of the trial, interfere with the subject's
             participation for the full duration of the trial, or is not in the best interest of
             the subject to participate, in the opinion of the treating investigator

          -  Has known psychiatric or substance abuse disorders that would interfere with
             cooperation with the requirements of the trial

          -  Is pregnant or breastfeeding, or expecting to conceive or father children within the
             projected duration of the trial, starting with the pre-screening or screening visit
             through 120 days after the last dose of trial treatment

          -  Has received prior therapy with an anti-programed death receptor 1 (PD-1), anti-PD-L1,
             anti-program death receptor ligand 2 (PD-L2) agent or anti-CTLA4

          -  Has a known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) (HIV 1/2 antibodies)

          -  Has known active hepatitis B (e.g., hepatitis B surface antigen [HBsAg] reactive) or
             hepatitis C (e.g., hepatitis C virus [HCV] ribonucleic acid [RNA] [qualitative] is
             detected)

          -  Has received a live vaccine within 30 days of planned start of study therapy

               -  Note: Seasonal influenza vaccines for injection are generally inactivated flu
                  vaccines and are allowed; however intranasal influenza vaccines (e.g., Flu-Mist)
                  are live attenuated vaccines, and are not allowed
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Seth Pollack</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fred Hutch/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutch/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Seth Pollack</last_name>
      <phone>206-667-6629</phone>
      <email>spollack@fredhutch.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Seth Pollack</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 30, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 30, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 5, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liposomal doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

