<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02880241</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MMV_MMV390048_16_02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02880241</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>MMV390048 POC in Patients With P. Vivax and P. Falciparum Malaria</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open Label Study to Assess the Efficacy, Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of a Single Dose of MMV390048 in Adult Patients With Acute, Uncomplicated Plasmodium Vivax or Falciparum Malaria Monoinfection Over a 35 Day Period</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medicines for Malaria Venture</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Gondar</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Jimma University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medicines for Malaria Venture</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The present proof-of-concept Phase IIa study aims to confirm, in patients, the observed
      activity of MMV390048 against P. falciparum in pre-clinical models and the human Induced
      Blood-Stage Malaria (IBSM) challenge model, and to determine the activity against P. vivax
      malaria in patients, both over 14 and 28 days. Additional aims are to characterise the safety
      of MMV390048 in patients. Patient safety will be monitored for up to 35 days post-dose
      including pharmacokinetic assessments. The study will investigate descending single doses of
      MMV390048 in response to results obtained in the first cohort/dose in each malaria sub-type.
      The results of this trial will identify active, well-tolerated doses for investigation in
      combination with a partner drug within a Phase IIb clinical trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The present Phase IIa study aims to confirm, in patients, the observed activity of MMV390048
      against P. falciparum in pre-clinical models and the human IBSM human challenge model, and to
      determine the activity against P. vivax malaria in patients, both over 14 and 28 days.
      Additional aims are to characterise the safety of MMV390048 in patients. Patient safety will
      be monitored for up to 35 days post-dose including pharmacokinetic assessments. The study
      will investigate descending single doses of MMV390048 in response to results obtained in the
      first cohort/dose in each malaria sub type.

      The results of this trial will identify active, well tolerated doses for investigation in
      combination with a partner drug within a Phase IIb clinical trial.

      Preclinical studies using SCID mice inoculated with P. falciparum-infected red blood cells
      link doses and exposures to the efficacy of MMV390048.38 The active dose in the SCID model
      causing maximum effect (ED90) against the parasites is 1 mg/kg/day. The MPC derived from the
      SCID data was 39 ng/ml.39 A human dose for the treatment of P. falciparum was sought that
      could maintain blood concentrations above 39 ng/ml (100 nM) for 8 days. Assuming linear
      pharmacokinetics and based on observed data from the Phase I exploratory formulation study in
      human volunteers, a dose of approximately 20 mg would be estimated to achieve the
      pharmacodynamic target drug concentration in humans based on the preclinical efficacy data
      generated in the SCID mice model. For new antimalarial drugs the translation of a predicted
      efficacious dose from the SCID mouse to the human challenge model and in turn to the
      treatment of acute, uncomplicated P. vivax or P. falciparum is unknown. To minimise the risk
      to patients and to ensure the highest probability of success, the maximum safe dose (as
      determined in healthy volunteers) that maintains a toxicokinetic safety margin to the repeat
      dose studies was selected for the first cohort in this study. This dose is expected to exceed
      the predicted MPC on Day 8 and provide significant target coverage at the site of action.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Pending analysis of intermediary data.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 20, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>For P. vivax: Crude Adequate Clinical and Parasitological Response (ACPR)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 14 post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>For P. falciparum: PCR-adjusted Crude Adequate Clinical and Parasitological Response (ACPR)</measure>
    <time_frame>On Day 14 post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">102</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1A - P. vivax malaria</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A single oral dose of up to 120mg MMV390048</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1B - P. falciparum malaria</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A single oral dose of up to 120mg MMV390048</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2A - P. vivax malaria</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A single oral dose (to be determined) of MMV390048</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2B - P. falciparum malaria</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A single oral dose (to be determined) of MMV390048</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3A - P. vivax malaria</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A single oral dose (to be determined) of MMV390048</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3B - P. falciparum malaria</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A single oral dose (to be determined) of MMV390048</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MMV390048</intervention_name>
    <description>Tablets of 20mg each</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1A - P. vivax malaria</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1B - P. falciparum malaria</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2A - P. vivax malaria</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2B - P. falciparum malaria</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3A - P. vivax malaria</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3B - P. falciparum malaria</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Body weight between 40 kg and 90 kg inclusive

          -  Presence of P. vivax or P. falciparum monoinfection confirmed by:

          -  Fever, as defined by axillary temperature ≥37.5°C or oral/rectal/tympanic temperature
             ≥38°C, or history of fever in the previous 48 hours for P. vivax and 24 hours for P.
             falciparum and,

          -  Microscopically confirmed parasite infection: 1,000 to 40,000 asexual parasite
             count/µL blood

          -  Written informed consent provided by the patient in accordance with local practice. If
             the patient is unable to write, witnessed consent is permitted according to local
             ethical considerations.

          -  Ability to swallow oral medication

          -  The patient is able to understand and comply with protocol requirements, instructions
             and protocol-stated restrictions and is likely to complete the study as planned

          -  Willing to be hospitalized for at least 72 hours or until malarial parasites are not
             detected by microscopy on 2 consecutive occasions whichever comes later and return to
             clinic for all follow-up visits

          -  Women must be of non-childbearing potential (WNCBP) as per one of the following
             definitions:

          -  postmenopausal defined as having age-appropriate, natural (spontaneous) amenorrhea for
             at least 12 months prior to screening in the absence of an alternative medical cause
             for the amenorrhea, or

          -  premenopausal with irreversible surgical sterilization by hysterectomy and/or
             bilateral oophorectomy or salpingectomy at least 6 months prior to screening (as
             determined by subject medical history)

          -  Sexually active men must agree to comply with strict appropriate contraception rules
             (barrier contraception, e.g. condom) or complete abstinence when this is in line with
             the preferred and usual lifestyle of the patient. The contraception coverage in this
             situation should ensure full elimination of MMV390048, i.e. until 120 days after
             MMV390048 administration to the enrolled male patient (covering a full sperm cycle of
             90 days starting after 5 x t½ of the drug). Abstinent patients must agree to use the
             above-mentioned contraceptive methods if they start sexual relationships during the
             study, and to continue these methods until 120 days after study medication.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with signs and symptoms of severe / complicated malaria according to the
             World Health Organisation Criteria 2012

          -  Mixed Plasmodium infection

          -  Vomiting more than three times in the 24 hours prior to inclusion in the study or
             inability to tolerate oral treatment, or diarrhea equivalent to three or more watery
             stools per day

          -  Women who are nursing (lactating)

          -  Presence of other serious or chronic clinical condition requiring hospitalisation

          -  Severe malnutrition (defined as a body mass index [BMI] of less than 16 kg/m2 as per
             local guidelines)

          -  Presence of concurrent febrile illness (e.g. typhoid fever)

          -  Known history or evidence of clinically significant:

          -  cardiovascular disease (including arrhythmia, QTcF interval &gt;450 msec, personal or
             family history of long QT syndrome, PR interval &gt;200msec; any relevant
             intra-ventricular heart block [QRS &gt;120msec]),

          -  respiratory conditions (including active tuberculosis),

          -  history of jaundice or other hepatic dysfunction,

          -  renal insufficiency,

          -  gastrointestinal disorder, or any condition that may affect absorption of the study
             medication (e.g. vomiting or diarrhea),

          -  immunological disorders (including known pre-existing HIV infection),

          -  endocrine disorders (including any type of diabetes mellitus whether controlled or
             not, diabetes insipidus, uncontrolled hypo- or hyperthyroidism, endocrine reproductive
             disorders not requiring concurrent medication, disorders of adrenal function),

          -  infectious conditions (other than minor skin or soft tissue infections or confirmed
             minor lower urinary tract infection),

          -  malignancy,

          -  psychiatric or neurological disorders (including a history of convulsions, major head
             trauma, focal neurological signs, psychosis, bipolar or major depressive disorder), or

          -  any other disorder or condition that in the opinion of the investigator may render the
             patient unfit for participation in the trial, may limit his/her ability to provide
             informed consent, may interfere with protocol adherence or place the patient at
             increased risk through participation in the study

          -  Known to have any of the following markers of active hepatitis:

          -  Hepatitis A IgM (HAV-IgM),

          -  Hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), or

          -  Hepatitis C antibody (HCV Ab) and HCV RNA

          -  Have received any antimalarial treatment (alone or in combination) during the
             following periods before screening (list of prohibited medication is provided in
             Appendix 2):

          -  Piperaquine, mefloquine, naphthoquine or sulphadoxine-pyrimethamine within 6 weeks
             prior to screening

          -  Amodiaquine, chloroquine, pyronaridine or tafenoquine within 4 weeks prior to
             screening

          -  Any artemisinin derivative (artesunate, artemether, arteether or dihydroartemisinin),
             quinine, halofantrine, lumefantrine and any other anti-malarial treatment or
             antibiotic with antimalarial activity (including cotrimoxazole, tetracyclines,
             quinolones and fluoroquinolones and azithromycin) within 14 days prior to screening

          -  Any herbal products or traditional medicines during the 7 days prior to screening

          -  Receipt of an investigational drug within 8 weeks or 5 half-lives (whichever is
             longer) prior to screening

          -  Current participation in any other clinical trial

          -  A history of regular abuse of alcohol, or use of drugs of abuse during the past 6
             months, or any clinical signs of substance abuse

          -  Neutrophil count &lt;1,000/µL

          -  Elevated liver function tests as follows:

          -  AST/ALT &gt;2 x the upper limit of normal (ULN), regardless of the level of total
             bilirubin

          -  AST/ALT &gt;1.5 and ≤2 x ULN and total bilirubin &gt;ULN

          -  AST/ALT &gt;ULN and ≤1.5 x ULN

          -  and total bilirubin &gt;1.5 and ≤2 x ULN,

          -  and conjugated bilirubin ≥35% of the total bilirubin

          -  Total bilirubin &gt;2 x ULN, regardless of the level of AST/ALT

          -  Hb level &lt;8g/dL

          -  Serum creatinine levels &gt;2 x ULN

          -  Platelet level &lt;50,000/mm3.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel Yilma Bogale, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Jimma University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rezika Mohammed, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Gondar</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Gondar Hospital/Maksegnit Health Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gondar</city>
        <state>Amhara</state>
        <zip>6200</zip>
        <country>Ethiopia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Jimma University Referral Hospital/Agaro District Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jimma</city>
        <state>Oromia</state>
        <country>Ethiopia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Ethiopia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 23, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 23, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 26, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Malaria, Falciparum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

