<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02881398</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ASEF-VALUES</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02881398</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mobile Health in Structural Heart Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>ASEF-VALUES</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Trial of Pocket-Echocardiography Integrated Mobile Health Device Assessments in Modern Structural Heart Disease Clinics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sri Sathya Sai Institute of Higher Medical Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sri Sathya Sai Institute of Higher Medical Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this investigation was to assess the impact of new mobile health
      devices on health outcomes among patients with rheumatic and structural heart disease in a
      resource limited area. To achieve this aim the investigators utilized smartphone-connected
      devices such as the smartphone-ECG, activity monitors, connected blood pressure devices and
      pocket-sized and handheld ultrasound. The main question asked in this investigation is if
      mobile health assessments accelerates medical-decision-making and if it shortens the time to
      definitive therapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A recent paradigm-shift in the global burden of cardiovascular diseases has been observed
      with a decreasing prevalence in industrialized nations and an increasing prevalence in
      resource limited areas. This problem is further compounded with resource-limited areas
      receiving a disproportionately low allocation of global resources including diagnostic tests
      and trained healthcare professionals. Such cardiovascular conditions include heart failure,
      coronary artery disease, atrial arrhythmias and hypertensive heart disease. Coupled with a
      rising epidemic of rheumatic and structural heart disease affecting over 15- million
      individuals in these regions creates an urgent need that requires innovative and scalable
      methods to improve population- health, methods that reduce the cost of care, and
      simultaneously improves outcomes.

      The World Health Organization's Millennium Developmental Goals has recently reported a rise
      in cellular phone technologies with 7-Billion devices in active circulation. Parallel
      developments with the globalization of Internet-based communication and the emergence of new
      smartphone-connected mobile health (mHealth) devices are providing new methods for patients
      to remotely monitor their chronic conditions and for providers to improve healthcare
      delivery. These technologies include smartphone 'apps', wearable and wireless devices such as
      the smartphone-ECG, sensor-based technologies, pocket-sized ultrasound and miniaturized
      lab-on-a-chip technologies. Several design features of mHealth are well suited for use in
      resource-limited areas and used as a practitioner-based diagnostic tool including
      portability, lower cost, and simple to use form factors. Although an attractive method for
      new technology utilization, the impact of mHealth used as a practitioner-based
      clinical-decision-support tool on subsequent management and outcomes has not been previously
      evaluated.

      Several barriers to effective healthcare exist in resource-limited areas that requires
      multidisciplinary collaborations between the community, medical centers, health workers and
      patients. Developing new digital programs with healthcare innovations in these regions brings
      together a collaboration of industry, researchers, engineers and information technology
      partners. In the aggregate, a cumulative effort across several disciplines is necessary in
      order to assess the feasibility, utility, and impact of new devices in resource constrained
      areas. The investigators describe a multidisciplinary and global effort across institutions
      in India and the United States. The investigators received support from international medical
      societies and device manufacturers to advance our knowledge for technology utilization and to
      improve healthcare access and outcomes for patients in resource limited areas.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to definitive treatment with Valvuloplasty or Valve Replacement</measure>
    <time_frame>Upto 12 months after enrollment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular Hospitalization and/or Death</measure>
    <time_frame>Upto 12 months after enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary outcomes included the occurrence of a cardiovascular hospitalization and/or death over 12-months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">253</enrollment>
  <condition>Rheumatic Heart Disease</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mHealth</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each participant randomized to a mHealth assessment were evaluated with: (1) structural abnormalities with handheld-echocardiography (Vscan®, General Electric Healthcare); (2) vital signs with smartphone-connected oxymetry and blood pressure monitors (iHealthLabs®); (3) functional assessments on a 6-minute walk test with a trial-axial activity monitor (Ozeri®); (4) cardiac rhythm abnormalities with smartphone-connected- iECG (AliveCor®) and; (5)point-of-care testing with fingerstick B-type natriuretic peptide (Alere). All study participants then underwent a comprehensive transthoracic echocardiogram for anatomical assessments of the severity of rheumatic and structural heart disease prior to percutaneous valvuloplasty or a surgical valve replacement.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard-Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each participant randomized to a standard-assessment were evaluated with the resource available at the institution including a physical examination,12 lead-ECG, radiographic, laboratory testing as clinically required. All study participants underwent a comprehensive transthoracic echocardiogram for anatomical assessments of the severity of rheumatic and structural heart disease prior to percutaneous valvuloplasty or a surgical valve replacement.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mHealth</intervention_name>
    <description>After randomization and at the time of the initial encounter, study subjects are assessed at the point-of-care with mHealth devices that measure symptoms, functional status, and for structural abnormalities. These devices include activity monitoring for an assessment of a 6-minute walk test, smartphone connected blood pressure, oxymetry and ECG for functional assessments, and structural assessments with handheld-echocardiography and point-of-care BNP. Treatment decisions for an intervention with percutaneous valvuloplasty or valve replacement were performed based on the aggregate of these mHealth findings. Confirmation of the severity of structural heart disease on transthoracic echocardiography was performed on all participants.</description>
    <arm_group_label>mHealth</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard-Care</intervention_name>
    <description>After randomization and at the time of the initial encounter, study subjects randomized to standard-care underwent a physical examination, 12-lead ECG, radiographic and laboratory tests as warranted and clinically required. Treatment decisions for percutaneous valvuloplasty or valve replacement were based on the aggregate of the standard-care findings. Confirmation of the severity of structural heart disease on transthoracic echocardiography was performed on all participants.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard-Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Symptomatic outpatients with a new or an established diagnosis of rheumatic and
             structural heart disease and included valvular disease, left/right ventricular
             failure, rheumatic valvular disease, congenital heart defects and included adult,
             pediatric, and pregnant patients. Patients with a prior valvuloplasty or valve
             replacement for structural heart disease were also included

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Exclusions included neonatal patients and those with an unstable hemodynamic status
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Srikanth Sola, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sri Sathya Sai Institute of Higher Medical Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sanjeev Bhavnani, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Scripps Clinic and Reseach Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Partho Sengupta, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mt. Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Singh S, Bansal M, Maheshwari P, Adams D, Sengupta SP, Price R, Dantin L, Smith M, Kasliwal RR, Pellikka PA, Thomas JD, Narula J, Sengupta PP; ASE-REWARD Study Investigators. American Society of Echocardiography: Remote Echocardiography with Web-Based Assessments for Referrals at a Distance (ASE-REWARD) Study. J Am Soc Echocardiogr. 2013 Mar;26(3):221-33. doi: 10.1016/j.echo.2012.12.012.</citation>
    <PMID>23439071</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bansal M, Singh S, Maheshwari P, Adams D, McCulloch ML, Dada T, Sengupta SP, Kasliwal RR, Pellikka PA, Sengupta PP; VISION-in-Tele-Echo Study Investigators. Value of interactive scanning for improving the outcome of new-learners in transcontinental tele-echocardiography (VISION-in-Tele-Echo) study. J Am Soc Echocardiogr. 2015 Jan;28(1):75-87. doi: 10.1016/j.echo.2014.09.001. Epub 2014 Oct 8.</citation>
    <PMID>25306222</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bhavnani SP, Narula J, Sengupta PP. Mobile technology and the digitization of healthcare. Eur Heart J. 2016 May 7;37(18):1428-38. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehv770. Epub 2016 Feb 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26873093</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bansal M, Sengupta PP. Setting global standards in adult echocardiography: Where are we? Indian Heart J. 2015 Jul-Aug;67(4):298-301. doi: 10.1016/j.ihj.2015.07.020. Epub 2015 Aug 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26304560</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Drain PK, Hyle EP, Noubary F, Freedberg KA, Wilson D, Bishai WR, Rodriguez W, Bassett IV. Diagnostic point-of-care tests in resource-limited settings. Lancet Infect Dis. 2014 Mar;14(3):239-49. doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(13)70250-0. Epub 2013 Dec 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24332389</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yusuf S, Rangarajan S, Teo K, Islam S, Li W, Liu L, Bo J, Lou Q, Lu F, Liu T, Yu L, Zhang S, Mony P, Swaminathan S, Mohan V, Gupta R, Kumar R, Vijayakumar K, Lear S, Anand S, Wielgosz A, Diaz R, Avezum A, Lopez-Jaramillo P, Lanas F, Yusoff K, Ismail N, Iqbal R, Rahman O, Rosengren A, Yusufali A, Kelishadi R, Kruger A, Puoane T, Szuba A, Chifamba J, Oguz A, McQueen M, McKee M, Dagenais G; PURE Investigators. Cardiovascular risk and events in 17 low-, middle-, and high-income countries. N Engl J Med. 2014 Aug 28;371(9):818-27. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1311890.</citation>
    <PMID>25162888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Marijon E, Ou P, Celermajer DS, Ferreira B, Mocumbi AO, Jani D, Paquet C, Jacob S, Sidi D, Jouven X. Prevalence of rheumatic heart disease detected by echocardiographic screening. N Engl J Med. 2007 Aug 2;357(5):470-6.</citation>
    <PMID>17671255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Engelman D, Kado JH, Reményi B, Colquhoun SM, Carapetis JR, Donath S, Wilson NJ, Steer AC. Focused cardiac ultrasound screening for rheumatic heart disease by briefly trained health workers: a study of diagnostic accuracy. Lancet Glob Health. 2016 Jun;4(6):e386-94. doi: 10.1016/S2214-109X(16)30065-1.</citation>
    <PMID>27198843</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mirabel M, Bacquelin R, Tafflet M, Robillard C, Huon B, Corsenac P, de Frémicourt I, Narayanan K, Meunier JM, Noël B, Hagège AA, Rouchon B, Jouven X, Marijon E. Screening for rheumatic heart disease: evaluation of a focused cardiac ultrasound approach. Circ Cardiovasc Imaging. 2015 Jan;8(1). pii: e002324. doi: 10.1161/CIRCIMAGING.114.002324.</citation>
    <PMID>25567654</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 18, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 23, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 29, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 23, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 23, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 29, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Sri Sathya Sai Institute of Higher Medical Sciences</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Srikanth Sola</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Additional Senior Consultant</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mobile Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Telemedicine</keyword>
  <keyword>Pocket-Echocardiography</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rheumatic Heart Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data will be made available to requesting investigators and 6 months after publication</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

