<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02883153</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>08121986</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02883153</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Zirconium-89-girentuximab PET/CT Imaging in Renal Cell Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Zirconium-89-girentuximab PET/CT Imaging in Patients Suspected of Primary or Relapse Clear Cell Renal Cell Carcinoma: The Impact on Clinical Decision Making.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Radboud University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Radboud University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Girentuximab is an antibody against Carbonic Anhydrase IX (CAIX), an antigen that is
      expressed on the cell surface of 95% of clear cell RCC (ccRCC). Zr-89-girentuximab PET/CT
      (Positron Emission Tomography) may be a valuable imaging technique in the diagnosis of
      patients with RCC. The aim of the present study is to show the impact of the
      Zr-89-girentuximab PET/CT on the clinical management of ccRCC patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      More advanced imaging methods are needed to reliably distinguish benign small renal masses
      (SRM) from renal cell carcinoma (RCC) to prevent invasive biopsies or unnecessary surgery.
      Similarly, improved imaging methods are needed for unambiguous detection of lesions suspect
      for metastatic and relapse RCC during follow-up. Girentuximab is an antibody against Carbonic
      Anhydrase IX (CAIX), an antigen that is expressed on the cell surface of 95% of clear cell
      RCC (ccRCC). Zr-89-girentuximab PET/CT may be a valuable imaging technique in the diagnosis
      of patients with RCC. The aim of the present study is to show the impact of the
      Zr-89-girentuximab PET/CT on the clinical management of ccRCC patients. Thirty patients will
      be included in whom conventional diagnostics are inconclusive. During a multidisciplinary
      team (MDT) the hypothetical next step in the clinical process will be noted (e.g. further
      diagnostics, treatment or active surveillance). Subsequently, in these patients a
      Zirconium-89-girentuximab PET/CT will be performed. Patients will receive a single
      intravenous dose of 5 mg Zirconium-89-girentuximab (37 MBq). A PET/CT scan will be acquired 4
      or 5 days after injection. The Zirconium-89-girentuximab PET/CT will be read by a clinician
      with extensive experience in radiolabeled girentuximab imaging. The results of the PET/CT
      will be discussed during the MDT and will be used to decide what the next step in the
      clinical process will be. This step will be compared with the hypothetical next step from the
      MDT before the scan.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 6, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 6, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact on clinical decision making</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Impact on clinical decision making, defined as present or absent:
Absent: e.g. no change in treatment or follow-up
Present: e.g. change in follow-up schedule, change in surgical technique, change from surgery to active surveillance, or change from surgery to systemic treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Zirconium-89 girentuximab PET/CT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A Zirconium-89-girentuximab PET/CT will be performed 4-5 days after single intravenous injection of 5 mg Zirconium-89-girentuximab (37 MBq).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Zirconium-89 girentuximab PET/CT</intervention_name>
    <description>Thirty patients (suspected of ccRCC) will be included in whom conventional diagnostics are inconclusive. During a multidisciplinary team (MDT) the hypothetical next step in the clinical process will be noted. Subsequently, in these patients a Zirconium-89-girentuximab PET/CT will be performed 4-5 days after single intravenous injection of 5 mg Zirconium-89-girentuximab (37 MBq). The results of the PET/CT will be discussed during the MDT and will be used to decide what the next step in the clinical process will be. This step will be compared with the hypothetical next step from the MDT before the scan. Whether or not the PET/CT scan had impact on clinical decision making will be assessed for each individual patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Zirconium-89 girentuximab PET/CT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>girentuximab</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        In order to participate in this study, a subject must meet all of the following criteria:

          1. His or her clinician should face a diagnostic dilemma; e.g.

               -  patients with a renal mass of unknown origin, or

               -  patients with a primary renal mass in whom it is unclear whether there is
                  metastatic disease, or

               -  patients with a history of clear cell RCC with a suspicion of relapse or
                  metastatic disease.

          2. Minimum age 18 years

          3. Signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of a CAIX-negative or non clear cell RCC.

          -  Administration of tyrosine kinase inhibiters within 1 month prior to inclusion.

          -  Any medical condition present that in the opinion of the investigator will affect
             patients' clinical status. - Administration of a radioisotope within 10 physical half
             lives prior to study enrollment

          -  Pregnancy or lactation.

          -  Known hypersensitivity or HACA (human anti chimeric antibodies) against Girentuximab.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wim JG Oyen, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Radboud University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter FA Mulders, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Radboud University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Radboudumc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 25, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 25, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 30, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 16, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 16, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Zirconium-89</keyword>
  <keyword>PET/CT</keyword>
  <keyword>imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>girentuximab</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data will be published anonymously</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

