<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03304704</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999917180</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>17-I-N180</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03304704</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Community Dynamics of Malaria Transmission and Mosquito Feeding in Bancoumana, Mali</brief_title>
  <official_title>Community Dynamics of Malaria Transmission and Mosquito Feeding in Bancoumana, Mali</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Half of the world's population is at risk of malaria. Malaria is a disease that affects many
      people in Mali and other parts of Africa. It is caused by germs spread by mosquito bites.
      Malaria may be mild. But it can also be serious or can lead to death if it is not diagnosed
      and treated promptly. Researchers want to learn more about the disease so they can develop
      new approaches to malaria control.

      Objective:

      To collect data on how mosquitoes spread malaria and how many people get malaria in the
      community by comparing different areas, seasons, and years.

      Eligibility:

      Residents of a certain area of Mali who are of any age

      Design:

      Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history.

      All participants will have at least 1 visit. They will answer questions about their health
      and malaria. They may have a physical exam. They will have blood collected.

      Some participants will have 1 visit every month for 3 years. They will repeat the procedures
      above.

      These participants will have mosquitoes collected in their home monthly. They may be able to
      catch some of the mosquitoes alive or may need to use a spray to kill the mosquitoes.
      Participants in this part of the study can be up to 65 years old.

      Some participants will also have about 60 mosquitoes directly feed on their arm or leg for
      15-20 minutes each month. These participants must be 5-65 years old.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A vaccine that interrupts malaria transmission is critical to eradicate the disease, but
      improved assays are needed to measure the efficacy of vaccines. Transmission-blocking
      vaccines (TBVs) work by inducing antibodies in vaccinees that inhibit parasite development in
      the mosquito interrupting transmission. Efficacy of vaccines may be estimated by in vitro
      membrane feeding assays using immune sera and laboratory mosquitoes, but qualified assays
      that measure transmission in the field are needed to assess transmission-blocking
      interventions in natura. Clinical trials of TBV have started in Bancoumana, and we expect to
      expand TBV studies here and in adjacent areas in the future. This protocol will use a
      longitudinal cohort to gather information on mosquito feeding and infection patterns in
      Bancoumana and surrounding villages in Mali. Individuals actively participating in LMIV
      vaccine trials will be approached first for participation, including permission to contact
      their household and neighbors of their compound for participation. Households will be
      identified using census data and individuals will be consented for participation. Malaria
      smears will be obtained at monthly visits, in conjunction with mosquito collections in/around
      village residences and with direct skin feeds (DSFs) using insectary-raised mosquitoes.
      Parasite transmission to mosquitoes will be assessed longitudinally for differences by season
      and year, and compared between wild-caught and laboratory-raised mosquitoes. Data will also
      be obtained on gametocyte and parasite carriage rates by season and year. Genotyping of
      individual subjects will be performed to pair with the bloodmeals of wild-caught mosquitoes.

      A total of 3,200 volunteers from Bancoumana and surrounding areas will be enrolled into three
      distinct cohorts. The Genotype Only Cohort (n=1000), which will include the vaccine trial
      participants, will complete a single visit to obtain a blood sample for genotyping with no
      additional follow up. The DSF Cohort (n=1200) will enroll subjects aged 5 to 65 years for
      monthly blood sampling, DSF, and mosquito collection at their household. The Parasite
      Surveillance Cohort (n=1000) will enroll subjects under the age of 5 years (as young as 6
      months) and subjects of any age who are unwilling to participate in DSF; they will have
      monthly blood sampling and mosquito collection at their household. Enrollment into the
      Genotype and Parasite Surveillance Cohorts will be linked to full enrollment of the DSF
      Cohort. Participants in the Parasite Surveillance and DSF cohorts, will be followed for up to
      3 years, to collect data that will guide the design of future community-based trials of TBV.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Infection rate in mosquitoes by DSF (number of infected vs. number of dissected mosquitoes)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Infection rate in wild live-caught mosquitoes (number of infected vs.number of dissected mosquitoes)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">4800</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Genotype Only Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>The Genotype Only Cohort (n=1000), which will include the vaccine trial participants, will complete a single visit to obtain a blood sample for genotyping with no additional follow up.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DSF Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>The DSF Cohort (n=1200) will enroll subjects aged 5 to 65 years for monthly blood sampling, DSF, and mosquito collection at their household.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Parasite Surveillance Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>The Parasite Surveillance Cohort (n=1000) will enroll subjects under the age of 5 years (as young as 6 months) and subjects of any age who are unwilling to participate in DSF; they will have monthly blood sampling and mosquito collection at their household.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        A total of 3,200 volunteers from Bancoumana and surrounding areas will be enrolled into
        three distinct cohorts. The Genotype Only Cohort (n=1000), DSF Cohort (n=1200) and Parasite
        Surveillance Cohort (n=1000)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  GENOTYPE ONLY COHORT

               -  Any age

               -  Known resident of Bancoumana or the surrounding villages

               -  Acceptance and signature of the written informed consent and the assent for
                  children aged 12-17 years

               -  Willingness to allow stored laboratory specimens to be used for future research

          -  PARASITE SURVEILLANCE COHORT

               -  6 months to 65 years of age

               -  Known resident of Bancoumana or the surrounding villages

               -  Willingness to allow stored laboratory specimens to be used for future research

               -  Acceptance and signature of the written informed consent and the assent for
                  children aged 12-17 years

          -  DSF COHORT

               -  Aged between 5 and 65 years, inclusive

               -  Good general health as determined by review of medical history and/or clinical
                  testing at the time of screening

               -  Known resident of Bancoumana or the surrounding villages

               -  Willingness to allow stored laboratory specimens to be used for future research

               -  Willingness to undergo DSF

               -  Acceptance and signature of the written informed consent and the assent for
                  children aged 12-17 years

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  GENOTYPE ONLY COHORT

               -  Behavioral, cognitive, or psychiatric disease that in the opinion of the
                  investigator affects the ability of the subject to understand and cooperate with
                  the study protocol

               -  Other condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would jeopardize the
                  safety or rights of a volunteer participating in the trial or would render the
                  subject unable to comply with the protocol

          -  PARASITE SURVEILLANCE CHORT

               -  Behavioral, cognitive, or psychiatric disease that in the opinion of the
                  investigator affects the ability of the subject to understand and cooperate with
                  the study protocol

               -  Other condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would jeopardize the
                  safety or rights of a volunteer participating in the trial or would render the
                  subject unable to comply with the protocol

               -  Currently enrolled participant in protocol 17-I-N006 or another active LMIV/MRTC
                  vaccine clinical trial

          -  DSF COHORT

               -  Behavioral, cognitive, or psychiatric disease that in the opinion of the
                  investigator affects the ability of the subject to understand and cooperate with
                  the study protocol

               -  Other condition that, in the opinion of the investigator, would jeopardize the
                  safety or rights of a volunteer participating in the trial or would render the
                  subject unable to comply with the protocol

               -  Currently enrolled participant in protocol 17-I-N006 or another LMIV/MRTC vaccine
                  clinical trial

               -  History of severe reaction to mosquito bites
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer C Hume</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer C Hume</last_name>
    <phone>(240) 747-7502</phone>
    <email>jennifer.hume@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bancoumana Malaria Vaccine Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bamako</city>
        <country>Mali</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mali</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toure YT, Doumbo O, Toure A, Bagayoko M, Diallo M, Dolo A, Vernick KD, Keister DB, Muratova O, Kaslow DC. Gametocyte infectivity by direct mosquito feeds in an area of seasonal malaria transmission: implications for Bancoumana, Mali as a transmission-blocking vaccine site. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 1998 Sep;59(3):481-6.</citation>
    <PMID>9749648</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Diallo M, Touré AM, Traoré SF, Niaré O, Kassambara L, Konaré A, Coulibaly M, Bagayogo M, Beier JC, Sakai RK, Touré YT, Doumbo OK. Evaluation and optimization of membrane feeding compared to direct feeding as an assay for infectivity. Malar J. 2008 Dec 2;7:248. doi: 10.1186/1475-2875-7-248.</citation>
    <PMID>19055715</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Drakeley C, Sutherland C, Bousema JT, Sauerwein RW, Targett GA. The epidemiology of Plasmodium falciparum gametocytes: weapons of mass dispersion. Trends Parasitol. 2006 Sep;22(9):424-30. Epub 2006 Jul 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16846756</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 17, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 6, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 6, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 9, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Assays</keyword>
  <keyword>Direct Skin Feeds</keyword>
  <keyword>Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Parasite</keyword>
  <keyword>Gametocyte</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

