<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03308773</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017000308</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03308773</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Disease Prevention in Clinical Practice Base on Patient Specific Physiology</brief_title>
  <acronym>STOPDISEASE</acronym>
  <official_title>Physiology of Disease Prevention Observational Study in Clinical Practice</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Pacific Coast Family Medical Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Pacific Coast Family Medical Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      It is well known that the Type 2 diabetes and vascular disease are preceded by over ten years
      by metabolic dysfunction and anatomic changes that can be quantified. In order to develop
      effective preventive strategies and reduce the cost burden to the health care system,
      recognition of the earliest pathophysiology of Type 2 diabetes and vascular disease is
      clinically relevant. The interval retrospective evaluation of data from patient records,
      reflect the effectiveness of the various treatments implemented in clinical practice.

      Prevalence of &quot;prediabetes&quot; among American adults is estimated to be ~84 million, or one out
      of three Americans. Over a 5-7 year period approximately one third of these prediabetic
      individuals will progress to type 2 diabetes. Prediabetes is a heterogenous group comprised
      of individuals with impaired fasting glucose (IFG), impaired glucose tolerance (IGT), and
      increased A1c (5.7-6.4%). Although different pathophysiologies are present in individuals
      with IFG and IGT, their conversion rate to overt type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) is similar.

      Insulin resistance is a common causal feature of many of the pathophysiologic mechanisms
      linking macrovascular disease and type 2 diabetes. Because hyperglycemia is the major factor
      responsible for the development of microvascular complications, it logically follows that
      prevention of progression of prediabetes to overt diabetes should retard/prevent the
      development of the microvascular complications. From the measurement of plasma glucose,
      insulin, and c-peptide levels during the oral glucose tolerance test, one can derive measures
      of the two core defects responsible for the development of T2DM, i.e. insulin resistance and
      beta cell dysfunction as well as the degree of dysglycemia.

      By combining a standard medical evaluation with the evaluation of cardiovascular biomarkers,
      patients at intermediate risk of vascular disease can be identified. In these patients,
      carotid intima media thickness (IMT) and carotid plaque evaluation is offered to attempt to
      clarify risk.

      The hypothesis of this observational study is that the characterization of the physiology and
      anatomy of patients at risk of developing type 2 diabetes and/or cardiovascular disease can
      stratify risk of developing disease and direct treatment strategies tailored to the
      identified physiologic defect, leading to improvements in the delay or prevention of disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      It is well known that the Type 2 diabetes and vascular disease are preceded by over ten years
      by metabolic dysfunction and anatomic changes that can be quantified. In order to develop
      effective preventive strategies and reduce the cost burden to the health care system,
      recognition of the earliest pathophysiology of Type 2 diabetes and vascular disease is
      clinically relevant. In patients with risk factors for type 2 diabetes and/or vascular
      disease, we have quantified this dysmetabolic state using glucose tolerance testing to
      quantify insulin resistance and beta cell function while measuring vascular biomarkers as
      well as Intima-media thickness and carotid plaque to characterize cardiovascular risk. The
      interval retrospective evaluation of data from patient records, reflect the effectiveness of
      the various treatments implemented in clinical practice.

      Prevalence of &quot;prediabetes&quot; among American adults is estimated to be ~84 million, or one out
      of three Americans. Over a 5-7 year period approximately one third of these prediabetic
      individuals will progress to type 2 diabetes. Prediabetes is a heterogenous group comprised
      of individuals with impaired fasting glucose (IFG), impaired glucose tolerance (IGT), and
      increased A1c (5.7-6.4%). Although different pathophysiologies are present in individuals
      with IFG and IGT, their conversion rate to overt type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM) is similar.

      Prospective epidemiologic studies have demonstrated that ~40% of subjects who progress to
      T2DM over 5 years had Normal glucose tolerance (NGT) at baseline, suggesting that a large
      group of NGT subjects also are at increased T2DM risk. It has previously been demonstrated
      that a 1-hour plasma glucose concentration &gt;155 mg/dl identifies a subgroup of NGT subjects
      with high future T2DM risk.

      Further, multiple studies have demonstrated that background retinopathy, microalbuminuria,
      and peripheral neuropathy are present in 10-20% of prediabetic individuals. Compared with
      normoglycemic patients, those with prediabetes were associated with a 13-30% higher risk for
      composite cardiovascular disease.

      Insulin resistance is a common causal feature of many of the pathophysiologic mechanisms
      linking macrovascular disease and type 2 diabetes. Because hyperglycemia is the major factor
      responsible for the development of microvascular complications, it logically follows that
      prevention of progression of prediabetes to overt diabetes should retard/prevent the
      development of the microvascular complications. From the measurement of plasma glucose,
      insulin, and c-peptide levels during the oral glucose tolerance test, one can derive measures
      of the two core defects responsible for the development of T2DM, i.e. insulin resistance and
      beta cell dysfunction as well as the degree of dysglycemia.

      The need for improvement in the identification of asymptomatic atherosclerosis is exemplified
      by the observation that nearly 50% of patients suffering a first myocardial infarction have
      either, none or only one of the standard risk factors; smoking, diabetes,
      hypercholesterolemia, hypertension and family history of heart disease. By combining a
      standard medical evaluation with the evaluation of cardiovascular biomarkers, patients at
      intermediate risk of vascular disease can be identified. In these patients, carotid intima
      media thickness and carotid plaque evaluation is offered to attempt to clarify risk.

      Further associations exist between insulin resistance and other medical conditions including;
      fatty liver, epicardial fat, diastolic dysfunction, arrhythmia, dementia and cancer.
      Quantifying insulin resistance may allow advances in preventive strategies.

      Following these evaluations, a discussion of the scientific literature as well as the risk,
      benefits and alternatives available, a personalized treatment plan is generated. Interval
      reassessment is carried out as part of the routine medical care of the patients in the
      practice.

      The hypothesis of this observational study is that the characterization of the physiology and
      anatomy of patients at risk of developing type 2 diabetes and/or cardiovascular disease can
      stratify risk of developing disease and direct treatment strategies tailored to the
      identified physiologic defect, leading to improvements in the delay or prevention of disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 5, 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2027</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2027</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who develop type 2 diabetes based on response to oral glucose tolerance test</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months and an average of every 2 years through the study completion, approximately 20 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will be monitored for up to 20 years (10 year retrospective plus 10 year prospective). The outcome measure will reflect the number of patients who develop of type 2 diabetes as evidenced by the response to oral glucose tolerance testing.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to development of type 2 diabetes</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months and an average of every 2 years through the study completion, approximately 20 years</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will be monitored for up to 20 years (10 year retrospective plus 10 year prospective). The outcome measure will reflect the time to the development of type 2 diabetes as evidenced by the response to oral glucose tolerance testing.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5000</enrollment>
  <condition>PreDiabetes</condition>
  <condition>Insulin Resistance</condition>
  <condition>Type2 Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>NASH - Nonalcoholic Steatohepatitis</condition>
  <condition>Diastolic Dysfunction</condition>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Carotid Plaque</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lifestyle modification in routine care of patients</intervention_name>
    <description>Diabetes Prevention Program Lifestyle recommendations and non-investigational pharmacotherapy in routine care of patients</description>
    <other_name>non-investigational drug in routine care of patients</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Internal Medicine/Endocrinology private practice in Southern California
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  American Diabetic Association (ADA)/American Association of Clinical Endocrinologists
             (AACE) criteria for patients at risk for developing type 2 diabetes

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with prior treatment with medications for type 2 diabetes
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John P Armato, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Providence St Josephs Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Menke A, Casagrande S, Geiss L, Cowie CC. Prevalence of and Trends in Diabetes Among Adults in the United States, 1988-2012. JAMA. 2015 Sep 8;314(10):1021-9. doi: 10.1001/jama.2015.10029.</citation>
    <PMID>26348752</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abdul-Ghani MA, Tripathy D, DeFronzo RA. Contributions of beta-cell dysfunction and insulin resistance to the pathogenesis of impaired glucose tolerance and impaired fasting glucose. Diabetes Care. 2006 May;29(5):1130-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16644654</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abdul-Ghani MA, Jenkinson CP, Richardson DK, Tripathy D, DeFronzo RA. Insulin secretion and action in subjects with impaired fasting glucose and impaired glucose tolerance: results from the Veterans Administration Genetic Epidemiology Study. Diabetes. 2006 May;55(5):1430-5.</citation>
    <PMID>16644701</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Diabetes Prevention Program Research Group. The prevalence of retinopathy in impaired glucose tolerance and recent-onset diabetes in the Diabetes Prevention Program. Diabet Med. 2007 Feb;24(2):137-44.</citation>
    <PMID>17257275</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DREAM Trial Investigators, Dagenais GR, Gerstein HC, Holman R, Budaj A, Escalante A, Hedner T, Keltai M, Lonn E, McFarlane S, McQueen M, Teo K, Sheridan P, Bosch J, Pogue J, Yusuf S. Effects of ramipril and rosiglitazone on cardiovascular and renal outcomes in people with impaired glucose tolerance or impaired fasting glucose: results of the Diabetes REduction Assessment with ramipril and rosiglitazone Medication (DREAM) trial. Diabetes Care. 2008 May;31(5):1007-14. doi: 10.2337/dc07-1868. Epub 2008 Feb 11.</citation>
    <PMID>18268075</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Asghar O, Petropoulos IN, Alam U, Jones W, Jeziorska M, Marshall A, Ponirakis G, Fadavi H, Boulton AJ, Tavakoli M, Malik RA. Corneal confocal microscopy detects neuropathy in subjects with impaired glucose tolerance. Diabetes Care. 2014 Sep;37(9):2643-6. doi: 10.2337/dc14-0279. Epub 2014 Jun 26.</citation>
    <PMID>24969581</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gibbons CH, Goebel-Fabbri A. Microvascular Complications Associated With Rapid Improvements in Glycemic Control in Diabetes. Curr Diab Rep. 2017 Jul;17(7):48. doi: 10.1007/s11892-017-0880-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28526993</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Defronzo RA. Banting Lecture. From the triumvirate to the ominous octet: a new paradigm for the treatment of type 2 diabetes mellitus. Diabetes. 2009 Apr;58(4):773-95. doi: 10.2337/db09-9028.</citation>
    <PMID>19336687</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Armato J, DeFronzo RA, Abdul-Ghani M, Ruby R. Successful treatment of prediabetes in clinical practice: targeting insulin resistance and β-cell dysfunction. Endocr Pract. 2012 May-Jun;18(3):342-50. doi: 10.4158/EP11194.OR.</citation>
    <PMID>22068250</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang Y, Cai X, Mai W, Li M, Hu Y. Association between prediabetes and risk of cardiovascular disease and all cause mortality: systematic review and meta-analysis. BMJ. 2016 Nov 23;355:i5953. doi: 10.1136/bmj.i5953. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27881363</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 28, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 11, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 13, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Pacific Coast Family Medical Group</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>John Armato</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Physician, Principle investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prediabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>insulin resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>T2DM</keyword>
  <keyword>Carotid IMT/Plaque</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin Resistance</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Prediabetic State</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucose Intolerance</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

