<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03307759</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SABRseq</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03307759</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sequencing of Stereotactic Ablative Body Radiotherapy in Combination With PD-1 Blockade Using Pembrolizumab in Metastatic Non-Small Cell Lung Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <acronym>SABRseq</acronym>
  <official_title>Sequencing of Stereotactic Ablative Body Radiotherapy in Combination With PD-1 Blockade Using Pembrolizumab in Metastatic Non-Small Cell Lung Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, Australia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre, Australia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This investigator driven Phase Ib study will examine the safety, efficacy and biological
      effects of two schedules of pembrolizumab, an antibody targeted against anti-programmed cell
      death 1 (PD-1), which will be given either before or after stereotactic ablative body
      radiotherapy (SABR) for metastatic NSCLC.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 4, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 4, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events measured using CTCAE version 4.03</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 24 months after commencement of treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response assessed using RECIST 1.1</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response assessed using irRECIST</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response assessed using PERCIST1.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response assessed using Peter Mac Metabolic Response Criteria</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomisation until the date of death from any cause assessed up to the date when the last patient has their 24 months assessment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From randomisation until the date of first progression or until the date of death from any cause, whichever occurs first, assessed up to the date when the last patient has their 24 months assessment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SABR plus pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>SABR followed by pembrolizumab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab plus SABR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pembrolizumab followed by SABR after cycle 1</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pembrolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Pembrolizumab</description>
    <arm_group_label>SABR plus pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab plus SABR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiotherapy (SABR)</intervention_name>
    <description>Radiotherapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>SABR plus pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pembrolizumab plus SABR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Have provided written informed consent for the trial.

          2. Be ≥ 18 years of age on day of signing informed consent.

          3. Have at least one lesion not planned for SABR that is measurable disease based on
             RECIST 1.1.

          4. Patients must have a histologically or cytologically confirmed metastatic non-small
             cell lung cancer.

          5. Patients with disease previously untreated with systemic therapy must have ≥ 50% PD-L1
             staining and patients who have previously received systemic therapy must have ≥ 1%
             PD-L1 staining on immunohistochemistry

          6. Patients must have at least 1-3 lesions suitable for treatment with stereotactic
             radiotherapy.

          7. Be willing to provide tissue from a newly obtained core or excisional biopsy of a
             tumour lesion where feasible. Newly-obtained is defined as a specimen obtained up to
             12 weeks prior to randomisation. Patients for whom newly-obtained samples cannot be
             provided (e.g. inaccessible or patient safety concern) may submit an archived specimen
             only upon agreement from the study principal investigators.

          8. Have a performance status of 0-1 on the ECOG Performance Scale (see Appendix 1).

          9. Demonstrate adequate organ function as defined in table 3 below, all screening labs
             should be performed within 10 days of randomisation.

             Table 3 Adequate Organ Function Laboratory Values

             Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1.5x109/L Platelets≥100x109L Haemoglobin ≥90 g/L
             without transfusion or EPO dependency (within 7 days of assessment)

             Serum creatinine OR Measured or calculated creatinine clearance (GFR can also be used
             in place of creatinine or CrCl) ≤1.5 X upper limit of normal (ULN) OR ≥30 mL/min for
             patients with creatinine levels &gt; 1.5 X institutional ULN

             Serum total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 X ULN OR Direct bilirubin ≤ ULN for patients with total
             bilirubin levels &gt; 1.5 ULN AST (SGOT) and ALT (SGPT)≤ 2.5 X ULN OR ≤ 5 X ULN for
             patients with liver metastases

             International Normalized Ratio (INR) or Prothrombin Time (PT) Activated Partial
             Thromboplastin Time (aPTT) ≤1.5 X ULN unless patient is receiving anticoagulant
             therapy as long as PT or PTT is within therapeutic range of intended use of
             anticoagulants ≤1.5 X ULN unless patient is receiving anticoagulant therapy as long as
             PT or PTT is within therapeutic range of intended use of anticoagulants

         10. Life expectancy &gt; 3 months.

         11. Be willing and able to comply with all study requirements, including treatment,
             attending assessments and follow-up.

         12. Female patient of childbearing potential should have a negative urine or serum
             pregnancy within 7 days of randomisation. If the urine test is positive or cannot be
             confirmed as negative, a serum pregnancy test will be required.

         13. Female patients of childbearing potential should be willing to use 2 methods of birth
             control or be surgically sterile, or abstain from heterosexual activity for the course
             of the study through 120 days after the last dose of study medication (See Section
             8.10). Patients of childbearing potential are those who have not been surgically
             sterilized or have not been free from menses for &gt; 1 year.

         14. Male patients should agree to use an adequate method of contraception starting with
             the first dose of study therapy through 120 days after the last dose of study therapy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has had previous high dose radiotherapy (biological equivalent of &gt;30Gy in 10#) to an
             area to be treated which includes vertebral bodies (see below).

             Note: Previous high dose radiotherapy is defined as a biological equivalent dose to
             above that of 30 Gy in 10 fractions using an alpha/beta ratio (50) of 3.

             Where a patient has received radiotherapy to an equivalent or lower dose than defined
             above, stereotactic radiotherapy of the area may be considered. In doing so,
             assessment of the volume and total dose received by any overlap region must be made,
             and documented by generating a cumulative plan incorporating both the previous and
             current treatment fields. It is the treating radiation oncologist's responsibility to
             review both the current plan and the cumulative plan inclusive of previous
             radiotherapy.

          2. Has had previous thoracic radiotherapy of &gt; 36Gy within the 6 months prior to
             randomisation.

          3. Has known active central nervous system (CNS) metastases and/or carcinomatous
             meningitis. Patients with small asymptomatic or previously treated brain metastases
             may participate provided they are stable (without evidence of progression by imaging
             for at least four weeks prior to the first dose of trial treatment and any neurologic
             symptoms have returned to baseline), have no evidence of enlarging brain metastases,
             and are not using steroids for intracranial neurological symptoms at least 7 days
             prior to trial randomisation. This exception does not include leptomeningeal disease
             which is excluded regardless of clinical stability.

          4. Has evidence of Spinal Cord Compression.

          5. Has a Spinal Instability Neoplastic Score ≥ 7 unless lesion reviewed by a
             neurosurgical service and considered stable (see Appendix 2).

          6. Requires surgical fixation of bone lesion for stability. All surgical fixation and
             instrumentation must be completed before randomisation on study.

          7. Is currently participating and receiving study therapy or has participated in a study
             of an investigational agent and received study therapy or used an investigational
             device within 4 weeks of randomisation.

          8. Has a diagnosis of immunodeficiency.

          9. Has a known history of active TB (Bacillus Tuberculosis).

         10. Has a hypersensitivity to pembrolizumab or any of its excipients.

         11. Has had a prior anti-cancer monoclonal antibody (mAb) within 4 weeks prior to
             randomisation or who has not recovered (i.e., ≤ Grade 1 or at baseline) from adverse
             events due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier.

         12. Has diagnosed and/or treated additional malignancy within 5 years prior to
             randomisation with the exception of: curatively treated basal cell carcinoma of the
             skin, squamous cell carcinoma of the skin, curatively treated early stage cervical
             cancer, breast cancer or prostate cancer with no evidence of active disease. Other
             exceptions may be considered following consultation with the principal investigator

         13. Has active autoimmune disease that has required systemic treatment in the past 2 years
             (i.e. with use of disease modifying agents, corticosteroids or immunosuppressive
             drugs). Replacement therapy (e.g. thyroxine, insulin, or physiologic corticosteroid
             replacement therapy for adrenal or pituitary insufficiency, etc.) is not considered a
             form of systemic treatment.

         14. Has a history of (non-infectious) pneumonitis that required steroids or current
             pneumonitis.

         15. Has had any systemic anti-cancer therapy or radiation therapy within 4 weeks prior to
             randomisation

         16. Has known interstitial lung disease

         17. Has an active infection requiring systemic therapy.

         18. Has a history or current evidence of any condition, therapy, or laboratory abnormality
             that might confound the results of the trial, interfere with the patient's
             participation for the full duration of the trial, or is not in the best interest of
             the patient to participate, in the opinion of the treating investigator.

         19. Has known psychiatric or substance abuse disorders that would interfere with
             cooperation with the requirements of the trial.

         20. Has received prior therapy with an anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, or anti-PD-L2 agent.

         21. Has a known history of Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) (HIV 1/2 antibodies).

         22. Has known active Hepatitis B (e.g., HBsAg reactive) or Hepatitis C (e.g., HCV RNA
             [qualitative] is detected).

         23. Has received a live vaccine within 30 days of randomisation. Note: Seasonal influenza
             vaccines for injection are generally inactivated flu vaccines and are allowed; however
             intranasal influenza vaccines (e.g., Flu- Mist®) are live attenuated vaccines, and are
             not allowed. -
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shankar Siva, Associate Professor</last_name>
    <phone>+61 3 8559 5000</phone>
    <email>Shankar.Siva@petermac.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Peter MacCallum Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shankar Siva, Associate Professor</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ben Solomon, Professor</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 6, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 11, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 12, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 12, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

