<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03304912</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R21DA043417-01A1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03304912</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Packaging PrEP to Prevent HIV Among WWID</brief_title>
  <official_title>Packaging Pre-Exposure Prophylaxis (PrEP) to Prevent HIV Transmission Among Women Who Inject Drugs</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Drexel University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Drexel University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) is a promising bio-medical HIV prevention strategy that
      involves the use of single daily dose of emtricitabine/tenofovir disoproxil fumarate
      (FTC/TDF) by HIV-negative individuals to reduce risk of acquiring HIV. Evidence suggests
      women who inject drugs (WWID) are disproportionately vulnerable to HIV. If HIV incidence
      continues unchecked, 1 in 23 WWID in the United States will acquire HIV. One concern
      regarding PrEP implementation for WWID is that they will face a number of challenges to
      engaging in PrEP care. To reduce barriers and thereby increase the individual and public
      health benefits of PrEP, alternative approaches based outside of traditional clinical
      settings are needed. The proposed research is significant, because PrEP could reduce HIV
      acquisition among WWID. However, at present, there is little knowledge to help address PrEP
      implementation challenges for this understudied group. The proposed research is highly
      innovative, because it will address this knowledge gap by evaluating a novel approach for the
      delivery of PrEP care: pairing PrEP with community-based syringe exchange program (SEP)
      services. This approach may represent a paradigm shift that enables and encourages women in
      this highly vulnerable population to engage in effective biomedical HIV prevention
      strategies. The rationale is that (1) SEPs may currently provide prescription medications and
      long-term monitoring for other conditions such as buprenorphine for opioid dependence, so
      providing PrEP care is a natural extension of what is already being done successfully; (2)
      SEPs are a viable access point for many HIV-uninfected WWID who would be considered eligible
      for PrEP under current clinical guidelines; and (3) PrEP interventions, delivered in settings
      already utilized and trusted by WWID, will increase uptake, adherence and retention in PrEP.
      To evaluate this approach, a prospective mixed methods study will be initiated within the
      largest SEP in the mid-Atlantic region. Through semi-structured and in-depth interviews based
      on the Behavioral Model for Vulnerable Populations, and drug-level monitoring for FTC/TDF
      adherence, the following specific aims will be addressed: (1) Describe WWID's engagement in
      the PrEP care continuum (focusing on critical moments when women could disengage or need
      additional support to remain in care). (2) Identify factors from the BVMP that are associated
      with WWID's engagement in the PrEP care continuum. (3) Explore how and why model factors are
      associated with WWID's decisions and ability to engage in PrEP care. A paired model of PrEP
      and SEP services has yet to be tested. This is exploratory study will provide preliminary
      data to generate hypotheses for future intervention studies. The long-term outcome of this
      research program will be a reduction in HIV among WWID through the delivery of HIV prevention
      interventions that include PrEP. The reproducibility of this approach, resulting from
      utilization of an already functional service delivery system, significantly increases the
      potential for translation to other settings and PWID populations, including men who inject
      drugs, in domestic and global contexts.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 3, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PrEP Uptake: Receiving a Prescription</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will operationalize PrEP uptake in two ways:
First, as receiving a PrEP prescription assessed through medical chart review</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PrEP Uptake: Filling a Prescription</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will operationalize PrEP uptake in two ways:
Second, receiving the prescription and filling the prescription verified through pharmacy fill data</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PrEP adherence based on urinalysis</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will operationalize PrEP adherence in two ways:
First, based on the concentration of FTC in urine</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PrEP adherence based on self-report</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will operationalize PrEP adherence in two ways:
Second, using a validated self-report measure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">125</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV/AIDS</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>The cohort will be comprised of women who inject drugs who are eligible for PrEP.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PrEP Education and option to accept a PrEP prescription</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive educational information about PrEP, be offered a PrEP prescription, and those who choose to initiated PrEP will be monitored for side-effects and adherence at their follow-up visit. There is no group assignment within this study and WWID do not have to choose to initiate PrEP. Rather, the goal of this study is to understand factors that impact PrEP initiation (and engagement in the PrEP care continuum).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Community sample to be recruited from a syringe exchange program.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV sero-negative

          -  Females

          -  Age ≥18 years

          -  Reporting non-prescription injection drug use and any of the following:

               1. Syringe sharing

               2. Injecting drugs with a HIV-positive partner

               3. Recent opioid agonist treatment but still injecting drugs

               4. Sex exchange

               5. Inconsistent condom use

               6. Recent bacterial STI

               7. and/or sex with a HIV-positive partner

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV seropositivity

          -  Currently taking PrEP

          -  Pregnant, breastfeeding or trying to become pregnant

          -  Previous enrollment in the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Drexel University Dornsife School of Public Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexis M Roth, PhD, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>267-359-6123</phone>
      <email>amr395@drexel.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Brogan L Piecara, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>2673596037</phone>
      <email>blp33@drexel.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alexis M Roth, PhD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 29, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 3, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 9, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Drexel University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alexis Roth</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pre-Exposure Prophylaxis</keyword>
  <keyword>Injection Drug Use</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>N/A, IPD will not be shared.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

