<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03306797</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2088 CE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03306797</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Music Therapy for Rehabilitation in Stroke Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>SONICHAND</acronym>
  <official_title>Hand Rehabilitation With Music Therapy Technique (Sonification) and Leap Motion Controller in Stroke Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Istituti Clinici Scientifici Maugeri SpA</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Istituti Clinici Scientifici Maugeri SpA</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study uses a specific hand tracking sensor (Leap Motion Controller) to catch the
      movements of the arm combined with proper pre-defined musical patterns (sonification) in a
      neurologic music therapy perspective. The aim of the experiment is to verify the efficacy of
      sonification technique (compared to usual care) in the hand rehabilitation of patients with
      stroke.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction:

      Every year in Italy occur over than 200.000 new stroke cases. The virtual and augmented
      reality offers a valid support to the rehabilitation program by providing objectives
      parameters for the patient evaluation, accelerating the motor recovery process and enhancing
      the motor performance after the discharge. This study uses a specific hand tracking sensor
      (Leap Motion Controller) to catch the movements of the arm combined with proper pre-defined
      musical patterns (sonification) in a neurologic music therapy perspective.

      In addition to its use in relational contexts, in fact, music therapy is widely used in the
      field of rehabilitation, and in particular in the neuromotor rehabilitation, due to the
      impact of the sound, as well as on paralimbic and limbic areas, the areas of the brain
      involved in the movements (motor cortex, supplementary motor area, cerebellum, basal ganglia,
      etc.).

      Recent studies uses sonification for the rehabilitation of the upper limbs assuming a
      replacement of the proprioceptive aspects damaged by the disease thanks to the audio-motor
      feedback. This study, furthermore, exploits the specificities of the Leap Motion Controller
      and the peculiarities of the sound stimuli that accompany the arm movement without requiring
      cognitive tasks.

      Objectives:

        -  To verify through a randomized controlled trial and a suitable motor assessment the
           efficacy of the rehabilitation of the hand in patients with stroke using the
           &quot;sonification&quot; technique

        -  To verify whether the &quot;sonification&quot; technique reduces the fatigue and the pain
           perceived during rehabilitation

        -  Assess the impact of &quot;sonification&quot; technique on patients quality of life

      Materials and Methods:

      In this randomized controlled trial 66 patients with stroke will be recruited and allocated
      in 2 groups. The control group will be undergone to a 35 minutes standard daily
      rehabilitation treatment lasting 4 weeks. The experimental group will be undergone to an
      analogue treatment based on 15 minutes of standard rehabilitation and 20 minutes of exercises
      with sonification. Randomisation will be centralized for the four Units involved in the
      study.

      The intervention will be assessed in blind at the baseline (T0), at the mid-treatment period
      (T1 = 2 weeks), at the end of the treatment (T2 = 4 weeks), and at a follow-up point (T3 = 8
      weeks).

      The following assessment tools will be used:

        -  Fugl-Meyer Motor Assessment Scale

        -  Box and Block Test

        -  Modified Ashworth Scale

        -  Visual Analogue Scale (VAS)

        -  Numerical Pain Rating Scale

        -  McGill Quality of Life

      At T0, T1, T2 and T3 some motion parameters will be recorded and monitored by the Leap Motion
      Controller to evaluate possible changes in the movements execution.

      Statistics:

      The Intention-To-Treat (ITT) population will be considered for the analysis. An unpaired
      Student's t test on the pre (T0)-post treatment (T2) differences will be used to assess the
      primary endpoint. Longitudinal trends over time will be assessed through repeated measures
      analysis of variance. Other analyses will be available in the statistical analysis plan.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 28, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fugl-Meyer Motor Assessment Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Primary endpoint of the study is given by the measurement of proximal and distal upper limb motor skills assessed by the Fugl-Meyer Motor Assessment Scale. The primary endpoint will be assessed by comparing the variation between T0 and T2 of the scale scores above mentioned in the experimental and control groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Box and Block Test (BBT)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of unilateral gross manual dexterity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Ashworth Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Measurement of spasticity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Analogue Scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of perceived fatigue</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Numerical Pain Rating Scale (NPRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of pain intensity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>McGill Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of Quality of Life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">66</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Hand Injuries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SONICHAND</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention is similar to the standard protocol (15 minutes of warm-up plus 20 minute of training) but involves the sonification of the exercises (4 weeks, daily)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>STANDARD REHAB</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The rehabilitative standard intervention (Occupational Therapy) consists of 15 minutes of warm-up exercises plus a 20 minutes training for 4 weeks (daily)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>STANDARD REHAB</intervention_name>
    <description>The rehabilitative standard intervention (Occupational Therapy) consists of 15 minutes of warm-up exercises plus a 20 minutes training with at least 6 exercises selected from:
wrist
ulnarization radialization
prono-supination
horizontal flexion-extension
vertical flexion-extension hand
grasping
pinching
extensors
interosseous shoulder-elbow
vertical flexion-extension
push forward</description>
    <arm_group_label>STANDARD REHAB</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SONICHAND</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is similar to the standard protocol (15 minutes of warm-up plus 20 minute of training) but involves the sonification of the exercises selected from the list. The Leap Motion Controller is managed with an ad-hoc developed application that is able to associate the movements with a 4 notes arpeggio or with a modulated texture.
With the first mode the movement produces and modulates an harmonic progression built on the consecutive grades of the major scale played as ascending and descending arpeggio with also a volume crescendo and decrescendo.
With the second mode, the movement modulates the volume and the low-pass cutoff frequency of a synthetic texture.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SONICHAND</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  40-85 years old

          -  ischemic lesion in one hemisphere (hemiplegia / hemiparesis right or left)

          -  Mini Mental State Examination &gt; 24 onset acute event not later than 180 days prior to
             study entry

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Dated lesions beyond 6 months from onset

          -  Multiple or bilateral lesions

          -  Mini Mental State Examination &lt;24

          -  Presence of neglect

          -  Previous or concomitant disabling diseases for upper limb function (Eg: Parkinson's
             disease, multiple sclerosis, shoulder's periarthritis, Dupuytren's disease, etc.)

          -  Previous rehabilitative treatments with music
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alfredo Raglio, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>3387291944</phone>
    <phone_ext>+39</phone_ext>
    <email>alfredo.raglio@icsmaugeri.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ICS Maugeri, Nervi Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Genoa</city>
        <state>Genova</state>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ICS Maugeri, Montescano Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montescano</city>
        <state>Pavia</state>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ICS Maugeri, Pavia Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pavia</city>
        <zip>27100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Giacomo Bazzini, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0382 592472</phone>
      <phone_ext>+39</phone_ext>
      <email>giacomo.bazzini@icsmaugeri.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fondazione Santa Lucia IRCCS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rome</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marco Tramontano, MD</last_name>
      <phone>06 51501420</phone>
      <phone_ext>+39</phone_ext>
      <email>m.tramontano@hsantalucia.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Altenmüller E, Marco-Pallares J, Münte TF, Schneider S. Neural reorganization underlies improvement in stroke-induced motor dysfunction by music-supported therapy. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2009 Jul;1169:395-405. doi: 10.1111/j.1749-6632.2009.04580.x.</citation>
    <PMID>19673814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bangert M, Altenmüller EO. Mapping perception to action in piano practice: a longitudinal DC-EEG study. BMC Neurosci. 2003 Oct 15;4:26.</citation>
    <PMID>14575529</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bangert M, Peschel T, Schlaug G, Rotte M, Drescher D, Hinrichs H, Heinze HJ, Altenmüller E. Shared networks for auditory and motor processing in professional pianists: evidence from fMRI conjunction. Neuroimage. 2006 Apr 15;30(3):917-26. Epub 2005 Dec 27.</citation>
    <PMID>16380270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baumann S, Koeneke S, Schmidt CF, Meyer M, Lutz K, Jancke L. A network for audio-motor coordination in skilled pianists and non-musicians. Brain Res. 2007 Aug 3;1161:65-78. Epub 2007 Jun 4.</citation>
    <PMID>17603027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cha Y, Kim Y, Hwang S, Chung Y. Intensive gait training with rhythmic auditory stimulation in individuals with chronic hemiparetic stroke: a pilot randomized controlled study. NeuroRehabilitation. 2014;35(4):681-8. doi: 10.3233/NRE-141182.</citation>
    <PMID>25318784</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen P, Lai CKY, Chung RCK, Ng SSM. The Jacket Test for assessing people with chronic stroke. Disabil Rehabil. 2017 Dec;39(25):2577-2583. doi: 10.1080/09638288.2016.1236413. Epub 2016 Oct 28.</citation>
    <PMID>27793076</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chong HJ, Han SJ, Kim YJ, Park HY, Kim SJ. Relationship between output from MIDI-keyboard playing and hand function assessments on affected hand after stroke. NeuroRehabilitation. 2014;35(4):673-80. doi: 10.3233/NRE-141166.</citation>
    <PMID>25318775</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Conklyn D, Novak E, Boissy A, Bethoux F, Chemali K. The effects of modified melodic intonation therapy on nonfluent aphasia: a pilot study. J Speech Lang Hear Res. 2012 Oct;55(5):1463-71. doi: 10.1044/1092-4388(2012/11-0105). Epub 2012 Mar 12.</citation>
    <PMID>22411278</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Desrosiers J, Bravo G, Hébert R, Dutil E, Mercier L. Validation of the Box and Block Test as a measure of dexterity of elderly people: reliability, validity, and norms studies. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1994 Jul;75(7):751-5.</citation>
    <PMID>8024419</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hayden R, Clair AA, Johnson G, Otto D. The effect of rhythmic auditory stimulation (RAS) on physical therapy outcomes for patients in gait training following stroke: a feasibility study. Int J Neurosci. 2009;119(12):2183-95. doi: 10.3109/00207450903152609.</citation>
    <PMID>19916847</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huskisson EC. Measurement of pain. Lancet. 1974 Nov 9;2(7889):1127-31.</citation>
    <PMID>4139420</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim SJ, Koh I. The effects of music on pain perception of stroke patients during upper extremity joint exercises. J Music Ther. 2005 Spring;42(1):81-92.</citation>
    <PMID>15839735</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim DS, Park YG, Choi JH, Im SH, Jung KJ, Cha YA, Jung CO, Yoon YH. Effects of music therapy on mood in stroke patients. Yonsei Med J. 2011 Nov;52(6):977-81. doi: 10.3349/ymj.2011.52.6.977.</citation>
    <PMID>22028163</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim SJ, Jo U. Study of accent-based music speech protocol development for improving voice problems in stroke patients with mixed dysarthria. NeuroRehabilitation. 2013;32(1):185-90. doi: 10.3233/NRE-130835.</citation>
    <PMID>23422471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iosa M, Morone G, Fusco A, Castagnoli M, Fusco FR, Pratesi L, Paolucci S. Leap motion controlled videogame-based therapy for rehabilitation of elderly patients with subacute stroke: a feasibility pilot study. Top Stroke Rehabil. 2015 Aug;22(4):306-16. doi: 10.1179/1074935714Z.0000000036. Epub 2015 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>26258456</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jun EM, Roh YH, Kim MJ. The effect of music-movement therapy on physical and psychological states of stroke patients. J Clin Nurs. 2013 Jan;22(1-2):22-31. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2702.2012.04243.x. Epub 2012 Sep 17.</citation>
    <PMID>22978325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gregson JM, Leathley MJ, Moore AP, Smith TL, Sharma AK, Watkins CL. Reliability of measurements of muscle tone and muscle power in stroke patients. Age Ageing. 2000 May;29(3):223-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10855904</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lim KB, Kim YK, Lee HJ, Yoo J, Hwang JY, Kim JA, Kim SK. The therapeutic effect of neurologic music therapy and speech language therapy in post-stroke aphasic patients. Ann Rehabil Med. 2013 Aug;37(4):556-62. doi: 10.5535/arm.2013.37.4.556. Epub 2013 Aug 26.</citation>
    <PMID>24020037</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Magee WL, Davidson JW. The effect of music therapy on mood states in neurological patients: a pilot study. J Music Ther. 2002 Spring;39(1):20-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12015809</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meyer M, Elmer S, Baumann S, Jancke L. Short-term plasticity in the auditory system: differential neural responses to perception and imagery of speech and music. Restor Neurol Neurosci. 2007;25(3-4):411-31.</citation>
    <PMID>17943016</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Purdie H, Hamilton S, Baldwin S. Music therapy: facilitating behavioural and psychological change in people with stroke--a pilot study. Int J Rehabil Res. 1997 Sep;20(3):325-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9331582</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Särkämö T, Tervaniemi M, Laitinen S, Forsblom A, Soinila S, Mikkonen M, Autti T, Silvennoinen HM, Erkkilä J, Laine M, Peretz I, Hietanen M. Music listening enhances cognitive recovery and mood after middle cerebral artery stroke. Brain. 2008 Mar;131(Pt 3):866-76. doi: 10.1093/brain/awn013.</citation>
    <PMID>18287122</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Särkämö T, Pihko E, Laitinen S, Forsblom A, Soinila S, Mikkonen M, Autti T, Silvennoinen HM, Erkkilä J, Laine M, Peretz I, Hietanen M, Tervaniemi M. Music and speech listening enhance the recovery of early sensory processing after stroke. J Cogn Neurosci. 2010 Dec;22(12):2716-27. doi: 10.1162/jocn.2009.21376.</citation>
    <PMID>19925203</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schlaug G. Part VI introduction: listening to and making music facilitates brain recovery processes. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2009 Jul;1169:372-3. doi: 10.1111/j.1749-6632.2009.04869.x.</citation>
    <PMID>19673811</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schneider S, Schönle PW, Altenmüller E, Münte TF. Using musical instruments to improve motor skill recovery following a stroke. J Neurol. 2007 Oct;254(10):1339-46. Epub 2007 Jan 27.</citation>
    <PMID>17260171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scholz DS, Rohde S, Nikmaram N, Brückner HP, Großbach M, Rollnik JD, Altenmüller EO. Sonification of Arm Movements in Stroke Rehabilitation - A Novel Approach in Neurologic Music Therapy. Front Neurol. 2016 Jun 30;7:106. doi: 10.3389/fneur.2016.00106. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27445970</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scholz DS, Rhode S, Großbach M, Rollnik J, Altenmüller E. Moving with music for stroke rehabilitation: a sonification feasibility study. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2015 Mar;1337:69-76. doi: 10.1111/nyas.12691.</citation>
    <PMID>25773619</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scholz DS, Wu L, Pirzer J, Schneider J, Rollnik JD, Großbach M, Altenmüller EO. Sonification as a possible stroke rehabilitation strategy. Front Neurosci. 2014 Oct 20;8:332. doi: 10.3389/fnins.2014.00332. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25368548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sguazzin C, Giorgi I, Alesii A, Fini M. Italian validation of the McGill Quality of Life Questionnaire (MQOL-It). G Ital Med Lav Ergon. 2010 Jul-Sep;32(3 Suppl B):B58-62.</citation>
    <PMID>21299077</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smeragliuolo AH, Hill NJ, Disla L, Putrino D. Validation of the Leap Motion Controller using markered motion capture technology. J Biomech. 2016 Jun 14;49(9):1742-1750. doi: 10.1016/j.jbiomech.2016.04.006. Epub 2016 Apr 8.</citation>
    <PMID>27102160</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Suh JH, Han SJ, Jeon SY, Kim HJ, Lee JE, Yoon TS, Chong HJ. Effect of rhythmic auditory stimulation on gait and balance in hemiplegic stroke patients. NeuroRehabilitation. 2014;34(1):193-9. doi: 10.3233/NRE-131008.</citation>
    <PMID>24284453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tamplin J, Baker FA, Jones B, Way A, Lee S. 'Stroke a Chord': the effect of singing in a community choir on mood and social engagement for people living with aphasia following a stroke. NeuroRehabilitation. 2013;32(4):929-41. doi: 10.3233/NRE-130916.</citation>
    <PMID>23867418</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thaut MH, McIntosh GC, Rice RR. Rhythmic facilitation of gait training in hemiparetic stroke rehabilitation. J Neurol Sci. 1997 Oct 22;151(2):207-12.</citation>
    <PMID>9349677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thaut MH, Leins AK, Rice RR, Argstatter H, Kenyon GP, McIntosh GC, Bolay HV, Fetter M. Rhythmic auditory stimulation improves gait more than NDT/Bobath training in near-ambulatory patients early poststroke: a single-blind, randomized trial. Neurorehabil Neural Repair. 2007 Sep-Oct;21(5):455-9. Epub 2007 Apr 10.</citation>
    <PMID>17426347</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tung JY, Lulic T, Gonzalez DA, Tran J, Dickerson CR, Roy EA. Evaluation of a portable markerless finger position capture device: accuracy of the Leap Motion controller in healthy adults. Physiol Meas. 2015 May;36(5):1025-35. doi: 10.1088/0967-3334/36/5/1025. Epub 2015 Apr 22.</citation>
    <PMID>25902961</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Delden AL, Peper CL, Nienhuys KN, Zijp NI, Beek PJ, Kwakkel G. Unilateral versus bilateral upper limb training after stroke: the Upper Limb Training After Stroke clinical trial. Stroke. 2013 Sep;44(9):2613-6. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.113.001969. Epub 2013 Jul 18.</citation>
    <PMID>23868279</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Wijck F, Knox D, Dodds C, Cassidy G, Alexander G, MacDonald R. Making music after stroke: using musical activities to enhance arm function. Ann N Y Acad Sci. 2012 Apr;1252:305-11. doi: 10.1111/j.1749-6632.2011.06403.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22524372</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Villeneuve M, Penhune V, Lamontagne A. A piano training program to improve manual dexterity and upper extremity function in chronic stroke survivors. Front Hum Neurosci. 2014 Aug 22;8:662. doi: 10.3389/fnhum.2014.00662. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25202258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weichert F, Bachmann D, Rudak B, Fisseler D. Analysis of the accuracy and robustness of the leap motion controller. Sensors (Basel). 2013 May 14;13(5):6380-93. doi: 10.3390/s130506380.</citation>
    <PMID>23673678</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wittwer JE, Webster KE, Hill K. Rhythmic auditory cueing to improve walking in patients with neurological conditions other than Parkinson's disease--what is the evidence? Disabil Rehabil. 2013 Jan;35(2):164-76. doi: 10.3109/09638288.2012.690495. Epub 2012 Jun 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22681598</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 4, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 5, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 11, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Music therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Sonification technique</keyword>
  <keyword>Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hand Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

