<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03165123</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ABCD</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03165123</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Using Erythromycin A Versus Placebo With Dexamethasone in Prevention of Post-spinal Nausea and Vomiting.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Adding Erythromycin A to Dexamethasone in Preventing Post-operative Nausea and Vomiting in Caesarean Section Under Spinal Anesthesia With Spinal Opiate.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assiut University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assiut University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Postoperative nausea and vomiting is defined as any nausea, retching, or vomiting occurring
      during the first 24-48 h after surgery in inpatients. Postoperative nausea and vomiting is
      one of the most common causes of patient dissatisfaction after anesthesia, with reported
      incidences of 30% in all post-surgical patients and up to 80% in high-risk patients. In
      addition, postoperative nausea and vomiting is regularly rated in preoperative surveys, as
      the anesthesia outcome the patient would most like to avoid. While suture dehiscence,
      aspiration of gastric contents, esophageal rupture, and other serious complications
      associated with postoperative nausea and vomiting are rare, nausea and vomiting is still an
      unpleasant and all-too-common postoperative morbidity that can delay patient discharge from
      the post-anesthesia care unit and increase unanticipated hospital admissions in outpatients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There are many well-established risk factors for Postoperative nausea and vomiting which are
      classified in two classes:

      A) Patient related risk factors:

        1. Female gender is consistently the strongest risk factor for postoperative nausea and
           vomiting, female patient are three times more likely than men to suffer from
           postoperative nausea and vomiting.

        2. For adult patient, age is a statistically, though not clinically, relevant risk factor,
           with the incidence of postoperative nausea and vomiting decreasing as patients age. For
           pediatric patients, however, age increases the risk of post-operative vomiting , such
           that children older than 3 years have been shown to have an increased risk of
           post-operative vomiting compared with children younger than 3 years.

        3. Obesity is a strong risk factor for postoperative nausea and vomiting : patients with
           body mass index more than 30 have the double risk of postoperative nausea and vomiting.

        4. Non-smoking status roughly doubles the patient's risk of postoperative nausea and
           vomiting. The specific mechanism underlying smoking's protective effect is unknown, but
           one of the most commonly believed theories is that polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in
           cigarette smoke induce cytochrome P450 enzyme which increase the metabolism of
           emetogenic volatile anesthetics.

        5. History of gastrointestinal disease as gastritis, gastric ulcer or duodenal ulcer
           increases the risk for postoperative nausea and vomiting.

        6. History of motion sickness, Meniere's disease or previous postoperative nausea and
           vomiting indicates a general susceptibility to postoperative nausea and vomiting.

      B) Anesthesia related risk factors:

        1. The use of volatile anesthetics is associated with a two-fold increase in the risk of
           postoperative nausea and vomiting , with risk increasing in a dose dependent manner.

        2. Intraoperative and postoperative opioid use increases the risk of postoperative nausea
           and vomiting in a dose dependent manner by the mechanism of reducing muscle tone and
           peristaltic activity, thereby delaying gastric emptying, inducing distention, and
           triggering the vomiting reflex.

        3. The duration of anesthesia can help predict the patient's risk of postoperative nausea
           and vomiting, since the duration of anesthesia describes the patient's exposure to
           emetogenic stimuli like volatile anesthetics and intraoperative opioids.

      There are two lines of anti-emetic drugs used to treat postoperative nausea and vomiting :

      The first line is classified into three classes: serotonin antagonists (e.g. ondansetron),
      corticosteroids (e.g. dexamethasone), and dopamine antagonists (e.g. droperidol) have similar
      efficacy against postoperative nausea and vomiting , with a relative risk reduction of ~25%.
      Moreover, they act independently and when used in combination, have additive effects.

      Dexamethasone can be effective in preventing postoperative nausea and vomiting in adults and
      children. Compared with other operative medications, dexamethasone has equal or even better
      efficacy in reducing the incidence of Postoperative nausea and vomiting and has the
      advantages of low cost and longer effectiveness as well. The mechanism of the antiemetic
      action of dexamethasone is still not clearly known. Glucocorticoids receptors are found in
      nucleus of the solitary tract, the raphe nucleus and the area postrema and all are associated
      with regulating nausea and vomiting. Dexamethasone may affect postoperative nausea and
      vomiting by modulating neurotransmission or receptor density in these nuclei. Clinically,
      dexamethasone as a preventive drug against postoperative nausea and vomiting has not caused
      fatal outcome; therefore, it is generally considered to be an effective and safe anti-emetic.
      Nevertheless, its use in this regard may lead to adverse effects, principally postoperative
      hyperglycemia and infection.

      The second line is characterized by less favorable side effect profiles or limited evidence
      of efficacy: Metoclopramide is a widely used D2 antagonist. Contrary to popular belief, the
      10 mg dose has no effect on post-operative nausea and vomiting, but 25-50 mg has similar
      efficacy compared with other anti-emetics. Metoclopramide use has been associated with
      extrapyramidal and sedative side-effects. Dimenhydrinate is an antihistamine like
      promethazine and cyclizine. There are few randomized controlled trials investigating its use
      for postoperative nausea and vomiting , and the drug is associated with a significant rate of
      side-effects like sedation, dry mouth, visual disturbance, and urinary retention.

      Erythromycin A, the first macrolide, was introduced in the 1950s and after years of clinical
      experience it still remains a commonly relied upon antibiotic but the function of
      erythromycin as a prokinetic agent has also been investigated recently for a range of
      gastrointestinal motility disorders and more recently within the context of critically ill
      patients. Erythromycin A has a gastrointestinal motility stimulating effect; it has been
      known for over 20 years that they act as a motilin receptor agonist in the gut and
      gallbladder stimulating enteric nerves and smooth muscle and triggering a phase of the
      migrating myoelectric complex. The antral motor effects of erythromycin A in humans are
      mediated via different pathways. The induction of a premature activity is mediated through
      activation of an intrinsic cholinergic pathway, while the induction of enhanced antral
      contractile activity may be mediated via a pathway potentially involving activation of non
      muscular receptor. Different doses of erythromycin A may have different effects - as
      suggested in studies in patients with diabetic gastro-paresis.

      Forty mg erythromycin A elicited a premature phase 3 complex that started in the stomach and
      migrated to the small intestine, while doses of 200 and 350 mg erythromycin A elicited a
      burst of antral phase-3-like contractions that did not migrate to the small intestine, but
      were followed by a prolonged period of antral contractile activity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Direct questionnaire of the patients about their nausea and/or vomiting</measure>
    <time_frame>The first 24 hours after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Did you experience nausea during the first 24 hours after your surgery?
yes
no [if no, please skip to question 5]
How long did the nausea last? ....... hours.
How would you describe the nausea at its worst?
mild
moderate
severe
intolerable
How many times you felt nauseated? ......
Did you experience vomiting during the first 24 hours after your surgery?
yes
no [ if no, please skip the next part of the questionnaire]
How would you describe the vomiting at its worst?
mild
moderate
severe
intolerable
How many times you vomited during the first 24 hours after your surgery? .......
Estimate the amount of the vomiting?
small amount
moderate amount
large amount</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">160</enrollment>
  <condition>Post-operative Nausea and Vomiting</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients will receive oral placebo tablet, one hour before induction of anesthesia and 5 mg Intra-venous dexamethasone within 1-2 minutes after the umbilical cord is clamped.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Erythromycin A group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients will receive 250 mg oral Erythromycin A tablet, one hour before induction of anesthesia and 5 mg Intra-venous dexamethasone within 1-2 minutes after the umbilical cord is clamped.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oral Erythromycin A tablet</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral erythromycin A tablet will be given one hour before induction of anaesthesia.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Erythromycin A group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intravenous dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>5 mg of intravenous dexamethasone is given within one to two minutes after the umbilical cord is clamped.</description>
    <arm_group_label>placebo group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Erythromycin A group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria: 1- women classified according to American Society of anaesthesiologists
        grade I between the ages 18 to 38 years scheduled for elective Caesarean Section under
        spinal anesthesia who are normal healthy women, non smokers, no or minimal alcohol use.

        2- women classified as American Society of Anaesthesiologists grade Il between the ages 18
        to 38 years scheduled for elective Caesarean Section under spinal anesthesia who are women
        with mild systemic disease without functional limitations as current smokers, social
        alcohol drinker, pregnant, women with body mass index between 30 and 40, women with
        well-controlled diabetas, hypertension or mild lung diseases.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Women who has obstetric complications.

          2. Women with evidence of foetal compromise.

          3. Patients who have gastro-intestinal diseases.

          4. Patients who administrated anti-emetic medication in the previous 24 hours before
             operation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>38 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Fatma Askar, MD</last_name>
    <phone>00201005803969</phone>
    <email>s.askar@aun.edu.eg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Khalid Morsy, MD</last_name>
    <phone>00201005677075</phone>
    <email>khaledmorsy@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abdel-Aleem M, Osman A, Morsy K. Effect of coadministration of dexamethasone with intrathecal morphine on postoperative outcomes after cesarean delivery. Int J Gynaecol Obstet. 2012 Feb;116(2):158-61. doi: 10.1016/j.ijgo.2011.10.002. Epub 2011 Oct 26.</citation>
    <PMID>22036059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rea E, Husbands E. Erythromycin: prophylaxis against recurrent small bowel obstruction. BMJ Support Palliat Care. 2017 Sep;7(3):261-263. doi: 10.1136/bmjspcare-2017-001343. Epub 2017 Mar 29.</citation>
    <PMID>28356304</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 22, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 24, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Assiut University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>KAGergis</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>principal investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nausea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vomiting</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Postoperative Nausea and Vomiting</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Erythromycin stearate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Erythromycin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Erythromycin Estolate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Erythromycin Ethylsuccinate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

