<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03162354</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STUDY00005613</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03162354</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The CDR Implementation Trial</brief_title>
  <official_title>Implementation Trial of a Validated Clinical Decision Rule for Pediatric Abusive Head Trauma (NIH Grant Number P50HD089922)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To increase the accuracy of doctors' decisions to launch or forgo child abuse evaluations in
      their young, acutely head-injured patients, investigators have derived and validated a
      clinical decision rule (CDR) that detects abusive head trauma (AHT) with 96% sensitivity in
      pediatric intensive care unit (PICU) settings. This &quot;CDR Implementation Trial&quot; across eight
      PICU sites will assess the CDR's actual impact on AHT screening accuracy, identify factors
      associated with maximal physician acceptance and application of this novel AHT screening
      tool, and assess the sustainability of active CDR implementation strategies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Investigators' long-term goal is to increase the accuracy of doctors' decisions to launch or
      forgo child abuse evaluations in their young, acutely head-injured patients. To this end,
      PediBIRN investigators have derived and validated a 4-variable clinical decision rule (CDR)
      that detects abusive head trauma (AHT) with 96% sensitivity in PICU settings. Applied at PICU
      admission, the CDR categorizes young, acutely head-injured patients as high risk vs. low
      risk, and recommends thorough abuse evaluations for all high risk patients.

      The &quot;CDR Implementation Trial&quot; across eight PICUs will assess the CDR's actual impact on AHT
      screening accuracy. The stratified cluster randomized trial design will facilitate direct
      comparison of child abuse evaluations at four, randomly selected, control sites to four
      matched intervention sites, where investigators will deploy active, multifaceted,
      implementation strategies designed to promote CDR acceptability and application. These
      strategies will include physician training with onsite visits, monthly &quot;booster training
      emails,&quot; access to an &quot;AHT probability calculator,&quot; audit and site-specific feedback, and
      local &quot;information sharing sessions&quot; designed to address local barriers to CDR acceptance and
      application.

      PediBIRN investigators will conduct the CDR Implementation Trial with three Specific Aims.
      Aim 1 is to assess the CDR's actual impact on AHT screening accuracy. Investigators
      hypothesize that deployment of CDR implementation strategies at the four intervention sites
      will be associated with higher percentages of high risk patients evaluated thoroughly for
      abuse, and lower percentages of low risk patients evaluated (even partially) for abuse. Aim 2
      is to identify factors that impact CDR application in PICU settings. Investigators
      hypothesize that PICUs with higher patient volumes, providers with child abuse expertise, and
      providers with more intense exposure to CDR implementation strategies will be predictive of
      higher percentages of high risk patients thoroughly evaluated for abuse, whereas patients of
      minority race or ethnicity will be predictive of higher percentages of low risk patients
      evaluated for abuse. Investigators' third Exploratory Aim is to measure the sustained impacts
      of CDR implementation strategies. Investigators hypothesize that CDR utilization at
      intervention sites will be sustained twelve months after CDR implementation strategies have
      been discontinued.

      Based on strong Preliminary Studies, investigators predict that CDR adoption as an AHT
      screening tool will increase AHT detection; reduce overall abuse evaluations and their
      associated risks; reduce unwarranted variation in current AHT screening practices; minimize
      the adverse impacts of doctors' inherent biases, uncertainty, and practice disparities;
      reduce AHT-associated acute health care costs in PICU settings; and save the lives of
      children who will be reinjured and killed if their AHT is missed or unrecognized.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The stratified cluster randomized trial design will facilitate direct comparison of child abuse evaluations at four, randomly selected, control sites to four matched intervention sites, where investigators will deploy active, multifaceted, implementation strategies designed to promote CDR acceptability and application.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The study statistician will remain blinded to PICU site group membership (control vs. intervention sites).</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>High risk patients evaluated for abuse</measure>
    <time_frame>To be measured 24 months after the start of the clinical trial</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of high risk patients evaluated thoroughly for abuse (with skeletal survey and retinal exam).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Low risk patients evaluated for abuse</measure>
    <time_frame>To be measured 24 months after the start of the clinical trial</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of low risk patients evaluated (at least partially) for abuse (with skeletal survey and/or retinal exam).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall diagnostic yield</measure>
    <time_frame>To be measured 24 months after the start of the clinical trial</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of patients with completed skeletal surveys and/or retinal exams that reveal corroborating findings of abuse.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimated cases of missed AHT</measure>
    <time_frame>To be measured 24 months after the start of the clinical trial</time_frame>
    <description>The mean, evidence-based estimate of abuse probability among all patients lacking skeletal surveys and/or retinal exams.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Unnecessary abuse evaluations</measure>
    <time_frame>To be measured 24 months after the start of the clinical trial</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of non-AHT patients evaluated (even partially) for abuse (with skeletal survey and/or retinal exam).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Pediatric Abusive Head Trauma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Sites</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>At the four intervention sites, investigators will deploy active, multifaceted, implementation strategies designed to promote CDR acceptability and application as an AHT screening tool. These strategies will include physician training with onsite visits, monthly &quot;booster training emails,&quot; access to an &quot;AHT probability calculator,&quot; audit and site-specific feedback, and local &quot;information sharing sessions&quot; designed to address local barriers to CDR acceptance and application.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Sites</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>At the four matched control sites, physicians will engage in &quot;AHT screening as usual.&quot;</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Application of a validated Clinical Decision Rule (CDR) as an AHT screening tool</intervention_name>
    <description>The Clinical Decision Rule (CDR) for AHT reads as follows:
Every acutely head-injured infant or young child hospitalized for intensive care presenting with any one or more of these four variables should be considered &quot;high risk&quot; and thoroughly evaluated for abuse: (1) any clinically significant respiratory compromise at the scene of injury, during transport, in the Emergency Department, or prior to admission; (2) Any bruising involving the child's ear(s), neck, or torso; (3) Any subdural hemorrhage(s) or fluid collection(s) that are bilateral OR involve the interhemispheric space; (4) Any skull fracture(s) other than an isolated, nondiastatic, linear, parietal, skull fracture.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Sites</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children under 3 years of age admitted to a PICU for management of symptomatic, acute,
             closed, traumatic, cranial, or intracranial injuries confirmed by computed tomography
             (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients admitted to a PICU with acute head injuries resulting from a collision
             involving a motor vehicle.

          -  Patients admitted to a PICU with acute head injuries and clear evidence on
             neuroimaging of pre-existing brain malformation, disease, infection, or
             hypoxia-ischemia.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>3 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kent P. Hymel, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Connecticut Children's Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hartford</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06106</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Wesley Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Wichita</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>67214</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Mercy Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kansas City</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>64108</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Nebraska Medical Cneter and Children's Hospital of Omaha</name>
      <address>
        <city>Omaha</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Children's Hospital, Baylor College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas health Sciences Center at San Antonio</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Primary Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84113</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Richmond, Virginia Commonwealth University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23298</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.pedibirn.com</url>
    <description>Website for &quot;The CDR Implementation Trial&quot;</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hymel KP, Willson DF, Boos SC, Pullin DA, Homa K, Lorenz DJ, Herman BE, Graf JM, Isaac R, Armijo-Garcia V, Narang SK; Pediatric Brain Injury Research Network (PediBIRN) Investigators. Derivation of a clinical prediction rule for pediatric abusive head trauma. Pediatr Crit Care Med. 2013 Feb;14(2):210-20. doi: 10.1097/PCC.0b013e3182712b09.</citation>
    <PMID>23314183</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hymel KP, Armijo-Garcia V, Foster R, Frazier TN, Stoiko M, Christie LM, Harper NS, Weeks K, Carroll CL, Hyden P, Sirotnak A, Truemper E, Ornstein AE, Wang M; Pediatric Brain Injury Research Network (PediBIRN) Investigators. Validation of a clinical prediction rule for pediatric abusive head trauma. Pediatrics. 2014 Dec;134(6):e1537-44. doi: 10.1542/peds.2014-1329. Epub 2014 Nov 17.</citation>
    <PMID>25404722</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hymel KP, Herman BE, Narang SK, Graf JM, Frazier TN, Stoiko M, Christie LM, Harper NS, Carroll CL, Boos SC, Dias M, Pullin DA, Wang M; Pediatric Brain Injury Research Network (PediBIRN) Investigators; Pediatric Brain Injury Research Network PediBIRN Investigators. Potential Impact of a Validated Screening Tool for Pediatric Abusive Head Trauma. J Pediatr. 2015 Dec;167(6):1375-81.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2015.09.018. Epub 2015 Oct 23.</citation>
    <PMID>26477871</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 12, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 19, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 3, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kent Hymel</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Child Abuse Pediatrician, Professor of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Craniocerebral Trauma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

