<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03160911</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016.711-T</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03160911</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Use of Over-the-scope-clip for Prevention of Rebleeding in High Risk Peptic Ulcers</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Use of Over-the-scope-clip (OTSC) Versus Standard Therapy for the Prevention of Rebleeding in High Risk Peptic Ulcers: a Randomised Controlled Trial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>Yes</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Non-variceal acute gastrointestinal bleeding is a common and potentially life-threatening
      problem. The conventional treatment of this condition is for esophagogastroduodenoscopy (OGD)
      for haemostasis. Treatment methods include heater probe, clipping and injection of
      adrenaline. Recently, a new device called the Over-the-scope clip (OTSC) has been device to
      treat perforations and bleeding in the gastrointestinal tract. Therefore, the aim of the
      study is to compare between the treatment outcomes between OTSC and conventional endoscopic
      haemostatic methods in ulcers that are of high risk for rebleeding.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Acute upper gastrointestinal bleeding is a common and potentially life-threatening condition.
      Non-variceal bleeding accounts for more than 80-90% of the cause with gastroduodenal peptic
      ulcer being the major cause. Endoscopic haemostasis has significantly improved the outcome of
      these patients. Recurrent bleeding remains one of the most important predictors of mortality.
      Previous studies have identified ulcers that are high risk for rebleeding.

      Conventionally, endoscopic haemostasis is achieved by injection therapy, thermocoagulation or
      mechanical therapy such as haemostatic clips. However, there are limitations to
      thermo-coagulation and conventional haemostatic clips. Over the past few years, a novel
      endoscopic clipping device, the Over-The-Scope Clip (OTSC; Oversco Endoscopy AG, Tübingen,
      Germany) has become available. The device provides a robust and strong tissue apposition. The
      system was developed to close perforations and treat bleeding in the gastrointestinal tract.
      In chronic ulcers, an anchor device can be used to pull the ulcer base toward the aspiration
      cap to facilitate accurate clip application. With a larger jaw width and greater strength,
      the OTSC is expected to have superior haemostatic properties when compared to hemo-clips.
      Case series have been published on the clinical experience of OTSC on gastrointestinal
      bleeding with promising results.

      Therefore, in this randomised controlled trial, we aim to compare the efficacy of the OTSC to
      standard endoscopic therapy in primary treatment of patients with peptic ulcer bleeding that
      are of high-risk for rebleeding. The hypothesis is that the use OTSC can significantly
      decrease the rebleeding rate in this group of patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">March 16, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>There are two separate interventional arms. In case of treatment failure, the two groups are allowed to crossover to the other group.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The participant, the investigator and the outcome assessor would be blinded.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of cases that develop clinical rebleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 30 days of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical rebleeding is defined as fresh hematemesis, fresh melena or hematochezia and signs of hypovolemic shock (systolic blood pressure of &lt;90mmHg and pulse rate &gt;110 per minute) and/or a drop in hemoglobin of &gt; 2 g/dl per 24 hours despite adequate transfusion. Rebleeding would be confirmed by an immediate endoscopy showing fresh blood in stomach or active bleeding from a previously seen ulcer. A clinical rebleeding will be independently reviewed by an adjudication panel.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of cases that died</measure>
    <time_frame>within 30 days of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Death from all causes within 30 days of therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of units of blood transfusion required in each patient</measure>
    <time_frame>within 30 days of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Number of units of blood transfusion required in each patient within 30 days of therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>up to one year</time_frame>
    <description>Hospital stay for the episode of bleeding</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of cases with failure of achieving primary haemostasis</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 30 days of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>The number of cases with failure of achieving primary haemostasis. Failure of primary haemostasis is defined by the inability to achieve haemostasis during the index endoscopy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of cases requiring further interventions such as repeat endoscopy, surgery or transarterial embolization</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 30 days of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>The number of cases requiring further interventions such as repeat endoscopy, surgery or transarterial embolization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital costs</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to one year</time_frame>
    <description>The total direct costs required for the hospital admission for the episode of bleeding measured in Hong Kong dollars</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">152</enrollment>
  <condition>Ulcer Bleeding</condition>
  <condition>Upper Gastrointestinal Tract Bleeding</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Over-the-scope clip</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patient would receive an esophagogastroduodenoscope to identify the bleeding source. The endoscopist can decided whether to pre inject the ulcer with adrenaline. Then the OTSC is used for haemostasis.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional endoscopic haemostasis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patient would receive an esophagogastroduodenoscope to identify the bleeding source. Haemostasis will be performed in the conventional way, either using heater probe, endoscopic clips and/or injection of adrenaline</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Over-the-scope clip (OTSC)</intervention_name>
    <description>The device provides a robust and strong tissue apposition. The system was developed to close perforations and treat bleeding in the gastrointestinal tract. In chronic ulcers, an anchor device can be used to pull the ulcer base toward the aspiration cap to facilitate accurate clip application. Endoscopic haemostasis would be achieved with the use of this device and/or injection of adrenaline</description>
    <arm_group_label>Over-the-scope clip</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional Endoscopic Haemostasis</intervention_name>
    <description>This includes the use of heater probe, endoscopic clipping and injection of adrenaline for endoscopic haemostasis</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional endoscopic haemostasis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Actively bleeding peptic ulcers (Forrest Ia, Ib), ulcers with non-bleeding visible
             vessel or Forrest IIa ulcer (defined as protuberant discoloration, or ulcers with an
             initial clot and upon irrigation shows a vessel) AND

          2. Ulcer size ≥ 1.5 cm as determined by an opened biopsy forceps;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients aged below 18

          2. Peptic ulcer with concomitant perforation

          3. Tumor bleeding

          4. Variceal bleeding

          5. Patients who are pregnant or lactating

          6. Moribund patients or patients with terminal malignancy or end-stage non-malignant
             conditions, in whom life expectancy is less than 30 days
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shannon M Chan, MBCHB, FRCS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shannon M Chan, MBCHB, FRCS</last_name>
    <phone>85235052627</phone>
    <email>shannonchan@surgery.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>James YW Lau, FRCS, MD</last_name>
    <phone>85235051411</phone>
    <email>laujyw@surgery.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prince of Wales Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <zip>00000</zip>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shannon M Chan, FRCS</last_name>
      <phone>852-35052627</phone>
      <email>shannonchan@surgery.cuhk.edu.hk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 14, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 19, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chinese University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>CHAN SHANNON MELISSA</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Resident Specialist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Over-the-scope clip</keyword>
  <keyword>endoscopic haemostasis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peptic Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hemostatics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Racepinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephryl borate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The IPD will only be used for the purposes of this study and not be disclosed to researchers of outside of this study.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

