<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03160209</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LCCC 1608</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03160209</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>HIV and Other Risk Factors for Esophageal Squamous Cell Carcinoma in Malawi</brief_title>
  <official_title>LCCC 1608 - HIV and Other Risk Factors for Esophageal Squamous Cell Carcinoma in Malawi</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UNC Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this single-center, case-control, non-interventional study is to
      determine risk factors which contribute to the development of esophageal squamous cell
      carcinoma (ESCC) at Kamuzu Central Hospital (KCH) and St. Gabriel Hospital (SGH) in Malawi.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE FOR RESEARCH

      The Rift Valley of Africa is a 'hot spot' for ESCC, yet little is known about the etiology of
      this disease in Sub-Saharan Africa. In Malawi, ESCC is the third commonest cancer nationwide
      behind Kaposi sarcoma and cervical carcinoma. Among cancers that are not classically
      HIV-related, ESCC has the highest incidence in Malawi. The ESCC burden recorded in the
      national cancer registry is also likely an underestimate, as many cases may go undiagnosed
      and unregistered. Additionally, few data are available on the epidemiology of ESCC in Malawi,
      and underlying reasons for high frequency of the disease are largely unknown. This knowledge
      gap is a major barrier to public health prevention efforts. Given that survival after ESCC
      diagnosis is dismal in Malawi (12% at 1 year), developing evidence-based prevention efforts
      is paramount.

      The proposed study will make a significant contribution to existing literature from Malawi
      and Sub-Saharan Africa in several important respects. First, previous epidemiologic studies
      of ESCC in Malawi have been limited by challenges with appropriate control selection, which
      may have limited the validity of their findings. Secondly, our study will include prospective
      clinical follow-up of confirmed ESCC cases as they receive treatment under local conditions
      to provide accurate survival estimates. Thirdly, biospecimens from consenting patients will
      permit etiology and pathogenesis studies to understand mechanisms of ESCC development, which
      can be correlated with high-quality clinical and epidemiologic data. Finally, we plan to
      coordinate with other ESCC researchers in eastern and southern Africa to harmonize data
      collection, and help create a regional consortium in which Malawi can be a founding member
      and active participant.

      Primary Objective: Identify demographic and environmental risk factors for ESCC through a
      case-control study implemented at KCH and SGH. Hypothesis: Modifiable risk factors contribute
      significantly to ESCC. These include polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbon (PAH) exposure from
      various sources, excessively hot beverages, dietary factors such as maize fumonisin and low
      selenium, and HIV infection.

      Secondary Objective: Identify common genetic and epigenetic alterations in germline and
      somatic DNA associated with ESCC development. Hypothesis: Recurring genetic and epigenetic
      alterations can facilitate risk stratification, development of early detection biomarkers,
      and identification of novel treatment strategies.

      Procedures

      After informed consent and study enrollment, subjects will be interviewed using a structured
      questionnaire and provide biological samples including saliva, blood, urine, and toenail
      clippings. Esophageal biopsies will be taken for diagnostic confirmation and to support
      molecular studies. If patients suspected to have ESCC are enrolled but then pathologically
      confirmed to have an alternate diagnosis, they will be withdrawn. HIV testing will be offered
      to all participants, and CD4, HIV RNA, and ART status documented for HIV-infected
      participants. Exposures will be measured using the questionnaire and laboratory analyses of
      saliva, blood, urine, and toenail samples. We will collect information on: demographic
      characteristics; HIV status; tobacco and drug use; alcohol consumption; medical history;
      family history of cancer; indoor air pollution; occupational history; diet, cooking, and food
      preservation; beverage history including temperature; farming; signs and symptoms of upper
      gastrointestinal disease; oral health; anthropometric indices; and reproductive history. To
      examine correlates with patient outcomes, telephone follow-up to assess vital status will be
      done every 3 months until 2 years from enrollment. Biological samples will be stored in
      freezers and transferred to the US only for assays that are currently unavailable in Malawi.
      Laboratory testing will include serum selenium level, blood and urine testing for PAH
      exposure, tumor immunohistochemistry assays, salivary DNA isolation for genetic studies, and
      molecular profiling of ESCC tumors.

      Analysis

      Sample size will include 300 ESCC cases and 300 controls; 66-68 case control pairs will be
      enrolled per year, over 3 years, assuming a response rate of 75% in the endoscopy clinic.
      With 300 case-control pairs, estimated statistical power for an exposure with control
      population prevalence of 10% and OR 2.0 is 81%, using alpha level 0.05, with higher power for
      higher control exposure rates and odds ratios. Expected prevalence for key exposures (tobacco
      and alcohol, hot tea, PAH exposure, selenium deficiency, HIV) is 10-50% in the control
      population. To assess epidemiologic risk factors for ESCC, we will use logistic regression to
      estimate odds ratios and 95% confidence intervals for each exposure, while controlling for
      possible confounders. Survival estimates will be generated using Kaplan-Meyer curves to
      estimate overall survival at 6, 12 and 24 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 26, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk factors for ESCC - HIV Infection</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To identify risk factors for ESCC through a case-control study implemented at a national teaching hospital, specifically focused on the following exposures: HIV infection, PAH exposure, Dietary factors including fumonisin and selenium, Scalding hot beverages and foods, Tobacco and alcohol consumption</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival estimates after ESCC diagnosis in Malawi.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To assess survival after ESCC diagnosis in Malawi.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk factors for ESCC - HIV Infection</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To identify risk factors for ESCC through a case-control study implemented at a national teaching hospital, specifically focused on the following exposures: HIV infection</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk factors for ESCC - PAH exposure</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To identify risk factors for ESCC through a case-control study implemented at a national teaching hospital, specifically focused on the following exposures: PAH exposure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk factors for ESCC - Dietary factors including fumonisin and selenium</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To identify risk factors for ESCC through a case-control study implemented at a national teaching hospital, specifically focused on the following exposures: Dietary factors including fumonisin and selenium</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk factors for ESCC - Scalding hot beverages and foods,</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To identify risk factors for ESCC through a case-control study implemented at a national teaching hospital, specifically focused on the following exposures: Scalding hot beverages and foods</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk factors for ESCC - Tobacco and alcohol consumption</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To identify risk factors for ESCC through a case-control study implemented at a national teaching hospital, specifically focused on the following exposures: Tobacco and alcohol consumption</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The common somatic genetic and epigenetic alterations in ESCC tumors from Malawi.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To identify and characterize common somatic genetic and epigenetic alterations in ESCC tumors from Malawi.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The germline genetic and epigenetic alterations associated with susceptibility to ESCC.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To identify and characterize germline genetic and epigenetic alterations associated with susceptibility to ESCC.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">600</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>300 esophageal cases</arm_group_label>
    <description>diagnosed with histologically confirmed ESCC</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>300 patient controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>without a history of esophageal cancer or esophageal squamous dysplasia, a history of other cancer, or upper gastrointestinal diseases</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        300 cases diagnosed with histologically confirmed ESCC and 300 patient controls without a
        history of esophageal cancer or esophageal squamous dysplasia, a history of other cancer,
        or upper gastrointestinal diseases, 18 years, and older, male/female in Malawi.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Cases Inclusion Criteria

               -  All patients &gt; 18 years of age diagnosed with histologically confirmed ESCC are
                  eligible to be a case regardless of sex or place of residence.

               -  Diagnosis of ESCC (histologically confirmed)

               -  Subject able to understand and provide written consent in English or Chichewa

               -  Able to understand and comply with study procedures for the entire length of the
                  study

        Controls Inclusion Criteria

          -  All patients &gt; 18 years of age without a history of esophageal cancer or esophageal
             squamous dysplasia, a history of other cancer, or upper gastrointestinal diseases are
             eligible to be controls, regardless of age, sex, or place of residence

          -  Subject able to understand and provide written consent in English or Chichewa

          -  Able to understand and comply with study procedures for the entire length of the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cases Exclusion Criteria

               -  Healthcare provider determines it is unsafe to perform a biopsy

               -  Mental impairment which precludes provision of informed consent

               -  Patients who are unable to provide their past medical history

        Controls Exclusion Criteria

          -  All patients &gt; 18 years of age with a history of esophageal cancer or esophageal
             squamous dysplasia, a history of other cancer, or upper gastrointestinal diseases are
             ineligible to be controls

          -  Patients with significant difficulty swallowing

          -  Mental impairment which precludes provision of informed consent

          -  Patients who are unable to provide their past medical history
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Satish Gopal, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UNC-CH</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Bongani Kaimila, MBBS, MSc</last_name>
    <phone>+265 1 750 610</phone>
    <email>bkaimila@unclilongwe.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNC Project, Lighthouse Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lilongwe</city>
        <country>Malawi</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sam Phiri, PhD</last_name>
      <email>samphiri@lighthouse.org.mw</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UNC Project</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lilongwe</city>
        <country>Malawi</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Satish Gopal, MD</last_name>
      <phone>265-1-755-056</phone>
      <email>gopal@med.unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Malawi</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu C, Hu Z, He Z, Jia W, Wang F, Zhou Y, Liu Z, Zhan Q, Liu Y, Yu D, Zhai K, Chang J, Qiao Y, Jin G, Liu Z, Shen Y, Guo C, Fu J, Miao X, Tan W, Shen H, Ke Y, Zeng Y, Wu T, Lin D. Genome-wide association study identifies three new susceptibility loci for esophageal squamous-cell carcinoma in Chinese populations. Nat Genet. 2011 Jun 5;43(7):679-84. doi: 10.1038/ng.849.</citation>
    <PMID>21642993</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parkin DM, Bray F, Ferlay J, Pisani P. Global cancer statistics, 2002. CA Cancer J Clin. 2005 Mar-Apr;55(2):74-108.</citation>
    <PMID>15761078</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Metzger R, Schneider PM, Warnecke-Eberz U, Brabender J, Hölscher AH. Molecular biology of esophageal cancer. Onkologie. 2004 Apr;27(2):200-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15138356</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dlamini Z, Bhoola K. Esophageal cancer in African blacks of Kwazulu Natal, South Africa: an epidemiological brief. Ethn Dis. 2005 Autumn;15(4):786-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16259509</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mlombe Y, Dzamalala C, Chisi J, Othieno-Abinya N. Oesophageal cancer and Kaposi's sarcoma in Malawi: a comparative analysis. Malawi Med J. 2009 Jun;21(2):66-8.</citation>
    <PMID>20345007</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Msyamboza KP, Dzamalala C, Mdokwe C, Kamiza S, Lemerani M, Dzowela T, Kathyola D. Burden of cancer in Malawi; common types, incidence and trends: national population-based cancer registry. BMC Res Notes. 2012 Mar 16;5:149. doi: 10.1186/1756-0500-5-149.</citation>
    <PMID>22424105</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Munishi MO, Hanisch R, Mapunda O, Ndyetabura T, Ndaro A, Schüz J, Kibiki G, McCormack V. Africa's oesophageal cancer corridor: Do hot beverages contribute? Cancer Causes Control. 2015 Oct;26(10):1477-86. doi: 10.1007/s10552-015-0646-9. Epub 2015 Aug 6.</citation>
    <PMID>26245249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kayamba V, Bateman AC, Asombang AW, Shibemba A, Zyambo K, Banda T, Soko R, Kelly P. HIV infection and domestic smoke exposure, but not human papillomavirus, are risk factors for esophageal squamous cell carcinoma in Zambia: a case-control study. Cancer Med. 2015 Apr;4(4):588-95. doi: 10.1002/cam4.434. Epub 2015 Jan 30.</citation>
    <PMID>25641622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen J, Zhang N, Wakai T, Wei L, He Y, Kumagai N, Kitsu K, Wang S, Akazawa K. Effect of the interaction between the amount and duration of alcohol consumption and tobacco smoking on the risk of esophageal cancer: A case-control study. Exp Ther Med. 2010 Nov;1(6):991-997. Epub 2010 Sep 29.</citation>
    <PMID>22993631</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang JB, Fan JH, Liang H, Li J, Xiao HJ, Wei WQ, Dawsey SM, Qiao YL, Boffetta P. Attributable causes of esophageal cancer incidence and mortality in China. PLoS One. 2012;7(8):e42281. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0042281. Epub 2012 Aug 2.</citation>
    <PMID>22876312</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kumagai N, Wakai T, Akazawa K, Ling Y, Wang S, Shan B, Okuhara Y, Hatakeyama Y, Kataoka H. Heavy alcohol intake is a risk factor for esophageal squamous cell carcinoma among middle-aged men: A case-control and simulation study. Mol Clin Oncol. 2013 Sep;1(5):811-816. Epub 2013 Jul 4.</citation>
    <PMID>24649251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jessri M, Rashidkhani B, Hajizadeh B, Jessri M, Gotay C. Macronutrients, vitamins and minerals intake and risk of esophageal squamous cell carcinoma: a case-control study in Iran. Nutr J. 2011 Dec 20;10:137. doi: 10.1186/1475-2891-10-137.</citation>
    <PMID>22185224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen Y, Tong Y, Yang C, Gan Y, Sun H, Bi H, Cao S, Yin X, Lu Z. Consumption of hot beverages and foods and the risk of esophageal cancer: a meta-analysis of observational studies. BMC Cancer. 2015 Jun 2;15:449. doi: 10.1186/s12885-015-1185-1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26031666</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sun G, Wang S, Hu X, Su J, Huang T, Yu J, Tang L, Gao W, Wang JS. Fumonisin B1 contamination of home-grown corn in high-risk areas for esophageal and liver cancer in China. Food Addit Contam. 2007 Feb;24(2):181-5.</citation>
    <PMID>17364919</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 4, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 19, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>risk factors</keyword>
  <keyword>case-control study</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

