<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03163264</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IIR 15-378</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>01607</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03163264</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Peer Asssisted Lifestyle Intervention</brief_title>
  <acronym>PAL</acronym>
  <official_title>Testing the Efficacy of a Technology-assisted Intervention to Improve Weight Management of Obese Patients Within Patient Aligned Care Teams at the VA</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The PAL intervention uses a new software tool delivered on tablets to facilitate 5As-based
      weight management counseling with a health coach and the VA PACT healthcare team to promote
      goal-setting, behavior change, and weight loss in the primary care (PC) setting. The PAL
      intervention also includes 10-12 health-coaching calls to the patient over 12 months.

      As part of a cluster-randomized controlled study, the investigators will randomize 17 PACT
      teams at the Brooklyn VA to receive either the PAL Intervention or an Enhanced Usual Care
      control. The primary aim of the study is to explore differences in feasibility,
      acceptability, and intermediate, behavioral, and weight loss outcomes at 6 and 12 months of
      520 patients recruited from the randomized PACTs.

      Objective:

      1) Explore the feasibility and impact of this intervention on intermediate, behavioral, and
      weight loss outcomes at 6 and 12 months post-intervention when compared to enhanced usual
      care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Veterans shoulder a disproportionate burden of obesity and its co-morbidities, including
      diabetes, hypertension, and hyperlipidemia. Modest weight loss in obese patients through diet
      and exercise improves health and prevents chronic disease, but primary care providers (PCPs)
      often fail to adequately counsel patients about their weight due to lack of time and
      training. Thus, tools and brief interventions are needed to support providers' behavior
      change counseling. The VA currently offers the MOVE! program to treat overweight and obese
      patients, but only 9% of eligible patients attend. At the same time, Veterans on average see
      their PCPs 3.6 times per year, which supports the importance of developing primary care
      (PC)-based interventions. The United States Preventive Services Task force (USPSTF)
      recommends the use of the 5As framework (Assess, Advise, Agree, Assist, Arrange) for
      counseling patients about weight.

      Interactive behavior change technologies utilizing expert system software programs are an
      innovative way to facilitate 5As counseling to promote behavior change in primary care. These
      programs perform computerized risk, lifestyle, and theory- based, behavioral assessment to
      provide computer-generated, tailored advice to patients. They also can provide information to
      healthcare teams. The MOVE!11 software is an expert system program for VA patients referred
      to MOVE!, but is not currently used in primary care by Patient-Aligned Care Teams (PACT).

      Collaborative goal setting can be used to achieve behavior change in this intervention. This
      construct, a critical component of several behavior change theories and models and
      corresponding to &quot;agree&quot; in the 5As model, has been widely recommended for health promotion
      in primary care. The investigators' formative work (MIRB #01333) using key informant
      interviews with PACT teamlets and MOVE! staff and focus groups with Veterans demonstrated
      that goal setting is feasible and acceptable to patients and PACT teamlets and provided
      insight on barriers to goal setting, and ways to facilitate goal-setting conversations.

      During the development phase of this project, the investigators developed a primary
      care-based intervention called MOVE! Toward Your Goals (MTG) to facilitate weight management
      within primary care and increase adoption of intensive VA programs such as MOVE!. The PAL
      intervention uses the MTG software tool (that the investigators developed) delivered on
      tablets to facilitate 5As-based weight management counseling with a health coach and
      healthcare team to promote goal-setting, behavior change, and weight loss in the primary care
      setting. The Veteran also receives follow up with 10-12 health coaching calls over 1 year.

      As part of a clustered randomized control trial, the investigators will randomize 17 PACT
      teams to either Enhanced Usual Care or the PAL Intervention, recruiting 520 subjects.

      STUDY OBJECTIVES

        -  Test the impact of the PAL intervention on weight change and behavioral/clinical
           outcomes

        -  Identify predictors of weight loss in Veterans participating in the intervention group
           related to goal setting processes and intervention components

        -  Determine the impact of the PAL intervention on PACT obesity-related counseling
           practices and attitudes
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 8, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Weight Loss</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Mann-Whitney tests for continuous outcomes (e.g., weight loss)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in achievement of 5% weight loss</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fisher's exact tests for categorical outcomes will be used to compare the two intervention arms at 12 months</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in HB A1C</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 month</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting blood tests will be used to determine if patients experience changes in HB A1C level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in waist circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Will be used to determine whether patients had changes in waist circumference.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Physical Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measure duration and intensity using the Paffenbarger questionnaire items and accelerometers. The ActiGraph Link (GT9X) accelerometer, worn on the wrist, will be used to objectively measure PA for 7 days at Baseline, and at 6 and 12 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">520</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Overweight</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PAL Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Body mass index of =30kg/m2 OR Body mass index of =25 kg/m2 with an obesity associated co-morbidity
Receiving Peer Assisted Lifestyle intervention (PAL tool, health coaching at baseline, follow-up health coaching calls, potential support of goals from primary care provider)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Usual Care (EUC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Body mass index of =30kg/m2 OR Body mass index of =25 kg/m2 with an obesity associated co-morbidity</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peer Assisted Lifestyle</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will use PAL online tool accessing weight management and lifestyle behaviors, and will meet with a health coach regularly to establish SMART goals.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PAL Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PAL arm</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enhanced Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be given information on &quot;healthy living messages&quot; that were created by the VA, and given more information on specific messages they are interested in from the health coaches, but will not receive official coaching. These messages are the current standard of care at the VA for obesity counseling.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Usual Care (EUC)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>EUC arm</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18-69 (this age range represents MOVE! eligibility)

          -  BMI of 30kg/m2 or a BMI of 25kg/m2 with obesity-associated condition

          -  Under the care of PCP with at least 1 prior visit with the provider in the past 24
             months

          -  Access to a telephone

          -  Able to travel to Brooklyn VA for in-person evaluations at baseline, 6, and 12 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-Veterans

          -  A documented current history of active psychosis, active bipolar disorder, or other
             cognitive issues via ICD-10 codes

          -  Undergoing insulin-therapy for diabetes

          -  Self-reported inability to read at a 5th grade level due to literacy level or vision
             problems

          -  Has attended more than 4 MOVE! sessions in the past year

          -  Has lost greater than 10% of body weight in last year

          -  Pregnancy

          -  PCP stating that Veteran should not participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>69 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Melanie R. Jay, MD MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Manhattan Campus of the VA NY Harbor Healthcare System, New York, NY</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Melanie R Jay, MD MS</last_name>
    <phone>(212) 686-7500</phone>
    <email>Melanie.Jay@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Shea E Cerveny</last_name>
    <phone>(212) 686-7500</phone>
    <email>Shea.Cerveny@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Manhattan Campus of the VA NY Harbor Healthcare System, New York, NY</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melanie R Jay, MD MS</last_name>
      <phone>212-686-7500</phone>
      <email>Melanie.Jay@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Melanie R. Jay, MD MS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 19, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 19, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>weight loss</keyword>
  <keyword>weight gain</keyword>
  <keyword>weight management</keyword>
  <keyword>primary care</keyword>
  <keyword>health coach</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

