<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03167983</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Demenz</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03167983</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Microbiome and Dementia</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Gut-Brain Axis in Dementia: Biomarker and Novel Intervention Strategies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of Graz</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Graz</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      From this study, it is hoped to learn if and how the gut microbiome composition, gut
      permeability and inflammation in patients with dementia are associated with each other.
      Dysbiosis may lead to an increased gut permeability, bacterial translocation and inflammation
      which may influence pathogenesis and progression of dementia.

      The novel aspect of the study will be to understand the association between gut microbiome
      composition, gut permeability and the presence of dementia. This will help to better
      understand the pathogenesis of dementia and lead to the development of novel therapeutic
      strategies. If this hypothesis holds true, the study will be the basis to develop new
      treatment options for dementia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Dementia is a disease that presents with deterioration in memory, thinking, behaviour and the
      ability to perform everyday activities. Worldwide 47.5 million people are affected and
      incidence of dementia is increasing. Dementia leads to disability and dependency among older
      people worldwide and thereby has a huge physical, psychological, social and economic impact
      on caregivers, families and society. Alzheimers disease (AD) is the most common form of
      dementia accounting for 60-70% of the cases; other forms include Lewy body dementia,
      frontotemporal dementia, vascular dementia and Parkinsons disease with dementia. In AD,
      pathologic protein aggregates of amyloid beta and hyperphosphorylated tangles of tau-protein
      which deposit as neurofibrillary tangles are typical features. This leads to
      neuroinflammation, mainly mediated by the innate immune system. The most important cells in
      this process are microglia cells, which represent the resident macrophages of the brain.
      Although microglia is able to remove extracellular amyloid beta, in later stages of the
      disease cells remain in a dystrophic state and cannot exert their beneficial functions.
      Microglia maturation and function is critically dependent on short-chain fatty acids produced
      by the gut microbiome and therefore highlights the microbiome as a potential diagnostic and
      therapeutic target in dementia.

      The role of the commensal microbial population of the human body - especially the intestinal
      microbiome - in various diseases is emerging due to the development of advanced analysis
      techniques. Recently the concept of the gut brain-axis has been established. Several pathways
      including the autonomic nervous system, the enteric nervous system, the neuroendocrine system
      and the immune system allow a communication between gut and brain but may also be involved in
      disease development.

      During ageing, the gut microbiome composition undergoes changes. A decrease in diversity, a
      loss of beneficial taxa and an increase of facultative pathogens has been described. Diet and
      the place of residence play an important role in the shaping of the microbiome. Aging is also
      associated with inflammation - often termed as &quot;inflammaging&quot; associated with an increase in
      gut permeability, mucosal inflammation and bacterial translocation.

      Since the main risk factor for developing dementia, especially AD, is aging, it is very
      likely that the gut-brain axis is critically involved in dementia development.

      Animal studies so far suggest that AD is associated with changes in the gut microbiome
      composition with a decrease in beneficial, anti-inflammatory genera. Furthermore, genetic
      alterations in amyloid genes can influence microbiome composition in mice, pointing towards a
      vicious cycle in AD development.

      In humans, so far no studies on the gut microbiome composition in patients with dementia have
      been published. However, there is evidence that the composition of the microbiome in
      subgingival plaques is altered in dementia and associated with cognitive function.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 7, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Alpha diversity</measure>
    <time_frame>single measurement at baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Chao1 index</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>gut permeability</measure>
    <time_frame>single measurement at baseline</time_frame>
    <description>zonulin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>bacterial translocation</measure>
    <time_frame>single measurement at baseline</time_frame>
    <description>serum biomarker of bacterial translocation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>inflammation</measure>
    <time_frame>single measurement at baseline</time_frame>
    <description>serum biomarker of inflammation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>dementia</arm_group_label>
    <description>patients with dementia</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control</arm_group_label>
    <description>healthy control</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Stool, serum, plasma
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with dementia and age matched healthy controls
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &gt;18y

          -  Dementia (Alzheimer type and mixed type)

          -  Informed consent signed by the patient or his legal representative

          -  Mini Mental State Examination ≤ 26

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Other forms of dementia

          -  Inflammatory bowel diseases

          -  Liver cirrhosis

          -  Antibiotic treatment within the last 14 days

          -  Any other condition or circumstance, which, in the opinion of the investigator, would
             affect the patient's ability to participate in the protocol

        Healthy controls

          -  Age &gt;18y

          -  Informed consent

          -  No known acute or chronic illness
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of Graz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Graz</city>
        <zip>8010</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Vanessa Stadlbauer-Köllner, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0043 316 385</phone>
      <phone_ext>82282</phone_ext>
      <email>vanessa.stadlbauer@medunigraz.at</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 15, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 24, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 30, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

