<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03161132</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GEICO-1601</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03161132</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Resistant Ovarian Cancer, Olaparib and Liposomal Doxorubicin</brief_title>
  <acronym>ROLANDO</acronym>
  <official_title>Multicentric Single Arm Phase II Clinical Trial, to Evaluate Safety and Efficacy of the Combination of Olaparib and PLD for Platinum Resistant Ovarian Primary Peritoneal Carcinoma, and Fallopian Tube Cancer Patients.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Grupo Español de Investigación en Cáncer de Ovario</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Grupo Español de Investigación en Cáncer de Ovario</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Impact of the combination of Olaparib and Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin on improvement of
      progression-free survival at 6 months in patients with platinum resistant advanced ovarian
      cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The combination of Poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase (PARP) inhibitors with PLD may provide a
      synergistic effect in patients with advanced ovarian cancer, especially those with Homologous
      recombination deficiency (HRD), because of the decreased ability to repair
      chemotherapy-induced DNA damage. Preclinical studies with PARP inhibitors have shown
      potentiation of the cytotoxic effects of chemotherapeutic agents and a recent phase I study
      has shown the tolerability of the combination and efficacy in recurrent ovarian cancer. In
      this study, encouraging efficacy results were seen in ovarian cancer patients and were not
      limited by Germline BRCA1/2 (gBRCA) Mutations status or sensitivity to platinum therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 13, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Multicentric</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of pacients with no progression of disease at 6 months after start of treatment with Olaparib plus PLD</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients with tumor size reduction. Response duration is measured from the time of initial response until documented tumor progression. The Objective Response Rate (ORR) is defined as the sum of partial responses plus complete responses according to RECIST 1.1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease Control Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients who have achieved complete response, partial response and stable disease of 8 or more months according to RECIST 1.1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response to treatment Rate according CA-125 levels</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients who have achieved a response according to CA-125: and it has occurred if there is at least a 50% reduction in CA-125 levels from a pretreatment sample.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time from the date of the first dose of study treatment to the date of objective disease progression or death (in the absence of progression) regardless of whether the subject withdraws from study treatment or receives another anti-cancer therapy prior to progression.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months</time_frame>
    <description>Time from inclusion until death of any cause.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health related quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in patient's quality of life during the study, using the self-reported European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life Questionnaire (QLQ) (EORTC QLQ-C30) and the EORTC ovarian cancer module (EORTC-OV-28). Both scores will be combined to report a final outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activity of tumor based on the growth modulation index (GMI)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months</time_frame>
    <description>The GMI is the ratio of time to progression with the nth line (TTP(n)) of therapy to the TTP(n)(-1) with the n-1th line. GMI &gt;1.33 is considered as a sign of activity in phase II trials.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events as assessed by CTCAE v4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency, nature and number of patients developing adverse events throughout follow up</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>DNA damage</measure>
    <time_frame>20 months</time_frame>
    <description>BRCA pathway and defects in homologous recombination repair (HRR) Phosphorylation of γH2AX as a marker of DNA damage.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Advanced Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Olaparib 300mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Olaparib bid orally at 300 mg (tablet formulation) continuously, combined with chemotherapy with Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin (up to 6 cycles), then, as monotherapy at the same dose and frequency (300mg bid orally) until progression of disease or unaccepted toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin (PLD)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>PLD 40mg/m2 every 28 days intravenous for up to 6 cycles. This treatment will be combined with Olaparib (as described earlier).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Olaparib</intervention_name>
    <description>Combination of continous olaparib 300mg for oral administration plus Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin (PLD), followed by maintenance treatment further described.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Olaparib 300mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lynparza</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin</intervention_name>
    <description>PLD 40mg/m2 every 28 days intravenous</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pegylated Liposomal Doxorubicin (PLD)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PLD</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Provision of informed consent prior to any study specific procedures. Procedures
             conducted as part of the subject's routine clinical management (e.g., blood count,
             imaging study) and those obtained prior to signing of informed consent may be utilized
             for screening or for baseline purposes provided these procedures are conducted as
             specified in the protocol.

          -  Patients with histological or cytological confirmed high grade serous or endometrioid
             epithelial ovarian cancer, primary peritoneal carcinoma, fallopian tube cancer and
             resistant platinum relapse with no prior treatment with PLD for their resistant
             relapse. Previous treatment with PLD is allowed as long as it was part of one platinum
             based regimen and the treatment was finalized at least six months previously to
             inclusion in this trial.

          -  Patients must have platinum-resistant disease, defined as progression within &lt;6 months
             from completion of at least 4 cycles of platinum and up to 3 prior chemotherapy
             regimens. Patients should have documented treatment-free interval of ≥6 months
             following 1st chemotherapy regimen received. Patients with a deleterious mutation in
             BRCA are eligible in any case with a resistant relapse including primary resistant
             relapse.

          -  Have measurable disease as defined by RECIST v1.1 Criteria. At least one lesion, not
             previously irradiated, that can be accurately measured at baseline as ≥ 10 mm in the
             longest diameter (except lymph nodes which must have short axis ≥ 15 mm) with computed
             tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and which is suitable for accurate
             repeated measurements.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status ≤2.

          -  Female patients with &gt; 18 years of age.

          -  Patients must have normal organ and bone marrow function measured within 28 days prior
             to administration of study treatment as defined below: Haemoglobin ≥ 10.0 g/dL;
             Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 109/L; No features suggestive of
             Myelodysplastic Syndrome/Acute Myeloid Leukemia on peripheral blood smear; White blood
             cells (WBC) &gt; 3x109/L; Platelet count ≥ 100 x 109/L; Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x
             institutional upper limit of normal (ULN); aspartate aminotransferase
             (AST/SGOT)/Alaninotransferase (ALT/SGPT) ≤ 2.5 x institutional upper limit of normal
             unless liver metastases are present in which case it must be ≤ 5x ULN.

          -  Patients must have creatinine clearance estimated using the Cockcroft-Gault equation
             of ≥51 mL/min. PLD is metabolised by the liver and excreted in the bile. Population
             pharmacokinetic data (in the range of creatinine clearance tested of 30-156 ml/min)
             demonstrate that PLD clearance is not influenced by renal function. No pharmacokinetic
             data are available in patients with creatinine clearance of less than 30 ml/min.

          -  Patients must have a life expectancy ≥ 16 weeks.

          -  Evidence of non-childbearing status for women of childbearing potential: negative
             urine or serum pregnancy test within 28 days of study treatment, confirmed prior to
             treatment on day 1 Postmenopausal is defined as: Amenorrheic for 1 year or more
             following cessation of exogenous hormonal treatments; luteinizing hormone (LH) and
             follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) levels in the postmenopausal range for women under
             50; Radiation-induced oophorectomy with last menses &gt;1 year ago; Chemotherapy-induced
             menopause with &gt;1 year interval since last menses; or surgical sterilisation
             (bilateral oophorectomy or hysterectomy).

          -  Patient is willing and able to comply with the protocol for the duration of the study
             including undergoing treatment and scheduled visits and examinations including follow
             up.

          -  Willingness and ability to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plans, laboratory
             tests and other study procedures.

          -  Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) ≥ 50%.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Platinum-refractory disease (progression during previous platinum therapy).

          -  Involvement in the planning and/or conduct of the study (applies to both Sponsor staff
             and/or staff at the study site).

          -  Previous enrolment in the present study.

          -  Participation in another clinical study with an investigational product during the
             last 14 days or five half-lives of a drug (whichever is longer) prior to the first
             dose of study treatment.

          -  Any previous treatment with a PARP inhibitor, including olaparib.

          -  Patients with second primary cancer, except: adequately treated non-melanoma skin
             cancer, curatively treated in-situ cancer of the cervix, or other solid tumours
             curatively treated with no evidence of disease for ≥5 years.

          -  Patients receiving any systemic chemotherapy, radiotherapy (except for palliative
             reasons), within 2 weeks from the last dose prior to study treatment (or a longer
             period depending on the defined characteristics of the agents used). The patient can
             receive a stable dose of bisphosphonates for bone metastases, before and during the
             study as long as these were started at least 4 weeks prior to treatment with study
             drug.

          -  Concomitant use of known CYP3A4 inhibitors such as ketoconazole, itraconazole,
             ritonavir, indinavir, saquinavir, telithromycin, clarithromycin and nelfinavir.

          -  Persistent toxicities (&gt;=CTCAE grade 2) with the exception of alopecia, caused by
             previous cancer therapy.

          -  Resting ECG with corrected QT interval (QTc) &gt;470 msec on 2 or more time points within
             a 24 hour period or family history of long QT syndrome.

          -  Blood transfusions within 28 days prior to study entry.

          -  Patients with myelodysplastic syndrome/acute myeloid leukaemia.

          -  Patients with symptomatic uncontrolled brain metastases. A scan to confirm the absence
             of brain metastases is not required. The patient can receive a stable dose of
             corticosteroids before and during the study as long as these were started at least 28
             days prior to treatment.

          -  Major surgery within 14 days of starting study treatment and patients must have
             recovered from any effects of any major surgery.

          -  Patients considered a poor medical risk due to a serious, uncontrolled medical
             disorder, non-malignant systemic disease or active, uncontrolled infection. Examples
             include, but are not limited to, uncontrolled ventricular arrhythmia, recent (within 3
             months) myocardial infarction, unstable spinal cord compression (untreated and
             unstable for at least 28 days prior to study entry), superior vena cava syndrome,
             extensive bilateral lung disease on high-resolution computed tomography (HRCT) scan or
             any psychiatric disorder that prohibits obtaining informed consent.

          -  Patients unable to swallow orally administered medication and patients with
             gastrointestinal disorders likely to interfere with absorption of the study
             medication.

          -  Breast feeding women.

          -  Immunocompromised patients, e.g., patients who are known to be serologically positive
             for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and are receiving antiviral therapy.

          -  Patients with known active hepatic disease (i.e., Hepatitis B or C) due to risk of
             transmitting the infection through blood or other body fluids.

          -  Patients with a known hypersensitivity to olaparib or any of the excipients of the
             product.

          -  Patients with a known hypersensitivity to the combination/comparator agent

          -  Patients with uncontrolled seizures.

          -  Previous allogeneic bone marrow transplant or double umbilical cord blood
             transplantation (dUCBT).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alejandro Pérez-Fidalgo, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Valencia, Hospital Clinico Universitario de Valencia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alejandro Pérez-Fidalgo, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+34 638628058</phone>
    <email>japfidalgo@msn.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ana Levin, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+34 638628058</phone>
    <email>alevin@grupogeico.net</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Corporación Sanitaria Parc Taulí</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sabadell</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yolanda García García, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+34 93 724 00 84</phone>
      <email>ygarcia@tauli.cat</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yolanda García García, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario de Gran Canaria Doctor Negrín</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palmas de Gran Canaria</city>
        <state>Gran Canaria</state>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Uriel Bohn Sarmiento, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+34 928 450 400</phone>
      <email>ubosar@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Uriel Bohn Sarmiento, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Son Llatzer</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palma De Mallorca</city>
        <state>Mallorca</state>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>María Iglesias González, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+34 871 202 000</phone>
      <phone_ext>2103</phone_ext>
      <email>miglegon@hsll.es</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>María Iglesias González, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Ramón y Cajal</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28034</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alfonso Cortés, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+34 91 336 80 00</phone>
      <email>acsalgado86@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alfonso Cortés, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario 12 de Octubre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Luis Manso Sánchez, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+34 913908003</phone>
      <email>luis_manso@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Luis Manso Sánchez, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Virgen del Rocío</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elisa Calvo García, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+34 955 013 068</phone>
      <email>elisa.calvo.garcia@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Elisa Calvo García, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario y Politécnico La Fe</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ana Santaballana, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+34 961 244 188</phone>
      <email>santaballa_ana@gva.es</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ana Santaballa, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clínico Universitario de Valencia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>José A Pérez Fidalgo, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+34 963862625</phone>
      <email>japfidalgo@msn.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>José A Pérez Fidalgo, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 17, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 17, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 19, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liposomal doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Olaparib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

