<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00384332</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>051235</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00384332</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Medication, Weight Gain and GI Hormones</brief_title>
  <official_title>Orally-Disintegrating vs. Regular Olanzapine Tablets: Effects on Weight and GI Hormones</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Vanderbilt University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eli Lilly and Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an 8 week study that compares two medications. One medication is olanzapine (5-20 mg
      daily) whereas the other medication is an orally disintegrating medication. Both medications
      are used to treat depressed bipolar patients. The main focus of this study is the comparison
      of these two medications on gastro-intestinal hormones and weight gain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Olanzapine is undeniably one of the most effective treatments available for all phases of
      bipolar disorder. After FDA approval for bipolar mania, the drug became one of the most
      widely prescribed of treatments for this difficult-to-treat disorder. However, concerns about
      weight gain and the associated metabolic syndrome/type II diabetes have impacted the use of
      olanzapine.

      In fact, weight gain is quite common with olanzapine. For example, in one large scale 8-week
      placebo-controlled trial of olanzapine in bipolar depression, the olanzapine-treated patients
      gained an average of 2.59 kg., while placebo patients lost an average of 0.47 kg. Further,
      weight gain can continue over an extended period of time, mounting to an average of about 6
      kg. over one year. It should be noted, however, that in prior studies, no efforts have been
      made to limit weight gain. More recent data suggest that interventions such as dietary
      counseling are effective in either preventing or reversing weight gain.

      Olanzapine is a potent antagonist of serotonin and histamine 1 receptors. Significant and
      potentially additive weight gain is associated with blockade of serotonin 2C and Histamine 1
      receptors. In addition, serotonin and its receptors are significantly involved in the
      regulation of gastrointestinal (GI) - related hormone secretion. Animal studies suggest
      significant involvement of other serotonin receptors in the regulation of appetite, satiety,
      and GI-related hormones. However, the interplay of selective activation or inhibition of
      these receptor subtypes is complex, and difficult to distinguish from effects on activity and
      anxiety. Suffice it to say that activation or blockade of these receptors have differential
      effects on appetite, satiety, metabolic activity, as well as leptin, secretin, insulin,
      glucagon, ghrelin, neuropeptide Y, and cholecystokinin.

      Weight gain and the corresponding metabolic syndrome represent a &quot;deal killer&quot; with regard to
      the treatment of most patients. However, one recent small study may be highly relevant to
      this discussion. De Haan et al. investigated the relative effects of standard olanzapine
      tablets to the orally-disintegrating form (Zydis) in adolescents and young adults who had
      gained weight with olanzapine. The group randomly assigned 18 patients to continuation
      olanzapine tablets or Zydis for a 16-week period. The Zydis-treated patients lost an average
      of 6.6 kg. while the continuation regular olanzapine group gained 3.7 kg. Although small,
      this study suggests a potential solution to the weight-gain problem associated with
      olanzapine.

      Most of the pharmacological effects on weight and hormones are thought to be mediated
      centrally. However, De Haan et al. (de Haan L, et al. Psychopharmacology (Berl).
      2004;175:389-390) proposed that at least some of the difference could be attributable to
      local effects in the GI tract. In particular, the site of absorption was suggested as a
      possible explanation, with the orally disintegrating form (Zydis) yielding less exposure of
      the pylorus to olanzapine than the standard Zyprexa tablets.

      In this project we will treat 20 patients with bipolar disorder with olanzapine (a
      widely-used and FDA approved treatment for this condition); patients will be randomly
      assigned (1:1) to either standard Zyprexa tablets or orally disintegrating Zydis. We will
      measure symptom improvement and weight gain over the course of the study. Patients will be
      given dietary counseling prior to initiating either medication. In addition, we will contrast
      the effects of the treatments on GI-related hormones.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight in Kilograms at Baseline, Weeks 1, 4, 6, and 8</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Change in weight from baseline to endpoint in kilograms. Reported as weight in Kilograms at Baseline, Weeks 1, 4, 6, and 8</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) total score. Construct: Depression severity. Scores below represent mean change scores, endpoint minus baseline. Minimum total score: 0 (no depression). Maximum total score: 60 (severe depression). Lower (more negative) scores indicate a better outcome. There are no subscales.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Bipolar Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Orally disintegrating olanzapine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>regular olanzapine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>orally-disintegrating olanzapine</intervention_name>
    <description>5 to 20 mg (daily) orally disintegrating olanzapine for approx.8 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zydis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>regular olanzapine</intervention_name>
    <description>5-20 mg. olanzapine daily for approximately 8 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Zyprexa</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A principal diagnosis of bipolar 1 or II disorder

          -  Ages 18-60

          -  Physically healthy

          -  Outpatient status

          -  Montgomery-Asberg Rating Scale (MADRS) Score greater than or equal to 15

          -  BMI 23-30

          -  Able and willing to give written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior history of diabetes (types I or II)

          -  BMI&gt;30

          -  Non-fasting blood glucose &gt;124

          -  Fasting blood glucose &gt;125 or random blood glucose &gt;200

          -  Presence of dyslipidemia (baseline total cholesterol &gt;240, HDL&lt;50, LDL&gt;160,
             triglycerides &gt;199)

          -  Current or past history of a non-affective psychotic disorder

          -  Alcohol or other substance abuse or dependence in the 6 months prior to the evaluation
             (except for caffeine)

          -  Current use of any nicotine products

          -  Schizoid, schizotypal, or borderline personality disorder

          -  Treatment with olanzapine in the prior 3 months or any history of non- response to or
             intolerance of olanzapine or the olanzapine-fluoxetine combination (SymbiaxTM)

          -  Suicide potential that, in the opinion of the investigator, precludes outpatient
             treatment or participation in a trial

          -  Participation of subjects in another drug trial within 30 days of evaluation

          -  The presence of any current medical condition judged by the investigator to
             potentially interfere with the study procedures or measures

          -  The likelihood of requiring hospitalization over the period of the study

          -  The presence of any clinically-significant laboratory abnormality as judged by the
             investigator

          -  Pregnancy or lactation

          -  History of seizure disorder, excluding febrile seizures of childhood

          -  Any disorder of taste or smell, including severe nasal allergies

          -  Any other condition which, in the investigator's judgment might increase the risk to
             the subject or decrease the chance of obtaining satisfactory data to achieve the
             objectives of the study

          -  Being unable to comprehend or follow the study procedures.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard C. Shelton, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37212</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mc.vanderbilt.edu/root/vumc.php?site=psychiatry&amp;doc=9683</url>
    <description>The research program, faculty and studies, including this one are listed on this website.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tohen M, Vieta E, Calabrese J, Ketter TA, Sachs G, Bowden C, Mitchell PB, Centorrino F, Risser R, Baker RW, Evans AR, Beymer K, Dube S, Tollefson GD, Breier A. Efficacy of olanzapine and olanzapine-fluoxetine combination in the treatment of bipolar I depression. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2003 Nov;60(11):1079-88. Erratum in: Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2004 Feb;61(2):176.</citation>
    <PMID>14609883</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shelton RC. Treating bipolar depression. J Fam Pract. 2003 Mar;Suppl:S14-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12676079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farwell WR, Stump TE, Wang J, Tafesse E, L'Italien G, Tierney WM. Weight gain and new onset diabetes associated with olanzapine and risperidone. J Gen Intern Med. 2004 Dec;19(12):1200-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15610330</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>eder-Ischia U, Ebenbichler C, Fleischhacker WW. Olanzapine-induced weight gain and disturbances of lipid and glucose metabolism. Essent Psychopharmacol. 2005;6(2):112-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15765795</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith RC, Lindenmayer JP, Bark N, Warner-Cohen J, Vaidhyanathaswamy S, Khandat A. Clozapine, risperidone, olanzapine, and conventional antipsychotic drug effects on glucose, lipids, and leptin in schizophrenic patients. Int J Neuropsychopharmacol. 2005 Jun;8(2):183-94.</citation>
    <PMID>15737248</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen D. Diabetes mellitus during olanzapine and quetiapine treatment in Japan. J Clin Psychiatry. 2005 Feb;66(2):265-6; author reply 266-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15705015</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gill SS. Stable monotherapy with clozapine or olanzapine increases the incidence of diabetes mellitus in people with schizophrenia. Evid Based Ment Health. 2005 Feb;8(1):24.</citation>
    <PMID>15671515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zimmermann U, Kraus T, Himmerich H, Schuld A, Pollmächer T. Epidemiology, implications and mechanisms underlying drug-induced weight gain in psychiatric patients. J Psychiatr Res. 2003 May-Jun;37(3):193-220. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12650740</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tecott LH, Sun LM, Akana SF, Strack AM, Lowenstein DH, Dallman MF, Julius D. Eating disorder and epilepsy in mice lacking 5-HT2c serotonin receptors. Nature. 1995 Apr 6;374(6522):542-6.</citation>
    <PMID>7700379</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kroeze WK, Hufeisen SJ, Popadak BA, Renock SM, Steinberg S, Ernsberger P, Jayathilake K, Meltzer HY, Roth BL. H1-histamine receptor affinity predicts short-term weight gain for typical and atypical antipsychotic drugs. Neuropsychopharmacology. 2003 Mar;28(3):519-26.</citation>
    <PMID>12629531</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 4, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 5, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 6, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>July 23, 2015</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>June 29, 2017</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">July 31, 2017</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 29, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 29, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 31, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Vanderbilt University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Richard C. Shelton</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bipolar Depression</keyword>
  <keyword>Weight gain bipolar medicine</keyword>
  <keyword>side effects olanzapine</keyword>
  <keyword>gastrointestinal hormones bipolar medicine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Weight Gain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bipolar Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hormones</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Olanzapine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Participants referred by treatment providers.</recruitment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Arm 1- ODT</title>
          <description>Orally disintegrating olanzapine
orally-disintegrating olanzapine: 5 to 20 mg (daily) orally disintegrating olanzapine for approx.8 weeks.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Arm 2- SOT</title>
          <description>regular olanzapine
regular olanzapine: 5-20 mg. olanzapine daily for approximately 8 weeks.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="13"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="10"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="9"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="10"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="4"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Lost to Follow-up</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="4"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Arm 1</title>
          <description>Orally disintegrating olanzapine
orally-disintegrating olanzapine: 5 to 20 mg (daily) orally disintegrating olanzapine for approx.8 weeks.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Arm 2</title>
          <description>regular olanzapine
regular olanzapine: 5-20 mg. olanzapine daily for approximately 8 weeks.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="13"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="10"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="23"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="23"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <description>Self-reported age.</description>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="36.4" spread="8.5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="39.7" spread="9.9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="38.05" spread="9.2"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="13"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="10"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="23"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Weight in Kilograms at Baseline, Weeks 1, 4, 6, and 8</title>
        <description>Change in weight from baseline to endpoint in kilograms. Reported as weight in Kilograms at Baseline, Weeks 1, 4, 6, and 8</description>
        <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Arm 1- ODT</title>
            <description>Orally disintegrating olanzapine
orally-disintegrating olanzapine: 5 to 20 mg (daily) orally disintegrating olanzapine for approx.8 weeks.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Arm 2- SOT</title>
            <description>regular olanzapine
regular olanzapine: 5-20 mg. olanzapine daily for approximately 8 weeks.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Weight in Kilograms at Baseline, Weeks 1, 4, 6, and 8</title>
          <description>Change in weight from baseline to endpoint in kilograms. Reported as weight in Kilograms at Baseline, Weeks 1, 4, 6, and 8</description>
          <units>kilograms</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Error</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="13"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="10"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Baseline</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="76.0" spread="0.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="76.1" spread="0.7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Week 1</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="77.4" spread="0.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="77.6" spread="0.7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Week 4</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="77.8" spread="0.6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="78.3" spread="0.7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Week 6</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="78.9" spread="0.7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="79.4" spread="0.7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Week 8</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="79.1" spread="0.7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="80.1" spread="0.7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change From Baseline Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale</title>
        <description>Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) total score. Construct: Depression severity. Scores below represent mean change scores, endpoint minus baseline. Minimum total score: 0 (no depression). Maximum total score: 60 (severe depression). Lower (more negative) scores indicate a better outcome. There are no subscales.</description>
        <time_frame>10 weeks</time_frame>
        <population>Patients with bipolar disorder randomized to orally disintegrating versus regular olanzapine.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Arm 1</title>
            <description>Orally disintegrating olanzapine
orally-disintegrating olanzapine: 5 to 20 mg (daily) orally disintegrating olanzapine for approx.8 weeks.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Arm 2</title>
            <description>regular olanzapine
regular olanzapine: 5-20 mg. olanzapine daily for approximately 8 weeks.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change From Baseline Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale</title>
          <description>Montgomery Asberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) total score. Construct: Depression severity. Scores below represent mean change scores, endpoint minus baseline. Minimum total score: 0 (no depression). Maximum total score: 60 (severe depression). Lower (more negative) scores indicate a better outcome. There are no subscales.</description>
          <population>Patients with bipolar disorder randomized to orally disintegrating versus regular olanzapine.</population>
          <units>units on a scale</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="13"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="10"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-15.5" spread="13.1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-15.5" spread="13.1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Arm 1- ODT</title>
          <description>Orally disintegrating olanzapine
orally-disintegrating olanzapine: 5 to 20 mg (daily) orally disintegrating olanzapine for approx.8 weeks.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Arm 2- SOT</title>
          <description>regular olanzapine
regular olanzapine: 5-20 mg. olanzapine daily for approximately 8 weeks.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="13"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="13"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>SNOMED CT</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="13"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Increased appetite</sub_title>
                <description>Increased appetite</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="5" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="13"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="6" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="10"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>Treatment was not blinded to participants or treating physicians.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Candace Cromer</name_or_title>
      <organization>University of Alabama at Birmingham</organization>
      <phone>2059753442</phone>
      <email>clreed@uab.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

