<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00381836</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2005-005658-37</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>LM: 2612-3148</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>Ethical: 20060074</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>Data Protection: 2005-41-6015</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00381836</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Darbepoetin Alfa (Aranesp®) on Anemia in Patients With Advanced Hormone Independent Prostate Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Multi-center Study to Assess the Effect of Darbepoetin Alfa (Aranesp®) for the Treatment of Anemia in Patients With Advanced Hormone Independent Prostate Cancer and Anaemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Aarhus</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Aarhus</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether or not Aranesp® (Darbepoetin Alfa),
      administered every fourth week, is effective in the treatment of blood shortage (anemia)
      compared to standard care of treatment (blood transfusions) in patients with anemia due to
      hormone refractory prostate cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the past, prostate cancer has been regarded a relatively benign disease, which elderly men
      were expected to die with rather than from, however, prostate cancer has become the second
      most common non-skin cancer in Danish men and the second most common cause of male cancer
      death. Two out of three patients with clinically significant prostate cancer die from and not
      with their cancer disease, and the misery of this population is evident. Regular treatments
      with opiates or equivalent drugs as well are required in nearly one third of the patients.

      Patients with advanced hormone insensitive (refractory) prostate cancer have a median
      survival rate of about one year and during this time they often suffer from anemia due to
      reasons like blood loss, tumor infiltration of the bone marrow and even treatment with
      androgen deprivation. Compared to patients with other cancer types patients with prostate
      cancer have a significantly lower mean haemoglobin level. However, patients with hormone
      refractory prostate cancer have not previously been given much attention and the treatment of
      the frequent condition of chronic anemia in this group of patients seems casual. Therefore,
      Best Standard of Care (BSC) is defined as RBC transfusion if the hemoglobin is &lt; 5,0 mmol/L
      (8,0 g/dl), and if there are signs or symptoms of anemia and supplemental iron if se-ferritin
      &lt; 200 mcg/L.

      Very little is known about erythropoietin treatment and quality of life in hormone refractory
      prostate cancer patients. A randomized Swedish study did investigate the influence of two
      different doses of epoetin beta on quality of life, hemoglobin level, need for red blood cell
      transfusion and safety, in the treatment of anemia in 180 patients suffering from advanced
      hormone-refractory prostate cancer. This study found the treatment to be safe and effective
      for the treatment in many of these patients. In many of these critically ill patients, the
      treatment improved quality of life and relieved fatigue symptoms.

      Darbepoetin alpha (Aranesp®) is produced by gene-technology in Chinese Hamster Cells
      (CHO-K1). It has a biological effect and toxicity profile comparable to r-HuEPO; with the
      exception of a longer half-life which means that it can be administered less frequently
      without loosing clinical efficiency. Aranesp® has been well tolerated in studies conducted to
      this date. In this setting Aranesp® appears to be safe and well tolerated. Adverse events
      reported to date have generally been mild to moderate in severity and consistent with events
      and symptoms in cancer patients with chronic disease receiving chemotherapy (i.e. fatigue and
      gastrointestinal symptoms). Clinical studies have shown a higher frequency of thromboembolic
      reactions including deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism in cancer patients receiving
      Aranesp therapy compared to patients receiving placebo. The clinical experience so far with
      Aranesp® has been published (15,16,17). Aranesp® is registered for clinical use in Europe and
      US.

      Based on this the present study will evaluate the effect of Aranesp® on the haematopoietic
      response in patients with advanced hormone independent prostate cancer and anemia. Moreover,
      the effect of Aranesp® on quality of life, hemoglobin, necessity for RBC transfusion and
      hospital admissions, will be evaluated. The study will be performed as an open randomized
      trial. The use of r-HuEPO in cancer patients has been established and registered in other
      settings (as supportive treatment), and it has been shown that the preparation can be given
      without significant side effects. On the contrary, it is likely that patients may benefit
      from additional improvement in wellbeing.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Terminated by sponsor due to general risk that aranesp caused tumor progression
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>October 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The haematopoietic response at week 4, 8, 12, 16 and 20</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (EQ-5D and QLQ-C30) at week 8 and 20</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of blood transfusions at week 4, 8, 12, 16 and 20</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in haemoglobin at week 4, 8, 12, 16 and 20</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of days admitted to hospital during the 20 week study period</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">140</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostatic Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Anemia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Darbepoetin Alfa</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male &gt; 18 years

          -  Histologically proven prostate cell carcinoma

          -  Progression in PSA (10% elevation of nadir-value documented by two tests) at least 4
             months after surgical orchiectomy or initiation of LHRH-agonist. Testosterone level
             must be below castration level

          -  All PSA values must be &gt; 5 ng/ml

          -  Haemoglobin level below 11 g/dl (6.8 mmol/l)

          -  Haemoglobin level tested no later than 14 days prior to randomization

          -  A life expectancy of more than 3 months

          -  Participants must sign Informed consent according to local and national regulations
             and European Clinical Trial Directive

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known primary haematological disorder, which could cause anaemia

          -  Hypertension (diastolic blood pressure &gt; 100 mmHg), refractory to treatment

          -  Symptomatic cardiovascular disease

          -  History of thromboembolic events during the last 12 months

          -  Concomitant Chemotherapy

          -  Active and severe liver disease

          -  Clinical significant inflammatory disease

          -  Concomitant or previous malignancies, which are likely to influence the treatment,
             evaluation and outcome of the current disease and therapy

          -  Concern of subject's compliance with the protocol procedures

          -  Previously included into the study

          -  Received erythropoietic therapy within 4 weeks before inclusion into the study

          -  Known positive antibody reaction to any erythropoietic agent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Borre, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Urology, Aarhus University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Urology, Aarhus University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aarhus</city>
        <zip>8000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aus G, Hugosson J, Norlén L. Long-term survival and mortality in prostate cancer treated with noncurative intent. J Urol. 1995 Aug;154(2 Pt 1):460-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>7541864</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Potosky AL, Miller BA, Albertsen PC, Kramer BS. The role of increasing detection in the rising incidence of prostate cancer. JAMA. 1995 Feb 15;273(7):548-52.</citation>
    <PMID>7530782</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Borre M, Nerstrøm B, Overgaard J. The dilemma of prostate cancer--a growing human and economic burden irrespective of treatment strategies. Acta Oncol. 1997;36(7):681-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9490083</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brasso K, Friis S, Kjaer SK, Iversen P. [Prostatic cancer men under age 65. Occurrence and need for study]. Ugeskr Laeger. 1997 Apr 21;159(17):2543-5. Danish.</citation>
    <PMID>9182383</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Borre M, Nerstrøm B, Overgaard J. The natural history of prostate carcinoma based on a Danish population treated with no intent to cure. Cancer. 1997 Sep 1;80(5):917-28.</citation>
    <PMID>9307192</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aus G, Hugosson J, Norlén L. Need for hospital care and palliative treatment for prostate cancer treated with noncurative intent. J Urol. 1995 Aug;154(2 Pt 1):466-9.</citation>
    <PMID>7541865</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Otnes B, Harvei S, Fosså SD. The burden of prostate cancer from diagnosis until death. Br J Urol. 1995 Nov;76(5):587-94.</citation>
    <PMID>8535677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carlsson P, Hjertberg H, Jönsson B, Varenhorst E. The cost of prostatic cancer in a defined population. Scand J Urol Nephrol. 1989;23(2):93-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2787931</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brasso K, Friis S, Juel K, Jørgensen T, Iversen P. The need for hospital care of patients with clinically localized prostate cancer managed by noncurative intent: a population based registry study. J Urol. 2000 Apr;163(4):1150-4.</citation>
    <PMID>10737485</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strum SB, McDermed JE, Scholz MC, Johnson H, Tisman G. Anaemia associated with androgen deprivation in patients with prostate cancer receiving combined hormone blockade. Br J Urol. 1997 Jun;79(6):933-41.</citation>
    <PMID>9202563</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ornstein DK, Beiser JA, Andriole GL. Anaemia in men receiving combined finasteride and flutamide therapy for advanced prostate cancer. BJU Int. 1999 Jan;83(1):43-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10233450</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johansson JE, Wersäll P, Brandberg Y, Andersson SO, Nordström L; EPO-Study Group. Efficacy of epoetin beta on hemoglobin, quality of life, and transfusion needs in patients with anemia due to hormone-refractory prostate cancer--a randomized study. Scand J Urol Nephrol. 2001 Sep;35(4):288-94.</citation>
    <PMID>11676354</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dunn A, Carter J, Carter H. Anemia at the end of life: prevalence, significance, and causes in patients receiving palliative care. J Pain Symptom Manage. 2003 Dec;26(6):1132-9.</citation>
    <PMID>14654265</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Egrie JC, Browne JK. Development and characterization of novel erythropoiesis stimulating protein (NESP). Br J Cancer. 2001 Apr;84 Suppl 1:3-10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11308268</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heatherington AC, Schuller J, Mercer AJ. Pharmacokinetics of novel erythropoiesis stimulating protein (NESP) in cancer patients: preliminary report. Br J Cancer. 2001 Apr;84 Suppl 1:11-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11308269</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glaspy J, Jadeja JS, Justice G, Kessler J, Richards D, Schwartzberg L, Rigas J, Kuter D, Harmon D, Prow D, Demetri G, Gordon D, Arseneau J, Saven A, Hynes H, Boccia R, O'Byrne J, Colowick AB. A dose-finding and safety study of novel erythropoiesis stimulating protein (NESP) for the treatment of anaemia in patients receiving multicycle chemotherapy. Br J Cancer. 2001 Apr;84 Suppl 1:17-23.</citation>
    <PMID>11308270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith RE Jr, Tchekmedyian NS, Chan D, Meza LA, Northfelt DW, Patel R, Austin M, Colowick AB, Rossi G, Glaspy J. A dose- and schedule-finding study of darbepoetin alpha for the treatment of chronic anaemia of cancer. Br J Cancer. 2003 Jun 16;88(12):1851-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12799626</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bohlius J, Langensiepen S, Schwarzer G, Seidenfeld J, Piper M, Bennet C, Engert A. Erythropoietin for patients with malignant disease. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2004;(3):CD003407. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2006;(3):CD003407.</citation>
    <PMID>15266483</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bohlius J, Langensiepen S, Schwarzer G, Seidenfeld J, Piper M, Bennett C, Engert A. Recombinant human erythropoietin and overall survival in cancer patients: results of a comprehensive meta-analysis. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2005 Apr 6;97(7):489-98. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15812074</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bohlius J, Wilson J, Seidenfeld J, Piper M, Schwarzer G, Sandercock J, Trelle S, Weingart O, Bayliss S, Djulbegovic B, Bennett CL, Langensiepen S, Hyde C, Engert A. Recombinant human erythropoietins and cancer patients: updated meta-analysis of 57 studies including 9353 patients. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2006 May 17;98(10):708-14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16705125</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Williams KJ, Parker CA, Stratford IJ. Exogenous and endogenous markers of tumour oxygenation status: definitive markers of tumour hypoxia? Adv Exp Med Biol. 2005;566:285-94. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16594164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Varlotto J, Stevenson MA. Anemia, tumor hypoxemia, and the cancer patient. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys. 2005 Sep 1;63(1):25-36. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16111569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 27, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 27, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 28, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 3, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 3, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 4, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prostate Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood transfusion</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Critical illness</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug efficacy</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug tolerability</keyword>
  <keyword>Erythropoietin</keyword>
  <keyword>Fatigue</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemoglobin</keyword>
  <keyword>Human</keyword>
  <keyword>Male</keyword>
  <keyword>Multicenter study</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>Questionnaire</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized controlled trial</keyword>
  <keyword>Recombinant erythropoietin</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hormones</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Darbepoetin alfa</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

