<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00382564</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>060249</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>06-DK-0249</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00382564</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Magnetic Resonance Angiography to Diagnose Atherosclerotic Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Magnetic Resonance Angiography (MRA) in the Diagnosis of Atherosclerotic Disease Using High Field (3T) MRI Scanners: A Pilot Technical Development Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will determine the usefulness of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) for examining
      the heart or blood vessels. MRI uses a magnetic field and radio waves to produce images of
      body tissues and organs. The subject lies on a table that can slide in and out of the scanner
      (a metal cylinder), wearing earplugs to muffle loud noises that occur during the scanning
      process. MRI of the heart and blood vessels, called magnetic resonance angiography (MRA), is
      a developing diagnostic method that permits evaluation of arteries and veins without the use
      of x-rays or invasive catheterization required by conventional angiography.

      People 18 years of age and older with known or suspected atherosclerotic disease may be
      eligible for this study.

      Participants have blood tests and MRA scanning. The MRA takes about 1.5 to 2 hours. During
      part of the scan, a contrast agent may be injected into a vein to brighten the images of the
      heart and blood vessels. Subjects are monitored with an electrocardiogram and are asked to
      hold their breath for about 5 to 20 seconds intermittently during the procedure.

      A CT scan may be done to confirm the MRA findings. CT uses x-rays to produce pictures of the
      heart and blood vessels. The subject lies on a bed during the scan and is given a contrast
      agent through a catheter inserted into a vein. Subjects are asked to hold their breath
      intermittently for about 5 to 20 seconds. A medicine called a beta blocker may be
      administered to slow the heart rate.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Magnetic Resonance Angiography (MRA) is a developing technique that permits the non-invasive
      evaluation of arterial and venous structures without the need for x-ray based catheter
      angiography. While dramatic progress has been made in the last few years, there are still
      substantial limitations in the accuracy of MRA in the evaluation of coronary artery. The
      primary aim of this study is to evaluate state-of-the-art techniques for coronary MRA in
      subjects with known or suspected coronary atherosclerosis. The secondary aim of this protocol
      is to generate natural history data for future hypothesis-driven clinical trials using MRA
      techniques developed in this current protocol. The long-term objective of this pilot study
      and research initiative is to improve coronary MRA to the point that it can reliably replace
      diagnostic x-ray catheter angiography in the evaluation of subjects with atherosclerotic
      disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 25, 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date>May 1, 2012</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment type="Actual">216</enrollment>
  <condition>Atherosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Hyperlipidemia</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Subjects with known or suspected atherosclerotic disease based on clinical
                  findings or documented by angiography (conventional, CT or MRA), or Doppler
                  ultrasound. Subjects at risk for atherosclerosis including: smoking,
                  hyperlipidemia, low levels of high density lipoproteins (less than 50 mg/dl for
                  women and less than 40 mg/dl for men), hypertension, family history (early onset
                  atherosclerosis less than 55 year old in male and less than 65 year old in female
                  who is first degree relative), and diabetes mellitus or metabolic syndrome.

               2. Subject must be willing to participate in the protocol.

               3. Subject age greater than 18 years old.

               4. Subject must be clinically stable and be able to come to the Clinical Center to
                  participate in the study.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Subjects with contraindication to MRI scanning. These contraindications include but
             are not limited to the following devices or conditions:

               1. Implanted cardiac pacemaker or defibrillator

               2. Cochlear Implants

               3. Ocular foreign body (e.g. metal shavings)

               4. Embedded shrapnel fragments

               5. Central nervous system aneurysm clips

               6. Implanted neural stimulator

               7. Medical infusion pumps

               8. Any implanted device that is incompatible with MRI.

          2. Unsatisfactory performance status as judged by the referring physician such that the
             subject could not tolerate an MRI scan. Examples of medical conditions that would not
             be accepted would include unstable angina and dyspnea at rest.

          3. Subjects requiring sedation for MRI studies.

          4. Subjects with a condition precluding entry into the scanner (e.g. morbid obesity,
             claustrophobia, etc.).

          5. Pregnant or lactating women.

          6. Subjects with severe back-pain or motion disorders who will be unable to tolerate
             supine positioning within the MRI scanner and hold still for the duration of the
             examination.

          7. Subjects who are unable to undergo a CTA within 1 month of the MRA part of this study,
             or are unable undergo or be scheduled for a cardiac catheterization within 1 month of
             the MRA.

             FOR GADOLINIUM BASED MRI STUDIES ONLY:

          8. History of severe allergic reaction to gadolinium contrast agents despite the use of
             premeditation with an anti-histaminic and cortisone.

          9. Creatinine value greater than 3.0 mg/dl

             FOR CARDIAC CT:

         10. Recent cardiac CT within a month. Both a coronary CTA and calcium score scan are
             required for this study. If any of these scans were performed at an outside facility
             and meet the necessary quality level, then that aspect of the cardiac CT scan
             (coronary CTA, calcium score scan or both) will not be performed at the NIH. Coronary
             CTA and/or calcium score CT obtained at the outside facility must be performed within
             one month of subject inclusion and acquired using a 16 slice scanner or higher and
             should be of good quality. The unformatted images of outside cardiac scans must be
             available to the primary investigator within one month of their acquisition for
             eligibility of inclusion in the study.

             FOR CORONARY CTA:

         11. Contraindication to the use of CT contrast agents:

               1. Creatinine value greater than 1.4 mg/dl

               2. History of multiple myeloma

               3. Use of metformin-containing products less than 24 hrs prior to contrast
                  administration

               4. History of significant allergic reaction to CT contrast agents despite the use of
                  premeditation with an anti-histaminic and cortisone.

         12. Subjects with contraindication precluding the use of beta blockers necessary to
             perform the coronary CTA. These include:

               1. Asthma

               2. Active bronchospasm

               3. Moderate or severe COPD

               4. Second or third degree AV block

               5. Decompensated cardiac failure

               6. Allergy to beta blockers

               7. Systolic blood pressure less than 100 mm Hg

               8. Pregnancy or nursing
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ahmed M Gharib, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim WY, Danias PG, Stuber M, Flamm SD, Plein S, Nagel E, Langerak SE, Weber OM, Pedersen EM, Schmidt M, Botnar RM, Manning WJ. Coronary magnetic resonance angiography for the detection of coronary stenoses. N Engl J Med. 2001 Dec 27;345(26):1863-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11756576</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lopez AD, Murray CC. The global burden of disease, 1990-2020. Nat Med. 1998 Nov;4(11):1241-3.</citation>
    <PMID>9809543</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoffmann MH, Shi H, Schmitz BL, Schmid FT, Lieberknecht M, Schulze R, Ludwig B, Kroschel U, Jahnke N, Haerer W, Brambs HJ, Aschoff AJ. Noninvasive coronary angiography with multislice computed tomography. JAMA. 2005 May 25;293(20):2471-8. Erratum in: JAMA. 2005 Sep 14;294(10):1208.</citation>
    <PMID>15914747</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 1, 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 28, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 28, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 29, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Arteriosclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Hardening of the arteries</keyword>
  <keyword>MRA</keyword>
  <keyword>Narrowing of Vessels</keyword>
  <keyword>Noninvasive Plaque Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>Atherosclerotic Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Plaque</keyword>
  <keyword>Arteries</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypertension</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atherosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperlipidemias</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperlipoproteinemias</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

