<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00385242</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCT-37412</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00385242</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PET and Recovery Following Revascularization (PARR 2)</brief_title>
  <official_title>PET and Recovery Following Revascularization: Outcome and Cost-effectiveness of FDG PET in Left Ventricular Dysfunction (PARR 2)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ottawa Heart Institute Research Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Heart and Stroke Foundation of Ontario</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ottawa Heart Institute Research Corporation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Patients with severe ventricular dysfunction and coronary disease have high
      morbidity and mortality. They may benefit from revascularization, but have significant
      peri-operative morbidity and mortality. Positron emission tomography (PET) imaging with
      F-18-fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG) can detect viable myocardium that may recover from
      revascularization in such patients. It is unclear whether use of FDG PET in this population
      is improves outcome or is cost-effective.

      Objectives: The principal aim is to determine whether FDG PET-guided therapy is effective
      versus standard care. Secondary objectives are to determine whether FDG PET-guided therapy
      improves LV function, quality of life and is good value for money versus standard care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients with severe ventricular dysfunction and coronary artery disease have high morbidity
      and mortality but may benefit from revascularization. However, there is also significant
      peri-operative morbidity and mortality among these patients. This accounts for the variable
      approach to these patients in different cardiac centres. Clearly this patient group has the
      most to gain when coronary revascularization is beneficial, but also the most to lose when it
      is not helpful. There is a need for an approach that can better define patients with severe
      ventricular dysfunction due to ischemia, who will be more likely to benefit from
      revascularization. Positron emission tomography (PET) imaging with F-18-Fluorodeoxyglucose
      (FDG) has been used to evaluate patients with ventricular dysfunction, to detect ischemic but
      viable myocardium more likely to recover from revascularization. Recently retrospective
      studies have shown that FDG PET can identify patients at high risk for cardiac events if they
      do not undergo revascularization. However, these studies did not evaluate whether FDG PET
      actually directed therapy decisions and because of their study design, could not determine
      whether FDG PET altered patient outcome. Our recent studies have shown that FDG PET can have
      important impact on therapy decisions and that patients with ischemic but viable myocardium
      are at increased risk. However it remains unclear whether an approach which utilizes FDG PET
      to define ischemic but viable myocardium can have a beneficial effect on patient outcome. It
      is also important to consider the potential clinical impact of FDG PET balanced against its
      limited availability. In addition, despite the cost of the technology, preliminary data from
      our group and others suggest a potential cost savings. Accordingly, a prospective randomized
      study is needed to evaluate whether FDG PET directed therapy has a beneficial effect on
      patient outcome and is cost-effective.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>time to occurence of the composite clinical endpoint of cardiac death,myocardial infarction, transplantation, or re-hospitalization for unstable angina or heart failure.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>occurrence of the composite endpoint; individual components of the composite endpoint; quality of life, costs, and cost-effectiveness of PET-guided therapy versus control.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">430</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <condition>Ventricular Dysfunction, Left</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PET guided Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to undergo positron emission tomography aspart of their clinical work up</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will be randomized to standard care will under go other types of imaging or work up for revascularization without PET imaging.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Positron emission tomography: FDG viability imaging</intervention_name>
    <description>FDG PET viability imaging</description>
    <arm_group_label>PET guided Therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PET imaging</intervention_name>
    <description>PET viability imaging</description>
    <arm_group_label>PET guided Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient is &gt; 18 years of age.

          -  Documented ejection fraction of &lt;35% attributable to CAD.

          -  Documented CAD

          -  Any patient being considered for revascularization, transplant/heart failure work up
             or where, in the opinion of the attending physician or surgeon, viability imaging
             would be considered useful in ongoing clinical management decisions.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Other co-morbid conditions making survival unlikely

          -  &lt; 6 weeks post myocardial infarction

          -  CAD unsuitable for revascularization

          -  emergency revascularization is required.

          -  severe valvular disease that requires surgery.

          -  Geographically inaccessible

          -  Lack of informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rob SB Beanlands, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ottawa Heart Institute Research Corporation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Ottawa Heart Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1Y 4W7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beanlands RS, Nichol G, Huszti E, Humen D, Racine N, Freeman M, Gulenchyn KY, Garrard L, deKemp R, Guo A, Ruddy TD, Benard F, Lamy A, Iwanochko RM; PARR-2 Investigators. F-18-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography imaging-assisted management of patients with severe left ventricular dysfunction and suspected coronary disease: a randomized, controlled trial (PARR-2). J Am Coll Cardiol. 2007 Nov 13;50(20):2002-12. Epub 2007 Oct 10.</citation>
    <PMID>17996568</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>D'Egidio G, Nichol G, Williams KA, Guo A, Garrard L, deKemp R, Ruddy TD, DaSilva J, Humen D, Gulenchyn KY, Freeman M, Racine N, Benard F, Hendry P, Beanlands RS; PARR-2 Investigators. Increasing benefit from revascularization is associated with increasing amounts of myocardial hibernation: a substudy of the PARR-2 trial. JACC Cardiovasc Imaging. 2009 Sep;2(9):1060-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jcmg.2009.02.017.</citation>
    <PMID>19761983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abraham A, Nichol G, Williams KA, Guo A, deKemp RA, Garrard L, Davies RA, Duchesne L, Haddad H, Chow B, DaSilva J, Beanlands RS; PARR 2 Investigators. 18F-FDG PET imaging of myocardial viability in an experienced center with access to 18F-FDG and integration with clinical management teams: the Ottawa-FIVE substudy of the PARR 2 trial. J Nucl Med. 2010 Apr;51(4):567-74. doi: 10.2967/jnumed.109.065938. Epub 2010 Mar 17.</citation>
    <PMID>20237039</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shukla T, Nichol G, Wells G, deKemp RA, Davies RA, Haddad H, Duchesne L, Freeman M, Gulenchyn K, Racine N, Humen D, Benard F, Ruddy TD, Chow BJ, DaSilva J, Garrard L, Guo A, Chen L, Beanlands RS. Does FDG PET-assisted management of patients with left ventricular dysfunction improve quality of life? A substudy of the PARR-2 trial. Can J Cardiol. 2012 Jan-Feb;28(1):54-61. doi: 10.1016/j.cjca.2011.09.012. Epub 2011 Dec 3.</citation>
    <PMID>22138342</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 6, 2006</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 6, 2006</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 9, 2006</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ottawa Heart Institute Research Corporation</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rob Beanlands</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Rob S. Beanlands, MD, FRCPC, Chief of Cardiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>coronary artery disease</keyword>
  <keyword>left ventricular dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>positron emission tomography</keyword>
  <keyword>viable myocardium</keyword>
  <keyword>revascularization</keyword>
  <keyword>cost effectiveness</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ventricular Dysfunction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ventricular Dysfunction, Left</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

