<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01442636</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FMRP-101021</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01442636</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Drug Eluting Stents In The Critically Ischemic Lower Leg 2</brief_title>
  <acronym>DESTINY 2</acronym>
  <official_title>a Prospective, Multicenter, Controlled Trial Evaluating the Implant of a Drug Eluting Stent (XIENCE PRIME, Abbott Vascular) in the Critically Ischemic Lower Leg</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Flanders Medical Research Program</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Flanders Medical Research Program</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this clinical evaluation is to evaluate the immediate and long term (up to
      12 months) outcome of the XIENCE PRIME Everolimus Eluting Coronary Stent System (Abbott
      Vascular) in a controlled prospective investigation for the treatment of patients with
      critical limb ischemia due to the presence of lesions between 3cm and 10cm in length at the
      level of the below the knee arteries. Specifically the trial aims to illicit angiographic and
      ultrasound patency, clinical improvement, and adverse events associated with the use of this
      stent. The trial design is single armed, prospective, controlled trial run over 12 months of
      follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this research is to evaluate the immediate and long term outcome of the XIENCE
      PRIME EverolimusEluting Coronary Stent System in a prospective investigation for the
      treatment of patients with critical limb ischemia due to the presence of lesions between 3cm
      and 10cm in length at the level of the below the knee arteries.

      The research question is &quot;Dose the use of an Everolimus coated stent in long tibial artery
      occlusions, between 3 and 10cm offer superior patency at 12 months compared to a historical
      cohort of bare metal stents in similar lesions?&quot; Our hypothesis is that the use of everolimus
      coated stents in tibial artery occlusions between 3 and 10cm will result in lower binary
      restenosis than was historically found in equivalent but non-drugcoated bare metal stents.

      Currently, there is evidence that angioplasty and drug eluting stents can be used as a
      therapy for patients with critical limb ischemia due to occlusive infrapopliteal disease. The
      XIENCE PRIME™ Everolimus Eluting Coronary Stent System (XIENCE PRIME EECSS or XIENCE PRIME
      stent system) is manufactured by Abbott. It is a device/drug combination product consisting
      of the CobaltChromium MULTILINK VISION 8 Coronary Stent System coated with a formulation
      containing everolimus, the active ingredient, embedded in a nonerodible polymer. The XIENCE
      PRIME Everolimus Eluting Coronary Stent is coated with everolimus (active ingredient),
      embedded in a nonerodible polymer (inactive ingredient). Everolimus is the active
      pharmaceutical ingredient in the XIENCE PRIME stent. It is a novel semisynthetic macrolide
      immunosuppressant, synthesized by chemical modification of rapamycin (sirolimus). The
      everolimus chemical name is 40O(2hydroxyethyl) rapamycin.

      The XIENCE PRIME stent contains inactive ingredients including poly n-butyl methacrylate
      (PBMA), a polymer that adheres to the stent and drug coating, and PVDFHFP, which is comprised
      of vinylidene fluoride and hexafluoropropylene monomers as the drug matrix layer containing
      everolimus. PBMA is a homopolymer with a molecular weight (Mw) of 264,000 to 376,000 dalton.
      PVDFHFP is a nonerodible semicrystalline random copolymer with a molecular weight (Mw) of
      254,000 to 293,000 dalton. The drug matrix copolymer is mixed with everolimus (83%/17% w/w
      polymer/everolimus ratio) and applied to the entire PBMA coated stent surface. The drug load
      is 100 μg/cm2 for all product sizes. No top-coat layer is used.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary patency at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Absence of restenosis (≥50% stenosis) or occlusion within the originally treated lesion based on angiography</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Technical success</measure>
    <time_frame>procedure</time_frame>
    <description>The ability to cross and dilate the lesion to achieve residual angiographic stenosis no greater than 30%</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemodynamic primary patency rate at 1, 6, 12-month follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 6, 12-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Patients that present without a hemodynamically significant stenosis at the target area on duplex ultrasound (systolic velocity ratio no greater than 2.4) and without prior TLR are defined as being primary patent at the given follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Limb-salvage rate at all follow-up visits</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 6, 12-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Absence of major amputation. Major amputation is defined as amputation at or above the ankle, as opposed to minor amputation, being an amputation at or below metatarsal level, preserving functionality of the foot).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary assisted patency rate at 1, 6, 12-month follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 6, 12-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as flow through the treated lesion maintained by repeat percutaneous intervention completed prior to complete vessel closure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary patency rate at 1, 6, 12-month follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 6, 12-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as flow through the treated lesion maintained by repeat percutaneous intervention after occlusion of the target lesion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Target lesion revascularization (TLR) at all follow-up visits</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 6, 12-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>A repeat intervention to maintain or re-establish patency within the region of the treated arterial vessel plus 5 mm proximal and distal to the treated lesion edge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical success at all follow-up visits</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 6, 12-month</time_frame>
    <description>An improvement of Rutherford classification at 1 day and 1, 6, 12-month follow-up of one class or more as compared to the pre-procedure Rutherford classification.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serious adverse events until follow-up completions</measure>
    <time_frame>1,6,12 months and interim visits</time_frame>
    <description>Any clinical event that is fatal, life-threatening, or judged to be severe by the investigator; resulted in persistent or significant disability; necessitated surgical or percutaneous intervention; or required prolonged hospitalization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Peripheral Arterial Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Xience Prime stent</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with critical limb ischemia due to below the knee arterial lesion between 30 and 100mm in length, treated with the XIENCE PRIME™ Everolimus Eluting Coronary Stent System.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>stent</intervention_name>
    <description>Implantation of one or more Everolimus-eluting XIENCE PRIME™ Everolimus Eluting Coronary Stent Systems.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Xience Prime stent</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Xience Prime stent</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient presenting with rest pain or minor tissue loss (Rutherford class 4 or 5)

          -  Patient is willing to comply with specified follow-up evaluations at the specified
             times

          -  Patient is &gt;18 years old

          -  Patient understands the nature of the procedure and provides written informed consent,
             prior to enrolment in the study

          -  Patient has a projected life-expectancy of at least 12 months

          -  Patient is eligible for treatment with the XIENCE PRIME stent (Abbott Vascular)

          -  Male, infertile female, or female of child bearing potential practicing an acceptable
             method of birth control with a negative pregnancy test within 7 days prior to study
             procedure

        Angiographic Inclusion Criteria:

          -  De novo lesion or restenotic lesion after PTA in the infrapopliteal arteries, suitable
             for endovascular therapy

          -  Total target lesion length minimally 30mm and maximally 100mm

          -  Target vessel diameter visually estimated to be &gt;2.0mm and &lt;3.5mm

          -  Guidewire and delivery system successfully traversed lesion

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient refusing treatment

          -  The reference segment diameter is not suitable for the available stent design

          -  Untreated flow-limiting inflow lesions

          -  Perioperative unsuccessful ipsilateral percutaneous vascular procedure to treat inflow
             disease just prior to enrollment

          -  Any previous surgery in the target vessel (including prior ipsilateral crural bypass)

          -  Aneurysm in the target vessel

          -  Non-atherosclerotic disease resulting in occlusion (e.g. embolism, Buerger's disease,
             vasculitis)

          -  Severe medical comorbidities (untreated CAD/CHF, severe COPD, metastatic malignancy,
             dementia, etc) or other medical condition that would preclude compliance with the
             study protocol or 1-year life expectancy

          -  Major distal amputation (above the transmetatarsal) in the study limb or non-study
             limb

          -  Septicemia or bacteremia

          -  Any previously known coagulation disorder, including hypercoagulability

          -  Contraindication to anticoagulation or antiplatelet therapy

          -  Known allergies to stent or stent components

          -  Known allergy to contrast media that cannot be adequately pre-medicated prior to the
             study procedure

          -  Patient with known hypersensitivity to heparin, including those patients who have had
             a previous incidence of heparin-induced thrombocytopenia (HIT) type II

          -  Currently participating in another clinical research trial

          -  Angiographic evidence of intra-arterial thrombus or atheroembolism from inflow
             treatment

          -  Target lesion access not performed by transfemoral approach.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marc Bosiers, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>A.Z. Sint-Blasius Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prince of Wales Private Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Randwick</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2031</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Imelda Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bonheiden</city>
        <state>Antwerp</state>
        <zip>2820</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department Vascular Surgery, A.Z. Sint-Blasius Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dendermonde</city>
        <state>East-Flanders</state>
        <zip>9200</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Herz-zentrum Bad Krozingen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bad Krozingen</city>
        <zip>79189</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Herzzentrum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leipzig</city>
        <zip>04289</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Fransiskus hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Münster</city>
        <zip>48145</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 22, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 27, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 28, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 9, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Arterial Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

