<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01441544</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>8630B</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01441544</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Variety on Physical Activity</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Variety on Physical Activity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Increasing physical activity continues to be a challenge among many individuals, particularly
      those who are overweight. Recent data from the National Health and Nutrition Examination
      Survey (NHANES) showed that individuals who reported engaging in a variety of activities were
      more likely to meet national physical activity recommendations compared to those who reported
      no variety. Incorporating a variety of activities into a physical activity program may be a
      way to increase physical increase physical activity levels.

      One method to increase variety in physical activities is to use active videogames. Videogames
      that use motion sensors allow a gamer to physically perform a variety of activities. Thus,
      the purpose ot this laboratory-based investigation is to conduct a study to examine the
      effect of engaging in a greater variety of active videogames on energy expenditure in 30
      non-obese, regularly active adults.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Thirty men and women, aged 18- to 35- years, recruited from the local area, with a normal
      body mass index (BMI) between 18.5 and 29.9 kg/m, will participate in two experimental
      sessions, VARIETY and NON-VARIETY, with order of experimental sessions counterbalanced across
      participants. Participants will be assessed on liking of the active videogames, energy,
      tiredness, motivation, to succeed, interest in the games, and energy expenditure during the
      experimental sessions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Energy expenditure in a laboratory session when active videogames are played</measure>
    <time_frame>End of each session</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Overweight</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VAREITY</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NON-VARIETY</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Variety of Active Videogames</intervention_name>
    <description>Thirty men and women, aged 18- to 35- years, recruited from the local area, with a normal body mass index (BMI) between 18.5 and 29.9 kg/m, will participate in two experimental sessions, VARIETY (playing the same active video game over 4 sessions) and NON-VARIETY (playing 4 different active video games over 4 sessions), with order of experimental sessions counterbalanced across participants.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VAREITY</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>NON-VARIETY</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women, ages 18-25 years are eligible to participate. They will be recruited
             from flyers posted around campus and in local gyms, and must be willing to
             participate. They must have a body mass index (BMI) between 18.5 and 29.9 kg/m2.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who have never played an active videogame or are unable to play an active
             videogame. If the participant dislikes (scoring &lt;50 on a 100 mm visual analogue scale
             [VAS]) playing the active videogames used in the investigation. Or if the participant
             engages in less than 150 minutes/week of moderate- to vigorous-intensity physical
             activity over the previous month.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hollie A Raynor, Ph. D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Tennessee</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dale Bond, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Miriam Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Tennessee</name>
      <address>
        <city>Knoxville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37996</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Troiano RP, Berrigan D, Dodd KW, Mâsse LC, Tilert T, McDowell M. Physical activity in the United States measured by accelerometer. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2008 Jan;40(1):181-8.</citation>
    <PMID>18091006</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tudor-Locke C, Brashear MM, Johnson WD, Katzmarzyk PT. Accelerometer profiles of physical activity and inactivity in normal weight, overweight, and obese U.S. men and women. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act. 2010 Aug 3;7:60. doi: 10.1186/1479-5868-7-60.</citation>
    <PMID>20682057</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perri MG, Martin AD, Leermakers EA, Sears SF, Notelovitz M. Effects of group- versus home-based exercise in the treatment of obesity. J Consult Clin Psychol. 1997 Apr;65(2):278-85.</citation>
    <PMID>9086691</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jakicic JM, Winters C, Lang W, Wing RR. Effects of intermittent exercise and use of home exercise equipment on adherence, weight loss, and fitness in overweight women: a randomized trial. JAMA. 1999 Oct 27;282(16):1554-60.</citation>
    <PMID>10546695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Otten JJ, Jones KE, Littenberg B, Harvey-Berino J. Effects of television viewing reduction on energy intake and expenditure in overweight and obese adults: a randomized controlled trial. Arch Intern Med. 2009 Dec 14;169(22):2109-15. doi: 10.1001/archinternmed.2009.430.</citation>
    <PMID>20008695</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jakicic JM, Wing RR, Butler BA, Robertson RJ. Prescribing exercise in multiple short bouts versus one continuous bout: effects on adherence, cardiorespiratory fitness, and weight loss in overweight women. Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord. 1995 Dec;19(12):893-901.</citation>
    <PMID>8963358</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haskell WL, Lee IM, Pate RR, Powell KE, Blair SN, Franklin BA, Macera CA, Heath GW, Thompson PD, Bauman A. Physical activity and public health: updated recommendation for adults from the American College of Sports Medicine and the American Heart Association. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 2007 Aug;39(8):1423-34.</citation>
    <PMID>17762377</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sherwood NE, Jeffery RW. The behavioral determinants of exercise: implications for physical activity interventions. Annu Rev Nutr. 2000;20:21-44. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10940325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fitzhugh EC, Thompson DL. Leisure-time walking and compliance with ACSM/AHA aerobic-related physical activity recommendations: 1999-2004 NHANES. J Phys Act Health. 2009 Jul;6(4):393-402.</citation>
    <PMID>19842452</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pereira MA, FitzerGerald SJ, Gregg EW, Joswiak ML, Ryan WJ, Suminski RR, Utter AC, Zmuda JM. A collection of Physical Activity Questionnaires for health-related research. Med Sci Sports Exerc. 1997 Jun;29(6 Suppl):S1-205.</citation>
    <PMID>9243481</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raynor HA, Epstein LH. The relative-reinforcing value of food under differing levels of food deprivation and restriction. Appetite. 2003 Feb;40(1):15-24.</citation>
    <PMID>12631501</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Levac D, Pierrynowski MR, Canestraro M, Gurr L, Leonard L, Neeley C. Exploring children's movement characteristics during virtual reality video game play. Hum Mov Sci. 2010 Dec;29(6):1023-38. doi: 10.1016/j.humov.2010.06.006. Epub 2010 Aug 17.</citation>
    <PMID>20724014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McAuley E, Duncan T, Tammen VV. Psychometric properties of the Intrinsic Motivation Inventory in a competitive sport setting: a confirmatory factor analysis. Res Q Exerc Sport. 1989 Mar;60(1):48-58.</citation>
    <PMID>2489825</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 25, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 26, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 27, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Tennessee, Knoxville</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hollie Raynor</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>active video games</keyword>
  <keyword>Energy expenditure</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

