<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01440907</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C023699-22</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01440907</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Impact of a Hospital Discharge Care Coordination Program in an Elderly Population</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of an HIE-Supported Care Coordination Package on Hospital Re-Admission Rates in an Elderly Population</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>New York State Department of Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Maimonides Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to evaluate the effect of a health information exchange
      (HIE)-supported care coordination package on 30-day readmission rates in a frail elderly
      population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND

      Reducing hospital readmission rates is a top national priority. Unplanned hospital
      readmission is estimated to have accounted for more than $17 billion of the roughly $103
      billion hospital payments made by Medicare in 2004.1 For patients in Medicare fee-for-service
      programs, the 30-day hospital readmission rates was recently found to be 19.6% nationally,
      and 20.7% in New York State (Jencks et al., 2009). Hospitals have urgent incentives to
      address readmission rates: readmission rates have been added to the National Quality Forum
      performance metrics (National Quality Forum, 2007); readmission rate comparisons are posted
      on www.hospitalcompare.hss.gov as public indicators of hospital quality; and provisions in
      health care reform legislation will soon mean that hospitals will not receive payment for
      many readmissions within 30 days of discharge.

      Targeted transitional programs and better coordination of care between inpatient and
      outpatient settings have the potential to reduce hospital readmission rates (Naylor et al,
      2004; Coleman et al, 2006; Peikes et al, 2009). Successful care coordination measures depend
      upon the effective transmission of health information between the inpatient and outpatient
      settings.

      The Brooklyn Health Information Exchange (BHIX) is a regional health information organization
      (RHIO) that provides secure health information exchange (HIE) services among participating
      health-care organizations in Brooklyn, Queens, and other parts of New York City. HIE allows
      the meaningful sharing of health information of locations where a patients may receive care
      or healthcare services and can be used to help improve the effective transmission of health
      information between inpatient and outpatient settings. Maimonides Medical Center is working
      with BHIX to offer a health information technology- and HIE-based care coordination program
      (CCP) to help improve the care of frail elderly patients upon discharge. The CCP includes:
      (1) access to a secure online personal health record (PHR) that people can logon and manage
      their health information, as well as receive alerts and reminders about action items for them
      to take on their healthcare; and (2) depending on the patient's health care needs, nursing
      support (either in-person or by phone).

      The main objective of this study to determine the impact of the CCP in a frail elderly
      population.

      SPECIFIC AIMS

      Weill Cornell Investigators will be analyzing a HIPAA-defined de-identified dataset from BHIX
      to evaluate the impact of the CCP. The two main outcomes we will be addressing in our data
      analysis are:

        1. Readmission to any BHIX hospital within 30 days of hospital discharge from Maimonides;

        2. Number of inpatient days within 30 days after being discharged from Maimonides Hospital.

      See CITATIONS, for references.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Readmission Rates Post 30-day Discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the impact of a health information exchange (HIE) care coordination program on reducing hospital readmissions rates post 30-day discharge from Maimonides Medical Center.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of inpatient hospital days within 30 days of discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the impact of a health information exchange (HIE) care coordination program on reducing the number of inpatient days patients experience within 30 days after being discharged from Maimonides Medical Center.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">201</enrollment>
  <condition>Hospital Readmission</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Those age 65 or older who are discharged from Maimonides Medical Center to home during the study period and enrolled in the Care Coordination Program</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Those age 65 or older who are discharged from Maimonides Medical Center to home</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Care Coordination Program</intervention_name>
    <description>The Care Coordination Program includes: (1) access to a secure online personal health record (PHR) that people can logon and manage their health information, as well as receive alerts and reminders about action items for them to take on their healthcare; and (2) depending on the patient's health care needs, nursing support (either in-person or by phone).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Safe at Home Project</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Weill Cornell Investigators will be receiving a HIPAA-compliant de-identified dataset
             from the Brooklyn Health Information Exchange (BHIX) that includes:

               -  Demographic data information

               -  Diagnoses (admission, discharge, readmission)

               -  Whether the patient was readmitted readmission, # of inpatients days if the
                  patients was readmitted

               -  Care coordination program statistics (e.g. usage of the personal health record,
                  and frequency of contact with nursing support staff).

          -  The data set will include data of the following individuals:

               1. Intervention Dataset (Group 1): Those age 65 or older who are discharged from
                  Maimonides to home during the study period and enrolled in the Care Coordination
                  Program.

               2. Control Dataset (Group 2): Those age 65 or older who are discharged from
                  Maimonides to home during the study period.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The exclusion criteria for this study for both the intervention &amp; control dataset is
             anybody who does not fall into the above inclusion category and anybody who was:

               1. Transferred on the day of discharge to another acute care hospital, admitted to a
                  hospital specialty unit, admitted to an inpatient rehabilitation facility, or
                  admitted to a long-term care hospital;

               2. Approached and declined to participate in the Care Coordination Program.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jessica S Ancker, MPH, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Melissa C Miller, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rainu Kaushal, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maimonides Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brooklyn</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11219</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brooklyn Health Information Exchange (BHIX)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brooklyn</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11220</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jencks SF, Williams MV, Coleman EA. Rehospitalizations among patients in the Medicare fee-for-service program. N Engl J Med. 2009 Apr 2;360(14):1418-28. doi: 10.1056/NEJMsa0803563. Erratum in: N Engl J Med. 2011 Apr 21;364(16):1582.</citation>
    <PMID>19339721</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Naylor MD, Brooten DA, Campbell RL, Maislin G, McCauley KM, Schwartz JS. Transitional care of older adults hospitalized with heart failure: a randomized, controlled trial. J Am Geriatr Soc. 2004 May;52(5):675-84. Erratum in: J Am Geriatr Soc. 2004 Jul;52(7):1228.</citation>
    <PMID>15086645</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coleman EA, Parry C, Chalmers S, Min SJ. The care transitions intervention: results of a randomized controlled trial. Arch Intern Med. 2006 Sep 25;166(17):1822-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17000937</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peikes D, Chen A, Schore J, Brown R. Effects of care coordination on hospitalization, quality of care, and health care expenditures among Medicare beneficiaries: 15 randomized trials. JAMA. 2009 Feb 11;301(6):603-18. doi: 10.1001/jama.2009.126.</citation>
    <PMID>19211468</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 26, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 27, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 24, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Health Information Technology</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Records, Personal</keyword>
  <keyword>Hospital Information Systems</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient Access to Records</keyword>
  <keyword>Medical Records</keyword>
  <keyword>Medical Record Systems, Computerized</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>A fully deidentified data set listing outcomes for the included patients is available by contacting the study PI (Jessica Ancker, jsa7002@med.cornell.edu)</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

