<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01447199</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DM94-060</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01447199</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Molecular Predisposition to Hereditary Nonpolyposis Colon Cancer (HNPCC)</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Molecular Predisposition to Hereditary Nonpolyposis Colon Cancer (HNPCC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to understand factors which may influence risk for colorectal and
      other cancers in families. These factors include genetic variability, in combination with
      diet and lifestyle. In order to achieve these goals, we need to contact as many eligible
      participants as possible.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      If you agree to take part in this study, you will have a single sample (8-10 teaspoons) of
      blood collected, depending upon current health status. The blood will be drawn at MD
      Anderson. If you cannot come to the clinic, a blood drawing kit will be sent to the your
      home, which will include instructions and a postage-paid return express mail envelope.
      Phlebotomy charges connected to this study will be paid by the study. The blood sample will
      be sent to a research laboratory at MD Anderson for analyses. If you are unwilling or unable
      to give a blood sample, you can give a saliva sample instead. In this case, a kit will be
      mailed to you with instructions for obtaining the saliva sample. A prepaid envelope will be
      included for its return. Participants who previously participated in Protocol PA11-0567 and
      provided a blood sample do not need to provide another blood sample. The previously stored
      blood sample collected by Protocol PA11-0567 may be used.

      You will be asked to answer a series of questions. These questions will ask about foods eaten
      either one year ago or one year before the first diagnosis of cancer. There will also be
      questions about cooking methods as well as overall health, and vitamin and medication use.
      Some of the questions are personal, but all answers will be kept strictly private.

      The questionnaire will be sent to your home via U.S. or express mail. It may take several
      hours to complete the survey, but there is no time limit on its completion. There are no
      right or wrong answers to the questions. A postage-paid return envelope will be provided for
      the return of the questionnaire.

      Solid tumor material and colonoscopy specimens of normal tissue will be collected from
      participants requiring either colonoscopy or surgery for routine clinical reasons. The tumor
      fragments will be collected from specimens. Tissue required for a clinical pathology
      diagnosis will not be used for research purposes.

      This is an investigational study. About 2,000 patients and family members will take part in
      this study. All will be enrolled at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 1994</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Family-Based</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Onset for Colorectal Cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>Overall study period up to 15 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Primary endpoint is time to onset for colorectal cancer using Cox proportional hazard regression for determining the role that polymorphic variants of genes have on risk for development of HNPCC at an early age.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Bladder Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Endometrial Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Kidney Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Skin Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Uterus Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Gene Mutation</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group with increased risk for developing colorectal and/or other cancers as the result of an inherited gene mutation, family history of cancer, or an early age of cancer onset.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Cancer History</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group with little/no personal or family history of cancer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Spouses</arm_group_label>
    <description>Spouses of those who may have an increased risk for developing colorectal and/or other cancers as the result of an inherited gene mutation, family history of cancer, or an early age of cancer onset, or little/no personal or family history of cancer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health and Diet Questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>Mailed questionnaires asking about foods eaten, cooking methods as well as overall health, and vitamin/medication use, taking several hours to complete.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Gene Mutation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>No Cancer History</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Spouses</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Survey</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Participants will have a single sample (8-10 teaspoons) of blood collected at M. D. Anderson,
      depending upon current health status. In the case of individuals not coming to the clinic, a
      blood drawing kit will be sent to the participant's home, which will include instructions and
      a postage-paid return express mail envelope. If participant unable or unwilling to give a
      blood sample, saliva samples can be collected instead.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Referrals from Departments of GI Oncology, GI Medicine and Nutrition, GI Surgery, GYN
        Oncology, Cancer Prevention and from the Genetic Counselors at UT MD Anderson Cancer
        Center, families and spouses.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. All patients with a new referral for a diagnosis of colorectal cancer (adenocarcinoma)
             and/or HNPCC-related cancers at the UTMDACC will be considered potentially eligible
             for this study regardless of prior treatment.

          2. Families maintained at the UTMDACC Hereditary Colon Cancer Registry that have a known
             germline mutation in a mismatch repair gene or contain two or more first degree
             relatives diagnosed with CRC and/or any HNPCC-related cancers, one of whom must be
             less than or equal to 50 years at diagnosis.

          3. First-degree and more distant relatives of individuals diagnosed with CRC and/or any
             HNPCC-related cancers from either of the groups in 1 and 2 (above).

          4. Any patient diagnosed with CRC and/or any HNPCC-related cancers less than or equal to
             45 years of age.

          5. Greater than or equal to age 18 at time of study.

          6. Able to provide informed consent to participate in this study indicating that they are
             aware of the investigational nature, in keeping with the policies of this hospital.

          7. Non-HNPCC quartets, defined as parents and two offspring who do not carry a mismatch
             repair gene mutation. These non-HNPCC quartets should have no personal history of
             cancer, nor cancer in any first degree relatives of the quartet members, nor history
             of trinucleotide repeat syndromes. Non-HNPCC parents in a quartet should be less than
             34 years old at the time the offspring were born.

          8. Lynch Syndrome patients identified and recruited through Protocol PA11-0567 who opt
             into Optional Procedure B, which consents the patient to participate in this study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of current major psychiatric disorder, per DSM-III-R (or DSM IV).

          2. Age less than 18 years at time of enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patrick Lynch, MD, JD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Patrick Lynch, MD, JD</last_name>
    <phone>713-794-5073</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>MD Anderson Health Information Specialist</last_name>
      <phone>877-632-6789</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 4, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 5, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 6, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bladder cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Colorectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Endometrial cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Kidney cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Skin cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Uterus cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Molecular Predisposition</keyword>
  <keyword>Hereditary Nonpolyposis Colon Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>HNPCC</keyword>
  <keyword>Molecular genetic testing</keyword>
  <keyword>Gene mutations</keyword>
  <keyword>Mutation analyses</keyword>
  <keyword>Genetic polymorphisms</keyword>
  <keyword>Family history of cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Early age of cancer onset</keyword>
  <keyword>Little/no personal or family history of cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Spouses</keyword>
  <keyword>Questionnaires</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood sample</keyword>
  <keyword>Saliva Sample</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colonic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endometrial Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Skin Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Disease Susceptibility</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms, Hereditary Nonpolyposis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uterine Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

