<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01441297</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCCCTS-10-525</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01441297</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BIBF 1120 as Second Line Treatment for Small Cell Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study Of BIBF 1120 as Second-line Treatment for Patients With Small Cell Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ji-youn Han</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Center, Korea</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cancer Center, Korea</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Although chemotherapy is the primary treatment option for small cell lung cancer (SCLC),
      longterm survival is rare. SCLC is initially chemosensitive, but rapidly relapses in a
      chemoresistant form with an overall survival of &lt;5%. Consequently, novel therapies are
      urgently required and will likely arise from an improved understanding of the disease
      biology. Some preclinical studies have showed that fibroblast growth factor-2 induces
      proliferation and
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chemotherapy is the primary treatment option for patients with small cell lung cancer (SCLC),
      leading to a 5-year survival of about 20% in limited disease (LD), and less than 5% in
      extensive disease (ED). Although initial tumor response rate to chemotherapy is very high (up
      to 96% for LD and up to 65% in ED), SCLC relapses in approximately 4 months in ED and 12
      months in LD. Despite the administration of second-line chemotherapy, the overall median
      survival of patients with limited and extensive disease is approximately 18 and 9 months,
      respectively. In the setting of second-line therapy, response rates to chemotherapy range
      between 15 and 25%, with median survival in the range of 4-6 months. Second-line therapeutic
      options include cyclophosphamide, doxorubicin and vincristine (CAV) given every 3 weeks or
      topotecan, which have similar response rates, time to progression and survival in the two
      treatment arms (topotecan 24%, 13 and 24.7 weeks; CAV 18%, 12 and 22 weeks, respectively).
      However, both treatments have substantial toxicities, with 9% of patients on trial
      withdrawing for toxicity reasons. Treatment-associated mortality was as high as 4.7%
      (possibly and definitely related), and many patients required transfusion support. Thus,
      while these treatments have acceptable activity second-line, more active and less toxic
      treatments are required for this patient population.

      The next generation of anti-angiogenic drugs aims to improve clinical efficacy by targeting
      multiple angiogenic factors. This approach was validated by a recent analysis of BIBF 1120,
      which inhibits vascular endothelial growth factor receptors (VEGFRs), platelet-derived growth
      factor receptors (PDGFRs) and the fibroblast growth factor receptors (FGFRs). BIBF 1120
      resulted in growth inhibition of tumours in syngeneic rats and human tumour xenografts in
      nude mice. It also displayed a favourable cellular duration of action and pharmacodynamic
      profile and was well-tolerated. These data complement early-phase clinical data suggesting
      that BIBF 1120 might be an effective anti-angiogenic agent. Some preclinical studies have
      showed that fibroblast growth factor-2 induces proliferation and chemoresistance in SCLC
      cells. In addition, the selective fibroblast growth factor receptor (FGFR) inhibitor PD173074
      blocks H-510 and H-69 SCLC proliferation and clonogenic growth in a dose-dependent fashion
      and prevents FGF-2-induced chemoresistance. BIBF1120 is a novel, orally available, potent
      triple angiokinase inhibitor that predominantly blocks the FGFR in addition to vascular
      endothelial growth factor (VEGF) and platelet-derived growth factor receptor (PDGFR).
      Therefore, the investigators will conduct a phase II trial to evaluate the efficacy of
      BIBF1120 in patients with recurrent SCLC.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 31, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 31, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>every 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the efficacy of BIBF1120 as second-line treatment in patients with recurrent small cell lung caner</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>every 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Survival time will be calculated from the date of study treatment start to the date of death (or date last seen).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>every 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Progression free survival will be calculated from the date of study treatment start to the first objective documentation of progressive disease or death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>every 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Safety will be evaluated by the frequency, severity, and relationship of adverse events graded by NCI Common Toxicity Criteria (CTC) version 4.0 that occur during the treatment and follow-up periods.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Small Cell Lung Cancer Recurrent</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>study arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BIBF 1120 study arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BIBF 1120</intervention_name>
    <description>BIBF 1120 200mg bid, PO, daily until PD</description>
    <arm_group_label>study arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically confirmed SCLC

          2. Progression during or after prior first line chemotherapy.

          3. At least one target tumor lesion RECIST 1.1)

          4. Life expectancy of at least three months

          5. ECOG PS 0-2

          6. Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous therapy with other VGFR inhibitors (other than bevacizumab)

          2. Persistence of clinically relevant therapy related toxicities from previous
             chemotherapy and/or radiotherapy

          3. Chemo-, hormone-, immunotherapy with monoclonal antibodies, treatment with tyrosine
             kinase inhibitors, or radiotherapy (except for brain and extremities) within the past
             3 weeks prior to treatment with the trial drug i.e., the minimum time elapsed since
             the last anticancer therapy and the first administration of BIBF 1120 must be 3 weeks

          4. Treatment with other investigational drugs or treatment in another clinical trial
             within the past three weeks before start of therapy or concomitantly with this trial

          5. Concomitant yellow fever vaccination

          6. Uncontrolled brain metastases, spinal cord compression, carcinomatous meningitis, or
             leptomeningeal disease. Patients should have completed surgery or radiation therapy
             for existing brain metastases, should not have documented increase in size over the
             previous 3 months and should be asymptomatic off steroids

          7. Radiographic evidence of cavitary or necrotic tumors

          8. Centrally located tumors with radiographic evidence (CT or MRI) of local invasion of
             major blood vessels

          9. History of clinically significant haemoptysis within the past 3 months (more than one
             teaspoon of fresh blood per day)

         10. Therapeutic anticoagulation (except low dose heparin and/or heparin flush as needed
             for maintenance of an indwelling intravenous device) or antiplatelet therapy (except
             for chronic low-dose therapy with acetylsalicylic acid ≤325mg per day)

         11. History of major thrombotic or clinically relevant major bleeding event in the past 6
             months

         12. Known inherited predisposition to bleeding or thrombosis

         13. Significant cardiovascular diseases (i.e., hypertension not controlled by medical
             therapy, unstable angina, history of myocardial infarction within the past 12 months,
             congestive heart failure &gt; NYHA II, serious cardiac arrhythmia, pericardial effusion)

         14. Calculated creatinine clearance by Cockcroft Gault &lt;45ml/min

         15. Proteinuria CTCAE grade 2 or greater

         16. Total bilirubin above the upper limit of normal

         17. ALT and/or AST &gt; 2.5 x upper limit of normal in the presence of live metastasis or ALT
             and/or AST &gt;1.5 x upper limit of normal in patients without liver metastasis.

         18. Prothrombin time and/or partial thromboplastin time greater than 50% deviation from
             normal limits

         19. Platelets &lt;100000 platelets/μL (=mm3)

         20. Significant weight loss (&gt; 10 %) within the past 6 weeks prior to treatment in the
             present trial

         21. Current peripheral neuropathy ≥ CTCAE(version4.0) Grade 2 except due to trauma

         22. Pre-existing ascites and/or clinically significant pleural effusion

         23. Major injuries and/or surgery within the past ten days prior to randomization with
             incomplete wound healing

         24. Serious infections requiring systemic antibiotic (e.g. antiviral, antimicrobial,
             antifungal) therapy

         25. Gastrointestinal disorders or abnormalities that would interfere with absorption of
             the study drug

         26. Active or chronic hepatitis C and/or B infection

         27. Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) seropositivity

         28. serious illness or concomitant non-oncological disease or

         29. Pregnancy or breast feeding

         30. Active alcohol or drug abuse

         31. Other malignancy within the past three years

         32. Hypersensitivity to BIBF 1120 and/or the excipients of the trial drugs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ji-Youn Han, PhD.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Center, Korea</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Goyang-si</city>
        <state>Gyeonggi-do</state>
        <zip>410-769</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 23, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 26, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 27, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National Cancer Center, Korea</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ji-youn Han</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head, Center for Lung Cancer</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>recurrent small cell lung cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Small Cell Lung Carcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nintedanib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

