<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01445483</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>080214</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>08-C-0214</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01445483</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00769444</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neuropsychological Changes in Patients Receiving Radiation Therapy for Brain Metastases</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study to Evaluate Neuropsychological Outcome Measures and Their Relationship With Prognosis in Patients Receiving Radiation Therapy for Brain Metastases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  There are no standardized sets of tests to measure changes in neuropsychological
           functioning in patients treated for brain metastasis (cancer that has spread beyond the
           original site to the brain).

        -  Neuropsychological function has an important effect on quality of life and should be
           included when determining treatment options.

      Objectives:

        -  To find out if there is a change in patients cognitive (thinking) and daily functioning
           after standard radiation treatment for brain metastasis that can be measured with tests.

        -  To see if any changes on these tests are related to patients response to radiation
           therapy.

      Eligibility:

      - Patients 18 years of age or older who have cancer that has spread to the brain.

      Design:

        -  Patients receive a 2-week course of radiation therapy to the brain, given daily 5 days a
           week. Some patients may require stereotactic radiosurgery (an additional boost of
           radiation therapy to specific sites of brain metastasis).

        -  Patients have the following evaluations before and after treatment to determine changes
           in cognition and functioning:

        -  Neuropsychological testing to measure cognitive (thinking) abilities like memory,
           attention, processing speed, and reading, and fine motor skills.

        -  Questionnaires to assess quality of life and daily living skills.

        -  Patients have MRI scans and blood and urine tests.

        -  At the completion of radiation treatment, patients return to the clinic for follow-up
           visits at 1, 2, 4, 6, 9 and 12 months for blood and urine tests, physical examination,
           MRI of the brain, neuropsychological testing and assessments of quality of life and
           daily living skills.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Metastatic brain tumors occur more frequently than primary brain tumors and occur in
           approximately 25 percent of patients who die of cancer each year.

        -  The Radiation Therapy Oncology Group (RTOG) developed three prognostic classes using a
           recursive partitioning analysis (RPA) of a large database. Theses classes are based on
           Karnofsky Performance Status (KPS), age and disease status.

        -  The RTOG RPA classes do not include neuropsychological function as a measure of outcome.

        -  There is no consensus of standardization of test selection to measure changes in
           neuropsychological functioning in this patient population.

        -  Neuropsychological function has an important effect on quality of life and should be
           included when determining prognosis and treatment options for patients.

        -  Neuropsychological functioning is important when determining the effects of treatments
           and for measuring outcomes in clinical trials.

      Objectives:

        -  To identify the neuropsychological test scores which detect significant change in
           neuropsychological functioning in patients receiving radiation therapy for brain
           metastases.

        -  To examine the relationship between neuropsychological function and survival in patients
           receiving radiation therapy for brain metastases.

      Eligibility:

        -  Patients age 18 years and older.

        -  Pathologically confirmed primary malignancy with at least one intraparenchymal brain
           metastasis as identified on brain MRI scan with intravenous contrast.

        -  The patient must communicate in English in order to complete the neuropsychological
           evaluations.

      Design:

        -  This is a longitudinal study that will administer serial neuropsychological assessments
           to patients with brain metastases who receive radiation therapy.

        -  Patients will undergo a battery of neuropsychological tests prior to radiotherapy (WBRT
           or WBRT followed by SRS), and then after radiation at one month post-baseline (2 weeks
           after radiation therapy), then at 3, and 6 months, and then every 3 months for up to 12
           months after baseline.

        -  The test battery will involve approximately 40 minutes of direct cognitive testing and
           15 minutes of questionnaires.

      There will be three cohorts of 20 patients each for a total of 60 patients. The three cohorts
      will be made up of differing histologies and will be sorted on the basis of their RTOG RPA
      Class.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 15, 2008</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To identify the neuropsychological test scores which detect significant change in neuropsychological functioning in patients receiving radiation therapy for brain metastases.</measure>
    <time_frame>Completion of study</time_frame>
    <description>To identify the neuropsychological test scores which detect significant change in neuropsychological functioning in patients receiving radiation therapy for brain metastases.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To examine the relationship between neuropsychological function and survival in patients receiving radiation therapy for brain metastases</measure>
    <time_frame>Completion of study</time_frame>
    <description>To examine the relationship between neuropsychological function and survival in patients receiving radiation therapy for brain metastases</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To further examine whether other measures from the following battery detect significant change in neuropsychological function or predict prognosis in this patient population.</measure>
    <time_frame>Completion of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To examine the relationship between the RTOG RPA classification for brain metastasis survival and baseline neuropsychological functioning.</measure>
    <time_frame>Completion of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To examine the strengths and weaknesses in neuropsychological functioning of patients with brain metastases after radiation therapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>Completion of Study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To explore the neuropsychological functioning of patients with brain metastases treated with different therapies (e.g. chemotherapy, corticosteroids, complete surgical resection).</measure>
    <time_frame>Completion of Study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To investigate the relationship between neuropsychological functioning, brain lesions (e.g., number and volume), MRI abnormalities, biomarkers, and disease progression or recurrence.</measure>
    <time_frame>Completion of Study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To investigate the role of biomarkers, including neuron specific enolase (NSE), S100B, MMPs and VEGF as potential markers of brain injury and disease progression in the serum, plasma and urine of patients with brain metastases.</measure>
    <time_frame>Completion of Study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To gather baseline neuropsychological data on patients with brain metastases for use as a reference in the development of new clinical trials involving this patient population in the ROB.</measure>
    <time_frame>Completion of Study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Metastasis</condition>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Primary clinical
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Patients must be 18 years of age or older.

          2. Pathologically confirmed primary malignancy with at least one intraparenchymal brain
             metastasis as identified on brain MRI scan with intravenous contrast.

               -  Cohort 1 (N=20): KPS greater than 70; Age less than or equal to 65; controlled
                  primary tumor and no extracranial metastases.

               -  Cohort 2 (N=20): KPS greater than 70 and at least one of the following: age
                  greater than 65, uncontrolled or synchronous primary disease, or extracranial
                  metastases

               -  Cohort 3 (N=20): KPS less than 70

          3. Patient must have a primary medical or surgical oncologist in the community or at NCI
             who is willing to collaborate with the ROB staff in the clinical management of the
             patient.

          4. All patients must sign a document of informed consent indicating their understanding
             of the investigational nature and the risks of this study BEFORE any of the protocol
             related studies are preformed (this does not include routine laboratory tests or
             imaging studies required to establish eligibility).

          5. Subjects of childbearing or child- fathering potential must be willing to use a
             medically acceptable form of birth control, which includes abstinence, while they are
             being treated on this study.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Cognitively impaired patients who cannot give informed consent, including patients
             assigned a power of attorney for medical decisions.

          2. Inability to communicate in the English language.

          3. Pre- existing or active psychiatric or neurologic impairments, not caused by the brain
             metastasis, which, in the opinion of the investigators, will interfere with the proper
             administration or completion of the protocol.

          4. Prior Therapy

               -  Patients must not have been treated for a previous brain metastasis.

               -  Patients must not have had previous cranial radiation.

               -  Patients must not undergo treatment with an investigational drug for the primary
                  disease within 7 days of baseline neuropsychological testing.

               -  Patients must not receive systemic therapy within 7 days prior to baseline
                  neuropsychological testing.

               -  Patients who have had surgery for their current brain metastasis must wait at
                  least 7 days before baseline neuropsychological testing.

          5. Concurrent Therapy

               -  Treatment of primary malignancy with systemic therapy (chemotherapy or biologic
                  agents) cannot be delivered concurrently with the treatment of the intracranial
                  disease. However, treatment of the primary site with local therapy, either
                  surgery or radiotherapy, can be performed concurrently with the treatment of the
                  intracranial disease.

               -  Patients receiving glucocorticoids should be tapered to the lowest possible dose,
                  or stopped altogether, by the treating physician. If glucocorticoid dose is
                  adjusted or given for the first time, the patient must remain on stable dose of
                  glucocorticoids for at least 24 hours prior to initial neurocognitive testing, CT
                  and MR imaging.

          6. Patients needing emergent radiation therapy for their brain metastases will be
             excluded

          7. Patients must not have evidence of leptomeningeal metastases.

          8. Patients must not be HIV positive.

          9. Other medical conditions deemed by the PI or associates to make the patient ineligible
             for protocol investigations.

         10. Pregnant or breast-feeding females are excluded because of the potential mutagenic
             effects on a developing fetus or newborn.

         11. Clinically significant unrelated systemic illness which in the judgment of the
             Principal or Associate Investigator would compromise the patient s ability to tolerate
             this therapy or are likely to interfere with the study procedures or results.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>DeeDee K Smart, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Theresa Cooley-Zgela, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(240) 760-6207</phone>
    <email>theresa.cooleyzgela@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>DeeDee K Smart, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-5457</phone>
    <email>ds526v@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact National Cancer Institute Referral Office</last_name>
      <phone>(888) NCI-1937</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2008-C-0214.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson JD, Young B. Demographics of brain metastasis. Neurosurg Clin N Am. 1996 Jul;7(3):337-44. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8823767</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Posner JB. Management of brain metastases. Rev Neurol (Paris). 1992;148(6-7):477-87. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1448668</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wen PY, Loeffler JS. Brain metastases. Curr Treat Options Oncol. 2000 Dec;1(5):447-58. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12057152</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 29, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 30, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 30, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 3, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 4, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiation</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuropsychological Outcome</keyword>
  <keyword>Metastasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain Metastasis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasm Metastasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

