<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01447563</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CLOPI Tabs No. 60-06</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01447563</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparative Bioavailability Study of Two Oral Formulations of Clopidogrel</brief_title>
  <official_title>Bioavailability of Two Oral Formulations of Clopidogrel: A Randomized, Open Label, Single Dose, Two-Period, Crossover Comparison in Healthy Mexican Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Clopidogrel, a potent inhibitor of adenosine diphosphate-induced platelet
      activation, is widely used to prevent and reduce the risk of thrombotic events. Objective:
      the aim of the present study is to evaluate the bioequivalence of two oral formulations of 75
      mg clopidogrel tablets. Method: The study is an open, randomized, single-dose, two-period
      crossover trial conducted on 32 healthy Mexican volunteers in a fasted state. A single oral
      dose of the test or reference drug will be followed by a 7 day washout period, after which
      subjects will receive the alternative formulation. Blood samples were collected up to 24 h
      after dosing. In order to determine bioequivalence, the plasma concentrations of clopidogrel
      carboxylic acid metabolite was determined using high-performance liquid chromatography-tandem
      mass spectrometry area under the plasma concentration time curve from zero to the last
      quantifiable level (AUC0-t), area under the plasma concentration time curve extrapolated to
      infinity (AUC0-∞), maximum plasma concentration (Cmax), the plasma elimination half-life
      (Tmax) and plasma half-life (T1/2) were calculated for both formulations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study procedure In each period, the subjects arrived at the clinical/unit site on the day
      before the commencement of the study and were randomized using Excel® 2007 to receive the
      test formulation followed by the reference formulation, or viceversa. No food was allowed
      from 10 h before until at least 4 h after drug administration. On the subsequent morning, a
      peripheral venous 21G catheter was inserted in the antecubital vein of the subjects and blood
      samples were collected (zero time). The subjects then received a single 75 mg tablet of
      either the test or the reference formulation, given with 250 mL water. Blood samples were
      collected at 0.16, 0.33, 0.5, 0.66, 0.83, 1, 1.5, 1.75, 2, 2.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16 and 24 h
      after drug administration. The blood samples were collected in coded EDTA tubes and plasma
      was obtained by centrifugation (2,053 g for 10 min at 5 C), after which the plasma was
      immediately transferred to prelabeled vials and stored at or below -70 After a week of
      washout, the alternative formulation was administered to the subjects and samples were drawn
      and analyzed as before.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>maximum plasma concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 0.16, 0.33, 0.5, 0.66, 0.83, 1, 1.5, 1.75, 2, 2.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16 and 24 h after drug administration</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>area under the plasma concentration time curve from zero to the last quantifiable level (AUC0-t),</measure>
    <time_frame>0.16, 0.33, 0.5, 0.66, 0.83, 1, 1.5, 1.75, 2, 2.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16 and 24 h after drug administration</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>area under the plasma concentration time curve extrapolated to infinity (AUC0-∞)</measure>
    <time_frame>at 0.16, 0.33, 0.5, 0.66, 0.83, 1, 1.5, 1.75, 2, 2.5, 3, 6, 8, 12, 16 and 24 h after drug administration</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Comparative Bioavailability of Clopidogrel Tablets</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Clopidogrel tablets 75mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subjects received a single 75 mg tablet of the reference formulation, given with 250 mL water</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Clopidogrel</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subjects received a single 75 mg tablet of the test formulation, given with 250 mL water</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clopidogrel bisulfate</intervention_name>
    <description>subjects received a single 75 mg tablet of the reference formulation, given with 250 mL water</description>
    <arm_group_label>Clopidogrel tablets 75mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Plavix</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clopidogrel</intervention_name>
    <description>subjects received a single 75 mg tablet of the test formulation, given with 250 mL water</description>
    <arm_group_label>Clopidogrel</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female and age is between 18 and 40 years, inclusive.

          2. Females must have negative results for pregnancy tests performed:at Screening on a
             urine specimen obtained within 2 weeks prior to initial study drug administration, and
             prior to dosing on urine sample obtained on Study Day -1 of each period

          3. Body Mass Index (BMI) is 19 to 26, inclusive. BMI is calculated as weight in kg
             divided by the square of height measured in meters.

          4. A condition of general good health, based upon the results of a medical history,
             physical examination, vital signs, laboratory profile and a 12-lead electrocardiogram
             (ECG).

          5. Must voluntarily sign and date each informed consent, approved by an Independent
             Ethics Committee (IEC)/Institutional Review Board (IRB), prior to the initiation of
             any screening or study-specific procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of significant sensitivity to any drug.

          2. Requirement for any over-the-counter and/or prescription medication, vitamins and/or
             herbal supplements, on a regular basis.

          3. Use of any medications, vitamins and/or herbal supplements, within the 1-week period
             prior to study drug administration.

          4. Pregnant or breastfeeding female.

          5. Recent (6-month) history of drug or alcohol abuse.

          6. Positive test result for hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) or HIV antibodies (HIV
             Ab). Negative HIV status will be confirmed at Screening and the results will be
             maintained confidentially by the study site.

          7. Use of known inhibitors (e.g., ketoconazole) or inducers (e.g., carbamazepine) of
             cytochrome P450 3A (CYP3A) within 1 month prior to study drug administration.

          8. Positive screen for drugs of abuse, or alcohol or nicotine or positive and clinically
             significant urine adulterants test.

          9. Receipt of any drug by injection within 30 days or within a period defined by 5
             half-lives, whichever is longer, prior to study drug administration.

         10. History of epilepsy, any clinically significant cardiac, respiratory (except mild
             asthma), renal, hepatic, gastrointestinal, hematologic or psychiatric disease or
             disorder, or any uncontrolled medical illness.

         11. History of gastric surgery, vagotomy, bowel resection or any surgical procedure that
             might interfere with gastrointestinal motility, pH or absorption.

         12. Donation or loss of 550 mL or more blood volume (including plasmapheresis) or receipt
             of a transfusion of any blood product within 8 weeks prior to study drug
             administration.

         13. Receipt of any investigational product within 8 weeks prior to study drug
             administration or 7 half-lives, whichever is longer.

         14. Consumption of alcohol within the 3-day period prior to study drug administration.

         15. Consumption of grapefruit or grapefruit products, Seville oranges, star fruit and
             quinine/tonic water from 3 days prior to study drug administration.

         16. Use of tobacco or nicotine-containing products within the 6-month period preceding
             study drug administration.

         17. Current enrollment in another clinical study.

         18. Consideration by the investigator, for an reason, that the subject is an unsuitable
             candidate to receive Ibuprofen
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lourdes Garza Ocañas, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Universitario Jose E Gonzalez</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Departamento de Farmacologia y Toxicologia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Monterrey</city>
        <state>Nuevo Leon</state>
        <zip>64460</zip>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 4, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 5, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 6, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 5, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 5, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 6, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lourdes Garza Ocañas</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bioequivalence</keyword>
  <keyword>Bioavailability</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Clopidogrel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ticlopidine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

