<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01447823</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KEK-ZH Nr 2011-0192</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01447823</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Observational Field Study of Acute Esophageal Food Bolus Impaction by Mean Esophageal Manometry and 24h-pH-monitoring</brief_title>
  <official_title>Observational Field Study of Acute Esophageal Food Bolus Impaction by Mean Esophageal Manometry and 24h-pH-monitoring</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Zurich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Zurich</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to evaluate standard investigations performed in patients with bolus
      impaction in a prospective observational field study. In bolus impaction, ingested food
      boluses have to be endoscopically removed. Oesophageal narrowing by scar tissue caused by
      reflux disease or motility disorders are possible causes of bolus impaction. How common these
      causes are has up to date never been investigated. The discovery of eosinophilic oesophagitis
      has broadened differential diagnosis of bolus impaction. Currently high resolution
      oesophageal manometry and 24-hour pHmetry are performed in addition to endoscopy in the
      assessment of bolus impaction at the University Hospital Zurich.

      The collection of these examination results is the aim of this prospective unrandomised
      observational field study to assess weather the currently applied procedures are valid to
      diagnose the cause of impaction to find optimal therapy for each patient.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The key function of the esophagus ist (i) the immediate transport of the food bolus from the
      mouth to the stomach and (ii) to inhibit reflux from the stomach back to the esophagus.

      Motility disorders of the esophagus lead to an impaired bolus transport and/or reflux of
      stomach content to the esophagus, and may cause symptoms such as (obstructive) dysphagia,
      chest pain, heart burn and/or regurgitation.

      Acute esophageal food impaction is a common acute condition of the upper GI tract that
      usually needs immediate medical attention. The food bolus, e.g. a peace of red meat or
      similar is blocked within the tubular part of the esophagus, e.g. proximal to the
      esophagogastric junction and neither passes spontaneously into the stomach nor can be
      regurgitated actively. In this case it usually requires upper endoscopy for endoscopic
      removal of the food bolus.

      Possible causes of food impaction are (i) structural obstruction within the esophagus such as
      a Schatzki's ring, an esophageal web, a peptic stenosis secondary to gastroesophageal reflux
      disease, or more rarely esophageal carcinoma [1, 2]; (ii) functional causes of obstruction
      are mainly Achalasia or Esophageal Esophagitis (EE). In Achalasia a idiopathic
      neurodegenerative destruction of the inhibitory neurons of the esophagus leads to a failure
      of the lower esophageal sphincter to relax and an impaired esophageal peristalsis. Patients
      usually present with a history of progressive dysphagia and regurgitation of undigested food,
      but rarely a food impaction can occur [3]. Eosinophilic Esophagitis is a idiopathic disorder
      in which eosinophilic infiltration of the mucosal wall leads to an impaired esophageal
      motility, which usually causes dysphagia, retrosternal pain or food bolus impaction.[3] Its
      etiology remains unknown but several studies suggest an allergic response to food and
      allergens. Previously believed to be a rather rare disease and therefore rare cause for bolus
      impaction, eosinophilic esophagitis has emerged as one of the most common causes for food
      impaction and dysphagia in general [4]. The increase in prevalence is not entirely clear;
      besides better recognition by gastroenterologists and pathologists there seems to be a true
      increase in incidence, probably due to an increased incidence of allergic diseases [5]. Its
      diagnosis is difficult due to other causes of eosinophilic infiltrate such as
      gastroesophageal reflux disease or eosinophilic gastroenteritis[3].

      The reason for an impaired motility in EE is unknown, although several hypothetic mechanisms
      are discussed [6]: (i) increased contraction of fibroblast secondary to presence of
      eosinophilic granulocytes, (ii) axonal necrosis secondary to eosinophilic degradation (iii)
      binding of eosinophil derived MBP (major basic protein) to muscarinic acetylcholine receptors
      leading to increased contraction.

      The true prevalence of eosinophilic esophagitis in patients with food impaction remains
      unknown. Desai et al evaluated 31 patients with acute bolus impaction of which more than 50%
      had an increased count of intraesophageal eosinophils per high power field [4]. However, the
      true share of EE remains unclear. Especially the amount of patients with eosinophilic
      infiltrate due to gastroesophageal reflux is not defined (half of all patients had PPI before
      endoscopy).

      The current clinical standard of care for patients with food bolus impaction at the Division
      of Gastroenterology at the University Hospital Zurich includes

        1. endoscopy to i) remove the food bolus; ii) take esophageal, gastric and duodenal
           biopsies to assess histological abnormalities and iii) assess structural causes for
           obstruction;

        2. a high resolution esophageal manometry (HRM) to assess esophageal motility;

        3. an ambulatory intraesophageal pH-monitoring to asses esophageal acid exposure and

        4. venous blood sampling to assess eosinophilic count in peripheral blood.

      These procedures are considered to be both i) necessary as well as ii) sufficient and
      accurate to elucidate the true cause of bolus impaction [3]. Our aim is now to objectify this
      standard procedure of care in an open, prospective, observational, unrandomized field study.
      It is important to mention that all procedures have been and are indicated in this situation
      as current standard procedure of care to assess patients with bolus impaction; they should be
      performed whether the patient is included in our field study or not. Therefore participation
      in the study does not lead to any additional diagnostic or therapeutic
      procedures/interventions
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>August 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Motility Disorders</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients undergoing upper endoscopy for removal of a food bolus are asked to sign the
        standard clinical informed consent form for interventional endoscopy of the Division of
        Gastroenterology at the University Hospital Zurich. After Diagnosis of food impaction has
        been made, the food bolus has been removed and the endoscopy has been completed, the
        patient will be informed of the Diagnosis and the standard procedure of care (High
        resolution manometry, pH-monitoring, blood sampling) will be explained, and an appointment
        for these procedures will be given (1-4days thereafter).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Patients with acute esophageal bolus impaction coming to the emergency unit of the
             University Hospital Zurich needing emergency endoscopy for bolus removal

          -  Age &gt; 18 years

          -  Informed consent

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Age under 18 years

          -  Inability to understand the informed consent form
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>01 Studienregister MasterAdmins</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>UniversitaetsSpital Zuerich</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Fried, Professor, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital Zurich, Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Andreas Steingoetter</last_name>
    <phone>+41 (0)44 255 5684</phone>
    <email>andreas.steingoetter@usz.ch</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Michael Fried, Professor, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+41 (0)44 255 2401</phone>
    <email>michael.fried@usz.ch</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Zurich, Gastroenterology and Hepatology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zurich</city>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 27, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 5, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 6, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 7, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 7, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 12, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Oesophageal bolus obstruction</keyword>
  <keyword>Gastroscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>phmetry</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Motility Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Spasm, Diffuse</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

