<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00535314</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RTA 402-C-0704</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00535314</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Two Dose Levels of RTA 402 in Patients With Advanced Malignant Melanoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Phase II, Randomized, Open Label Trial of 2 Dose Levels of RTA 402 in Patients With Advanced Malignant Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Reata Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Reata Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of the study is to determine the proportion of patients without
      progression at 6-months in patients with unresectable Stage III or Stage IV melanoma who are
      taking RTA 402.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase II, open label, randomized study in patients with unresectable Stage III or
      Stage IV malignant melanoma. Patients will be randomly assigned to two different doses of RTA
      402 administered orally once daily for 28 consecutive days, for up to 18 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the proportion of patients without progression at 6 months in patients with unresectable Stage III or Stage IV melanoma treated with RTA 402.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the overall response rate and duration of responses</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RTA 402 Dose1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose1 of RTA 402 to be administered orally once daily for 28 consecutive days, for up to 18 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RTA 402 Dose2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose2 of RTA 402 to be administered orally once daily for 28 consecutive days, for up to 18 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RTA 402 Dose1</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>RTA 402 Dose1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RTA 402 Dose2</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>RTA 402 Dose2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Greater than or equal to 18 years of age

          -  Confirmed diagnosis of malignant (unresectable Stage III or Stage IV) melanoma

          -  Measurable disease, defined as at least 1 lesion which measures more than or equal to
             20 mm by conventional techniques, or more than or equal to 10 mm by spiral CT scan, or
             cutaneous lesion of greater than or equal to 10 mm by caliper.

          -  May have received no more than 1 prior chemotherapy for metastatic disease.

          -  May have received prior vaccine therapy in the adjuvant setting.

          -  May have received cytokine therapy in the adjuvant setting and/or 1 prior cytokine
             therapy for metastatic disease.

          -  ECOG performance of 0-1

          -  Must have adequate liver and renal function documented by laboratory test results.

          -  Must have adequate bone marrow function documented by lab results.

          -  Must have completed any prior chemotherapy, immunotherapy, radiation, biological, or
             other investigational cancer therapy at least 4 weeks prior to starting this study,
             and have recovered from all acute side effects. Patients receiving mitomycin C or
             nitrosoureas must be 6 weeks from the last administration of chemotherapy.

          -  Man or woman must agree to practice effective contraception during the study and for
             at least 2 months after the last dose of RTA 402.

          -  Must have life expectancy of more than 3 months.

          -  Must be willing and able to sign the informed consent form.

          -  Must be willing and able to take and document oral doses of RTA 402.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  May have received no more than 1 prior chemotherapy.

          -  May have received no more than 1 prior cytokine therapy for metastatic disease.

          -  Diagnosis of ocular melanoma.

          -  Inability to swallow tablets or capsules

          -  Symptomatic malabsorptive disorder (eg, Crohn's Disease), or removal of either the
             terminal ileus or more than 2/3 of the small intestine.

          -  Active brain metastases or primary central nervous system malignancies; patients with
             a previously treated brain metastasis may be included provided that there is no
             requirement for steroids and no evidence for progression for greater than or equal to
             8 weeks after treatment.

          -  Active second malignancy.

          -  Weight loss greater than or equal to 10% over the 6 weeks prior to dosing

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding

          -  Clinically significant illnesses which could compromise participation in the study,
             including: uncontrolled diabetes; active or uncontrolled infection; acute or chronic
             liver disease; confirmed diagnosis of HIV infection; uncontrolled hypertension,
             symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, myocardial infarction
             within the last 6 months, or uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmia.

          -  Psychiatric illness that would limit compliance with study requirements.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 24, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 24, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 26, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 27, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 27, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 29, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Melanoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

