<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00539877</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2004-05-017</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00539877</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase I Study of Interperitoneal Chenotherapy in Patients With Gastric Adenocarainoma With Peritoneal Seeding</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Study of Interperitoneal Chenotherapy in Patients With Gastric Adenocarainoma With Peritoneal Seeding</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Samsung Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Samsung Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Stomach cancer is the most common cancer, and is still leading cause of death in Korea.
      Peritoneal seeding is the most common metastases of gastric cancer, and is the most frequent
      cause of death from this disease. In addition, there is no standard treatment for peritoneal
      dissemination. Even though systemic intravenous chemotherapy is the standard treatment for
      metastatic stomach cancer at present, it does not improve the survival of patients with
      peritoneal dissemination. Because intraperitoneal(IP) administration results in high
      concentration locally with low systemic toxicity, clinical investigators have confirmed the
      safety and pharmacokinetic advantage associated with IP delivery of a number of
      antineoplastic agents with known activity in cancer. In ovarian cancer, a large randomized
      trial demonstrated a small but statistically and clinically significant survival advantage
      for women receiving a portion of their therapy intraperitoneally. Drugs such as
      5-fluorouracil, cisplatin, mitomycin-C, paclitaxel and docetaxel are used for IP chemotherapy
      in patients with gastric cancer. Even the small number of phase III trials reported, some
      studies showed improvement in survival for patients randomized to IP therapy compared to
      those receiving no postoperative treatment.
      Irinotecan(7-ethyl-10-[4-(1-pipperidino)-1-piperidino] carbonyloxy camptothecin; CPT-11),
      clinically effective in the treatment of colorectal, lung and gastric cancer, is a carbamate
      prodrug metabolized to its active metabolite, 7-ethyl-10-hydroxycamptothecin (SN-38). In
      mouse model, IP administration of CPT-11 was significantly more effective than intravenous
      administration for control of both peritoneal seeding and liver metastasis. However,
      phamacokinetics of CPT-11 with peritoneal administration in human beings is not well studied.
      Although Japanese investigators reported pharmacokinetic data of CPT-11 with few patients,
      there is no data about maximum tolerated dose of CPT-11 intraperitoneally.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives : The objectives of this study are to assess the feasibility, to determine the
      maximum tolerated dose, and to assess the toxicities of intraperitoneally administered CPT-11
      in gastric cancer patients with peritoneal seeding.

      Methods : This is open-labeled, non-randomized phase I study in the patients eligible for the
      following criteria. Patients more than 18 years old with gastric adenocarcinoma,
      histologically proven, will be enrolled at the time of surgery, and the signed informed
      consent will be obtained prior to surgery. Preoperative studies should have resectable
      advanced disease. The operative finding and biopsy of suspected peritoneum must show
      peritoneal involvement of adenocarcinoma. The subjects should not have any previous
      chemotherapy, immunotherapy or radiotherapy and any major biological abnormalities. Prior to
      the initiation of study, patient will receive palliative gastrectomy(total or subtotal) and
      has a CAPD catheter. Postoperative day 1, IP chemotherapy will be given by CAPD catheter. For
      dose level 1, CPT-11(provided by CJ Pharmaceutical Company) 50mg/m2 in 1L of normal saline,
      prewarmed to 37°C will be given intraperitoneally. Plasma samples will be collected prior IP
      chemotherapy, and samples of plasma, peritoneal fluid and urine will be obtained at 0.5, 1.5,
      2, 3.5, 8, 12, and 25.5, 49, 56 hours following chemotherapy. Three patients will be accrued
      to each dose level. If none of these three patients experienced a dose-limiting toxicity
      (DLT), the dose will be increased in a subsequent group of three patients to 100 mg/m2.If one
      of the first three patients experienced DLT, three more patients will be accrued to that dose
      level. If none of these additional three patients experienced DLT, then the dose will be
      escalated. If one of the additional three patients experienced DLT, then either an additional
      cohort of patients could be added or escalation terminated. If two or more of the second
      group of three patients experienced DLT, then accrual is stopped. If two of the first three
      patients experienced DLT, then an additional three patients could be accrued at that dose
      level, but dose escalation could take place only if none of the additional cohort experienced
      DLT. The last planned dose escalation is to 300 mg/m2. Cohorts of at least 3 patients will be
      entered at each dose level and monitored for at least 4 weeks after treatment before dose
      escalation. Intrapatient dose escalation is not permitted.

      Dose level Dose of IP CPT-11(mg/m2)

        1. 50

        2. 100

        3. 150

        4. 200

        5. 300

      In this study, DLT is defined as follows: any grade 4 non-hematologic toxicity or as noted
      below; ≥ grade 3 diarrhea or stomatitis lasting ≥ 7 days despite optimal supportive care;
      hematologic dose-limiting toxicity is defined grade 4 neutropenia complicated by fever ≥
      38°C; grade 4 hemorrhage or thrombocytopenia; failure to recover neutrophils (≥ 1500/ mm3) or
      platelets (≥ 100 000/ mm3) by day 28. The maximal tolerated dose is defined as that dose
      level that produced dose-limiting toxicity in ≥ 50% of patients. The recommended dose is one
      level below that. During the study, the evaluation of toxicities will be done daily of
      postoperative 6 days then weekly using National Cancer Institute-Common Toxicity Criteria
      (NCI-CTC). Physical examination, complete blood count, and blood chemistry, and serum
      electrolytes will be measured. Pharmacokinetic study : Plasma, peritoneal fluid and urine
      samples will be assayed for irinotecan and its metabolites: SN-38,
      7-ethyl-10-[4-N-(5-aminopentanoic acid)-1-piperidino] carbonyl camptothecin (APC), and SN-38
      glucuronide(SN-38G).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2006</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The objectives of this study are to assess the feasibility, to determine the maximum tolerated dose, and to assess the toxicities of intraperitoneally administered CPT-11 in gastric cancer patients with peritoneal seeding.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">17</enrollment>
  <condition>Stomach Neoplasms</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>irinotecan</intervention_name>
    <description>Postoperative day 1, IP CPT-11 chemotherapy will be given by CAPD catheter. CPT-11 in 1L of normal saline, prewarmed to 37°C will be given intraperitoneally.
If there is no DLT and patients agree with the treatment, patients can receive 3 more times of IP chemotherapy with same dose of CPT-11 at 3 weeks interval. After total 4 cycles of IP chemotherapy, peritoneal disease will be reassessed with abdominal-pelvis CT. Pharmacokinetic study is not planned with this treatment.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:Patients will be eligible for the following criteria are met;

          -  Histologic diagnosis of gastric adenocarcinoma

          -  Preoperative studies of resectable disease; endoscopic finding of advanced gastric
             cancer, radiologic finding of T3 or T4 disease with or without suspicious peritoneal
             seeding

          -  Males or females at least 18 years of age

          -  Performance status 0-1 on the ECOG criteria

          -  The operative finding and biopsy of suspected peritoneum must show peritoneal
             involvement of adenocarcinoma

          -  No previous chemotherapy, immunotherapy or radiotherapy

          -  No biological major abnormalities.

          -  Adequate hematologic (WBC count ≥ 4,000/mm3, platelet count ≥ 150,000/mm3), hepatic
             (bilirubin level £ 1.5 mg/dL), and renal (creatinine concentration £ 1.5 mg/dL)
             function.

          -  Informed consent from patient or patient's relative

          -  If female: childbearing potential either terminated by surgery, radiation, or
             menopause, or attenuated by use of an approved contraceptive method (intrauterine
             device [IUD], birth control pills, or barrier device) during and for 3 months after
             trial. If male, use of an approved contraceptive method during the study and 3 months
             afterwards

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Myocardial infarction within preceding 6 months or symptomatic heart disease,
             including unstable angina, congestive heart failure or uncontrolled arrhythmia

          -  Serious concomitant infection

          -  Second primary malignancy (except in situ carcinoma of the cervix or adequately
             treated basal cell carcinoma of the skin or prior malignancy treated more than 5 years
             ago without recurrence)

          -  History of significant neurologic or psychiatric disorders

          -  Pregnant or lactating women

          -  Women of child bearing potential not using a contraceptive method
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Young Suk Park, M.D.,Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Samsung Medical Center, Seoul, Korea</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Samsung Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>135-710</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Guichard S, Chatelut E, Lochon I, Bugat R, Mahjoubi M, Canal P. Comparison of the pharmacokinetics and efficacy of irinotecan after administration by the intravenous versus intraperitoneal route in mice. Cancer Chemother Pharmacol. 1998;42(2):165-70.</citation>
    <PMID>9654118</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Maruyama M, Nagahama T, Yuasa Y. Intraperitoneal versus intravenous CPT-11 for peritoneal seeding and liver metastasis. Anticancer Res. 1999 Sep-Oct;19(5B):4187-91.</citation>
    <PMID>10628373</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rosen HR, Jatzko G, Repse S, Potrc S, Neudorfer H, Sandbichler P, Zacherl J, Rabl H, Holzberger P, Lisborg P, Czeijka M. Adjuvant intraperitoneal chemotherapy with carbon-adsorbed mitomycin in patients with gastric cancer: results of a randomized multicenter trial of the Austrian Working Group for Surgical Oncology. J Clin Oncol. 1998 Aug;16(8):2733-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9704725</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Rothenberg ML, Liu PY, Braly PS, Wilczynski SP, Hannigan EV, Wadler S, Stuart G, Jiang C, Markman M, Alberts DS. Combined intraperitoneal and intravenous chemotherapy for women with optimally debulked ovarian cancer: results from an intergroup phase II trial. J Clin Oncol. 2003 Apr 1;21(7):1313-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12663720</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 3, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 3, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 5, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 22, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 22, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 23, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Gstric cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Pritoneal seeding</keyword>
  <keyword>Intraperitoneal chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Irinotecan</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stomach Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Irinotecan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

