<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00537043</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CFD110733</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00537043</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Compare COREG CR to COREG CR Fixed-dose Combination in Patients With High Blood Pressure</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label, Randomized, Crossover, Repeat-dose Study to Evaluate the Steady-State Pharmacokinetic Profile of the Final Fixed Dose Combination (FDC) Formulation of COREG CR and Lisinopril as Compared to COREG CR in Subjects With Essential Hypertension</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Carvedilol controlled release is a marketed drug to treat high blood pressure. This study is
      to compare carvedilol controlled release to carvedilol controlled release plus lisinopril
      (fixed-dose combination) after repeat dosing in patients with high blood pressure. This is to
      make sure that when carvedilol controlled release is given with lisinopril it acts the same
      in the body as when given alone. The study will also assess the safety and tolerability of
      the fixed-dose combination.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of the amount of SB-568859 found in the blood after a 7 days of dosing with carvedilol controlled release and carvedilol controlled release plus lisinopril</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of the safety and tolerability of carvedilol controlled release and the fixed dose combination based on blood and urine tests, vital signs, and reporting of side effects.</measure>
    <time_frame>7 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The pharmacokinetic parameters to be evaluated are the Tmax, Ct, and t1/2 of carvedilol [R(+)- and S(-)-enantiomers] when administered as the FDC formulation compared to COREG CR alone.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability as assessed by clinical data from AE reporting, nurse/physician observations, vital signs, ECGs and safety laboratory tests.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SK&amp;F-105517 (COREG CR FDC)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Adult males or females of non-child bearing potential who are between 18 and 60 years
             old.

          -  Have a history of mild to moderate essential hypertension or present with mild to
             moderate essential hypertension defined by Diastolic Blood Pressure &gt;/90 and &lt;/109
             mmHg, and/or Systolic Blood Pressure &gt;/140 and &lt;/179 mmHg

          -  Body weight &gt; 60 kg (132 pounds) and body mass index (BMI) between 19 and 35

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Any clinically relevant abnormality identified on the screening history, physical or
             laboratory examination, or any other medical condition or circumstances making the
             volunteer unsuitable for participation in the study.

          -  History of advanced retinopathy (i.e., Keith-Wagener Grade III or IV)

          -  Secondary forms of hypertension including (but not limited to) coarctation of the
             aorta, primary aldosteronism, renal artery stenosis, or pheochromocytoma

          -  Type 1 diabetics [note: Type 2 diabetics with HgbA1c less than or equal to 9.0% can be
             enrolled provided the Investigator considers the subject clinically stable]

          -  Signs, symptoms, or history of congestive heart failure, angina pectoris, myocardial
             infarction, cerebrovascular accident, or transient ischemic attacks

          -  History or presence of clinically significant hepatic disease

          -  Liver function tests (ALT, AST, total bilirubin or alkaline phosphatase) more than 2
             times the upper limit of the laboratory reference range

          -  History of severe pulmonary disease including asthma or chronic obstructive lung
             disease or previous history of 'hypersensitivity' to B-blockers

          -  Previously treated hypertension in subjects in whom, at the discretion of the
             Investigator, antihypertensive therapy cannot be safely withdrawn during the study

          -  Subjects who are on more than 3 antihypertensive or diuretic medications [Note:
             combination antihypertensive and/or diuretic products (such as lisinopril and
             hydrochlorothiazide) should be considered as 2 medications, and the doses of each
             component should be recorded.]

          -  Subjects who metabolize carvedilol poorly based on CYP2D6 genotyping as determined at
             screening

          -  History of regular alcohol consumption exceeding 7 drinks/week for women or 14
             drinks/week for men (1 drink = 5 ounces of wine or 12 ounces of beer or 1.5 ounces of
             hard liquor) within 6 months of screening

          -  Positive urine drug screen (UDS) including alcohol at screening. A minimum list of
             drugs that will be screened for include amphetamines, barbiturates, cocaine, opiates,
             cannabinoids and benzodiazepines.

          -  Treatment with an investigational drug within 30 days or five half-lives, whichever is
             longer, prior to the first dose of study medication (this includes investigational
             formulations of marketed products)

          -  Subjects receiving ongoing treatment or anticipated to receive treatment with any of
             the following medications during treatment with study medication:

               -  monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors

               -  any Class I or III antiarrhythmic

               -  alpha-adrenergic receptor blockers

               -  beta-2-adrenergic receptor agonists

               -  lithium

          -  Consumption of grapefruit or grapefruit juice within 7 days prior to dosing

          -  Women of child-bearing potential

          -  NOTE: Pre-menopausal females with a documented tubal ligation or hysterectomy are
             eligible. Postmenopausal females are eligible, defined as 12 months of spontaneous
             amenorrhea [in questionable cases a blood sample with simultaneous follicle
             stimulating hormone (FSH) &gt; 40 MlU/ml and estradiol &lt; 40 pg/ml (&lt;140 pmol/L) is
             confirmatory].

          -  Resting pulse rate of ≤ 50 beats per minute (bpm) at screening

          -  QTc ≥ 450 msec

          -  ECG criteria as defined in protocol

          -  Refusal or inability to discontinue use of medications known to be inhibitors/inducers
             of cytochrome P-450 2C9, 2D6 and 3A4 for at least 14 days or 5 half-lives [which ever
             is longer] prior to Day 1 of Session 1 and until 48 hours after the last dose of study
             medication. [Examples include: paroxetine, isoniazid, &quot;azole&quot;antifungal drugs (e.g.
             itraconazole), erythromycin, ticlopidine, amiodarone, quinidine, rifampin,
             phenobarbital]

          -  Donation of blood in excess of 500 mL within a 56-day period including the estimated
             210 mL of blood to be drawn during this study

          -  History of sensitivity to carvedilol, lisinopril, alpha-blockers, beta-blockers or ACE
             inhibitors

          -  History of sensitivity to heparin, heparin-induced thrombocytopenia, or sensitivity to
             any of the study medications or components thereof

          -  History of angioedema

          -  Positive for Hepatitis B surface antigen

          -  Positive for HIV

          -  Unwillingness or inability to follow the procedures outlined in the protocol or
             inability to provide written informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78704</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 27, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 27, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 28, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <disposition_first_submitted>October 13, 2010</disposition_first_submitted>
  <disposition_first_submitted_qc>October 13, 2010</disposition_first_submitted_qc>
  <disposition_first_posted type="Estimate">October 19, 2010</disposition_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 13, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 13, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 19, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Study Director</name_title>
    <organization>GSK</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hypertension,</keyword>
  <keyword>carvedilol,</keyword>
  <keyword>repeat-dosing</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carvedilol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted, but a results disposition has been submitted           -->
</clinical_study>

