<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03125928</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BR-093</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>17-1010</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03125928</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Trial of Atezolizumab With Paclitaxel, Trastuzumab, and Pertuzumab in Patients With Metastatic HER-2 Positive Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Single Arm, Phase IIA Clinical Trial Assessing The Safety And Efficacy of Atezolizumab in Combination With Paclitaxel, Trastuzumab, and Pertuzumab in Patients With Metastatic HER-2 Positive Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fox Chase Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fox Chase Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single arm, Phase IIA clinical trial assessing the safety and efficacy of
      atezolizumab in combination with paclitaxel, trastuzumab, and pertuzumab in 50 patients with
      locally advanced, unresectable, or metastatic HER2-overexpressing breast cancer. Due to
      concerns that corticosteroids may have a negative effect on tumor immunity expected with
      addition of atezolizumab to the standard of care regimen, patients will receive premedication
      with dexamethasone only for weeks 1 and 2 of the weekly paclitaxel, and then corticosteroid
      premedication will be discontinued subsequently.

      Patients must have pathologically confirmed HER2-overexpressing breast cancer that is locally
      recurrent, unresectable, or metastatic, with measurable disease as defined by RECIST v1.1.
      Tumor measurements and bone scans will be performed every 9 weeks while patients are on
      study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 13, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with treatment-related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years after stopping study treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Treatment-related adverse events will be assessed by CTCAE v4.0</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Antitumor activity of atezolizumab plus the standard regimen of paclitaxel, trastuzumab, and pertuzumab</measure>
    <time_frame>An average of 18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Antitumor activity will be measured by RECIST v1.1</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years after the last patient stops treatment</time_frame>
    <description>OS is defined as the time from initiation of treatment until death from any cause or end of the study period, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to tumor progression (TTP)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years after the last patient stops treatment</time_frame>
    <description>TTP is defined as the duration of time from the start of treatment to the first objectively documented instance of progressive disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to treatment failure (TTF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years after the last patient stops treatment</time_frame>
    <description>TTF is defined as the duration of time from start of treatment to discontinuation of study treatment for reasons defined in the protocol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years after the last patient stops treatment</time_frame>
    <description>PFS is defined as the duration of time from start of treatment to time of progression or death, whichever occurs first.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical benefit rate (CBR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years after the last patient stops treatment</time_frame>
    <description>CBR is defined as the rates of complete response (CR), partial response (PR) and stable disease (SD).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response (DOR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years after the last patient stops treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Per RECIST v1.1, DOR will be assessed by the duration of overall response, duration fo CR/PR, and duration of SD.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of biomarkers related to PD-L1 blockade with objective response rate (ORR), CBR, PFS, OS, and DOR.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years after the last patient stops treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Efficacy will be assessed according to tumor PD-L1 expression level and tumor infiltrating lymphocytes PD-L1 expression levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy according to hormone receptor status (ER/PR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years after the last patient stops treatment</time_frame>
    <description>This will be a future subset analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of discontinuation of corticosteroids use after 2 weekly doses of paclitaxel</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years after the last patient stops treatment</time_frame>
    <description>This will be assessed by CTCAE v4.0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of occurrence of paclitaxel-related infusion hypersensitivity reaction after discontinuation of corticosteroids</measure>
    <time_frame>An average of 18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>This will be assessed by CTCAE v4.0.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac safety</measure>
    <time_frame>An average of 18 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Quarterly MUGA or ECHO results assessing occurrence of left ventricular dysfunction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>HER2-positive Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Investigational Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Atezolizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Monoclonal antibody</description>
    <arm_group_label>Investigational Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paclitaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Chemotherapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Investigational Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Trastuzumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Monoclonal antibody</description>
    <arm_group_label>Investigational Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pertuzumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Monoclonal antibody</description>
    <arm_group_label>Investigational Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women diagnosed with pathologically confirmed HER2-overexpressing breast cancer, that
             is locally recurrent, unresectable or metastatic (negative or positive for ER/PR, and
             positive for HER2).

          -  HER2 status confirmed positive by means of immunohistochemistry (IHC) or in situ
             hybridization (ISH) according to ASCO/CAP 2013 guidelines. It is considered positive
             if scored as 3+ by an IHC method defined as uniform membrane staining for HER2 in 10%
             or more of tumor cells or demonstrate HER2 gene amplification by an ISH method (single
             probe, average HER2 copy number ≥ 6.0 signals/cell; dual probe HER2/CEP17 ratio ≥2.0
             with an average HER2 copy number ≥4.0 signals/cell; dual probe HER2/chromosome
             enumeration probe (CEP)17 ratio ≥2.0 with an average HER2 copy number &lt;4.0
             signals/cell; HER2/CEP17 ratio &lt;2.0 with an average HER2 copy number ≥ 6.0
             signals/cell).

          -  Have measurable clinical disease: Measurable disease, defined as at least 1 measurable
             lesion on a CT scan as defined by RECIST (version v1.1).

          -  Age &gt; 18 years.

          -  ECOG performance status 0,1or 2.

          -  Adequate organ function (defined by the following parameters): Absolute neutrophil
             count (ANC) ≥ 1.5 x 109/L. Hemoglobin ≥ 10 g/dL.Platelets ≥ 100 x 109/L. Serum
             bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x upper normal limit (UNL), except patients with Gilbert's syndrome.
             Serum alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 2 x UNL or ≤ 5.0 x UNL in case of liver
             metastases. Serum aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 2 x UNL or ≤ 5.0 x UNL in case of
             liver metastases. Serum creatinine &lt; 140 μmol/L (&lt; 1.6 mg/dL) or 1.5x the upper limit
             of normal, whichever is less. Serum alkaline phosphatase (ALP) ≤ UNL or ≤ 2.5 x ULN in
             case of liver and bone metastases.

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction of 50% or more at baseline (by echocardiography or
             multiple-gated acquisition scanning).

          -  Patients may have received one prior hormonal treatment for metastatic disease.

          -  Patients may have received adjuvant or neoadjuvant chemotherapy with or without
             trastuzumab and pertuzumab with an interval greater than than 12 months since
             completion of adjuvant/neoadjuvant treatment.

          -  Ability to understand and willingness to sign a written informed consent and HIPAA
             consent document.

          -  Female participants of childbearing age must be willing to use contraception methods,
             or abstain from sexual activity throughout the course of the study and for 7 months
             after the last dose of atezolizumab.

          -  Have provided tissue from a newly obtained biopsy obtained from a focus of metastatic
             disease, and be willing to consider repeat biopsy post-treatment after at least 4
             cycles of treatment (an archival tissue sample may be substituted if new biopsy cannot
             be obtained and by discretion of Sponsor Investigator).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients participating in another trial of an investigational agent within 4 weeks of
             the 1st dose of the study.

          -  Patients with tumors that cannot be measured or clinically followed.

          -  Patients who had received therapy for metastatic breast cancer (other than that
             described above).

          -  Patients with active central nervous system (CNS) metastases and/or carcinomatous
             meningitis. Subjects with previously treated brain metastases may participate provided
             they are stable (without evidence of progression by imaging for at least four weeks
             prior to the first dose of trial treatment and any neurologic symptoms have returned
             to baseline), have no evidence of new or enlarging brain metastases, and are not using
             steroids for at least 4 weeks prior to trial treatment.

          -  Patients with any baseline grade 2 neuropathy.

          -  Patients with known prior hypersensitivity reaction to any of the study drugs.

          -  Active autoimmune disease that is requiring systemic treatment within the past 3
             months or documented history of clinically active autoimmune disease that requires
             systemic corticosteroids or immunosuppressive therapy.

          -  Diagnosis of immunosuppression or receiving steroid therapy or other immunosuppressive
             therapy within 4 weeks of the study.

          -  Have evidence of interstitial lung disease or active, non-infectious pneumonitis.

          -  Patients with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV1/2). An HIV test must be performed to
             confirm status prior to enrollment.

          -  Patients who are carriers of hepatitis virus B and C. Hepatitis B and C testing must
             be performed to confirm status prior to enrollment.

          -  Prior therapy with an anti-programmed cell death 1 (PD-1), anti-programmed cell death
             1 ligand (PDL-1), anti-PD-L2, anti-CD137 antibody, or anti-cytotoxic T-lymphocyte
             -associated antigen-4 (CTLA-4) antibody.

          -  Pregnant, breastfeeding, or expecting to conceive within the projected time of the
             trial, starting with the pre-screening or screening visit and through 7 months after
             the last dose of trial treatment.

          -  Active infection requiring systemic therapy.

          -  Active substance abuse or psychiatric disorders.

          -  The use of a RANKL inhibitor (denosumab) must be discontinued during the study.
             Bisphosphonate therapy is permitted.

          -  The following treatments must be discontinued: Herbal Medications. Immunomodulatory
             agents, including but not limited to interferons or IL-2. Immunosuppressive
             medications, including but not limited to cyclophosphamide, azathioprine,
             methotrexate, and thalidomide. Systemic corticosteroids. Anti−TNF-α agents.

          -  Any live, attenuated vaccine within 28 days prior to the first day of treatment or
             during study treatment, or unwillingness to avoid live, attenuated vaccines within 90
             days following the last dose of atezolizumab.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lori J Goldstein, MD</last_name>
    <phone>215-214-1515</phone>
    <email>lori.goldstein@fccc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fox Chase Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lori J Goldstein, MD</last_name>
      <phone>215-214-1515</phone>
      <email>lori.goldstein@fccc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 22, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 19, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Atezolizumab</keyword>
  <keyword>PD-L1</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atezolizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pertuzumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albumin-Bound Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Trastuzumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

