<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03122145</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB201700132 - A</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03122145</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Normal Breathing and Swallowing in Healthy Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Establishing Normal Swallowing and Breathing Profiles in Healthy Adults Across the Age Span</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to establish normative values for clinical testing measures of
      swallow, respiratory and cough functions. This will aide in establishing degree of impairment
      in disordered populations, and in identifying efficacious treatment paradigms for dysphagia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The prevalence of dysphagia may be as high as 22% in individuals over 50 years of age. There
      are few therapeutic options and minimal management strategies offered to treat these
      individuals and improve sequelae of dysphagia. Dysphagia contributes to malnutrition,
      aspiration, pneumonia, reduced quality of life and increased mortality in neurodegenerative
      disease such as ALS. One reason for this is the lack of normative data across various
      measures of swallowing and respiratory function. As a result, detecting early impairments in
      swallowing physiology is difficult, given the variability of swallowing and unknown normative
      value range of swallowing physiology. Therefore, the goal of this study is to complete
      clinical tests of swallowing and cough function in healthy volunteers to establish normative
      data. This will contribute to future study in disordered populations, to determine degree and
      severity of impairment and efficacious treatment and management strategies based on
      impairment.

      The purpose of this study is to establish normative values for clinical testing measures of
      swallow, respiratory and cough functions. This will aide in establishing degree of impairment
      in disordered populations, and in identifying efficacious treatment paradigms for dysphagia.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 23, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 15, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Swallowing Pressure with High Resolution Manometry (HRM)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>HRM will measures maximum pressure (mmHg) across 4 anatomical zones.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Pressure with High Resolution Manometry (HRM)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>HRM will measure rate of pressure (mmHg) increase across 4 anatomical swallowing zones.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Pressure with High Resolution Manometry (HRM)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>HRM will measure mean pressure (mmHg) across 4 anatomical swallowing zones.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Swallowing Efficiency (with NRRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The validated Normalized Residue Ratio Scale (NRRS) is a validated measurement tool that is used to quantify the amount of residue remaining in the valleculae and pyriform sinus after bolus trials. Inefficient swallows are those swallows with an NRRS valleculae (NRRSv) rating of 0.07 or greater and an NRRS pyriform sinus (NRRSp) rating of 0.2 or greater. Efficient swallows will be those calculated to have an NRRSv value of &lt;.07 and/or NRRSp value of &lt;.02.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reflexive Cough Testing (with Urge-to-Cough)</measure>
    <time_frame>25 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Reflexive cough testing will use a capsaicin challenge that will assess individual's cough motor and cough sensory thresholds. A modified Borg scale ranging from 0 (no cough) to 10 (maximal urge to cough) will be used to quantify these thresholds. A cough sensory threshold will be defined as a concentration of capsaicin eliciting a perceived urge to cough of 1 (very slight) &gt;2/3 trials. A cough motor threshold will be the lowest concentration of capsaicin eliciting &gt;2 cough responses in 2/3 trials.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Voluntary Peak Cough Flow Testing (with Electronic Peak Cough Flow Meter Device)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Voluntary peak cough flow testing will be used to capture the volume of air expelled in the 1st second of cough as measured in PEF and FEV1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Expiratory Pressure with Pulmonary Function Testing (with hand-held digital manometer)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Pulmonary Function Testing will be used to determine maximum expiratory pressure (MEP).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Inspiratory Pressure with Pulmonary Function Testing (with hand-held digital manometer)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Pulmonary function testing will be used to determine maximum inspiratory pressure (MIP).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Forced Vital Capacity with Pulmonary Function Testing (with hand-held digital manometer)</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Pulmonary function testing will be used to determine forced vital capacity (FVC).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tongue Function Examination Iowa Oral Pressure Instrument (IOPI)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Normal IOPI = 60kPa, anything below 40kPa would be considered a red flag for further evaluation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lingual Strength with Lingual Function Testing (with IOPI)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Lingual function testing will be used to measure maximum anterior lingual pressure (kPA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lingual Physiologic Reserve with Lingual Function Testing (IOPI)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Lingual function testing will be used to measure lingual physiologic functional reserve (kPA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lingual Swallowing Pressure with Lingual Function Testing (IOPI)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Lingual strength testing will be used to measure lingual pressure during swallowing (kPA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Lingual Resistance with Lingual Electrical Impedance Myography (with SFB7 ImpediMed device)</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Lingual EIM will be used to assess the health of the lingual musculature by assessing this muscle using an electrode that will apply a current and a frequency spectrum ranging from 500 Hz to 2 megahertz (MHz) will be analyzed to determine resistance (Ohms) of the tongue.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">115</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This study will involve a single 90-minute visit. All women under the age of 62 will be asked to complete a pregnancy test as part of the screening process during to radiation exposure. Eligible participants will then undergo testing to determine their individualized Maximum Expiratory Pressure (MEP), maximum inspiratory pressures (MIP), voluntary and reflexive cough testing, tongue pressure testing and a comprehensive instrumental swallowing evaluation (that will include either videofluoroscopy, manometry, or simultaneous swallowing and manometry study). The entire duration of the exam will be under 90 minutes and the participant will be free to leave at any point during the examination.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Capsaicin</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will inspire deeply through the nebulizer coupled to the facemask and pneumotachograph. Each test inhalation will be separated by an interval of 2 minutes. This experimental trial consists of six (instead of 8) test solutions: 0, 25, 50, 100, 200 and 500 μM capsaicin in 80% physiological saline, 20% ethanol. Participants will inhale single vital capacity breaths of capsaicin solution via an air-powered dosimeter (KoKoDigidoser; Pulmonary Data Services Instrumentation Inc; Louisville, CO). The reflex cough test ends when the participant coughs at least 2 times in response to one inhalation dose, or receives a dose of the highest concentration (500 μM).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Volunteers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Videofluoroscopic swallow study</intervention_name>
    <description>The swallowing systems core laboratory is fully equipped to perform videofluoroscopy with a c-arm (OEC 9900) that is dedicated solely to research purposes. Videofluoroscopy recordings will be kept to a minimum and turned on only during completion of a specific testing task. Video recording and images captured during the videofluoroscopy will be synced and saved for data analysis. Videofluoroscopy allows for time-synced, frame-by-frame data analysis for the specific measures taken during swallowing tasks. The physiological swallowing measures (temporal and kinematic movement of the base of tongue and hyolaryngeal complex during swallowing) to be analyzed cannot be visualized with any other technique. All swallowing tasks will be completed using barium in order to visualize the bolus during movement of various swallowing muscles and structures.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Volunteers</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>OEC 9900</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A total of 120 individuals will be included in this study.

          -  Subjects will include both male and females who are aged between 18-100

          -  Healthy and with no major medical conditions.

          -  No specific gender or race will be excluded or targeted for participation in this
             study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults who are pregnant

          -  Those with major medical conditions (i.e., swallowing impairment, brain injury) will
             be excluded from this study.

          -  Anyone with allergy to barium will be excluded from this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Emily Plowman, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lauren Tabor, MS CCCSLP</last_name>
    <phone>3522738632</phone>
    <email>ltabor@ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jessica Zipper, MS</last_name>
    <phone>3522738632</phone>
    <email>jzipper@phhp.ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.swallowingsystemscore.com</url>
    <description>Laboratory Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 17, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 19, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 14, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 14, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>healthy</keyword>
  <keyword>volunteer</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Capsaicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The study team will not be sharing individual IDP information with other researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

