<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03123874</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB #: 1608006566</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2T32DK007158-42</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NYC-399436</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03123874</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Milk in Life Conditions (MiLC): Bacterial Composition of Human Milk Pumped and Stored in &quot;Real-Life&quot; Conditions</brief_title>
  <acronym>MiLC</acronym>
  <official_title>Milk in Life Conditions (MiLC): Characterizing the Bacterial Composition of Human Milk Pumped and Stored in &quot;Real-life&quot; Conditions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Idaho</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Food and Agriculture</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cornell University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The MiLC trial is a randomized control trial of two different types of breast pumps--mother's
      own and sterile. The objective of this trial is to investigate the bacterial composition of
      human milk pumped and stored in &quot;real-life&quot; conditions. To meet this objective, lactating
      mothers will fully express breast milk from one breast on two consecutive pumping sessions at
      home, once with the participant's own pumps and bottles and once with a sterile,
      hospital-grade pump and sterile bottles. Randomization will be used to determine which pump
      participants use first. From the total volume of milk pumped during each pumping session, the
      researchers will collect 1 oz. Milk from both pumps will be stored at home and sampled on
      days 0, 2, 4, and 30 after expression for analysis of its bacterial composition.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants will donate 1 oz of human milk during each of two consecutive pumping sessions,
      for a total volume of 2 oz donated on one day. To collect this human milk, participants will
      be asked to fully express one breast during each pumping session. Participants will pump once
      with the participant's own pump and bottles and once with the sterile pump and sterile
      bottles (provided by the research team). Women will be randomized to which pump is used
      first. All human milk collections will occur at participants' homes between 0700 and 1100
      hours. The second pumping session must begin 3 hours (+/-30 minutes) after the beginning of
      the first pumping session (e.g. the first pumping session at 7:30 am and the second at 10:30
      am). Participants will elect from which breast to donate human milk and that breast will be
      used for both pumping sessions. Participants will be asked not to nurse from or pump that
      breast during the 2 hours before the first pumping session and not until after the second
      pumping session (a total of ~5.5 hours).

      From the milk produced during each pumping session (which could be up to ~6 oz), researchers
      will collect 1 oz using a sterile, plastic syringe. Participants will keep the remaining
      volume of milk. Each ounce of milk collected will be separated into 5 sterile containers
      (provided). Participants will store donated milk at home until it is picked up by a
      researcher 2, 4, and 30 days after pumping.

      A secondary objective of this trial is to understand how infant feeding status (human milk
      ONLY or human milk AND complementary foods) influences the human milk microbiome. The
      researchers aim to have 25 participants whose infants are fed human milk ONLY and 25 whose
      infants are fed human milk AND complementary foods. Once 20 participants have been enrolled
      in one group, researchers will temporarily restrict enrollment to women whose infants are
      part of the other group. If the researchers are unable to achieve 25 participants per group
      in a timely manner, enrollment of all eligible women will be resumed, regardless of infant
      feeding status.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 22, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 15, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Bacterial communities</measure>
    <time_frame>0 days after pumping</time_frame>
    <description>Bacterial communities will be determined by next-generation sequencing of the V1-V3 or the V3-V4 region of the 16S rRNA bacterial gene.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bacterial growth</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after pumping</time_frame>
    <description>Bacterial growth will be tested in human milk collected with each pump. Human milk will be held under home refrigeration for 4 days then transferred to participants' freezers until 30 days after pumping. Bacterial growth will be measured by aerobic culturing on selective media.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">52</enrollment>
  <condition>Human Milk Microbiome</condition>
  <condition>Bacterial Growth</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mom's own pump (reference)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will use two pumps--Mom's own and a sterile pump (Medela Symphony). Participants will be asked to fully express one breast on two consecutive pumping sessions. The second pumping sessions will occur 3 hours (+/- 30 minutes) from the beginning of the first pumping session. Participants will be randomized to which pump is used first. One ounce of human milk will be collected from each pumping session and stored at home for 0, 2, 4, and 30 days after pumping.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Home storage</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>One ounce of human milk will be collected from each pumping session and stored at home for 0, 2, 4, and 30 days after pumping.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sterile pump</intervention_name>
    <description>Medela symphony breast pump (model number 0240108) and sterile collection kits (model number 6007092).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mom's own pump (reference)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Home storage</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mom's own pump</intervention_name>
    <description>Mom's own pump and mom's own collection kit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Mom's own pump (reference)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Home storage</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Home storage</intervention_name>
    <description>One ounce of human milk will be collected from each pumping session and stored at home for 0, 2, 4, and 30 days after pumping.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Home storage</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Lactating women over the age of 18 years

          -  Self-reported as healthy women and infants

          -  Use an electric breast pump

          -  Able to donate 1 oz of milk from one breast during each of two consecutive pumping
             sessions where pumping sessions are 3 hours (+/- 30 minutes) apart and between
             0700-1100 hours.

          -  Able to store donated milk at home for 30 days

          -  Have infants who do not consume formula or only consume formula episodically as long
             as the most recent formula-feeding occurred &gt; 2 weeks before the day milk is pumped
             for this study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to donate 1 oz of milk from one breast during each of two consecutive pumping
             sessions, 3 hours (+/- 30 minutes) apart and between the hours of 0700-1100 hours.

          -  Infant consumption of formula in the past 2 weeks

          -  Current indication of breast infection (e.g., breast pain, discomfort, lumps, mastitis
             with fever, red streaks, or hard red portions of the breast)

          -  Breast pain that the woman does not consider &quot;normal&quot; for lactation/breastfeeding

          -  Signs/symptoms of acute illness in woman or infant in past 7 days including fever
             (rectal or temporal temperature ≥99.5 F), dark green nasal discharge, diarrhea (abrupt
             onset of 3 or more excessively &quot;loose&quot; stools in one day), vomiting (where infant
             vomiting is not associated with feeding), or severe cough.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathleen M. Rasmussen, ScD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anthony Hay, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sarah Reyes, MS</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Cornell University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hay Laboratory, B75C Wing Hall, Cornell University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ithaca</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14853</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 6, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 17, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 21, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>human milk</keyword>
  <keyword>breast milk</keyword>
  <keyword>expressed human milk</keyword>
  <keyword>bacterial communities</keyword>
  <keyword>microbiome</keyword>
  <keyword>breast pump</keyword>
  <keyword>bacterial growth</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The researchers are currently undecided about how all the data from the study will be released but 16S rRNA data will be released through INSDC (the International Nucleotide Sequence Database Collaboration, which encompasses NCBI, EBI and DDBJ).</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

