<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03128918</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15-002-MUHC</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03128918</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Non-invasive Diagnosis of Non-alcoholic Steatohepatitis in Liver Transplant Recipients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Non-invasive Diagnosis of Non-alcoholic Steatohepatitis in Liver Transplant Recipients: a Prospective, Longitudinal Study Employing Serum Cytokeratin 18 and Transient Elastography (Fibroscan)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>McGill University Health Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian National Transplant Research Program</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McGill University Health Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is is to use non-invasive diagnostic tests, Fibroscan and a simple
      blood test, to diagnose NASH in patients who undergo liver transplantation. Liver
      transplantation is a life-saving procedure for people with cirrhosis. Fatty liver is a common
      reason for liver transplantation due to obesity and diabetes. Fatty liver can happen again to
      the new transplanted liver and it is often due to metabolic risk factors (including diabetes,
      rapid weight gain, and immunosuppressive therapy, which are used to avoid rejection of the
      new liver). Some patients with fatty liver after liver transplant have non-alcoholic
      steatohepatitis (NASH) injury to liver the tissue (inflammation) and damage which is caused
      by a build-up of fat in the liver. This is a serious problem and can lead to cirrhosis and
      loss of the transplanted liver. There has been no detailed study into the recurrence of NASH.
      One reason for this is one of the only ways to detect fatty liver and NASH is to have a liver
      biopsy, which can be painful and have complications. Recently, a new technology (Fibroscan)
      and a simple blood test (cytokeratin 18) have been developed which can tell doctors how much
      a liver is damaged and how much fat it contains without pain or complications. This is a year
      long study involving one screening visit and 3 study visits, 3 months apart.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, longitudinal, pilot study of non-invasive diagnostic tests to explore
      recurrent or de novo NAFLD/NASH in liver transplant recipients. The study will be conducted
      at the Royal Victoria Hospital, McGill University Health Centre (MUHC) Solid Organ Transplant
      Unit, which carries out 60 liver transplants per year. A dedicated liver transplant database
      is in place since 1990 and prospectively collects demographic and clinical characteristics of
      all patients. In November 2013, two fully equipped Fibroscan machines have been acquired by
      the Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology of the MUHC. The MUHC is the first center in
      Quebec to have access to the latest modules of Fibroscan (CAP and XL probe) that are
      essential to diagnose hepatic steatosis. In preparation for the current project, the
      Investigators performed an analysis of frequencies of hepatitis C, alcoholic liver disease,
      NASH, hepatitis B as indications for liver transplantation MUHC Center Solid Organ Transplant
      in 2000 and 2013. NASH was the only indication that significantly increased (8% in 2000 vs
      20% in 2013; p&lt;0.0001) and currently represents the third indication.

      Enrolled participants will be followed every 3 months for one year, in conjunction with their
      regular care visit.

      Blood samples obtained during the screening and the study visits will be processed by the
      research technician of the MUHC Solid Organ Transplant Unit. The plasma will be stored at
      -80C until used for quantitative measurement of CK-18 levels by the Human cytokeratin ELISA
      kit.

      The fibroscan examination will be performed on a 4-hour fasting participants. The standard M
      probe will be used in all participants. The XL probe will be used in obese patients (BMI&gt;30
      Kg/m2) and in case of failure of Fibroscan by the M probe. CAP examination will be performed
      at the same time to diagnose hepatic steatosis. A valid Fibroscan result will be defined by
      10 validated measures and IQR &lt; 30% of the median. Validated cut-off values will be applied
      to diagnose hepatic steatosis and fibrosis by Fibroscan/CAP. Grading of steatosis will be as
      following: mild steatosis (&lt;30% of the hepatocytes); moderate steatosis (30-60%); severe
      steatosis (&gt;60%).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of NASH in liver transplant recipients</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>CK-18 to indicate NASH</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of liver steatosis in liver transplant recipients</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fibroscan with CAP to indicate steatosis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of fibrosis</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Liver stiffness measurement by Fibroscan</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Accuracy of noninvasive tests to diagnose NAFLD/NASH and hepatic fibrosis as compared to standard of care histology</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the accuracy of CK-18 and Fibroscan/CAP</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        post liver transplant
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Liver transplant recipient of any etiology;

          -  &gt;18 years old;

          -  Able to provide informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Liver transplant due to alcoholic liver disease as primary etiology;

          -  Liver transplant due to chronic hepatitis C, genotype 3.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Giada Sebastiani</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>McGill University Health Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Maria Osikowicz</last_name>
    <phone>514-934-1934</phone>
    <phone_ext>31343</phone_ext>
    <email>maria.osikowicz@mail.mcgill.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mcgill University Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H4A 3J1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maria Osikowicz</last_name>
      <phone>514-934-1934</phone>
      <phone_ext>31343</phone_ext>
      <email>maria.osikowicz@mail.mcgill.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 7, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 21, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>McGill University Health Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Giada Sebastiani</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>md</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

