<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03125590</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>05141991</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03125590</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Validation, Reliability and Pilot Test of the Personalized Exercise Questionnaire (PEQ)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Reliability and Validity Study of the Facilitators and Barriers Exercise Questionnaire</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>McMaster University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McMaster University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The PEQ is the first tool to measure facilitators, barriers, and preferences to exercise in
      people with osteoporosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Osteoporosis is a disease of the bones characterized by low bone mass and microarchitectural
      deterioration of bone tissue. This disease can increase the risk of bone fragility fractures
      and is indirectly associated with premature death. These fractures are more common than
      cancer or heart disease in North American women 50 years or older, with an osteoporotic
      fracture occurring every 3 seconds worldwide, and are a major issue to patients and the
      healthcare system. Increased fracture rates, particularly in the hip and spine, may lead to
      hospitalization and subsequent immobility.

      Some studies have shown fitness to be a better predictor of bone mineral density than age,
      yet adherence to exercise is poor. Studies suggest that 50% of those registered in an
      exercise program drop out within the first 6 months, lack of time being the number one
      barrier in many populations. To increase adherence to an exercise program, a systematic
      review has identified a number of facilitators and barriers to exercise in adults with
      osteoporosis and osteopenia.

      Hitherto, no measurement tool has been created to measure these facilitators and barriers in
      people with osteoporosis. The investigators have developed and validated the PEQ
      (Personalized Exercise Questionnaire), a new tool that can measure the facilitators,
      barriers, and preferences to exercise. The next steps are to test the reliability,
      known-group validity, and pilot test this tool in the osteoporosis population.

      Future physical activity or exercise interventions could benefit from using this tool to
      leveraging the facilitators and limiting the barriers to exercise to increase adherence to an
      exercise program.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 11, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 9, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reliability of the PEQ</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>This study requires 114 participants for pilot testing of the questionnaire. A subset of 46 patients will be used for the reliability study to determine the test-retest. The questionnaire will be administered at baseline and subsequently completed again after approximately 1 week.
Test-retest will determine the reproducibility of this questionnaire. Intraclass correlation (ICC) model 2, form 2 (ICC 2, 2) will be used.
Internal consistency is expressed by Cronbach's alpha, which is a measure of the reliability of the summative rating scale will also be used.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Known Group-Validity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Known Group Validity is a type of validity that measures the extent to which a questionnaire is sensitive to the differences and similarities between two groups. For example, the investigators may hypothesize that participants from lower socio-economic status (SES) would have cost as a barrier to exercise compared to participants from a higher SES. Hypothesizes will be identified from the literature and tested to determine known group validity.
Differences between hypothesized groups will be assessed using an ANOVA and Chi-Square test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preferences to exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Using the PEQ, domains two and four, will be used to quantify the frequency of each preference. Results will be presented in a table with column one representing the survey item and column two representing the frequency of the reported outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Barriers to exercise</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Using the PEQ, domain six, will be used to quantify the frequency of each barrier. Results will be presented in a table with column one representing the survey item and column two representing the frequency of the reported outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exercise Goals</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Using the PEQ, domain three, will be used to quantify the frequency of each goal. Results will be presented in a table with column one representing the survey item and column two representing the frequency of the reported outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">114</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoporosis, Postmenopausal</condition>
  <condition>Osteopenia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Testing the PEQ (Personalized Exercise Questionnaire)</intervention_name>
    <description>Administer the questionnaire to 114 participants to classify their facilitators, barriers and preferences to exercise</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Peoples with a diagnosis of primary osteoporosis or osteopenia.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. The participant is able and willing to provide informed consent

          2. The participant is male or female, 18+

          3. The participant has received a diagnosis, from a physician, of primary osteopenia or
             osteoporosis (T &lt; - 1.0)

          4. The participant can read and write English

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. The participant has been diagnosed with secondary osteopenia or osteoporosis

          2. The participant has a history of smoking, alcoholism, gastrointestinal disease,
             hypercalciuria and/or steroid use.

          3. The participant is diagnosed with a reading disability or dyslexia

          4. The participant has a cognitive impairment of some severity as to adversely affect the
             validity of the data
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Joseph's Health Care Centre; Charlton Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamitlon</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8N1Y2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 17, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 19, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 28, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 28, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 29, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>McMaster University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Isabel Rodrigues</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Master's student</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Osteoporosis, osteopenia, test-retest, validity, PEQ, questionnaire, facilitators, barriers, exercise, physical activity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoporosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bone Diseases, Metabolic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoporosis, Postmenopausal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Currently, there is no plan, however, if other researchers would like to use this data set they may. Patient names have been changed and associated with an ID. Data sets reveal no patient information.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

