<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03126253</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FET-CA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03126253</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Burden of Childhood Anemia in Bangladesh: Does Socioeconomic Status Matter?</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Burden of Childhood Anemia in Bangladesh:</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shahjalal University of Science and Technology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shahjalal University of Science and Technology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Childhood anemia is a global public health problem that is associated with life-threatening
      consequences such as growth retardation, impaired motor and cognitive development, and
      increased morbidity and mortality. Anemia can be caused by a variety of factors such as
      nutritional deficiencies (i.e., iron, folic acid, vitamin B12, and vitamin A), infections
      (i.e., helminth), and blood disorders (i.e., hemoglobinopathies). The World Health
      Organization (WHO) estimates that approximately 50% of anemia cases can be attributed to iron
      deficiency. This is an estimated global average that varies widely depending upon the
      location in question. The World Bank estimates for 2011 claim that approximately 55.60% of
      all Bangladeshi children under five years of age are suffering from anemia. The relationship
      between socioeconomic status (SES) inequality and anemia among the children has never been
      conclusively and it is unclear if the children of the age group of 6-59 months have uniformly
      high levels of anemia during all the stages of development, e.g., during the infant, toddler,
      and preschool stages. In addition, there is a dearth of evidence from Bangladesh, where the
      meaning of sociodemographic characteristics may be different from that in other countries.
      Therefore, this study attempts to fill the above-mentioned lacuna by investigating and
      evaluating the association of SES inequality, among other explanatory variables, on the
      development of childhood anemia during different stages of child development and to answer
      the questions: (a) Is SES a factor impeding childhood anemia along with other explanatory
      variables? (b) In which stage of child development, the chance of disparaging with childhood
      anemia is highest? (c) Is there evidence of between child development stages differences in
      the strength and form of association disparities between having childhood anemia and SES? (c)
      What are the predictive margins for SES-associated anemia in the case of infants, toddlers,
      and preschool children? The results of this analysis will be reported for elucidating the
      potential effects of SES and the stages of child development that are usually neglected in
      the conventional scientific literature. Moreover, as anemia is one of the current key health
      issues in Bangladesh, it is also expected that the findings of this study would contribute
      significantly toward shaping the health policy strategy of the country.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The data collected by the 2011 Bangladesh Demographic Health Survey (BDHS), conducted by the
      National Institute for Population Research and Training (Ministry of Health and Family
      Welfare, Bangladesh), will be used for the purpose of this study. in the BDHS 2011, A
      nationally representative household-based sample was created through a stratified, multistage
      cluster sampling strategy in which 600 primary sampling units were constructed (207 in urban
      areas and 393 in rural areas). The primary sampling units were derived from a sampling frame
      created for the 2001 Bangladeshi census from seven divisions of Bangladesh. Households were
      selected randomly from each primary sampling unit. The data pertaining to the socioeconomic
      and sociodemographic factors were collected using a structured open-ended interview. The
      questionnaire used for this purpose was modeled on the MEASURE DHS questionnaires. Prior to
      the use, these questionnaires were adapted for the use in Bangladesh through a series of
      meetings with a Technical Working Group (TWG) that comprised of representatives from the
      National Institute of Population Research and Training (NIPORT,) Mitra and Associates, the
      International Centre for Diarrheal Diseases and Control in Bangladesh (ICDDR, B),
      USAID/Bangladesh, and MEASURE DH. The questionnaires were drafted in English and then
      translated into Bangla which is the national language of Bangladesh. The translations were
      reviewed by the experts as well as by the volunteers and a pilot study was conducted to
      validate the same. Of the total of 17,964 selected households, face-to-face interviews were
      successfully completed for 17,141 corresponding to a household response rate of 98%. The
      subjects for the examination of anemia were 2320 children aged 6-59 months, were raised from
      every third household of the BDHS sample. After excluding subjects with missing data, a total
      of 2068 individuals were selected for this analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 11, 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 18, 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 8, 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Ecologic or Community</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Anemia</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Blood hemoglobin level will be used as the parameter for diagnosing anemia.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2320</enrollment>
  <condition>Anemia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anemia</intervention_name>
    <description>Hemoglobin level will be used as the parameter for diagnosing anemia. The HemoCue system was used to estimate the concentration of hemoglobin in capillary blood. WHO guidelines for the diagnosis of anemia that were adopted by the Demographic Health Surveys will be used in this study. Briefly, a hemoglobin concentration of less than 70 g/L will be consider to define severe anemia, 70-99 g/L for moderate anemia, and 100-109 g/L will be presumed to correspond to mild anemia. The above-mentioned classification of anemia as &quot;severe&quot; &quot;moderate&quot; and &quot;mild&quot; categories is based on blood hemoglobin cutoffs (will be adjusted for altitude and smoking) recommended by the Center for Disease Prevention of United States; this classification has also been adopted by the World Health Organization.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        children 6-59 month of age in Bangladesh
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Infant: Less than or equal to 12 months old

          -  Toddler: between 13-36 months

          -  Preschool children: between 37-59 month

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Child 0-5 months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>59 Months</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GM MI Islam, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Shahjalal University of Science and Technology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Data analysis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sylhet</city>
        <zip>3114</zip>
        <country>Bangladesh</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Bangladesh</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/fr265/fr265.pdf</url>
    <description>Report of the survey</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 19, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 21, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Shahjalal University of Science and Technology</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>G.M. Rabiul Islam</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>childhood anemia, socioeconomic status</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <study_docs>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_type>Report of the survey along with sampling plan</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://dhsprogram.com/pubs/pdf/fr265/fr265.pdf</doc_url>
    </study_doc>
  </study_docs>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

