<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03126175</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Above X below-elbow casting</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03126175</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Above-versus Below-elbow Casting for Conservative Treatment of Distal Radius Fractures</brief_title>
  <official_title>Above-versus Below-elbow Casting for Conservative Treatment of Distal Radius Fractures: a Randomized Controlled Trial and Study Protocol.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Dr. Fernando Mauro Pires da Rocha</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Federal University of São Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Dr. Fernando Mauro Pires da Rocha</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      For the non-surgical treatment of distal radius fractures in adults a variety cast options
      are available, including or not the elbow joint. The literature is inconclusive regarding the
      need to immobilize the elbow joint after reduction of the distal radius fracture.This study
      was undertaken to evaluate the best method of immobilization between the above and
      below-elbow cast groups at the end of 6 months of follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To determine the best method of immobilization ( below elbow versus above elbow splint) in
      patients with distal radius fractures at the end of 6 months of follow-up:

        -  Type of study: Prospective, randomized and controlled trial.

        -  Patient recruitment: Adults attended in emergency room with closed acute displaced
           distal radius fracture will be reduced under general venous anesthesia with fluoroscopic
           control.

      Displaced and reducible fractures (after venous anesthesia) will be included if one of these
      conditions is present: Radial height - loss &gt; 2 mm , radial Inclination- loss &gt; 4°, dorsal
      tilt - &gt; 10°, ulnar variance - loss &gt; 3 mm, intra-articular step off or gap - &gt; 2mm . The
      contralateral side will be used as a reference.

      The eligible participants will be informed about the nature and purpose of the study by
      reading the &quot;Informed Consent Term&quot; after ageeement, patients will included in the trial and
      randomized.

        -  Maintenace of reduction will be defined as the maintenance of the parameters listed
           above.

        -  Patients with above elbow immobilization will remain for 4 weeks with splint followed by
           2 weeks of below elbow immobilization. The immobilization will be removed with 6 weeks.

        -  The primary outcome is: maintenance of reduction by evaluation of radiographic
           parameters (wrist radiographs) at one, two, three, four, six, eight, twelve and twenty
           four weeks after fracture reduction and self-reported function assessment Disabilities
           of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand questionnaire(DASH).

        -  Secondary outcomes:Patient Rated Wrist Evaluation- PRWE. Pain (VAS - &quot;Visual Analogue
           Pain Scale&quot;). Objective functional evaluation (goniometry and dynamometry) and rate of
           complications and failures.

        -  Sample Size calculation was calculated based on data derived from one recent randomized
           clinical trial on the subject. We considered as relevant differences on DASH scores
           (clinically relevant) when scores are greater than 10 points and standard deviation 15
           points. To detect this difference (Student T-test) and statistical power of 95% resulted
           in a 58 patient sample size per group. We considered an extra 10% for balancing follow
           up losses. Thus, our inclusion target will be 64 patients per group. We considered the
           test as bicaudal.

      Benefits: Below elbow splinting is easier to apply, lower cost, more comfortable and permits
      better function for daily life activity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 2, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>open label</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>maintenance of reduction by evaluation of radiographic parameters (wrist radiographs).</measure>
    <time_frame>One, two, three, four, six, eight, twelve and twenty four weeks after fracture reduction(radiographs).</time_frame>
    <description>Posteroanterior and lateral x-rays of the wrist to measure radiographic parameters to determine maintenance of reduction will be done every follow up visit. Measurements of the alignment will be made on the radiographs with a marker, straight edge, and protractor. The radiographic measurement technique will be standardized, and repeatability testing demonstrated by a complete blinded assessor. All radiographs will be reviewed by one of the four authors.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DASH questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Two, six , eight, twelve and twenty four weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The DASH questionnaire was developed as an instrument for patients with upper-extremity injuries. The survey contains 37 questions related to the function of the hand, wrist, elbow, and shoulder.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Rated Wrist Evaluation (PRWE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Eight, twelve and twenty four weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>The PRWE contains 15 items that are specific to determine the degree of musculoskeletal disability related to the wrist. Both are validated tools of upper extremity function.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain (VAS - &quot;Visual Analogue Pain Scale&quot;).</measure>
    <time_frame>one, two, three, four, six, eight, twelve and twenty four weeks after fracture reduction</time_frame>
    <description>Visual Analogue Pain Scale(VAS). It is a unidimensional measure of pain intensity, which has been widely used in diverse adult populations. Pain in VAS is a continuous scale comprised of a horizontal line with 10 centimeters (100 mm) in length, anchored by 2 verbal descriptors, one for each symptom extreme by &quot;no pain&quot; (score of 0) and &quot;pain as bad as it could be&quot; or &quot;worst imaginable pain&quot; (score of 100 [100-mm scale]). The participants are asked to report pain intensity in the last 24 hours. The respondent is asked to place a line perpendicular to the VAS line at the point that represents their pain intensity. Using a ruler, the score is determined by measuring the distance (mm) on the 100mm line between the &quot;no pain&quot; anchor and the patient's mark, providing a range of scores from 0-100.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective functional evaluation (goniometry and dynamometry)</measure>
    <time_frame>Six, eight, twelve and twenty four weeks follow up visit.</time_frame>
    <description>The objective functional evaluation measurement will be made with protactor to measure wrist flexion, extension, ulnar deviation, radial deviation and pronosupination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">128</enrollment>
  <condition>Distal Radius Fracture</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Above elbow immobilization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Above elbow immobililization with short radial splint that will be performed with 20cm wide gypsum cut to fit the thumb. The splint will be applied to the radial aspect of the wrist covering the volar and dorsal portion of the radius to the elbow. Additional splint with a 15cm width splint on the ulnar aspect of the forearm that begins at the middle of the forearm and extends into the armpit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Below elbow immobilization</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Below elbow immobilization with exclusively short radial splint that will be performed with 20cm wide gypsum cut to fit the thumb. The splint will be applied to the radial aspect of the wrist covering the volar and dorsal portion of the radius to the elbow.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Below elbow immobilization</intervention_name>
    <description>20cm wide gypsum in the forearm cut to fit the thumb.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Below elbow immobilization</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Plaster immobilization with elbow free (Below elbow)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Above elbow immobilization</intervention_name>
    <description>20cm wide gypsum in the forearm cut to fit the thumb associated a elbow splint made with a 15cm width on the ulnar aspect of the forearm that begins at the middle of the forearm and extends into the armpit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Above elbow immobilization</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Plater immobilization including elbow (Above elbow)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults with growth plate closured, both gender, with closed acute displaced distal
             radius fracture (up to 1 week), associated or not with the ulnar styloid fractures
             with no other fractures, which may be closed reduced after intravenous anesthesia. No
             previous fractures to the ipsilateral or contralateral forearm.

          -  Displaced and reducible fractures (after venous anesthesia) classified by AO as type
             A2, A3, C1, C2 and C3.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Open fractures.

          -  Vascular ou neurological compromise
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>João Carlos Belloti, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Federal University of São Paulo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Aldo Okamura, MD</last_name>
    <phone>5511 99788 8869</phone>
    <email>aldookamura@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>João Carlos Belloti, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>5511 995095575</phone>
    <email>jcbelloti@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Municipal Dr. Fernando Mauro Pires da Rocha</name>
      <address>
        <city>São Paulo</city>
        <state>SP</state>
        <zip>05835-005</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aldo Okamura, MD</last_name>
      <phone>5511 997888869</phone>
      <email>aldookamura@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>João CArlos Belloti, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>5511 955095575</phone>
      <email>jcbelloti@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bünger C, Sølund K, Rasmussen P. Early results after Colles' fracture: functional bracing in supination vs dorsal plaster immobilization. Arch Orthop Trauma Surg. 1984;103(4):251-6.</citation>
    <PMID>6391415</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bong MR, Egol KA, Leibman M, Koval KJ. A comparison of immediate postreduction splinting constructs for controlling initial displacement of fractures of the distal radius: a prospective randomized study of long-arm versus short-arm splinting. J Hand Surg Am. 2006 May-Jun;31(5):766-70.</citation>
    <PMID>16713840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stewart HD, Innes AR, Burke FD. Functional cast-bracing for Colles' fractures. A comparison between cast-bracing and conventional plaster casts. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 1984 Nov;66(5):749-53.</citation>
    <PMID>6389558</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bohm ER, Bubbar V, Yong Hing K, Dzus A. Above and below-the-elbow plaster casts for distal forearm fractures in children. A randomized controlled trial. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2006 Jan;88(1):1-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16391243</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pool C. Colles's fracture. A prospective study of treatment. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 1973 Aug;55(3):540-4.</citation>
    <PMID>4125714</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sarmiento A, Pratt GW, Berry NC, Sinclair WF. Colles' fractures. Functional bracing in supination. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 1975 Apr;57(3):311-7.</citation>
    <PMID>1123382</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 17, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 19, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>conservative treatment, treatment outcome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Radius Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The data will be made available through contact with the researcher.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

