<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03124199</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R+OCA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03124199</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rifaximin Associated With Classic Triple Therapy for the Eradication of Helicobacter Pylori Infection</brief_title>
  <acronym>R+OCA</acronym>
  <official_title>Rifaximin Associated With Classic Triple Therapy (Inhibitor of Proton Pump, Amoxicillin and Clarithromycin) for the Eradication of Helicobacter Pylori Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fundación de Investigación Biomédica - Hospital Universitario de La Princesa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fundación de Investigación Biomédica - Hospital Universitario de La Princesa</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: A progressive decrease in Helicobacter pylori eradication rates has been
      described over the years, so new combinations of antibiotics for treatment are needed.

      Aim: To evaluate the efficacy and safety of the addition of rifaximin to standard triple
      therapy (omeprazole, amoxicillin and clarithromycin) for the eradication of H. pylori.

      Methods: Independent prospective pilot clinical trial (EUDRA CT: 2013-001080-23). Forty
      consecutive adult patients were included with H. pylori infection, dyspeptic symptoms and
      naive to eradication treatment. A full blood test was performed in the first 5 patients
      included to evaluate the safety of the treatment. H. pylori eradication was confirmed with
      urea breath test at least 4 weeks after the end of treatment. Treatment: Rifaximin 400 mg/8
      h, clarithromycin 500 mg/12 h, amoxicillin 1 g/12 h, and omeprazole 20 mg/12 h for 10 days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      4. STUDY DESIGN 4.1. Endpoints Main endpoint Eradication of infection &quot;by intention to
      treat&quot;. Secondary endpoints Eradication of infection &quot;per protocol&quot;. Adherence to treatment.
      Medication side effects.

      Clinical and demographic variables:

      1) Age; 2) Sex; 3) Smoking habit; 4) Comorbidity (diabetes mellitus, hypertension, ischemic
      heart disease, dyslipidemia, others); 5) Indication of eradication (peptic ulcer vs.
      functional dyspepsia or not investigated) 6) Initial diagnosis test of H. pylori infection.

      4.2. Clinical trial design Phase III clinical trial, prospective, pilot, open, not
      controlled. The recruitment period will be five months. All the tests to confirm infection
      with Helicobacter pylori made within a maximum period of one year, provided the patient has
      not taken any antibiotics able to eradicate bacteria from conducting the test until the day
      of inclusion, will be given as valid, for the inclusion of the patient, Patients with proven
      infection and that have already prescribed standard triple therapy by routine clinical
      practice, will be required written informed consent to participate in the study, after which
      treatment with Rifaximin will be added.

        1. At the time of enrollment, after reviewing the inclusion and exclusion criteria and
           obtaining the patient's consent, a medical history and complete examination will take
           place including: antiulcer treatment received, history of smoking and alcohol intake,
           aspirin consumption and NSAID. Other concomitant medications that the patient is
           receiving for any other process will be also recorded.

        2. Between days 5-15 after taking the last dose, the procedures of the follow up visit
           specified in section 7.3.2 will be performed to the patients. Similarly, these
           procedures will be performed at the time when the patient leaves the study prematurely,
           if need be.

        3. Control breath test or histology between 4 and 8 weeks after treatment ends. Before the
           control test, it will be confirmed that the patient has not taken proton pump inhibitors
           during the 15 days before or antibiotics within 4 weeks prior to the breath test.

      The breath test is approved for the detection of H. pylori infection and post-eradication
      control. Sample collection can be performed in the same hospital.

      Breath test has been chosen as post-eradication control because it is the test that, in
      isolation, has a higher diagnostic accuracy, so is currently considered as the diagnostic
      method of choice to confirm eradication of H. pylori. In cases of gastric ulcer where
      gastroscopy after treatment control is required, the biopsy is valid also as post-eradication
      control.

      A single test post-treatment control is requested at least four weeks after completion of
      therapy since it has been observed an excellent correlation between it and the long-term
      results in previous studies.

      4.3. Treatment Description Control treatment: N/A Experimental treatment: rifaximin 400 mg (2
      tablets of Rifaximin 200 mg)/8 hours for 10 days.

      Study medication will be donated by &quot;Alfa Wassermann&quot; and re-labeled in accordance with the
      recommendations of the Royal Decree 223/2004 for medication trials.

      4.5. Withdrawal criteria and analysis The patient can discontinue his/her participation in
      the study at any time he/she wishes. In his opinion and judgment, the researcher doctor may
      also decide to withdraw a patient from the trial if it does not comply with the protocol.

      The occurrence of chronic diseases during the trail will result in the permanent exclusion of
      the subject. The onset of acute pathology during the trial period will delay the
      administration of test drugs until the patient is healed. Patients who may vomit within 3
      hours after taking the drug (verified by asking the patient) or other clinically relevant
      process that may affect the pharmacokinetics of study drug, will be excluded from analysis
      Only subjects excluded from the trial before receiving the study medication will be replaced
      by others, so that the number of patients will remain as provided by the sample size
      calculation. Individual sheets of collecting data from these excluded subjects will also be
      sent to the Sponsor organization for evaluation.

      4.6. Investigational drug accountability procedures Patients will receive Rifaximin and will
      be asked to return the remaining investigational medication in follow up visit after
      treatment. They will be asked to collaborate also bringing the remains of standard triple
      therapy for counting. The doctor will ask the patient about treatment compliance and count
      the residual medication after which he will return the remains of the standard triple therapy
      to the patient and preserve the remains of Rifaximin for later destruction by appropriate
      methods.

      4.8. Definition of end of trial Date on which the last patient completed the study follow-up
      visit.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With H.Pylori Infection Eradication</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of Participants with H.Pylori Infection Eradication confirmed with urea breath test at least 4 weeks after the end of treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tolerability of Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Patients with side effects present during treatment and in the 4 weeks after end of treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Compliance With Treatment of Patients That Completed the Study</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients that has comply with treatment, considered as intake of more than 90% of study drugs in patients who attended the post-treatment visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Bacterial Infection Due to Helicobacter Pylori (H. Pylori)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rifaximin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient with Helicobacter pylori infection with standard triple therapy prescribed by clinical practice.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rifaximin</intervention_name>
    <description>Rifaximin 400 mg/8 h added to the standard triple therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rifaximin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age greater than or equal to 18 years.

          2. Patients with dyspeptic symptoms, ie pain or discomfort (including abdominal bloating,
             early satiety and bloating) centered on the upper abdomen, persistent or recurrent,
             with proven H. pylori infection (through testing breath or gastric biopsy based
             methods, if it has been done) with a validity period of one year.

          3. Having been previously prescribed by routine clinical practice the standard triple
             therapy as eradication treatment:

               -  Proton Pump Inhibitor. Omeprazole 40 mg (or equivalent) every 12 hours. Treatment
                  duration: 10 days.

               -  Clarithromycin. Dose: 500 mg every 12 hours. Treatment duration: 10 days.

               -  Amoxicillin. Dose: 1000 mg every 12 hours. Treatment duration: 10 days.

          4. Not having yet begun taking the eradication therapy.

          5. Written informed consent from the patient.

          6. The first five patients included in the study, should had cited from the outpatient
             and prior to his arrival in consultation, a routine analysis in the month after the
             completion of the eradication therapy.

          7. If the patient is a woman of childbearing age, she will be asked to commit to not get
             pregnant or to use an adequate contraception method.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous eradication treatment for H. pylori (these patients are often carriers of
             antibiotic resistant strains and have a much lower response than those that had never
             received treatment).

          2. Allergy to any of the antibiotic in the treatment.

          3. Taking antibiotics or bismuth salts since performing the breath test.

          4. Previous gastric surgery.

          5. Presence of severe pulmonary, hepatic, renal, endocrine, metabolic, hematologic or
             tumor disease.

          6. Very advanced chronic disease or other conditions that prevent attending to controls
             and follow ups.

          7. Previous history of alcohol or drugs abuse.

          8. Patients who are pregnant or lactating.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Javier Perez, Gisbert</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fundación de Investigación Biomédica - Hospital Universitario de La Princesa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario de La Princesa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28006</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gisbert JP, Calvet X, Bermejo F, Boixeda D, Bory F, Bujanda L, Castro-Fernández M, Dominguez-Muñoz E, Elizalde JI, Forné M, Gené E, Gomollón F, Lanas Á, Martín de Argila C, McNicholl AG, Mearin F, Molina-Infante J, Montoro M, Pajares JM, Pérez-Aisa A, Pérez-Trallero E, Sánchez-Delgado J. [III Spanish Consensus Conference on Helicobacter pylori infection]. Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2013 May;36(5):340-74. doi: 10.1016/j.gastrohep.2013.01.011. Epub 2013 Apr 18. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>23601856</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gisbert JP, Pajares R, Pajares JM. Evolution of Helicobacter pylori therapy from a meta-analytical perspective. Helicobacter. 2007 Nov;12 Suppl 2:50-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17991177</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Graham DY. Helicobacter pylori eradication therapy research: Ethical issues and description of results. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2010 Dec;8(12):1032-6. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2010.07.002. Epub 2010 Jul 23. Erratum in: Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2011 Mar;9(3):280.</citation>
    <PMID>20656062</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Graham DY, Fischbach L. Helicobacter pylori treatment in the era of increasing antibiotic resistance. Gut. 2010 Aug;59(8):1143-53. doi: 10.1136/gut.2009.192757. Epub 2010 Jun 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20525969</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hawkey CJ, Atherton JC, Treichel HC, Thjodleifsson B, Ravic M. Safety and efficacy of 7-day rabeprazole- and omeprazole-based triple therapy regimens for the eradication of Helicobacter pylori in patients with documented peptic ulcer disease. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2003 Apr;17(8):1065-74.</citation>
    <PMID>12694089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paoluzi P, Iacopini F, Crispino P, Nardi F, Bella A, Rivera M, Rossi P, Gurnari M, Caracciolo F, Zippi M, Pica R. 2-week triple therapy for Helicobacter pylori infection is better than 1-week in clinical practice: a large prospective single-center randomized study. Helicobacter. 2006 Dec;11(6):562-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17083378</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Veldhuyzen Van Zanten S, Machado S, Lee J. One-week triple therapy with esomeprazole, clarithromycin and metronidazole provides effective eradication of Helicobacter pylori infection. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2003 Jun 1;17(11):1381-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12786632</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vakil N, Lanza F, Schwartz H, Barth J. Seven-day therapy for Helicobacter pylori in the United States. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2004 Jul 1;20(1):99-107.</citation>
    <PMID>15225176</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laine L, Fennerty MB, Osato M, Sugg J, Suchower L, Probst P, Levine JG. Esomeprazole-based Helicobacter pylori eradication therapy and the effect of antibiotic resistance: results of three US multicenter, double-blind trials. Am J Gastroenterol. 2000 Dec;95(12):3393-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11151867</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laine L, Suchower L, Frantz J, Connors A, Neil G. Twice-daily, 10-day triple therapy with omeprazole, amoxicillin, and clarithromycin for Helicobacter pylori eradication in duodenal ulcer disease: results of three multicenter, double-blind, United States trials. Am J Gastroenterol. 1998 Nov;93(11):2106-12.</citation>
    <PMID>9820381</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calvet X, Ducons J, Bujanda L, Bory F, Montserrat A, Gisbert JP; Hp Study Group of the Asociación Española de Gastroenterología. Seven versus ten days of rabeprazole triple therapy for Helicobacter pylori eradication: a multicenter randomized trial. Am J Gastroenterol. 2005 Aug;100(8):1696-701.</citation>
    <PMID>16086704</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gisbert JP, Domínguez-Muñoz A, Domínguez-Martín A, Gisbert JL, Marcos S. Esomeprazole-based therapy in Helicobacter pylori eradication: any effect by increasing the dose of esomeprazole or prolonging the treatment? Am J Gastroenterol. 2005 Sep;100(9):1935-40.</citation>
    <PMID>16128936</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Della Monica P, Lavagna A, Masoero G, Lombardo L, Crocellá L, Pera A. Effectiveness of Helicobacter pylori eradication treatments in a primary care setting in Italy. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2002 Jul;16(7):1269-75.</citation>
    <PMID>12144576</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Altintas E, Sezgin O, Ulu O, Aydin O, Camdeviren H. Maastricht II treatment scheme and efficacy of different proton pump inhibitors in eradicating Helicobacter pylori. World J Gastroenterol. 2004 Jun 1;10(11):1656-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15162544</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gumurdulu Y, Serin E, Ozer B, Kayaselcuk F, Ozsahin K, Cosar AM, Gursoy M, Gur G, Yilmaz U, Boyacioglu S. Low eradication rate of Helicobacter pylori with triple 7-14 days and quadriple therapy in Turkey. World J Gastroenterol. 2004 Mar 1;10(5):668-71.</citation>
    <PMID>14991935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Howden CW, Hunt RH. Guidelines for the management of Helicobacter pylori infection. Ad Hoc Committee on Practice Parameters of the American College of Gastroenterology. Am J Gastroenterol. 1998 Dec;93(12):2330-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9860388</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malfertheiner P, Megraud F, O'Morain CA, Atherton J, Axon AT, Bazzoli F, Gensini GF, Gisbert JP, Graham DY, Rokkas T, El-Omar EM, Kuipers EJ; European Helicobacter Study Group. Management of Helicobacter pylori infection--the Maastricht IV/ Florence Consensus Report. Gut. 2012 May;61(5):646-64. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-2012-302084.</citation>
    <PMID>22491499</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Egan BJ, Marzio L, O'Connor H, O'Morain C. Treatment of Helicobacter pylori infection. Helicobacter. 2008 Oct;13 Suppl 1:35-40. doi: 10.1111/j.1523-5378.2008.00639.x.</citation>
    <PMID>18783520</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yakoob J, Abid S, Abbas Z, Jafri SN. Antibiotic susceptibility patterns of Helicobacter pylori and triple therapy in a high-prevalence area. Br J Biomed Sci. 2010;67(4):197-201.</citation>
    <PMID>21294447</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vakil N, Hahn B, McSorley D. Clarithromycin-resistant Helicobacter pylori in patients with duodenal ulcer in the United States. Am J Gastroenterol. 1998 Sep;93(9):1432-5.</citation>
    <PMID>9732920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 7, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 18, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 21, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>April 24, 2017</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>August 7, 2017</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">February 19, 2018</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Eradication</keyword>
  <keyword>Helicobacter pylori</keyword>
  <keyword>rifaximin</keyword>
  <keyword>therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>standard triple therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bacterial Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Helicobacter Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rifaximin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rifamycins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Forty consecutive adult patients were included with H. pylori infection, dyspeptic symptoms and naive to eradication treatment</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>There were no significant events in the study after patient enrollment and before assignment</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Rifaximin</title>
          <description>Patient with Helicobacter pylori infection with standard triple therapy prescribed by clinical practice.
Rifaximin: Rifaximin 400 mg/8 h added to the standard triple therapy</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="40"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="36"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="4"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Lost to Follow-up</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="4"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Rifaximin</title>
          <description>Patient with Helicobacter pylori infection with standard triple therapy prescribed by clinical practice.
Rifaximin: Rifaximin 400 mg/8 h added to the standard triple therapy</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="40"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="40"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="44" spread="15"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="21"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="19"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Spain</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="40"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Percentage of Participants With H.Pylori Infection Eradication</title>
        <description>Percentage of Participants with H.Pylori Infection Eradication confirmed with urea breath test at least 4 weeks after the end of treatment</description>
        <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Rifaximin</title>
            <description>Patient with Helicobacter pylori infection with standard triple therapy prescribed by clinical practice.
Rifaximin: Rifaximin 400 mg/8 h added to the standard triple therapy</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Percentage of Participants With H.Pylori Infection Eradication</title>
          <description>Percentage of Participants with H.Pylori Infection Eradication confirmed with urea breath test at least 4 weeks after the end of treatment</description>
          <units>percentage of participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="40"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="61" lower_limit="45" upper_limit="77"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Tolerability of Treatment</title>
        <description>Patients with side effects present during treatment and in the 4 weeks after end of treatment</description>
        <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Rifaximin</title>
            <description>Patient with Helicobacter pylori infection with standard triple therapy prescribed by clinical practice.
Rifaximin: Rifaximin 400 mg/8 h added to the standard triple therapy</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Tolerability of Treatment</title>
          <description>Patients with side effects present during treatment and in the 4 weeks after end of treatment</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="36"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>with diarrhea</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="13"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>with metallic taste</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>headache</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>nausea</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>abdominal pain</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Compliance With Treatment of Patients That Completed the Study</title>
        <description>Percentage of patients that has comply with treatment, considered as intake of more than 90% of study drugs in patients who attended the post-treatment visit.</description>
        <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Rifaximin</title>
            <description>Patient with Helicobacter pylori infection with standard triple therapy prescribed by clinical practice.
Rifaximin: Rifaximin 400 mg/8 h added to the standard triple therapy</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Compliance With Treatment of Patients That Completed the Study</title>
          <description>Percentage of patients that has comply with treatment, considered as intake of more than 90% of study drugs in patients who attended the post-treatment visit.</description>
          <units>percentage of participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="36"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="100"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>1 month and 10 days</time_frame>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Rifaximin</title>
          <description>Patient with Helicobacter pylori infection with standard triple therapy prescribed by clinical practice.
Rifaximin: Rifaximin 400 mg/8 h added to the standard triple therapy</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="40"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="40"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <default_assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="27" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Diarrhea</sub_title>
                <description>Diarrhea</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="13" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Metallic Taste</sub_title>
                <description>Metallic Taste</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="9" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nausea</sub_title>
                <description>Nausea</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>abdominal pain</sub_title>
                <description>Abdominal pain</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Headache</sub_title>
                <description>Headache</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="36"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Mercedes Ramas</name_or_title>
      <organization>Hospital Universitario de la Princesa</organization>
      <phone>913093911</phone>
      <email>mercedesramas@gmail.com</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

