<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03123094</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1368-0009</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03123094</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Single Rising Dose Trial of BI 655130 for Healthy Japanese Male Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of Single Rising Intravenous Dose and Single Subcutaneous Dose of BI 655130 in Healthy Japanese Male Volunteers (Double-blind, Randomised, Placebo-controlled Design).</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boehringer Ingelheim</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boehringer Ingelheim</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this trial is to investigate the safety and tolerability of BI
      655130 following administration of single rising intravenous doses and single subcutaneous
      dose in healthy Japanese male volunteers.

      Secondary objective is the exploration of the pharmacokinetics including dose proportionality
      of BI 655130 in healthy Japanese male volunteers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 16, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 4, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 4, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with drug-related Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 148 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC0-∞ (area under the concentration-time curve of the analyte in plasma over the time interval from 0 extrapolated to infinity) for IV and SC administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 148 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax (maximum measured concentration of the analyte in plasma) for IV and SC administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 148 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CL (total clearance of the analyte in the plasma after intravenous administration) for IV administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 148 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vss (Volume of distribution at steady state after intravenous administration) for IV administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 148 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BI 655130 dose group 1 (Intravenous)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BI 655130 dose group 2 (Intravenous)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BI 655130 dose group 3 (Intravenous)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BI 655130 dose group 4 (Subcutaneous)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Matching placebo for each dose group (Intravenous)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Matching placebo (Subcutaneous)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BI 655130</intervention_name>
    <description>single dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>BI 655130 dose group 1 (Intravenous)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BI 655130 dose group 2 (Intravenous)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BI 655130 dose group 3 (Intravenous)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>BI 655130 dose group 4 (Subcutaneous)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>single dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>Matching placebo for each dose group (Intravenous)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Matching placebo (Subcutaneous)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy male according to the investigator's assessment, based on a complete medical
             history including a physical examination, vital signs (Blood Pressure [BP], Pulse Rate
             [PR]), 12-lead Electrocardiogram [ECG], and clinical laboratory tests.

          -  Japanese ethnicity, according to the following criteria:

             -- born in Japan, have lived outside of Japan &lt;10 years, and have parents and
             grandparents who were all born in Japan

          -  Age of 20 to 45 years (incl.)

          -  Body Mass Index [BMI] of 18.5 to 25.0 kg/m2 (incl.)

          -  Signed and dated written informed consent prior to admission to the study in
             accordance with GCP and local legislation

          -  Male subjects who agree to minimize the risk of female partners being pregnant by
             fulfilling any of the following criteria starting from the first administration of
             trial medication and until 30 days after trial completion:

               -  Use of adequate contraception, e.g. any of the following methods plus condom:

        combined oral contraceptives, intrauterine device

          -  A vasectomised sexual partner (vasectomy at least 1 year prior to enrolment)

          -  Surgically sterilised (including hysterectomy) female partner

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any finding in the medical examination (including Blood Pressure [BP], Pulse Rate [PR]
             or Electrocardiogram [ECG]) is deviating from normal and judged as clinically relevant
             by the investigator

          -  Repeated measurement of systolic blood pressure outside the range of 90 to 140 mmHg,
             diastolic blood pressure outside the range of 50 to 90 mmHg, or pulse rate outside the
             range of 45 to 90 bpm

          -  Any laboratory value outside the reference range that the investigator considers to be
             of clinical relevance

          -  Any evidence of a concomitant disease judged as clinically relevant by the
             investigator

          -  Gastrointestinal, hepatic, renal, respiratory, cardiovascular, metabolic,
             immunological or hormonal disorders

          -  Diseases of the central nervous system (including but not limited to any kind of
             seizures or stroke), and other relevant neurological or psychiatric disorders

          -  History of relevant orthostatic hypotension, fainting spells, or blackouts

          -  Chronic or relevant acute infections including active tuberculosis, HIV or viral
             hepatitis; QuantiFERON TB test will be performed at screening.

          -  History of relevant allergy or hypersensitivity (including allergy to the trial
             medication or its excipients)

          -  Use of drugs within 30 days prior to administration of trial medication if that might
             reasonably influence the results of the trial (incl. QT/QTc interval prolongation)

          -  Participation in another trial where an investigational drug has been administered
             within 5 half-lives prior to planned administration of trial medication, or current
             participation in another trial involving administration of investigational drug.

          -  Administered live vaccine within 6 weeks prior to randomisation or Have plans for
             administration of live vaccines during the study period.

          -  Smoker (more than 10 cigarettes or 3 cigars or 3 pipes per day)

          -  Inability to refrain from smoking on specified trial days

          -  Alcohol abuse (consumption of more than 30 g per day)

          -  Drug abuse or positive drug screening

          -  Blood donation of more than 100 mL within 30 days prior to administration of trial
             medication or intended donation during the trial

          -  Intention to perform excessive physical activities within one week prior to
             administration of trial medication or during the trial

          -  Inability to comply with dietary regimen of trial site

          -  A marked baseline prolongation of QT/QTc interval (such as QTc intervals that are
             repeatedly greater than 450 ms in males) or any other relevant Electrocardiogram [ECG]
             finding at screening

          -  A history of additional risk factors for Torsades de Pointes (such as heart failure,
             hypokalemia, or family history of Long QT Syndrome)

          -  Subject is assessed as unsuitable for inclusion by the investigator, for instance,
             because considered not able to understand and comply with study requirements, or has a
             condition that would not allow safe participation in the study

          -  Further exclusion criteria apply
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Inje University Busan Paik Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Busan</city>
        <zip>47392</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 13, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 18, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">April 21, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

