<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02393040</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UICatalunya</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02393040</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Assess Efficacy of Platelet-Rich Plasma in Androgenetic Alopecia</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRP</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective Double Blind, Placebo Controlled Study to Assess the Efficacy of Platelet-Rich Plasma on the Treatment of Androgenetic Alopecia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universitat Internacional de Catalunya</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universitat Internacional de Catalunya</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the efficacy of treatment with Platelet-rich plasma
      on Androgenetic alopecia (compared with placebo), between six months and baseline.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Androgenetic alopecia (AGA) is a non-scarring patterned alopecia, multifactorial and a
      genetic determined skin condition. This pathology is one of the most common forms of
      progressive hair loss. It's an increasingly frequent complaint of dermatology clinic patients
      and has a high impact psychologically.

      The onset of AGA is gradual and when this pathology progresses, the anagen phase shortens and
      the telogen phase remains constant. As a result, more hairs are in the telogen phase, and the
      patient may notice an increase in hair shedding. This area varies from patient to patient and
      is usually most marked at the vertex in men while women with androgenetic alopecia generally
      lose hair diffusely over the crown. The incidence and prevalence of AGA increases with age.

      Topical minoxidil and oral finasteride are the gold standard therapies for AGA and the only
      two drugs currently that have US Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved indications for
      the treatment of androgenetic alopecia. Minoxidil and finasteride are known to be effective
      medical treatments in AGA, especially during the initial grades.

      PRP is a plasma concentrate reaped from the patient's whole blood that comprises
      predominantly platelets. Numerous growth factors (GFs) are present within platelet α
      granules. Some of the most important of these include platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF),
      transforming growth factor-beta (TGF-β), vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), epidermal
      growth factor (EGF), and insulin-like growth factor (IGF). This GFs stimulate cell
      proliferation and differentiation.

      PRP was identified as having a beneficial effect on bone grafting with applications in oral
      and maxillofacial surgery, orthopedic and cardiac surgery. More recently, increasing interest
      is seen in the application of PRP in dermatology, for example, tissue regeneration, wound
      healing such and fat grafting. It has also been shown to promote hair survival and growth,
      both in vitro and in vivo.

      The production of autologous PRP involves extraction of a specific volume of the patient's
      whole blood, which is then placed in an automated centrifuge to separate the layers of whole
      blood by their specific weight into 3 separate layers: (1) platelet-poor plasma, (2)
      platelet-rich plasma and (3) red blood cells.

      The patients were divided into two groups (A and B): group A received treatment with PRP on
      the right half-head and the placebo on the left half-head, whereas group B received treatment
      with PRP on the left half-head and the placebo on the right half-head.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the treatment efficacy by measuring hair regrowth score for each side of scalp.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the treatment efficacy by measuring hair density for each side of scalp</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Determine the treatment efficacy by measuring mean hair density for each side of scalp using the trichogram analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the treatment efficacy by measuring anagen/telogen ratio for each side of scalp</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Determine the treatment efficacy by measuring anagen/telogen ratio for each side of scalp using the trichogram analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global photographs of three areas of the scalp (evaluation of hair growth will be assessed by comparison of standardized images)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The evaluation of hair growth will be assessed by comparison of standardized images between baseline and 6 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Androgenetic Alopecia</condition>
  <condition>Alopecia</condition>
  <condition>Hair Loss</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PRP/Saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PRP/Saline
Briefly, for PRP preparation, approximately 18 mL of blood from each patient is drawn into a tube containing 3,8 % sodium citrate. The tubes were centrifuged at 450 g for 8 minutes, resulting in three basic layers: an erythrocyte layer at the bottom of the tube, a PRP layer in the middle, and a platelet-poor plasma (PPP) layer at the top of the tube. After removing the platelet-poor plasma (PPP) layer, the PRP is obtained, activated with 10 % calcium chloride.
In the same patient, PRP will be injected to half-head and in the other half-head will be injected with saline solution (placebo).
This study includes 4 visits: 3 visits (with 1-month interval) and 1 visit of follow-up (month 6).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PRP/Saline</intervention_name>
    <description>PRP/Saline: Two groups were defined: group A and group B. Group A received treatment with PRP on the right half-head and placebo on the left half-head while group B received administration of PRP on left half-head and placebo on the right half-head.
Same patient will be injected with PRP and a saline solution. Each patient will be injected on half-head.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PRP/Saline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PRP</other_name>
    <other_name>androgenetic alopecia</other_name>
    <other_name>alopecia</other_name>
    <other_name>hair Loss</other_name>
    <other_name>placebo</other_name>
    <other_name>saline</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients ≥18 years and &lt; 65 years

          -  Male patients with a clinical diagnosis of AGA (stage II to V according to the
             Hamilton-Norwood Scale)

          -  Female patients with a clinical diagnosis of AGA (stage I to III according to Ludwig
             Classification)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with other types of alopecia, other than AGA

          -  Fasting &lt; 3h prior of each injection

          -  Use of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs one week before treatment.

          -  Platelet count &lt; 150 000 μL

          -  Alterations of coagulation

          -  Heavy smokers (&gt; 20 cigarettes/day)

          -  Medications: anticoagulants/ acetylsalicylic acid

          -  Patient unable to accomplishing all fases of treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rubina Alves, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Specialist Dermatology, Universitat Internacional Catalunya</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ramon Grimalt, M.D.; PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Prof. Dermatology, Universitat Internacional Catalunya</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitat Internacional Catalunya</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08195</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 3, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 18, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 19, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 18, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 18, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 19, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universitat Internacional de Catalunya</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rubina Alves</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Specialist in Dermatology, M.D.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Alopecia</keyword>
  <keyword>Androgenetic Alopecia</keyword>
  <keyword>Alopecia, Male Pattern</keyword>
  <keyword>Hair loss</keyword>
  <keyword>Platelet-Rich Plasma</keyword>
  <keyword>Alopecia, Female Pattern</keyword>
  <keyword>placebo</keyword>
  <keyword>double-blind</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alopecia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alopecia Areata</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>April 28, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>June 6, 2016</returned>
    <submitted>June 29, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>August 10, 2016</returned>
    <submitted>August 18, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>October 12, 2016</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

