<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02392793</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BMNIRN</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2015-00255</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02392793</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Talazoparib Plus Irinotecan With or Without Temozolomide in Children With Refractory or Recurrent Solid Malignancies</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Study of Talazoparib (BMN 673) Plus Irinotecan With or Without Temozolomide in Children With Refractory or Recurrent Solid Malignancies</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>BioMarin Pharmaceutical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alliance Pharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The drug, talazoparib, seems to work against cancer in test tubes and animals by preventing
      DNA repair in damaged cells leading to their death. Investigators do not know if talazoparib
      combined with irinotecan will work in humans. Talazoparib has been used in only a small
      number of adults and children, and there is much not yet known about it.

      In Arm A of this study, investigators seek to find the safest dose of irinotecan to give with
      talazoparib to children and young adults. In a phase I study, different dose levels of drug
      may be tested. The first 2 or 3 patients will be given a dose, and if none of them has a bad
      side-effect, the next 2 or 3 patients will be given a higher dose. No temozolomide will be
      given in in Arm A.

      The experimental drug combination of talazoparib and irinotecan will be tested in the hopes
      of finding a treatment that may be effective against recurrent or refractory solid tumors.
      The goals of study Arm A are:

        -  To determine whether the combination of talazoparib and irinotecan is a beneficial
           treatment for your cancer;

        -  To learn what kind of side effects talazoparib can cause;

        -  To learn what kind of side effects talazoparib in combination with irinotecan can cause;

        -  To learn more about the biology of talazoparib in children diagnosed with solid tumors.

      The purpose of Arm B is to to find the safest doses of irinotecan and temozolomide to give
      with talazoparib to children and young adults with a solid malignancy.. Talazoparib belongs
      to a family of drugs called &quot;poly ADP ribose polymerase or PARP inhibitors.&quot; Irinotecan and
      temozolomide belong to a family of drugs called &quot;DNA damaging agents.&quot;

      There are two arms of this trial, A and B. In this study, investigators hope that irinotecan
      (administered in Arm A) and irinotecan plus temozolomide (administered in Arm B) will damage
      the DNA of the cancer cells. Then, talazoparib (which is a PARP inhibitor) will block the
      repair of the cancer cell's damaged DNA, causing the cancer cell to die (a process called
      &quot;apoptosis&quot;).

      There are different types of cancers found in children and young adults which appear to be
      vulnerable to the combination of chemotherapy agents that will be given in this study. Work
      carried out in the lab show that these agents may be very promising in the treatment of ewing
      sarcoma, germ cell tumors, wilms tumor, medulloblastoma and possibly neuroblastoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In Arm A of this study, talazoparib will be administered orally on day 1 either once or twice
      per day depending on the dose level of the enrolled participant. Both oral talazoparib and
      intravenous (IV) irinotecan will then be administered daily, on days 2-6. Each cycle will
      last 21 days.

      Once the maximum tolerated doses (MTDs) for talazoparib and irinotecan are determined, a
      second arm of the study (Arm B) will open administering talazoparib, irinotecan and
      temozolomide. Talazoparib will be given orally, on days 1-6. Intravenous irinotecan and oral
      temozolomide will be given on days 2-6. The study will estimate the maximum tolerated doses,
      describe the toxicities of therapy, estimate the response rate and characterize the
      pharmacokinetics of the combined talazoparib plus irinotecan with or without temozolomide.

      This study is a traditional dose escalation study using a standard 3+3 phase I design. In Arm
      A, six or more dose levels will be evaluated for the combination of talazoparib and
      irinotecan. Once the MTDs of Arm A are determined, Arm B will open and evaluate the
      combination of talazoparib, irinotecan and temozolomide.

      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES - ARM A

        -  To estimate the maximum tolerated doses (MTDs) of talazoparib (daily, days 1-6) combined
           with irinotecan (daily, days 2-6) given every 21 days in children with refractory or
           recurrent solid malignancies.

        -  To identify and describe the dose limiting toxicities of talazoparib and irinotecan
           administered in combination to patients with refractory or recurrent solid malignancies.

      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES - ARM B

        -  To estimate the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of temozolomide (given daily, days 2-6)
           when combined with talazoparib (daily, days 1-6) and irinotecan (daily, days 2-6) given
           every 21 days in children with refractory or recurrent solid malignancies.

        -  To identify and describe the dose limiting toxicities of temozolomide, talazoparib and
           irinotecan administered in combination to patients with refractory or recurrent solid
           malignancies.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES

        -  To estimate the response rate, within the confines of a phase I study, to talazoparib
           plus irinotecan and talazoparib plus irinotecan and temozolomide administered in
           combination in pediatric patients with refractory or recurrent solid malignancies.

        -  To characterize the pharmacokinetics of talazoparib plus irinotecan and talazoparib plus
           irinotecan and temozolomide when given in combination to children with refractory or
           recurrent solid malignancies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 25, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of talazoparib combined with irinotecan</measure>
    <time_frame>After first cycle (21 days) therapy of patients of Arm A.</time_frame>
    <description>This study is a traditional dose escalation study using a standard 3+3 phase I design to define the MTD. Six or more dose levels will be evaluated for the combination of talazoparib and irinotecan. Each cycle will last 21 days with talazoparib given daily on days 1-6 and irinotecan given daily on days 2-6.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose-limiting toxicities (DLT) of talazoparib combined with irinotecan</measure>
    <time_frame>After first cycle (21 days) therapy of patients of Arm A.</time_frame>
    <description>Dose-limiting toxicities defined in the first cycle of the combination of talazoparib and irinotecan will be summarized for patients treated at each dose level with DLTs type and grade.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of temozolomide combined with talazoparib</measure>
    <time_frame>After first cycle (21 days) therapy of patients of Arm B.</time_frame>
    <description>Once the MTD is defined for the combination of talazoparib plus irinotecan in Arm A, then temozolomide will be added to make a triple drug combination, talazoparib plus irinotecan and temozolomide. This is a traditional dose escalation study using a standard 3+3 phase I design to define the MTD. Six or more dose levels will be evaluated for the combination of talazoparib plus irinotecan and temozolomide. Each cycle will last 21 days with talazoparib given daily on days 1-6 and irinotecan and temozolomide given daily on days 2-6.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose-limited toxicities (DLT) of combination therapy with temozolomide, talazoparib and irinotecan</measure>
    <time_frame>After first cycle (21 days) therapy of patients of Arm B.</time_frame>
    <description>DLT defined in the first cycle of the combination of talazoparib plus irinotecan and temozolomide will be summarized for patients treated at each dose level with DLTs type and grade.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>After 34 cycles of therapy (approximate 24 months).</time_frame>
    <description>We will provide summary statistics for the best overall response (complete response, partial response, stable disease and progressive disease) of patients experienced during treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Irinotecan Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>days 1 and 5 (week 1) of course 1</time_frame>
    <description>A population average value and variance will be reported for week 1 of course 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Talazoparib Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>days 1 and 5 (week 1) of course 1</time_frame>
    <description>A population average value and variance will be reported for week 1 of course 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Irinotecan AUC</measure>
    <time_frame>days 1 and 5 (week 1) of course 1</time_frame>
    <description>A population average value and variance will be reported for week 1 of course 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Talazoparib AUC</measure>
    <time_frame>days 1 and 5 (week 1) of course 1</time_frame>
    <description>A population average value and variance will be reported for week 1 of course 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Irinotecan Clearance</measure>
    <time_frame>days 1 and 5 (week 1) of course 1</time_frame>
    <description>A population average value and variance will be reported for week 1 of course 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Talazoparib Clearance</measure>
    <time_frame>days 1 and 5 (week 1) of course 1</time_frame>
    <description>A population average value and variance will be reported for week 1 of course 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Irinotecan Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>days 1 and 5 (week 1) of course 1</time_frame>
    <description>A population average value and variance will be reported for week 1 of course 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Talazoparib Tmax</measure>
    <time_frame>days 1 and 5 (week 1) of course 1</time_frame>
    <description>A population average value and variance will be reported for week 1 of course 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Irinotecan t1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>days 1 and 5 (week 1) of course 1</time_frame>
    <description>A population average value and variance will be reported for week 1 of course 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Talazoparib t1/2</measure>
    <time_frame>days 1 and 5 (week 1) of course 1</time_frame>
    <description>A population average value and variance will be reported for week 1 of course 1</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Childhood Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Talazoparib Plus Irinotecan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Talazoparib will be administered orally on day 1 either once or twice per day depending on the dose level of the enrolled patient. Both oral talazoparib and IV irinotecan will then be administered daily, on days 2-6. Each cycle will last 21 days. Filgrastim or peg-filgrastim will be given following the last dose of chemotherapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Talazoparib Plus Irinotecan Plus Temozolomide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Once the maximum tolerated doses (MTDs) for talazoparib and irinotecan are determined, a second arm of the study will open administering talazoparib, irinotecan and temozolomide. Talazoparib will be given orally, days 1-6. Intravenous irinotecan and oral temozolomide will be given days 2-6. Filgrastim or peg-filgrastim will be given following the last dose of chemotherapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Talazoparib</intervention_name>
    <description>Given orally once or twice on day 1 (depending on the dose level), then daily on days 2-6.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Talazoparib Plus Irinotecan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Talazoparib Plus Irinotecan Plus Temozolomide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>BMN 673</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Irinotecan</intervention_name>
    <description>Given intravenously daily, days 2-6 immediately following the talazoparib dose.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Talazoparib Plus Irinotecan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Talazoparib Plus Irinotecan Plus Temozolomide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Camptosar®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Temozolomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Given orally daily. Dose to be determined after MTD established with talazoparib plus irinotecan.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Talazoparib Plus Irinotecan Plus Temozolomide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Temodar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Filgrastim</intervention_name>
    <description>Given subcutaneously (SubQ) once per day starting 24-36 hours after last dose of chemotherapy and continuing until post-nadir ANC is &gt;2,000/μL, unless peg-filgrastim is given.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Talazoparib Plus Irinotecan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Talazoparib Plus Irinotecan Plus Temozolomide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>G-CSF</other_name>
    <other_name>Neupogen®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peg-filgrastim</intervention_name>
    <description>Given subcutaneously (SubQ) once per day starting 24-36 hours after last dose of chemotherapy and continuing until post-nadir ANC is &gt;2,000/μL, unless filgrastim is given.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A: Talazoparib Plus Irinotecan</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B: Talazoparib Plus Irinotecan Plus Temozolomide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Pegylated filgrastim</other_name>
    <other_name>Neulasta®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Patients with refractory or recurrent solid tumors for which there is no standard
             therapy are eligible. Patients must have had histologic verification of malignancy at
             original diagnosis or at the time of relapse.

          -  12 months - 25 years at the time of enrollment on study.

          -  Patients must have a BSA of ≥ 0.42 m^2 at the time of study enrollment due to capsule
             strength(s).

          -  Patients must have either measureable or evaluable disease.

          -  Life expectancy must be at least 8 weeks.

          -  Performance status: Karnofsky ≥ 50 for patients &gt; 16 years of age; Lansky ≥ 50 for
             patients ≤ 16 years of age.

          -  Prior therapy: Patients who have received prior therapy with an irinotecan-based or
             temozolomide-based regimen are eligible. Patients who have received prior therapy with
             a PARP inhibitor other than talazoparib are eligible; however, patients who have
             progressed on a PARP inhibitor plus irinotecan regimen are not eligible.

          -  Organ function: Must have adequate organ and bone marrow function as defined by the
             following parameters:

               -  Patients with solid tumors not metastatic to bone marrow:

               -  Peripheral absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1,000/mm^3

               -  Platelet count ≥ 100,000/mm^3 (no transfusion within 7 days of enrollment)

               -  Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL (with or without support)

               -  Patients with solid tumors metastatic to bone marrow will be eligible for study
                  but not evaluable for hematologic toxicity. These patients must not be known to
                  be refractory to red cell or platelet transfusions. At least 2 of every cohort of
                  3 patients must be evaluable for hematologic toxicity. If dose limiting
                  hematologic toxicity is observed at any dose level, all subsequent patients
                  enrolled must be evaluable for hematologic toxicity.

               -  Adequate renal function defined as: Serum creatinine concentration ≤3x the
                  institutional upper limit of normal (ULN) or creatinine clearance or radioisotope
                  GFR ≥ 70ml/min/1.73m^2.

               -  Adequate liver function defined as: For Part A participants: normal liver
                  function as defined by SGPT (ALT) concentration ≤5x the institutional ULN, a
                  total bilirubin concentration ≤2x the institutional ULN for age, and serum
                  albumin ≥ 2g/dL.

               -  Adequate liver function defined as: For Part B participants: normal liver
                  function as defined by SGPT (ALT) concentration &lt; 2.5 times institutional ULN, a
                  total bilirubin concentration ≤ 1.5 times the institutional ULN for age, and
                  serum albumin ≥ 2 g/dL.

          -  Patients must have fully recovered from the acute toxic effects of chemotherapy,
             immunotherapy, surgery, or radiotherapy prior to entering this study:

               -  Myelosuppressive chemotherapy: Patient has not received myelosuppressive
                  chemotherapy within 3 weeks of enrollment onto this study (6 weeks if prior
                  nitrosourea).

               -  Hematopoietic growth factors: At least 7 days must have elapsed since the
                  completion of therapy with a growth factor. At least 14 days must have elapsed
                  after receiving pegfilgrastim.

               -  Biologic (anti-neoplastic agent): At least 7 days must have elapsed since
                  completion of therapy with a biologic agent. For agents that have known adverse
                  events occurring beyond 7 days after administration, this period prior to
                  enrollment must be extended beyond the time during which adverse events are known
                  to occur.

               -  Monoclonal antibodies: At least 3 half-lives must have elapsed since prior
                  therapy that included a monoclonal antibody.

               -  Radiotherapy: At least 2 weeks must have elapsed since any irradiation; at least
                  6 weeks must have elapsed since craniospinal RT or substantial bone marrow
                  irradiation.

          -  All patients and/or their parents or legally authorized representatives must sign a
             written informed consent. Assent will be obtained, when appropriate, according to
             institutional guidelines.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding.

               -  If sexually active and with childbearing potential, must agree to use effective
                  method of contraception, such as intrauterine device, bilateral tubal ligation
                  for ≥ 6 months before randomization, partner vasectomized for ≥ 6 months before
                  randomization, and sexual abstinence when in relation to the preferred and usual
                  lifestyle of the subject.

               -  Male subjects must use a condom when having sex with a pregnant woman and when
                  having sex with a woman of childbearing potential from the time of the first dose
                  of study drug through 105 days after the last dose of study drug.

               -  Contraception should be considered for a nonpregnant female partner of
                  childbearing potential.

               -  Male subjects with partners of childbearing potential must use a condom and
                  contraception should be considered for the female partner from the time of the
                  first dose of study drug through 105 days after the last dose of study drug.

               -  Male subjects whose partners are pregnant should use condoms for the duration of
                  the pregnancy.

               -  Male and female subjects must agree not to donate sperm or eggs, respectively,
                  from the first dose of study drug through 105 days and 45 days after the last
                  dose of study drug, respectively (hormonal contraception is not allowed) prior to
                  study entry, during treatment, and for 45 days after last dose of study drug.

               -  Females considered not of childbearing potential include those who are surgically
                  sterile (bilateral salpingectomy, bilateral oophorectomy, or hysterectomy) or who
                  are post menopausal, defined as: &lt; 55 years of age with no spontaneous menses for
                  ≥ 12 months before randomization and with a postmenopausal follicle stimulating
                  hormone (FSH) concentration &gt; 30 IU/L (or meeting criteria for post-menopausal
                  status by the local laboratory).

               -  If females with childbearing potential, a negative serum pregnancy test at
                  Screening and willing to have additional serum and urine pregnancy tests during
                  the study

               -  Note: Females without childbearing potential include those in menopause ≥2 years,
                  with tubal ligation ≥1 year before screening, or with total hysterectomy.

          -  Concomitant medications

               -  Corticosteroids: Patients receiving corticosteroids that have not been on a
                  stable or decreasing dose for at least 7 days prior to enrollment are not
                  eligible.

               -  Investigational drugs: Patients cannot receive other investigational drugs while
                  on this study.

               -  Anti-GVHD drugs post-transplant: Patients receiving cyclosporine, tacrolimus or
                  other GVHD agents are not eligible.

          -  Prior treatment with talazoparib.

          -  Unable to swallow capsules.

          -  Active, uncontrolled infection.

          -  Prior solid organ transplant.

          -  Prior total body irradiation (TBI).

          -  Unwilling or unable to comply with the safety monitoring requirements of this
             protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>25 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sara M. Federico, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sara M. Federico, MD</last_name>
    <phone>866-278-5833</phone>
    <email>referralinfo@stjude.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Memphis</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>38105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sara M. Federico, MD</last_name>
      <phone>866-278-5833</phone>
      <email>referralinfo@stjude.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sara M. Federico, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stjude.org</url>
    <description>St. Jude Children's Research Hospital</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.stjude.org/protocols</url>
    <description>Clinical Trials Open at St. Jude</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 6, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 13, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 19, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Irinotecan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Camptothecin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Temozolomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Talazoparib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dacarbazine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenograstim</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

