<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02392143</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>542376</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02392143</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Promoting CRC Screening in an Urban Minority Population</brief_title>
  <official_title>Promoting CRC Screening in a Hard-To-Reach, Low-Income Minority Population</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Teachers College, Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>1199SEIU Benefit and Pension Funds</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Teachers College, Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study (Healthy Colon Project II) is to evaluate different educational
      approaches for increasing rates of colorectal cancer (CRC) screening in a hard-to-reach urban
      minority population with health insurance.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This project is an extension of the investigators' earlier study (Healthy Colon Project I) in
      which the investigators demonstrated that telephone outreach to individuals had a significant
      effect on CRC screening in a hard-to-reach, working class, urban minority population (~27.0%
      screened who received telephone outreach vs. ~6.1% screened who received printed educational
      materials). Additional investigation suggested the possible benefits of intervening with
      primary care physicians (PCPs) regarding their CRC screening referral and follow-up
      practices.

      In the current project, the investigators conducted a 3-group randomized trial. The aims are
      as follows: Aim 1: Evaluate the incremental effect of tailored telephone education (TTE),
      over and above the effect of academic detailing (AD), for increasing rates of CRC screening
      12-months post-randomization; Aim 2: Evaluate the effect of academic detailing alone (AD)
      over minimal intervention (control group), for increasing rates of CRC screening 12-months
      post-randomization; Aim 3: Identify factors that mediate the effectiveness of the
      interventions; and Aim 4: Identify factors that moderate the effectiveness of the
      interventions among subgroups.

      In one group, participants received printed education materials. In a second group,
      participants' PCPs received academic detailing (AD) to improve CRC screening referral and
      follow-up practices. And in a third group, PCPs received AD and participants received
      tailored telephone education (TTE). Participants were members of a union-based,
      self-administered and self-insured benefit fund in the NYC metropolitan area.

      The educational intervention approaches were informed by the investigators' earlier study
      among this population, with the goal of helping participants to make an informed choice about
      screening. The CRC PEM described the importance of early detection and prevention, risk
      factors, and the importance of talking to the subject's doctor about CRC screening. The PEM
      highlighted colonoscopy as being the only test that can identify and prevent CRC and
      described how to prepare for a colonoscopy beginning seven days prior to the test. The PEM
      also described other CRC screening tests, including the FOBT, FIT, sigmoidoscopy, barium
      enema and virtual colonoscopy. Academic detailing (AD) involved an in-person visit from a
      member of the research team who attempted to communicate strategies for improving CRC
      screening uptake in the practice's patient panel. In cases where the PCP was unavailable, an
      office staff member was approached. A brief description of the RCT was followed by a
      semi-structured interview assessing usual practice regarding CRC screening referral and
      follow up. The direction of the discussion was guided by PCP responses. A variety of
      resources were provided: a binder with up-to-date scientific evidence about CRC screening
      recommendations and printed patient education materials, and order forms for refilling
      supplies. Specific directives were following up to make sure patients had made appointments
      with a gastroenterologist and offering 3-day FOBT. The detailer attempted to elicit a verbal
      commitment to do at least one new thing to strengthen the probability that patients would be
      screened. The TTE was based on the investigators' previously tested model and involved a
      semi-structured protocol in which the first goals were to build rapport and assess level of
      knowledge and readiness to be screened. In contrast to the earlier RCT, the current study's
      TTE clearly represented colonoscopy as the screening method of choice, while encouraging
      alternative screening methods as well. This emphasis was consistent with goals of the New
      York City Department of Health and Mental Hygiene and the American Cancer Society at the time
      of the study. Rapport established, the TTE dialogue focused on identifying and addressing
      barriers that might impede receipt of screening. Verbal commitments were elicited: to speak
      with the PCP and make an appointment for a colonoscopy, or request a home stool test, as
      appropriate. Follow up calls assessed progress towards achieving goals.

      Three types of data were collected. Baseline survey data assessed eligibility and measured a
      variety of demographic and other variables. Implementation data monitored the extent to which
      the AD and TTE interventions had been conducted as planned. And outcome data (CRC screening
      one year post-randomization) was based on medical claims data.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Colorectal Cancer Screening</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
    <description>defined as colonoscopy, flexibile sigmoidoscopy, barium enema, CT colonography or DNA stool test based on medical claims paid by benefit fund</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">564</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Printed Education Material</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants received printed education materials (PEM) sent by first class mail.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Academic Detailing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants' primary care physicians (PCPs) received academic detailing (AD) to improve colorectal cancer screening referral and follow-up practices.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Academic Detailing+Telephone Education</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants' primary care physicians (PCPs) received academic detailing (AD) to improve colorectal cancer screening referral and follow-up practices and participants received tailored telephone education (TTE).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Printed Education Material</intervention_name>
    <description>The printed education material described the importance of early detection and prevention, risk factors, and the importance of talking to your doctor about CRC screening. The PEM highlighted colonoscopy as being the only test that can identify and prevent CRC and described how to prepare for a colonoscopy beginning seven days prior to the test [18]. The PEM also described other CRC screening tests, including the FOBT, FIT, sigmoidoscopy, barium enema and virtual colonoscopy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Printed Education Material</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Print education</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Academic Detailing</intervention_name>
    <description>Academic detailing (AD) involved an in-person visit from a member of the research team who attempted to communicate strategies for improving CRC screening uptake in the practice's patient panel. A brief description of the RCT was followed by a semi-structured interview assessing usual practice regarding CRC screening referral and follow up. The direction of the discussion was guided by PCP responses. A variety of resources were provided. Specific directives were following up to make sure patients had made appointments with a gastroenterologist and offering home stool tests. The detailer attempted to elicit a verbal commitment to do at least one new thing to strengthen the probability that patients would be screened.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Academic Detailing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Academic Detailing+Telephone Education</intervention_name>
    <description>PCPs received AD as described in the Academic Detailing arm. In addition, participants received tailored telephone education (TTE) which focused on identifying and addressing barriers that might impede screening. Verbal commitments were elicited to speak with their PCP and make an appointment for a colonoscopy, or request a home stool test, as appropriate. Follow-up calls assessed progress towards achieving goals.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Academic Detailing+Telephone Education</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Academic Detailing+Tailored Telephone Education</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  out of compliance with recommended CRC screening

          -  having a 'regular doctor' (for women, could be gynecologist)

          -  stated intention to remain in benefit fund for at least one year

          -  age 50 to 75

          -  reachable by telephone

          -  able to communicate in English

          -  ability to grant informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  colonoscopy in past 10 years

          -  flexible sigmoidoscopy, barium enema or CT colonography in past 5 years

          -  stool DNA in past 3 years

          -  3 day FOBT or FIT within past year

          -  history of colorectal polyps, inflammatory bowel disease, irritable bowel syndrome,
             Crohn's disease, ulcerative colitis, or current treatment for any type of cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Charles E Basch, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Teachers College, Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 12, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 17, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 18, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 17, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 17, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 18, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>colorectal cancer screening</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

