<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02390544</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014-5123</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02390544</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pharmacokinetic Study of Melphalan in Children</brief_title>
  <official_title>Melphalan Pharmacokinetics in Children Undergoing Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to examine the pharmacokinetics (PK) of melphalan in children
      undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT). Melphalan is an important
      component of HSCT preparative regimens, but can be associated with significant toxicity. PK
      data is a powerful clinical tool that, when used to develop individualized treatment plans
      for a specific patient, may ultimately increase the likelihood of selecting the right dose
      for the right patient and/or of reducing the number of adverse drug events. The
      investigators' goal is to establish baseline pediatric melphalan PK data. These data may be
      used for patient specific dosing of melphalan in the future to minimize toxicity and improve
      transplant outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (HSCT) continues to be the only curative therapy for
      patients with many hematological diseases. The adverse effects associated with chemotherapy
      agents used as part of HSCT preparative regimens are not insignificant and can be life
      threatening at times. The investigators' central hypothesis is that increased systemic
      exposure to melphalan due to variation in PK in younger children leads to increased toxicity
      seen in them. Although the PK of melphalan has been studied in animal models and in adult
      patients, limited data exists in pediatric patients especially those undergoing allogeneic
      HSCT. The objective of this study is to describe the pharmacokinetics of melphalan in
      children undergoing hematopoietic stem cell transplantation. Up to forty patients who are
      scheduled to receive melphalan as part of their preparative regimen will be enrolled. Prior
      to the start of the preparative regimen, study participants will receive a test dose of
      melphalan (10% of the standard dose). Blood samples will be collected at specific time points
      prior to and after the administration of the test dose and again around the full standard
      dose of melphalan. This study will establish that a novel method (dry blood spot assay) of
      determining PK of melphalan can be utilized in the clinical setting. Additionally, urine
      samples will be collected to measure markers of kidney injury, which will help correlate
      melphalan exposure with toxicity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To characterize the pharmacokinetics of melphalan in children undergoing HSCT</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to the melphalan infusion, and then approximately 5 min, 15 min, 30 min, 45 min, 60 min, 2, 2.5, 4, and 6 hours after the end of the melphalan infusion.</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected at the above time points around the test dose of melphalan and again around the standard full dose of melphalan. AUC will be used to characterize the pharmacokinetics of melphalan.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perform measurement of acute kidney injury marker, KIM-1</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to the melphalan infusion and approximately 8 hours and 24 hours following the end of melphalan infusion.</time_frame>
    <description>Urine samples will be collected at the above time points around the test dose of melphalan and again around the standard full dose of melphalan for measurement of KIM-1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Perform measurement of acute kidney injury marker, NGAL</measure>
    <time_frame>Prior to the melphalan infusion and approximately 8 hours and 24 hours following the end of melphalan infusion.</time_frame>
    <description>Urine samples will be collected at the above time points around the test dose of melphalan and again around the standard full dose of melphalan for measurement of NGAL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Melphalan in Patients Receiving HSCT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The investigators will recruit approximately 30 patients who are scheduled to undergo allogeneic transplant with reduced intensity conditioning that includes melphalan. Approximately 10 patients who will receive melphalan as part of their conditioning regimen for an autologous transplant will also be recruited.
A test dose of melphalan will be administered prior to the start of the HSCT preparative regimen. The test dose will equal 10% of the standard dose. Blood samples will be drawn for pharmacokinetic measurement prior to and after the administration of the test dose and again around the full standard dose of melphalan. Urine samples will also be collected around the test dose and full standard dose of melphalan to measure markers of kidney injury.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Melphalan</intervention_name>
    <description>Melphalan is a bifunctional alkylating agent that inhibits DNA and RNA synthesis, cross-links strands of DNA and acts on both resting and rapidly dividing cells including tumor cells. It is administered intravenously.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Melphalan in Patients Receiving HSCT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Alkeran</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients undergoing either allogeneic RIC HSCT, or autologous transplant containing
             melphalan as part of the preparative regimen at CCHMC will be included.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Failure to sign informed consent, or inability to undergo informed consent process.

          -  It is not medically advisable to obtain the specimens necessary for this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sharat Chandra, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Parinda Mehta, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Medical Center, Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sara K Loveless, BSN, RN</last_name>
    <phone>513-803-7656</phone>
    <email>sara.loveless@cchmc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Melanie Jordan</last_name>
    <phone>513-636-4379</phone>
    <email>melanie.jordan@cchmc.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Children's Hospital Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 4, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 11, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 17, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 5, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>children</keyword>
  <keyword>bone marrow transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melphalan</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

