<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02398721</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UW 14-500</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02398721</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study on HRQOL and Cost-effectiveness Analysis in Management of Patients With &lt;2cm Thyroid Nodules</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Randomized Study on Health-related Quality of Life of Patients With Incidental Small (&lt;2cm) Asymptomatic Thyroid Nodules and Cost-effectiveness Analysis in Managing Small Incidental Thyroid Nodules</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Ideally randomized controlled trials should be carried out to compare the cost-effectiveness
      between FNAC and watchful waiting but such studies are very difficult to conduct in practice
      because they require following up very large number of subjects for a long period of time.

      The aims are to determine the health-related quality of life (HRQOL) and HRQOL preference
      (utility) of patients undergoing watchful observation (no FNAC) and routine FNAC, and to
      determine the cost-effectiveness of two strategies in managing small incidental thyroid
      nodules for the Chinese population in Hong Kong.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 31, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The measurement of HRQoL by SF-6D Health Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
    <description>Health-related Quality of Life (HRQoL) preference value measured by The Chinese (HK) SF-6D Health Survey will be calculated by the Hong Kong population specific algorithm. It ranges from 0 (dead) to 1 (perfect health)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effectiveness of managing small incidental thyroid nodules and treatment effect on the HRQOL of patients with thyroid carcinoma</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
    <description>The effectiveness of managing small incidental thyroid nodules is quantified by quality-adjusted life years (QALYs), which will be calculated as the product of average duration of each stage (including no illness) and the SF-6D preference value for that particular health state.
The direct health care costs of different strategies in managing small incidental thyroid nodules will be estimated using the costs published by the Government Gazette and previous literatures.
HRQOL measured by the Chinese (Hong Kong) Short Form-12 (SF-12) Health Survey version 2 and FACT-G will be evaluated to identify these major problem of life.
Health service utilizations of patients with thyroid neoplasm will be surveyed.
Treatment effect on the HRQOL of patients with thyroid carcinoma will be explored.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">314</enrollment>
  <condition>Thyroid Nodules</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FNAC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients will then be randomized routine FNAC strategy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No FNAC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients will be randomized to watchful observation strategy (no FNAC)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fine Needle Aspiration Cytology</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>FNAC</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>FNAC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 18 or above

          -  Have life expectancy of at least 6 months

          -  Have an incidental nodule which measures between 1.0 to 2.0cm in the largest dimension
             on ultrasound guidance (USG) and has benign ultrasonographic features such as
             spongiform or honeycomb appearance, purely-cystic, egg shell type calcification,
             iso-echoic or hyper-echoic in relation to the rest of the thyroid tissue and
             peripheral vascularity on Doppler USG. For subjects with more than one nodule on USG,
             provided that the other nodules are not &gt;2.0cm or have suspicious features (see
             below), they will still be eligible.

          -  Normal thyroid function (both serum thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH) and free T4
             levels within normal range)

          -  Given consent to take part in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have suspicious ultrasonographic features such as microcalcifications, marked
             hypoechogenicity, irregular margins and / or taller than wide and intranodular
             vascularity on transverse view on Doppler USG that warrant a FNAC

          -  Nodule size &gt; 2.0cm

          -  Insisting or refusing FNAC or surgical intervention despite medical reassurance

          -  Inability to understand or communicate in Cantonese or Chinese

          -  Significant cognitive impairment judged by the doctor to be unable to answer the
             questionnaire

          -  Too ill to carry out interview

          -  Refusal to give consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Mary Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reiners C, Wegscheider K, Schicha H, Theissen P, Vaupel R, Wrbitzky R, Schumm-Draeger PM. Prevalence of thyroid disorders in the working population of Germany: ultrasonography screening in 96,278 unselected employees. Thyroid. 2004 Nov;14(11):926-32.</citation>
    <PMID>15671771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Van den Bruel A, Francart J, Dubois C, Adam M, Vlayen J, De Schutter H, Stordeur S, Decallonne B. Regional variation in thyroid cancer incidence in Belgium is associated with variation in thyroid imaging and thyroid disease management. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2013 Oct;98(10):4063-71. doi: 10.1210/jc.2013-1705. Epub 2013 Aug 21.</citation>
    <PMID>23966243</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mazzaferri EL. Management of a solitary thyroid nodule. N Engl J Med. 1993 Feb 25;328(8):553-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8426623</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mehanna HM, Jain A, Morton RP, Watkinson J, Shaha A. Investigating the thyroid nodule. BMJ. 2009 Mar 13;338:b733. doi: 10.1136/bmj.b733. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19286747</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McLeod DS, Sawka AM, Cooper DS. Controversies in primary treatment of low-risk papillary thyroid cancer. Lancet. 2013 Mar 23;381(9871):1046-57. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)62205-3. Epub 2013 Mar 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23668555</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sosa JA, Hanna JW, Robinson KA, Lanman RB. Increases in thyroid nodule fine-needle aspirations, operations, and diagnoses of thyroid cancer in the United States. Surgery. 2013 Dec;154(6):1420-6; discussion 1426-7. doi: 10.1016/j.surg.2013.07.006. Epub 2013 Oct 2.</citation>
    <PMID>24094448</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonavita JA, Mayo J, Babb J, Bennett G, Oweity T, Macari M, Yee J. Pattern recognition of benign nodules at ultrasound of the thyroid: which nodules can be left alone? AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2009 Jul;193(1):207-13. doi: 10.2214/AJR.08.1820.</citation>
    <PMID>19542415</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ito Y, Miyauchi A, Inoue H, Fukushima M, Kihara M, Higashiyama T, Tomoda C, Takamura Y, Kobayashi K, Miya A. An observational trial for papillary thyroid microcarcinoma in Japanese patients. World J Surg. 2010 Jan;34(1):28-35. doi: 10.1007/s00268-009-0303-0.</citation>
    <PMID>20020290</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pacini F. Management of papillary thyroid microcarcinoma: primum non nocere! J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2013 Apr;98(4):1391-3. doi: 10.1210/jc.2013-1634.</citation>
    <PMID>23564944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moon WJ, Baek JH, Jung SL, Kim DW, Kim EK, Kim JY, Kwak JY, Lee JH, Lee JH, Lee YH, Na DG, Park JS, Park SW; Korean Society of Thyroid Radiology (KSThR); Korean Society of Radiology. Ultrasonography and the ultrasound-based management of thyroid nodules: consensus statement and recommendations. Korean J Radiol. 2011 Jan-Feb;12(1):1-14. doi: 10.3348/kjr.2011.12.1.1. Epub 2011 Jan 3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21228935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Thyroid Association (ATA) Guidelines Taskforce on Thyroid Nodules and Differentiated Thyroid Cancer, Cooper DS, Doherty GM, Haugen BR, Kloos RT, Lee SL, Mandel SJ, Mazzaferri EL, McIver B, Pacini F, Schlumberger M, Sherman SI, Steward DL, Tuttle RM. Revised American Thyroid Association management guidelines for patients with thyroid nodules and differentiated thyroid cancer. Thyroid. 2009 Nov;19(11):1167-214. doi: 10.1089/thy.2009.0110. Erratum in: Thyroid. 2010 Jun;20(6):674-5. Thyroid. 2010 Aug;20(8):942. Hauger, Bryan R [corrected to Haugen, Bryan R].</citation>
    <PMID>19860577</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 20, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 24, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 25, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Lang Hung Hin, Brian</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>FNAC</keyword>
  <keyword>Small Incidental Thyroid Nodules</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Thyroid Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thyroid Nodule</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

