<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00663650</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00663650</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Periocular Basal Cell Carcinoma (BCC): Permanent vs. Frozen Section Pathological Control</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Clinical Trial in the Surgical Treatment of Basal Cell Carcinoma of the Eyelid: Surgical Excision With Frozen Section vs. Permanent Section Control</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Queen's University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Queen's University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is an equivalency study designed as a randomized clinical trial. Patients with a
      biopsy proven nodular periocular basal cell carcinoma (BCC) who have agreed to have surgical
      excision will be eligible. Study patients will undergo surgical excision of the lesion and
      then be randomized to having frozen section or permanent section pathological control. For
      those patients randomized to permanent section control the sample will be sent to pathology
      and surgical reconstruction will be performed. Patients randomized to frozen section will
      have additional margins re-excised before reconstruction depending on the pathologic results.
      Tumor clearance rates after surgical excision will be compared between the two techniques as
      a primary study question. Patients will be followed long-term to determine recurrence rates
      in the two groups. The study is designed to determine if the two techniques are equivalent
      within a given margin of error with respect to outcome measures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Basal cell carcinoma (BCC) accounts for 80-90% of skin cancers and is the most common skin
      cancer of the periocular region. Surgical excision is considered the gold-standard in
      therapy. Previous literature has shown comparable recurrence rates of BCC between surgical
      excision with frozen section control and surgical excision and permanent section control. To
      data, there are no prospective studies comparing frozen section control with permanent
      section control. We hypothesize that short term tumor clearance rates between frozen section
      and permanent section control will be similar and that long-term tumor recurrence rates will
      be similar between the two techniques. If we find that these two treatment options are
      equivalent with respect to margin control and recurrence rates, then considerable time and
      money savings can be accrued through using permanent section control amongst patients with
      periocular BCC.

      The study design is a single-blind randomized controlled trial. Patients who have already
      agreed to surgical excision of nodular type periocular BCC will be eligible. All patients
      will undergo a detailed informed consent process. All patients will undergo a punch biopsy to
      confirm the histopathological diagnosis of BCC. The study design will be a single-blinded,
      randomized clinical trial. Statistically, the study will be designed as an equivalency study.
      Prior to randomization the BCC will be excised with 3mm clinical margins in a standard
      fashion. Subjects will then be randomized to one of two groups: 1. Frozen section control; 2.
      Permanent section control. For those patients randomized to permanent section control the
      clinical sample will be sent for pathologic analysis and surgical reconstruction will be
      performed immediately using standard oculoplastic techniques. Patients randomized to frozen
      section will have additional margins re-excised if necessary depending on the pathologic
      results. Oculoplastic reconstruction will be performed after all margins are clear. Patients
      will undergo examinations at the following times to assess for clinical recurrence: 1. 2
      weeks and as necessary thereafter to assess surgical result and wound healing, 2. 6 months,
      3. 1 year, 4. yearly up to 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>August 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of BCC's that are pathologically clear of tumor cells in the permanent section group compared with the frozen section group (presumably clear for all patients).</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical recurrence at 3 years</measure>
    <time_frame>4.5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">290</enrollment>
  <condition>Basal Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Permanent Section Control</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Frozen Section Control</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Permanent Section Control</intervention_name>
    <description>After surgical excision of the tumor, margins will be sent for permanent section pathologic control to determine if the tumor was completely excised</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Frozen Section Control</intervention_name>
    <description>After surgical excision of the tumor, tumor edges will be analyzed by frozen section at the time of surgery. If tumor margins are positive with the frozen section, additional tissue will be excised and analyzed again. This process will be repeated until all tissue edges are clear of tumor. Finally, the area of tumor excision will be surgically reconstructed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years old or greater

          -  Diagnosed with clinically nodular BCC in the periocular region confirmed by tissue
             biopsy

          -  Agreeable and medically able to undergo surgical excision of the BCC

          -  Able to give informed consent and consent has been signed

          -  Able to return for all follow up visits

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  BCC greater than 2cm in diameter (based on clinical examination)

          -  Patient with a medical condition predisposing to multiple BCC's (ex. basal cell nevus
             syndrome)

          -  Recurrent BCC's (i.e. a BCC that has been treated previously by surgical or other
             modality and has recurred will not be eligible)

          -  Clinically aggressive morpheaform subtype of BCC
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vladimir Kratky, MD, FRCSC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, Queen's University, Kingston, ON</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vladimir Kratky, MD, FRCSC</last_name>
    <phone>613-544-3400</phone>
    <phone_ext>2169</phone_ext>
    <email>kratkyv@queensu.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hotel Dieu Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kingston</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K7L 5G2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 18, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 21, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 22, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 11, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 11, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 12, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Vladimir Kratky, MD, FRCSC</name_title>
    <organization>Department of Ophthalmology, Queen's University, Kingston, ON, Canada</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Basal Cell Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>BCC</keyword>
  <keyword>Periocular BCC</keyword>
  <keyword>Frozen Section Control</keyword>
  <keyword>Permanent Section Control</keyword>
  <keyword>Recurrence Rates</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Basal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

