<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00669981</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R34MH076813</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R34MH076813</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>DSIR 83-ATAS</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00669981</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness of Cognitive Behavioral Couples Therapy for Post-traumatic Stress Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cognitive-Behavioral Couples Therapy for Posttraumatic Stress Disorder</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ryerson University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ryerson University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the effectiveness of cognitive behavioral couples therapy designed
      for post-traumatic stress disorder in reducing symptoms of post-traumatic stress disorder and
      in improving relationship functioning.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) is a highly prevalent and disabling disorder that
      affects about 7.7 million adults in the United States. PTSD can develop after someone
      experiences a particularly distressing event that may involve the threat of or actual
      physical harm. Common symptoms of PTSD include avoidance of situations or cues that may act
      as reminders of the event, reoccurring flashbacks of the event, loss of interest in
      previously enjoyed activities, and numbing of emotions. Additionally, PTSD is often
      associated with far-reaching and devastating interpersonal relationship problems that can
      maintain or aggravate other PTSD symptoms. These interpersonal problems can also interfere
      with successful treatment delivery, so addressing such problems is important for improving
      treatment compliance, effectiveness, and long-term success. Cognitive behavioral therapy
      (CBT) is a type of psychotherapy that teaches ways to modify thoughts and behaviors that
      contribute to PTSD. CBT that is adapted for couples in which one partner has PTSD may be the
      most effective means of decreasing individual PTSD symptoms and improving the couple's
      relationship. This study will evaluate the effectiveness of cognitive behavioral couples
      therapy (CBCT) for PTSD in reducing symptoms of PSTD and in improving relationship
      functioning for couples in which one partner has PTSD.

      Participation in this study will last 8 months. All participants will undergo baseline
      assessments that will include an interview about exposure to traumatic events, PTSD symptoms,
      mental health problems, and substance use; self-report questionnaires about mood, social and
      leisure activities, and relationships; and a brief video-recorded communication session as a
      couple. Eligible participants will then be assigned randomly to receive immediate CBCT for
      PTSD or delayed CBCT for PTSD. Participants in the delayed treatment group will receive
      active treatment after a 3-month waitlist period. CBCT for PTSD will include fifteen
      75-minute couples therapy sessions, occurring twice weekly for 3 weeks and weekly for the
      remaining 9 weeks of treatment. Sessions will follow manual-based couples therapy and will
      aim to both decrease individual PTSD symptoms and enhance dyadic functioning. After each
      session, participants will also complete out-of-session practice assignments that will
      include completing worksheets and practicing skills taught in therapy sessions.

      Participants receiving immediate CBCT for PTSD will undergo subsequent assessments at
      mid-treatment, end of treatment, and 3 months after the end of treatment. Participants
      receiving delayed treatment will undergo assessments 1 and 3 months into the wait-list period
      and at the end of treatment. Assessments will include questions about PTSD and mental health
      symptoms, alcohol and substance use, intimate relationship functioning, and family and social
      activities. Participants will repeat the communication session after the end of treatment for
      the group receiving immediate therapy and at the end of the wait-list period for the delayed
      treatment group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinician-Administered PTSD Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, and 3-month follow-up</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dyadic Adjustment Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at pre-treatment, mid-treatment, post-treatment, and 3-month follow-up</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Post-traumatic Stress Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive immediate cognitive behavioral couples therapy for PTSD.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive delayed cognitive behavioral couples therapy for PTSD after a 3-month waitlist period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive behavioral couples therapy for post-traumatic stress disorder (CBCT for PTSD)</intervention_name>
    <description>CBCT for PTSD is a 15-session manualized couples therapy that aims to both decrease individual PTSD symptoms and improve dyadic functioning.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Current diagnosis of PTSD

          -  An intimate partner willing to participate in treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Both partners have PTSD

          -  Either partner with substance dependence not in remission for at least 3 months before
             study entry, current uncontrolled bipolar or psychotic disorder, or severe cognitive
             impairment

          -  Couple currently experiencing severe intimate aggression or a desire to separate or
             end their intimate relationship
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Candice M. Monson, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ryerson University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Boston Healthcare System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02130</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ryerson University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5B 2K3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Monson CM, Schnurr PP, Stevens SP, Guthrie KA. Cognitive-Behavioral Couple's Treatment for posttraumatic stress disorder: initial findings. J Trauma Stress. 2004 Aug;17(4):341-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15462542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Monson CM, Fredman SJ, Adair KC. Cognitive-behavioral conjoint therapy for posttraumatic stress disorder: application to operation enduring and Iraqi Freedom veterans. J Clin Psychol. 2008 Aug;64(8):958-71. doi: 10.1002/jclp.20511.</citation>
    <PMID>18613094</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 29, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 29, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 1, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 22, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 22, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 26, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ryerson University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Candice Monson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor &amp; Director of Clinical Training</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PTSD</keyword>
  <keyword>Relationship Distress</keyword>
  <keyword>Couple Therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

