<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00665314</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AMD3100-EU23</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>EudraCT number: 2006-00424729</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00665314</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Safety and Efficacy of the Addition of AMD3100 to a G-CSF Mobilization Regimen in Patients With Lymphoma (NHL and HD) and Multiple Myeloma (MM).</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multicenter, Randomized, Comparative, Patient-blinded Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of G-CSF Alone Versus AMD3100 (240 µg/kg) Added to a G-CSF Mobilization Regimen in Adult Patients With Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma (NHL), Hodgkins Disease (HD) or Multiple Myeloma (MM) Who Have Previously Failed Stem Cell Collections or Collection Attempts</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Genzyme, a Sanofi Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sanofi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Some patients with multiple myeloma or lymphoma will need treatment with high dose
      chemotherapy to treat their condition. This potent treatment will kill many of the
      blood-forming cells in the bone marrow. The patient will therefore need these blood-forming
      cells replaced after the chemotherapy treatment. This is done by collecting some of teh
      patients own blood-forming stem cells before chemotherapy, storing them and then infusing
      them into the patient after chemotherapy (in the same way as a blood transfusion is given).
      The stem cells will then make their way unto the bone marrow and re-populate it. Having stem
      cells collected and returned later is called an &quot;Autologous Transplant&quot;.

      In most patients these blood-forming stem cells (which normally live in the bone marrow) are
      &quot;mobilized&quot; into the blood stream where they are then collected by a process called apheresis
      (a bit like donating blood). This process of mobilization is not always successful. In this
      study patients who did not collect enough stem cells in a previous cell collection attempt to
      have an autologous stem cell transplant will participate. Patients will be mobilized with
      G-CSF (current standard treatment to mobilize stem cells) and the effect of adding AMD3100 to
      G-CSF will be studied by comparing outcomes in patients who get G-CDF with placebo
      (non-active substance which looks like AMD3100) to patients who get G-CSF with AMD3100.

      AMD3100 is a member of a new class of medications called &quot;chemokine inhibitors&quot;. The drug
      triggers the movement of stem cells out of the bone marrow into the blood stream. In previous
      studies with healthy volunteers and cancer patients, when AMD3100 and G-CSF were used in
      combination, a greater number of stem cells were mobilized into the blood stream than by
      using g-CSF alone.

      The purposes of this study are to measure how many stem cells can be collected, the number of
      days to collect those cells and the safety of a mobilization regimen of AMD3100 with G-CSF
      compared to G-CSF with placebo. If enough cells are collected to have a transplant, the study
      will also evaluate how well the cells grow when transplanted.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter, randomized, comparative, patient-blinded study. Patients with NHL, HD
      or MM who would benefit from an autologous stem cell transplant, who failed previous
      collections or collection attempts with a mobilization regimen of chemotherapy with or
      wihoutG-CSF, and who meet the inclusion/exclusion criteria are eligible to receive
      AMD3100(240µg/kg) or placebo (both given as an evening dose).

      Patients will undergo mobilization with G-CSF (10µg/kg) for 4 consecutive days. On Day 4,
      AMD3100 (240µg/kg) or placebo will be administered in the evening prior to the first
      apheresis and each subsequent evening prior to apheresis thereafter, such that there is a 10
      to 11 hour interval between dosing and the initiation of apheresis. Patients will continue to
      receive G-CSF on each day of apheresis. G-CSF will be administered in the morning and
      approximately 1 hour prior to apheresis. Patients will undergo a minimum of 2 and a maximum
      of 7 aphereses until a minimum of 2x10^6 CD34+ cells/kg or greater than or equal to 5x10^6
      CD34+cells/kg are collected. More cells may be collected, if done within the 7 aphereses.
      Patients who are to receive a tandem transplant will undergo a minimum of 2 and maximum of 7
      aphereses until a minimum of 4x10^6 CD34+ cells/kg are collected. Aphereses should be
      performed on consecutive days (including weekend days)

      The patient will have a peripheral blood (PB) sample collected to measure the number of CD34+
      cell in PB at baseline prior to administration of G-CSF, prior to each administration of
      AMD3100 or placebo and at the initiation of apheresis. In addition, a sample will be obtained
      from each apheresis product to measure the number of CD34+ cells collected in the apheresis
      product.

      Patients who fail to collect greater than or equal to 0.8x10^6 CD34+ cells/kg in 7 aphereses
      will be offered a rescue arm giving AMD3100 plus G-CSF.

      Patients will undergo their ablative chemotherapy before transplantation. Patients will then
      be transplanted. The success of the transplantation will be evaluated. Graft durability will
      be evaluated to 12 months post-transplant. In the event that a sufficient number of cells for
      transplantation are not obtained from the collections, cells may be retained, pooled, and
      transplanted at a later date at the Investigator's discretion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine if patients reach a target of ≥ 2x10^6 CD34+ cells/kg within 2 days of apheresis in Non-Hodgkin's Lymphoma (NHL), Hodgkin's Disease (HD) or Multiple Myeloma (MM) patients who are proven poor mobilizer.</measure>
    <time_frame>after last apheresis</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To examine and compare the safety of both mobilization regimens, G-CSF plus AMD3100(240µg/kg) and G-CSF plus placebo in NHL, MM and HD patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>After each dose of AMD3100</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To measure the daily and total number of CD34+ cells harvested during apheresis.</measure>
    <time_frame>After each dose of AMD3100</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To measure the number of days of apheresis needed to harvest ≥ 2x10^6 CD34+ cells/kg.</measure>
    <time_frame>After each dose of AMD3100 transplantation and engraftment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To measure the number of days of apheresis needed to harvest ≥ 5x10^6 CD34+ cells/kg.</measure>
    <time_frame>After each dose of AMD3100, transplantation and engraftment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the times of platelet (PLT) and polymorphonuclear leukocyte (PMN) engraftment.</measure>
    <time_frame>After each dose of AMD3100, transplantation and engraftment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the durability of engraftment.</measure>
    <time_frame>After each dose of AMD3100, transplantation and engraftment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine if patient reach the Optimum Target of 5x10^6 CD34+ cells/kg within 4 days of apheresis.</measure>
    <time_frame>After each dose of AMD3100, transplantation and engraftment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine if NHL tumor cells are mobilized after either G-CSF mobilization of AMD3100 administration</measure>
    <time_frame>After G-CSF mobilization period and after each dose of AMD3100</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Non Hodgkin's Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Hodgkin's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AMD3100 added to a G-CSF Mobilisation regimen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>AMD3100 added to a G-CSF Mobilisation regimen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>G-CSF plus placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>G-CSF plus placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Plerixafor (AMD3100)</intervention_name>
    <description>0.24mg/kg SC for 2 to 7 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AMD3100 added to a G-CSF Mobilisation regimen</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Can be any registered nonpegylated form of G-CSF</intervention_name>
    <description>10mcg/kg SC for 4 days followed by an additional 2 to 7 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>G-CSF plus placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Eligible to undergo autologous transplantation.

          -  Diagnosis of NHL, HD or MM [patients with plasma cell leukemia or other leukemias
             including chronic lymphocytic leukemia (CLL), are excluded].

          -  In the last collection attempt prior to entry into this trial, the patient has failed
             to collect 0.8x10^6 cells/kg in at least 2 apheresis sessions or 2x10^6 cells/kg in 4
             apheresis sessions using a mobilization regimen of chemotherapy, with or without
             G-CSF.

          -  A minimum of a 7 day interval between last collection attempt and randomization.

          -  Cardiac, pulmonary and renal function deemed clinically adequate to be able to undergo
             mobilization and transplant.

          -  Performance status, Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) of 0 or 1

          -  ≥ 21 days between the last cycle of chemotherapy and randomization (thalidomide,
             dexamethasone, and other corticosteroids, Rituxan® and Velcade® are not considered
             prior chemotherapy for the purpose of this study).

          -  The patient has recovered from all acute toxic effects of prior chemotherapy.

          -  WBC ≥ 2.5x10^9/l.

          -  Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1.5x10^9/l.

          -  Platelet count ≥ 75x10^9/l.

          -  Adequate renal function as demonstrated by serum creatine ≤ or equal to 2.2 mg/dl or
             creatinine clearance (24 hr urine collection)≥ 60 ml/min

          -  Serum Glutamate Oxaloacetate Transaminase (SGOT), Serum Glutamate Pyruvate
             Transaminase (SGPT) and total bilirubin ≤ 2.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN).

          -  Signed informed consent.

          -  All patients must agree to use a highly effective method of contraception (including
             both female patients of child-bearing potential and male patients with child-bearing
             potential partners). Effective birth control includes: a) birth control pills,
             depo-progesterone, or an IUD PLUS one barrier method, or b) two barrier methods.
             Effective barrier methods are: male and female condoms, diaphragms, and spermicides
             (creams or gels that contain a chemical to kill sperm). For patients using hormonal
             contraceptive method, information about any interaction of MAD3100 with hormonal
             contraceptives is not known.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A co-morbid condition which, in the view of the Investigators, renders the patient at
             high risk from treatment complications.

          -  A residual acute medical condition resulting from prior chemotherapy.

          -  Received thalidomide, dexamethasone or corticosteroids, Rituxan® and Velcade® within 7
             days prior to randomization.

          -  Brain metastases or carcinomatous meningitis.

          -  Active acute or chronic infection or anti-infective therapy within 1 week prior to
             randomization.

          -  Fever (temperature ≥ 38 degrees celsius).

          -  Hypercalcemia (≥ 1mg/dl above the ULN).

          -  Known to be HIV-positive.

          -  Pregnant and nursing females.

          -  Patient unwilling to implement adequate birth control (including both female patients
             of child-bearing potential and male patients with child-bearing potential partners).

          -  Patients who previously received experimental therapy within 4 weeks of randomization
             or who are currently enrolled in another experimental protocol during the Mobilization
             phase.

          -  Patients who have failed previous collection attempt within 7 days or less from
             randomization.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>78 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Monitor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Genzyme, a Sanofi Company</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Cologne</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Dresden</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Nürnberg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Würzburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 21, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 22, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 23, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 10, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 10, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 11, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mobilisation stem cells</keyword>
  <keyword>G-CSF Mobilisation Regimen</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Multiple Myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>Adult patients with lymphoma (Non Hodgkin's Lymphoma, Hodgkin's Disease) or Multiple Myeloma who previously failed Stem Cell Collections or Collection attempts.</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, Non-Hodgkin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hodgkin Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lenograstim</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>JM 3100</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

