<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02848209</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PEEL1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02848209</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Histological Skin Changes of Different Peeling Agents in Surgically Subcutaneous Undermined Skin</brief_title>
  <official_title>Histological Evaluation of Peeling Induced Skin Changes of Different Peeling Agents in Surgically Subcutaneous Undermined Skin Flaps in Facelift Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital Tuebingen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ocean Clinic Marbella, Spain</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital Tuebingen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to examine the histological skin changes induced by different
      peeling agents (Trichloroacetic acid 25% and 40% and phenol/croton oil) in subcutaneous
      undermined facial skin flaps.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Written informed consent has to be obtained from 9 random female Caucasian patients aged
      between 40 and 80 years who will receive a Peeling assisted volume enhancing (PAVE) facelift
      procedure in Ocean Clinic, Marbella Spain, to take part in the histologic case control study
      with a within-subjects design.

      After completing the facelift, the subcutaneous undermined abundant pre-auricular skin of
      both sides which is to be resected as consequence of the lift anyhow of each study patient is
      not resected and split completely in half to yield four samples of the same size, two on each
      side, without contacting each other in order to prevent any interaction between the peeling
      agents (n=9 samples per treatment). One sample serves as the control, while the other three
      samples are each treated with different peeling agents by the same surgeon: Trichloroacetic
      acid (TCA) peel at concentrations of 20% and 40% and a phenol/croton oil peel. The TCA
      samples are peeled immediately for 2 to 4 minutes until even frosting and neutralized at the
      even frosting point. The phenol/croton oil peeled samples are occluded with silicone tape for
      24 hours and not neutralized. After 24 hours during the routine in-hospital stay of the
      patient, the skin samples are resected, the preauricular wound is closed, and all samples are
      placed in 10 % neutral buffered formalin. The samples are immediately processed, trimmed,
      embedded, sectioned and stained with haematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) by the same researcher.
      Histological evaluation which will take place in Tuebingen is carried out using a microscope,
      and pictures are captured at 10x, 25x and 100x magnification using a digital camera. Two
      trained histological examiners blinded to the study design independently perform histological
      evaluations. The depth of necrosis in µm is determined by analysing the tissue damage in
      relation to histological skin layers. All slices are evaluated using light microscopy to
      assess the mean depth of necrosis in three samples at three different sites for each
      specimen. The vertical height in µm between the cutaneous basal membrane and the deepest
      penetration of tissue damage is measured as well as the total thickness of the epidermis and
      dermis. Based on the histomorphological changes, actual peeling depth is determined and
      classified analogously to the current classification of burns: superficial,
      superficial-partial, deep-partial and full thickness.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Peeling depth</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The vertical height in µm between the cutaneous basal membrane and the deepest penetration of tissue damage is measured as well as the total thickness of the epidermis and dermis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Chemical burn grade</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Based on the histomorphological changes, actual peeling depth is determined and classified analogously to the current classification of burns: superficial, superficial-partial, deep-partial and full thickness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">9</enrollment>
  <condition>Burn of Face, Head and/or Neck</condition>
  <condition>Peeling</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No peeling applied on the skin flap</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Drug: TCA 20% Peeling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Trichloroacetic acid 20% applied on the skin flap until even frosting for 2-4 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Drug: TCA 40% Peeling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Trichloroacetic acid 40% applied on the skin flap until even frosting for 2-4 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Drug: Phenol/croton oil Peeling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Phenol/croton oil applied on the skin flap occluded with silicone tape for 24 hours and not neutralized.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TCA 20% Peeling</intervention_name>
    <description>TCA peel at a concentration of 20% is applied on subcutaneous undermined skin samples for 2 to 4 minutes until even frosting and neutralized at the even frosting Point.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Drug: TCA 20% Peeling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Phenol/croton oil Peeling</intervention_name>
    <description>Phenol/croton oil is applied on subcutaneous undermined skin samples and occluded with silicone tape for 24 hours and not neutralized.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Drug: Phenol/croton oil Peeling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TCA 40% Peeling</intervention_name>
    <description>TCA peel at a concentration of 40% is applied on subcutaneous undermined skin samples for 2 to 4 minutes until even frosting and neutralized at the even frosting Point.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Drug: TCA 40% Peeling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The population consists of all female English-speaking Caucasian patients of the
             Department for plastic and aesthetic surgery of Ocean Clinic Marbella, Spain, between
             40 and 80 years seeking for elective facial rejuvenation with the PAVE-lift technique
             (peeling assisted volume enhancing Facelift) who give formal written informed consent
             to take part in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  any known cardiac problems like arrhythmia or conduction disorders, such as Wolff
             Parkinson White Syndrome

          -  previous facelift surgery

          -  previous facial peeling

          -  Fitzpatrick skin type 4, 5 and 6 (dark tanned skin types in which the applied peeling
             agents are known to lead to unpleasant results such as hypopigmentation and skin
             lightening)

          -  any former episode of skin cancer

          -  any inability to give informed written consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Phillipp Gonser, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>BG Trauma Centre Tuebingen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ocean Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marbella</city>
        <state>Malaga</state>
        <zip>29600</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.oceanclinic.net</url>
    <description>Homepage of the recruiting and treating clinic</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.bgu-tuebingen.de</url>
    <description>Homepage of the evaluating clinic</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kaye KO, Schaller HE, Jaminet P, Gonser P. The PAVE (peeling-assisted volume-enhancing) lift: A retrospective 6-year clinical analysis of a combined approach for facial rejuvenation. J Plast Reconstr Aesthet Surg. 2016 Aug;69(8):1128-33. doi: 10.1016/j.bjps.2016.04.012. Epub 2016 May 4.</citation>
    <PMID>27320171</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 25, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 25, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 28, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 16, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 16, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Peeling</keyword>
  <keyword>Histological skin changes</keyword>
  <keyword>Trichloroacetic acid peel</keyword>
  <keyword>phenol/croton oil peel</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Phenol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Croton Oil</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

