<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02841358</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>38RC13.200</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02841358</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Screening of Niemann-Pick Disease, Type C in a Psychiatric Population</brief_title>
  <acronym>NPCPsy</acronym>
  <official_title>Study Qbout the Screening of Niemann-Pick Disease, Type C in a Psychiatric Population</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Grenoble</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Grenoble</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Niemann-Pick disease, Type C is a rare genetic disorder characterized by a failing in
      intracellular cholesterol transport, inducing an accumulation of sphingolipids in the brain.

      Neurological signs are at the forefront of the disease. There are also psychiatric signs of
      psychotic kind among 28 to 45 % of patients according to studies, and a thirty cases were
      published. These signs can be concomitant with neurological signs or precede them.

      Is is likely that psychotic disorders are the first signs of a Niemann-Pick disease not yet
      non encore diagnosed for some patients. Yet, no prevalence study for this disease in a
      psychiatric population of patients currently exists. In response to this problem this study
      proposes to search patients whose disease could be of organic origin or patients whose
      disease is suspected, based on clinical data. The diagnosis will be confirmed certified with
      a genetic and/or biochemical test.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to search among a population psychotic adult patients, the ones that
      present a Type C Niemann-Pick disease in order to to estimate the prevalence.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood sampling</measure>
    <time_frame>3 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>For patients with suspicion of Type C Niemann-Pick Disease, to determine blood/plasma oxysterols level.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood sampling</measure>
    <time_frame>2 to 4 half days</time_frame>
    <description>For patients with no longer suspicion of Type C Niemann-Pick Disease, according to blood/plasma oxysterols level, for genotyping with the search of NPC 1 or NPC 2 mutation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Psychiatric Adults Patients</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Psychiatric adults patients presenting psychologic disorders</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood sampling</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Psychiatric adults patients presenting psychologic disorders</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biopsy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Psychiatric adults patients presenting psychologic disorders</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Hallucinations visual

          -  Confusion

          -  Catatonia

          -  Significant fluctuation of symptoms

          -  Unusual or paradoxical reaction to the treatment

          -  Progressive cognitive deterioration

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients under 18 years

          -  Patients unable to give their free consent and without a legal representative

          -  Breastfeeding or pregnant women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Claire Buis, Doctor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Grenoble Hospital University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UniversityHospitalGrenoble</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Tronche</city>
        <zip>38700</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vanier MT. Niemann-Pick disease type C. Orphanet J Rare Dis. 2010 Jun 3;5:16. doi: 10.1186/1750-1172-5-16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20525256</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>NP-C Guidelines Working Group, Wraith JE, Baumgartner MR, Bembi B, Covanis A, Levade T, Mengel E, Pineda M, Sedel F, Topçu M, Vanier MT, Widner H, Wijburg FA, Patterson MC. Recommendations on the diagnosis and management of Niemann-Pick disease type C. Mol Genet Metab. 2009 Sep-Oct;98(1-2):152-65. doi: 10.1016/j.ymgme.2009.06.008. Epub 2009 Jun 14.</citation>
    <PMID>19647672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garver WS, Francis GA, Jelinek D, Shepherd G, Flynn J, Castro G, Walsh Vockley C, Coppock DL, Pettit KM, Heidenreich RA, Meaney FJ. The National Niemann-Pick C1 disease database: report of clinical features and health problems. Am J Med Genet A. 2007 Jun 1;143A(11):1204-11.</citation>
    <PMID>17497724</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sévin M, Lesca G, Baumann N, Millat G, Lyon-Caen O, Vanier MT, Sedel F. The adult form of Niemann-Pick disease type C. Brain. 2007 Jan;130(Pt 1):120-33. Epub 2006 Sep 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17003072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Webber D, Klünemann H Psychiatric manifestations of Niemann-Pick Disease European Psychiatric Review, 2011;4(1):25-31</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walterfang M, Fietz M, Abel L, Bowman E, Mocellin R, Velakoulis D. Gender dimorphism in siblings with schizophrenia-like psychosis due to Niemann-Pick disease type C. J Inherit Metab Dis. 2009 Dec;32 Suppl 1:S221-6. doi: 10.1007/s10545-009-1173-1. Epub 2009 Jul 17.</citation>
    <PMID>19609713</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sandu S, Jackowski-Dohrmann S, Ladner A, Haberhausen M, Bachmann C. Niemann-Pick disease type C1 presenting with psychosis in an adolescent male. Eur Child Adolesc Psychiatry. 2009 Sep;18(9):583-5. doi: 10.1007/s00787-009-0010-2. Epub 2009 Mar 7.</citation>
    <PMID>19267177</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trendelenburg G, Vanier MT, Maza S, Millat G, Bohner G, Munz DL, Zschenderlein R. Niemann-Pick type C disease in a 68-year-old patient. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2006 Aug;77(8):997-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16844962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Walterfang M, Fietz M, Fahey M, Sullivan D, Leane P, Lubman DI, Velakoulis D. The neuropsychiatry of Niemann-Pick type C disease in adulthood. J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci. 2006 Spring;18(2):158-70.</citation>
    <PMID>16720792</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tyvaert L, Stojkovic T, Cuisset JM, Vanier MT, Turpin JC, De Sèze J, Vermersch P. [Presentation of Niemann-Pick type C disease with psychiatric disturbance in an adult]. Rev Neurol (Paris). 2005 Mar;161(3):318-22. French.</citation>
    <PMID>15800453</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Battisti C, Tarugi P, Dotti MT, De Stefano N, Vattimo A, Chierichetti F, Calandra S, Federico A. Adult onset Niemann-Pick type C disease: A clinical, neuroimaging and molecular genetic study. Mov Disord. 2003 Nov;18(11):1405-9.</citation>
    <PMID>14639697</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Turpin JC, Baumann N. [Presenting psychiatric and cognitive disorders in adult neurolipidoses]. Rev Neurol (Paris). 2003 Jul;159(6-7 Pt 1):637-47. Review. French.</citation>
    <PMID>12910071</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Josephs KA, Van Gerpen MW, Van Gerpen JA. Adult onset Niemann-Pick disease type C presenting with psychosis. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 2003 Apr;74(4):528-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12640083</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Imrie J, Vijayaraghaven S, Whitehouse C, Harris S, Heptinstall L, Church H, Cooper A, Besley GT, Wraith JE. Niemann-Pick disease type C in adults. J Inherit Metab Dis. 2002 Oct;25(6):491-500.</citation>
    <PMID>12555942</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Campo JV, Stowe R, Slomka G, Byler D, Gracious B. Psychosis as a presentation of physical disease in adolescence: a case of Niemann-Pick disease, type C. Dev Med Child Neurol. 1998 Feb;40(2):126-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9489503</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shulman LM, David NJ, Weiner WJ. Psychosis as the initial manifestation of adult-onset Niemann-Pick disease type C. Neurology. 1995 Sep;45(9):1739-43. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>7675237</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shulman LM, Lang AE, Jankovic J, David NJ, Weiner WJ. Case 1, 1995: psychosis, dementia, chorea, ataxia, and supranuclear gaze dysfunction. Mov Disord. 1995 May;10(3):257-62.</citation>
    <PMID>7651440</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hulette CM, Earl NL, Anthony DC, Crain BJ. Adult onset Niemann-Pick disease type C presenting with dementia and absent organomegaly. Clin Neuropathol. 1992 Nov-Dec;11(6):293-7.</citation>
    <PMID>1473312</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonnot O, Leroy A, Lucanto R, Cohen D Pourquoi s'intéresser à la maladie de Niemann-Pick de type C quand on est psychiatre d'enfant et d'adolescent Neuropsychiatrie de l'enfance et de l'adolescence 2011</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonnot O, Cohen D. [Psychiatric and cognitive signs associated with inborn errors of metabolism]. Rev Neurol (Paris). 2011 Dec;167(12):881-5. doi: 10.1016/j.neurol.2011.03.014. Epub 2011 Oct 29. Review. French.</citation>
    <PMID>22041824</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muller A, Balding DJ, Kluenemann HH, Linden D, Ory DS, Patterson MC, Pineda M, Priller J, Sedel F, Chadha-Boreham H, Wraith JE, Bauer P. Challenges in screening rare diseases: the ZOOM experience. Abstract accepté pour un poster au 28ème congrès de l'&quot; International Society for Pharmacoepidemiology &quot; Barcelone - août 2012&quot; + données internes</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Psychiatric Association - DSM IV TR, Manuel diagnostique et statistique des troubles mentaux, 4° édition, Texte révisé (Washington DC, 2000), Traduction française par J-D Guelfi et al., Masson, Paris, 2003, 1120 p.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 11, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 19, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 12, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 12, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Niemann-Pick Disease, Type C</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychiatric</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychotic disorders</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pick Disease of the Brain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aphasia, Primary Progressive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Frontotemporal Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Niemann-Pick Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Niemann-Pick Disease, Type A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Niemann-Pick Disease, Type C</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

