<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02844348</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>38RC15.176</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>ID/RCB : 2015-A00921-48</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02844348</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Hypnosis on Pain Management During Dialysis on Patients Suffering From Arterial Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>HYPNODIAL</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of Hypnosis on the Management of Chronic and Breakthrough Pain of Chronic Dialysis Patients Suffering From Arterial Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Grenoble</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Grenoble</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A chronic renal disease can results in the development of cardiovascular complications,
      including chronic arterial disease ; but a cardiovascular disease may be from a kidney
      malfunction that will end in end stage renal disease (ESRD). Two thirds of the chronic
      hemodialysis patients taken in charge in Grenoble in the last years suffered from an arterial
      disease at a symptomatic stage. Breakthrough pain can appear during the hemodialysis
      sessions. These sessions induce sudden hemodynamic changes and a peripheral vasoconstriction
      reaction that increases in particular all pain phenomena related to chronic low limbs
      ischemia. Therefore, patients have to face pain, sometimes chronic but also breakthrough
      pain, during the dialysis sessions, in all its dimensions.

      The analgesic balance through the classical drug treatment is extremely complex, as they are
      both at risk of overdose and of partial effectiveness. Strict medical treatment remains
      unsatisfactory, as it takes into account only the expressions of symptoms during dialysis
      sessions, when most of the time pain is already installed and analgesic treatment is not
      completely effective.

      The combination of classic pharmacological treatment with hypnosis, already used in other
      indications (chronic pain, analgesia, depression and anxiety), may mitigate the painful
      feeling on patients suffering from arterial disease during the dialysis sessions, with a
      beneficial impact on their overall quality of life. There is also evidence to suggest that
      hypnosis may be more effective treating neuropathic or vascular pain, those experienced by
      our patients, than musculoskeletal pain, like back pain.

      Hypnosis is a mind-body approach focused on the subject, and not on the disease or the act of
      dialysis. It can be described at the same time as a modified state of consciousness and a
      particular intersubjective relation between a practitioner and his patient. The practice of
      this kind of hypnoanalgesia by the nurses is particularly relevant in hemodialysis, as the
      trust developed during regular chronic treatment can become an asset to shorten the induction
      phase and help to install this intersubjective relation.

      The high incidence of this complication, the difficulties of current pain management and the
      impact on everyday life for the patients, justify the choice of this approach, where more
      further research is needed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Enrollment problem
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>February 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of pain intensity when hypnosis is applied during dialysis</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 60 sec</time_frame>
    <description>Pain is evaluate with a scale : Visual Analogue Pain Scale (VAPS) according to patients impression.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard pain control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Classical pain assessment and drug treatment at each dialysis session.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hypnosis</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Besides the classical pain assessment and drug treatment, hypnosis sessions during 2 periods of one week of dialysis sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hypnosis session</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Hypnosis</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic hemodialysis patients, requiring dialysis at least 3 times per week.

          -  Patients rating pain on a Visual analogue scale (VAS) &gt; or = to 3 during hemodialysis
             sessions for lower limb pain related to chronic arterial disease.

          -  Patients affiliated to a health insurance company.

          -  Patients having consented to participate in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Minors.

          -  Patients protected by law (under guardianship, deprived of liberty ...).

          -  Pregnant women.

          -  Refusal

          -  Patients not understanding French.

          -  Patients with cognitive, psychotic or behavioral disorders.

          -  Patients with a hearing loss limiting communication.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hemodialysis Unit University Hospital Grenoble</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <zip>38043</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Labeeuw M, Merono Nombret A, Boyer S, Guillermin MN. Rapport du Rein Rhone Alpes Année 2012. Agence de la Biomedicine, Coordination Nationale REIN.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pernod G, Bosson JL, Golshayan D, Barro C, Alloatti S, Turc-Baron C, Quarello F, Jeantet A, Von Albertini B, Forêt M, Lauren G, Cordonnier D, Piccoli G, Wauters JP; Diamant Alpin Collaborative Dialysis Study Group. The Diamant Alpin Dialysis cohort study: clinico-biological characteristics and cardiovascular genetic risk profile of incident patients. J Nephrol. 2004 Jan-Feb;17(1):66-75.</citation>
    <PMID>15151261</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rüger. Prise en charge de la douleur dans l'ischémie chronique des membres inferieurs Pain 2008 Septembre 30 139 (1) 2 : 201-208</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Santoro D, Satta E, Messina S, Costantino G, Savica V, Bellinghieri G. Pain in end-stage renal disease: a frequent and neglected clinical problem. Clin Nephrol. 2013 Jan;79 Suppl 1:S2-11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23249527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murtagh FE, Addington-Hall J, Higginson IJ. The prevalence of symptoms in end-stage renal disease: a systematic review. Adv Chronic Kidney Dis. 2007 Jan;14(1):82-99. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17200048</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bioy A. Traiter la douleur par l'hypnose. Cahier scientifique AFIDTN 2010 Dec, N°93 : 13-15.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Le choix de l'hypnose pour soulager la douleur. Institut Upsa de la Douleur. La Douleur N°7 des recommandations à la pratique Mars 2009.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elkins G, Jensen MP, Patterson DR. Hypnotherapy for the management of chronic pain. Int J Clin Exp Hypn. 2007 Jul;55(3):275-87. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17558718</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dillworth T, Mendoza ME, Jensen MP. Neurophysiology of pain and hypnosis for chronic pain. Transl Behav Med. 2012 Mar;2(1):65-72. doi: 10.1007/s13142-011-0084-5.</citation>
    <PMID>24073099</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jensen M, Patterson DR. Hypnotic treatment of chronic pain. J Behav Med. 2006 Feb;29(1):95-124. Epub 2006 Jan 11.</citation>
    <PMID>16404678</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Iserson KV. An hypnotic suggestion: review of hypnosis for clinical emergency care. J Emerg Med. 2014 Apr;46(4):588-96. doi: 10.1016/j.jemermed.2013.09.024. Epub 2014 Jan 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24472351</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kekecs Z, Varga K. Positive suggestion techniques in somatic medicine: A review of the empirical studies. Interv Med Appl Sci. 2013 Sep;5(3):101-11. doi: 10.1556/IMAS.5.2013.3.2. Epub 2013 Sep 16.</citation>
    <PMID>24265899</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Editorial. Comfortably numb. The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland 2013 ;Vol 68 : 896-898.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Communication Journées de Néphrologie. Prouteau-Chartier M. Hypnoanalgésie en Hémodialyse chronique. Quibéron 2012</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haute Autorité de Santé. [Management of chronic lower-limb obliterative atherosclerosis (indications for drug treatment, revascularisation and physiotherapy). Professional Guidelines Department - April 2006]. Ann Dermatol Venereol. 2007 Feb;134(2):199-206. French.</citation>
    <PMID>17375025</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chauveau S. &quot; Malades ou consommateurs ? La consommation de médicaments en France (second XXe siècle) &quot;, Au nom du consommateur. Consommation et politique en Europe et aux Etats-Unis au XXe siècle, sous la direction de Marie Chessel, Alain Chatriot et Matthew Hilton, Paris, La Découverte, 2005, p. 182-198.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chan YM, Zalilah MS, Hii SZ. Determinants of compliance behaviours among patients undergoing hemodialysis in Malaysia. PLoS One. 2012;7(8):e41362. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0041362. Epub 2012 Aug 3.</citation>
    <PMID>22870215</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allen D, Wainwright M, Hutchinson T. 'Non-compliance' as illness management: Hemodialysis patients' descriptions of adversarial patient-clinician interactions. Soc Sci Med. 2011 Jul;73(1):129-34. doi: 10.1016/j.socscimed.2011.05.018. Epub 2011 May 27.</citation>
    <PMID>21665340</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cojan Y, Waber L, Schwartz S, Rossier L, Forster A, Vuilleumier P. The brain under self-control: modulation of inhibitory and monitoring cortical networks during hypnotic paralysis. Neuron. 2009 Jun 25;62(6):862-75. doi: 10.1016/j.neuron.2009.05.021.</citation>
    <PMID>19555654</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Howard J. Do Bach flower remedies have a role to play in pain control? A critical analysis investigating therapeutic value beyond the placebo effect, and the potential of Bach flower remedies as a psychological method of pain relief. Complement Ther Clin Pract. 2007 Aug;13(3):174-83. Epub 2007 Apr 23.</citation>
    <PMID>17631260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thaler K, Kaminski A, Chapman A, Langley T, Gartlehner G. Bach Flower Remedies for psychological problems and pain: a systematic review. BMC Complement Altern Med. 2009 May 26;9:16. doi: 10.1186/1472-6882-9-16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19470153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rainville P. Neurophenomenologie des etats et des contenus de conscience dans l'hypnose et l'analgesie hypnotique. Théologiques, Université de Montréal, Montréal, Canada. 2004, vol. 12, no1-2, pp. 15-38.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 30, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 25, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 26, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 6, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 6, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 7, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypnosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Dialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Arterial Disease</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

