<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02840734</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Tamusa</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02840734</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Kinesio Taping on Performance</brief_title>
  <official_title>Kinesio Taping and Muscular Function in Obese Adults</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Texas A&amp;M University San Antonio</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Texas A&amp;M University San Antonio</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study investigated the immediate effects of Kinesio taping on muscular power, strength,
      endurance, and lower limb fatigue when taping is applied to rectus femoris and around the
      patella of obese adults based on Kinesio taping techniques.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double-blind, crossover, and clinical trial. Ethical approval was
      obtained from the University's Institutional Review Board (#2015-51). Participants were
      recruited by flyers posted on the University campus. Informed consent was completed by all
      participants prior to the study procedures. The subjects were obese college students. A total
      of 13 subjects, four males and nine females (mean age of 24.38 ± 3.01 years, mean percent
      body fat of 39.10 ± 6.91 % [male: 41.93 ± 7.47 %, female: 38.16 ± 6.91 %]), were enrolled
      this study. All subjects underwent three different trials which include no taping (NT),
      placebo taping (PT), and Kinesio taping (KT). All individuals were assessed for peak and mean
      power, muscular strength, endurance, and muscle fatigue after each condition.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physique characteristic</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week (Each subject was measured their anthropometrics variables in an Initial visit the LAB for trial)</time_frame>
    <description>- variables:(1) Body weight and height (Detecto DR400C platform scale (Webb City, MO) and Seca S-214 height rod (Hanover, MD), respectively), (2) Waist and hip circumference (Gulik tape measure), (3) % Body fat (bioelectrical impedance analysis, RJL Quantum X).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>muscular power</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks (30 minutes after applied each trial)</time_frame>
    <description>Peak power and mean power were measured with automatic Power cycle (Powercycle, USA). The subjects started from rest and accelerated maximally for approximately 3-4 seconds. Data was recorded for 6.5 pedal revolutions, and the increase in kinetic energy resulting from the acceleration of the ergometer flywheel was averaged over every pedal revolution and used to calculate power. The highest power and mean power (average two of the highest values) recorded during a pedal revolution was defined as Pmax and Pmean respectively.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>muscular strength</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks (30 minutes after applied each trial)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of muscle strength was measured by Muscle Testing system. A hand-held dynamometer (Lafayette, USA) used to measure isometric knee extensor and flexor strength. Specifically, subjects were seated on a table in supine position, with the knee and hip positioned at 90º. The subjects were instructed to remain seated and place both hands on the table. The dynamometer force pad placed just proximal to the ankle joint, the knee extensor strength was quantified in pound force. All subjects performed two maximal trials for 3 to 5 seconds with a 30 seconds rest interval. The higher value of two trials was recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>muscle fatigue</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks (immediately after be completed each trial)</time_frame>
    <description>To measure the sensation of lower limb muscle fatigue, subjects' subjective feelings were evaluated using a Visual Analogue Scale (VAS). A 100 mm VAS (on a 0-10 scale) was used, ranging from &quot;not in the least (0)&quot; on the left to &quot;extremely (10)&quot; on the right end. Participants were asked to score the amount of lower limb muscle fatigue experienced before and immediately after each trial.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Kinesio taping</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects wore an eye mask and the taped leg was covered by clothes for preventing subjects and researchers from identifying different tapings due to double-blinding. Subjects layed down on the mat in a supine position with the hip flexed 30º and the knee flexed 60º. Y type tape was applied from a point 10 cm below the anterior superior iliac spine, bisected at the junction between quadriceps femoris tendon and the patella, ending at its inferior side. And another Y type tape was applied from the tibial tuberosity, bisected at the junction between patella tendon and the patella, ending at its superior side. The first 5 cm tape was not stretched and acted as the anchor. I type tapes were applied downward and inward to the superior and inferior meniscus of the patella respectively.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo taping</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo tapes (3M tape) were applied with same method with Kinesio taping.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No taping</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>In case of the no taping condition, the subject was treated along the same procedure which was closed subject's eyes with eye mask and covered the legs with clothes although applied anything on their legs. It might be able to minimize the error, because the researchers did not realize which condition the subject had.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Kinesio taping</intervention_name>
    <description>This study was conducted in a randomized crossover double-blind design. Each subject was tested for muscular power, strength, endurance, and fatigue of the lower extremities under three conditions: 1) NT (no taping), 2) PT (placebo taping, 3M tape) and 3) KT (Kinesio taping). For allocation of treatment sequence, the participants drew straws for which treatment first (each treatment indicated different numbers).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Kinesio taping</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo taping</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo taping</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  percent body fat of 25 % in males, 30 % in females or more

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  lower limb surgery within previous 6 months

          -  presence of any other lower limb joint diseases such as degenerative arthritis,
             rheumatoid arthritis.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>30 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sukho Lee, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Texas A&amp;M University San Antonio</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 6, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 18, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 21, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 18, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 18, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 21, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Texas A&amp;M University San Antonio</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Suk H. Lee</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Program Director &amp; Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Kinesio taping</keyword>
  <keyword>Obese adults</keyword>
  <keyword>Muscular function</keyword>
  <keyword>Fatigue</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

