<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02841319</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SKaleibar</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02841319</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Virtual Reality on Upper Extremity Function in Hemiplegic Cerebral Palsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effects of Virtual Reality Therapy Compared With Home Exercise Program on Upper Extremity Functions in Children With Hemiplegic Cerebral Palsy: a Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Istanbul University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Istanbul University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators have planned a research on the effects of virtual reality therapy and home
      exercise program on hand functions in children with hemiplegic cerebral palsy in Istanbul
      University Istanbul Faculty of Medicine in the Department of Physical Medicine and
      Rehabilitation. The eligible patients will be randomized into two groups. The patients in
      intervention group will participate in a computer based virtual reality exercise program for
      a period of 8 weeks supervised by the investigators. In addition, these patients will receive
      a home exercise program. The patients in the control group will receive only a home exercise
      program for 8 weeks. All patients will be evaluated before treatment, immediately after
      treatment, and 3 months after the end of the treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The current study is a prospective, randomized controlled interventional trial, which will
      conduct in the Istanbul University Istanbul Faculty of Medicine in 2016. The study was
      approved by the Ethics Committee in conformity with the Declaration of Helsinki. Prior to
      data collection, all participants will provide informed consent. By the order of application
      to the outpatient clinics, the eligible participants will randomly allocated to two groups
      using the computer-generated random numbers: intervention group (n=17) and control group
      (n=17). Information on demographic characteristics (age, gender, body mass index, educational
      level), pre-natal history, parent educational level and past medical history will obtain at
      baseline assessment. After baseline assessment, the patients in intervention group will
      participate in a computer based virtual reality exercise program with HandTutor equipment.
      The supervised intervention program consists of a forty-minute exercise session three times a
      week for 8 weeks. In addition, these patients will receive a home exercise program. The
      patients in the control group will receive only a home exercise program for 8 weeks. The home
      exercise program consists of different games and exercises such as range of motion, stretch,
      and strengthening exercises for hand. All patients will be evaluated before treatment,
      immediately after treatment, and 3 months after the end of the treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assisting Hand Assessment (AHA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 7 Days</time_frame>
    <description>AHA measures are valid and reliable for children aged between 18 months and 12 years with the diagnosis of unilateral cerebral palsy. It measures how effectively children with unilateral hand dysfunction use their involved hand in collaboration with their uninvolved hand to perform bimanual tasks.The test is administered in two steps. First, a video-recorded play session lasting 10 to 15 minutes is conducted with specific toys from the AHA test kit.Second, the scoring is performed by a review of the video on 22 items by certificated professional. The AHA version 4.4 includes 22 test items each rated on a 4-point scale, with a total raw score range between 22-88 points. The higher score indicating higher ability.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hand Grip Measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 7 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Grip strength will measured with BASELINE Dynamometer. The participants will seat and the shoulder is hold in the adducted and minimally internal rotated, elbow flexed at 90 degrees, forearm in natural position and wrist flexed between 0 and 30 degrees (Kg/f).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ABILHAND</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 7 Days</time_frame>
    <description>ABILHAND-Kids is a measure of manual ability for children with upper limb impairments. The scale measures a person's ability to manage daily activities that require the use of the upper limbs. 21 manual activities perceived by the children parents. Each item is answered on a 3-level scale (impossible, difficult, easy). The Parent is asked to fill in the questionnaire by estimating their child's performance independent of the limb the child actually. The online analysis converts the raw scores into a linear measure of manual ability. ABILHAND-Kids has been validated in cerebral palsy children (age 6-15).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Range of Motion (ROM)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 7 Days</time_frame>
    <description>By using the Universal Goniometer, the active and passive ROM will be assessed based on the 360-degrees system in radioulnar pronation and supination, wrist flexion and extension, 2nd to 5th metacarpophalangeal joints</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modified Ashworth Scale (MAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 7 Days</time_frame>
    <description>One of the methods for measuring muscle spasticity includes manually moving a limb through its ROM to passively stretch specific muscle groups. Modified Ashworth Scale for Grading Spasticity is six-point scale (0-5).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>TARDIEU SCALE</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 7 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Tardieu Scale (TS):
It assesses the response of the muscle to passive movement of limb in both slow and fast speeds, on the other word it evaluated velocity dependent muscle tonicity. Intensity of muscle reaction (Y) is included six-point scale (0-5)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulp Pinch Strength Measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 7 Days</time_frame>
    <description>Pulp pinch strength is measured by the &quot;JAMAR Hydraulic Pinch Gauge&quot; which evaluates the pinch strength between first and second digits. The participants will seat and the shoulder is hold in the adducted and minimally internal rotated, elbow flexed at 90 degrees, forearm in natural position and wrist flexed between 0 and 30 degrees (Kg/f).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">34</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Palsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Virtual reality exercises using Hand Tutor for 8 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Home exercises for 8 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Virtual Reality Exercises using Hand Tutor</intervention_name>
    <description>Virtual reality technology is rapidly becoming a popular application for physical rehabilitation and motor control research. The prototype, which includes a built-in movement sensor, allows the user to do controlled exercises as part of a rehabilitation program. The supervised intervention program consists of a forty-minute exercise session three times a week for 8 weeks. In addition, these patients will receive a home exercise program. The patients in the control group will receive only a home exercise program for 8 weeks. The home exercise program consists of different games and exercises such as range of motion, stretch, and strengthening exercises for hand.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Children with hemiplegic cerebral palsy diagnosed by the specialist

          -  Active wrist extension ≥ 20 °

          -  Gross Motor Function Classification System score: 1-2

          -  Manual Ability Classification System score: 1-3

          -  The ability to follow simple commands and participate in the task

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Contracture in upper limb

          -  Absence of vision and hearing problems

          -  Uncontrolled seizure

          -  Lack of movement in the hemiplegic upper limb

          -  History of orthopedic surgery (tendon transfer / tendon lengthening) to the affected
             upper extremity

          -  Any treatment for upper limb in the last 6 months including BTX-A or orthopedic
             interventions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Resa Aydin, MD, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Istanbul University Istanbul Faculty of Medicine Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sara Asghari Kaleibar, MD</last_name>
    <phone>00905380390939</phone>
    <email>saraasghari@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Resa Aydin, MD, Prof</last_name>
    <phone>00902124142000</phone>
    <phone_ext>12850</phone_ext>
    <email>resaaydin@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Istanbul Faculty of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Istanbul</city>
        <zip>34093</zip>
        <country>Turkey</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sara Asghari Kaleibar, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Turkey</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gabis LV, Tsubary NM, Leon O, Ashkenasi A, Shefer S. Assessment of Abilities and Comorbidities in Children With Cerebral Palsy. J Child Neurol. 2015 Oct;30(12):1640-5. doi: 10.1177/0883073815576792. Epub 2015 Apr 8.</citation>
    <PMID>25855688</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Surveillance of Cerebral Palsy in Europe. Surveillance of cerebral palsy in Europe: a collaboration of cerebral palsy surveys and registers. Surveillance of Cerebral Palsy in Europe (SCPE). Dev Med Child Neurol. 2000 Dec;42(12):816-24.</citation>
    <PMID>11132255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Green D, Schertz M, Gordon AM, Moore A, Schejter Margalit T, Farquharson Y, Ben Bashat D, Weinstein M, Lin JP, Fattal-Valevski A. A multi-site study of functional outcomes following a themed approach to hand-arm bimanual intensive therapy for children with hemiplegia. Dev Med Child Neurol. 2013 Jun;55(6):527-33. doi: 10.1111/dmcn.12113. Epub 2013 Mar 5. Erratum in: Dev Med Child Neurol. 2016 Mar;58(3):316.</citation>
    <PMID>23458353</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basu AP, Pearse J, Kelly S, Wisher V, Kisler J. Early intervention to improve hand function in hemiplegic cerebral palsy. Front Neurol. 2015 Jan 6;5:281. doi: 10.3389/fneur.2014.00281. eCollection 2014. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25610423</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morris C. Definition and classification of cerebral palsy: a historical perspective. Dev Med Child Neurol Suppl. 2007 Feb;109:3-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17370476</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meyer-Heim A, van Hedel HJ. Robot-assisted and computer-enhanced therapies for children with cerebral palsy: current state and clinical implementation. Semin Pediatr Neurol. 2013 Jun;20(2):139-45. doi: 10.1016/j.spen.2013.06.006. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23948688</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gilliaux M, Renders A, Dispa D, Holvoet D, Sapin J, Dehez B, Detrembleur C, Lejeune TM, Stoquart G. Upper limb robot-assisted therapy in cerebral palsy: a single-blind randomized controlled trial. Neurorehabil Neural Repair. 2015 Feb;29(2):183-92. doi: 10.1177/1545968314541172. Epub 2014 Jul 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25015650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosenbaum P, Paneth N, Leviton A, Goldstein M, Bax M, Damiano D, Dan B, Jacobsson B. A report: the definition and classification of cerebral palsy April 2006. Dev Med Child Neurol Suppl. 2007 Feb;109:8-14. Erratum in: Dev Med Child Neurol. 2007 Jun;49(6):480.</citation>
    <PMID>17370477</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schiariti V, Klassen AF, Cieza A, Sauve K, O'Donnell M, Armstrong R, Mâsse LC. Comparing contents of outcome measures in cerebral palsy using the International Classification of Functioning (ICF-CY): a systematic review. Eur J Paediatr Neurol. 2014 Jan;18(1):1-12. doi: 10.1016/j.ejpn.2013.08.001. Epub 2013 Sep 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24051208</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 21, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 19, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 25, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 25, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 26, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Istanbul University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sara Asghari Kaleibar</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Sara ASGHARI KALEIBAR, MD Resident in the Department of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation Istanbul Faculty of Medicine, Istanbul University, Istanbul, Turkey</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Virtual reality</keyword>
  <keyword>Hemiplegic</keyword>
  <keyword>Cerebral Palsy</keyword>
  <keyword>upper extremity</keyword>
  <keyword>hand function</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paralysis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Palsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We have no permission to share individual participant data.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

