<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02849704</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-013001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02849704</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fat Malabsorption in Chronic Pancreatitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Diagnosing Pancreatic-Based Malabsorption in Patients With Chronic Pancreatitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AbbVie</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Phoenix Indian Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to evaluate the malabsorption blood test (MBT), stool
      coefficient of fat absorption (CFA) and stool bomb calorimetry (BC) methods as potential
      screening or diagnostic tests for reduced exocrine pancreatic function or pancreatic
      insufficiency (RPF/PI). A further objective is to determine the test responses before and
      after pancreatic enzyme medication administration (Creon36™) in the patients with chronic
      pancreatitis (CP).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Reduced exocrine pancreatic function or pancreatic insufficiency (RPF/PI) contributes to poor
      clinical outcome in a number of diseases and conditions. The incidence, mechanism and
      substantial adverse clinical outcomes of pancreatic insufficiency (PI) are well known in
      patients with cystic fibrosis (CF), and the life sustaining role of pancreatic enzyme
      medication in CF care is well established. Much less is known about the incidence and impact
      of RPF/PI in patients with chronic pancreatitis (CP). Reliable non-invasive screening or
      diagnostic tests with acceptable patient burden are not available for RPF/PI.

      This is a cohort study of subjects with CP who will be evaluated before and after pancreatic
      enzyme medication (Creon36™) administration. A cohort of healthy subjects will serve as a
      comparison group and will be evaluated only once.

      Subjects with CP will receive Creon36™, a pancreatic enzyme medication, and fat and energy
      absorption will be evaluated using three methods: MBT, CFA, and BC before and after
      administration of Creon36™. Many patients with CP are at risk for RPF/PI yet they rarely
      undergo diagnostic testing. Pancreatic enzyme medication will likely improve clinical
      outcomes and quality of life in some of those with RPF/PI. A cohort of healthy volunteers
      will be evaluated with the three methods to provide essential comparison data to optimize the
      understanding and interpretation of the findings from the three methods and the RPF/PI cohort
      with CP. There will be no intervention for the healthy cohort.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in mean malabsorption blood test (MBT) between groups</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 72 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The fat and energy absorption pattern in CP subjects after treatment with Creon36™ will be compared with healthy controls. Mean MBT will be calculated for the CP subjects and the healthy controls and compared to determine whether there is a difference in the fat and energy absorption pattern between the two groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pancreatitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic Pancreatitis (CP) Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>CP subjects will fast for 12 hours prior to the malabsorption blood test (MBT) testing, consume the MBT breakfast meal following this fast, have blood drawn (MBT, vitamins A, D, E and K, zinc, selenium, and prealbumin) prior to MBT breakfast consumption and each hour for 8 hours after consumption, consume a low-fat study lunch, eat a moderate fat diet for 4 days during home diet and stool collection, maintain a 3-day food record, collect stool over 72 hours, have body size and composition assessment, complete quality of life questionnaires, home environment and health questionnaires, and adverse events diary.
Subjects will take Creon36™ for 9 days.
Subjects will have two study visits, one before and one after treatment initiation with Creon36™. Both visits will be identical with the exception of completion of questionnaires and fecal elastase assessment (only Visit 1).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Healthy controls will fast for 12 hours prior to the malabsorption blood test (MBT) testing, consume the MBT breakfast meal following this fast, have blood drawn (MBT, vitamins A, D, E and K, zinc, selenium, and prealbumin) prior to MBT breakfast consumption and each hour for 8 hours after consumption, consume a low-fat study lunch, eat a moderate fat diet for 4 days during home diet and stool collection, maintain a 3-day food record, collect stool over 72 hours, have body size and composition assessment, complete quality of life questionnaires, home environment and health questionnaires, and adverse events diary. Controls will only have 1 study visit and receive no intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Creon36™</intervention_name>
    <description>Creon36™ delayed-release capsules, a pancreatic enzyme preparation, is an FDA approved medication. Subjects with chronic pancreatitis (CP) will take Creon36™ for nine days, at a daily dose of 72,000 lipase units per meal (two capsules) and 36,000 units per snack (one capsule), with each capsule containing 36,000 lipase units. Subjects will take Creon36™ for three days prior to Visit 2, the day of Visit 2 and then for five days after the visit until they have completed stool collections.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Chronic Pancreatitis (CP) Subjects</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Pancrelipase</other_name>
    <other_name>CREON</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria (CP):

          -  Chronic pancreatitis diagnosis by gastroenterologist. Participants with CP will be
             characterized based on the TIGAR-O (toxic, genetic, autoimmune, recurrent,
             obstructive) etiology system, on pancreatic morphology (Cambridge criteria) when
             available, and on physiological state (exocrine and endocrine function) as recommended
             by the recent American Pancreatic Association Practice Guidelines4.

          -  Age 30-70 years old

          -  Evidence of at-risk for malabsorption including: 1) history of use of and response to
             pancreatic enzyme medication; 2) history of unintentional weight loss; 3) history of
             increased stools per week or fatty stools; and/or 4) other clinical signs or symptoms
             suggestive of fat malabsorption

          -  In usual state of health for past two weeks including no change in medications

          -  Able to consume a moderate fat diet for stool evaluations

          -  Able to participate in the study for about four weeks with two study visits

        Inclusion Criteria (Healthy Volunteers):

          -  Age 30-70 years old

          -  No known chronic disease that would affect dietary intake or fat absorption

          -  In usual state of health for past two weeks, with stable medications, diet and weight

          -  BMI from 18-29

          -  Able to consume a moderate fat diet for stool evaluations

          -  Able to participate in the study for about one week with one study visit

        Exclusion Criteria (CP):

          -  Evidence of normal fat absorption in medical record

          -  Medications that alter fat absorption (i.e. orlistat, other weight loss medications,
             ursodeoxycholic acid)

          -  Allergy to pork products

          -  History of intestinal blockage or fibrosing colonopathy

          -  History of gout, kidney disease, or high blood uric acid (hyperuricemia)

          -  Pregnancy or breast feeding

        Exclusion Criteria (Healthy Volunteers):

          -  Evidence of fat malabsorption

          -  Medications that alter fat absorption (i.e. orlistat, other weight loss medications,
             ursodeoxycholic acid)

          -  Pregnancy or breast feeding
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Babette Zemel, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Virginia Stallings, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carolyn McAnlis, BS</last_name>
    <phone>267-426-9381</phone>
    <email>mcanlisc@email.chop.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Carolyn McAnlis, BS</last_name>
      <phone>267-426-9381</phone>
      <email>mcanlisc@email.chop.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Virginia Stallings, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Babette Zemel, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 27, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 27, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 29, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chronic Pancreatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Pancreatic Function</keyword>
  <keyword>Reduced Exocrine Pancreatic Function</keyword>
  <keyword>Pancreatic Insufficiency</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatitis, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Malabsorption Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancrelipase</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pancreatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

