<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02840630</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RT10087-10</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02840630</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of FISH Intake on MEtabolic Health in a Diabetic South Asian popuLation (FISH MEAL)</brief_title>
  <acronym>FISHMEAL</acronym>
  <official_title>Effect of FISH Intake on MEtabolic Health in a Diabetic South Asian popuLation (FISH MEAL)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Aberdeen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Aberdeen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators will recruit non-diabetic volunteers (n=30) and diabetic volunteers
      controlled by diet and lifestyle (n=300). The non-diabetic volunteers will be in the
      non-diabetic group while the diabetic volunteers will be randomised to a diabetic control
      intervention group or a diabetic fish intervention group. Baseline data will be collected
      from all three groups but only diabetic control intervention group and diabetic fish
      intervention group will go through the 16-week study. This will allow the investigators to
      compare the metabolic health across South Asian population in people with and without
      diabetes.

      The recommended intake of EPA and DHA daily is ~450 mg per day for cardiovascular health, or
      approximately 3 g per week. Over the course of 16 weeks, subjects in the diabetic control
      intervention group will continue with their habitual diet, while subjects in the diabetic
      fish intervention group will receive two 125 g portion of tinned mackerel (containing 7.8 g
      n-3 LCPUFA26) every week, to replace a portion of red meat or poultry. Previous n-3 LCPUFA
      intervention study among South Asian people in the United Kingdom was able to reverse lipid
      abnormalities with supplementation of 2.5 g of EPA and DHA per day for 12 weeks. However, the
      same study also shows that their daily consumption of EPA and DHA is only 68±99 and 112±171
      mg respectively. Therefore, only 1.1 g n-3 LCPUFA per day is given in this study to increase
      compliance.

      Recipe recommendations using mackerel will be provided. Non-diabetic volunteers will be
      recruited only to obtain baseline data in order to compare their metabolic profile with that
      of the diabetic volunteers. This will allow us to investigate the link between omega 3 status
      and glycaemic control in a South Asian population.

      Fish is chosen as an intervention as opposed to EPA and DHA supplements in order to capture
      the benefits of eating fish as an important source of not only n-3 LCPUFA, but also other key
      nutrients such as vitamin D, selenium and iodine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      During the study period, participants will be asked to maintain their routine dietary and
      social habits to avoid changes in body weight. In addition volunteers will be asked to record
      their weights first thing in the morning on the same set of scales every week. Any changes
      can be documented in a food frequency questionnaire. Volunteers without diabetes will be
      recruited for baseline data and will not be involved in the 16-week intervention study.
      Diabetic volunteers will be randomized by BioSS in batches of ~20 people into the diabetic
      control or the diabetic fish intervention group that will be matched for gender, age and BMI.
      The diabetic control group will be asked to continue with their routine dietary habits while
      the diabetic fish intervention group will be asked to substitute poultry or red meat with 2
      tins of mackerels each week. Study kits will be posted two weeks before the study initiates
      to consenting volunteers.

      All volunteers will be asked to provide finger prick blood spots on filter paper at week 0,
      while subjects allocated to diabetic control and diabetic fish intervention groups will be
      asked to provide blood spots again at week 8 and 16. A dried blood spot (DBS) sampling kit
      containing two Whatman 903 filter papers, two lancets, alcohol pads, bandaids, guidelines on
      spotting blood on filter paper, prepaid envelope, FFQ, tinned mackerel and a fish recipe
      book. Every volunteer will be asked to prick the inside tip of a non-dominant finger and
      gently spot a total of ten circles in the filter papers. A volunteer might experience slight
      discomfort when the lancet goes into the finger. The volunteers will then allow the filter
      paper to dry for about an hour before closing the flap over the filter paper. All information
      and tools to help with obtaining the dried blood spots, as well as guidelines on how to spot
      blood on filter paper will be included with the DBS kit. Volunteers are required to spot 2
      filter papers at one collection point and post them in a pre-paid envelope complete with a
      return address.

      The DBS samples will be analyzed for omega 3 index, glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c),
      triglycerides, Vitamin D status, genetic (TCF7L2 7903146) and epigenetic marker (FADS 174546)
      of lipid and glucose control.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Glycated Hemoglobin (HbA1c)</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0 and 16</time_frame>
    <description>HbA1c will be analysed from DBS samples at week 0 and 16.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Omega 3 Index</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0, 16</time_frame>
    <description>Omega 3 Index will be analysed from DBS samples at week 0, and 16.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Triglycerides</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0, and 16</time_frame>
    <description>Triglycerides will be analysed from DBS samples at week 0 and 16.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Vitamin D</measure>
    <time_frame>week 0, 16</time_frame>
    <description>Vitamin D will be analysed from DBS samples at week 0 and 16.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">330</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-diabetic group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Non-diabetic volunteers will be recruited for baseline data. They will only be required to provide dried blood samples (DBS) samples and information at week 0. They have to collect finger prick DBS, weigh themselves and fill in food frequency questionnaire only at one time point.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Diabetic control intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The diabetic control group will provide finger prick DBS at week 0, 8 and 16, fill in food frequency questionnaire at week 0 and 16 and weekly weighing from week 0 until 16. This group will not be receiving tinned mackerel and will be asked to continue with their habitual diet and lifestyle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Diabetic fish intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>This intervention group will receive two 125 g portion of tinned mackerel fish (containing 7.8 g n-3 LCPUFA) per week from week 0 until 16 and a mackerel recipe book each. They will be required to provide finger prick DBS at week 0, 8 and 16, fill in food frequency questionnaire at week 0 and 16 and weekly weighing from week 0 until 16.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tinned mackerel fish</intervention_name>
    <description>Diabetic fish intervention group will be given two tinned mackerels per week from week 0 until week 16.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Diabetic fish intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tesco tinned mackerel fish</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Non-diabetic group:

        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Of South Asian origin (defined by country of birth, last name and self-report
             ethnicity)

          -  Men and women between the age of 25 and 65;

          -  Body mass index (BMI) of ≥23 kg/m2 according to WHO classification for Asian
             population;

          -  Ability to speak, read and understand the English language.

        Exclusion criteria

          -  Use of tobacco;

          -  Use of insulin or oral hypoglycaemic agents;

          -  Use of medications that are known to affect lipid metabolism,

          -  Haemophiliacs,

          -  Use of medications that are known to generally alter the haemostatic system;

          -  Diagnosis of diabetes;

          -  Diagnosis of hypertension, renal, hepatic, haematological disease or coronary heart
             disease;

          -  Have previously donated blood for transfusion purposes within the last month;

          -  Inability to understand participant information sheet.

        Diabetic control intervention and diabetic fish intervention group:

        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Of South Asian origin (defined by country of birth, last name and self-report
             ethnicity)

          -  Men and women between the age of 25 and 65;

          -  Body mass index (BMI) of ≥23 kg/m2 according to WHO classification for Asian
             population;

          -  Diagnosed with diabetes only controlled by diet and lifestyle;

          -  Ability to speak, read and understand the English language.

        Exclusion criteria

          -  Use of tobacco;

          -  Use of insulin or oral hypoglycemic agents;

          -  Use of medications that are known to affect lipid metabolism;

          -  Haemophiliacs;

          -  Use of medications that are known to generally alter the hemostatic system;

          -  Diagnosis of hypertension, renal, hepatic, haematological disease or coronary heart
             disease;

          -  Have previously donated blood for transfusion purposes within the last month;

          -  Inability to understand participant information sheet.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Baukje De Roos, BSc, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Aberdeen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Baukje De Roos, BSc, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>44 (0)1224 438636</phone>
    <email>b.deroos@abdn.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nigel Hoggard, BSc, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>44 (0)1224 438655</phone>
    <email>n.hoggard@abdn.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Aberdeen Rowett Institute of Nutrition and Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aberdeen</city>
        <zip>AB21 9SB</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nigel Hoggard</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <email>N.Hoggard@abdn.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nigel Hoggard, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 14, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 18, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 21, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>n3 LC-PUFA</keyword>
  <keyword>Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</keyword>
  <keyword>South Asian</keyword>
  <keyword>HbA1c</keyword>
  <keyword>Omega 3 status</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

