<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02844075</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4-2016-0199</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02844075</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase II Trial of Preoperative Chemoradiotherapy and MK-3475 for Esophageal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yonsei University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yonsei University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study, participants with esophageal squamous cell carcinoma will receive preoperative
      chemoradiotherapy with paclitaxel,carboplatin and pembrolizumab then undergo surgery. The
      primary study hypothesis is that adding pembrolizumab will increase complete pathologic
      response rate at surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>complete pathologic response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint of phase II study is to assess complete pathologic response rate. Definition of complete pathologic response is &quot;no cancer cell, including lympho nodes&quot; which corresponds with tumor regression score 0. Definition of pathologic response is as follows. Tumor regression score Grade 0 and 1 will be defined as &quot;responder&quot; and 2 and 3 will be considered as &quot;non-responders&quot;</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Disease free survival is defined from the time of surgery to initial replace or death.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival is defined from the time of surgery to death or last follow-up date.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathologic response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Pathologic response rate is defined as tumor regression score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse event based on CTCAE 4.0.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of adverse event in patients during treatment period graded according to Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.03</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">28</enrollment>
  <condition>Esophageal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MK-3475(pembrolizumab)</intervention_name>
    <description>Neo-adjuvant chemoradiation period:The treatment consisted of taxol, carboplatin, pembrolizumab and radiation. The radiation treatment comprises 44.1Gy (2.1Gy/Fr, total 21Fr) and that will be about 5 weeks. Intensity modulated RT (IMRT) or 3D CRT (three-dimensional conformal radiotherapy) will be allowed.
Surgery:Before surgery, abdomen/chest CT scan, endoscopic ultrasound (EUS), and gastroscopy with biopsy will be done. Surgery should be done within 12 weeks after last neo-adjuvant treatment.
Adjuvant period:Adjuvant treatment with pembrolizumab 200mg every 2week (maximum 2 years) should be performed within 8 weeks after surgery (recommended period : 3-6 weeks after surgery). Gastroscopy and abdomen/chest CT scan will be performed at 6 month after surgery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>pembrolizumab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically confirmed ESCC

          2. Clinical stage T1N1-2 or T2-34aN0-12 (AJCC 7 TNM classification)

          3. No evidence of metastasis

          4. Be willing and able to provide written informed consent/assent for the trial.

          5. Be 20 years of age on day of signing informed consent.

          6. Be willing to provide tissue from a newly obtained core or excisional biopsy of a
             tumor lesion through repeated biopsies. Newly-obtained is defined as a specimen
             obtained up to 6 weeks (42 days) prior to initiation of treatment on Day 1. Subjects
             for whom newly-obtained samples cannot be provided (e.g. inaccessible or subject
             safety concern) may submit an archived specimen only upon agreement from the Sponsor.

          7. Have a performance status of 0 or 1 on the ECOG Performance Scale.

          8. Demonstrate adequate organ function as defined in Table 1, all screening labs should
             be performed within 10 days of treatment initiation.

          9. Female subject of childbearing potential should have a negative urine or serum
             pregnancy within 72 hours prior to receiving the first dose of study medication. If
             the urine test is positive or cannot be confirmed as negative, a serum pregnancy test
             will be required.

         10. Female subjects of childbearing potential (Section 5.7.2) must be willing to use an
             adequate method of contraception as outlined in Section 5.7.2 - Contraception, for the
             course of the study through 120 days after the last dose of study medication.

             - Note: Abstinence is acceptable if this is the usual lifestyle and preferred
             contraception for the subject.

         11. Male subjects of childbearing potential (Section 5.7.1) must agree to use an adequate
             method of contraception as outlined in Section 5.7.1- Contraception, starting with the
             first dose of study therapy through 120 days after the last dose of study therapy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Currently participating and receiving study therapy or has participated in a study of
             an investigational agent and received study therapy or used an investigational device
             within 4 weeks of the first dose of treatment.

          2. Has a diagnosis of immunodeficiency or is receiving systemic steroid therapy or any
             other form of immunosuppressive therapy within 7 days prior to the first dose of trial
             treatment.

          3. Has a known history of active TB (Bacillus Tuberculosis)

          4. Hypersensitivity to pembrolizumab or any of its excipients.

          5. Has had a prior anti-cancer monoclonal antibody (mAb) within 4 weeks prior to study
             Day 1 or who has not recovered (i.e., ≤ Grade 1 or at baseline) from adverse events
             due to agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier.

          6. Has had prior chemotherapy, targeted small molecule therapy, or radiation therapy
             within 2 weeks prior to study Day 1 or who has not recovered (i.e., ≤ Grade 1 or at
             baseline) from adverse events due to a previously administered agent.

               -  Note: Subjects with ≤ Grade 2 neuropathy are an exception to this criterion and
                  may qualify for the study.

               -  Note: If subject received major surgery, they must have recovered adequately from
                  the toxicity and/or complications from the intervention prior to starting
                  therapy.

          7. Has another malignancy within the last 5 years. Exceptions include basal cell
             carcinoma of the skin, squamous cell carcinoma of the skin that has undergone
             potentially curative surgery, or in situ cervical cancer.

          8. Has active autoimmune disease that has required systemic treatment in the past 2 years
             (i.e. with use of disease modifying agents, corticosteroids or immunosuppressive
             drugs). Replacement therapy (eg., thyroxine, insulin, or physiologic corticosteroid
             replacement therapy for adrenal or pituitary insufficiency, etc.) is not considered a
             form of systemic treatment.

          9. Has known history of, or any evidence of active, non-infectious pneumonitis.

         10. Has an active infection requiring systemic therapy.

         11. Has a history or current evidence of any condition, therapy, or laboratory abnormality
             that might confound the results of the trial, interfere with the subject's
             participation for the full duration of the trial, or is not in the best interest of
             the subject to participate, in the opinion of the treating investigator.

         12. Has known psychiatric or substance abuse disorders that would interfere with
             cooperation with the requirements of the trial.

         13. Is pregnant or breastfeeding, or expecting to conceive or father children within the
             projected duration of the trial, starting with the pre-screening or screening visit
             through 120 days after the last dose of trial treatment.

         14. Has received prior therapy with an anti-PD-1, anti-PD-L1, or anti-PD-L2 agent.

         15. Has a known history of Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) (HIV 1/2 antibodies).

         16. Has known active Hepatitis B (e.g., HBsAg reactive) or Hepatitis C (e.g., HCV RNA
             [qualitative] is detected).

         17. Has received a live vaccine within 30 days of planned start of study therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Byoung Chul Cho, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>82-2-2228-0880</phone>
    <phone_ext>82-2-393-3652</phone_ext>
    <email>CBC1971@yuhs.ac</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yonsei Cancer Center, Yonsei University College of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>03722</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Byoung Chul Cho, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
      <phone>82-2-2228-0880</phone>
      <phone_ext>82-2-393-3652</phone_ext>
      <email>CBC1971@yuhs.ac</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 8, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 21, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 26, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Esophageal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>pembrolizumab</keyword>
  <keyword>PD-1</keyword>
  <keyword>neoadjuvant</keyword>
  <keyword>chemoradiation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pembrolizumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

