<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02845206</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15/SS/0058</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02845206</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bespoke vs Standard Instrumentation in TKR</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomised Controlled Trial of Patient Specific Instrumentation vs Standard Instrumentation in Total Knee Arthroplasty</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NHS Lothian</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NHS Lothian</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Total knee replacement (TKR) is an established treatment for knee osteoarthritis and leads to
      a satisfactory outcome in over 75% of patients. The pain and function after TKR can be
      dependent on the accuracy of initial implantation, as deviation of more than 3 degrees from
      the normal alignment of the limb can lead to abnormal stresses on the implant and accelerated
      failure. Patient specific cutting blocks may result in a more individualised implant
      placement, improved pain and function following surgery, and a long-lasting implant.

      This trial is designed to investigate if there is any benefit to bespoke instrumentation in
      terms of pain and function to the patient, and an economic benefit to the NHS.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Total knee replacement (TKR) is an established treatment for 'wear and tear' arthritis and
      leads to a satisfactory outcome in over 75% of patients. However, this means that up to 25%
      of patients are not entirely satisfied with their TKR. The longevity and stability of a TKR
      is greatly dependent on the accuracy of the initial surgery. Deviation of more than 3 degrees
      from the normal axis can lead to abnormal stresses causing the implants to fail. 'Patient
      specific' technology involves preoperative computer assessment of the patients' knee and
      allows for a 'patient specific' cutting block to be manufactured. This will allow for
      individual bony cuts specific to the patients own anatomy.

      'Patient specific' implants and cutting blocks may allow a more optimal implant positioning
      and are implanted without the need for instrumentation of the femoral medullary canal
      (thigh), so lower blood loss may result. This could result in improved early range of
      movement and decreased pain following surgery. The total knee replacement used in this study
      will be the GMKSphere (Medacta International) TKR. It has a specific design which more
      closely resembles a natural unreplaced knee than any other knee replacement. It may help
      address the phenomenon of 'mid flexion instability', which is where the patient perceives
      their replaced knee to be unsteady on stairs and slopes.

      Patient specific technology may also result in a cost saving, as it potentially reduces the
      number of sterilised trays required during the surgery.

      This study will allow for comparison in knee function and patient outcomes between patients
      who have undergone their TKR with patient specific cutting blocks compared to conventional
      cutting blocks. The scans obtained following the surgery could lead to world leading
      methodology for the assessment of knee replacements and would set a blue print for the
      evaluation of other knee implants in the future.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Limb alignment</measure>
    <time_frame>1 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measured in degrees from Hip-Knee-Ankle radiographs from centre of femoral head to midpoint of the ankle</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference between baseline pre-op and one year post-op change in gait measured using a bespoke clinic-appropriate motion analysis system.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Knee range of motion, strength and gait analysis assessments will be carried out on a bespoke clinic-appropriate motion analysis system. This system consists of 8 Vicon B10 Bonita cameras (Vicon Systems, Oxford) which immediately surround a self-paced N-Mill treadmill (Motekforce Link, Amsterdam).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in patient reported knee pain level as measured by Oxford Knee Score between baseline and one year and also between study groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Validated patient reported knee pain questionnaires as measured by Oxford Knee Score (out of 48 points) pre-operation and at one year post-operation. Difference between baseline and one year scores for each patient and also analysed between groups (patient specific cutting blocks compared to conventional cutting blocks).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in patient reported knee function between baseline and one year and also between study groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Validated patient reported knee function questionnaires as measured by EQ-5D pre-operation and at one year post-operation. Difference between baseline and one year scores for each patient and also analysed between groups (patient specific cutting blocks compared to conventional cutting blocks).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in patient reported quality of life questionnaires between baseline and one year and also between study groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Validated quality of life questionnaires as measured by SF-12 score pre-operation and at one year post-operation. Difference between baseline and one year scores for each patient and also analysed between groups (patient specific cutting blocks compared to conventional cutting blocks).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Healthcare cost</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Healthcare cost measured in pounds sterling (GBP). Total cost of performing knee replacement using conventional cutting blocks compared to using bespoke cutting blocks and disposable instrumentation. The measurable contributors to the costs of healthcare include operating time (minutes), number of instrument trays requiring sterilisation (number of trays), length of hospital stay (days), patient transfusion requirement (number of units of packed cells required), cost of bespoke disposable instrumentation (GBP).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">172</enrollment>
  <condition>Knee Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Specific Cutting Blocks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For the bespoke individualised cutting blocks to be manufactured, the patients will undergo a preoperative CT scan under a set protocol. The CT radiation dose will be considerably less than a conventional diagnostic CT scan.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Cutting Blocks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients in this arm will be operated on using conventional instruments.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient specific cutting blocks</intervention_name>
    <description>'MyKnee' Instrumentation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Specific Cutting Blocks</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conventional cutting blocks</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard Instrumentation</description>
    <arm_group_label>Conventional Cutting Blocks</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with osteoarthritis ('wear and tear') of the knee which is sufficiently
             symptomatic to require knee arthroplasty as assessed by their consultant orthopaedic
             surgeon

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with inflammatory arthropathy, patients requiring bone augmentation, ligament
             incompetence, values deformity &gt; 5 degrees
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leela C Biant, FRCSEd(Tr&amp;Orth) MSres MFSTEd</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Edinburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Susan Shepherd</last_name>
    <email>susan.shepherd@nhslothian.scot.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Douglas Young</last_name>
    <email>douglas.young@nhslothian.scot.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Infirmary of Edinburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edinburgh</city>
        <state>Lothian</state>
        <zip>EH16 4SA</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <phone>0131 536 1000</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 21, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 22, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 27, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 22, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 22, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 27, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Total Knee Replacement</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient Specific Instrumentation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data available to bone fide researchers at the end of the study</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

