<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01699880</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HLM_JDR1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01699880</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of High Flow Nasal Cannula Oxygen to Reduce Desaturation During Tracheal Intubation</brief_title>
  <acronym>HAPI</acronym>
  <official_title>High Flow Nasal Cannula Oxygen for Pre and During Procedure Oxygenation During Tracheal Intubation: Comparison With High FiO2 Non Rebreathing Bag Reservoir Facemasks</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hôpital Louis Mourier</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hôpital Louis Mourier</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Tracheal intubation of critically ill patients is associated in the intensive care unit (ICU)
      with significant complications and morbidity. Patient desaturation is one of the most common
      complications that may lead to cardiac arrest despite pre-intubation oxygenation.
      Preoxygenation can be improved by the use of non-invasive ventilation, but this technique can
      be cumbersome to implement in the context of urgent intubation and more importantly it does
      not insure oxygenation during intubation. High flow nasal cannula oxygen therapy is a
      technique that has been shown to improve patient oxygenation in the context of acute
      hypoxemic respiratory failure. It bears the potential to be of clinical benefit in the
      setting of tracheal intubation in the ICU to ensure patient safety. The purpose of this study
      is to compare pre- and per-intubation (during intubation) oxygenation with either a
      conventional high FiO2 oxygen bag reservoir facemask (current standard practice) or high flow
      nasal cannula oxygen therapy (new practice to be implemented in our ICU).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pre-oxygenation is ensured in our ICU with a high FiO2 nonrebreathing facemask, except in
      patients already under high flow nasal cannula oxygen therapy because of acute hypoxemic
      respiratory failure. A nasal catheter is positioned to ensure a low oxygen flow during
      laryngoscopy. Whether or not all patients should benefit from high flow nasal cannula oxygen
      therapy for pre-oxygenation remains unknown. In order to improve quality of care delivered to
      our patients and in anticipation of a change in our practice, we decided to record
      prospectively oxygen parameters during and immediately of intubation using a facemask and to
      compare them with parameters obtained in patients intubated after our change in practice. The
      change of practice consists in the systematic use of high flow nasal cannula oxygen therapy
      to ensure pre and during procedure (tracheal intubation)oxygenation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>lowest pulse oxymetry (SpO2) during intubation</measure>
    <time_frame>from beginning of laryngoscopy to completed intubation</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>mean pulse oxymetry during intubation</measure>
    <time_frame>from beginning of laryngoscopy to completed intubation</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>pulse oxymetry after preoxygenation</measure>
    <time_frame>3min prexoxygenation</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>pulse oxymetry after intubation</measure>
    <time_frame>at connection of the patient to the ventilator</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>mean pulse oxymetry</measure>
    <time_frame>one, five and thirty minutes after intubation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>number of pulse oxymetry below 90%</measure>
    <time_frame>from laryngoscopy to 30 minutes once tracheal intubation completed</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>number of pulse oxymetry below 80%</measure>
    <time_frame>from laryngoscopy to 30 minutes once tracheal intubation completed</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>cardiac arrest</measure>
    <time_frame>during and immediately after procedure</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>hemodynamic instability defined as arterial systolic blood pressure below 80 mmHg</measure>
    <time_frame>during and immediately after procedure</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">101</enrollment>
  <condition>Need for Intubation</condition>
  <condition>Oxygenation Before and During Intubation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>conventional high FiO2 bag reservoir facemask</arm_group_label>
    <description>this group of patients is intubated according to our current practice that requires the use of a high FiO2 nonrebreathing with bag reservoir facemask to ensure preoxygenation in patients requiring tracheal intubation. a small nasal catheter is inserted just before laryngoscopy to ensure a low oxygen flow to allow oxygenation during laryngoscopy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>high flow nasal cannula oxygen</arm_group_label>
    <description>we wish to change our standard practice of preoxygenation and expand our use of high flow nasal cannula oxygen therapy to the tracheal intubation setting. Currently, used of high flow oxygen nasal cannula oxygen therapy to ensure oxygenation during intubation is limited to the patients already under high flow nasal cannula oxygen. the change of practice consists in the systematic use of high flow nasal cannula oxygen therapy in all patients requiring tracheal intubation in the ICU.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        ICU patients requiring tracheal intubation
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ICU patient requiring tracheal intubation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  age &lt; 18 years

          -  cardiac arrest

          -  acute respiratory failure requiring immediate high flow nasal cannula oxygen, defined
             as patient with SpO2 &lt; 95% while under 15 L:min oxygen with a nonrebreathing facemask
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean-Damien Ricard, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hopital Louis Mourier, AP-HP, Colombes, France</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medico-surgical ICU</name>
      <address>
        <city>Colombes</city>
        <zip>92701</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sztrymf B, Messika J, Bertrand F, Hurel D, Leon R, Dreyfuss D, Ricard JD. Beneficial effects of humidified high flow nasal oxygen in critical care patients: a prospective pilot study. Intensive Care Med. 2011 Nov;37(11):1780-6. doi: 10.1007/s00134-011-2354-6. Epub 2011 Sep 27.</citation>
    <PMID>21946925</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ricard JD. High flow nasal oxygen in acute respiratory failure. Minerva Anestesiol. 2012 Jul;78(7):836-41. Epub 2012 Apr 24. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22531566</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sztrymf B, Messika J, Mayot T, Lenglet H, Dreyfuss D, Ricard JD. Impact of high-flow nasal cannula oxygen therapy on intensive care unit patients with acute respiratory failure: a prospective observational study. J Crit Care. 2012 Jun;27(3):324.e9-13. doi: 10.1016/j.jcrc.2011.07.075. Epub 2011 Sep 29.</citation>
    <PMID>21958974</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lenglet H, Sztrymf B, Leroy C, Brun P, Dreyfuss D, Ricard JD. Humidified high flow nasal oxygen during respiratory failure in the emergency department: feasibility and efficacy. Respir Care. 2012 Nov;57(11):1873-8. doi: 10.4187/respcare.01575. Epub 2012 Mar 13.</citation>
    <PMID>22417844</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 1, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 3, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 4, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 11, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 11, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 12, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hôpital Louis Mourier</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prof Jean-Damien RICARD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Intensive Care Medicine, assistant head of ICU</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>tracheal intubation</keyword>
  <keyword>preoxygenation</keyword>
  <keyword>desaturation</keyword>
  <keyword>hypoxemia</keyword>
  <keyword>oxygen therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>high flow nasal cannula oxygen therapy</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

