<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01690624</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1315.1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01690624</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BI 836858 Dose Escalation in Patients With Refractory or Relapsed Acute Myeloid Leukemia and in Patients in Complete Remission With High Risk to Relapse</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I, Open-label, Cohort Dose Escalation Trial With BI 836858 in Patients With Refractory or Relapsed Acute Myeloid Leukemia and Patients With Acute Myeloid Leukemia in Complete Remission With High Risk to Relapse.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boehringer Ingelheim</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boehringer Ingelheim</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with acute myeloid leukemia who experience a relapse after at least one prior
      regimen may be enrolled in this trial. In addition, acute myeloid leukemia patients who are
      in complete remission with high risk to relapse may be eligible for this trial. The trial
      will examine whether monotherapy with BI 836858 is safe and tolerable at escalating dose
      levels.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 13, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 21, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 21, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determination of the maximum tolerated dose of BI 836858</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with dose limiting toxicity during maximum tolerated dose evaluation for patients with refractory or relapsed acute myeloid leukemia</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with dose limiting toxicity during maximum tolerated dose evaluation for acute myeloid leukemia patients in complete remission with high risk to relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum measured plasma concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 168 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time from dosing to the maximum plasma concentration (tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 168 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve over the time interval of one week (AUC0-168)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 168 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve over the time interval of one treatment cycle (AUC0-tz)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 336 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve over the time interval from zero extrapolated to infinity (AUC0-infinity)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 168 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal half-life (t1/2)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 168 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean residence time after intravenous infusion (MRT)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 168 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total plasma clearance (CL)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 168 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Apparent volume of distribution during the terminal phase (Vz)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 168 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Volume of distribution after intravenous infusion at steady state (Vss)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 168 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve over the time interval from zero to the time of the last quantifiable data point (AUC0-tz)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 168 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Best overall response rate according to International Working Group (IWG) criteria (for refractory or relapsed acute myeloid leukemia patients only)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 22 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival for patients with refractory or relapsed acute myeloid leukemia</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 22 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to treatment failure for patients with refractory or relapsed acute myeloid leukemia</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 22 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to treatment failure for acute myeloid leukemia patients in complete remission with high risk to relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 22 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival for acute myeloid leukemia patients in complete remission with high risk to relapse</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 22 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with relapsed or refractoryAML</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with acute myeloid leukemia who have relapsed after 1 prior treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BI 836858</intervention_name>
    <description>Monotherapy with BI 836858 administered as intravenous infusion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with relapsed or refractoryAML</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of relapsed or refractory AML with at least one prior treatment for acute
             myeloid leukemia and patients with diagnosis of acute myeloid leukemia in complete
             remission with high risk to relapse.

          2. Expression of CD33 on more than 30% of bone marrow blasts at screening for patients
             with refractory or relapsed acute myeloid leukemia is required. CD33 positive
             expression of bone marrow blasts at the time of initial acute myeloid leukemia
             diagnosis is sufficient for those patients in complete remission with high risk to
             relapse.

          3. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group Performance Status 0, 1 or 2

          4. Age 18 years or older

          5. Written informed consent which is consistent with International Conference on
             Harmonization, Good Clinical Practice (ICH-GCP) guidelines and local legislation.

        Exclusion criteria:

          1. Patients with acute promyelocytic leukemia according to WHO definition.

          2. Patients with refractory or relapsed acute myeloid leukemia &gt; 5.000 blasts in the
             peripheral blood.

          3. Anti-leukemia therapy within two weeks before first treatment with BI 836858, 4 weeks
             for biologics. Parallel treatment with Hydroxyurea ia allowed with refractory or
             relapsed acute myeloid leukemia patients.

          4. Allogeneic stem cell transplantation within the last 28 days before first treatment
             with graft versus host disease requiring more than 20 mg of steroids per day. Steroid
             dosage must be stable within two weeks prior to start of treatment.

          5. Patients who are candidates for allogeneic stem cell transplantation (for patients
             with refractory or relapsed acute myeloid leukemia).

          6. Second malignancy currently requiring active therapy.

          7. Symptomatic central nervous system involvement

          8. Aspartate amino transferase (AST) or alanine amino transferase (ALT) greater than 2.5
             times the upper limit of normal (ULN), or AST or ALT greater than 5 times the ULN for
             those with Gilbert syndrome.

          9. Prothrombin time (PT) &gt;1.5 x ULN for subjects not on therapeutic vitamin K antagonists
             (phenprocoumon, warfarin)

         10. Bilirubin greater than 1.5 mg/dl (&gt;26 µmol/L) unless elevation is thought to be due to
             hepatic infiltration by AML, Gilbert syndrome, or hemolysis.

         11. Serum creatinine greater than 2.0 mg/dl

         12. Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection or active hepatitis B virus or
             hepatitis C virus infection.

         13. Concomitant intercurrent illness, or any condition which in the opinion of the
             Investigator, would compromise safe participation in the study, e.g. active severe
             infection, unstable angina pectoris, new onset of exacerbation of a cardiac arrhythmia

         14. Psychiatric illness or social situation that would limit compliance with trial
             requirements

         15. Concomitant therapy, which is considered relevant for the evaluation of the efficacy
             or safety of the trial drug

         16. Female patients of childbearing potential who are sexually active and unwilling to use
             a medically acceptable method of contraception during the trial and for 6 months after
             the last administration of BI 836858

         17. Male patients with partners of childbearing potential who are unwilling to use condoms
             in combination with a second effective method of contraception during the trial and
             for 6 months after the last administration of BI 836858

         18. Pregnant or nursing female patients

         19. Treatment with another investigational agent under the following conditions:

               1. Within two weeks (4 weeks for biologics or 5 half-lives, whichever is longer) of
                  first administration of BI 836858; or

               2. Patient has persistent toxicities from prior anti-leukemic therapies which are
                  determined to be relevant by the Investigator.

               3. Concomitant treatment with another investigational agent while participating in
                  this trial.

         20. Prior treatment with a CD33 antibody

         21. Patient unable or unwilling to comply with the protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Boehringer Ingelheim</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Boehringer Ingelheim</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center at Johns Hopkins</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21287</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Ohio State University Wexner Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 13, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 19, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 24, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

