<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02851862</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015P002399</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02851862</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Natural History of Late Onset Tay-Sachs Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Natural History of Late Onset Tay-Sachs Disease: MGH Site</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to learn more about the natural history of Late Onset GM2
      Gangliosidosis (Tay-Sachs disease and Sandhoff Disease) to inform future clinical trials.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      For this study, subjects will come to Massachusetts General Hospital for two study visits,
      six months apart. At each visit, the following tests will be done:

      A Neurological Exam, Several Ataxia Rating Scales, A Formal Speech assessment, Magnetic
      resonance imaging and spectroscopy, A blood draw, An optional lumbar puncture.

      Outcome measures and biomarkers (MRI atrophy measures, chemical shift imaging (CSI), MRS and
      CSF metabolites) will be compared to the clinical disease course in Late Onset GM2
      Gangliosidosis. The natural history by retrospective surveys (previously acquired) will shed
      light on how changes in outcome measures compare to the larger context of changing symptoms
      (that occurs on the scale of years and decades). This combined approach will elucidate
      optimal outcome measures and determine eligibility criteria for a future clinical trial in
      Late Onset GM2 Gangliosidosis.

      The international web-based platform for clinical research networks, NeuroBANK™, in which
      clinicians and researchers collect and share their patients' clinical and research data, will
      be used. This system has been implemented by and deployed at the Neurological Clinical
      Research Institute at Massachusetts General Hospital. This platform allows clinicians to
      enter patient data, either a) manually via a Web-based interface, or b) by exporting the data
      from the electronic health record (EHR) and clinical data repositories.

      GLOBAL UNIQUE IDENTIFIERS (GUID):

      A patient Global Unique Identifier (GUID) will be used as the identifier for individuals
      participating in the study in NeuroBANK™. The GUID is an 11-character string that is
      generated using encryption technology and algorithms licensed by the NCRI from the National
      Institutes of Health (NIH).

      The GUID is generated on a secure website that utilizes 128-bit Secure Socket Layer (SSL). Of
      note, this website is not linked to NeuroBANK™. The GUID is generated using an irreversible
      encryption algorithm - it accepts twelve identifying data elements, (e.g. last name at birth,
      first name at birth, gender at birth, day, month and year of birth, city and country of
      birth, etc.), and produces a unique random-generated character string, or GUID. No
      identifying information is stored in the system; it is simply used to generate the GUID. If
      the same information is entered again, the same GUID will be returned.

      The GUID is entered into NeuroBANK™ when the patient is being created in the system. As the
      same patient may participate in multiple studies, NeuroBANK™ will also allow capturing a
      study-specific ID for the patient. For more information about NeuroBANK™ or the GUID, please
      go to: www.neurobank.org.

      Data Management:

      The NCRI Data Management Team is trained and knowledgeable regarding confidentiality and
      integrity of data. They will be responsible for all aspects of data procedures. Alex Sherman
      is the ALD Connect network strategist and member of the NEALS ALS consortium. He is the
      director of Strategic Development and Systems of NCRI, serves on the Executive Committee of
      the ALS Research Group, and is one of the leaders of the NEALS ALS Consortium.

      Data Quality Checks, Logic Checks and Queries:

      The Data Manager (DM) at the Neurological Clinical Research Institute (NCRI) at the
      Massachusetts General Hospital will conduct monthly Data Quality Checks, Logic Checks, and
      internal data quality audits. Data field queries will be resolved in an established workflow
      according to the Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs). The queries may be created either at
      the point of entry during the data entry process, manually by the NCRI DM, or as the result
      of executing monthly Logic Checks.

      Study-Specific Database Backup and Maintenance:

      The NCRI personnel will be responsible for the database backups that will be conducted daily.
      Simultaneously, a separate copy of the backup in the encrypted compressed format will be
      maintained and saved by the System Analysts. The backups will be saved on a separate computer
      partition in a password-protected compressed format and also will be burnt into DVD medium
      and stored in a secure location.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2016</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>6 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Brief Ataxia Rating Scale over six months</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 month visits</time_frame>
    <description>Ataxia rating scale incorporating gait, dysarthria, and coordination</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change over six months in metabolite levels seen on magnetic resonance spectroscopy</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change over six months in lipid levels found in the cerebrospinal fluid</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>GM2 Gangliosidosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Late Onset GM2 Gangliosidosis</arm_group_label>
    <description>10-15 subjects with Late Onset GM2 Gangliosidosis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood will be collected to establish lymphoblast cell lines. Cerebrospinal fluid will also be
      collected from some subjects.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects diagnosed with Late Onset GM2 Gangliosidosis
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The subject must have a confirmed diagnosis of Late Onset GM2 Gangliosidosis as
             defined by (a) absent to near-absent beta-hexosaminidase enzymatic activity in the
             serum or white blood cells or (b) mutation analysis of the HEXA and HEXB genes to
             distinguish pseudo deficiency alleles from disease-causing alleles

          -  The subject must be older than 7 years of age

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  If a patient is very severely affected by the disease, the PI will assess whether it
             is in the best interest of the patient to exclude them from the study for their own
             comfort and well being. In cases where the PI deems it appropriate, severely affected
             patients will be excluded. Patients under the age of 7 years will be excluded from
             this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Florian Eichler, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Peter James, BA</last_name>
    <phone>617-643-4218</phone>
    <email>pfjames@partners.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Peter James, BA</last_name>
      <phone>617-643-4218</phone>
      <email>pfjames@partners.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Florian Eichler, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 19, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 28, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 2, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 16, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Florian Eichler</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of the Center for Rare Neurological Diseases</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gangliosidoses</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tay-Sachs Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gangliosidoses, GM2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Data from this study will be stored in a computer data repository at the Massachusetts General Hospital (MGH) Neurological Clinical Research Institute (NCRI). The purpose of this data repository is to capture and store data for clinical research. The repository will combine data from multiple studies. Datasets will be shared with researchers who want to advance understanding of Neurological Disease. These datasets will not contain any personal identifiable information.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

