<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02852499</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>38RC13.579</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02852499</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Following of Atmospheric Pollution Exposure During Pregnancy and Effects on Health</brief_title>
  <acronym>SEPAGES-1337</acronym>
  <official_title>SEPAGES : Following of Atmospheric Pollution Exposure During Pregnancy and Effects on Health</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Grenoble</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Grenoble</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The SEPAGES couple-child cohort is coordinated by an Inserm (French National Institute of
      Health and Medical Research) team of environmental epidemiology. SEPAGES cohort is based on
      the general population and aims to cover several areas of environmental health research,
      including endocrine disruptors and air pollutants.

      The main objectives is to quantify the impact of pollution during pregnancy and the first
      years of life on three main health outcomes : growth, respiratory health and
      neuro-development ; and to better understand the biological mechanism (such as genetic
      analysis to study the role of environmental factors on genes expression as well as the role
      of genetic factors on health). The objective is to include 500 families.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      SEPAGES is a new type of longitudinal couple-child cohort with repeated clinical examinations
      during pregnancy and childhood, extensive collection of repeated biological samples from both
      parents and the child, use of new technologies to assess exposure to air pollution (GPS,
      personal dosimeter etc.) Throughout the study (during pregnancy and the first years of the
      child's life), clinical examination and many biological tests (urine, blood, hair) are
      performed. Exposure to different environmental factors are made several times during
      pregnancy and the first years of the child's life thanks to personal dosimeters, GPS and
      accelerometers. During labor and childbirth a number of samples are taken (placenta, tissues,
      blood, urines, hair, meconium and breast milk). Finally, during the study a number of
      evaluation questionnaires are given to volunteers via a computer platform in order to have a
      better understanding of the environment in which they are living.

      The SEPAGES cohort follows the rule of the biomedical research. Informed consents are signed
      by both the father and the mother during the inclusion visit which takes place in the
      hospital. All ethical and data privacy agreements had been obtained : a favorable opinion was
      issued by the Comité de Protection des Personnes (CPP) on November 13th, 201 and by the
      CCTIRS (Comité Consultatif sur le Traitement de l'Information en matière de Recherche dans le
      domaine de la Santé) on January 09th, 2014. The study was authorised by the Agence Nationale
      de Sécurité du Médicament(ANSM), on Decmber 17th, 2013 and by the Comité Nationale de
      l'Informatique et des Libertés (CNIL) on June 26th, 2014.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical exam : biological sampling</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to one hour</time_frame>
    <description>Sampling of : meconium, strands of hair, mouth cells, nose cells and a skin test in g</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical exam : biological sampling</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to one hour</time_frame>
    <description>Sampling of : urines, blood in mL</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1010</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mothers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Pregnant women.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fathers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Futur fathers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Children</arm_group_label>
    <description>Children after childbirth.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Urine sampling</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Mothers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fathers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carry a GPS and BET</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Mothers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Carry pollution sensor</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Mothers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sampling at the maternity</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Mothers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Self-questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Mothers</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Fathers</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sampling in partum period</intervention_name>
    <description>Meconium and a strand of hair.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Children</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Pregnant women before 19 getsationel week, older than 18 years old Father of the children
        Children at birth
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  pregnant women

          -  &lt; 19 gestational weeks

          -  &gt; 18 years old

          -  living in the area of Grenoble

          -  planning to give birth in one of the four maternities located in Grenoble

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  not speaking French

          -  no access to the French social security
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>iSABELLE Pin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Grenoble</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Couple Enfant - Grenoble</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Tronche</city>
        <zip>38700</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barker DJ, Osmond C, Golding J, Kuh D, Wadsworth ME. Growth in utero, blood pressure in childhood and adult life, and mortality from cardiovascular disease. BMJ. 1989 Mar 4;298(6673):564-7.</citation>
    <PMID>2495113</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barker DJ, Winter PD, Osmond C, Margetts B, Simmonds SJ. Weight in infancy and death from ischaemic heart disease. Lancet. 1989 Sep 9;2(8663):577-80.</citation>
    <PMID>2570282</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barker DJ. The developmental origins of adult disease. J Am Coll Nutr. 2004 Dec;23(6 Suppl):588S-595S. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15640511</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lawlor DA, Ebrahim S, Davey Smith G. Association of birth weight with adult lung function: findings from the British Women's Heart and Health Study and a meta-analysis. Thorax. 2005 Oct;60(10):851-8. Epub 2005 Jul 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16055617</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rona RJ, Gulliford MC, Chinn S. Effects of prematurity and intrauterine growth on respiratory health and lung function in childhood. BMJ. 1993 Mar 27;306(6881):817-20.</citation>
    <PMID>8490372</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martinez FD, Wright AL, Taussig LM, Holberg CJ, Halonen M, Morgan WJ. Asthma and wheezing in the first six years of life. The Group Health Medical Associates. N Engl J Med. 1995 Jan 19;332(3):133-8.</citation>
    <PMID>7800004</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Håland G, Carlsen KC, Sandvik L, Devulapalli CS, Munthe-Kaas MC, Pettersen M, Carlsen KH; ORAACLE. Reduced lung function at birth and the risk of asthma at 10 years of age. N Engl J Med. 2006 Oct 19;355(16):1682-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17050892</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stern DA, Morgan WJ, Wright AL, Guerra S, Martinez FD. Poor airway function in early infancy and lung function by age 22 years: a non-selective longitudinal cohort study. Lancet. 2007 Sep 1;370(9589):758-64.</citation>
    <PMID>17765525</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jensen TK, Jørgensen N, Punab M, Haugen TB, Suominen J, Zilaitiene B, Horte A, Andersen AG, Carlsen E, Magnus Ø, Matulevicius V, Nermoen I, Vierula M, Keiding N, Toppari J, Skakkebaek NE. Association of in utero exposure to maternal smoking with reduced semen quality and testis size in adulthood: a cross-sectional study of 1,770 young men from the general population in five European countries. Am J Epidemiol. 2004 Jan 1;159(1):49-58.</citation>
    <PMID>14693659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moshammer H, Hoek G, Luttmann-Gibson H, Neuberger MA, Antova T, Gehring U, Hruba F, Pattenden S, Rudnai P, Slachtova H, Zlotkowska R, Fletcher T. Parental smoking and lung function in children: an international study. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2006 Jun 1;173(11):1255-63. Epub 2006 Feb 16.</citation>
    <PMID>16484675</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McKeever TM, Lewis SA, Smith C, Collins J, Heatlie H, Frischer M, Hubbard R. Early exposure to infections and antibiotics and the incidence of allergic disease: a birth cohort study with the West Midlands General Practice Research Database. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2002 Jan;109(1):43-50.</citation>
    <PMID>11799364</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li YF, Langholz B, Salam MT, Gilliland FD. Maternal and grandmaternal smoking patterns are associated with early childhood asthma. Chest. 2005 Apr;127(4):1232-41.</citation>
    <PMID>15821200</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaheen SO, Sterne JA, Montgomery SM, Azima H. Birth weight, body mass index and asthma in young adults. Thorax. 1999 May;54(5):396-402.</citation>
    <PMID>10212102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller RL, Ho SM. Environmental epigenetics and asthma: current concepts and call for studies. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2008 Mar 15;177(6):567-73. doi: 10.1164/rccm.200710-1511PP. Epub 2008 Jan 10. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18187692</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Breton CV, Byun HM, Wenten M, Pan F, Yang A, Gilliland FD. Prenatal tobacco smoke exposure affects global and gene-specific DNA methylation. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2009 Sep 1;180(5):462-7. doi: 10.1164/rccm.200901-0135OC. Epub 2009 Jun 4.</citation>
    <PMID>19498054</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shaheen SO, Adcock IM. The developmental origins of asthma: does epigenetics hold the key? Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2009 Oct 15;180(8):690-1.</citation>
    <PMID>19824169</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Foley DL, Craig JM, Morley R, Olsson CA, Dwyer T, Smith K, Saffery R. Prospects for epigenetic epidemiology. Am J Epidemiol. 2009 Feb 15;169(4):389-400. doi: 10.1093/aje/kwn380. Epub 2009 Jan 12. Review. Erratum in: Am J Epidemiol. 2009 Jun 1;169(11):1409. Olsson, Craig J [corrected to Olsson, Craig A].</citation>
    <PMID>19139055</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baccarelli A, Wright RO, Bollati V, Tarantini L, Litonjua AA, Suh HH, Zanobetti A, Sparrow D, Vokonas PS, Schwartz J. Rapid DNA methylation changes after exposure to traffic particles. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2009 Apr 1;179(7):572-8. doi: 10.1164/rccm.200807-1097OC. Epub 2009 Jan 8.</citation>
    <PMID>19136372</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bråbäck L, Forsberg B. Does traffic exhaust contribute to the development of asthma and allergic sensitization in children: findings from recent cohort studies. Environ Health. 2009 Apr 16;8:17. doi: 10.1186/1476-069X-8-17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19371435</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brauer M, Hoek G, Smit HA, de Jongste JC, Gerritsen J, Postma DS, Kerkhof M, Brunekreef B. Air pollution and development of asthma, allergy and infections in a birth cohort. Eur Respir J. 2007 May;29(5):879-88. Epub 2007 Jan 24.</citation>
    <PMID>17251230</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mortimer K, Neugebauer R, Lurmann F, Alcorn S, Balmes J, Tager I. Air pollution and pulmonary function in asthmatic children: effects of prenatal and lifetime exposures. Epidemiology. 2008 Jul;19(4):550-7; discussion 561-2. doi: 10.1097/EDE.0b013e31816a9dcb.</citation>
    <PMID>18520616</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pinkerton KE, Joad JP. Influence of air pollution on respiratory health during perinatal development. Clin Exp Pharmacol Physiol. 2006 Mar;33(3):269-72. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16487273</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ritz B, Yu F. The effect of ambient carbon monoxide on low birth weight among children born in southern California between 1989 and 1993. Environ Health Perspect. 1999 Jan;107(1):17-25.</citation>
    <PMID>9872713</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Slama R, Darrow L, Parker J, Woodruff TJ, Strickland M, Nieuwenhuijsen M, Glinianaia S, Hoggatt KJ, Kannan S, Hurley F, Kalinka J, Srám R, Brauer M, Wilhelm M, Heinrich J, Ritz B. Meeting report: atmospheric pollution and human reproduction. Environ Health Perspect. 2008 Jun;116(6):791-8. doi: 10.1289/ehp.11074.</citation>
    <PMID>18560536</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jedrychowski W, Bendkowska I, Flak E, Penar A, Jacek R, Kaim I, Spengler JD, Camann D, Perera FP. Estimated risk for altered fetal growth resulting from exposure to fine particles during pregnancy: an epidemiologic prospective cohort study in Poland. Environ Health Perspect. 2004 Oct;112(14):1398-402.</citation>
    <PMID>15471732</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Slama R, Thiebaugeorges O, Goua V, Aussel L, Sacco P, Bohet A, Forhan A, Ducot B, Annesi-Maesano I, Heinrich J, Magnin G, Schweitzer M, Kaminski M, Charles MA; EDEN Mother-Child Cohort Study Group. Maternal personal exposure to airborne benzene and intrauterine growth. Environ Health Perspect. 2009 Aug;117(8):1313-21. doi: 10.1289/ehp.0800465. Epub 2009 Apr 1.</citation>
    <PMID>19672414</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Slama R, Morgenstern V, Cyrys J, Zutavern A, Herbarth O, Wichmann HE, Heinrich J; LISA Study Group. Traffic-related atmospheric pollutants levels during pregnancy and offspring's term birth weight: a study relying on a land-use regression exposure model. Environ Health Perspect. 2007 Sep;115(9):1283-92.</citation>
    <PMID>17805417</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lepeule J, Caïni F, Bottagisi S, Galineau J, Hulin A, Marquis N, Bohet A, Siroux V, Kaminski M, Charles MA, Slama R; EDEN Mother–Child Cohort Study Group. Maternal exposure to nitrogen dioxide during pregnancy and offspring birth weight: comparison of two exposure models. Environ Health Perspect. 2010 Oct;118(10):1483-9. doi: 10.1289/ehp.0901509. Epub 2010 May 14.</citation>
    <PMID>20472526</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu J, Ren C, Delfino RJ, Chung J, Wilhelm M, Ritz B. Association between local traffic-generated air pollution and preeclampsia and preterm delivery in the south coast air basin of California. Environ Health Perspect. 2009 Nov;117(11):1773-9. doi: 10.1289/ehp.0800334. Epub 2009 Jun 23.</citation>
    <PMID>20049131</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gulliver J, Briggs DJ. Time-space modeling of journey-time exposure to traffic-related air pollution using GIS. Environ Res. 2005 Jan;97(1):10-25.</citation>
    <PMID>15476729</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cooper AR, Page AS, Wheeler BW, Hillsdon M, Griew P, Jago R. Patterns of GPS measured time outdoors after school and objective physical activity in English children: the PEACH project. Int J Behav Nutr Phys Act. 2010 Apr 22;7:31. doi: 10.1186/1479-5868-7-31.</citation>
    <PMID>20412582</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Colquhoun DR, Goldman LR, Cole RN, Gucek M, Mansharamani M, Witter FR, Apelberg BJ, Halden RU. Global screening of human cord blood proteomes for biomarkers of toxic exposure and effect. Environ Health Perspect. 2009 May;117(5):832-8. doi: 10.1289/ehp.11816. Epub 2008 Dec 2.</citation>
    <PMID>19478969</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hauser R, Meeker JD, Park S, Silva MJ, Calafat AM. Temporal variability of urinary phthalate metabolite levels in men of reproductive age. Environ Health Perspect. 2004 Dec;112(17):1734-40. Erratum in: Environ Health Perspect. 2004 Dec;112(17):1740.</citation>
    <PMID>15579421</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Klerk NH, English DR, Armstrong BK. A review of the effects of random measurement error on relative risk estimates in epidemiological studies. Int J Epidemiol. 1989 Sep;18(3):705-12.</citation>
    <PMID>2807678</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zanobetti A, Canner MJ, Stone PH, Schwartz J, Sher D, Eagan-Bengston E, Gates KA, Hartley LH, Suh H, Gold DR. Ambient pollution and blood pressure in cardiac rehabilitation patients. Circulation. 2004 Oct 12;110(15):2184-9. Epub 2004 Oct 4.</citation>
    <PMID>15466639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amsallem F, Gauthier R, Ramonatxo M, Counil F, Voisin M, Denjean A, Matecki S; Groupe des EFR pédiatriques, Société Français de Physiologie. [Respiratory function testing in infants: recommendations on normal values]. Rev Mal Respir. 2008 Apr;25(4):405-32. Review. French.</citation>
    <PMID>18536627</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horsley A. Lung clearance index in the assessment of airways disease. Respir Med. 2009 Jun;103(6):793-9. doi: 10.1016/j.rmed.2009.01.025. Epub 2009 Feb 25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19246184</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 26, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 28, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 2, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 29, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>environmental epidemiology</keyword>
  <keyword>cohort</keyword>
  <keyword>atmospheric pollutant</keyword>
  <keyword>chemical pollutant</keyword>
  <keyword>growth, neuro-development, respiratory health</keyword>
  <keyword>big data</keyword>
  <keyword>biological samples (RNA, DNA, urines ...)</keyword>
  <keyword>e-dohad and exposome</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

