<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02857348</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO16070572</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02857348</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Trial of a Video Game Intervention to Recalibrate Physician Heuristics</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial of a Video Game Intervention to Recalibrate Physician Heuristics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Carnegie Mellon University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to compare the efficacy of a video game designed to
      recalibrate physician heuristics in trauma triage with a standard educational program.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Treatment at trauma centers improves outcomes for patients with moderate-to-severe injuries.
      Accordingly, professional organizations, state authorities, and the federal government have
      endorsed the systematic triage and transfer of these patients to trauma centers either
      directly from the field or after evaluation at a non-trauma center. Nonetheless, between 30
      to 40% of patients with moderate-to-severe injuries still only receive treatment at
      non-trauma centers, so-called under-triage. Most of this under-triage occurs because of
      physician decisions (rather than first-responder decisions). Existing efforts to change
      physician decision making focus primarily on knowledge of clinical practice guidelines and
      attitudes towards the guidelines. These strategies ignores the growing consensus that
      decision making reflects both knowledge as well as intuitive judgments (heuristics).
      Heuristics, mental short cuts based on pattern recognition, drive the majority of decision
      making. The investigators have developed an adventure video game (Night Shift) to serve as a
      novel method of recalibrating physician heuristics in trauma triage and will compare its
      efficacy with a standard educational program.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Under-triage rate</measure>
    <time_frame>After completion of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Physicians in both arms of the study will be randomized to complete one of two versions of a virtual simulation: a control version and a cognitive load version. They will complete the simulation upon completion of the intervention, ideally within one month of enrollment.
The virtual simulation replicates the environment of the ED. Physicians have to manage 10 patients that appear concurrently, while also responding to a series of audio-visual distractors. Specifically, they must provide information on whether they will admit, transfer, or discharge the patients home. The investigators will calculate an under-triage rate for each physician (the number of simulated patients with severe injuries not transferred to a trauma center), summarize the under-triage rate by group (Night Shift v. educational control), and will compare the difference in those rates.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The effect of cognitive load on the under-triage rate</measure>
    <time_frame>After completion of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>As described above, participants will complete either a control or cognitive load version of the virtual simulation upon completion of the intervention, ideally within one month of the enrollment. As a secondary outcome measure, the investigators will assess the difference in under-triage rates of physicians who complete the simulation under control and cognitive load conditions, by intervention type.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">368</enrollment>
  <condition>Wounds and Injuries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Adventure video game</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Physicians in this arm of the trial will be asked to play Night Shift, an adventure video game, for one hour.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Educational Module</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Physicians in this arm of the trial will be asked to use myATLS, an app designed by the American College of Surgeons to serve as an adjunct to the ATLS course, and Trauma Life Support MCQ Review, an app designed to help students prepare for the ATLS exam. They will be asked to spend at least one hour on the combined tasks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Night Shift</intervention_name>
    <description>Night Shift is an adventure video game with the transformational goal of teaching physicians key characteristics of patients with non-representative severe injuries - injuries classified by the American College of Surgeons as life-threatening or critical but that do not fit the archetype of injuries typically requiring treatment at a trauma center. Players take on the persona of Andy Jordan, a young emergency physician who moves home after the disappearance of his estranged grandfather (Robert Jordan) and takes up a job in the local Emergency Department (ED). In the preamble, players learn they have two explicit objectives. First, they must diagnose and treat patients who present to their ED. Second they must solve the mystery of Robert's disappearance: was he murdered or has he simply chosen to disappear?</description>
    <arm_group_label>Adventure video game</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Educational Module</intervention_name>
    <description>The educational module consists of two separate apps, both commercially available. myATLS includes a review of each chapter of the Advanced Trauma Life Support (ATLS) textbook, a series of videos demonstrating common trauma procedures, and clinical resources including checklists for use at the bedside. Trauma Life Support MCQ Review includes 550 multiple-choice questions with correct answers and explanations. The investigators will ask physicians to review the myATLS app and then complete questions in the Trauma Life Support MCQ Review, spending at least 1 hour on the combined tasks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Educational Module</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Physicians who care for adult patients in the Emergency Department.

          -  Physicians who work at a non-trauma center.

          -  Physicians who work at a Level III/IV trauma center.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Physicians who work at a Level I/II trauma center.

          -  Physicians who do not practice in the US.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Deepika Mohan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 28, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 2, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 5, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 24, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Deepika Mohan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>decision making</keyword>
  <keyword>heuristics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified data will be made available on application to the investigator team.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

