<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02859493</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15E2899</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02859493</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effect of Saccharomyces Cerevisiae on Vulvo-vaginal Candidiasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Effect of Saccharomyces Cerevisiae on the Improvement of the Conventional Treatment for Vulvo-vaginal Infection to Candida Spp (Local Administration)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lesaffre International</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lesaffre International</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to evaluate the effect of a specific strain of Saccharomyces cerevisiae on
      improving the effectiveness of conventional treatment of vulvo-vaginal candidiasis. This is a
      randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. The administration of yeast will be local
      (vaginal).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2016</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diminution of the vaginal load in Candida spp (Candida albicans, Candida glabrata) in subjects presenting a vulvo-vaginal candidosis</measure>
    <time_frame>after 7 days and 14 days of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>valuation of the effect of vaginal administration of Saccharomyces cerevisiae on the vaginal load in Candida spp (Candida albicans, Candida glabrata) in subjects presenting a vulvo-vaginal candidosis, by counting Candida spp in vaginal samples, before treatment and after 7 days and 14 days of treatment, in addition to a conventional medical treatment and in comparison to the placebo product.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Candidiasis, Vulvovaginal</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Inactivated whole yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae presented in vaginal capsules. 1 capsule a day for 14 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Maize starch and magnesium stearate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo presented in a vaginal capsule. 1 capsule a day for 14 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Maize starch and magnesium stearate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject suffering from a vulvo-vaginal candidiasis (according to clinical examination)
             characterized by a vaginal discharge associated with any of the following symptoms:
             itching and burning vaginal feeling, dyspareunia and dysuria.

          -  Amenorrheic subject, or subject having a regular menstrual cycle.

          -  Subject psychologically able to understand the study related information and to give a
             written informed consent.

          -  Subject having given freely and expressly her informed consent.

          -  Subject able to comply with protocol requirements, as defined in the protocol.

          -  Subject affiliated to a health social security system.

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential should use a medically accepted
             contraceptive regimen (except latex condom, latex diaphragm, spermicidal) during the
             D0-D14 period, since at least 12 weeks before the beginning of the study, during all
             the study and at least 1 month after the study end, at the investigator's discretion

        Exclusion Criteria:

        In terms of population

          -  Pregnant or nursing woman or planning a pregnancy during the study.

          -  Post-menopausal women.

          -  Subject who will have her period between the first and the second visit to the
             gynaecologist (between D0 and D7).

          -  Subject who had been deprived of their freedom by administrative or legal decision or
             who is under guardianship.

          -  Subject in a social or sanitary establishment.

          -  Subject suspected to be non-compliant according to the investigator's judgment.

          -  Subject enrolled in another clinical trial on the same test zone within the four
             previous weeks and during the study period, being in an exclusion period for a
             previous study, having tested a food supplement or a medication in the 4 previous
             weeks.

          -  Subject in an emergency situation. In terms of associated pathology

          -  Subject with a condition or receiving a medication which, in the investigator's
             judgment, put the subject at undue risk.

          -  Subject suffering from systemic diseases using concurrent therapy that may interfere
             with the evaluation of the study results.

          -  Subject with a known allergy to one of the component of the study products or to the
             medication (vaginal ovule and/or antifungal cream).

          -  Subject presenting an hypersensitivity to any antifungal of imidazole family or to one
             of the excipient.

          -  Uterine or vaginal bleeding of unknown origin

          -  Subject with known sexually transmitted infections such as Neisseria gonorrhoea,
             Chlamydia trachomatis, Treponema pallidum, herpes simplex, Trichomonas vaginalis,
             human papilloma virus or HIV 1 or 2.

          -  Immunocompromised subjects

        Relating to previous or ongoing treatment

        • Subject undergoing a topical treatment on the test area or a systemic or intravaginal
        treatment:

          -  antibiotics currently or within the past 2 weeks (systemic antibiotic are accepted if
             the treatment was stopped until the day before the inclusion visit)

          -  anti-fungal agents currently or within the past 2 weeks,

          -  anticoagulant within the past 2 weeks and during the study,

          -  anti-inflammatory medication and/or anti-histamines during the previous 2 weeks and
             during the study,

          -  corticosteroids during the 2 previous weeks and during the study,

          -  retinoids and/or immunosuppressors during the 3 previous months and during the study,

          -  any medication stabilized for less than one month.

        In terms of lifestyle

          -  Subject planning to change her usual hygiene habits and products during the study.

          -  Subjects not willing to stop taking probiotics dietary supplements and food products
             enriched with probiotics.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Amélie Cayzeele Decherf</last_name>
    <phone>+33 3 20 14 83 20</phone>
    <email>ace@lesaffre.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dermscan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Villeurbanne</city>
        <zip>69100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Céline Lhéritier</last_name>
      <phone>+33 (0)4 72 82 36 56</phone>
      <email>clh@dermscan.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 4, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 4, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 9, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 2, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 2, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 5, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Candidiasis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Candidiasis, Vulvovaginal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

