<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02853396</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16/NW/0332</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02853396</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of an Cognitive Behaviour Therapy for Internalised Stigma Intervention for Inpatients With Psychosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot of a Brief Cognitive Behaviour Therapy Formulation Focused Intervention for Internalised Stigma With Acute Inpatients That Experience Psychosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lisa Wood</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Manchester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Stigma is a significant concern for those who experience psychosis. People with psychosis are
      the most stigmatised group of all mental health difficulties. There is a lack of research
      examining the effectiveness of psychological therapies for people who experience psychosis
      who are also experiencing negative impacts of stigma. To date, all studies examining stigma
      therapies have been conducted with outpatients and no support have been developed for
      inpatients. The aim of this study to conduct a pilot randomised controlled trial of a brief
      therapy (based on cognitive behavioural therapy)to help participants cope with stigma. It
      will be compared to a educational control intervention. Both therapies will last
      approximately two hours and be conducted in one or two sessions by the principal investigator
      (clinical psychologist). Participants will be given a number of questionnaires assessing a
      number of outcomes such as impacts of stigma, depression, recovery, and self-esteem.
      Participants will be assessed on these measure prior to the therapy, post therapy and at
      follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A single-blind randomised controlled pilot trial will be conducted comparing a Cognitive
      Behaviour Therapy formulation driven internalised stigma intervention (experimental group)
      against a psychoeducational control intervention (control group). It will follow
      recommendations outlined by the Medical Research Council's framework for the development and
      evaluation of complex interventions. This will allow for the medication of the intervention
      if necessary in order to examine what type of intervention is best suited to the inpatient
      environment.

      Aim: To examine the efficacy of a formulation driven intervention for internalised stigma in
      psychosis with acute inpatients. The intervention will be compared to a brief
      psychoeducational internalised stigma intervention.

      Description of therapies:

      Experimental Condition The experimental condition will receive a two hour intervention
      session (across one or two sessions) which will be based on a Cognitive Behaviour therapy
      formulation. These sessions will be undertaken within a two week period. The sessions will
      collaboratively assess and create a narrative of the participants' experiences of stigma, and
      develop a personalised stigma formulation. A stigma-related goal will be identified and a
      brief intervention will be collaboratively developed to tackle this goal. The intervention
      formulation and change mechanisms will draw upon strategies for people who experience
      psychosis. Intervention strategies may include guided discovery, skills development,
      normalising and belief change strategies, including behavioural experiments targeting
      stigma-relevant appraisals and negative beliefs about self including public stereotypes of
      psychosis, and supporting decisions about whether to disclose.

      Control Condition The control condition will receive a two hour session receiving
      psychoeducation and normalising material relating to stigma in psychosis. The aim of the
      material is normalise experiences of psychosis and stigma. Information includes prevalence
      rates of psychosis, experiences of stigma and discrimination commonly reported by those who
      experience psychosis.

      Both interventions will be delivered by the same therapist.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Internalised stigma of mental illness scale</measure>
    <time_frame>10 minutes</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Process of Recovery Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Depression Inventory</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Beck Hopelessness Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>5 mins</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Self-Esteem Rating scale</measure>
    <time_frame>5 mins</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Attitudes towards mental health scale</measure>
    <time_frame>5 mins</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Cognitive Behaviour Therapy for Internalised Stigma</condition>
  <condition>Psychoeducation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive behavioural therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cognitive behaviour therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Psychoeducation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>psychoeducation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Behaviour Therapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cognitive behavioural therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psychoeducation</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Psychoeducation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 18-65

          -  Who meet criteria for a schizophrenia-spectrum diagnoses (schizophrenia,
             schizophreniform disorder, schizoaffective disorder, delusional disorder or psychotic
             disorder not otherwise specified; ICD-10)

          -  Able to give in-formed consent and have capacity to consent

          -  Receiving care from a clinical in-patient team

          -  Able to complete the interview in English

          -  Self-report being concerned about stigma

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Non-English speakers (due to translation costs)

          -  An acquired brain injury or substance misuse judged to be the acute cause of the
             psychotic experiences

          -  Lacking capacity for informed consent (the applicant will work with the participant to
             assess whether they understand the information sheet and study and therefore their
             ability to give informed consent)

          -  Experiencing severe thought disorder
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>North east london foundation trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ilford</city>
        <state>Essex</state>
        <zip>IG3 8XJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lisa Wood, DClinPsy</last_name>
      <email>lisa.wood@nelft.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 29, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 1, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 2, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 3, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 3, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 5, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Manchester</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Lisa Wood</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Psychologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>internalised stigma</keyword>
  <keyword>self stigma</keyword>
  <keyword>inpatients</keyword>
  <keyword>CBT</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive therapy</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

