<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02858050</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13/16</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02858050</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Portal-724 MEMS for Medication Adherence Patients Taking HCV Medications</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Saint Michael's Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Saint Michael's Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study will look at real-times adhernce monitoring with Portal-724 MEMS cap. It integrates
      medication bottle, Smart Cap, Pill Dispenser, Embedded Computer, Embedded Cellular Modem and
      Tamper Proof apparatus. This device is capable of transmitting pill dispensing events from
      the patient's home to the Cloud over Cellular and IP networks. The transmission is done in
      real time if cellular coverage is above 1-bar, but if cell is not available or if the signal
      is below threshold, then the device Store-and-Forward feature is automatically activated..
      Patient will be randmized to real-time monitoring or to have monitoring data download monthly
      at each study visit while taking hepatitis C medications
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of Portal724-MEMS Service on medication adherence in the treatment of Hepatitis C in patients, defined as compliance to regimen 95% of the time.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the effect of the use of Portal724-MEMS Service on medication adherence in the treatment of Hepatitis C in patients, defined as compliance to regimen 95% of the time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Adherence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Portal-724 MEMs Cap Real-Time Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group 1 will consist of patient taking hepatitis C medicaitons and will have Portal-724 MEMs cap place in their medication bottle and will transmit data in real-time</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Portal-724 MEMs Cap Without Real-Time Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group 2 will consist of patient taking hepatitis C medicaitons and will have Portal-724 MEMs cap place in their medication bottle and data will be downloaded at each study visit while taking hepatitis C medications</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Portal-724 MEMs Cap</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Portal-724 MEMs Cap Real-Time Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Portal-724 MEMs Cap Without Real-Time Monitoring</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Treatment-naïve and treatment-experienced genotype 1 or 4 HCV patients with or without
        compensated cirrhosis will be enrolled in this study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female 18 years old and above.

          2. HCV treatment naïve or HCV trreatment experienced

          3. HCV RNA PCR &gt; 10,000 IU/L

          4. Confirmed infection with Hepatitis C virus (HCV) by HCV serum antibody assay and by
             HCV Ribonucleic Acid (RNA) Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) and Confirmed chronicity
             with 2 PCR's 6 months apart.

          5. Patients with HCV Genotype 1, 4

          6. Patients are candidates for treatment of HCV with oral Direct-Acting Agents (DAA)

          7. understand the study procedures, alternative treatments available, risks involved with
             the study, and voluntarily agrees to participate by giving written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patient not willing to sign written informed consent

          2. Patients deemed not suitable for HCV treatment as deemed by the treating physician at
             the liver center

          3. Patients with decompensated liver cirrhosis, defined as follows:

               1. Liver biopsy within the last year showing Scheuer Stage 4 or transient
                  elastography (Fibroscan®) in the last year with a reading of &gt;12.5 kPa; AND

               2. Any clinical sign of hepatic decompensation such as ascites (fluid in the
                  abdomen), jaundice (yellowing of eyes and skin), esophageal varices with bleeding
                  (enlarged veins of the esophagus seen on endoscopy) or hepatic encephalopathy
                  (tremors, confusion, sleepiness)

          4. Co-Infection with the Hepatitis B virus

          5. Any liver disease of non-HCV etiology such as Hemochromatosis, Wilson's Disease,
             Alcoholic liver disease or Non-Alcoholic Steato-Hepatitis (NASH)

          6. Hepatocellular carcinoma or any other malignancy

          7. Untreated psychiatric conditions such as major depression, schizophrenia, bipolar
             disorder which in the opinion of the Principal Investigator will not interfere with
             protocol visit and/or procedures

          8. Current and untreated substance abuse (cocaine, opiates, alcohol, marijuana, other
             recreational drugs, controlled substances)

          9. Patient is pregnant or breastfeeding.

         10. Patients unwilling to use cellular phones

         11. Patients unwilling to follow specific instructions for medication intake

         12. Patient has any of the following conditions:

               -  Organ transplants (including hematopoietic stem cell transplants) other than
                  cornea and hair.

               -  Poor venous access that precludes routine peripheral blood sampling required for
                  this trial.

               -  History of gastric surgery (e.g., stapling, bypass) or subject with a history of
                  malabsorption disorders (e.g., celiac sprue disease).

               -  History of a medical/surgical condition that resulted in hospitalization within
                  the 3 months prior to enrollment, other than for minor elective procedures

               -  Medical/surgical conditions that may result in a need for hospitalization during
                  the period of the study

               -  any medical condition requiring, or likely to require, chronic systemic
                  administration of corticosteroids, TNF antagonists, or other immunosuppressant
                  drugs during the course of the trial

         13. has exclusionary laboratory values as listed below: Noncirrhotic/Cirrhotic Subjects
             Creatinine clearance &lt; 50 mL/min Hemoglobin &lt;9.5 g/dL for both male and female
             subjects Platelets &lt;50 x 103/μL serum albumin &lt; 3.0 g/dL INR &gt;1.7, unless subject has
             a stable INR on an anticoagulant regimen. HbA1c &gt;10% ALT &gt;10XULN AST &gt;10XULN

         14. is or has an immediate family member (e.g., spouse, parent/legal guardian, sibling or
             child) who is investigational site or sponsor staff directly involved with this trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jihad Slim, MD</last_name>
    <phone>9738772663</phone>
    <email>jsmdsmmc@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saint Michael's Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newark</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07102</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 3, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 5, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 8, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 5, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 5, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 8, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Saint Michael's Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jihad Slim, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief and Program Director, Infectious Diseases</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>April 25, 2018</submitted>
    <submission_canceled>Unknown</submission_canceled>
    <submitted>May 1, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

