<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02852226</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15-17574</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02852226</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CRUSH-PrEP for Women Project</brief_title>
  <official_title>Connecting Resources for Urban Sexual Health: CRUSH-PrEP for Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Gilead Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Lifelong Medical Care</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      UCSF is conducting an evaluation of a demonstration project. The aims of the CRUSH-PrEP for
      Women project are to integrate the delivery of a comprehensive PrEP package for HIV-negative
      at-risk women into primary care settings. The delivery of the PrEP package will leverage the
      well regarded reputation of the LifeLong primary care clinicians to provide a highly
      effective combination HIV prevention strategy including; PrEP, post-exposure prophylaxis
      (nPEP), repeat HIV and STI testing, treatment of sexually transmitted infections. Counselling
      for for sexual health promotion and services specifically designed for vulnerable women such
      as staying free of violence and domestic abuse will be offered as an integrated part of this
      package. UCSF will conduct evaluation activities only. The investigators expect that UCSF
      will enroll 50 participants in the evaluation assessments across the 15 months of data
      collection. Evaluation cohort participants will provide quantitative data to evaluate the
      linkage and engagement in care among clinic attendees as well as the uptake and use of
      Pre-Exposure Prophylaxis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The overall goal of the CRUSH PrEP for Women Project is to enhance and extend a response to
      the local HIV/AIDS epidemic in Alameda County with a set of innovative, evidence-based
      interventions across the continuum of HIV prevention and care, which target the individuals
      and communities that are the most vulnerable to HIV infection. The investigators hypothesize
      that women in Oakland will be interested in accessing PrEP through a community based clinic.
      Specifically, the CRUSH PrEP for Women Project is a 16month demonstration project designed to
      evaluate and assess the adherence of PrEP within a community based clinic. The specific aims
      of the project are as follows:

      Aim 1. Assess uptake and adherence to PrEP among women in the study: Uptake will be measured
      as the proportion of female patients at the LifeLong clinic who are approached that start
      PrEP after being offered PrEP, the numbers and rate of PrEP discontinuation, the reasons
      given for PrEP discontinuation (side effects, no longer at risk, fear of stigma, inability to
      adhere), and drug concentrations. Drug concentrations are monitored using dried blood spots,
      which have a large dynamic range capable of detecting use of a few pills every month up
      through daily use. The main measure of PrEP utilization is the proportion of time that PrEP
      is used effectively among those attempting to use PrEP. Because the effective dose of PrEP is
      less well characterized for women, only blood concentration levels consistent with daily use
      will be considered effective use for this analysis. After the supply of study provided
      medication is ended at 12 months, participants will be followed for an additional 3 months to
      determine the proportion who continued on PrEP. The investigators will describe patterns of
      use and the barriers and facilitators to continued use beyond one year. The investigators
      will look at demographic, and psychosocial and risk factors that may be associated with less
      than daily adherence to medication, and describe reasons for early discontinuation of PrEP
      among any women who choose to stop taking medication prior to the end of the first 12 months.
      Factors associated with discontinuation at the end of the 12-month study provided supply of
      medication will also be described. Although these analyses will be exploratory, the
      investigators hypothesize that changes in relationships and pregnancy intentions will be
      related to changes in PrEP use.

      Aim 2. Assess the characteristics of women who enroll in the PrEP study: For Aim 2, the
      investigators are interested in characterizing the women who decide to take PrEP through this
      project. Demographic and psychosocial variables will be used to describe the population who
      enroll. Sexual and behavioral risk profiles of those who decide to initiate PrEP will also be
      described as part of this study. Demographics of women who uptake PrEP through our community
      partners will also be compared to the demographics of Alameda County women who have incident
      HIV infection. In addition to demographics and risk behavior, the investigators will also
      describe the contraceptive use and intentions of women on PrEP towards future pregnancies as
      these may be important factors driving interest in PrEP among women.

      Aim 3: Assess the referral sources of women who enroll in the PrEP study: Process data will
      capture the outreach efforts made to recruit participants for this study. At the time of
      baseline visit, the source of referral for each woman screened will be captured, as well as
      the primary reason for joining the study. Enrollment progress will be carefully tracked
      against outreach activities to monitor the relationship between outreach efforts and demand
      generation. This will help to inform future implementation of PrEP among women.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of women eligible for PrEP who choose to access PrEP.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Monitor adherence to PrEP through pharmacy pick up information. Self reported adherence and blood levels.</measure>
    <time_frame>48 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Pharmacy records will be accessed to monitor pick-up records. Self administered quantitative interviews will collect self reported adherence to PrEP. Dried blood spot tests are conducted to establish the amount of PrEP taken.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Sexually Transmitted Diseases</condition>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Study Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Assess PrEP among women in the study. Assess the characteristics of women who enroll in the PrEP study. Assess the referral sources of women who enroll in the PrEP study</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pre Exposure Prophylaxis</intervention_name>
    <description>Uptake will be measured as the proportion of female patients at the LifeLong clinic who are approached that start PrEP after being offered PrEP, the numbers and rate of PrEP discontinuation, the reasons given for PrEP discontinuation (side effects, no longer at risk, fear of stigma, inability to adhere), and drug concentrations. Drug concentrations are monitored using dried blood spots, which have a large dynamic range capable of detecting use of a few pills every month up through daily use. The main measure of PrEP utilization is the proportion of time that PrEP is used effectively among those attempting to use PrEP.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PrEP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Characteristics of women who enroll</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigators are interested in characterizing the women who decide to take PrEP through this project. Demographic and psychosocial variables will be used to describe the population who enroll. Sexual and behavioral risk profiles of those who decide to initiate PrEP will also be described as part of this study. Demographics of women who uptake PrEP through community partners will also be compared to the demographics of Alameda County women who have incident HIV infection. In addition to demographics and risk behavior, the investigators will also describe the contraceptive use and intentions of women on PrEP towards future pregnancies as these may be important factors driving interest in PrEP among women.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>referral sources of women who enroll</intervention_name>
    <description>Process data will capture the outreach efforts made to recruit participants for this study. At the time of baseline visit, the investigators will capture the source of referral for each woman screened, as well as the primary reason for joining the study. Enrollment progress will be carefully tracked against outreach activities to monitor the relationship between outreach efforts and demand generation. This will help to inform future implementation of PrEP among women.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Study Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women who are over 18, able to provide consent in English and intending to reside in
             the study area for the next 15 months and meeting the eligibility criteria for PrEP
             per the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists 2014 recommendations will
             be enrolled and complete a baseline evaluation visit.

        Eligibility criteria include: women not infected with HIV who are in one or more of the
        following risk groups:

          1. have a male sexual partner who is HIV positive

          2. engage in sexual activity within a high HIV-prevalence area or social network, and who
             have one or more of the following risk factors:

             Inconsistent or no condom use,

             Diagnosis of sexually transmitted infections,

             Exchange of sex for commodities,

             Use of intravenous drugs or alcohol dependence or both,

          3. have sexual partners of unknown HIV status with any of the factors previously listed.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Absolute Exclusion Criteria:

               -  Under the age of 18

               -  Inability to provide informed consent in English

               -  Intention to leave the study area within the following 15 months

               -  Insufficient renal function (estimated creatinine clearance less than 60 mL/min)

               -  HIV infected

               -  Breastfeeding

        Potential Exclusion Criteria:

          -  High risk known or suspected exposure to HIV within 72 hours prior to presentation;

          -  Osteoporosis;

          -  History of pathological bone fractures not related to trauma;

          -  Ongoing therapy with a drug with significant nephrotoxic potential (other than over
             the counter non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs taken as directed);

          -  Concomitant participation in a clinical trial using investigational agents, including
             placebo-controlled clinical trials using such agents;

          -  Any other conditions that are deemed contraindications for PrEP by the NP/MD; or

          -  Any other condition that would preclude provision of informed consent; make
             participation in the project unsafe; complicate interpretation of outcome data; or
             otherwise interfere with achieving the project objectives, based on the opinion of the
             investigators and/or treating clinician.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janet Myers, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCSF Center for AIDS Prevention</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mi-Suk Kang Dufour, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCSF Center for AIDS Prevention</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kimberly A Koester, MA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UCSF Center for AIDS Prevention</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rebecca Packard, BA</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>UCSF Center for AIDS Prevention</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Janet Myers, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>415-476-6336</phone>
    <email>Janet.Myers@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Rebecca Packard, BA</last_name>
    <phone>707-483-0133</phone>
    <email>becky.packard@ucsf.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Lifelong Medical Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oakland</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94605</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eric Henley, MD</last_name>
      <phone>510-981-4102</phone>
      <email>ehenley@lifelongmedical.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Frances Herb, MD</last_name>
      <phone>510.486.3427</phone>
      <email>fherb@lifelongmedical.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Frances Herb, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eisingerich AB, Wheelock A, Gomez GB, Garnett GP, Dybul MR, Piot PK. Attitudes and acceptance of oral and parenteral HIV preexposure prophylaxis among potential user groups: a multinational study. PLoS One. 2012;7(1):e28238. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0028238. Epub 2012 Jan 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22247757</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gupta N, Schmidt H, Buisker T, Dufour MS, Goldenson J, Myers J, Tulsky J. After the Fact: A Brief Educational Program on HIV Postexposure Prophylaxis for Female Detainees in a Local Jail. J Correct Health Care. 2015 Apr;21(2):140-51. doi: 10.1177/1078345815572335.</citation>
    <PMID>25788609</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koester KA, Maiorana A, Vernon K, Myers J, Rose CD, Morin S. Implementation of HIV prevention interventions with people living with HIV/AIDS in clinical settings: challenges and lessons learned. AIDS Behav. 2007 Sep;11(5 Suppl):S17-29. Epub 2007 Apr 11.</citation>
    <PMID>17436072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Auerbach JD, Kinsky S, Brown G, Charles V. Knowledge, attitudes, and likelihood of pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) use among US women at risk of acquiring HIV. AIDS Patient Care STDS. 2015 Feb;29(2):102-10. doi: 10.1089/apc.2014.0142. Epub 2014 Dec 16.</citation>
    <PMID>25513954</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 10, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 28, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 2, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 7, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 7, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 9, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Janet Myers</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sexually Transmitted Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Access is restricted to those who successfully submit a protocol to the UCSF IRB.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

