<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03043885</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-13360</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03043885</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ridge Preservation With Platelet Rich Fibrin Augmented With Freeze Dried Bone Allograft</brief_title>
  <official_title>Ridge Preservation With Platelet Rich Fibrin Augmented With Freeze Dried Bone Allograft: A Comparative Clinical, Histological, and Micro-computed Tomography Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Francisco</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Francisco</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Improved predictability and quality of bone healing after a tooth is removed is clinically
      relevant, in that, it improves our ability to achieve successful implant placement at
      edentulous sites. Currently, a variety of grafting materials and biologic agents are utilized
      clinically to improve bone healing and provide sufficient dimensions of bone to support a
      dental implant. Platelet rich fibrin (PRF) is one such product that can be used for this
      application. PRF is a concentrated blood product attained from the patient's own blood
      consisting of a natural bioscaffold with integrated growth factors capable of sustained
      release. Once processed, PRF is implanted back into the patient at the wound or defect site
      to encourage healing. The literature regarding PRF is currently dominated by heterogeneous
      applications of PRF for reparative and regenerative therapies without a consensus of its
      clinical efficacy and appropriate application. In this clinical study, PRF will be evaluated
      to ascertain its clinical efficacy in improving bone formation and alveolar dimensional
      stability after tooth extraction. A classic bone grafting material used for this purpose,
      freeze dried bone allograft (FDBA), will be incorporated with the PRF or compared directly to
      PRF alone. It is hypothesized that the natural scaffold and incorporated growth factors of
      PRF augmented with the solubility resistance of FDBA will function as an ideal bioscaffold to
      promote bone healing to a greater extent compared to PRF, FDBA, or blood clot alone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized controlled clinical study evaluating the efficacy of four treatment
      modalities for ridge preservation after extraction of a tooth in preparation for dental
      implant placement. After tooth extraction the alveolar crest remodels during healing with
      reductions in vertical and horizontal dimensions. The resulting reduced dimensions after
      healing of the alveolar crest may be inadequate to successfully place a dental implant to
      replace the missing tooth. In an attempt to minimize the reductions in dimensions and provide
      mature healthy bone to support the dental implant, different ridge preservation techniques
      (treatment of the extraction socket) have been utilized.

      Forty subject from the UCSF Dental School who will be having a tooth extracted and replaced
      with a dental implant will be randomly assigned into the four ridge preservation treatment
      groups. After three months of healing bone samples from the ridge preservation site will be
      collected during the implant placement when bone is removed during the osteotomy preparation
      for the implant. Samples will be evaluated for the extent and quality of bone healing via
      histomorphometric and micro-CT analysis. Clinical measures of alveolar ridge dimensions will
      be taken before and after tooth extraction to determine extent of dimensional stability under
      the different treatment groups.

      The four treatments modalities for ridge preservation include autologous platelet rich fibrin
      (PRF), PRF+freeze dried bone allograft (FDBA), FDBA, collagen barrier membrane. Subjects will
      be enrolled in the study from the time the socket treated to the time of implant placement (3
      months). The results of this study will help to elucidate the extent and quality of bone
      healing using four different methods for ridge preservation in preparation for implant
      placement. Further, this study will advance our knowledge of PRF, an autologous sourced blood
      product used in dentoalveolar surgeries with proven in-vitro qualities but still requiring
      more extensive clinical testing to demonstrate its full clinical utility.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 5, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 9, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of vital bone</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of vital bone at healed extraction socket</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Extent of ridge width preservation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes of alveolar ridge width (in millimeters) during healing phase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Extent of ridge height preservation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Changes of alveolar ridge height (in millimeters) during healing phase</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Alveolar Ridge Preservation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PRF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PRF+FDBA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>FDBA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Blood Clot</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FDBA</intervention_name>
    <description>Graft material used to graft extraction socket</description>
    <arm_group_label>PRF+FDBA</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>FDBA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PRF</intervention_name>
    <description>Autologous blood product used to graft extraction socket</description>
    <arm_group_label>PRF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>PRF+FDBA</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood Clot</intervention_name>
    <description>Surgical treatment of extraction socket without addition of graft material</description>
    <arm_group_label>Blood Clot</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Single rooted teeth requiring extraction

          2. Intact buccal and lingual plate within approximately 3-4 mm from gingival crest

          3. No clinical or radiographic signs of periapical pathology

          4. Acceptable oral hygiene

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Unable to comply with necessary scheduled visits

          2. Poor oral hygiene

          3. Failing/failed endodontic treatment with history/presence of sinus tracts

          4. Pregnant woman or patients who intend to become pregnant

          5. Tobacco use

          6. Immunosuppressed

          7. Type I or type II diabetes

          8. Patient with any blood disorder
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>February 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 1, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 3, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 6, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 3, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 3, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Francisco</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mark Ryder</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

