<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03048669</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R01HD087993</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01HD087993</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03048669</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Long Term Outcomes of Therapy in Women Initiated on Lifelong ART Because of Pregnancy in DR Congo</brief_title>
  <official_title>Continuous Quality Improvement Interventions to Improve Long Term Outcomes of Antiretroviral Therapy in Women Initiated on Therapy During Pregnancy or Breastfeeding in the Democratic Republic of Congo</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kinshasa School of Public Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ohio State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Despite the rapid adoption of the World Health Organization's 2013 guidelines, many children
      continue to be infected with HIV perinatally because of sub-optimal adherence to the
      continuum of HIV care in maternal and child health clinics (MCH). To achieve the UNAIDS goal
      eliminating mother-to-child HIV transmission, multiple, adaptive interventions will need to
      be implemented to improve adherence to the HIV continuum. The aim of this open label,
      parallel groups, randomized controlled trial is to evaluate the effectiveness of Continuous
      Quality Improvement (CQI) interventions implemented at facility and health district level to
      improve retention in care and virological suppression through 24 months postpartum among
      pregnant and breastfeeding women receiving ART in MCH clinics in Kinshasa, Democratic
      Republic of Congo. Prior to randomization, the current monitoring and evaluation system will
      be strengthen to enable collection of high quality individual patient-level data necessary
      for the timely production of indicators and monitoring of program outcomes to inform CQI
      interventions. Following randomization, in health districts randomized to CQI, quality
      improvement (QI) teams will be established at the district level and at MCH clinics level.
      For 18 months, QI teams will be brought together quarterly to identified key bottlenecks in
      the care delivery system using data from the monitoring system, develop an action plan to
      address those bottlenecks, and implement the action plan at the level of their district or
      clinics. If proven to be effective, CQI as designed here, could be scaled up rapidly in DRC
      and other resource-limited settings to accelerate progress towards the goal of an AIDS free
      generation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The US President's Emergency Plan for AIDS Relief (PEPFAR) goal of an AIDS-free generation,
      re-emphasized in PEPFAR 3.0, will not be achieved without substantial improvement in the
      adherence to the HIV care continuum among women in maternal and child health clinics (MCH) in
      resource-limited settings. In a recent meta-analysis of loss to follow-up (LTFU) across the
      prevention of mother-to-child transmission of HIV (PMTCT) cascade, about 50% of HIV+ pregnant
      women are already LTFU by delivery; within 3 months of delivery 33.9% of mother-infant pairs
      are also LTFU. Consequently, half of pediatric infections are currently estimated to occur in
      the postpartum period during breastfeeding and fewer than 40% of HEI are tested for HIV at
      2-3 months. Determinants of this poor performance occur at multiple levels: healthcare
      delivery systems, providers, and beneficiaries (HIV-infected mothers). Current evidence
      suggest that beyond individual-level factors, healthcare delivery system level factors are
      paramount. Quality Improvement (QI) Collaborative is one of the most popular methods for
      organizing sustained improvement efforts at hospitals and ambulatory practices worldwide. In
      the Breakthrough Series approach also refer to as continuous quality improvement (CQI),10 QI
      teams from multiple sites across a region or country are brought together to focus on a
      common problem. Over one or two years, experts in clinical and performance improvement
      provide the group with periodic instructions and encourage the teams to share lessons learned
      and best practices. However, its popularity, CQI effectiveness has never been demonstrated in
      a randomized trial or a well-designed comparative study. The aims of the proposed study are:
      1) to evaluate the effectiveness of CQI interventions in improving long-term retention in
      care and virological suppression in women who start lifelong ART in MCH clinics and 2) to
      identify modifiable health delivery system factors associated with retention in care and
      sustained virological suppression in women who start lifelong ART in MCH clinics. The study
      will be implemented in Kinshasa, Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC): an extremely
      resource-limited country that has struggled to emerge from decades of gross mismanagement,
      rampant corruption, and wars that have left its health infrastructures in shambles. We will
      conduct a cluster-randomized trial with health districts as the randomization unit. MCH
      clinics in the intervention group, will undergo CQI initiatives using participatory
      data-driven approaches and on-site monitoring and supervisory support. We will use surveys of
      health facilities, including selected staff, and service beneficiaries (HIV infected mothers)
      to collect data on key characteristics of the service delivery's organization and providers'
      and patients' perspective of the HIV care delivery performance. The main outcomes will be
      LTFU/retention in care, virological suppression and MTCT rates evaluated at 24 months
      postpartum.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The intervention will be implemented at the health facility level by the health facility staff under the supervision of health districts supervisors and investigators. As such, care providers nor investigations cannot be masked from the intervention. however, participant will not be told about the intervention or which study group they are in.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Loss-to-follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>delivery, six weeks, 12 and 24 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>the proportion of participants for whom the whereabouts is unknown at the evaluation time</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Virological suppression</measure>
    <time_frame>delivery, 12 and 24 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of participants with undetectable viral load</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timely Infant HIV diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>delivery, six weeks, 12 and 24 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of HIV-exposed infant with an appropriate HIV test result</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timely ART initiation</measure>
    <time_frame>two weeks from HIV diagnosis</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of HIV-infected participants (mother or infant) initiated on ART within two weeks of diagnosis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MTCT rates</measure>
    <time_frame>delivery, six weeks, 12 and 24 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of HIV-exposed infant who test positive for HIV</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>delivery, six weeks, 12 and 24 weeks postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of participating mothers and infants know to be alive</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">6000</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV/AIDS</condition>
  <condition>Antiretroviral Therapy</condition>
  <condition>Pregnancy Outcomes</condition>
  <condition>HIV-exposed Infants</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Continuous quality improvement (CQI)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Quality improvement initiatives implemented at facility level using participatory data-driven approaches and on-site monitoring and supervisory support</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>In health districts randomized to standard of care, the same strengthening of the data collection system for the monitoring of indicators as in the intervention group will be implemented. At least once a month, a study staff will visit each clinics irrespective of their randomization to extract information for the mother-infant register into an electronic database. No report on indicators will be produced for those clinic for the duration of the study. Staff from clinics and health district bureau in the standard of care group will not be associated with the quarterly review of the indicators. The study will not influence with any other HIV service provision activity in the standard of care group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Continuous quality improvement</intervention_name>
    <description>A quality improvement team at the health district and at the clinics levels. A clinic level QI team will include at least one staff each from antenatal care (ANC), delivery/maternity, and well-child services. The head of the each QI team plus a supervisor from the health district bureau and a study team member constitute the district QI team. Immediately following randomization, we will bring together QI teams to review program and quality indicators from their clinics and across districts to identify key bottlenecks in the care delivery system and agree on an action plan to modify them. QI teams will be responsible for the implementation of the action plan at the level of their respective clinics. Every three months, using data from the monitoring system, the process will be repeated for a duration 18 months. To limit possible contamination, all staff from a randomized district/clinic who may have a dual appointment in another facility will be excluded from QI teams.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Continuous quality improvement (CQI)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women receiving care in one of the participating maternal
             and child health clinics

          -  HIV-exposed infants born from participating mothers

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  refuse to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marcel Yotebieng, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ohio State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Emile W Okitolonda, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kinshasa School of Public Health</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marcel Yotebieng, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>614 688 2133</phone>
    <email>myotebieng@cph.osu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kinshasa School of Public Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kinshasa</city>
        <country>Congo, The Democratic Republic of the</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Emile W Okitolonda, MD, PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Bienvenu Kawende, MD</last_name>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Congo, The Democratic Republic of the</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 7, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 9, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ohio State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marcel Yotebieng</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The final dataset will include self-reported demographic and behavioral data from interviews with the subjects, clinical and laboratory data from the mother-infant pair, and blood specimens provided. Although the final dataset will be stripped of identifiers prior to release for sharing, we believe that there remains the possibility of deductive disclosure of subjects with unusual characteristics. Thus, we will make the data and associated documentation available to users only under a data-sharing agreement that provides for: (1) a commitment to using the data only for the proposed research purposes and not to identify any individual participant; (2) a commitment to securing the data using appropriate computer technology; and (3) a commitment to destroying or returning the data after analyses are completed and results publish.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

