<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03041766</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Sm14-2a-Sn</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03041766</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Safety and Immune Response of the Sm14 Vaccine in Adults of Endemic Regions</brief_title>
  <official_title>Safety and Immunogenicity Evaluation of the Vaccine Candidate Sm14 in Combination With the Adjuvant Glucopyranosyl Lipid A (GLA-SE) in Adults Living in Endemic Regions for S. Mansoni and S. Haematobium in Senegal. A Comparative, Randomized, Open-label Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oswaldo Cruz Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Orygen Biotecnologia SA</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Biomedical Research Center EPLS</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>IDRI</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oswaldo Cruz Foundation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The clinical trial phase 2a is designed to assess the safety of the active ingredient
      (protein + adjuvant) and secondarily its immunogenicity in healthy male adults from 18 to 49
      years of age with a history of infection with intestinal and urinary schistosomiasis, living
      in the Valley of the Senegal River, a highly endemic area for schistosomiasis. Two arms in
      the study will test different doses of GLA-SE adjuvant (2.5 and 5 μg). This phase IIA in
      adults is considered to be a preliminary step in safety before starting trials in children in
      endemic areas to S. mansoni or S. haematobium, target population of the vaccine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A phase 2a trial, self-contained, open-label, randomized, dose-escalation study in two
      parallel arms receiving three (3) injections at D0, D28, D56; both groups receiving 50 μg
      Sm14 vaccine candidate solution, either combined with 2.5µg GLA-SE for the first group and
      5µg for the second one in adults living in a S. mansoni and S. haematobium endemic area.

      Sm14: recombinant protein produced in yeast following Good Manufacturing Practices (GMP)
      conditions, presented in vials containing 0.55 ml solution Sm14, 0.4 ml solution is diluted
      with 0.4 ml of GLA (Synthetic Glucopyranosyl lipid A) for intramuscular administration.

      Medical examinations are performed at D0 (before injection, 1 hr and 4 hr after), and a
      safety evaluation at 24 hrs and 48 hrs, after each injection.

      Blood analysis: Liver function tests - renal function tests - blood counts, at W-1 before
      inclusion, and then 7 days after each injections and at W13 and W21 during the follow-up.

      Blood samples for immune response analysis at time of each injection, and then W12 and W20.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 6, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 6, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability.</measure>
    <time_frame>within 7 days of the administration of the first dose</time_frame>
    <description>. Local signs and symptoms included Pain, Swelling and Inflammation at the injection site, Heaviness or pain upon passive or active movement of the injected limb, Complete physical examination including an examination of general appearance, body weight and forehead temperature, head, eyes, ears, nose and throat, neck, skin, cardiovascular and respiratory system, abdominal system, nervous system, lymphatic area, blood pressure, pulse and respiratory rates. General signs and symptoms including fever, headache, nausea, vomiting, myalgia, arthralgia, irritability/fussiness and drowsiness, loss of appetite and sleep disturbances. Laboratory tests (blood count, liver and kidney biological functions).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>D30-D37: within 7 days of the administration of the second dose</time_frame>
    <description>. Local signs and symptoms included Pain, Swelling and Inflammation at the injection site, Heaviness or pain upon passive or active movement of the injected limb, Complete physical examination including an examination of general appearance, body weight and forehead temperature, head, eyes, ears, nose and throat, neck, skin, cardiovascular and respiratory system, abdominal system, nervous system, lymphatic area, blood pressure, pulse and respiratory rates. General signs and symptoms including fever, headache, nausea, vomiting, myalgia, arthralgia, irritability/fussiness and drowsiness, loss of appetite and sleep disturbances. Laboratory tests (blood count, liver and kidney biological functions).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>D60-67 : within 7 days of the administration of the third dose</time_frame>
    <description>Local signs and symptoms included Pain, Swelling and Inflammation at the injection site. Heaviness or pain upon passive or active movement of the injected limb, Complete physical examination including an examination of general appearance, body weight and forehead temperature, head, eyes, ears, nose and throat, neck, skin, cardiovascular and respiratory system, abdominal system, nervous system, lymphatic area, blood pressure, pulse and respiratory rates. General signs and symptoms including fever, headache, nausea, vomiting, myalgia, arthralgia, irritability/fussiness and drowsiness, loss of appetite and sleep disturbances. Laboratory tests (blood count, liver and kidney biological functions).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>D90 : three months after the first injection</time_frame>
    <description>injection Local signs and symptoms included pain or tenderness, swelling, induration and erythema at the site of injection. Complete physical examination including an examination of general appearance, body weight and forehead temperature, head, eyes, ears, nose and throat, neck, skin, cardiovascular and respiratory system, abdominal system, nervous system, lymphatic area, blood pressure, pulse and respiratory rates. General signs and symptoms including fever, headache, nausea, vomiting, myalgia, arthralgia, irritability/fussiness and drowsiness, loss of appetite and sleep disturbances. Laboratory tests (blood count, liver and kidney biological functions).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>D120 : four months after the first injection</time_frame>
    <description>Local signs and symptoms included pain or tenderness, swelling, induration and erythema at the site of injection. Complete physical examination including an examination of general appearance, body weight and forehead temperature, head, eyes, ears, nose and throat, neck, skin, cardiovascular and respiratory system, abdominal system, nervous system, lymphatic area, blood pressure, pulse and respiratory rates. General signs and symptoms including fever, headache, nausea, vomiting, myalgia, arthralgia, irritability/fussiness and drowsiness, loss of appetite and sleep disturbances. Laboratory tests (blood count, liver and kidney biological functions).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative and quantitative assessment of the Immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>Day of first administration</time_frame>
    <description>Immunogenicity was evaluated by Isotype analysis of the antibodies produced specifically against the rSm14 and vaccine-induced (ELISA) and Specific rSm14 cellular response (on PBMC), production of intracellular cytokines (PBMCs stimulation and cytokine dosing). Cellular immune responses measured by PBMC luminex assay for T-cell cytokines (Milliplex ® MAP kit).
Correlation between the development and magnitude of humoral responses measured by antibody IgG production to the Sm14 Schisto protein using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative and quantitative assessment of the Immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after the first administration</time_frame>
    <description>Immunogenicity was evaluated by Isotype analysis of the antibodies produced specifically against the rSm14 and vaccine-induced (ELISA) and Specific rSm14 cellular response (on PBMC), production of intracellular cytokines (PBMCs stimulation and cytokine dosing). Cellular immune responses measured by PBMC luminex assay for T-cell cytokines (Milliplex ® MAP kit).
Correlation between the development and magnitude of humoral responses measured by antibody IgG production to the Sm14 Schisto protein using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative and quantitative assessment of the Immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>60 days after the first administration</time_frame>
    <description>Immunogenicity was evaluated by Isotype analysis of the antibodies produced specifically against the rSm14 and vaccine-induced (ELISA) and Specific rSm14 cellular response (on PBMC), production of intracellular cytokines (PBMCs stimulation and cytokine dosing). Cellular immune responses measured by PBMC luminex assay for T-cell cytokines (Milliplex ® MAP kit).
Correlation between the development and magnitude of humoral responses measured by antibody IgG production to the Sm14 Schisto protein using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative and quantitative assessment of the Immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>90 days after the first administration</time_frame>
    <description>Immunogenicity was evaluated by Isotype analysis of the antibodies produced specifically against the rSm14 and vaccine-induced (ELISA) and Specific rSm14 cellular response (on PBMC), production of intracellular cytokines (PBMCs stimulation and cytokine dosing). Cellular immune responses measured by PBMC luminex assay for T-cell cytokines (Milliplex ® MAP kit).
Correlation between the development and magnitude of humoral responses measured by antibody IgG production to the Sm14 Schisto protein using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative and quantitative assessment of the Immunogenicity</measure>
    <time_frame>120 days after the first administration</time_frame>
    <description>Immunogenicity was evaluated by Isotype analysis of the antibodies produced specifically against the rSm14 and vaccine-induced (ELISA) and Specific rSm14 cellular response (on PBMC), production of intracellular cytokines (PBMCs stimulation and cytokine dosing). Cellular immune responses measured by PBMC luminex assay for T-cell cytokines (Milliplex ® MAP kit).
Correlation between the development and magnitude of humoral responses measured by antibody IgG production to the Sm14 Schisto protein using enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Schistosomiasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Adults with an infectious history of S. haematobium and S. mansoni and pretreated with 1 dose of Praziquantel (3 weeks prior to the first vaccine injection) receiving three (3) intramuscular injections of 50 μg Sm14 with 2.5 μg GLA-SE solution at D0, W4, W8 (D=day; W=week). Three-month follow-up (W12, W20).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Adults with an infectious history of S. haematobium and S. mansoni and pretreated with 1 dose of Praziquantel (3 weeks prior to the first vaccine injection) receiving three (3) intramuscular injections of 50 μg Sm14 with 5.0 μg GLA-SE solution at D0, W4, W8 (D=day; W=week). Three-month follow-up (W12, W20).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sm14</intervention_name>
    <description>Three 0.5 mL intra-muscular injections of the vaccine solution (50µg Sm14) will be administered on D0, W4, W8 (D = day, W = week).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>rSm14</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GLA-SE solution</intervention_name>
    <description>Two (2) adjuvant concentrations will be made and packaged at 0.4 mL/vial, per GMP standards. One lot at the concentration of 10µg/mL for injection in the first cohort at 2.5µg GLA-SE/injection and one lot at the concentration of 20µg/mL for the second cohort intended to receive 5.0µg of GLA-SE/injection</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Glucopyranosyl Lipid A in Stable Emulsion</other_name>
    <other_name>Glucopyranosyl Lipid Adjuvant-Stable Emulsion</other_name>
    <other_name>Toll-like Receptor 4 Agonist GLA-SE</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults, male, 18 to 49 years old (inclusive) at the time of inclusion.

          -  Living in one of selected villages in Saint-Louis Region (Senegal).

          -  Free of obvious/severe health problems except schistosomiasis, as established by
             clinical examination and blood analysis, i.e. hematological exams, liver and renal
             function tests.

          -  Written informed consent to participate obtained

          -  Treated with 40mg/kg Praziquantel (PZQ) before inclusion (W-5 to W-4 before the first
             injection) in case of infection with S. mansoni and S. haematobium

          -  Residence in the area during the period of the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult who does not respond to one of the inclusion criteria

          -  Current or previous chronic administration (defined as more than 14 days) of
             immunosuppressive drugs or other immuno-modifying drugs.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to any component in the Sm14 vaccine or history of allergic
             disease.

          -  Knowledge of non-infectious chronic disease

          -  Acute disease at time of enrollment.

          -  Other conditions which in opinion of the PI may potentially represent a danger for the
             patient to be enrolled.

          -  Non residence in the study area or intent to move during the study period
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Miriam Tendler, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Oswaldo Cruz Foundation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Doudou DIOP, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Biomedical Research Center ESPOIR POUR LA SANTE (BRC-EPLS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gilles RIVEAU, PharmD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Biomedical Research Center ESPOIR POUR LA SANTE (BRC-EPLS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Biomedical Research Center EPLS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <zip>BP226</zip>
        <country>Senegal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Senegal</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Moser D, Tendler M, Griffiths G, Klinkert MQ. A 14-kDa Schistosoma mansoni polypeptide is homologous to a gene family of fatty acid binding proteins. J Biol Chem. 1991 May 5;266(13):8447-54.</citation>
    <PMID>2022660</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ramos CR, Spisni A, Oyama S Jr, Sforça ML, Ramos HR, Vilar MM, Alves AC, Figueredo RC, Tendler M, Zanchin NI, Pertinhez TA, Ho PL. Stability improvement of the fatty acid binding protein Sm14 from S. mansoni by Cys replacement: structural and functional characterization of a vaccine candidate. Biochim Biophys Acta. 2009 Apr;1794(4):655-62. doi: 10.1016/j.bbapap.2008.12.010. Epub 2008 Dec 25.</citation>
    <PMID>19150418</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Coler RN, Bertholet S, Moutaftsi M, Guderian JA, Windish HP, Baldwin SL, Laughlin EM, Duthie MS, Fox CB, Carter D, Friede M, Vedvick TS, Reed SG. Development and characterization of synthetic glucopyranosyl lipid adjuvant system as a vaccine adjuvant. PLoS One. 2011 Jan 26;6(1):e16333. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0016333.</citation>
    <PMID>21298114</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Santini-Oliveira M, Coler RN, Parra J, Veloso V, Jayashankar L, Pinto PM, Ciol MA, Bergquist R, Reed SG, Tendler M. Schistosomiasis vaccine candidate Sm14/GLA-SE: Phase 1 safety and immunogenicity clinical trial in healthy, male adults. Vaccine. 2016 Jan 20;34(4):586-594. doi: 10.1016/j.vaccine.2015.10.027. Epub 2015 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26571311</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lambert SL, Yang CF, Liu Z, Sweetwood R, Zhao J, Cheng L, Jin H, Woo J. Molecular and cellular response profiles induced by the TLR4 agonist-based adjuvant Glucopyranosyl Lipid A. PLoS One. 2012;7(12):e51618. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0051618. Epub 2012 Dec 28.</citation>
    <PMID>23284726</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 16, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 31, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 3, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 12, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 12, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oswaldo Cruz Foundation</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>MIRIAM TENDLER</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Schistosomiasis</keyword>
  <keyword>Recombinant vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>rSm14</keyword>
  <keyword>GLA-SE</keyword>
  <keyword>Fatty acid-binding protein (FABP)</keyword>
  <keyword>Phase II Clinical Trial</keyword>
  <keyword>Senegal</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schistosomiasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pharmaceutical Solutions</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

