<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03046810</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SC-01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03046810</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment of Incontinence Associated Dermatitis - Automated</brief_title>
  <acronym>TRIAD-A</acronym>
  <official_title>Treatment of Incontinence Associated Dermatitis - Automated</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>SchwabCare</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>SchwabCare</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Incontinence and the skin irritation (dermatitis) associated with it are common problems.
      Treatment of dermatitis is effective, but requires effective cleaning and application of a
      barrier substance to prevent further contact between urine or feces and the skin. Water based
      cleansing with the addition of a pH balanced cleanser is more effective than standard
      abrasive cleansing with paper or a cloth, and is better tolerated by those with skin
      irritation. Zinc oxide based barriers effectively promote healing and prevent further skin
      damage. Spray forms are less cumbersome and generally preferred, but are difficult to for the
      patient to apply independently given the challenge of accessing the perineum.

      40 patients, recruited from 3 specialty pelvic floor centers and 1 assisted living center
      will be provided a device that cleans, dries, and applies zinc oxide barrier spray with each
      use of the toilet. Dermatitis will be evaluated at the beginning of the study, and at weeks
      1, 2 and 6 by medical staff using a standard scale (The Kennedy Scale).Quality of life will
      be measured using a visual analog scale derived from the quality of life in incontinence
      scale.

      The investigators hypothesize that the device will 1) effectively treat incontinence
      associated dermatitis, 2) prevent recurrence, and 3) be preferred over standard treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Incontinence and incontinence associated dermatitis (IAD) are common problems. A recent CDC
      study noted that up to 50% of noninstitutionalized patients aged 65 and older experienced
      episodes of incontinence at least monthly, and that 40% of those with incontinence develop
      secondary IAD The treatment of IAD is focused on effective cleaning and prevention of further
      exposure to irritant liquids and solids through barrier creams. Enzymatic washes have proven
      efficacy over soap and water, and zinc oxide is the standard of care for barrier function.
      Combined, effective cleansing and barrier use treats IAD in as little as 6 days, and
      effectively prevents recurrent skin damage. In one study, an effective preventive regimen of
      regularly applied skin therapy reduced the incidence of IAD in an at risk population from 25%
      to 5%. The combination of enzymatic skin cleanser and barrier protection is the standard of
      care for maintenance of skin integrity in patients with chronic urinary and fecal
      incontinence.

      Adherence to prescribed regimens is a major barrier to regular use of substances applied to
      the perineum. Difficulty in accessing the perineum make adherence challenging to those with
      both full and limited mobility, often requiring assistance from a caregiver. The associated
      loss of independence and dignity are major detriments to quality of life. Novel formulations
      of zinc oxide, using aerosol based spray application, facilitate use and improve patient
      acceptance. In a 2014 nursing home based industry study, spray based zinc oxide was preferred
      by 80% of patients and caregivers, and improved treatment and prevention of IAD in 70% of the
      study participants.

      Adequate cleansing and drying prior to the application of barrier products is key to
      effective prevention of skin breakdown. Water-based cleaning of the perineum after toileting
      has been demonstrated to improve hygiene over standard mechanical, paper-based cleansing,
      especially in those with limited mobility or incontinence. Evidence further demonstrates that
      the addition of pH balanced cleansers, applied without mechanical abrasion from cloths or
      wipes, advances hygiene and minimizes risk of secondary infection.

      Study Aims

      The aims of this study are to evaluate the efficacy of an automated delivery system for
      cleansing the perineum, and applying zinc oxide barrier spray to effectively treat and
      prevent incontinence associated dermatitis in a population with active or recurrent IAD.
      Secondary aims will be to assess preference for the automated delivery system over standard
      wash and manually applied barrier sprays.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment of dermatitis</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement in the Kennedy Score for Dermatitis</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevention of recurrent dermatitis</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>prevention of recurrent dermatitis by clinical criteria</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement in quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by visual analog scale derived from quality of life in incontinence scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Incontinence, Urinary</condition>
  <condition>Dermatitis</condition>
  <condition>Incontinence, Fecal</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wellness toileting system</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will use the wellness toileting system for their perineal hygiene and treatment of dermatitis</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Wellness toileting system</intervention_name>
    <description>This group will use the wash, dry, cleanse, and apply zinc oxide barrier spray routinely for all toileting.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Wellness toileting system</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SchwabCare Wellness Toileting System</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ability to give informed consent.

          -  Active functional urinary or fecal incontinence

          -  Kennedy Scale Grade &gt;2 with active incontinence associated dermatitis

          -  Willingness to have device installed in home/care center

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Active perineal infection

          -  Prior pelvic radiation

          -  Perineal surgery within the prior 6 months

          -  Known allergy or sensitivity to applied agents

          -  Treatment for dermatitis within the prior 2 weeks.

          -  Pre-existing pressure ulcer stage 2-4

          -  Weight exceeding 300 pounds

          -  Known allergy or hypersensitivity to cleanser or zinc oxide barrier spray

          -  Home bathroom needs excessive upgrades, or needs ownership authorization
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard S Tilson, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Director of Clinical Investigation</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jacqueline Silvia</last_name>
    <phone>+1 (855) 239-2106</phone>
    <email>jsilvia@schwabcare.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Richard S Tilson, MD MPH</last_name>
    <phone>(978) 459-6737</phone>
    <email>mtilson2@lowellgi.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Skyline Urology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Torrance</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90505</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jacqueline Silvia</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 6, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 7, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 8, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dermatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Incontinence</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Enuresis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fecal Incontinence</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No plan to share individual participant data at this time</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

