<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01744717</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ESCID-02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01744717</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Validation of &quot;Escala de Conductas Indicadoras de Dolor&quot; ESCID Scale for Measuring Pain in Critically Ill Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>ESCID-MQ</acronym>
  <official_title>&quot;Estudio multicéntrico de Validez y Fiabilidad de la Escala de Conductas Indicadoras de Dolor ESCID Para Medir el Dolor en Pacientes críticos, no Comunicativos y Sometidos a ventilación mecánica&quot;</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Puerta de Hierro University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundación de Investigación Biomédica - Hospital Universitario de La Princesa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Universitario Getafe</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Universitario 12 de Octubre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Universitario Ramon y Cajal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital San Carlos, Madrid</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital De la Santa Creu y Sant Pau</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Quirón Madrid University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital de Cruces</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital de Basurto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Galdakao-Usansolo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Universitario Fundación Alcorcón</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Universitario de Fuenlabrada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Puerta de Hierro University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pain is an unpleasant and important stress factor, and a potentially harmful experience for
      critically ill patients. Pain is harder to evaluate in non-communicative patients, who can´t
      report their own pain. Behavioral indicators have been proved as useful and reliable for
      detecting and measuring pain in these patients, and have been the basis for constructing
      scales for measuring pain, such as the Behavioural Pain Scale (BPS), the Critical Care
      Observation Tool (CPOT) and the Scale of Behaviors Indicating Pain (ESCID) .

      The BPS and ESCID were tested in a study with a sample of 42 critically ill patients in
      Spain, showing good validity and reliability.

      The objective of this Spanish multicentre study is to test the validity and reliability of
      the ESCID scale in a large sample of critically ill patients with medical and postsurgical
      pathology for the detection and measurement of pain.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The specific Aims for the study are :

      To determine the validity and reliability of the ESCID scale to assess pain in
      non-communicative critically ill patients on mechanical ventilation, in a large sample of
      critically ill medical and surgical patients.

      To assess the relationship between the application of a common and painful procedure, usual
      in daily practice, and its associated changes in physiological indicators of pain: variation
      of heart rate, blood pressure, respiratory rate, sweating.

      To assess the degree of pain when applying two painful procedures documented as common in the
      usual care of critically ill patients, and one non-painful procedure, using two pain scales:
      ESCID and BPS.

      To assess the differences in the employment of the pain scales in patients with medical and
      surgical pathology.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain intensity</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Pain intensity will be measured through the use of 2 scales based on behaviour items, the Behavioural Pain Scale (BPS) and the ''Scale of Behavioral Indicators of Pain'' (ESCID-Escala de Conductas Indicadoras de Dolor), by two independent observers with blind result among them, when the application of two procedures registered as painful (PD) and common in clinical practice, mobilization and tracheal suctioning, and one non-painful procedure (PND). The measurement will be performed once per each patient and procedure. The measurement of pain will be carried out in 3 stages: 5 minutes before the PD/PND, during PD/PND and 15 minutes after PD/PND.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">286</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Critically ill uncommunicative patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Critically ill non-communicative patients, on mechanical ventilation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pain measurement</intervention_name>
    <description>Pain intensity will be measured using 2 scales based on behaviour items, the Behavioural Pain Scale (BPS) and the ESCID scale (Escala de Conductas Indicadoras de Dolor), by two independent observers , when applying two procedures registered as painful (PD) and common in clinical practice, and a non-painful procedure (PND). The measurement will be performed once per each patient and procedure.
The procedures to be studied are the following:
TURNING / POSITIONING (moving side to side or up or down in bed)
ENDOTRACHEAL SUCTIONING (insertion of suction catheter into the endotracheal tube or tracheostomy in order to aspirate secretions)
NON PAINFUL PROCEDURE (Soft friction with gauze cloth on a healthy skin tissue portion, in the outer arm, forearm or anterior tibial area)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Critically ill uncommunicative patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        ICU patients who are uncommunictive, receiving mechanical ventilation and undergoing any of
        the study procedures. Consent to participate will be requested to the family of the
        patient. Adults age 18 and over will be eligible for the study if they meet study inclusion
        criteria and don't meet any exclusion criteria.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient must be 18 years of age or older

          -  Patient's primary language spanish where the evaluation is performed

          -  Patient meets IRB/Central EC requirements of the institution/ country where the
             evaluation is performed

          -  Patient is receiving the study's procedures as part of standard care, excepting the
             non painful procedure

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient's condition is very unstable at the time of measurement of pain

          -  Patient is receiving neuromuscular blocking medications at the time of measurement of
             pain

          -  Patient´s probable or diagnosed delirium
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ignacio Latorre, RN</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Puerta de Hierro Majadahonda University Hospital. Medical ICU. Spain.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Puerta de Hierro Majadahonda University Hospital. Intensive Care Unit.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Majadahonda, Madrid</city>
        <state>Madrid</state>
        <zip>28222</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Latorre-Marco I, Solís-Muñoz M, Acevedo-Nuevo M, Hernández-Sánchez ML, López-López C, Sánchez-Sánchez Mdel M, Wojtysiak-Wojcicka M, De las Pozas-Abril J. Validation of the Behavioural Indicators of Pain Scale ESCID for pain assessment in non-communicative and mechanically ventilated critically ill patients: a research protocol. J Adv Nurs. 2016 Jan;72(1):205-16. doi: 10.1111/jan.12808. Epub 2015 Sep 11.</citation>
    <PMID>26358885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Latorre-Marco I, Acevedo-Nuevo M, Solís-Muñoz M, Hernández-Sánchez L, López-López C, Sánchez-Sánchez MM, Wojtysiak-Wojcicka M, de Las Pozas-Abril J, Robleda-Font G, Frade-Mera MJ, De Blas-García R, Górgolas-Ortiz C, De la Figuera-Bayón J, Cavia-García C. Psychometric validation of the behavioral indicators of pain scale for the assessment of pain in mechanically ventilated and unable to self-report critical care patients. Med Intensiva. 2016 Nov;40(8):463-473. doi: 10.1016/j.medin.2016.06.004. Epub 2016 Aug 31. English, Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>27590592</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 14, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 5, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 7, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 16, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 16, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 19, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Puerta de Hierro University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ignacio Latorre Marco</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Nurse Degree, Intensive Care Unit nurse staff</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>mechanical ventilation</keyword>
  <keyword>uncommunicative</keyword>
  <keyword>Adult ICU patients pain</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

