<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01742767</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2011-001963-37</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01742767</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cisplatinum/Pemetrexed Versus Split-dose Cisplatinum/Pemetrexed In NSCLC</brief_title>
  <acronym>PemSplitCisp</acronym>
  <official_title>Randomized Phase II Trial of Three-weekly Cisplatinum and Pemetrexed Versus Split-dose d1 and d8 Cisplatinum and Pemetrexed In Advanced and Inoperable Non-squamous Non-small-cell Lung Cancer (NSCLC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universität Duisburg-Essen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eli Lilly and Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universität Duisburg-Essen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Cisplatinum and pemetrexed (ALIMTA®) has become an effective first-line regimen for advanced
      and inoperable non-squamous NSCLC without somatic activating mutations of epidermal growth
      factor receptor (EGFR). In the standard regimen the cisplatinum dose is 75 mg/m2 on day 1 of
      a 21-day cycle. Due to the high platinum-dose patients do need a strict hyperhydration and
      often have to be hospitalized for survey. Split-dose cisplatinum with two administrations on
      Day 1 and 8 of a 21-day-cycle has already been administered in other platin-containing
      chemotherapy regimens (cis/gem cis/nav cis/paclitaxel cis/docetaxel) with favourable toxicity
      profiles and generally with an excellent patient compliance.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is a current need to develop a split-dose cisplatinum regimen in combination with
      pemetrexed with high efficacy, excellent treatment compliance, administration convenience and
      the possibility to open up easier outpatient administration of the chemotherapy protocol.
      Dosing of cisplatinum at 40 mg/m2 d 1 and day 8 seems to be very effective and useful for
      this strategy. The current trial will address this issue within a prospective randomized
      phase-II trial. Treatment will be given on day 1 and 8 in the split-dose arm. A comparator
      arm of the current three-weekly higher cisplatinum schedule will be added to this study. For
      evaluation of this strategy observation of the toxicity/efficacy ratio within this trial will
      be of major importance. Efficacy will be analyzed by objective response rate, symptom control
      and life-quality. Toxicity will be looked at with treatment toxicity, treatment compliance
      and adherence to protocol.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <condition>NSCLC</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cis (D1) + Pem (D1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cisplatinum 75 mg/m2 d 1 Pemetrexed 500 mg/m2 d 1 q d 21</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CIS (D1+8) + Pem (D!)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Cisplatinum 40 mg/m2 d 1 + d 8 Pemetrexed 500 mg/m2 d 1 q d 21</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cisplatinum</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cis (D1) + Pem (D1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CIS (D1+8) + Pem (D!)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pemetrexed</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Cis (D1) + Pem (D1)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CIS (D1+8) + Pem (D!)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients are eligible to be included in the study only if they meet all of the
             following criteria:

               1. Histologically or cytologically confirmed diagnosis of non-squamous-cell
                  non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) Stage IV (American Joint Committee on Cancer
                  Staging Criteria [AJCC], Version 7, 2009)

               2. No prior systemic chemotherapy for lung cancer

               3. At least one unidimensionally measurable lesion meeting Response Evaluation
                  Criteria in Solid Tumours (RECIST; version 1.1, Eisenhauer et al. 2009), longest
                  diameter ≥10 mm with computed tomography (CT) scan [CT scan slice thickness no
                  greater than 5 mm] , or ≥ 20 mm with chest x-ray. Positron emission tomography
                  (PET) scans and ultrasounds should not be used.

               4. ECOG performance status of 0 or 1 (Oken et al. 1982)

               5. ≥ 18 years of age &lt; 75 years

               6. Adequate organ function,

               7. Prior radiation therapy allowed to &lt;25% of the bone marrow (Cristy and Eckerman
                  1987). Prior radiation to the whole pelvis is not allowed. Prior radiotherapy
                  must be completed at least 4 weeks before study enrollment. Patients must have
                  recovered from the acute toxic effects of the treatment prior to study
                  enrollment.

               8. Patient must understand and sign an informed consent document before the start of
                  specific protocol procedures.

               9. A pretreatment FFPE tumour biopsy must be available for central biomarker
                  analysis. If consented by the patient and clinically feasible, a fresh
                  pretreatment biopsy is obtained and submitted for central biomarker analysis.

              10. Female patients with childbearing potential must use highly effective methods of
                  contraception (combined oral contraceptives, hormon-releasing intrauterine
                  contraceptive device, hormonal contraceptive implants, hormonal contraceptive
                  injectables) or have sexual intercourse with a vasectomised partner only during
                  and for 6 months after the study and their pregnancy test must be negative within
                  7 days prior to study enrollment.

                  A female subject is considered to be of childbearing potential unless she is age
                  ≥ 50 years and naturally amenorrhoeic for ≥ 2 year or unless she is surgically
                  sterile.

                  Male patients must agree to use condoms during the study and for 6 months after
                  the study if their partner is of childbearing potential and does not use highly
                  effective method of contraception.

              11. Estimated life expectancy of 12 weeks

              12. Patient compliance and geographic proximity that allow adequate follow up.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients will be excluded from the study if they meet any of the following criteria:

               1. Active participation in other clinical studies or treatment with any experimental
                  drug within 30 days prior to study enrollment or during study participation.

               2. Patients with known somatic activating mutations of EGFR, as these patients
                  should be offered EGFR- tyrosine kinase inhibitor (EGFR-TKI) treatment as
                  first-line therapy. Detection of EGFR mutations and additional somatic mutations
                  with relation to treatment will be performed centrally at the
                  Universitätsklinikum Essen. In case immediate treatment initiation is required
                  for medical reasons (such as superior vena cava syndrome, severely symptomatic
                  disease) patients may be enrolled before results from EGFR testing are available.
                  As EGFR-TKI treatment is equally effective in second-line therapy, such patients
                  may remain on study treatment if a clinical benefit is derived.

               3. Peripheral neuropathy of ³CTCAE Grade 1

               4. Inability to comply with protocol or study procedures

               5. A serious concomitant systemic disorder that, in the opinion of the investigator,
                  would compromise the patient's ability to complete the study.

               6. A serious cardiac condition, such as myocardial infarction within 6 months prior
                  to study enrollment, symptomatic coronary artery disease, cardiac arrhythmia, or
                  other heart disease, as defined by the New York Heart Association Class III or IV
                  (functional capacity)

               7. Second primary malignancy that is clinically detectable at the time of
                  consideration for study enrollment

               8. Documented brain metastases unless the patient has completed successful local
                  therapy for central nervous system metastases and has been off of corticosteroids
                  for at least 4 weeks before enrollment. Brain imaging is required in symptomatic
                  patients to rule out brain metastases,but is not required in asymptomatic
                  patients

               9. The effect of third space fluid, such as pleural effusion and ascites, on
                  pemetrexed is unknown. In patients with clinically significant third space fluid,
                  consideration should be given to draining the effusion prior to pemetrexed
                  administration.

              10. Significant weight loss (that is 10%) over the previous 6 weeks before study
                  entry

              11. Significant hearing function impairment, especially high-frequency hearing
                  function impairment

              12. Any active or uncontrolled infection

              13. Concurrent administration of any other antitumour therapy

              14. Inability to interrupt aspirin or other nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents,
                  other than an aspirin dose &lt;1.3 grams per day, for a 5-day period (8-day period
                  for long-acting agents, such as piroxicam)

              15. Inability or unwillingness to take folic acid or vitamin B12 supplementation

              16. Inability to take corticosteroids

              17. Hypersensitivity to cisplatinum or to any other platinum compound

              18. Hypersensitivity to pemetrexed or to any of the excipients of ALIMTA®

              19. Pregnant or breast-feeding patient

              20. Yellow fever vaccination within the 30 days previous to study entry.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wilfried Eberhardt, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Universital hospital essen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wilfried Eberhardt, MD</last_name>
    <phone>00492017232011</phone>
    <email>wilfried.eberhardt@uk-essen.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mathias Hoiczyk</last_name>
    <phone>00492017232011</phone>
    <email>mathias.hoiczyk@uk-essen.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University hospital essen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Essen</city>
        <state>Northrhine westphalia</state>
        <zip>45122</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Diana Cortes-Incio</last_name>
      <phone>02017232011</phone>
      <email>diana.cortez-incio@uk-essen.de</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 3, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 4, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 5, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 4, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 4, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 5, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universität Duisburg-Essen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mathias Hoiczyk</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>NSCLC; split dose Cisplatinum; Pemetrexed</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pemetrexed</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

