<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01741441</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LTF-2002-TO</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01741441</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Laparoscopic Total Fundoplication for Duodenogastroesophageal Reflux</brief_title>
  <official_title>Study of Prognostic Factors for Long Term Results of Total Laparoscopic Fundoplication for Weakly Acidic or Mixed Reflux</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Turin, Italy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Turin, Italy</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      After laparoscopic total fundoplication (LTF) 12-15% of patients have persistent reflux
      symptoms and 20-25% develop gas-related symptoms. Reflux symptoms, gas bloating and inability
      to belch occurring after surgery have been associated with mixed (acid and weakly acid) (MR)
      or weakly acidic reflux (WAR). To date, few studies have evaluated functional outcome after
      LTF in patients with MR or WAR, with the majority reporting only short-term results.

      It has been shown that delayed gastric emptying (DGE) might also be an important factor for
      abdominal distension and adverse outcome after LTF.9,10 However, the correlation between poor
      long-term outcome after LTF and DGE is controversial. In addition, the effect of DGE in
      patients with MR or WAR is poorly investigated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the last years the study of gastro-oesophageal reflux has been revolutionized by the
      development of combined 24-h esophageal pH and multichannel intraluminal impedance (MII)
      monitoring.

      Combined esophageal MII and pH-monitoring allow for the timed correlation of esophageal pH
      changes with reflux events and achieve high sensitivity for the detection of acid (pH &lt;4),
      weakly acidic (pH 4-7) and weakly alkaline (pH &gt;7) reflux episodes. Use of this technology is
      bringing into focus the potential role of weakly acidic and weakly alkaline reflux in
      symptoms that persist despite acid suppressive therapy or anti-reflux surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>number of acidic and weakly acidic reflux</measure>
    <time_frame>60 months after LTF</time_frame>
    <description>number of acidic and weakly acidic reflux at 24 hour pH impedance monitoring</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GERD Health related quality of Life score</measure>
    <time_frame>60 months after LTF</time_frame>
    <description>Standard and previous validate questionnaire was employed in the study to assess gastroesophageal function and quality of life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gastro-esophageal junction pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>60 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Gastroesophageal junction pressure was evaluated with esophageal manometry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gastric emptying</measure>
    <time_frame>1 months before surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Gastric emptying was evaluated with gastric scintigraphy before LTF</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">188</enrollment>
  <condition>Duodenogastric Reflux</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>WAR and MR patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Consecutive patients with MR and WAR selected for laparoscopic total fundoplication (LTF) were included in a prospective clinical study. Gastroesophageal function was assessed by clinical validated questionnaires, upper endoscopy, esophageal manometry and 24-h impedance pH monitoring before and 12 and 60 months after LTF. Gastric scintigraphy was preoperatively performed in all patients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laparoscopic total fundoplication</intervention_name>
    <description>LTF was performed using a standard five-trocar technique in all cases and carried out by two expert surgeons who had previously performed more than 50 laparoscopic fundoplications. A floppy 360° total fundoplication of 2-2,5 cm was constructed after full esophageal mobilization and posterior crural repair with nonabsorbable sutures.</description>
    <arm_group_label>WAR and MR patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Laparoscopic Nissen fundoplication</other_name>
    <other_name>Laparoscopic 360° degree fundoplication</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Between June 2002 and June 2007 188 patients with MR and WAR underwent LTF; 172 (91.5%)
        completed the 5-year protocol. Among them, forty-two (24.4%) had preoperative moderately
        delayed GE (DGE).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - The study population consisted of consecutive patients with weakly acidic
        gastroesophageal reflux (GER) confirmed by 24 hour pH and impedance monitoring and eligible
        for laparoscopic antireflux surgery (LARS).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - Exclusion criteria were presence of severe gastric emptying, functional heartburn, giant
        hiatal hernia, underlying primary esophageal motility disorder, American Association of
        Anaesthetists (ASA) score IV, previous upper abdominal surgery, and contraindications to
        pneumoperitoneum.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>14 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fabrizio Rebecchi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Turin, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mario Morino, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Turin, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marco Ettore Allaix, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Turin, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Claudio Giaccone, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Turin, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Digestive, Colorectal, Oncologic and Minimally Invasive Surgery, Department of Surgical Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Turin</city>
        <zip>10126</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Broeders JA, Mauritz FA, Ahmed Ali U, Draaisma WA, Ruurda JP, Gooszen HG, Smout AJ, Broeders IA, Hazebroek EJ. Systematic review and meta-analysis of laparoscopic Nissen (posterior total) versus Toupet (posterior partial) fundoplication for gastro-oesophageal reflux disease. Br J Surg. 2010 Sep;97(9):1318-30. doi: 10.1002/bjs.7174. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20641062</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Broeders JA, Bredenoord AJ, Hazebroek EJ, Broeders IA, Gooszen HG, Smout AJ. Reflux and belching after 270 degree versus 360 degree laparoscopic posterior fundoplication. Ann Surg. 2012 Jan;255(1):59-65. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e31823899f8.</citation>
    <PMID>22167002</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Broeders JA, Bredenoord AJ, Hazebroek EJ, Broeders IA, Gooszen HG, Smout AJ. Effects of anti-reflux surgery on weakly acidic reflux and belching. Gut. 2011 Apr;60(4):435-41. doi: 10.1136/gut.2010.224824. Epub 2010 Dec 30.</citation>
    <PMID>21193452</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Namasivayam V, Arora AS, Murray JA. Weakly acidic reflux. Dis Esophagus. 2011 Jan;24(1):56-62. doi: 10.1111/j.1442-2050.2010.01100.x. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20659138</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frazzoni M, Conigliaro R, Melotti G. Reflux parameters as modified by laparoscopic fundoplication in 40 patients with heartburn/regurgitation persisting despite PPI therapy: a study using impedance-pH monitoring. Dig Dis Sci. 2011 Apr;56(4):1099-106. doi: 10.1007/s10620-010-1381-4. Epub 2010 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>20737211</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Frazzoni M, Conigliaro R, Melotti G. Weakly acidic refluxes have a major role in the pathogenesis of proton pump inhibitor-resistant reflux oesophagitis. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2011 Mar;33(5):601-6. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2036.2010.04550.x. Epub 2010 Dec 29.</citation>
    <PMID>21198705</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Castell DO, Murray JA, Tutuian R, Orlando RC, Arnold R. Review article: the pathophysiology of gastro-oesophageal reflux disease - oesophageal manifestations. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2004 Dec;20 Suppl 9:14-25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15527461</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boeckxstaens GE. Review article: the pathophysiology of gastro-oesophageal reflux disease. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2007 Jul 15;26(2):149-60. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17593062</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nakos A, Kouklakis G, Pitiakoudis M, Zezos P, Efraimidou E, Giatromanolaki A, Polychronidis A, Liratzopoulos N, Sivridis E, Simopoulos K. The histological and immunohistochemical aspects of bile reflux in patients with gastroesophageal reflux disease. Gastroenterol Res Pract. 2011;2011:905872. doi: 10.1155/2011/905872. Epub 2011 Jul 24.</citation>
    <PMID>21822428</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rebecchi F, Giaccone C, Farinella E, Campaci R, Morino M. Randomized controlled trial of laparoscopic Heller myotomy plus Dor fundoplication versus Nissen fundoplication for achalasia: long-term results. Ann Surg. 2008 Dec;248(6):1023-30. doi: 10.1097/SLA.0b013e318190a776.</citation>
    <PMID>19092347</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morino M, Giaccone C, Pellegrino L, Rebecchi F. Laparoscopic management of giant hiatal hernia: factors influencing long-term outcome. Surg Endosc. 2006 Jul;20(7):1011-6. Epub 2006 Jun 8.</citation>
    <PMID>16763927</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 25, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 30, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 5, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 30, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 30, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 5, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Turin, Italy</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Fabrizio Rebecchi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Duodenogastroesophageal reflux</keyword>
  <keyword>Weakly acidic reflux</keyword>
  <keyword>Gastric emptying</keyword>
  <keyword>Laparoscopic fundoplication</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gastroesophageal Reflux</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Duodenogastric Reflux</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

