<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01742065</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UH3CA188640</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1UH2AT007782-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01742065</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Strategies and Opportunities to Stop Colon Cancer in Priority Populations</brief_title>
  <acronym>STOPCRC</acronym>
  <official_title>Strategies and Opportunities to Stop Colon Cancer in Priority Populations</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kaiser Permanente</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kaiser Permanente</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Only an estimated 50 million US adults aged 50-75 are up-to-date on colorectal cancer (CRC)
      screening according to guidelines set by the federal government. CRC is 90% curable with
      timely detection and appropriate treatment of precancerous polyps; increased screening could
      reduce incidence by up to 50%. Groups least likely to undergo screening, those with minimal
      education, low income, low access to health care, recent immigrants or Hispanics, are the
      same people who frequently receive care at Federally Qualified Healthcare Center's (FQHCs).
      The use of fecal occult blood tests (FOBT) and fecal immunochemical tests (FIT) is
      exceedingly low in FQHCs (7-9% of patients in the past year) and far below national averages
      and target rates. Our results will provide valuable information on how to use electronic
      health record (EHR) resources to optimize guideline-based screening in FQHC clinics whose
      patient populations have disproportionately low CRC screening rates.

      This project, in conjunction with the research team, will use an advisory panel to direct the
      research activities. The advisory panel will be made up of clinicians, leaders, researchers,
      and patients. The panel and team will guide the development of materials, the outreach to
      patients, and the research protocol to best reach FQHC patients who are due for colorectal
      cancer screening.

      This project will be conducted in two phases, Phase I is conducting a pilot at two FQHC's,
      and Phase II is rolling out the intervention to between 20-30 clinics.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Phase I (Pilot Aims)

        -  Aim 1 Conduct preliminary analyses of EHR data at two pilot clinics.

        -  Aim 2: Use codes and methods developed in Aim 1 to test the feasibility, reach,
           effectiveness, and cost of an EHR-based CRC screening intervention using a subset of 100
           patients at each of two pilot clinics. We will use codes defined in Aim 1 to create a
           Solutions-based, Epic-integrated system to track CRC screening, mail FIT kits, and track
           patient test results and receipt of follow-up care. The system will be pilot-tested in
           two clinics.

        -  Aim 3: Use results from the pilot intervention to prepare for a large-scale,
           cluster-randomized pragmatic trial across 18 OCHIN clinics (see Phase II).

      Transition from Phase I to Phase II

      -Changes to our original proposal include going from a three arm to a two-arm pragmatic
      cluster trial with revised evaluation and power calculation and refinements to the
      intervention components for both usual care (now described as enhanced usual care) and the
      intervention (now described as enhanced auto).

      Phase II (Full trial Aims)

        -  Primary Aim 1. Assess the effectiveness of a large-scale, two-arm CRC screening program
           among diverse CLINIC patients, and assess difference in CRC screening outcomes (overall
           and by age, sex, insurance status, Hispanic ethnicity/race). The intervention will
           consist of an automated data-driven, EHR-linked program for mailing FIT kits (with
           linguistically appropriate pictographic instructions and return postage) to patients due
           for CRC screening.

        -  Primary Aim 2. Assess the costs and long-term cost-effectiveness of the automated
           program.

      We have also included two secondary aims:

        -  Secondary Aim 1. Assess adoption, implementation, reach and potential maintenance and
           spread of the program, using a mixed-method rapid assessment process, field notes, and
           other ethnographic data.

        -  Secondary Aim 2. Adapt and pilot-test the adaptation of STOP CRC in an alternate EHR
           platform, Allscripts, and develop an implementation guide to assist sites in adopting
           the program.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increased Screening Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 4 years (study period)</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators will determine if the auto and auto-plus interventions increase the rates of screening compared to usual care at FQHC clinics.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">62155</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Clinics in usual care will go about clinic practices to complete recommended screening for colorectal cancer.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Auto Plus</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Clinics randomized to the Auto-Plus arm will engage in all activities (send an introductory letter to participants, then a FIT Kit, then a reminder letter encouraging the return of the FIT Kit) in addition to a PDSA (Plan Do Study Act) cycle to refine or improve their process.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Auto Plus</intervention_name>
    <description>Clinics randomized to the Auto-Plus arm will engage in all activities in the Auto arm (send an introductory letter to participants, then a FIT Kit, then a reminder letter encouraging the return of the FIT Kit) in addition to one other outreach effort.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Auto Plus</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients aged 50-74 with no evidence of a colonoscopy within 9 years or fecal testing
             within 11 months, and no history of colorectal disease will be eligible to receive a
             mailed FIT.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  End Stage Renal Disease (ESRD)

          -  Hospice/Nursing Home
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>74 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gloria Coronado, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Center for Health Research, Kaiser Permanente Northwest</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Beverly Green, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kaiser Permanente</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Open Door Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Arcata</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95521</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mosaic Medical</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bend</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97701</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Benton and Linn County Health Centers</name>
      <address>
        <city>Corvallis</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97330</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Garcia Memorial Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hillsboro</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97124</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>La Clinica Health Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Medford</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97501</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Community Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Medford</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97504</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Multnomah County Health Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97214</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oregon Health and Science University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scappoose</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97056</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coronado GD, Sanchez J, Petrik A, Kapka T, DeVoe J, Green B. Advantages of wordless instructions on how to complete a fecal immunochemical test: lessons from patient advisory council members of a federally qualified health center. J Cancer Educ. 2014 Mar;29(1):86-90. doi: 10.1007/s13187-013-0551-4.</citation>
    <PMID>24057692</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coronado GD, Vollmer WM, Petrik A, Taplin SH, Burdick TE, Meenan RT, Green BB. Strategies and Opportunities to STOP Colon Cancer in Priority Populations: design of a cluster-randomized pragmatic trial. Contemp Clin Trials. 2014 Jul;38(2):344-9. doi: 10.1016/j.cct.2014.06.006. Epub 2014 Jun 14.</citation>
    <PMID>24937017</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coronado GD, Vollmer WM, Petrik A, Aguirre J, Kapka T, Devoe J, Puro J, Miers T, Lembach J, Turner A, Sanchez J, Retecki S, Nelson C, Green B. Strategies and opportunities to STOP colon cancer in priority populations: pragmatic pilot study design and outcomes. BMC Cancer. 2014 Feb 26;14:55. doi: 10.1186/1471-2407-14-55.</citation>
    <PMID>24571550</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coronado GD, Schneider JL, Sanchez JJ, Petrik AF, Green B. Reasons for non-response to a direct-mailed FIT kit program: lessons learned from a pragmatic colorectal-cancer screening study in a federally sponsored health center. Transl Behav Med. 2015 Mar;5(1):60-7. doi: 10.1007/s13142-014-0276-x.</citation>
    <PMID>25729454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coronado GD, Burdick T, Petrik A, Kapka T, Retecki S, Green B. Using an Automated Data-driven, EHR-Embedded Program for Mailing FIT kits: Lessons from the STOP CRC Pilot Study. J Gen Pract (Los Angel). 2014 Jan 5;2. pii: 1000141.</citation>
    <PMID>25411657</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coronado GD, Petrik AF, Spofford M, Talbot J, Do HH, Taylor VM. Clinical perspectives on colorectal cancer screening at Latino-serving federally qualified health centers. Health Educ Behav. 2015 Feb;42(1):26-31. doi: 10.1177/1090198114537061. Epub 2014 Jun 20.</citation>
    <PMID>24952378</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coronado GD, Retecki S, Schneider J, Taplin SH, Burdick T, Green BB. Recruiting community health centers into pragmatic research: Findings from STOP CRC. Clin Trials. 2016 Apr;13(2):214-22. doi: 10.1177/1740774515608122. Epub 2015 Sep 29.</citation>
    <PMID>26419905</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson KE, Tachibana C, Coronado GD, Dember LM, Glasgow RE, Huang SS, Martin PJ, Richards J, Rosenthal G, Septimus E, Simon GE, Solberg L, Suls J, Thompson E, Larson EB. A guide to research partnerships for pragmatic clinical trials. BMJ. 2014 Dec 1;349:g6826. doi: 10.1136/bmj.g6826.</citation>
    <PMID>25446054</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 3, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 4, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 5, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Colorectal Cancer Screening</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer Screening</keyword>
  <keyword>Pragmatic Trial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colonic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

