<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01747967</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>K 091101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01747967</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Immune Biomarkers of Residual Beta-cell Mass in Type 1 Diabetes</brief_title>
  <acronym>IMMADIAB</acronym>
  <official_title>Immune Biomarkers of Residual Beta-cell Mass in Type 1 Diabetes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>URC/CIC Cochin-Necker</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There is currently no imaging technique allowing to directly visualize and measure pancreatic
      beta-cell mass. Consequently, the best parameter to estimate this mass is the insulin (and
      its C-peptide byproduct) that residual beta cells are able to produce. This insulin secretion
      is measured during a meal test, before and at different times after drinking a standardized
      quantity of nutrients. However, this test is cumbersome (lasting 3 h, with blood samples
      taken every 30 minutes) and it holds poor sensitivity, probably insufficient to detect very
      few residual beta cells. Nevertheless, these few residual cells can improve glycemic control
      and can be instrumental for the clinical efficacy of immune and/or regenerative therapies.

      We hypothesize that residual beta cells may not only represent the remaining insulin
      secretory capacity, but also the antigenic load capable of stimulating beta-cell-reactive T
      lymphocytes. The disappearance of these T lymphocytes from circulating blood over time may
      thus be correlated with beta-cell loss. Measuring beta-cell-reactive T-cell responses may
      therefore provide simple and sensitive immune surrogate markers of residual insulin
      secretion. Other surrogate markers may be obtained by measuring urinary C peptide or residual
      secretion of the counter-regulatory hormone glucagon.

      The main objectives of this study are:

        1. To evaluate the correlation between beta-cell-reactive T-cell responses and residual
           insulin secretion.

        2. To evaluate the correlation between the residual insulin secretion measured by serum C
           peptide and by urinary C peptide.

        3. To evaluate the correlation between the residual insulin and glucagon secretion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Type 1 Diabetes (T1D) displays an average 4% annual increase in incidence in most Western
      countries, particularly in children and young adults. As it requires life-long treatments and
      it carries significant risks of hypoglycemic and long-term micro- and macrovascular
      complications, it is a leading cause of disability and public health expenditure.

      T1D is an autoimmune disease which comprises humoral responses (antibody-producing B
      lymphocytes) and cellular responses (T lymphocytes). However, antibodies are merely disease
      markers and do not play any major pathogenic role. Rather, T1D is caused by an abnormal
      recognition of beta-cell epitopes by T lymphocytes. This recognition leads to destruction of
      pancreatic insulin-secreting beta cells, hence the need for lifelong insulin treatment.
      However, beta-cell destruction is rarely complete at the time of T1D onset.

      The hypothesis under testing is that the residual beta-cell mass may represent not only the
      endogenous insulin secretory capacity, but also the antigenic load capable of maintaining
      activation of autoreactive T lymphocytes. In other words, the disappearance of
      beta-cell-reactive T-cell responses over time may be correlated with beta-cell loss.
      Measurement of these T-cell responses may thus provide surrogate immune markers of residual
      beta cells.

      The primary objective is to evaluate the correlation between residual insulin secretion and
      T-cell responses directed against beta-cell antigens.

      The secondary objectives are to evaluate the correlation between residual insulin secretion
      estimated by serum and urine C-peptide measurement; and to evaluate the correlation between
      residual insulin and glucagon secretion.

      The ImMaDiab study is a cohort-based investigation with blood sample collection. Both
      new-onset T1D children and adults will be recruited. Insulin secretion will be stimulated by
      a standardized meal test. Following T1D diagnosis, blood and urine samples will be collected
      every 6 months during 30 months in order to measure serum and urine C peptide, glucagon and
      T-lymphocyte responses against selected beta-cell antigens.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 15, 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 30, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 30, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between residual insulin secretion and T-cell responses against beta-cell antigens.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the correlation between residual insulin secretion and T-cell responses against beta-cell antigens.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between residual insulin secretion and T-cell responses against beta-cell antigens.</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 30 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the correlation between residual insulin secretion and T-cell responses against beta-cell antigens.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between residual insulin secretion estimated by serum and urine C-peptide measurement.</measure>
    <time_frame>at Day 1 and at 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the correlation between residual insulin secretion estimated by serum and urine C-peptide measurement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between residual insulin and glucagon secretion.</measure>
    <time_frame>at Day 1 and at 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the correlation between residual insulin and glucagon secretion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between residual insulin secretion estimated by serum and urine C-peptide measurement.</measure>
    <time_frame>at Day 1 and at 30 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the correlation between residual insulin secretion estimated by serum and urine C-peptide measurement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between residual insulin and glucagon secretion.</measure>
    <time_frame>at Day 1 and at 30 months</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the correlation between residual insulin and glucagon secretion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">156</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 1 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Meal test</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Both new-onset T1D children and adults will be recruited and followed up through 4 meal tests at 0, 6, 12 , 18, 24 and 30 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meal Test</intervention_name>
    <description>Insulin secretion is stimulated by a standardized meal test. Blood and urine samples are collected in order to measure serum and urinary C peptide, glucagon and T-lymphocyte responses against selected beta-cell antigens. The meal test is performed at 0, 6, 12, 18, 24 and 30 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Meal test</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Pre-inclusion criteria :

          -  children 6-18 years old;

          -  adults 19-60 years old;

          -  patients with a likely diagnosis of T1D, defined by an hyperglycaemia with ketonuria
             and/or weight loss ≥5% in the last 6 months, requiring insulin therapy.

        Inclusion criteria:

          -  presence of serum anti-GAD antibodies; and/or

          -  presence of serum anti-IA-2 antibodies; and/or

          -  for children, presence of serum IAA antibodies; and/or

          -  presence of T-cell autoimmune responses;

          -  meal test feasible within 10 weeks of diagnosis.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  recipients of solid organ or hematopoietic tissue transplantations ;

          -  immunosuppressive therapies (anti-histamine agents are not included);

          -  thyroid disease treated by methimazole;

          -  known HIV, HBV or HCV infection;

          -  known progressive cancer disease;

          -  known primary immune deficiency
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Etienne LARGER, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Service de Diabétologie, Hôtel Dieu, AP-HP, Paris</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roberto MALLONE, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>INSERM , AP-HP</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>INSERM U1016 - DeAR Lab Avenir, Hôpital Cochin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75014</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.dearlab.org/</url>
    <description>DeAR Lab Avenir Homepage</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scotto M, Afonso G, Østerbye T, Larger E, Luce S, Raverdy C, Novelli G, Bruno G, Gonfroy-Leymarie C, Launay O, Lemonnier FA, Buus S, Carel JC, Boitard C, Mallone R. HLA-B7-restricted islet epitopes are differentially recognized in type 1 diabetic children and adults and form weak peptide-HLA complexes. Diabetes. 2012 Oct;61(10):2546-55.</citation>
    <PMID>22997432</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Culina S, Mallone R. Immune biomarkers in immunotherapeutic trials for type 1 diabetes: cui prodest? Diabetes Metab. 2012 Nov;38(5):379-85. doi: 10.1016/j.diabet.2012.05.005. Epub 2012 Jul 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22858113</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scotto M, Afonso G, Larger E, Raverdy C, Lemonnier FA, Carel JC, Dubois-Laforgue D, Baz B, Levy D, Gautier JF, Launay O, Bruno G, Boitard C, Sechi LA, Hutton JC, Davidson HW, Mallone R. Zinc transporter (ZnT)8(186-194) is an immunodominant CD8+ T cell epitope in HLA-A2+ type 1 diabetic patients. Diabetologia. 2012 Jul;55(7):2026-31. doi: 10.1007/s00125-012-2543-z. Epub 2012 Apr 20.</citation>
    <PMID>22526607</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Martinuzzi E, Afonso G, Gagnerault MC, Naselli G, Mittag D, Combadière B, Boitard C, Chaput N, Zitvogel L, Harrison LC, Mallone R. acDCs enhance human antigen-specific T-cell responses. Blood. 2011 Aug 25;118(8):2128-37. doi: 10.1182/blood-2010-12-326231. Epub 2011 Jun 28.</citation>
    <PMID>21715316</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brezar V, Carel JC, Boitard C, Mallone R. Beyond the hormone: insulin as an autoimmune target in type 1 diabetes. Endocr Rev. 2011 Oct;32(5):623-69. doi: 10.1210/er.2011-0010. Epub 2011 Jun 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21700723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 10, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 11, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 12, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 31, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 31, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 1, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Antibodies</keyword>
  <keyword>Beta cells</keyword>
  <keyword>C-peptide</keyword>
  <keyword>GAD</keyword>
  <keyword>Glucose</keyword>
  <keyword>Glycemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Insulin</keyword>
  <keyword>Meal test</keyword>
  <keyword>Pancreas</keyword>
  <keyword>Proinsulin,</keyword>
  <keyword>T lymphocytes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

