<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01749969</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TCD11863</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1119-3107</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01749969</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SAR650984 (Isatuximab), Lenalidomide, and Dexamethasone in Combination in RRMM Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1b Study of SAR650984 (Anti-CD38 mAb) in Combination With Lenalidomide and Dexamethasone for the Treatment of Relapsed or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sanofi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sanofi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objectives:

        -  To determine the maximum tolerated dose of SAR650984 (isatuximab) with lenalidomide and
           dexamethasone (LD) in patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma.

        -  Expansion Phase Only: To further evaluate preliminary evidence of antitumor activity
           (objective response rate [ORR]) of SAR650984 (isatuximab) in combination with LD using
           International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) criteria.

      Secondary Objectives:

        -  To evaluate the safety, including immunogenicity, of SAR650984 (isatuximab) in
           combination with LD in relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma. The severity, frequency
           and incidence of all toxicities will be assessed.

        -  To evaluate the pharmacokinetics (PK) of SAR650984 (isatuximab) when administered in
           combination with LD and the PK of lenalidomide in combination with SAR650984 and
           dexamethasone.

        -  To assess the relationship between clinical (adverse event [AE] and/or tumor response)
           effects and pharmacologic parameters (PK/pharmacodynamics), and/or biologic (correlative
           laboratory) results.

        -  For the dose expansion phase, estimate the activity (ORR) using IMWG defined response
           criteria of SAR650984 (isatuximab) plus LD.

        -  To describe progression-free survival (PFS) in patients treated with this combination.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study duration for an individual patient will include a screening period for inclusion of
      up to 21 days, and at least 4 weeks of treatment in the absence of severe adverse reaction,
      dose limiting toxicity or disease progression plus up to 60 days post-treatment follow up.
      The treatment period may continue until disease progression, intolerable toxicity, or
      Investigator, sponsor, or patient decision to discontinue therapy. After study treatment
      discontinuation, an end of treatment (EOT) visit will be done at 30 days to assess safety,
      and at 30 and 60 days for anti-drug antibody (ADA) and PK. If the ADA is positive or
      inconclusive at day 60, then PK and ADA will be repeated every 30 days until ADA is negative.
      Patients who discontinue treatment for reasons other than progression of disease will be
      followed monthly until progression, initiation of subsequent therapy, or until the primary
      analysis cutoff date, whichever comes first.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 6, 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 28, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 28, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with adverse events when treated with SAR650984 (isatuximab) in combination with LD</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 30 days for patients experiencing progressive disease and continuously while patients are on treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preliminary assessment of overall response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months from the last investigational medicinal product (IMP)/non-IMP (NIMP) administration</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preliminary assessment of progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to disease progression</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of PK parameters - maximum concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to disease progression plus 60 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of PK parameters - time to reach Cmax (Tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to disease progression plus 60 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of PK parameters - concentration observed at end of infusion (Ceoi)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to disease progression plus 60 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of PK parameters - area under the plasma concentration versus time curve over the dosing interval (AUCtau)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to disease progression plus 60 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of PK parameters - plasma concentration observed just before treatment administration during repeated dosing (Ctrough)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to disease progression plus 60 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of CD38 receptors occupied by SAR650984 (isatuximab)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to disease progression plus 60 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CD38 receptor density</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to disease progression plus 60 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Immunogenicity: Number of anti-SAR650984 (isatuximab) antibodies in response to SAR650984 (isatuximab)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to disease progression plus 60 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Plasma Cell Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SAR650984 (isatuximab)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>SAR650984 (isatuximab) (escalating dose) plus lenalidomide 25 mg on Days 1 to 21 plus dexamethasone 40 mg on Days 1, 8, 15, 22 in 28-day cycles for all cohorts up to disease progression.
For Q2W cohorts: SAR650984 (isatuximab) on Days 1 and 15 of every cycle. For QW/Q2W cohorts: SAR650984 (isatuximab) on Days 1, 8, 15, and 22 of first cycle and Days 1 and 15 of every subsequent cycle.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>isatuximab SAR650984</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmaceutical form:solution Route of administration: intravenous</description>
    <arm_group_label>SAR650984 (isatuximab)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmaceutical form:capsules Route of administration: oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>SAR650984 (isatuximab)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Revlimid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>Pharmaceutical form:solution or tablet Route of administration: intravenous or oral</description>
    <arm_group_label>SAR650984 (isatuximab)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

        Male or female patients age 18 years or older. Diagnosis of multiple myeloma and
        documentation of at least 2 prior therapies (induction therapy, autologous stem cell
        transplant, consolidation and maintenance therapy is considered one prior therapy); there
        is no maximum number of prior regimens and prior bone marrow transplant is acceptable.

        Confirmed evidence of disease progression from immediately prior MM therapy or refractory
        to the immediately prior therapy.

        Patients may have received prior immunomodulatory drugs (IMiDs®) (eg, lenalidomide or
        thalidomide).

        Patients with measurable disease. Patients with a Karnofsky ≥60% performance status.
        Females of childbearing potential (FCBP). Voluntary written informed consent before
        performance of any study-related procedure not part of routine medical care with the
        understanding that consent may be withdrawn by the subject at any time without prejudice to
        future medical care.

        Ability to understand the purpose and risks of the study and provide signed and dated
        informed consent and authorization to use protected health information (in accordance with
        national and local subject privacy regulations).

        Able to take aspirin daily as prophylactic anti-coagulation therapy (patients intolerant to
        aspirin may use warfarin, low molecular weight heparin or equivalent anti-platelet
        therapy).

        Adequate organ function.

        Exclusion criteria:

        Diagnosed or treated for another malignancy within 3 years prior to enrollment, with the
        exception of complete resection of basal cell carcinoma or squamous cell carcinoma of the
        skin, an in situ malignancy, or low risk prostate cancer after curative therapy.

        Prior anti-cancer therapy (chemotherapy, targeted agents, radiotherapy, and immunotherapy)
        within 21 days except for alkylating agents (eg, melphalan) where 28 days will be required
        or participated in another clinical trial during the past 30 days.

        History of significant cardiovascular disease within the past 6 months, unless the disease
        is well-controlled.

        Prior autologous stem cell transplant within 12 weeks of the first dose of study treatment
        and/or prior allogeneic transplant within 1 year or has evidence of active
        graft-versus-host disease (GVHD) requiring &gt;10 mg prednisone daily.

        Daily requirement for corticosteroids (&gt;10 mg prednisone qd for 7 consecutive days) (except
        for inhalation corticosteroids and patients being treated for adrenal
        insufficiency/replacement therapy).

        Evidence of mucosal or internal bleeding. Prior radiation therapy or major surgical
        procedure within 4 weeks of the first dose of study treatment.

        Known active infection requiring parenteral or oral anti-infective treatment. Serious
        psychiatric illness, active alcoholism, or drug addiction that may hinder or confuse
        follow-up evaluation.

        Any medical conditions that, in the Investigator's opinion, would impose excessive risk to
        the patient.

        Hypersensitivity to any of the components of study therapy that is not amenable to
        premedication with steroids and H2 blockers.

        Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or active hepatitis B or C viral infection.

        Neuropathy ≥ Grade 3 or painful neuropathy ≥ Grade 2. Gastro-intestinal abnormalities,
        including bowel obstruction, inability to take oral medication, requirement for intravenous
        (IV) alimentation, active peptic ulcer or prior surgical procedures or bowel resection
        affecting absorption.

        Pregnancy.

        The above information is not intended to contain all considerations relevant to a patient's
        potential participation in a clinical trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Clinical Sciences &amp; Operations</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Sanofi</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigational Site Number 840004</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94117</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigational Site Number 840001</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigational Site Number 840002</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigational Site Number 840005</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Investigational Site Number 840003</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 10, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 12, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 17, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

