<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01749566</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00059752</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>KL2TR000455</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>ACTSIKL22012</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01749566</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exploring HIV Entry Blockade as a Pre-exposure Prophylaxis Strategy in Women</brief_title>
  <acronym>MVC-PREP</acronym>
  <official_title>Exploring HIV Entry Blockade as a Pre-exposure Prophylaxis Strategy in Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) is an HIV prevention strategy in which HIV medicines are used
      by a person before they are exposed to HIV in order to decrease his or her chance of getting
      infected. In this study, we will investigate a new PrEP strategy in women using a drug called
      maraviroc, a medicine used in the treatment of HIV infection called a CCR5 antagonist. We
      hypothesize that maraviroc could be a particularly good drug for PrEP because it achieves
      high concentrations in the genital tract in women and decreases the number of HIV-susceptible
      cells in the genital tract, and thus could potentially be dosed in more favorable ways than
      the current PrEP drugs.

      In order to further evaluate this PrEP strategy, we plan to measure the amount of maraviroc
      in the blood and genital tract of HIV-negative healthy female volunteers before, during, and
      after they are given maraviroc dosed either in the standard (twice a day) or reduced (once a
      day) dose for 7 days compared with women who are not given maraviroc. We will also study
      immune cells from the blood and genital tract from these women to see if maravoric has an
      effect on these cells that would prevent them from becoming infected with HIV.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE Globally, over half of HIV-infected adults are women, and in the United States, 25%
      of all HIV/AIDS cases occur in women. Women often lack control over many available prevention
      measures, underscoring a critical need to enhance HIV prevention options for women.
      Pre-exposure prophylaxis (PrEP) is an HIV prevention strategy in which antiretroviral (ARV)
      drugs are used prior to potential HIV exposure to reduce the likelihood of infection. This
      strategy, which usually contains the drug tenofovir disoproxil fumarate (TDF), has recently
      shown promise, but efficacy data suggest room for improvement, particularly for women, in
      whom these data are conflicting. This study aims to prospectively examine ARV pharmacology
      and mucosal immunology in order to evaluate a novel PrEP strategy in women - blockade of HIV
      entry from its target cells at the mucosal surface using the CCR5 receptor antagonist
      maraviroc (MVC). These actions of CCR5 receptor antagonism, if validated, could lead to
      reduced HIV acquisition risk at more favorable dosing strategies than available for current
      PrEP. Knowledge of pharmacological modulation of mucosal immunity and HIV acquisition risk is
      fundamental to understanding, improving, and designing new PrEP strategies.

      DESIGN This is a prospective, observational cohort study with an intensive pharmacokinetic
      component conducted in HIV-negative healthy women. Genital tract and whole blood samples will
      be collected before, during, and after treatment with 7 days of oral MVC, dosed at 300mg
      twice daily (standard) or 300mg daily (reduced) compared with no treatment (control). Genital
      tract and plasma MVC concentration will be measured using intensive pharmacokinetic sampling
      to generate concentration-time profiles. Peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) and
      endocervical cells harvested from whole blood and cervicovaginal lavage respectively will be
      analyzed for CCR5 receptor occupancy, the number of CCR5-expressing HIV target cells, and
      level of T cell activation.

      DURATION 21 days after the first visit of the last participants. Enrollment is expected to
      take 12 months.

      SAMPLE SIZE 30 subjects (10 subjects per study group)

      POPULATION HIV-negative healthy women, age 18 years or older, with normal menses.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in female genital tract maraviroc concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, 7, 10-12</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Female genital tract HIV target cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, 7, 10-12, 14, 21</time_frame>
    <description>HIV target cell availability (CCR5+ CD4+ T lymphocytes) in the FGT compared with blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Female genital tract T cell activation</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, 7, 10-12, 14, 21</time_frame>
    <description>T cell activation (HLA-DR+ CD38+ CD4+ T-lymphocytes) in the FGT compared with blood</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vaginal microbiome</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0, 7, 10-12, 14, 21</time_frame>
    <description>Determine the effect of CCR5 receptor blockade on the vaginal microbiome in healthy women</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">31</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A (standard maraviroc dosing)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>maraviroc 300mg po bid x 7 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B (reduced maraviroc dosing)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>maraviroc 300mg po daily x 7 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group C (no drug)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>No additional drug</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>maraviroc</intervention_name>
    <description>Maraviroc administered at standard (300mg po bid) or reduced (300mg po daily) dosing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A (standard maraviroc dosing)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B (reduced maraviroc dosing)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Selzentry</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female sex, defined by sex at birth

          -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years

          -  Negative HIV serology at screening

          -  Normal menses (within 22-35 day intervals) for at least 3 cycles

          -  Intact uterus and cervix

          -  Normal chemistry and CBC panels at screening, including

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) greater than 750/mm3

               -  Hemoglobin greater than 10.0 g/dL

               -  Platelet count greater than 100,000/mm3

               -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT), and alkaline
                  phosphatase less than 3 x upper limit of normal

               -  Total bilirubin less than 2.5 x upper limit of normal

               -  CrCl greater than or equal to 60 mL/min as estimated by the Cockcroft- Gault
                  equation

          -  Negative hepatitis B surface antigen

          -  Willing to use condoms for the duration of the study and abstain from sexual
             intercourse for 48 hours before each genital tract sampling

          -  Able and willing to provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy (by clinical history or positive urine pregnancy test at screening)

          -  Breastfeeding

          -  Alcohol or substance use that, in the opinion of the study investigator, would
             interfere with the conduct of the study

          -  History of loop electrosurgical excision procedure (LEEP), conization, or cryosurgery

          -  Use of systemic hormonal contraception

          -  Orthostasis at screening, defined as systolic blood pressure decrease of at least 20
             mm Hg or a diastolic blood pressure decrease of at least 10 mm Hg within three minutes
             of standing.

          -  Known history of heart or liver disease

          -  Known history of any medical condition that would interfere with conduct of the study,
             in the opinion of the study investigator

          -  Symptoms of active vaginal infection at the time of screening, including new
             ulcerative genital lesions or purulent and/or foul-smelling vaginal discharge

          -  Visible ulcerative genital lesions or purulent vaginal discharge during speculum
             pelvic examination performed at the time of screening

          -  Concomitant use of medications that interact with maraviroc or known allergy to
             maraviroc
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Anandi Sheth, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University School of Medicine, Department of Medicine, Division of Infectious Diseases</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grady Infectious Diseases Program</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30303</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 9, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 12, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 13, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 9, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Anandi Sheth</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV/AIDS, preexposure prophylaxis, women's health</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Maraviroc</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

