<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01747837</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-02-213</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01747837</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>REnal SympathetiC Denervation to sUpprEss Tachyarrhythmias in ICD Recipients</brief_title>
  <acronym>RESCUE</acronym>
  <official_title>REnal SympathetiC Denervation to sUpprEss Tachyarrhythmias in ICD Recipients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Vivek Reddy</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this trial is to determine the efficacy and safety of adjunctive
      catheter-based renal sympathetic denervation (RSDN) in the primary prevention of ICD therapy
      in patients with ischemic or non-ischemic ventricular dysfunction, who are to receive an ICD
      for either i) secondary prevention, or ii) primary prevention + inducible VT by programmed
      ventricular stimulation at the time of ICD implantation. These patients will be randomized to
      ICD alone or ICD + RSDN.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale for this Study

      Despite significant advances in the management of ventricular arrhythmias through the use of
      ICD therapy, AADs, and catheter-based ablation strategies, considerable challenges remain.
      The optimal method for the prevention of ICD shocks remains unclear. RSDN may be an effective
      tool for preventing ventricular arrhythmias, and associated ICD therapies, by reducing
      central sympathetic tone, catecholamine levels, and the renin-angiotensin-aldosterone system.
      Although RSDN has been shown to reduce the recurrence of VT in a case report of 2 patients
      suffering from electrical storm, to date no large prospective randomized study has evaluated
      the impact of RSDN in the primary prevention of ICD therapy in patients with ischemic or
      non-ischemic ventricular dysfunction. Also of note, there is data suggesting that RSDN may
      even decrease the rate of supraventricular arrhythmias such as atrial fibrillation. Thus,
      RESCUE will specifically evaluate the safety and efficacy of RSDN in the prevention of ICD
      therapy in patients with ventricular dysfunction who are to receive an ICD for either
      secondary prevention, or primary prevention if they have inducible VT by programmed
      ventricular stimulation at the time of ICD implantation.

      Description of Procedures

      Screening:

      To take part in this study, you must meet all study requirements. The screening visit tests
      and procedures are done to see if you are eligible to be in the study. The study doctor will
      review these with you and let you know if you qualify. The study doctor will make a final
      decision about your possible study qualification.

      Pre-randomization Procedures:

      After providing written consent the following data will be collected and examinations and
      tests performed:

        -  A physical examination

        -  Your blood pressure will be taken

        -  A review of your medical history and what medications you are taking

        -  A blood sample will be drawn for routine laboratory tests.

        -  Women who can have children will take a urine pregnancy test. The test must be negative
           for you to be in this study.

        -  A Transthoracic Echocardiogram (TTE)-a non-invasive test where a probe is placed on the
           chest wall and images are taken through the chest wall of the heart valves and heart
           muscle, that will measure the left ventricular size (heart wall thickness) and mitral
           inflow (flow of blood through the heart valve).

        -  An ICD interrogation (if you already have an ICD implanted) - a non-invasive test where
           a device is placed over the chest wall near your ICD, and data is transmitted wirelessly
           from your ICD to a laptop for your physician to review.

        -  An electrocardiogram (EKG) - a non-invasive test where several probes are placed on the
           chest wall that will measure electrical activity in your heart.

      Randomization:

      Immediately following the catheter ablation, patients will undergo a renal angiogram in order
      to assess suitability for catheter-based renal sympathetic denervation. A renal angiogram is
      an x-ray study of the blood vessels in the kidney to evaluate for blockage, and abnormalities
      that could be affecting the blood supply to the kidney. It is performed by injecting contrast
      dye through a catheter (a tiny tube) into the blood vessels of the kidney. The study doctor
      will assess whether the renal arteries are suitable to receive catheter-based renal
      denervation. Once you agree to participate in this study, by signing this informed consent,
      and are it is determined that you are eligible to participate you will be randomized to one
      of two treatment groups immediately following the renal angiogram.

      Randomization means that you are put into a group by chance. It is like flipping a coin. You
      will have an equal chance (50%) of being placed in either group. This study design is
      single-blinded; you will not know ahead of time which group you will be in. Only your
      physician will know which group you are randomized to.

      If you do not already have an ICD, you will undergo ICD placement as part of routine clinical
      care. You may undergo ICD placement up to 1 month (30 days) before randomization. An ICD
      (implantable cardioverter-defibrillator) is a small battery-powered electrical impulse
      generator which is implanted in patients who are at risk of sudden cardiac death due to
      ventricular fibrillation and ventricular tachycardia. The device is programmed to detect
      abnormal heart beats (cardiac arrhythmia) and correct it by delivering a jolt of electricity.

      The first group will undergo catheter-based sympathetic renal denervation. Renal Sympathetic
      Denervation is a procedure that uses a catheter probe inserted into the renal (kidney) artery
      that deactivates the nerves that are linked to high blood pressure.

      The second group (control group) will receive no further intervention after ICD implantation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 23, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first event requiring ICD therapy or Incessant VT</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint of this study is the time to first event requiring ICD therapy or Incessant VT.(VT occurring below the ICD rate cut-off); this will be assessed in the on-treatment patient cohort. An event requiring ICD therapy is defined as an anti-tachycardia pacing (ATP) or shock therapy for ventricular tachycardia or fibrillation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Appropriate ICD therapy assessed in the full intention-to-treat patient cohort</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>An Appropriate ICD therapy is defined as anti-tachycardia pacing (ATP) or shock therapy for ventricular tachycardia or fibrillation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Inappropriate ICD therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Inappropriate shocks are shocks given by the ICD for atrial fibrillation, supraventricular tachycardia or an abnormal sensing.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Hospitalizations for Cardiovascular Causes</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of Hospitalizations for Cardiovascular Causes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total VT burden</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Total VT burden (Number of episodes)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All-Cause Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>All-Cause Mortality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>occurrence of ICD storm</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>The occurrence of ICD storm, defined as ≥3 appropriate shock therapies within 24 hours</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>BUN/creatinine measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Differences in BUN/creatinine measurements</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Procedure related adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Procedure related adverse events including, but not limited to hematomas, pseudoaneurysms and renal artery stenosis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of orthostatic hypotension</measure>
    <time_frame>at 1 month, 6 months, 12 months, 24 months, 36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Development of orthostatic hypotension</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Major Complication Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>within first 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>30-day Major Complication Rate defined as death, stroke, MI or any other serious adverse events related to the treatment or procedure within the first 30 days or through hospital discharge (whichever is longer)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">462</enrollment>
  <condition>Ventricular Tachycardia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>standard ICD implantation alone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>These subjects will undergo standard ICD implantation alone (if not already present)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Boston Scientific Vessix Renal Denervation System</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>These subjects will undergo standard ICD implantation (if not already present) plus renal sympathetic denervation.
Ablation arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Boston Scientific Vessix Renal Denervation System</intervention_name>
    <description>Renal sympathetic denervation is modulation of the nerves which run along the renal arteries (the renal sympathetic nerves) with radiofrequency energy. This is the same energy source used to perform your heart ablation.
Boston Scientific Vessix Renal Denervation System, Boston Scientific, Inc., Quincy, Massachusetts</description>
    <arm_group_label>Boston Scientific Vessix Renal Denervation System</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Renal sympathetic denervation</other_name>
    <other_name>Renal denervation</other_name>
    <other_name>Denervation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ≥ 18 years of age

          -  Structural heart disease (post-MI, dilated cardiomyopathy, sarcoid myopathy,
             hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, etc.)

          -  Planned for ICD implantation for:

               -  i. Secondary prevention (eg: VT/VF arrest, sustained VT, syncope/inducible VT)

               -  ii. Primary prevention + inducible MMVT during induction via ICD lead testing

          -  Accessibility of renal vasculature (determined by renal angiography)

          -  Ability to understand the requirements of the study

          -  Willingness to adhere to study restrictions and comply with all post- procedural
             follow-up requirements

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient taking a Class I or III antiarrhythmic drug.

          -  Planned to undergo a cardiac VT ablation procedure

          -  NYHA Class IV Congestive Heart Failure

          -  MI within 30 days

          -  Known renovascular abnormalities that would preclude RSDN (eg, renal artery stenosis,
             previous renal artery stenting or angioplasty)

          -  Baseline orthostatic hypotension

          -  End stage renal failure on dialysis

          -  Life expectancy &lt;1 year for any medical condition

          -  Known pregnancy or positive β-HCG within 7 days of procedure.

          -  Coronary Artery Bypass Graft (CABG) within 30 days of the procedure
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Vivek Reddy, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Cardiac</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Na Homolce Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Prague</city>
        <zip>15030</zip>
        <country>Czechia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Academician E.N. Meshalkin Novosibirsk State Budget Research Institute of Circulation Pathology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Novosibirsk</city>
        <country>Russian Federation</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Czechia</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Czech Republic</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 1, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 11, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 12, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Vivek Reddy</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director Cardiac Arrhythmia Service, Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Renal sympathetic denervation</keyword>
  <keyword>Renal catheter ablation</keyword>
  <keyword>Ventricular tachycardia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tachycardia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tachycardia, Ventricular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

