<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01740258</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00038098</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01740258</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bevacizumab Beyond Progression (BBP)</brief_title>
  <acronym>BBP</acronym>
  <official_title>Phase II Trial of Bevacizumab, Radiation Therapy and Temodar Followed by Bevacizumab and Temodar With Continuation of Bevacizumab Beyond Progression (BBP-Bevacizumab Beyond Progression)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Studies which have separately studied bevacizumab for recurrent gliomas and bevacizumab for
      newly-diagnosed glioma have shown good results and the regimens have been well-tolerated by
      patients. This study seeks to investigate the use of bevacizumab with the standard therapy
      (radiation therapy and temozolomide) in newly diagnosed patients, followed by bevacizumab and
      temozolomide with the continuation of bevacizumab following progression. Two critical
      questions remain- the role of bevacizumab maintenance and bevacizumab at the time of
      progression in a patient previously treated with bevacizumab at the time of initial
      diagnosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Given the possible synergism with irinotecan and bevacizumab for colorectal carcinomas, the
      combination has been studied in gliomas. In a study of 21 patients, the combination of
      irinotecan and bevacizumab produced a 43% response rate, with acceptable toxicity. The
      response rate is significantly higher than irinotecan alone and any other therapy for
      recurrent glioma. There were two serious adverse events, one intracranial hemorrhage and one
      bowel perforation. At the Duke Brain Tumor Center, the investigators have treated over 1000
      glioblastoma patients with a bevacizumab-containing regimen, and there is marked clinical
      benefit and acceptable toxicity. Our initial study looking at the combination of bevacizumab
      and irinotecan for patients with recurrent glioblastoma published in 2007 found impressive
      response rates and survival and corroborated the earlier experience of Starks-Vance.

      The investigators completed a study for newly diagnosed glioblastoma that utilized
      bevacizumab, radiation therapy and temozolomide followed by 6 months of bevacizumab,
      irinotecan and temozolomide. In addition, the group at University of California at Los
      Angeles published a study with bevacizumab, radiation therapy and temozolomide followed by 12
      months of bevacizumab and temozolomide for newly diagnosed glioblastoma. These two phase II
      studies reported acceptable toxicity and a suggestion of improved survival compared to
      historical controls, and led to two large phase III randomized, placebo controlled studies of
      the addition of bevacizumab for newly diagnosed glioblastoma patients. The current proposal
      builds on the encouraging results of the addition of bevacizumab to the standard therapy for
      newly diagnosed glioblastoma patients. Two critical questions remain- the role of bevacizumab
      maintenance and bevacizumab at the time of progression in a patient previously treated with
      bevacizumab at the time of initial diagnosis. In addition, a retrospective analysis of data
      collected at our center from patients with recurrent disease suggests that continuation of
      bevacizumab at the time of progression may improve overall survival in comparison with
      cessation of bevacizumab.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival</measure>
    <time_frame>5 Years</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the effect on overall survival of continuing bevacizumab treatment after disease progression in patients treated with bevacizumab from the time of first diagnosis of grade IV malignant glioma.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Describe Toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>5 Years</time_frame>
    <description>To describe the toxicity of bevacizumab, 10 mg every other week (QOW), in combination with radiation therapy and daily Temodar, followed by bevacizumab and 5-day Temodar with continuation of bevacizumab beyond progression.
For each type of toxicity observed, the maximum grade experienced by each patient will be tabulated overall and for each 6-month period of follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free Survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 Years</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the effect on progression-free survival of continuing bevacizumab treatment after disease progression in patients treated with bevacizumab from the time of initiation of treatment to the first occurrence of progression, or death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Malignant Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Grade 4 Malignant Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Glioblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Gliosarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bevaczimab, Radiation Therapy, Temozolomide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In Part A, newly-diagnosed patients with Grade 4 malignant gliomas will receive standard radiation therapy, daily Temodar 75mg/M for 6-8 weeks. Bevacizumab will be given concurrently with radiation therapy and Temodar, 10 mg/kg every two weeks.
If they are stable at the end of Part A, they will continue to Part B. In Part B patients will receive up to 12 cycles of bevacizumab and Temodar. Bevacizumab will be given on Days 1 and 15 of a 28-day cycle. Temodar will be 200 mg/meter squared daily for 5 days (days 1-5) of each cycle.
If they have not progressed, patients will start Part C. In Part C, patients will receive bevacizumab 10mg/kg approximately every 2 weeks or 15 mg/kg approximately every 3 weeks.
If patients progress during Part B or C, they will start Part D. In Part D, patients will receive bevacizumab-based therapy containing bevacizumab in combination with a chemotherapy and/or biologic agent, as determined by the Duke treating physician.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiation Therapy</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Bevaczimab, Radiation Therapy, Temozolomide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>XRT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Temozolomide</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Bevaczimab, Radiation Therapy, Temozolomide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>temo</other_name>
    <other_name>temodar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bevacizumab</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Bevaczimab, Radiation Therapy, Temozolomide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Avastin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with histologically confirmed WHO Grade IV primary malignant glioma
             (glioblastoma or gliosarcoma);

          -  Patients ≥ 18 years of age;

          -  An interval of at least 2 weeks, but not ≥ 8 weeks between prior surgical procedure
             and initiation of treatment;

          -  Karnofsky Performance Status (KPS) ≥ 60%

          -  Laboratory Values:

               -  Platelet Count ≥ 125,000 cells/µL

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,500 cells/µL

               -  Adequate renal function indicated by all of the following:

                    -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.25 x upper limit of normal (ULN) or calculated
                       creatinine clearance ≥ 50 ml/min

                    -  Urine dipstick for proteinuria &lt; 2+ unless a 24-hour urine protein &lt; 1 g of
                       protein is demonstrated

               -  internationalized normalized ratio (INR) ≤ 1.5 and activated partial
                  thromboplastin time (aPTT) ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) within 7 days
                  prior to first study treatment for patients not receiving anti-coagulation. The
                  use of full-dose oral or parenteral anticoagulants is permitted as long as the
                  INR or aPTT is within therapeutic limits (according to the medical standard of
                  the enrolling institution) and the patient has been on a stable dose of
                  anticoagulants for at least two weeks prior to the first study treatment.

          -  Patients will sign an Institutional Review Board-approved informed consent form.

          -  Female patients must not be pregnant or breast-feeding. Female patients of
             childbearing potential (defined as &lt; 2 years after last menstruation or not surgically
             sterile) must use a highly effective contraceptive method (allowed methods of birth
             control, [i.e. with a failure rate of &lt; 1% per year] are implants, injectables,
             combined oral contraceptives, intra-uterine device [Intrauterine Device (IUD); only
             hormonal], sexual abstinence or vasectomized partner) during the trial and for a
             period of &gt; 6 months following the last administration of trial drug(s). Female
             patients with an intact uterus (unless amenorrhea for the last 24 months) must have a
             negative serum pregnancy test within 7 days prior to first study treatment.

          -  Fertile male patients must agree to use a highly effective contraceptive method
             (allowed methods of birth control [i.e. with a failure rate of &lt; 1% per year] include
             a female partner using implants, injectables, combined oral contraceptives,
             Intrauterine Device (IUDs) [only hormonal], sexual abstinence or prior vasectomy)
             during the trial and for a period of &gt; 6 months following the last administration of
             trial drugs.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any prior treatment for any grade glioma, including, but not limited to gliadel
             wafers, immunotherapy (including vaccine therapy), radiation therapy or chemotherapy,
             irrespective of grade of the tumor (NOTE: 5-aminolevulinic acid (ALA)-mediated
             photodynamic therapy administered prior to surgery to aid in optimal surgical
             resection is not considered a chemotherapy agent.);

          -  Co-medication that may interfere with study results; e.g. immuno-suppressive agents
             other than corticosteroids;

          -  Active infection requiring intravenous antibiotics;

          -  Prior or current treatment with bevacizumab or other anti-angiogenic treatment (i.e.
             anti-vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) or vascular endothelial growth factor
             receptor (VEGFR) therapies or tyrosine kinase inhibitors) for any condition;

          -  Treatment with any other investigational agent within 28 days or 2 investigational
             agent half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to first study treatment;

          -  Prior, unrelated malignancy requiring current active treatment with the exception of
             cervical carcinoma in situ and adequately treated basal cell or squamous cell
             carcinoma of the skin;

          -  Evidence of &gt; Grade 1 central nervous system (CNS) hemorrhage on post-operative MRI
             scan, unless repeat MRI or CT performed prior to initiating bevacizumab shows stable
             grade 1 or resolving (&lt; grade 1) CNS hemorrhage.

        Bevacizumab-Specific Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inadequately controlled hypertension (defined as systolic blood pressure &gt; 150 mmHg
             and/or diastolic blood pressure &gt; 100 mmHg) within 28 days of first study treatment;

          -  Prior history of hypertensive crisis, hypertensive encephalopathy, reverse posterior
             leukoencephalopathy syndrome (RPLS);

          -  Prior history of gastrointestinal perforation or abscess;

          -  Clinically significant (i.e. active) cardiovascular disease, for example
             cerebrovascular accidents ≤ 6 months prior to study enrollment, myocardial infarction
             ≤ 6 months prior to study enrollment, unstable angina, New York Heart Association
             (NYHA) Grade II or greater congestive heart failure (CHF), or serious cardiac
             arrhythmia uncontrolled by medication or potentially interfering with protocol
             treatment;

          -  History or evidence upon physical/neurological examination of central nervous system
             disease (e.g. seizures) unrelated to cancer unless adequately controlled by medication
             or potentially interfering with protocol treatment;

          -  Significant vascular disease (e.g., aortic aneurysm requiring surgical repair or
             recent arterial thrombosis) within 6 months prior to start of study treatment. Any
             previous venous thromboembolism &gt; NCI common toxicity criteria adverse event (CTCAE)
             Grade 3;

          -  History of pulmonary hemorrhage/hemoptysis ≥ grade 2 (defined as ≥ 2.5 mL bright red
             blood per episode) within 1 month of first study treatment;

          -  History or evidence of inherited bleeding diathesis or significant coagulopathy at
             risk of bleeding (i.e. in the absence of therapeutic anticoagulation);

          -  Current or recent (within 10 days of study enrollment) use of aspirin (&gt;325 mg/day),
             clopidogrel (&gt;75 mg/day) or equivalent. Prophylactic use of anticoagulants is allowed;

          -  Surgical procedure (including open biopsy, surgical resection, wound revision, or any
             other major surgery involving entry into a body cavity) or significant traumatic
             injury within 28 days prior to first study treatment, or anticipation of need for
             major surgical procedure during the course of the study;

          -  Minor surgical procedure, e.g. stereotactic biopsy, within 7 days of first study
             treatment; placement of a vascular access device, within 2 days of first study
             treatment;

          -  History of intracranial abscess within 6 months prior to first study treatment;

          -  History of active gastrointestinal bleeding within 6 months prior to first study
             treatment;

          -  Serious, non-healing wound, active ulcer, or untreated bone fracture;

          -  Known hypersensitivity to any component of bevacizumab or any of the study drugs;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Annick Desjardins, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University Health System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.cancer.duke.edu/btc/</url>
    <description>Preston Robert Tisch Brain Tumor Center at Duke</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.dukecancerinstitute.org/</url>
    <description>Duke Cancer Institute</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.dukehealth.org/cancer/locations/duke-cancer-center</url>
    <description>Duke Cancer Center - Patient Care</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 30, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 3, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 4, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 19, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 19, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>malignant glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>Grade 4 malignant glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>glioblastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>gliosarcoma</keyword>
  <keyword>adult brain tumor</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gliosarcoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bevacizumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Temozolomide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

