<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03320421</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NCC2016YQ-19</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03320421</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hypofractionated Radiation Therapy With Concomitant Boost in Treating Women After Breast Conserving Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Trial of Hypofractionated Whole-breast Radiation and Concomitant Boost to the Surgical Bed After Breast Conserving Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II study is to evaluate the safety of hypofractionated whole breast radiation
      (HFRT) with simultaneous tumor bed boost(SIB) in women with early breast cancer after
      breast-conserving surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary:

      To determine the toxicity with adjuvant hypofractionated whole breast radiation with
      simultaneous tumor bed boost (SIB) in women with early breast cancer after breast conserving
      surgery.

      Secondary:

      To determine the short term cosmetic and quality of life of the participants treated with
      this regimen.

      To determine the local control of the participants treated with this regimen.

      OUTLINE: Patients undergo adjuvant hypofractionated whole breast radiation with simultaneous
      tumor bed boost once daily a week for 3 weeks. Toxicity, quality of life and cosmetic result
      is assessed before radiation, at the end of the radiation, within 2, 4, 6 weeks after
      completion of radiotherapy, and then every 3 months for 1 ear.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: A total of 90 participants will be accrued for this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 31, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>acute radiation induced dermatitis by CTCAE within 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>radiation induced skin toxicity, including rash, dry skin, ulceration etc., occurring immediately after radiation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>late radiation toxicity by CTCAE every 3 months to 1 years after 3 months of completion of radiation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>any radiation induced toxicity occurring after the radiation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>breast cosmetic result as measured by Harvard scale of breast cosmesis (excellent, good, fair, poor) every 3 months for 1year</measure>
    <time_frame>every 3 months for 1year</time_frame>
    <description>breast cosmetic evaluation after breast conserving surgery and radiation, using Harvard scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>quality of life as measured by Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Breast Scale (FACT-B) every 3 months for 1 year</measure>
    <time_frame>every 3 months for 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Breast Scale (FACT-B) is used to evaluated the quality of life: all scale range: 0-144; sub-scale range: physical well being: 0-28; social well being: 0-28; emotional well being 0-24; functional well being 0-28; additional consideration: 0-36; the higher the better</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>quality of life as measured by Breast Cancer Treatment Outcome Scale(BCTOS) every 3 months for 1 year</measure>
    <time_frame>every 3 months for 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Functional Assessment of Breast Cancer Treatment Outcome Scale(BCTOS) is used to evaluated the quality of life. the range of BCTOS is 22-88, the smaller the better</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>in-breast recurrence rate at 1 year of radiation completion</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>recurrence occurred in the treated breast.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer Female</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SIB group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Radiation therapy:
daily 5 days per week for 3 weeks. 43.5 Gy in 15 fractions to the whole breast 49.5 Gy in 15 fractions to the tumor bed boost</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Radiation to the whole breast: 43.5 Gy in 15 fractions in 3 weeks. Simultaneous radiation to the surgical cavity: 49.5 Gy in 15 fractions in 3 weeks.
Intensity modulated radiation treatment is used.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SIB group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  female, aged between 18-70

          -  pathological confirmed breast invasive carcinoma

          -  patients after breast lumpectomy(including quadrantectomy) with axillary lymph nodes
             dissection or sentinel node biopsy

          -  stage p T 1-2 N 0

          -  metastasis omitted by routine examinations in 1 months before enrollment

          -  complete blood count obtained in 2 weeks prior to study entry should meet the
             following criteria: absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1.8 *10^9/L, hemoglobin &gt; 8.0g/dl,
             platelet &gt; 75 * 10^9/L

          -  hepatic and renal function in 2 weeks prior to study entry should be normal

          -  study entry within 60 days from whichever comes later: surgery or last chemotherapy

          -  women of childbearing potential must have a negative urine or serum pregnancy test
             with 2 weeks of study entry

          -  signs study specific informed consent prior to study entry

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  breast cancer with stage III/III (AJCC 7th)

          -  occult breast cancer

          -  in-situ breast carcinoma

          -  bilateral breast cancer

          -  male breast cancer

          -  breast lymphoma or breast sarcoma

          -  combined with Paget's disease

          -  received preoperative treatment(including neoadjuvant chemotherapy, endocrine therapy
             and target therapy

          -  positive surgical margin

          -  axillary lymph nodes dissection or sentinel lymph node biopsy omitted

          -  regional lymph nodes radiation needed

          -  boost volume larger than 1/4 of the whole breast

          -  tumor bed unable to recognize on CT

          -  prior invasive malignant tumor history

          -  prior radiation to thoracic

          -  connective tissue disease, such as active systemic lupus erythematosus and
             scleroderma, etc.

          -  severe, active co-morbidity, defined as follows:

               -  unstable angina and/or congestive heart failure requiring hospitalization within
                  the last 6 months

               -  severe, acute bacterial or fungal infection within the last 2 weeks

               -  chronic obstructive pulmonary disease exacerbation or other respiratory illness
                  within 30 days

          -  pregnant women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yexiong Li, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cancer Hospital/Institution, Chinese Academic Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Yu Tang, Doctor</last_name>
    <phone>8601087788122</phone>
    <email>tangyu.pumc@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Shulian Wang, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>8601087788122</phone>
    <email>wangshulian@sohu.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cancer Center/Cancer Hosptial, Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences and Peking Union Medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <state>Beijing</state>
        <zip>100021</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Yu Tang, Doctor</last_name>
      <phone>8601087788122</phone>
      <email>tangyu.pumc@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Shulian Wang, Professor</last_name>
      <phone>8601087788122</phone>
      <email>wangshulian@sohu.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Yexiong Li, Professor</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Early Breast Cancer Trialists' Collaborative Group (EBCTCG), Darby S, McGale P, Correa C, Taylor C, Arriagada R, Clarke M, Cutter D, Davies C, Ewertz M, Godwin J, Gray R, Pierce L, Whelan T, Wang Y, Peto R. Effect of radiotherapy after breast-conserving surgery on 10-year recurrence and 15-year breast cancer death: meta-analysis of individual patient data for 10,801 women in 17 randomised trials. Lancet. 2011 Nov 12;378(9804):1707-16. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(11)61629-2. Epub 2011 Oct 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22019144</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>START Trialists' Group, Bentzen SM, Agrawal RK, Aird EG, Barrett JM, Barrett-Lee PJ, Bliss JM, Brown J, Dewar JA, Dobbs HJ, Haviland JS, Hoskin PJ, Hopwood P, Lawton PA, Magee BJ, Mills J, Morgan DA, Owen JR, Simmons S, Sumo G, Sydenham MA, Venables K, Yarnold JR. The UK Standardisation of Breast Radiotherapy (START) Trial A of radiotherapy hypofractionation for treatment of early breast cancer: a randomised trial. Lancet Oncol. 2008 Apr;9(4):331-41. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(08)70077-9. Epub 2008 Mar 19.</citation>
    <PMID>18356109</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>START Trialists' Group, Bentzen SM, Agrawal RK, Aird EG, Barrett JM, Barrett-Lee PJ, Bentzen SM, Bliss JM, Brown J, Dewar JA, Dobbs HJ, Haviland JS, Hoskin PJ, Hopwood P, Lawton PA, Magee BJ, Mills J, Morgan DA, Owen JR, Simmons S, Sumo G, Sydenham MA, Venables K, Yarnold JR. The UK Standardisation of Breast Radiotherapy (START) Trial B of radiotherapy hypofractionation for treatment of early breast cancer: a randomised trial. Lancet. 2008 Mar 29;371(9618):1098-107. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(08)60348-7. Epub 2008 Mar 19.</citation>
    <PMID>18355913</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Whelan TJ, Pignol JP, Levine MN, Julian JA, MacKenzie R, Parpia S, Shelley W, Grimard L, Bowen J, Lukka H, Perera F, Fyles A, Schneider K, Gulavita S, Freeman C. Long-term results of hypofractionated radiation therapy for breast cancer. N Engl J Med. 2010 Feb 11;362(6):513-20. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0906260.</citation>
    <PMID>20147717</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hamilton DG, Bale R, Jones C, Fitzgerald E, Khor R, Knight K, Wasiak J. Impact of tumour bed boost integration on acute and late toxicity in patients with breast cancer: A systematic review. Breast. 2016 Jun;27:126-35. doi: 10.1016/j.breast.2016.03.002. Epub 2016 Apr 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27113229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chadha M, Vongtama D, Friedmann P, Parris C, Boolbol SK, Woode R, Harrison LB. Comparative acute toxicity from whole breast irradiation using 3-week accelerated schedule with concomitant boost and the 6.5-week conventional schedule with sequential boost for early-stage breast cancer. Clin Breast Cancer. 2012 Feb;12(1):57-62. doi: 10.1016/j.clbc.2011.09.002. Epub 2011 Nov 6.</citation>
    <PMID>22056970</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cante D, Franco P, Sciacero P, Girelli G, Marra AM, Pasquino M, Russo G, Borca VC, Mondini G, Paino O, Barmasse R, Tofani S, Numico G, La Porta MR, Ricardi U. Five-year results of a prospective case series of accelerated hypofractionated whole breast radiation with concomitant boost to the surgical bed after conserving surgery for early breast cancer. Med Oncol. 2013 Jun;30(2):518. doi: 10.1007/s12032-013-0518-7. Epub 2013 Mar 5.</citation>
    <PMID>23460537</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Freedman GM, White JR, Arthur DW, Allen Li X, Vicini FA. Accelerated fractionation with a concurrent boost for early stage breast cancer. Radiother Oncol. 2013 Jan;106(1):15-20. doi: 10.1016/j.radonc.2012.12.001. Epub 2013 Jan 17. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23333014</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 25, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 23, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 23, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 23, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Chinese Academy of Medical Sciences</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Yu Tang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>hypofractionated radiation</keyword>
  <keyword>breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>breast conserving surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>simultaneous boost radiation</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

