<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03320616</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EYP001-102</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2016-004713-27</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03320616</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>EYP001a Food Effect Study in Subjects With Chronic Hepatitis B Virus (HBV) Infection</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1, Open-Label, Randomized, 4-Way Crossover Study in Subjects With Chronic Hepatitis B Virus Infection to Assess Pharmacokinetics (Fasted/Fed), Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacodynamics of Single Oral Doses of Farnesoid X Receptor Agonist EYP001a</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Enyo Pharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>PRA Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Enyo Pharma</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The farnesoid X receptor (FXR) regulates hepatitis B virus replication through the bile acids
      pathway. EYP001a is a selective, synthetic FXR agonist under development for the treatment of
      hepatitis B.

      This Phase 1 study is designed primarily to assess Pharmacokinetics (PK) under fed and fasted
      conditions, and to assess the safety, tolerability and Pharmacodynamics (PD) of single oral
      doses of EYP001a in subjects with chronic HBV infection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-center, open-label, randomized, 4-way crossover study.

      A total of 14 chronic HBV subjects will participate. Subjects will receive 4 single dose
      administrations of EYP001a during the study. There will be 2 separate dosing periods: 1
      period with 2 single administrations of EYP001a in the morning, once under fasted conditions
      and once under fed condition (separated by 48.5 hours), and 1 period with 2 single
      administrations of EYP001a in the evening, once under fasted conditions and once under fed
      condition (separated by 48.5 hours).

      The subjects will be randomized to 1 of 4 treatment sequences:

        -  Sequence 1: Period 1 first dose morning fasted, second dose morning fed; Period 2 first
           dose evening fasted, second dose evening fed.

        -  Sequence 2: Period 1 first dose evening fasted, second dose evening fed; Period 2 first
           dose morning fasted, second dose morning fed.

        -  Sequence 3: Period 1 first dose morning fed, second dose morning fasted; Period 2 first
           dose evening fed, second dose evening fasted.

        -  Sequence 4: Period 1 first dose evening fed, second dose evening fasted; Period 2 first
           dose morning fed, second dose morning fasted.

      Participation will include an eligibility screening period of maximally 40 days, clinic stay
      during the treatment periods, and a followup visit 4 to 6 days after the last study drug
      administration.

      The safety and tolerability of EYP001a will be assessed by evaluating vital signs, ECGs,
      liver ultrasound, clinical laboratory and adverse events.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 10, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 12, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 12, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The subjects will be randomized to 1 of 4 treatment sequences.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Type and frequencies of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of Period 1 through Day 7 to Day 9 of Period 2</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum observed plasma concentration (Cmax) of EYP001a</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose to 48 hours after dosing</time_frame>
    <description>ng/mL</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to attain maximum observed plasma concentration (Tmax) after EYP001a administration</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose to 48 hours after dosing</time_frame>
    <description>h</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose to 48 hours after dosing</time_frame>
    <description>ng*h/mL</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bile acid precursor C4 (7α hydroxy-4-cholesten-3-one)</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose to 48 hours after dosing</time_frame>
    <description>ng/mL</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bile-regulating fibroblast growth factor 19 (FGF-19)</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose to 48 hours after dosing</time_frame>
    <description>pg/mL</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">11</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis B, Chronic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>4 single doses of EYP001a: Period 1 first dose morning fasted, second dose morning fed; Period 2 first dose evening fasted, second dose evening fed</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>4 single doses of EYP001a: Period 1 first dose evening fasted, second dose evening fed; Period 2 first dose morning fasted, second dose morning fed</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>4 single doses of EYP001a: Period 1 first dose morning fed, second dose morning fasted; Period 2 first dose evening fed, second dose evening fasted</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>4 single doses of EYP001a: Period 1 first dose evening fed, second dose evening fasted; Period 2 first dose morning fed, second dose morning fasted</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EYP001a</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral EYP001a capsules - 100 mg strength</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 4</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Has given voluntary written informed consent before performance of any study related
             procedure

          2. Has documented chronic HBV infection (documented within 12 months of screening visit),
             with criteria at screening: hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg) ≥ 50 IU/mL; HBV DNA &gt;
             100 IU/mL; hepatitis Be antigen (HBeAg) negative or positive

          3. Gender: male or female

          4. Age: 18-65 years, inclusive, at screening

          5. Body mass index (BMI): 17.0-35.0 kg/m2 inclusive, at screening

          6. Weight: &gt;60 kg for males and &gt;45 kg for females

          7. Has clinical chemistry, hematology, coagulation and urinalysis tests within normal,
             allowable limits (with the exception of alanine aminotransferase (ALAT) [see inclusion
             criterion #10]); if there is an out of range value, it must be considered clinically
             insignificant in order to be eligible

          8. Has normal vital signs after at least 5 minutes resting in supine position at
             screening: 95 mm Hg &lt; systolic blood pressure &lt; 140 mm Hg; 45 mm Hg &lt; diastolic blood
             pressure &lt; 90 mm Hg; 40 bpm &lt; heart rate &lt; 90 bpm

          9. Has no clinically significant abnormal 12-lead automatic electrocardiogram (ECG)
             (incomplete right bundle branch block can be accepted) at screening: 120 ms &lt;
             PR-interval &lt; 210 ms, QRS-duration &lt; 120 ms, corrected QT interval (QTc)
             (Fridericia's) ≤ 450 msec for males and females

         10. Has ALAT ≤ 3 x upper limit of normal (ULN) at screening

         11. Has documented liver histology with Metavir score (F0, F1, F2 or F3) or liver fibrosis
             documented with non-invasive alternatives to liver biopsy (Fibroscan) or shear wave
             elastography (Aixplorer) value &lt; 14.6 kPa

         12. Agrees to abstain from all medication, including non-prescription and prescription
             medication (including vitamins and natural or herbal remedies, e.g. St. John's Wort)
             for 28 days prior to (each) admission to the clinical research center until discharge,
             except for authorized medications such as hormonal contraceptives for females
             (registered in The Netherlands) and paracetamol. On a case-by-case basis, regular
             co-medication either as defined on the separate medication exception list or as
             documented by written approval from the Sponsor and the PI as acceptable prior to
             randomization, will not be considered as a deviation from this criterion. All other
             situations related to co-medications are considered as deviations

         13. At screening, females must be non-pregnant and non-lactating, or of non-childbearing
             potential (either surgically sterilized or physiologically incapable of becoming
             pregnant, or at least 1 year postmenopausal [amenorrhoea duration of 12 consecutive
             months); non-pregnancy will be confirmed for all females by a serum pregnancy test
             conducted at screening and at (each) admission to the clinical research center

         14. Female subjects of child-bearing potential, with a fertile male sexual partner, should
             be willing to use adequate contraception from screening until 90 days after the
             followup visit. Adequate contraception is defined as using hormonal contraceptives or
             an intrauterine device combined with at least 1 of the following forms of
             contraception: a diaphragm or cervical cap, or a condom. Also, total abstinence, in
             accordance with the lifestyle of the subject, is acceptable

         15. Male subjects, if not surgically sterilized, should be willing to use adequate
             contraception and not donate sperm from (first) admission to the clinical research
             center until 90 days after the follow-up visit. Adequate contraception for the male
             subject (and his female partner) is defined as using hormonal contraceptives or an
             intrauterine device combined with at least 1 of the following forms of contraception:
             a diaphragm or cervical cap, or a condom. Also, total abstinence, in accordance with
             the lifestyle of the subject is acceptable

         16. At screening, has no recent (&lt;3 months) history of any clinically significant
             conditions, which, in the opinion of the PI, would jeopardize the safety of the
             subject or impact the validity of the study results

         17. Willingness to abstain from alcohol and methylxanthine-containing beverages or food
             (coffee, tea, cola, chocolate, energy drinks) from 48 hours prior to (each) admission
             to the clinical research center

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Previous participation in the current study

          2. Employee of PRA or the Sponsor

          3. Currently receives or has received during the 60 days (or 5 half-lives of the specific
             drug, whichever is longer) before (first) admission to the clinical research center
             until (the last) discharge a nucleos(t)ide-analogue therapy or other anti HBV
             treatment (interferons, experimental anti HBV drugs or vaccines)

          4. Coinfection with hepatitis C virus (HCV), hepatitis D virus (HDV) or human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV)

          5. Receives or plans to receive systemic immunosuppressive medications during the study
             or ≤2 months prior to the first study drug administration

          6. Receiving or planning to receive interferon (IFN) during the study or ≤12 months prior
             to the first study drug administration

          7. Has significant immunosuppression from, but not limited to immunodeficiency conditions
             such as common variable hypogammaglobulinemia

          8. Clinical diagnosis of substance abuse with alcohol (regular alcohol consumption &gt;21
             units [men] and &gt;14 units [women] per week [1 unit = ½ pint of beer, 25 mL shot of 40%
             spirit or a 125 mL glass of wine]), narcotics, or cocaine ≤12 months prior to
             screening

          9. Has any known pre-existing medical or psychiatric condition that could interfere with
             the subject's ability to provide informed consent or participate in study conduct, or
             that may confound study findings.

         10. Has a history of clinically significant gastrointestinal disease, especially peptic
             ulcerations, gastrointestinal bleeding, ulcerative colitis, cholecystectomy, Crohn's
             disease or Irritable Bowel Syndrome, renal, hepatic, neurologic, hematologic,
             endocrine, oncologic, pulmonary, immunologic, or cardiovascular disease or any other
             condition which, in the opinion of the PI, would jeopardize the safety of the subject
             or impact the validity of the study results

         11. Has had acute diarrhea or constipation in the 7 days before (first) admission to the
             clinical research center. Diarrhea will be defined as the passage of liquid feces
             and/or a stool frequency of &gt; 3 times per day. Constipation will be defined as a
             failure to open the bowels more frequently than every other day.

         12. Has a history of long QT syndrome

         13. Has participated in a drug study within 30 days prior to the first drug administration
             in the current study

         14. Has a positive drug and alcohol screen (opiates, methadone, cocaine, methamphetamines,
             amphetamines, ecstasy, barbiturates, benzodiazepines, tricyclic antidepressants,
             phencyclidine and alcohol)

         15. Any current or previous (ie, ≤12 months prior to screening) abuse of drugs such as
             opiates, cocaine, ecstasy, or intravenous amphetamines. Subjects who admit to
             occasional use of cannabis will not be excluded as long as they are able to abstain
             from cannabis when they are in the clinical research center.

         16. Has an uncontrolled current illness (e.g., active infection)

         17. Has had major surgery within 30 days prior to the first drug administration, or 12
             months prior to the first drug administration for gastrointestinal surgery

         18. Has lost more than 100 mL of blood within 60 days prior to the first drug
             administration

         19. Has a history of relevant drug and/or food allergies

         20. Smokes more than 20 cigarettes per day

         21. Non-willingness to consume the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) breakfast

         22. Poor venous accessibility
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeroen van de Wetering, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>PRA-EDS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PRA-EDS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Groningen</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 20, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 24, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 25, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

