<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03325699</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>643399</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03325699</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Support Monitoring and Reminder Technology</brief_title>
  <acronym>SMART4MD</acronym>
  <official_title>Support Monitoring and Reminder Technology for Mild Dementia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johan Sanmartin Berglund</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alzheimer Europe</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>POW Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Andaluz Health Service</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Blekinge Institute of Technology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Consorci Sanitari de Terrassa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>DEX Innovation Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Anglia Ruskin University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University College Leuven – Limburg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universidad Politecnica de Madrid</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Athena ICT</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Blekinge Institute of Technology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This multicentre randomized control trial aims to evaluate the effects of an intervention
      consisting of an health application developed to improve the quality of life (QoL) in older
      people with mild dementia and their informal caregivers. The study is a collaboration between
      five European countries where the clinical trials will be conducted in four of these
      countries (Sweden, Belgium, Spain and Czech Republic).

      In total 1200 dyads (consisting of a person with mild dementia (PWD) and their informal
      caregiver (carer) will be recruited for this study. Participant dyads will be randomized in a
      1:1 ratio in two parallel groups: PWD to receive either usual care from primary or
      specialized providers (control group) or to receive usual care plus access to a tablet with
      the SMART4MD health application (intervention group).

      Participants in the trial will be assessed for a period of 18 months. After the baseline
      visit, all participants will have follow-up visits every 6 months together with a checkup of
      the PWDs capacity to remain in the study. In the follow up visits, investigators will assess
      the PWD's quality of life, their cognitive and functional status, adherence to prescribed
      medication and attendance at healthcare appointments and admissions to healthcare services
      institutions. Investigators will also assess the burden of the informal caregivers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      SMART4MD has been developed from an existing general health management application in a
      process involving the structured participation of PWD, their informal carers, and clinicians.

      STANDARD OPERATING PROCEDURES

      Participants will be recruited over a period of six months by the nominated/approved licensed
      providers of relevant medical care at the different sites. Participants will not receive
      financial reimbursement for taking part in this trial.

      Participants will be identified from people with cognitive impairment that has been present
      for more than six months and who meet all the study eligibility criteria (listed in section
      Eligibility). The Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) and Geriatric Depression Scale
      (GDS-15) will be used to screen PWD at recruitment. participants can be under primary care
      services as well as secondary care services. Participants will also be identified from
      patient databases such as those integrated in the network of Consorci Sanitari de Terrassa
      (CST) and Database of all patients participating in the Swedish National Study on Aging and
      Care (SNAC). In order to assure that all clinical sites have a similar approach in recruiting
      participants, a guide with best practices for patient recruitment have been developed.

      The following data will be collected in this trial:

        -  Mini Mental State examination (MMSE)

        -  Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS)

        -  Demographic data

        -  Medical history - PWD only

        -  Familiarity with comparable technological devices

        -  Quality of Life AD (QoL-AD)

        -  Adherence to medication

        -  The Lawton Instrumental Activities of Daily Living (IADL)

        -  EuroQoL 5 Dimension (EQ5D)

        -  The Short-form Zarit Caregiver Burden Interview (ZBI-12)

        -  Attendance at healthcare appointments and admissions to healthcare institutions

        -  Data from the SMART4MD application focusing on user behaviour and usage of core
           functionalities.

      All variables collected in this study is listed and detailed described in a electronic case
      report form, with associated guidelines, to ensure consistency in all gathered data.

      Any relevant changes to physical health will be noted during these investigations including
      whether the PWD is still in charge of their own medication and whether the same individual is
      still the informal carer of PWD. In case of an adverse event (AE) or serious adverse event
      (SAE), medical or psychosocial, the investigator and his or her team are responsible for
      detecting, recording, reporting and taking appropriate actions in according to the
      requirements of the local institutional review board (IRB) and the appropriate regulatory
      body with health- and social care in respective country of the study. Reporting of any AE and
      SAE must be done within 24 hours by an SAE Report Form sent to the clinical lead of this
      study.

      SAMPLE SIZE ASSESSMENT To compare two groups (Intervention and Control) using a two- sample,
      two-sided t-test with a 5% statistical significance level, the minimum number of evaluable
      PWDs required in each group is 470 (940 overall), to give a power of 80%. If there would be a
      drop-out rate of 20% of the PWDs then the number of PWDs registered on the study would need
      to be 564 in each group (1128 overall).

      STATISTICS ANALYSIS PLAN Data collected for the study will be analyzed to measure and assess
      the SMART4MD health application impact on QoL-AD for the PWDs as the primary outcome. In
      addition, functional status (IADL) for PWD, adherence to prescribed medication, health care
      appointment and admissions records and carer burden will be analyzed as secondary outcome.

      All the baseline data variables collected will be summarized by group and overall, and also
      by site. Among the statistical summary statistics considered for presentation for continuous
      measures in summary tables will be the mean, median, minima and maxima, lower and upper
      quartiles, and standard deviation. Categorical variables will be summarized using counts and
      percentages. As the PWDs will be assigned to the intervention and control using random
      allocation it is known in advance that any differences between these groups at baseline will
      be as a result of chance and so no formal comparison of the groups using statistical
      significance tests will be carried out at baseline.

      Primary outcome analysis:

      The primary analysis will be the comparison of the 18-month total QoL-AD score means using a
      two- sample, two-sided Monte Carlo permutation t-test. The use of a permutation test will
      avoid the need for strong assumptions about the distribution of the data. Similarly, a
      bootstrap approach will be used to obtain the 95% confidence limits for the difference
      between the group means.

      Secondary outcome analyses:

      The secondary analysis focus on a cost-effectiveness and/or cost-utility analysis from a
      Health Service perspective (financer perspective) measured by QUALYs. Furthermore, a
      user-behavior analysis of the SMART4MD health application by analyzing the frequency of
      access to the application, the length of this interaction, and the quality of the inputs
      provided. Usability tests will be performed based on the System Usability Scale (SUS). At
      last, a technical familiarity score is calculated to assess prior experience of technology
      and the effect on the outcomes analyzed by statistical regression analysis.

      PLAN FOR MISSING DATA Each partner are responsible for ensuring that any missing data will be
      reported as missing in the study database.For analyses involving multiple regression analysis
      a multiple imputation approach will be considered and used if statistically sound, depending
      on the proportion and pattern of missing values.

      QUALITY ASSURANCE PLAN

      The monitor(s) will review and report process during the course of the trial covering
      participant enrolment, consent, eligibility and allocation to trial groups, policies to
      protect participants, including reporting of harm and completeness, accuracy and timeliness
      of data collection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 3, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>QoL-AD score</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Improvement of the QoL of people with mild dementia</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to medication</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Increase adherence to prescribed medication prescription</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mini mental state examination (MMSE)</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Reduce functional decline of PWD</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Attendance to health care appointments</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Monitor PWD´s attendance at health care appointments and admissions to health care institutions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Zarit Burden Interview (ZBI)</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Monitor the mental well-being of informal caregivers</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1200</enrollment>
  <condition>Mild Dementia</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Impairment, Mild</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants assigned to the intervention group will have access to the SMART4MD health application and participate in clinical visits every 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants assigned to the intervention group will NOT have access to the SMART4MD health application and participate in clinical visits every 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SMART4MD Health Application</intervention_name>
    <description>SMART4MD is a general health application which has been adapted specifically for people with mild dementia through a structured process. The application is intended to be used daily at home, mainly by the participants themselves, with the help of their informal carers. The application is optimized for tablet devices running on Android operating system (OS). Participants will be provided with a tablet with the SMART4MD health application.
The core functionalities of the application are based on reminders (medication, appointments with healthcare providers), brain supporting activities (clock, calendar, brain games, photos) and optional status and health information sharing with family and informal carers (including daily feeling status, specific health problems, and quality of life). An important feature of SMART4MD is its personalization facility: main users (PWD and informal carers) will be able to switch off/on various features and information sharing possibilities.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria (PWD only):

          -  Participants score 20-26 points on Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE) Participants
             +55 years of age

          -  Male or female. No preference will be given to either

          -  Participants are home-care recipients

          -  Participants have an informal carer

          -  Those participants who take prescribed medication are in charge of their own
             medication use

          -  Participants have no specific conditions reducing their physical ability to use the
             application to a point that makes their participation in the project impossible, as
             evaluated by the responsible investigator (the nature of the conditions should be
             recorded in such cases)

          -  The place where the participant is normally resident has sufficient wireless or phone
             network connectivity to enable them to use SMART4MD on a daily basis

          -  Cognitive impairment must have been present for more than six months

        Exclusion criteria (PWD only):

          -  Participants have a terminal illness with &lt;3 years expected survival

          -  Participants score above 11 on the Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS-15)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>120 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tomer Regev, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Anglia Ruskin University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University College Leuven - Limburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Genk</city>
        <zip>3600</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Evi Lemmens, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+3211180600</phone>
      <email>evi.lemmens@ucll.be</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Evi Verdonck, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+3211180600</phone>
      <email>evi.verdonck@ucll.be</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>DEX Innovation Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Praha</city>
        <zip>16200</zip>
        <country>Czechia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michal Stefan, MsC</last_name>
      <phone>+420777477497</phone>
      <email>michal.stefan@dex-ic.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Aretha Elischer, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+420 603 443 922</phone>
      <email>geriatr@post.cz</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Consorci Sanitaria de Terrassa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Terrassa</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <zip>08227</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Maite Garolera, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+34937310007</phone>
      <phone_ext>1557</phone_ext>
      <email>mgarolera@cst.cat</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Maria Quintana, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+34937310007</phone>
      <phone_ext>1557</phone_ext>
      <email>mquintana@cst.cat</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Servicio Andaluz Salud</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sevilla</city>
        <zip>41071</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Fermin Mayoral, PhD, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+34687952521</phone>
      <email>fermin.mayoral.sspa@juntadeandalucia.es</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Pilar Barnestein, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+34951290310</phone>
      <email>pilar.barnestein@ibima.eu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Blekinge Institute of Technology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Karlskrona</city>
        <state>Blekinge</state>
        <zip>37179</zip>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Johan Sanmartin Berglund, Professor, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+46455385471</phone>
      <email>johan.sanmartin.berglund@bth.se</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Peter Anderberg, Ass. Prof, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+46455385436</phone>
      <email>peter.anderberg@bth.se</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Czechia</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.smart4md.eu</url>
    <description>Project website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 26, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 26, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 30, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 26, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 26, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 30, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Blekinge Institute of Technology</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Johan Sanmartin Berglund</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, MD, PhD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mild dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>Cognitive impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>Informal caregiver</keyword>
  <keyword>Aging</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>Health application</keyword>
  <keyword>Information and communication technology (ICT)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

