<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03323749</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SPIMM-301</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03323749</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Trial to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Elamipretide in Subjects With Primary Mitochondrial Myopathy Followed by an Open-Label Extension</brief_title>
  <acronym>MMPOWER-3</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase 3 Randomized, Double-Blind, Parallel-Group, Placebo-Controlled Trial to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Daily Subcutaneous Injections of Elamipretide in Subjects With Primary Mitochondrial Myopathy Followed by an Open-Label Treatment Extension</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stealth BioTherapeutics Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stealth BioTherapeutics Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter phase 3 randomized, double-blind, parallel-group, placebo-controlled
      trial to evaluate the safety and efficacy of daily subcutaneous injections of elamipretide in
      subjects with primary mitochondrial myopathy. This will be followed by an open-label
      treatment extension.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 27, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in distance walked on the six minute walk test (6MWT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 24 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in total fatigue score on the on the Primary Mitochondrial Myopathy Symptom Assessment (PMMSA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Each individual item score ranges from 1 (none) to 4 (severe). The total fatigue score ranges from 4-16. Lower values represent a better outcome. The total fatigue score is the sum of question 1 through question 4 on the Primary Mitochondrial Myopathy Symptom Assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in fatigue during activities score on the Primary Mitochondrial Disease Symptom Assessment (PMMSA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Each individual item score ranges from 1 (none) to 4 (severe). Lower values represent a better outcome. The total fatigue during activities score is the sum of question 2 and question 4 on the Primary Mitochondrial Myopathy Symptom Assessment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the Neuro-QoL Fatigue Item Bank score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Each individual item score ranges from 1-5. Total raw score for the entire item bank ranges from 19-95. Raw scores will be calibrated using Item Response Theory Model. Lower values represent a better outcome. Individual items will be summed to calculate total scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the most bothersome symptom score on the Primary Mitochondrial Myopathy Symptoms Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The item score rangers from 1 (none) to 4 (severe). Lower values represent a better outcome. The most bothersome score is the average of the identified most bothersome symptom of the Primary Mitochondrial Myopathy Symptom Assessment by each subject.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate safety and tolerability through incidence of treatment emergent adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 28 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Part 2: Evaluate the long term safety and tolerability of elamipretide using the elamipretide delivery system through incidence of treatment emergent adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Starting at week 24 up to 144 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">202</enrollment>
  <condition>Primary Mitochondrial Myopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: Elamipretide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be randomized to receive either elamipretide or placebo for 24 weeks. For the elamipretide arm, subjects will administer daily 40 mg (0.5mL) subcutaneous injections of elamipretide.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be randomized to receive either elamipretide or placebo for 24 weeks. For the placebo arm, subjects will administer daily 40 mg (0.5 mL) subcutaneous injections of placebo for 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: Elamipretide open label</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Once subjects complete part 1, and meet continuation criteria, they will have the option to continue into an open-label treatment extension. Subjects will receive 40 mg (0.5 mL) subcutaneous injections of elamipretide for up to 144 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>elamipretide</intervention_name>
    <description>40 mg of elamipretide administered as once daily 0.5 mL subcutaneous injections for 24 weeks using the elamipretide delivery system</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: Elamipretide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MTP-131</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo comparator</intervention_name>
    <description>40 mg of placebo administered as once daily 0.5 mL subcutaneous injections for 24 weeks using the elamipretide delivery system</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Combination Product</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>elamipretide open label treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>40 mg of elamipretide administered as once daily 0.5 mL subcutaneous injections for up to 144 weeks using the elamipretide delivery system</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: Elamipretide open label</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        PART 1:

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Willing and able to provide a signed informed consent form prior to participation in
             any trial-related procedures

          -  Agrees to adhere to the trial requirements for the length of the trial, including the
             use of the elamipretide delivery system

          -  Subject is ≥ 16 and ≤ 80 years of age

          -  Enrolled in SPIMM-300

          -  Diagnosed with PMM in the opinion of the investigator

          -  Woman of childbearing potential must agree to use a highly effective method of birth
             control

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has myopathic signs and or/symptoms due to a neuropathic process or gait
             problem that would interfere with the 6MWT, in the opinion of the Investigator

          -  Female who are pregnant, planning to become pregnant, or breastfeeding/lactating

          -  At Screening, the estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) &lt; 30 mL/min/1.73 m^2

          -  Subject has undergone an in-patient hospitalization within the 30 days prior to the
             Baseline Visit or has a planned hospitalization or a surgical procedure during the
             trial.

          -  Subject has clinically significant cardiac disease or prior interventional procedure
             and/or respiratory disease (medical history or current clinical findings) within 3
             months of the Baseline Visit, in the opinion of the Investigator.

          -  Subject has QTc elongation (using the correction factor utilized at the clinical site)
             defined as a QTc &gt;450 msec in male subjects and &gt;480 msec in female subjects.

          -  ECG evidence of acute ischemia, atrial fibrillation, or active conduction system
             abnormalities with the exception of any of the following:

               1. First degree AV-block

               2. Second degree AV-block Type 1 (Mobitz Type 1 / Wenckebach type)

               3. Right bundle branch block

          -  Subject has severe vision impairment that, in the opinion of the Investigator, may
             interfere with their ability to complete all trial requirements

          -  Subject has a seizure disorder that, in the opinion of the Investigator, may interfere
             with their ability to complete all trial requirements.

          -  Active malignancy or any other cancer from which the subject has been disease-free for
             &lt; 2 years.

          -  Subject has a solid organ transplant and/or is currently receiving treatment with
             therapy for immunosuppression, in the opinion of the Investigator.

          -  Subject has been previously diagnosed with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV),
             hepatitis B, or hepatitis C infection.

          -  Subject has a history of a systemic eosinophilic illness and/or an eosinophil count
             &gt;1,000 cells x10^6/L at the Screening Visit.

          -  Subject is currently participating or has participated in an interventional clinical
             trial (i.e.,investigational product or device, stem cell therapy, gene therapy) within
             30 days of the Baseline Visit; or is currently enrolled in a non-interventional
             clinical trial (except for SPIMM-300) at the Baseline Visit which, in the opinion of
             the Investigator, may be potentially confounding with results of the current trial
             (e.g., exercise therapy trial).

          -  Subject has previously received elamipretide (MTP-131), for any reason.

          -  Subject has a history of active substance abuse during the year before the Baseline
             Visit, in the opinion of the Investigator.

          -  Subject has any prior or current medical condition that, in the judgment of the
             Investigator, would prevent the subject from safely participating in and/or completing
             all trial requirements.

        PART 2:

        Continuation Criteria:

          -  Subjects must continue to be able and willing to adhere to the trial requirements.

          -  Subject is appropriate to continue in Part 2 (i.e. subject was compliant in Part 1),
             in the opinion of the Investigator.

          -  Subject has not had a serious adverse event (SAE)/serious adverse device effect (SADE)
             attributed to the elamipretide delivery system.

          -  Subject has not permanently discontinued the elamipretide delivery system.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Akron Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Akron</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44308</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Philadelphia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Health Science Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Seattle Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98105</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 12, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 24, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">October 27, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Myopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>PMD</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary Mitochondrial Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>MTP-131</keyword>
  <keyword>elamipretide</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mitochondrial Myopathies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

