<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02982122</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>COGITATE</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02982122</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>CPPopt Guided Therapy: Assessment of Target Effectiveness</brief_title>
  <acronym>COGITATE</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Clinical Trial Assessing the Effect of &quot;Optimal&quot; Cerebral Perfusion Pressure Monitoring in the Management of Severe Traumatic Brain Injury</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Maastricht University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>European Society of Intensive Care Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maastricht University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Despite improvements in management, mortality in severe traumatic brain injury (TBI) remains
      25% and only 40% of patients survive without major handicap. Medical/surgical interventions
      aim to maintain adequate brain perfusion, which is critically dependent on cerebral perfusion
      pressure (CPP); calculated as the difference between mean arterial pressure (MAP) and
      intracranial pressure (ICP). Current guidelines aim for a CPP above 50 mmHg, based on
      population means. However, this 'one size fits all' approach is flawed, because the relation
      between CPP and brain perfusion varies between individuals. Further, this approach takes no
      account of autoregulation, a key protective mechanism that maintains cerebral perfusion
      despite CPP fluctuations.

      Autoregulation is variably preserved following TBI, and there are large between patient
      variances in the 'optimal' CPP (CPPopt) at which autoregulation operates best. Individual
      CPPopt can be retrieved automatically by plotting autoregulation data against the CPP over a
      certain time window. The investigators have shown that maintenance of CPP close to CPPopt is
      associated with improved outcomes. These data pose the hypothesis that optimisation of
      management in individuals may be achieved by using the zone of optimal autoregulation as a
      basis for defining individualised CPP targets.

      The investigators propose, together with collaborators in the CPPopt study group (Maastricht,
      Cambridge, Leuven and Aachen) to set up a pilot (multicenter) feasibility study to develop a
      protocol for a definitive outcome randomized controlled trial (RCT). This study aims to
      develop protocols for CPPopt guided critical care, and show that they maintain patients
      closer to their optimum perfusion levels than standard protocols which keep above a
      population CPP threshold of 60 mmHg.

      Hence, the main objective is to offer clinicians monitoring and therapy algorithms that
      achieve individualized optimal CPPopt targets and potentially improve TBI outcome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of monitoring time with measured CPP within 5 mmHg of calculated CPPopt</measure>
    <time_frame>First 5 days during intensive care unit admission</time_frame>
    <description>Main feasible endpoint: In pilot studies, we showed that, on average, patients spent a mean (+SD) of 30% ( 8%) of their monitored time with measured CPP within 5 mmHg of CPPopt. The study will be powered to target an increase in this metric to 50% of monitored time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Intensity Level (TIL) score</measure>
    <time_frame>First 5 days during intensive care unit admission</time_frame>
    <description>Main safety secondary endpoint: A change in daily TIL score of &gt; 3 is representative of a clinical significant escalation of TBI treatment from basic ICP management to second tier therapies known to carry risk of harm and therefore is expected to represent a clinically significant potentially harmful effect of CPPopt guided management.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</condition>
  <condition>Cerebrovascular Circulation</condition>
  <condition>Homeostasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CPPopt intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients are managed according to Brain Trauma Foundation guidelines, except for CPP where the CPPopt is targeted.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CPP control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients are managed according to Brain Trauma Foundation guidelines with CPP between 60 and 70 mmHg.
CPPopt information is recorded but hidden for the treating clinicians.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>For both groups, CPP targets will be achieved first by ICP control if this is raised and then by ABP support by titration (up or down) of vasopressors and fluids according to local protocols.</intervention_name>
    <description>For both groups, CPP targets will be achieved first by ICP control if this is raised and then by ABP support by titration (up or down) of vasopressors and fluids according to local protocols.</description>
    <arm_group_label>CPPopt intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>CPP control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Any adult severe TBI patient requiring multimodality monitoring and ICP-directed
             therapy for at least 24 hrs on the assessment of the recruiting team.

          -  Start randomization within 24 hrs after ICU admission.

          -  Deferred informed consent or deferred proxy assent from relatives/legal representative
             (consultee).

          -  Exception for enrolling a patient past the 24 hour window: A patient who is admitted
             to the hospital and later experiences neuro-worsening that is not due to a systemic
             insult, (e.g. myocardial infarction, arrhythmia, pulmonary embolus, systemic
             hemorrhage) but due to a presumptive intracranial cause, and subsequently requires an
             ICP monitor, may be screened for enrolment. Consent, randomization, and monitor
             placement must be done within 48 hours from injury in order for the patient to
             qualify.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients &lt; 18 years old.

          -  Known pregnancy.

          -  Moribund at presentation (e.g. bilaterally absent pupillary responses)

          -  Patients with primary decompressive craniectomy.

          -  Patients already enrolled in &gt; 2 other research studies.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Roekaerts, professor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Maastricht University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marcel Aries, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0031-6-18473154</phone>
    <email>marcel.aries@mumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ari Ercole, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0044-7971449296</phone>
    <email>ae105@cam.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Academic Hospital Leuven</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Geert Meyfroidt, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>geert.meyfroidt@uzleuven.be</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Bart Depreitere, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>bart.depreitere@uzleuven.be</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Addenbrooke's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cambridge</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ari Ercole, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>ae105@cam.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Joseph Donnelly, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>donnelly87@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Aries MJ, Wesselink R, Elting JW, Donnelly J, Czosnyka M, Ercole A, Maurits NM, Smielewski P. Enhanced Visualization of Optimal Cerebral Perfusion Pressure Over Time to Support Clinical Decision Making. Crit Care Med. 2016 Oct;44(10):e996-9. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0000000000001816.</citation>
    <PMID>27270178</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zuercher P, Groen JL, Aries MJ, Steyerberg EW, Maas AI, Ercole A, Menon DK. Reliability and Validity of the Therapy Intensity Level Scale: Analysis of Clinimetric Properties of a Novel Approach to Assess Management of Intracranial Pressure in Traumatic Brain Injury. J Neurotrauma. 2016 Oct 1;33(19):1768-1774. Epub 2016 Feb 11.</citation>
    <PMID>26866876</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Donnelly J, Aries MJ, Czosnyka M. Further understanding of cerebral autoregulation at the bedside: possible implications for future therapy. Expert Rev Neurother. 2015 Feb;15(2):169-85. doi: 10.1586/14737175.2015.996552. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25614952</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Aries MJ, Czosnyka M, Budohoski KP, Steiner LA, Lavinio A, Kolias AG, Hutchinson PJ, Brady KM, Menon DK, Pickard JD, Smielewski P. Continuous determination of optimal cerebral perfusion pressure in traumatic brain injury. Crit Care Med. 2012 Aug;40(8):2456-63. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0b013e3182514eb6.</citation>
    <PMID>22622398</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 23, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 30, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 5, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 25, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 25, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Injuries, Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vasoconstrictor Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

