<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02989246</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CHLA-14-00473</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02989246</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effort of Breathing Guided Ventilator Protocol</brief_title>
  <acronym>EOBvent</acronym>
  <official_title>Effort of Breathing Guided Ventilator Management for Children Using Pressure Rate Product: a Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot study tests the feasibility of using a computerized ventilator management protocol
      seeking to encourage lung protective ventilation during the acute phase of ventilation, and
      esophageal manometry based titration of ventilator settings during the weaning phase of
      ventilation, for children with acute respiratory failure. The investigators hypothesize that
      such an approach will reduce time on mechanical ventilation, largely by preserving diaphragm
      muscle function.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives: This pilot study will help refine a computer based ventilator management protocol
      which will be used in both acute and weaning phases of ventilation for children with acute
      respiratory failure. The acute phase protocol is an adaptation of the Acute Respiratory
      Distress Syndrome Network protocol for pediatrics, and the weaning phase involves an
      esophageal manometry guided weaning protocol based on effort of breathing. The investigators
      seek to test the safety and feasibility of the protocol recommendations and the software
      system , and help determine the potential effect size of the intervention to determine
      feasibility of a randomized controlled trial. They also seek to determine the feasibility and
      reproducibility of serial diaphragm ultrasound measurements on mechanically ventilated
      children.

      Study Population: All children intubated and mechanically ventilated in the Children's
      Hospital Los Angeles Pediatric ICU with an anticipated length of intubation &gt; 48 hours will
      be eligible, with some exclusion criteria based on ability to perform the measurements.

      Study methodology: After consent, an esophageal catheter will be placed. A software
      management tool for ventilator management will be placed at the bedside for each enrolled
      patient, and recommendations regarding changing ventilator support will be provided to the
      clinicians every several hours during both acute and weaning phases. When ventilator support
      is below a threshold, recommendations will be made to perform spontaneous breathing trials.
      The clinicians will ultimately decide whether to accept or reject the recommendations, and
      will evaluate the patient before each potential change to the ventilator. The acceptance or
      rejection of recommendations will be tracked, and used to refine the intervention. Daily
      diaphragm ultrasound measurements will also be obtained to monitor diaphragm thickness and
      contractile activity.

      Follow up: Clinical outcomes will be followed while in the ICU including re-intubation,
      medications administered, and ICU length of stay. No follow up after ICU discharge is
      planned.

      Analysis plans: Data will be used to refine the intervention, test the acceptability of
      protocol recommendations to bedside providers, and determine sample size estimates for a
      follow up randomized controlled trial. These analyses will be descriptive. A pilot of 40
      patients is anticipated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 1, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 18, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Protocol Recommendations which are accepted by the clinical provider</measure>
    <time_frame>With each protocol recommendation, approximately every 4 hours during the course of mechanical ventilation (up to 28 days)</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will track the percentage of recommendations which are accepted by providers, as well as the reasons why recommendations were not accepted</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Ventilators, Mechanical</condition>
  <condition>Work of Breathing</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ventilator management using the proposed protocol in both acute and weaning phases. Patients will be managed according the the Ventilator protocol using the esophageal catheter for the weaning phase</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ventilator protocol</intervention_name>
    <description>Open loop ventilator management by a computer based protocol</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Esophageal Catheter</intervention_name>
    <description>Esophageal manometry measurements of patient effort of breathing will be used to guide the protocol recommendations</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Intubated and mechanically ventilated patients in the Children's Hospital Los Angeles
             Pediatric ICU

          -  Anticipated length of intubation &gt; 48 hours.

          -  The primary attending physician approves use of the protocol on the patient.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Corrected gestational age less than 37 weeks

          -  Contraindications to nasoesophageal catheter placement (nasopharyngeal or esophageal
             abnormalities) or Respiratory Inductance Plethysmography bands (abdominal wall defects
             such as omphalocele).

          -  Significant lower airway obstruction (asthma or bronchiolitis), confirmed by
             ventilator spirometry
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>37 Weeks</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robinder Khemani, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Hospital Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Los Angeles</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90027</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 6, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 7, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 12, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 6, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 6, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pediatrics</keyword>
  <keyword>ventilator weaning</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Aspiration</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

