<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02986477</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>00118038</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02986477</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Applications of Contrast-Enhanced Ultrasonography in Pediatric Population - Intravesicle Administration</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Applications of Contrast-Enhanced Ultrasonography in Pediatric Population - Intravesicle Administration</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johns Hopkins University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In children, specifically the intravesicle administration to study vesicoureteral reflux in
      children already catheterized and scheduled for voiding cystourethrogram (VCUG).
      Contrast-enhanced ultrasonography is a tremendous advancement from conventional B-mode and
      color Doppler ultrasonography, as it permits noninvasive, non-ionizing delineation of
      physiology and pathophysiology with higher resolution and accuracy in children. The technique
      is particularly useful in pediatric population whose lifetime risk of cancer significantly
      increases with higher frequency of ionizing radiation. Voiding cystourethrogram is a
      fluoroscopy technique that can study reflux real time but at the risk of radiation side
      effects. In this regard, intravesicle administration of ultrasound contrast agent can help
      avoid radiation in children and potentially replace the conventionally used voiding
      cystourethrogram.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The most commonly used genitourinary application of ultrasound contrast agent is for the
      diagnosis of vesicoureteral reflux via intra-vesicle administration of contrast agent. The
      utility of ultrasound contrast agent in contrast-enhanced voiding urosonography is well
      established and published over two decades (Darge 2002, Darge 2008, Darge 2010). As with
      other applications of ultrasound contrast agents, the method offers the advantages of no
      radiation, low cost, excellent anatomic detail, and higher sensitivity for reflux detection
      than VCUG. The most comprehensive study to detail the safety profile of intravesicle
      ultrasound contrast is by Papadopoulou et al. (Papadopoulou, Ntoulia et al. 2014) which
      described a total of 1,010 children (563 girls, 447 boys) with a mean age of 2.9 years. No
      adverse events were reported at 1 hour after exam. Follow-up phone interviews revealed no
      adverse events in the majority (973 of 1,010). The remaining 37 children experienced mild
      symptoms including dysuria (n=26) and urinary retention (n=2) which may have been related to
      catheterization rather than the contrast agent. A recent European survey at 29 centers
      evaluating the use of ultrasound contrast agent in 4,131 children for pediatric reflux
      diagnosis reported no adverse events (Riccabona 2012).

      The procedure consists of pre-contrast, post-contrast, voiding phase, and post-void depiction
      of the kidneys, ureters, bladder, and transperineal scan of the urethra, for identification
      of potential ectopic ureters (Darge 2008, Duran, del Riego et al. 2012) that can easily be
      missed on non-distended ureters on CT, MRI, or radionuclide imaging. The two primary methods
      of contrast injection includes direct injection into a partially filled bladder (Darge 2008)
      and another using a saline bag for subsequent drip infusion via the catheter into the bladder
      (Back, Edgar et al. 2015).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    PI leaving institution
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 9, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 9, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Applications of Contrast-Enhanced Ultrasonography in Pediatric Population - Intravesicle Administration</measure>
    <time_frame>10 years</time_frame>
    <description>The presence of vesicoureteral reflux is assessed as the primary outcome measure.
Qualitative evaluation is performed to assess the presence of contrast within the collecting systems, which then correlates with vesicoureteral reflux.
Since this is a qualitative evaluation based on the acquired radiologic images, there is no unit, but the degree of vesicoureteral reflux is assessed. Vesicoureteral reflux is graded into I to V grades based on the severity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Vesico-Ureteral Reflux</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Contrast Ultrasound</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with vesicoureteral reflux will receive contrast ultrasound via Foley catheter for study of vesicoureteral reflux.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Contrast Ultrasound</intervention_name>
    <description>For diagnostic purposes, intravesicle administration of contrast ultrasound agent will be performed to study vesicoureteral reflux.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Contrast Ultrasound</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female patients aged 0-17 years undergoing an ultrasound for a clinical
             indication at the Johns Hopkins Hospital

          -  Willing to either extend a previously scheduled clinically indicated voiding
             cystourethrogram

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known or suspected right-to-left, bi-directional, or transient right-to-left cardiac
             shunts

          -  History of hypersensitivity reactions to sulfur hexafluoride lipid microsphere
             components or to any of the inactive ingredients in LUMASON. Inactive ingredients
             include 1,2-Dipalmitoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphoglycerol, sodium salt (DPPG), a minor
             (1-2%) component normally present in most cell membranes,
             Diasteroylphosphatidylcholine (DSPC), a commonly used synthetic phospholipids, and
             palmitic acid, the most commonly found fatty acid in animals.

          -  Patient subjects in unstable clinical condition.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 5, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 7, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 8, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vesico-Ureteral Reflux</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

