<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01264120</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PB-PG-0909-20178 NIHR</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01264120</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Impact of a Bariatric Rehabilitation Service on Patient Outcomes</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Impact of a Bariatric Rehabilitation Service on Weight Loss and Psychological Adjustment.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Surrey</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Western Sussex Hospitals NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute for Health Research, United Kingdom</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Surrey</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obesity is a major health problem that is affecting more and more people's lives. One of the
      most successful treatments for obesity is weight loss surgery. Not all patients, however,
      lose the desired amount of weight, some regain weight and some have the surgery reversed.
      Interviews with patients and discussions with patient support groups indicate that many of
      the 'unsuccessful' patients feel unprepared for the operation and describe how although the
      surgery fixes their body it neglects their mind. They would therefore like to have more
      psychological support.

      The present study aims to set up and evaluate a health psychology led bariatric
      rehabilitation service (BRS) and determine the impact of such a service on patient outcomes
      following surgery. The BRS would offer information, support and mentoring pre and post
      surgery and address psychological issues such as dietary control, self esteem, coping and
      emotional eating. It is predicted that a bariatric rehabilitation service would primarily
      improve weight loss following surgery but would also aid changes in other aspects of the
      patient's well being.

      Obesity is a risk factor for a multitude of illnesses such as heart disease, diabetes and
      cancer. If effective, obesity surgery improves a patient's health and reduces their need for
      NHS care. If unsuccessful then the costs include not only subsequent NHS costs due to these
      other illnesses but also the costs of the unsuccessful operation and the emotional cost to
      the patient. The bariatric rehabilitation service should help to improve the effectiveness of
      surgery which in the longer term is likely to be cost effective.

      This research is a direct response to the needs identified by patients and by offering a more
      comprehensive bariatric service the success and subsequent health and well being of obese
      patients should be improved.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Design: The study will involve a trial (open randomised parallel group control trial) with
      patients allocated to receive either usual care or the bariatric rehabilitation service (BRS)
      pre and post bariatric (obesity) surgery. Follow up measures will be recorded at 3, 6 and 12
      months post-surgery at routine follow-up clinics. In addition, qualitative interviews will be
      carried out with 20 participants from both arms of the trial (BRS n=10; usual care n=10).

      Piloting: The contents of the bariatric service and the follow up measures are based on pilot
      work. This pilot work has already been completed exploring what bariatric patients want and
      why bariatric surgery either fails or succeeds from the patients' perspective. Furthermore,
      pilot research has explored the impact of bariatric surgery on changes in mood, cognitions
      and eating behaviours. The quantitative measures and qualitative responses derived from these
      studies will form the basis of the intervention and the measures for the present study.

      Sample: St Richard's Hospital in Chichester, West Sussex offers a NHS based bariatric service
      for obese patients with a BMI over 40 (or 35 with serious co morbidities). This is the
      largest centre in the UK, with 600 patients per year receiving a bariatric operation at this
      clinic (70% being a primary bypass and 20% bands (the remaining 10% are revisions)). Patients
      will be recruited if they have been approved for surgery and had their date set for their
      operation. The consultant surgeon, Mr Chris Pring is a collaborator on this proposal.

      Procedure: Ethical approval will be in place before the start of the project. In the week
      before their operation patients attend the bariatric clinic for routine tests. When patients
      are sent their appointment letters they will be sent the information sheet along with it to
      give them approximately 2 weeks to think about whether they would like to take part. At the
      appointment patients will see the researcher who will explain the trial, obtain consent and
      randomly allocate the patient to either the usual care condition or the bariatric
      rehabilitation service (BRS) condition.

      Randomisation: All patients who fulfil the inclusion criteria will be approached by the
      researcher, asked to read an information sheet and if interested offered a written consent
      form. Once a patient is consented the researcher will contact the clinical trial unit at
      Surrey University who will provide third party blinded randomization to either the BRS or
      usual care.

      Timeline: The study will take 34 months. New patients will be recruited over a 12 month
      period and followed up for 12 months postoperatively. The first 6 months will involve
      preparation, setting up procedures for data collection and training the health psychologist.
      The next 25 months will involve rolling out the intervention, recruitment, randomly
      allocating patients to the 2 conditions, providing the BRS and collecting data on the
      evaluation of service. At 18 months the 20 interviews will take place and be transcribed. The
      final 3 months will be spent analyzing the data, assessing cost-effectiveness, disseminating
      the results to patients and health professionals and writing up findings for publication.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Enrolling by invitation</last_known_status>
  <start_date>September 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in weight and BMI</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3, 6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The weight and height of patients will be obtained to determine BMI change over the duration of the intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in psychological measures</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3,6 and 12 months.</time_frame>
    <description>The secondary outcome measure is the impact of the BRS on patients' quality of life, dietary control, coping strategies and emotional eating.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of the intervention</time_frame>
    <description>The cost-effectiveness of the intervention will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">290</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Bariatric Surgery Candidate</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Health Psychology Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A 50 minute health psychology behavioural intervention with sessions pre-surgery, post-surgery and at 3 month follow up.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group receive usual care through the bariatric surgery process.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health Psychology Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The health psychology intervention will involve a bariatric rehabilitation service (BRS) which will involve those allocated to the intervention receiving usual care plus three 50 minute sessions with a health psychologist pre-operatively (1 week before surgery), perioperatively (before they are discharged from hospital) and at 3 month follow up.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Health Psychology Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Bariatric rehabilitation</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  if they consent

          -  aged 18 or over

          -  have attended the bariatric clinic at Chichester

          -  been accepted for surgery

          -  have funding in place for surgery (i.e. their primary care trust has agreed to pay for
             their surgery).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  those who do not wish to take part in the randomisation

          -  those who do not wish to take part in the intervention

          -  those who will not be having bariatric surgery because they are not a suitable patient

          -  those who will not be having bariatric surgery because they can not secure funding
             from their primary care trust for the surgery

          -  those who cannot effectively read or speak English, as this would pose a difficulty in
             implementing the intervention and for data collection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jane Ogden, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Surrey</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St Richards Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chichester</city>
        <state>West Sussex</state>
        <zip>PO19 6SE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hollywood A, Ogden J, Pring C. The impact of a bariatric rehabilitation service on weight loss and psychological adjustment--study protocol. BMC Public Health. 2012 Apr 5;12:275. doi: 10.1186/1471-2458-12-275.</citation>
    <PMID>22480247</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 16, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 20, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 21, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 23, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 23, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 24, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Bariatric surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Psychology</keyword>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>March 23, 2016</submitted>
    <returned>April 22, 2016</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

