<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01269944</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>dGEMRIC HTO</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01269944</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Osteotomies Around the Knee on Cartilage Glycosaminoglycan Content Using dGEMRIC Non-invasive Imaging</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Osteotomies Around the Knee on Cartilage Glycosaminoglycan Content Using dGEMRIC Non-invasive Imaging, a Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>UMC Utrecht</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>UMC Utrecht</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Medial compartment osteoarthritis of the knee is commonly treated by a surgical intervention
      called 'high tibial osteotomy' (VTO). Although it has repeatedly been shown that pain
      improves following this procedure, it is unknown how cartilage quality is affected by the
      procedure. In this study, a recently developed MRI technique is used to evaluate changes in
      cartilage quality before and after the surgery. Changes in MRI signals are correlated to
      subjective improvements (score lists). 10 patients participate in this study. Approval has
      been granted by the Medical Ethical Committee of the University Medical Center Utrecht. All
      participants are required to give informed consent before participation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Medial compartment osteoarthritis (OA) of the knee is an invalidating disorder and
      leads to pain, decreased range of motion and inactivity. Two procedures aiming at maintaining
      original cartilage are the high tibial osteotomy (HTO) and the femur osteotomy. However,
      effects of this procedure on cartilage quality are not known.

      Recently, a new technique has been developed which enables analysing changes in cartilage
      composition in vivo: the dGEMRIC. The dGEMRIC-technique is based on binding of negatively
      charged contrast agent Gadolinium (Gd(DPTA)2) to the glycosaminoglycans in the knee
      cartilage. The T1-signal reflects the gadolinium uptake by the proteoglycans of the knee and
      thus provides us with an indicative parameter of the cartilage quality. Visualising changes
      in cartilage composition enables better pre-operative patient selection as well as optimal
      timing of the operative procedure.

      Objective: Primary objective: Evaluate changes in cartilage glycosaminoglycan content using
      dGEMRIC, in patients with osteoarthritis of the knee undergoing axial correction (HTO, femur
      osteotomy). Secondary objective: Correlate quantitative MRI data to subjective symptom scores
      (KOOS, WOMAC, VAS, Knee Society Score)

      Study design: This study is a prospective observational study.

      Study population: Ten patients will be included satisfying the following inclusion criteria:

        -  Both males and females older than 18 years

        -  Indication as set by treating physician for operative procedure around the knee: HTO
           (high tibial osteotomy), femoral osteotomy

      Main study parameters/endpoints: In addition to their regular treatment, patients will
      receive an MRI scan with dGEMRIC settings before and 9 months after the surgical procedure,
      after removal of orthopaedic hardware. They will further receive questionnaires (VAS, WOMAC,
      KOOS, Knee Society Scale) before the surgical procedure and at 6,12, and 24 months after the
      surgical procedure.

      Nature and extent of the burden and risks associated with participation, benefit and group
      relatedness: In addition to their regular treatment, patients participating in this study
      will undergo two MRI scans of their knee. Performing of these scans will take about 4 hours.
      Further, orthopaedic hardware will be removed in daycare before the second MRI (burden: 1
      day). Patients are asked to fill out questionnaires before- and after their surgical
      treatment. Filling out these questionnaires will take around 20 minutes per time moment (4 in
      total). Risks associated with the MRI scan are the very infrequently occurring allergic
      reactions to the contrast agent, which is used to depict the cartilage. Risks associated with
      removal of orthopaedic hardware at 9 months and not different than removal of hardware at a
      later stage: infection, bleeding, allergic reaction, dental damage or paresthesias.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MRI T1 signal, change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline 9 months after surgery (HTO)</time_frame>
    <description>MRI T1 signal is deducted from dGEMRIC measurements</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>KOOS clinical score, change from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline 9 months after surgery (HTO)</time_frame>
    <description>Knee and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (clinical score, completed by all participants)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Medial Compartment Osteoarthritis of the Knee</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Medial compartment knee osteoarthritis</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients with medial compartment osteoarthritis of the knee, as proven by x-rays and clinical examination</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients above 18 years with osteoarthritis of the knee and a future planned osteotomy
        of the tibia or femur are eligible for participation in this study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Ten patients will be included satisfying the following inclusion criteria:

          -  Both males and females

          -  Patients &gt;18 years old

          -  Indication as set by treating physician for operative procedure around the knee: HTO
             (high tibial osteotomy), femoral osteotomy

          -  Patient informed consent signed Note: Patients with previous surgery, history of
             intra-articular medication, meniscectomy or ACL lesions can be included in this study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The following patients are excluded from participating in this study:

          -  Known anaphylactic reactions to Gadolinium or related substances

          -  Kidney diseases with a creatinin excretion of &lt; 20 ml/min

          -  Risk groups for MRI scanning due to magnetic field or contrast agent (9, 10): Metal in
             body: Pacemaker / AICD / ICD (coronary defibrillator), Nervus vagus (X) stimulator,
             Artificial heart valve (depending on type), Metal clips on cerebral arteries or veins,
             Metal particles in eye, Port-a-cath, Metal stents, Hydrocephalic pump / insuline pump,
             Metal implants; f/e screws, prostheses, piercings.

          -  Claustrofibia

          -  First three months of pregnancy (not sufficient information available about effects of
             contrast agent on foetal development in this stage). Patients will be asked if they
             may be pregnant (&lt; 3 months of pregnancy): if uncertain, they will be excluded.

        Contra-indications for MRI scanning, as well as contra-indications to intra-venous
        administration of contrast agents were discussed with Ms. Shanta Kalaykhan-Sewradj, head of
        MRI technicians in the UMC Utrecht. For further information, the booklet 'Bijwerkingen van
        contrastmiddelen: de gadoliniumverbindingen' by Esther Ensing and Janet Hoven was used
        (Published by Nederlandse Vereniging voor Slachtoffers van Medische Contrastmiddelen,
        2004).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel B Saris, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University Medical Center Utrecht, the Netherlands</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Center Utrecht</name>
      <address>
        <city>Utrecht</city>
        <zip>3584 CX</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.umcutrecht.nl</url>
    <description>Affiliation site</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burstein D. Tracking longitudinal changes in knee degeneration and repair. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2009 Feb;91 Suppl 1:51-3. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.H.01412.</citation>
    <PMID>19182025</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brouwer RW, Bierma-Zeinstra SM, van Koeveringe AJ, Verhaar JA. Patellar height and the inclination of the tibial plateau after high tibial osteotomy. The open versus the closed-wedge technique. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 2005 Sep;87(9):1227-32.</citation>
    <PMID>16129748</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 29, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 3, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 4, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>UMC Utrecht</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>D.B.F. Saris</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. dr.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>osteoarthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>knee</keyword>
  <keyword>high wedge tibial osteotomy</keyword>
  <keyword>dGEMRIC</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis, Knee</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

