<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01260597</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0002</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R21CA14156801</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01260597</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tobacco Quit Line Re-enrollments for the Underserved</brief_title>
  <official_title>Re-engagement in Evidence-based Quit Line Treatment for Low Income Smokers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alere Wellbeing</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Indiana University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Alere Wellbeing</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this proposed study is to develop, refine and test the use of Interactive
      Voice Response (IVR) technology as a means of increasing re-engagement of low income smokers
      in telephone support for tobacco cessation (quit lines). If this strategy proves to be
      acceptable and feasible, it may offer a technological solution to increase access to and
      utilization of a widely available evidence-based form of behavioral treatment for low income
      smokers.

      The primary aims of this research are to:

        1. Develop an IVR system that delivers tailored audio messages to increase low income
           smokers' re-engagement in treatment offered by two state quit lines (Washington and
           Indiana). The investigators will develop: a) a menu of audio messages that can be
           delivered by an IVR system; b) an IVR algorithm (i.e., a set of decision rules) to make
           proactive automated calls to deliver brief, tailored messages for re-engaging low income
           smokers who previously used the quit line.

        2. Evaluate the feasibility and efficacy of an IVR system as a tool to re-engage low income
           smokers into quit line treatment measured by number of IVR calls answered, number of
           smokers who re-engage in treatment and satisfaction with IVR calls. Hypothesis 2.1 - It
           is hypothesized that the rates of re-engagement into treatment among those receiving the
           IVR intervention will be higher than smokers not proactively invited to re-engage in
           quit line services.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We propose a randomized controlled trial to compare re-engagement into quit line treatment
      between low income smokers receiving IVR intervention to re-engage into treatment through
      quit line services and those receiving usual care (no intervention to re-engage). Subjects
      will be recruited from two state quit lines (Washington (WA) and Indiana (IN)). WA and IN
      were selected because they both contract with Free &amp; Clear for quit line services and have
      supported research collaborations in the past. Both states have agreed to participate in this
      study. Three thousand subjects will be randomized to the intervention or usual care prior to
      entry into the IVR calling database. This sampling frame was defined based in our past
      research experience in using similar method to re-engage low income smokers from ethnic
      populations and assumed a high proportion of invalid phone numbers and difficulties on
      successfully reaching individuals even after several call attempts. In our previous
      re-engagement study, 29% of the phone numbers provided by quit line users were invalid 12
      months later and 38% of the subjects were never reached after five attempted calls.
      Therefore, in this study we are anticipating successfully reaching 30% of the sample.

      This is a feasibility study and the main outcome is re-engagement into treatment, measured by
      re-enrollment into quit line support after receiving the IVR intervention. Process measures
      are IVR calls answered and satisfaction with IVR calls. Thirty-day point prevalence
      abstinence at 6 months after intervention will be also measured, as a way to preliminarily
      evaluate the efficacy of this intervention.

      The target population of this study is low income smokers, defined as being a Medicaid
      recipient or uninsured by the time of their first enrollment into quit line treatment. This
      working definition for eligibility criterion was chosen because health insurance status is
      routinely assessed in the provision of quit line services and it is a good proxy indicator of
      income.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quit line re-enrollment</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate the feasibility and efficacy of an IVR system as a tool to re-engage low income smokers into quit line treatment measured by number of IVR calls answered, number of smokers who re-engage in treatment and satisfaction with IVR calls.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tobacco Abstinence</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Thirty-day point prevalence abstinence at 6 months after intervention will be also measured, as a way to preliminarily evaluate the efficacy of this intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2985</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Life Style Counseling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>For individuals who report being quit, a brief congratulatory message will be delivered, independent of each arm of the study they were randomized to. For individuals who report not being quit and are randomized to the intervention condition, tailored messages are delivered via the IVR system. The automated calls would include an assessment of the individual's interest in another quit attempt and deliver brief, tailored messages to perceived barriers for re-engaging into treatment. The system is programmed to transfer the caller to a live quit line counselor if the individual is willing to re-engage in cessation treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Life Counseling</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>For individuals who report being quit, a brief congratulatory message will be delivered, independent of each arm of the study they were randomized to. For individuals who report still smoking the IVR will thank them for their time and the call will end.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IVR intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>If individuals report having any smoking in the previous 30 days, the IVR will deliver questions to identify barriers to quit line re-enrollment and motivational messages to promote the re-enrollment</description>
    <arm_group_label>Life Style Counseling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IVR control</intervention_name>
    <description>If individuals report any smoking in the last 30 days the IVR will thank them for their time and the call will end</description>
    <arm_group_label>Life Counseling</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Enrolled in Medicaid or uninsured, 18 years or older, able to read and speak English,
             provided verbal consent to be contacted by quit line to follow-up, sought quit line
             services for being primarily a smoker

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Primary use of other forms of tobacco such as smokeless tobacco, not understanding
             English
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Beatriz Carlini, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Free &amp; Clear, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Free &amp; Clear, Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 14, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 14, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 15, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 10, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 10, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 11, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>smoking</keyword>
  <keyword>quit line re-enrollment and IVR systems</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

