<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01266603</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2010-0113</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2011-00282</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01266603</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>High-Dose Interleukin-2 (HDIL-2), Combined With recMAGE-A3 + AS15 ASCI</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Trial of High Dose Interleukin-2 (HDIL-2) With Recombinant MAGE-A3 Protein Combined With Adjuvant System AS15 (recMAGE-A3 + AS15) in Patients With Unresectable or Metastatic Melanoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn if high-dose interleukin-2 (HDIL-2),
      when given in combination with recMAGE-A3 + AS15 ASCI (Antigen-Specific Cancer
      Immunotherapeutic), can help to control unresectable or metastatic melanoma in patients whose
      tumor tissue has the MAGE-A3 protein. The safety of this drug combination will also be
      studied. Researchers will also use samples of the original tumor or metastatic tissue (for
      example, lymph nodes or liver or lung) that are collected during screening to study if
      response to the study drug is related to the genes in the tissue.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Study Drugs:

      HDIL-2 is similar to a hormone naturally found in the body that boosts the immune system by
      helping &quot;natural killer&quot; (NK) cells live longer and work better. NK cells are a type of white
      blood cell that kill other cells, and they may kill cancer cells.

      ASCI is a immunotherapy designed to teach your immune system to fight cancer in the same way
      that you are given vaccines to prevent disease by teaching your immune system to fight an
      infection caused by germs. Because the cancer is made by your own body, the immune system
      does not recognize the cancer cells as being harmful. Your immune system needs to be
      &quot;trained&quot; to recognize the cancer cells. This is done by injecting a protein (the MAGE-A3
      protein) that is found in the tumor and training your body to recognize it and to destroy the
      cells that have this protein. This may increase the effectiveness of IL-2 by slowing the
      growth of the cancer cells, which may cause them to die.

      Study Drug Administration:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will begin the study drugs
      within 14 days of signing the second consent form. To receive the study drugs, you will be
      admitted to the hospital, either in the intensive care unit (ICU) or a specifically
      designated nursing unit where study drugs can be administered, on Day 2 of each cycle and may
      remain in the hospital for up to 7 days each cycle.

      You may receive a total of 24 ASCI doses either in combination with HDIL-2 or alone. You may
      receive the study drugs in combination for up to 30 weeks. After that, you may receive the
      ASCI study medication alone for up to 157 more weeks.

      Cycle 1 is 14 days (Weeks 1 and 2):

        -  On Day 1 of Cycle 1, you will receive the ASCI study medication as an injection. Each
           injection will be given in the muscle of your upper arm or in your thigh. You will be
           watched in the clinic for at least 30 minutes after each injection.

        -  On Day 2 (+/- 2 business days), you will receive HDIL-2 through a catheter (a small
           plastic tube that is put into your vein under your collar bone or in your arm) over 15
           minutes. HDIL-2 treatment will be delayed in cycles 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, or 8 until all
           HDIL-2 related side effects either go away or the study doctor thinks they are under
           control.

      Cycle 2 is 42 days (Weeks 3-8):

        -  On Day 1 of Weeks 3, 5, and 7 (+/- 2 business days) , you will receive the ASCI study
           medication as an injection.

        -  On Day 2 of Week 3 (+/- 2 business days), you will receive HDIL-2 by vein.

      Cycle 3 is 14 days (Weeks 9 and 10):

        -  On Day 1 of Week 9 (+/- 2 business days), you will receive the ASCI study medication as
           an injection.

        -  On Day 2 of Week 9 (+/- 2 business days), you will receive HDIL-2 by vein.

      Cycle 4 is 49 days (Weeks 11-17):

        -  On Day 1 of Weeks 11 and 15 (+/- 2 business days), you will receive the ASCI study
           medication as an injection.

        -  On Day 2 of Week 11 (+/- 2 business days), you will receive HDIL-2 by vein.

      Cycle 5 is 21 days (Weeks 18-20):

        -  On Day 1 of Week 18 (+/- 2 business days), you will receive the ASCI study medication an
           injection.

        -  On Day 2 of Week 18 (+/- 2 business days), you will receive HDIL-2 by vein.

      Cycle 6 is 42 days (Weeks 21-26):

        -  On Day 1 of Weeks 18, 21, and 24 (+/- 2 business days), you will receive the ASCI study
           medication as an injection.

        -  On Day 2 of Weeks 18 and 21 (+/- 2 business days), you will receive HDIL-2 by vein.

      Cycle 7 is 21 days (Weeks 27-29):

        -  On Day 1 of Week 27 (+/- 2 business days), you will receive the ASCI study medication as
           an injection.

        -  On Day 2 of Week 27(+/- 2 business days), you will receive HDIL-2 by vein.

      Cycle 8 is 28 days (Weeks 30-33):

        -  On Day 1 of Week 30 (+/- 2 business days), you will receive the ASCI study medication as
           an injection.

        -  On Day 2 of Week 30 (+/- 2 business days), you will receive HDIL-2 by vein.

      On Day 1 of Weeks 34, 40, 46, 52, 64, 76, 88, and 100 (+/- 2 business days), you will receive
      the ASCI study medication as an injection.

      Study Visits:

      On Day 1 of Weeks 1, 3, 5, 7, 9, 11, 15, 18, 21, 24, 27, and 30 (+/- 2 business days):

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your weight and vital signs.
           °Blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  You will be asked about any side effects you may be having and drugs you are taking.

      On Day 2 of Weeks 1, 3, 5, 7, 9, 11, 18, 21, 27, and 30 (+/- 2 business days):

        -  Blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  You will be asked about any side effects you may be having and drugs you are taking.

      During Weeks 8, 17, 26, 33, 39, 51, 63, 75, 87, 99, 123, 147, 171, and 195 (+/- 1 week):

        -  You will have and a CT scan of your chest, abdomen, and pelvis to check the status of
           the disease.

        -  You will also have an MRI scan or CT scan of the brain to check the status of the
           disease.

        -  You will have photographs of your lesions taken if indicated by your doctor.

      On Day 1 of Weeks 34, 40, 46, 52, 64, 76, 88, 100, 124, 148, 172, and 196 (+/- 2 business
      days):

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your weight and vital signs.

        -  Blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  You will be asked about any side effects you may be having and drugs you are taking.

      Additional Blood Draws:

      Additional blood (about 4 tablespoons each time) will be drawn for laboratory tests to look
      at how the study drug combination may affect the immune system. These blood draws will be
      collected on Day 1 of cycle 1 and again during cycle 1 48 hours after the last dose of IL-2.
      Additional blood draws (about 4 tablespoons each time) will also Part of the blood drawn for
      these tests will be sent to GSK Biologicals (or a contracted laboratory) for testing.

      Length of Study:

      You may continue to receive the study drug combination for up to 8 cycles (33 weeks) and ASCI
      alone for up to 76 more weeks (+/- 2 business days). If you continue beyond completing 8
      cycles of HDIL-2, you will receive the ASCI on Day 1 (+/- 2 business days) every 6 weeks for
      4 doses (weeks 34, 50, 46, and 52), then on Day 1 (+/- 2 business days) every 12 weeks (weeks
      64, 76, 98, and 110) for 4 doses, then on Day 1 (+/- 2 business days) of every 24 weeks
      (Weeks 134, 158, 182, and 187) for 4 doses.

      You will be taken off the study therapy early if the disease gets worse, you experience
      intolerable side effects, or the study doctor thinks it is in your best interest. If you are
      removed from the study because of intolerable side effects, you will be followed weekly by
      either a phone call or clinic visit until the side effect is tolerable.

      End-of-Dosing Visit:

      After receiving the last dose of study drug combination, you will have an end-of-dosing
      visit:

        -  Your medical history will be reviewed and you will be asked about any side effects you
           may be having and drugs you are taking.

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your weight and vital signs.

        -  Blood (about 3 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests and ANA testing.

      Follow-Up Visits:

      You will have follow-up visits after your last dose of study drug, if the disease does not
      get any worse. Starting after the last dose of study drug, you will have 1 visit every 3
      months for the 1st year, every 4 months for the 2nd year, every 6 months for the 3rd and 4th
      year, then once a year for up to 10 years (+/- 2 business days). At these visits, the
      following will be performed:

        -  You will have a physical exam, including measurement of your weight and vital signs.

        -  If the study doctor thinks it is needed, blood (about 2 tablespoons) will be drawn for
           routine tests.

        -  If the study doctor thinks it is needed, you will have a chest x-ray, CT scan of your
           chest, abdomen, and pelvis, and/or MRI scan or CT scan of the brain to check the status
           of the disease.

      If the disease begins to get worse, information about the status of your health will be
      collected every 2 months. If you are not able to come into the clinic to complete this visit,
      you will be asked for this information over the phone. The phone call should last about 10-15
      minutes each time.

      This is an investigational study. IL-2 is commercially available and FDA approved for the
      treatment of metastatic melanoma. HDIL-2 is a higher dose than the standard approved dose of
      IL-2. The ASCI study medication is not FDA approved or commercially available. It is
      currently being used for research purposes only.

      Up to 30 patients will take part in this study. All will be enrolled at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Objective response is either a complete response or a partial response measured at week 8. Tumor response defined by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) solid tumor response criteria by MR or CT.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Melanoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HDIL-2 + recMAGE-A3 + AS15</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HDIL-2 720,000 IU/kg by vein over an approximate 15 minute period every eight hours, for a maximum of 14 doses per cycle. recMAGE-A3 300 μg plus 420 μg of CpG7909 (a part of the Adjuvant System AS15) by intermuscular injection within 24 hours from first dose of HDIL-2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HDIL-2</intervention_name>
    <description>720,000 IU/kg by vein over an approximate 15 minute period every eight hours, for a maximum of 14 doses per cycle.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HDIL-2 + recMAGE-A3 + AS15</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Interleukin-2</other_name>
    <other_name>IL-2</other_name>
    <other_name>Aldesleukin</other_name>
    <other_name>Proleukin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>recMAGE-A3 + AS15</intervention_name>
    <description>300 μg plus 420 μg of CpG7909 (a part of the Adjuvant System AS15) by intermuscular injection within 24 hours from first dose of HDIL-2.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HDIL-2 + recMAGE-A3 + AS15</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Recombinant MAGE-A3 Protein</other_name>
    <other_name>recMAGE-A3 + AS15 ASCI</other_name>
    <other_name>MAGE-A3</other_name>
    <other_name>MAGE-A3 ASCI</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. STEP 1 Written informed consent has been obtained from the patient before the
             performance of any protocol-specific procedure.

          2. Male or female patient with histologically proven, measurable unresectable or
             metastatic cutaneous melanoma

          3. Patient is &gt;/= 18 years of age.

          4. Formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded (FFPE) tumor tissue must be available for MAGE-A3
             expression screening test from cutaneous, subcutaneous, lymph node lesion, lung or
             liver lesion. Archival FFPE tumor tissue can be provided for the MAGE-A3 screening
             test, as long as the FFPE tumor tissue was obtained from a biopsy or resection and no
             systemic chemotherapy, immunotherapy or targeted therapy has been received by the
             patient between the tumor collection and the MAGE-A3 screening test. Fresh tumor
             tissue in RNAlater must be also available for gene signature testing. Patients must
             have at least one biopsiable cutaneous, subcutaneous, lymph node lesion, The tumor
             sample should be preferably from the same lesion as the FFPE tumor tissue. Cutaneous
             lesions must measure &gt;/= 4mm and lymph nodes, subcutaneous, lung or liver lesions must
             measure &gt;/= 1cm.

          5. STEP 2 ANA (antinuclear antibody) titer &lt; 1:80

          6. STEP 2 The patient's tumor shows expression of MAGE-A3 gene.

          7. ECOG performance status of 0 or 1.

          8. WBC &gt;/= 3000/mm^3 and Hemoglobin &gt;/= 9 g/dl

          9. Platelet count &gt;/= 100,000/mm^3.

         10. Normal AST and ALT except for patients with liver metastases, in which serum ALT and
             AST &lt;/= 2.5 X upper limit of normal (ULN) will be permitted.

         11. Creatinine &lt;/= 1.5 mg/dL

         12. Normal total bilirubin except for patients with liver metastases, in which total
             bilirubin &lt;/= 1.5 X ULN will be permitted (patients with Gilbert's syndrome must have
             a total bilirubin less that 3.0 mg/dL).

         13. LDH &lt;/= 2 X ULN

         14. Stress cardiac test (stress thallium, stress MUGA, dobutamine echocardiogram or other
             stress test that will rule out cardiac ischemia) with estimated ejection fraction &gt;50%
             within 6 months of signing consent form

         15. Pulmonary function tests showing FEV1 &gt; 65% or FVC &gt; 65% of predicted within 6 months
             of signing consent form

         16. Women of childbearing potential (WOCBP) must be using an adequate method of
             contraception prior to treatment, throughout the study, and for up to 8 weeks after
             the last dose of investigational product, in such a manner that the risk of pregnancy
             is minimized. In general, the decision for appropriate methods to prevent pregnancy
             should be determined by discussions between the investigator and the study subject.
             WOCBP include any female who has experienced menarche and who has not undergone
             successful surgical sterilization (hysterectomy, bilateral tubal ligation, or
             bilateral oophorectomy) or is not post-menopausal. Post-menopause is defined as:
             Amenorrhea for 12 consecutive months without another cause, or For women with
             irregular menstrual periods and taking hormone replacement therapy (HRT), a documented
             serum follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) level 35 mIU/mL.

         17. (Continued #16) Women who are using oral contraceptives, other hormonal contraceptives
             (vaginal products, skin patches, or implanted or injectable products), or mechanical
             products such as an intrauterine device or barrier methods (diaphragm, condoms,
             spermicides) to prevent pregnancy, or are practicing abstinence or where their partner
             is sterile (eg, vasectomy) should be considered to be of childbearing potential. WOCBP
             must have a negative serum or urine pregnancy test (minimum sensitivity 25 IU/L or
             equivalent units of HCG) within 14 days before the start of treatment.

         18. Men must also agree to use an adequate method of contraception.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. The patient has at any time received systemic chemotherapy, immunotherapy or targeted
             therapy (except for isolated limb perfusion, interferon, or radiation in the adjuvant
             setting, as long as this was performed at least 4 weeks before first study treatment
             administration).

          2. Brain metastasis or history of brain metastasis.

          3. Any types of melanoma other than cutaneous, i.e. ocular or mucosal .

          4. The patient received any cancer immunotherapeutic containing a MAGE-A3 antigen.

          5. Patients with a history of second malignancies are eligible provided that they have
             been free of recurrence from secondary malignancy for at least 3 years, does not
             include squamous cell carcinoma, basal cell carcinoma, or carcinoma in situ.

          6. The patient has a history of an autoimmune disease such as, but not limited to,
             multiple sclerosis, lupus, rheumatoid arthritis, and inflammatory bowel disease or an
             antinuclear antibody (ANA) titer &gt; 1:80.

          7. The patient has a history of allergic disease or reactions likely to be exacerbated by
             any component of the study investigational compound.

          8. The patient has a family history of congenital or hereditary immunodeficiency.

          9. Known to be positive for viral hepatitis B or C (HBsAg or Anti HCV) or HIV (HIV
             antibodies) Patients should have a negative test within 6 months of starting
             treatment.

         10. Systemic steroid therapy, steroid-containing compounds or any other immunosuppressive
             agents or to be used for more than 7 consecutive days (at a dose of prednisone or
             equivalent of &gt;/= 0.125 mg/kg/day).

         11. The patient has psychiatric or addictive disorders that may compromise his/her ability
             to give informed consent, or to comply with the trial procedures. Each patient will be
             evaluated by the principal investigator or his designee.

         12. The patient has concurrent severe medical problems, unrelated to the malignancy, that
             would significantly limit full compliance with the study or expose the patient to
             unacceptable risk. Each patient will be evaluated by the principal investigator or his
             designee.

         13. Initiation of another anti-cancer therapy.

         14. For female patients: the patient is pregnant or lactating.

         15. WOCBP who are unwilling or unable to use an acceptable contraceptive method to avoid
             pregnancy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wen-Jen Hwu, MD,PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 23, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 24, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 15, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Metastatic Melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Unresectable Melanoma</keyword>
  <keyword>HDIL-2</keyword>
  <keyword>Interleukin-2</keyword>
  <keyword>IL-2</keyword>
  <keyword>Aldesleukin</keyword>
  <keyword>Proleukin</keyword>
  <keyword>recMAGE-A3 + AS15</keyword>
  <keyword>ASCI</keyword>
  <keyword>recMAGE-A3</keyword>
  <keyword>Recombinant MAGE-A3 protein</keyword>
  <keyword>recMAGE-A3 + AS15 ASCI</keyword>
  <keyword>MAGE-A3</keyword>
  <keyword>MAGE-A3 ASCI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melanoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aldesleukin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interleukin-2</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

