<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01266616</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A5281</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10846</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01266616</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety of and Immune Response to an Investigational HIV-1 Vaccine With or Without Interleukin-12 (IL-12) in HIV-1 Infected Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Randomized, Partially Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Dose-Escalation Study to Evaluate the Safety and Immunogenicity of a Cytokine Enhanced HIV-1 Multi-Antigen (HIV MAG) pDNA Vaccine Delivered Intramuscularly Followed by in Vivo Electroporation (IM/EP) or Intramuscularly in HIV-1 Infected Adults Receiving ART</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Therapeutic HIV vaccines are designed to control HIV infection by boosting the body's natural
      immune response. There are currently no FDA-approved therapeutic HIV vaccines. This study
      will test whether giving an HIV-1 vaccine together with or without interleukin 12 (IL-12) is
      safe and effective. This study will also test a new way of giving the vaccine called
      electroporation (EP).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Although highly active antiretroviral therapy (HAART) has greatly reduced HIV
      infection-related morbidity and mortality, individual response to therapy can be variable.
      Therapeutic vaccination works by augmenting virus-specific immunity and can be given with or
      without immunomodulatory agents or adjuvants. In conjunction with HAART, therapeutic
      vaccination may be a more effective treatment for the suppression of HIV-1 replication. This
      study will examine the safety and efficacy of giving an investigational vaccine with or
      without IL-12 in HIV-1 infected adults receiving HAART. This study will also test whether
      delivering the vaccine using EP is safe and increases the efficacy of the vaccine.

      Participation in this study will last approximately 36 weeks. Participants will be randomly
      assigned to one of five cohorts. Cohort 1 will receive the HIV multi-antigen plasmid DNA (HIV
      MAG pDNA) vaccine or placebo intramuscularly (IM) in the upper arm followed by EP. Cohorts 2
      through 4 will receive the HIV MAG pDNA vaccine and sequentially increasing doses of GENEVAX
      IL-12 pDNA or placebo by IM/EP. Cohort 5 will receive the HIV MAG pDNA vaccine with the
      highest dose of IL-12 pDNA or placebo by needle and syringe in the upper arm.

      Participants receive two injections at Weeks 0, 4, and 12. Participants will complete a
      questionnaire that assesses the acceptability of the vaccine and remain at the clinic 30
      minutes for observation after each vaccination. Participants will be contacted by telephone 2
      to 3 days post-vaccination to assess vaccination-related signs and/or symptoms. All
      participants will be asked to record their temperatures and any symptoms they experience
      daily for 4 days following each vaccination on a Vaccination Report Card (VRC). All nonstudy
      vaccines or medications should also be recorded on the VRC. Study visits will occur at Weeks
      0, 1, 2, 4, 5, 6, 8, 12, 13, 14, 16, 24, and 36. At most visits, participants will undergo a
      physical examination. Women of reproductive potential will also undergo pregnancy testing
      before receiving injections on Weeks 0, 4, and 12. Blood will be drawn at various time points
      to evaluate participants' health and measure immunologic markers, CD4 and CD8 T-cell counts,
      and cytokine levels. Blood and plasma will also be stored for future exploratory studies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of at least one greater than Grade 3 adverse event (AE) including signs/symptoms, lab toxicities, and/or clinical events that is possibly, probably, or definitely related to study treatment, as judged by the core team</measure>
    <time_frame>From the first day of study treatment until 28 days after the last study vaccine administration</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in the number of interferon (IFN)-gamma generating (in response to gag) CD4 T cells/million peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) as measured by intracellular cytokine staining (ICS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From Baseline to Week 14</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Answering &quot;no&quot; to the question, &quot;In your opinion, would this study's vaccination procedure be acceptable as part of a treatment for HIV, if it proved to be effective?&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>From Week 0 to Week 36</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Answering &quot;no&quot; to the question, &quot;In your opinion, would this study's vaccination procedure be acceptable if it could contribute to increased scientific knowledge about how best to administer vaccines to prevent or treat infections?&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>From Week 0 to Week 36</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Premature treatment discontinuation for reasons related to study treatment or related to any real or perceived effect of study vaccination or its administration</measure>
    <time_frame>From Week 0 to Week 36</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rated pain (for participants administered vaccine/placebo by the EP device)</measure>
    <time_frame>When the device was placed on the skin and the vaccine/placebo was injected; at the time of the electrical stimulation and muscle contraction; and at 10 and 30 minutes after the procedure was completed at Weeks 0, 4, and 12</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline and absolute values of multiple functions of CD4 and CD8 T cells in response to gag and other vaccine-coded antigens individually and in sum</measure>
    <time_frame>At Week 8, Week 14, and possibly other time points depending on the first set of data in an ICS assay</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>10</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">62</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Vaccine alone IM/EP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HIV MAG pDNA alone IM/EP</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo given as an injection in each upper arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Vaccine plus IL-12 IM/EP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HIV MAG pDNA plus 50 mcg of IL-12 pDNA IM/EP</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo given as an injection in each upper arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: Vaccine plus IL-12 IM/EP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HIV MAG pDNA plus 250 mcg of IL-12 pDNA IM/EP</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo given as an injection in each upper arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4: Vaccine plus IL-12 IM/EP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HIV MAG pDNA plus 1,000 mcg of IL-12 pDNA IM/EP</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo given as an injection in each upper arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5: Vaccine plus IL-12 IM</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>HIV MAG pDNA plus 1,000 mcg (or highest dose reached) IL-12 pDNA IM</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo given as an injection in each upper arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Profectus HIV MAG pDNA vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>3,000 mcg admixture of two vaccine plasmids: ProfectusVax DNA Plasmid (HIV-1 gag/pol) and ProfectusVax DNA Plasmid (HIV-1 nef/tat/vif, env) at Weeks 0, 4, and 12</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Vaccine alone IM/EP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Vaccine plus IL-12 IM/EP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: Vaccine plus IL-12 IM/EP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4: Vaccine plus IL-12 IM/EP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5: Vaccine plus IL-12 IM</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>IL-12</intervention_name>
    <description>Administered at Weeks 0, 4, and 12</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Vaccine plus IL-12 IM/EP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: Vaccine plus IL-12 IM/EP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4: Vaccine plus IL-12 IM/EP</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5: Vaccine plus IL-12 IM</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Saline injections at Weeks 0, 4, and 12</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 4: Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 5: Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV-1 infected

          -  Stable antiretroviral therapy (ART) for a minimum of 6 consecutive months prior to
             study entry and intention to remain on stable ART until study completion

          -  CD4 T-cell count greater than or equal to 500 cells/mm3 (within 30 days prior to study
             entry)

          -  At least two measurements of HIV-1 RNA levels less than or equal to 200 copies/mL
             (first measurement must be performed at least 6 months prior to study entry and second
             measurement must be performed between 6 months prior to study entry and at least 30
             days prior to study entry)

          -  Screening HIV-1 RNA less than 50 copies/mL (within 30 days prior to study entry)

          -  Hepatitis B surface antigen negative (within 30 days prior to study entry)

          -  Hepatitis C antibody negative or, if hepatitis C antibody positive, hepatitis C virus
             RNA negative (within 30 days prior to study entry)

          -  Certain laboratory values obtained within 30 days prior to study entry; more
             information can be found in the protocol

          -  Females of reproductive potential must have a negative urine pregnancy test within 3
             days prior to study entry

          -  All study participants participating in sexual activity that could lead to pregnancy
             must agree to use at least one of the following forms of birth control for at least 21
             days prior to study entry until the final study visit:

               -  Condoms (male or female) with or without a spermicidal agent

               -  Diaphragm or cervical cap with spermicide

               -  Intrauterine device (IUD)

               -  Hormone-based contraceptive

          -  Females who are not of reproductive potential are eligible without requiring the use
             of a contraceptive

          -  Ability and willingness of subject to provide written informed consent

          -  Collection of a pre-entry PBMC specimen for immunologic assays and entered into the
             Laboratory Data Management System (LDMS)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Confirmed (defined as two consecutive values) CD4 T-cell count less than 200 cells/mm3
             at any time or any history or subject recollection of CD4 T-cell count less than 200
             cells/mm3 prior to screening

          -  Any active malignancy that may require chemotherapy or radiation therapy

          -  Bleeding diathesis or condition associated with prolonged bleeding time that would
             contraindicate IM injection

          -  A skin-fold measurement of the cutaneous and subcutaneous tissue for eligible
             injection sites (on the medial deltoid muscles) that exceeds 40 mm

          -  Use of immunomodulatory, cytokine, or growth stimulating factors such as systemic
             corticosteroids, cyclosporine, methotrexate, azathioprine, anti-CD25 antibody,
             granulocyte macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF), chondrocyte
             colony-stimulating factor (C-CSF), IFN, or interleukin-2 (IL-2) (within 30 days prior
             to study entry)

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding

          -  Use of any prior HIV vaccine (prophylactic and/or therapeutic) within 1 year before
             study entry

          -  Use of any investigational treatment within 6 months before study entry

          -  Use of any licensed or experimental non-HIV vaccination (e.g., hepatitis B, influenza,
             pneumococcal polysaccharide) within 4 weeks prior to study entry

          -  Use of any infusion blood product or immune globulin within 3 months prior to study
             entry

          -  Known or suspected hypersensitivity to any vaccine component, including
             hypersensitivity to amide-type local anesthetics, such as lidocaine (Xylocaine),
             mepivacaine (Polocaine/Carbocaine), etidocaine (Duranest), bupivacaine (Marcaine), or
             prilocaine

          -  Active drug or alcohol use or dependence that, in the opinion of the site
             investigator, would interfere with adherence to study requirements

          -  Serious illness requiring systemic treatment and/or hospitalization within 7 days
             prior to study entry

          -  Current use of any electronic stimulation device, such as cardiac demand pacemakers,
             automatic implantable cardiac defibrillators, nerve stimulators, or deep brain
             stimulators

          -  History of cardiac arrhythmia or palpitations (e.g., supraventricular tachycardia,
             atrial fibrillation, frequent ectopy, or sinus bradycardia [i.e., &lt;50 beats per minute
             on exam]) prior to study entry (NOTE: Sinus arrhythmia is not excluded)

          -  History of syncope or fainting episode within 1 year of study entry

          -  Seizure disorder or any history of prior seizure

          -  Extensive tattoos covering the site of administration (upper left and right medial
             deltoid muscles)

          -  Presence of any surgical or traumatic metal implants at the site of administration
             (medial deltoid muscles)

          -  Any chronic inflammatory disease (e.g., ankylosing spondylitis, psoriasis,
             inflammatory bowel disease)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Jacobson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Division of Infectious Diseases and HIV Medicine, Drexel University College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA CARE Center CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90035</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford AIDS Clinical Trials Unit CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304-5350</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ucsf Hiv/Aids Crs</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Hospital CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital Clinical Research Site (MGH CRS) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital Therapeutics Clinical Research Site (BWH TCRS) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University Therapeutics (WT) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Trillium Health ACTG CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14607</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Univ. of Rochester ACTG CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45219</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn Therapeutics Crs</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213-2582</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Houston AIDS Research Team CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Finzi D, Blankson J, Siliciano JD, Margolick JB, Chadwick K, Pierson T, Smith K, Lisziewicz J, Lori F, Flexner C, Quinn TC, Chaisson RE, Rosenberg E, Walker B, Gange S, Gallant J, Siliciano RF. Latent infection of CD4+ T cells provides a mechanism for lifelong persistence of HIV-1, even in patients on effective combination therapy. Nat Med. 1999 May;5(5):512-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10229227</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koup RA, Safrit JT, Cao Y, Andrews CA, McLeod G, Borkowsky W, Farthing C, Ho DD. Temporal association of cellular immune responses with the initial control of viremia in primary human immunodeficiency virus type 1 syndrome. J Virol. 1994 Jul;68(7):4650-5.</citation>
    <PMID>8207839</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luxembourg A, Evans CF, Hannaman D. Electroporation-based DNA immunisation: translation to the clinic. Expert Opin Biol Ther. 2007 Nov;7(11):1647-64. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17961089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 23, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 23, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 24, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 24, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 24, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 25, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Interleukin-12</keyword>
  <keyword>Electroporation</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV Therapeutic Vaccine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Interleukin-12</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

