<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01330693</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R01MH081854-01A2</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01MH081854-01A2</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01330693</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cortical Excitability: Phenotype and Biomarker in Attention-deficit, Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cortical Excitability: Phenotype and Biomarker in ADHD Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Cincinnati</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Cincinnati</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to find out if children with attention-deficit, hyperactivity
      disorder (ADHD) have a difference in how their brain cells &quot;fire&quot; or react. The investigators
      also want to find if brain cell &quot;firing&quot; can tell us how severe of symptoms a child has from
      ADHD. Finally, the investigators want to see if giving an ADHD medication called atomoxetine
      can make the ADHD symptoms in a child better and if the improvement shows a change in brain
      &quot;firing&quot;.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate Short Interval Intracortical Inhibition (SICI) measured by pTMS as a
      marker of the hyperactive-impulsive dimension in 120 ADHD 7-12 years, medication-free
      children. This study will characterize the effects of a single dose of atomoxetine compared
      to placebo on cognitive correlates of SICI change. Participants will be randomized 2:1 to
      either atomoxetine or placebo. The study will also characterize the effects of four weeks of
      atomoxetine treatment on cortical inhibition and will correlate SICI change with clinical
      outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>September 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy outcome as change from baseline in ADHDRS total score</measure>
    <time_frame>At 4 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>SICI as a marker of ADHD Behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline visit</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate pTMS-evoked Short Interval Cortical Inhibition (SICI) as a marker of the hyperactive-impulsive dimension in Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive Correlates of SICI Change</measure>
    <time_frame>2 hours (at baseline visit)</time_frame>
    <description>To determine cognitive correlates of SICI change, the study will first measure SICI at at rest and concurrently during the Stop-task. This process will then be repeated 2 hours after a single dose (0.5 mg/kg) of atomoxetine (ATX) or placebo.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Attention Deficit Disorder With Hyperactivity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Atomoxetine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Atomoxetine is FDA-approved for the treatment of ADHD symptoms in children</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Sugar pill</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Atomoxetine</intervention_name>
    <description>Atomoxetine is FDA-approved for the treatment of ADHD symptoms in children. Single dose of 0.5 mg/kg at baseline visit. Then dose adjusted in an open-label design afterwards.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Atomoxetine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Strattera</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sugar Pill</intervention_name>
    <description>In-active sugar pill randomly assigned at baseline visit</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Signed informed consent and assent

          2. Meets DSM-IV criteria for ADHD, combined or inattentive subtype, based on K-SADS
             interview

          3. Scores at least 1.5 SD higher than age and gender mean on ADHD RS, keyed to ADHD
             subtype (i.e., combined score for the combined subtype, inattentive subscale only for
             inattentive subtype, etc.)

          4. Age: 7 - 12 years at study entry

          5. Findings on physical exam, laboratory studies and ECG are judged to be normal for age
             and gender, as determined by study physician at study entry

          6. There is not a co-existing medical condition for which TMS or ATX is contraindicated
             (for example pheochromocytoma).

          7. Pulse and blood pressure within 95% of age and gender mean

          8. Full scale IQ &gt;75 (i.e., excluding mental retardation and the lower level of the
             borderline range)

          9. Able to complete study instruments and swallow capsules

         10. Willing to commit to the entire visit schedule for the study

         11. No previous treatment with Atomoxetine

         12. Must either be naive to ADHD study medication or not doing well on the current ADHD
             medication.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has one of the following exclusionary diagnoses: autism/ pervasive developmental
             disorder, mental retardation, schizophrenia, a psychotic disorder, bipolar disorder,
             severe depressive or conduct disorder

          2. Has a comorbid disorder that is otherwise allowable, but which requires a treatment
             that is not being offered in the study, and should be the primary focus of treatment,
             in the opinion of the PI

          3. Has a medical or neurologic disorder that would preclude taking the ATX, or which
             would potentially confound the assessment of ADHD and/or TMS outcomes, in the opinion
             of the PI (for example pheochromocytoma, or for specific purposes of this study
             uncontrolled seizure disorder or organic brain syndrome).

          4. Taking a systemic medication which might interfere with the metabolism or efficacy
             assessment of ATX in this study

          5. History of allergic reactions to multiple medications

          6. History of alcohol or drug abuse in the past 3 months Has been in a medication
             treatment study in the past 30 days

          7. Females of childbearing age who are sexually active, do not use acceptable birth
             control (double barrier method), or are not abstinent. Abstinence is defined as no
             sexual activity for at least 3 months before the start of the study and the intention
             to abstain from sexual activity during the study period). Double barrier methods
             allowed include: condoms or diaphragms combined with spermicide use, intrauterine
             devices (IUD), and oral, transdermal, injectable or implantable hormonal medications
             (Ortho-Evra, Norplant, Depo-Provera, and similar prescription products) for at least
             one month before entering the study and continuing its use throughout the study. Birth
             control pills alone are not acceptable forms of birth control for this study.

          8. Has any prior neurological condition that might increase the risk of an adverse event
             with TMS. For the purpose of this study we are excluding children with a current or
             prior history of epilepsy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Floyd R Sallee, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Cincinnati</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Cincinnati</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45219</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cincinnati Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 5, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 6, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 7, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 17, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 17, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 19, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Cincinnati</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Floyd Sallee</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ADHD</keyword>
  <keyword>Atomoxetine</keyword>
  <keyword>Biomarker</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Attention Deficit Disorder with Hyperactivity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperkinesis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atomoxetine Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

