<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01335763</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LANTU_L_05128*</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01335763</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacist Intervention for Glycemic Control in The Community</brief_title>
  <acronym>RxING</acronym>
  <official_title>Pharmacist Intervention for Glycemic Control in The Community (The RxING Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sanofi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alberta</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background: Approximately 1.9 million Canadians are living with diabetes and this is
      estimated to increase by 75% over the next few decades. Pharmacists are front line primary
      healthcare professionals who see patients with diabetes frequently and in Alberta, they have
      been allowed to prescribe medications and order laboratory tests. As such, pharmacists could
      systematically identify poorly controlled diabetes patients and provide greater access to
      diabetes interventions to improve blood sugar control.

      Objective: The aim of this study is to determine the effect of a community pharmacist
      intervention on blood sugar control in individuals with poorly controlled diabetes.

      Project description:

      100 adults with type 2 diabetes and uncontrolled blood sugar will be defined by the
      participating pharmacists. Blood sugar control is going to assessed using hemoglobin A1c test
      (a blood test to measure individual's blood sugar control over the last 3 months). This test
      requires obtaining a blood spot from the patient which will be obtained by pricking his/her
      fingertip. Based on the hemoglobin A1c test result the pharmacist will assess the patient's
      need for insulin glargine, if the patient needs insulin glargine the pharmacist is going to
      prescribe it for him/her and educate him/her on its use. Patients are going to be followed up
      closely by the pharmacists for 6 months with regular updates to the patients' family
      physicians. This multi-centre study should demonstrate pharmacists' ability to improve
      glycemic control and improve access to care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND/RATIONALE:

      Approximately 1.9 million Canadians are living with diabetes. Estimates are that this number
      will increase by 75% over the next few decades. Glycemic control in patients with type 2
      diabetes mellitus is poor, and poorly controlled patients contribute significantly to the
      cost of primary health care in Canada. 10% of all acute care hospital admissions in 2006 were
      attributed to diabetes and its complications.

      As type 2 diabetes is a progressive disease, most patients with type 2 diabetes will
      eventually require insulin. In patients who present with type 2 diabetes and a HbA1C over 9%,
      insulin can be started immediately, however, historically physicians generally perceive their
      to be patient difficulties in starting insulin therapy.

      INSIGHT demonstrated improved glycemic control with addition of insulin glargine to oral
      hypoglycemic agents in patients with type 2 diabetes. However, physicians are often reluctant
      to initiate insulin in these patients. In addition, physicians do not have a system to
      systematically identify potential candidates for insulin add-on therapy

      Pharmacists are front line primary care professionals who see patients with diabetes more
      frequently than family physicians and as such, could systematically and proactively identify
      patients with type 2 diabetes with poor glycemic control as a public health approach to
      chronic disease management. This approach has been used successfully by our group in the past
      with dyslipidemia and hypertension management involving patients with diabetes.

      The scope of practice for pharmacists is changing, with legislation in Alberta (and soon
      other provinces) allowing pharmacists to prescribe Schedule I medications and order
      laboratory tests. As such, there is an opportunity to provide greater access, convenience and
      improved glycemic control by engaging community pharmacists and their patients.

      PRIMARY OBJECTIVE: To determine the effect of a community pharmacist prescribing intervention
      on glycemic control in patients with poorly controlled type 2 diabetes.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

        -  To determine the effects of pharmacist-directed diabetes care focusing on glycemic
           control on:

             -  patient satisfaction

             -  quality of life

             -  dosage changes of oral agents

             -  persistence on insulin glargine and the end of follow-up

             -  hypoglycemic episodes

        -  To conduct a health economic assessment of the costs and benefits of the intervention

      METHODS:

      Design: multicentre pragmatic before-after design trial

      Setting: Ten community pharmacies in Alberta for recruitment and follow-up, engaging both
      patients and family physicians

      • participating pharmacists will have additional prescribing authorization. For pharmacists
      not having additional prescribing authorization, we will facilitate their application as done
      in the rural RxACTION study.

      Recruitment: Pharmacists will systematically identify potential candidates by inviting all
      patients with type 2 diabetes receiving oral hypoglycemic medications to check their HbA1c
      using a point of care test. HbA1c is going to be measured in the pharmacy. The patient has to
      sign the first stage consent form in order to get his/her HbA1c measured. After signing the
      consent form, the patient's HbA1c will be measured using a digital meter which requires a
      blood spot which will be gained by pricking the patient's fingertip. If the result of HbA1c
      test is normal the patient will be given his/her result and told to keep up the good work. If
      the result of HbA1c test is high (7.5-11 %) and the patient meets the other inclusion
      criteria for the study the patient will be asked if he/she wants to participate in the study.
      If the patient agrees on participating in the study he/she will be asked to sign the second
      stage consent form. After signing the consent form the patient will be started on insulin
      glargine at bedtime and will be taught how to use the insulin pen. If HbA1c is &gt; 11% the
      patient will be assessed by the study investigators, treatment recommendations will be
      checked and will be referred to his/her family physician.

      Follow-up: Patients will be followed at 2, 4, 8, 14, 20, and 26 weeks to capture adverse
      events, adherence to the insulin regimen, fasting blood sugars (measured by the patient),
      insulin dose and titration. HbA1c will be measured at baseline and then at week 14 visit and
      week 26. Interim telephone follow-up may be performed at the discretion of the pharmacist
      investigator, however telephone follow-up cannot be used for 2 consecutive visits, nor for
      week 14 or 26 visits. Fasting glucose will be measured at the discretion of the pharmacist
      and patients will monitor their blood glucose at home and record in a standard patient diary.

      After each follow up study the pharmacists is going to inform the patient's family physician
      if there were any changes in the patient's treatment regimen and also about the results of
      any tests conducted.

      One year after the final follow up visit, the pharmacy is going to receive a phone call from
      the study investigators to check if the patient is still taking insulin.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in HbA1c from baseline to week 26</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The change of the patients' HbA1c between the baseline and the 26 week visits</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life and patient satisfaction.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of life and patient satisfaction is going to be measured through using the questionnaires Audit of Diabetes-Dependent Quality of Life (ADDQoL), Diabetes Treatment Satisfaction Questionnaire and Diabetes Treatment Satisfaction Questionnaire change (DTSQ and DTSQc)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients achieving the target HbA1c</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients achieving HbA1c of ≤7.0% during follow-up</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Type and degree of dosage changes in oral hypoglycemic agents</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The type and the degree of changes in the oral hypoglycemic dosing regimen</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Persistence on insulin glargine</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of patients still taking insulin at the end of follow-up</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of hypoglycemic episodes; symptomatic confirmed and severe (i.e., Requiring the help from a third party), as defined by the CDA guidelines</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health economic evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Cost-effectiveness analyses from a healthcare payor (government) perspective. Costs will include pharmacist training, time spent with patients, pharmaceutical care processes (includes number of face-to-face meetings, time spent with the patient, number and duration of phone calls, number and type of testing per patient, equipment and testing costs, medication costs and out of pocket costs for patients). Clinical benefits will be estimated by modeling the A1C reduction with clinical trials estimates of event reductions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 2 Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Insulin glargine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 units at bedtime of insulin glargine will be prescribed to the patients who has HbA1c levels of 7.5-11%. Insulin glargine dose is going to be titrated by increments of 1 unit daily by the patient to achieve a morning fasting glucose of &lt;=5.5mmol/L</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Insulin glargine</intervention_name>
    <description>10 units at bedtime of insulin glargine will be prescribed to the patients who has HbA1c levels of 7.5-11%. Insulin glargine dose is going to be titrated by increments of 1 unit daily by the patient to achieve a morning fasting glucose of &lt;=5.5mmol/L</description>
    <arm_group_label>Insulin glargine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lantus</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or Female over 18 years of age

          -  Type 2 diabetes for at least 6 months

          -  Taking 1 or more oral hypoglycemic agents

          -  Patient attending your community pharmacy where you decided that addition of insulin
             glargine may be of benefit to the patient

          -  Baseline HbA1c 7.5 - 11%

          -  Signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Have used, or currently using, Insulin

          -  History of ketoacidosis

          -  Pregnant

          -  Works night shift

          -  Renal impairment(Serum Creatinine: females ≥ 124 mmol/l, males ≥ 133 mmol/l)

          -  Clinically unstable

          -  Unwilling/unable to attend follow up visits

          -  Unlikely to adhere to study procedures (eg. due to cognitive limitations, severe
             psychiatric disorder or alcoholism)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>EPICORE Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 2C8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 13, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 13, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 14, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 4, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 4, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 6, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Alberta</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ross T. Tsuyuki</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine (Cardiology) and Director, EPICORE Centre University of Alberta</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HbA1c</keyword>
  <keyword>Multicentre before-after design</keyword>
  <keyword>Glycemic control</keyword>
  <keyword>Community pharmacists</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin, Globin Zinc</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin Glargine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

