<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01339858</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1008-12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01339858</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of N-Acetyl Cysteine on Cortical Erosion in Early Stage Schizophrenia</brief_title>
  <acronym>Breier-Stanley</acronym>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Indiana University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stanley Medical Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indiana University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to determine if NAC, added to existing antipsychotic
      treatment, is superior to placebo for cortical erosion in patients with early stage
      psychosis. The primary hypothesis is that there will be significantly less cortical erosion
      as measured by cortical thickness, cortical volume and cortical white matter density
      (assessed by DTI) in patients treated for 12 months with NAC as compared to those treated
      with placebo. The secondary objectives of this study are to determine if 12 months of NAC
      add-on treatment is superior to placebo for fMRI determined working memory and semantic
      memory tasks, cortical MR spectroscopy measures (glutathione, N-acetylaspartate, and
      glutamine/glutamate levels), electrophysiologically determined attention measures (e.g.,
      mismatch negativity, P300), symptoms, functional measures and cognitive functioning.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Schizophrenia is a severe, debilitating illness that typically begins during the teen-age
      years and early twenties, and worsens over time as it evolves into a chronic, life-long
      disorder. Existing treatments suppress psychotic symptoms but do not prevent the evolution of
      underlying disease processes that results in poor, long term outcomes. Recent studies have
      shown that progressive erosion of cortical mass occurs during the early stages of
      schizophrenia (1-3). The investigators hypothesize that arresting cortical erosion during the
      early phases of schizophrenia will prevent subsequent clinical deterioration and the
      descending course of illness associated with this disorder. The investigators propose to
      establish a research program that will assess the ability of agents with neuroprotective
      properties to halt cortical loss and thereby prevent subsequent clinical deterioration.

      N-acetyl cysteine (NAC) is an attractive molecule for the proposed study because of two of
      its mechanistic properties. First, it is an established neuroprotective agent. NAC is a
      precursor to glutathione which is a primary detoxifier of reactive oxygen and other radical
      molecules which damage neuronal tissue (4-6). Glutathione deficiencies have been well
      documented in schizophrenia (7, 8). Second, NAC modulates glutamate release. NMDA
      hypofunction and altered glutamate release have been hypothesized to contribute to the
      cortical atrophy observed in early stage schizophrenia (9, 10). NAC has been shown to
      antagonize both the phencyclidine (PCP) effects of increased frontal glutamate levels and
      induction of social isolation in rodents (11). PCP is a pharmacological model of
      schizophrenia. In a controlled clinical trial of patients with chronic schizophrenia, NAC
      improved mismatch negativity, a pre-attentive measure of cortical information processing that
      has been consistently implicated in the pathophysiology of schizophrenia and has been shown
      to correlate with cortical erosion in early stage patients (12, 13). In a double-blind,
      placebo controlled clinical trial of chronic schizophrenic patients, NAC significantly
      improved general psychopathology scores, negative symptoms and extrapyramidal symptoms (14).
      NAC was well tolerated with no significant effects on any safety parameter or adverse events.
      The favorable tolerability of NAC has been further demonstrated in a recent study conducted
      at IUSM Riley Hospital in children (ages 4 to 12 years) with autism at relatively high doses
      (dose range of 900 to 4200 mg/day) in which there were no serious adverse events reported and
      NAC was well tolerated (15).

      The investigators propose to determine if NAC has disease modifying potential in early stage
      schizophrenia. The investigators hypothesize that NAC will improve measures of cortical
      integrity in early stage schizophrenia and these brain effects will be related to
      improvements in negative symptoms and cognitive functioning. Primary outcome measures in the
      trials will be serial assessments of cortical integrity using magnetic resonance structural
      (cortical thickness, cortical volume, diffuses tensor imaging, DTI). In addition the
      investigators will assess the possible effects of NAC treatment on other parameters linked to
      cortical erosion including fMRI coupled with working memory and semantic memory tasks, MR
      spectroscopy (cortical glutathione, N-acetylaspartate, and glutamine/glutamate levels) and
      electrophysiological measures (e.g., mismatch negativity, P300). The investigators will also
      determine the relationship between effects of NAC on negative symptoms, positive symptoms,
      functional status, cognition (BACS), and safety parameters; and brain indices.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Care Provider)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cortical erosion</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>We anticipate that 12 months treatment with NAC as an add-on treatment will show significantly less cortical erosion as measured by cortical thickness, cortical volume and cortical white matter density (assessed by Diffusion Tensor Imaging [DTI]) than treatment with placebo</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>working memory and semantic memory tasks as measure by fMRI</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>determine if 12 months of NAC add-on treatment is superior to placebo for fMRI determined working memory and semantic memory tasks as measured by fMRI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>glutathione, N-acetylaspartate, and glutamine/glutamate levels</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>We anticipate that 12 months treatment with NAC as an add-on treatment will show significantly less reduction in glutathione, N-acetylaspartate, and glutamine/glutamate levels as compared to placebo as measured by cortical MR spectroscopy measures</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>attention measures</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>determine if 12 months of NAC add-on treatment is superior to placebo for attention measures (e.g., mismatch negativity, P300) as measured by electrophysiology methods. Electrophysiology measures will be recorded from a 64 channel, silver/silver-chloride scalp electrode montage.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptoms of a psychotic disorder</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>determine if 12 months of NAC add-on treatment is superior to placebo for symptom management of a psychotic disorder as assessed by the Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) and the Clinical Global Impressions Severity Scale (CGI-S)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>cognitive functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>determine if 12 months of NAC add-on treatment is superior to placebo for cognitive functioning as measured by the Brief Assessment of Cognition in Schizophrenia (BACS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>functional status</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>determine if 12 months of NAC add-on treatment is superior to placebo for functional measures and as measured by the Quality of Life (EuroQuoL)and the Personal and Social Performance Scale (PSP)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>spontaneously reported adverse events, Barnes Akathisia Scale,Simpson-Angus Scale, and medical evaluations including: Physical exam, vital signs, weight, waist circumference, pregnancy tests, and other laboratory measures of metabolic status</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <condition>Psychotic Disorder NOS</condition>
  <condition>Schizoaffective Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Schizophreniform</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>N-Acetyl Cysteine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>NAC and matched placebo will be supplied in unmarked capsules. Each NAC capsule will contain 480 mg of NAC. Dosing will begin at 480 mg/d and titrated up by 480 mg/d each week until a maximum dose of 2880 mg/d (BID) is reached. This approximate dose was effective and well tolerated in a recent study of treatment refractory obsessive-compulsive disorder by Krystal and colleagues at Yale (16). In addition, a double-blind placebo controlled trial recently completed at IUSM Riley Hospital in children (age 4 to 12 years) with autism spectrum disorders used doses ranging from 900 mg/day to 4200 mg/day and reported no serious adverse events and found the agent well tolerated (15). Dose adjustments downward to 1920 mg/d will be permitted if tolerability issues are encountered at the maximum dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar Pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>matched placebo</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>N-Acetyl Cysteine</intervention_name>
    <description>NAC and matched placebo will be supplied in unmarked capsules. Each NAC capsule will contain 480 mg of NAC. Dosing will begin at 480 mg/d and titrated up by 480 mg/d each week until a maximum dose of 2880 mg/d (BID) is reached. This approximate dose was effective and well tolerated in a recent study of treatment refractory obsessive-compulsive disorder by Krystal and colleagues at Yale (16). In addition, a double-blind placebo controlled trial recently completed at IUSM Riley Hospital in children (age 4 to 12 years) with autism spectrum disorders used doses ranging from 900 mg/day to 4200 mg/day and reported no serious adverse events and found the agent well tolerated (15). Dose adjustments downward to 1920 mg/d will be permitted if tolerability issues are encountered at the maximum dose</description>
    <arm_group_label>N-Acetyl Cysteine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sugar pill</intervention_name>
    <description>matched placebo will be supplied in unmarked capsules. Dosing regimen will be the same as in the N-Acetyl Cysteine arm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar Pill</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        SUBJECTS DIAGNOSED WITH A PSYCHOTIC DISORDER

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with a DSM-IV diagnosis of schizophrenia, schizophreniform, schizoaffective,
             psychosis disorder NOS

          -  Age range 16-35 years

          -  Male or female

          -  Within 2 years of the first onset of psychotic symptoms that resulted in
             work/school/social dysfunction and/or treatment (PI will review potential subjects who
             have been experiencing symptoms &gt;2 years but &lt;5 years and will allow to enter the
             trial on a case-by-case basis)

          -  Ability to provide informed consent and/or assent (all subjects)

          -  For subjects 16 and 17 years of age, parental/guardian consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unstable medical conditions

          -  Active seizure disorder

          -  Pregnant or lactating women

          -  Females unwilling to utilize birth control

          -  Implanted pacemaker, medication pump, vagal stimulator, deep brain stimulator, TENS
             unit, or ventriculoperitoneal shunt (because of MR studies).

          -  Known IQ less than 70

          -  DSM-IV-TR diagnosis of substance dependence (with the exception of nicotine or
             caffeine dependence)

          -  Psychotic symptoms secondary to substance use

          -  Considered a high risk for suicidal acts - active suicidal ideation with intent to act
             as determined by clinical interview

        HEALTHY CONTROL SUBJECTS

        The comparison subjects will consist of 40 healthy normal volunteers recruited from the
        community who will be age and gender matched to subjects diagnosed with a psychotic
        disorder entering the NAC treatment study

        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age range of 18-30 (inclusive) and able to give voluntary informed consent (Note:
             Subjects diagnosed with a psychotic disorder under the age of 18 will be age matched
             to control subjects aged 18).

          2. Male or Female

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Current severe mental disorder (Schizophrenia, schizophreniform disorder, other
             psychotic disorders, bipolar disorder, major depressive disorder)

          2. Known/documented IQ &lt; 70

          3. Pregnant or lactating women

          4. Acute, serious, or unstable medical condition

          5. Metallic implants or other contraindication to MRI (including but not limited to:
             Implanted pacemaker, medication pump, vagal stimulator, deep brain stimulator, TENS
             unit, or ventriculoperitoneal shunt)

          6. First degree relative with a psychotic disorder (i.e. schizophrenia, schizophreniform,
             schizoaffective, psychosis disorder NOS, substance induced psychosis, major depression
             with psychotic features, or bipolar disorder with psychotic features).

          7. Current DSM-IV-TR diagnosis of substance abuse or dependence (with the exception of
             nicotine or caffeine) as diagnosed within the 6 months prior to screening visit

          8. Known history of seizure disorder, head trauma, stroke, traumatic brain injury,
             significant loss of consciousness
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>35 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prevention and Recovery Center for Early Psychosis (PARC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University Psychotic Disorders Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46222</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://psychiatry.medicine.iu.edu/iupdp</url>
    <description>Indiana University Psychotic Disorders Program</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 19, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 20, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 21, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Indiana University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alan Breier</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Psychiatrist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acetylcysteine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>N-monoacetylcystine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

