<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00921609</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>8997</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00921609</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study Examining the Peri- and Post-operative Dynamics of the Growth Hormone (GH) - IGF-1 Axis in Subjects With Acromegaly During the First Year After Surgical Resection</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study Examining the Peri- and Post-operative Dynamics of the GH-IGF-1 Axis in Subjects With Acromegaly During the First Year After Surgical Resection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Acromegaly is a rare disorder characterized by excessive production of growth hormone most
      often by a pituitary adenoma. A pituitary adenoma is a tumor, almost always benign or
      non-cancerous, that grows on the pituitary, a small gland located at the base of the brain.
      Treatment of acromegaly usually involves surgery, medication, or radiation, but can involve a
      combination of these three treatments.

      Subjects for this study will be recruited if they are:

        1. Adults, male or female, between the ages of 18-90.

        2. Have been diagnosed with acromegaly, based on elevated levels of growth hormone, IGF-I
           (a hormone made in response to growth hormone), and a pituitary adenoma visualized on an
           MRI.

        3. Patients would have already agreed to have their acromegaly treated with surgery prior
           to study entry.

      Subjects will have measurements of growth hormone using an oral glucose tolerance test
      (OGTT), IGF-I, free IGF-I and levels of IGF binding proteins at four time points after their
      pituitary surgery: Day 1, Day 42 (6 weeks), Day 84 (12 weeks), and day 365 (1 year). Subjects
      will also have an MRI of the pituitary done at 12 weeks and 1 year. OGTT and IGF-I are
      routinely measured to assess whether or not a person is cured of their acromegaly. An MRI of
      the pituitary is routinely done at 12 weeks and 1 year after surgery to assess the results of
      surgery. Free IGF-I and IGF binding proteins are not routinely measured after surgery, but
      are being done to see if they relate more strongly to disease activity than IGF-I and growth
      hormone.

      OGTT and the IGF-I binding proteins are not routinely measured on the day after surgery, but
      are being done to examine the predictive ability of these tests at a very early time after
      surgery. Data obtained from these tests will be compared to the data gathered at the 1 year
      time point.

      IGF-I and growth hormone will be measured by a commercial clinical lab, Quest Diagnostics,
      for clinical decision-making at the time of service. IGF-I and growth hormone will also be
      measured using other methods to attempt to investigate the variability of these hormones when
      different assays are used.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary objective of this study will be to determine the natural course of acromegaly treated with surgery in subjects with non-suppressed GH nadir values and normal total IGF-I values.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A second objective of the study will be to determine the reliability of GH nadir to OGTT, free IGF-I, total IGF-I, and IGF binding proteins on post-operative day 1 in predicting long-term cure outcomes in acromegaly.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A third objective will be to determine inter-assay variability in the measurement of GH and IGF-I levels.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Acromegaly</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Acromegaly peri- and post-op patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>All patients will undergo the same procedures throughout the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OGTT</intervention_name>
    <description>An OGTT is a test that lowers growth hormone in the body to very low levels for a short time in order to see how low the growth hormone levels are in your blood.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Acromegaly peri- and post-op patients</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Enrollment will include subjects diagnosed with acromegaly caused by GH secreting adenomas
        who undergo surgical treatment for their disease provided they meet all inclusion/exclusion
        criteria.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or Female age 18-90

          -  Diagnosed with acromegaly from a pituitary adenoma visualized by MRI, and with
             elevated IGF-1 levels compared to age and gender matched control values and nadir GH
             response to OGTT&gt;1mg/L

          -  Having already agreed to undergo surgical resection of their pituitary adenoma prior
             to study entry

          -  Must provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to complete the protocol due to intercurrent medical or psychiatric illness

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding

          -  Use of insulin

          -  Use of estrogen, progesterone, testosterone or thyroid hormone will be allowed as long
             as the dose is stable during the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Odelia Cooper, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Vivian Hwe, BS</last_name>
    <phone>424-315-4489</phone>
    <email>hwev@cshs.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center, Pituitary Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90048</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 15, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 15, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 16, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Odelia Cooper</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine, Division of Endocrinology, Diabetes, and Metabolism</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acromegaly</keyword>
  <keyword>OGTT</keyword>
  <keyword>post-op</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acromegaly</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

