<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00442052</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PA325-101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00442052</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>To Compare the Gastroprotective Effects and Pharmacokinetic Profile of PA Versus Enteric-Coated Aspirin</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label, Investigator-Blinded, Randomized, Parellel Group Study to Compare the Gastroprotective Effects and Pharmacokinetic Profile of PA 325 Versus Enteric-Coated Aspirin.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>POZEN</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>POZEN</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary: To compare the gastroprotective effects of a once-daily dose of PA 325 combination
      tablet combining 325 mg pH sensitive aspirin and 20 mg immediate release omeprazole versus a
      once-daily dose of 325 mg enteric coated aspirin utilizing Lanza scores from endoscopy
      findings in normal healthy volunteers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PA 325 is proposed for the reduction in the risk of aspirin-associated gastrointestinal (GI)
      adverse events in patients requiring daily aspirin. This study is designed as a Proof of
      Concept study to evaluate the gastroprotective effects, pharmacokinetic profile, and safety
      of PA 325 in healthy volunteers.

      To compare the gastroprotective effects of a once-daily dose of PA 325 combination tablet
      combining 325 mg pH-sensitive aspirin and 20 mg immediate release omeprazole versus a
      once-daily dose of 325 mg enteric coated aspirin utilizing Lanza scores from endoscopy
      findings in normal healthy volunteers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date>January 2007</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare the gastroprotective effects of a once-daily dose of PA 325</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the safety and GI tolerability including ulcerogenic potential, the pharmacokinetic profile, and the effect on gastric pH of PA 325</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>80</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>aspirin</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>omeprazole</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. A subject will be eligible for inclusion in this study if all of the following
             criteria apply:

               -  Subject is a male or non-pregnant female

               -  Subject is 50-75 years of age

               -  Subject does not currently smoke

               -  Physical status within normal limits of age and consistent with observations at
                  screening

               -  BMI of 20-30 kg/m2

          2. Female subjects are eligible for participation in the study if they are of:

               -  Non-childbearing potential (i.e., physiologically incapable of becoming
                  pregnant); or,

               -  Childbearing potential, have a negative pregnancy test (urine) at screening, and
                  at least one of the following applies or is agreed to by the subject:

                    -  Complete abstinence from intercourse for at least 14 days prior to first
                       dose of study medication, throughout the study, and for 30 days after
                       completion of the study

                    -  Female sterilization or sterilization of male partner; or,

                    -  Hormonal contraception by oral route, implant, injectable, vaginal ring; or,

                    -  Any intrauterine device (IUD) with published data showing that the lowest
                       expected failure rate is less than 1% per year;

                    -  Double barrier method (2 physical barriers or 1 physical barrier plus
                       spermicide); or

                    -  Any other method with published data showing that the lowest expected
                       failure rate is less than 1% per year

          3. Each subject must be able to understand and comply with study procedures required of a
             subject and is able and willing to provide written informed consent prior to any study
             procedures being performed

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of hypersensitivity to omeprazole or to another proton-pump inhibitor

          2. History of allergic reaction or intolerance to aspirin or any NSAIDs and/or subject
             has a history of NSAID-induced symptoms of asthma, rhinitis, and/or nasal polyps

          3. Participation in any study of an investigational treatment in the 4 weeks before Day 1
             dosing

          4. Presence of uncontrolled acute or chronic medical illness, e.g. gastrointestinal
             disorder, diabetes, hypertension, thyroid disorder, depression and/or infection that
             would endanger a subject if they were to participate in the study

          5. Gastrointestinal disorder or surgery leading to impaired drug absorption

          6. Evidence of uncontrolled, or unstable cardio- or cerebrovascular disorder, which in
             the investigator’s opinion would endanger a subject if they were to participate in the
             study

          7. Schizophrenia or bipolar disorder

          8. Use of any concomitant medication not approved by the study physician during the
             washout period and during the study conduct

          9. Serious blood coagulation disorder including use of systemic anticoagulants

         10. Subjects who donated 50 to 499 mL of blood within 30 days and more than 499 mL within
             56 days prior to dosing

         11. Subjects who, through completion of the study, would have donated in excess of:

               -  500 mL of blood in 14 days;

               -  1,500 mL of blood in 180 days;

               -  2,500 mL of blood in 1 year.

         12. Baseline endoscopy showing any gastric or duodenal mucosal abnormality (hemorrhages,
             ulcers or erosions)

         13. Gastric pH &gt; 3 at screening

         14. Screening laboratory value for ALT, AST &gt;2 times the upper limit of normal

         15. Estimated creatinine clearance &lt; 30 ml/min

         16. Other than noted specifically, any screening laboratory value that is clinically
             significant in the investigator’s opinion and would endanger a subject if they were to
             participate in the study

         17. History of hepatitis B or C, a positive test for hepatitis B surface antigen,
             hepatitis C antibody, a history of HIV infection, or demonstration of HIV antibodies

         18. History of malignancy, treated or untreated, within the past 5 years, with the
             exception of successfully treated basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin

         19. Subjects who have previously been a screen failure in this study

         20. Subject has excessive alcohol use (&gt; 2 units per day on average; for example 2 bottles
             of beer, two glasses of wine, 2 ounces of liquor/spirits), or recent history (in the
             past 3 months) suggestive of alcohol or drug abuse or dependence.

         21. Subject has ingested grapefruit or grapefruit juice within 10 days of dosing or will
             ingest grapefruit or grapefruit juice during the duration of the study.

         22. Positive illicit drug screen
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gaetano Morelli, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>MDS Pharma Services</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>POZEN</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27517</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MDS Pharma Services</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H4R2N6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 27, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 28, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 1, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 28, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 28, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 1, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Gastroprotective effects</keyword>
  <keyword>Aspirin</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aspirin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Omeprazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

