<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00442130</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>06-196</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00442130</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reduced Intensity Stem Cell Transplantation for Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia Followed by Vaccination</brief_title>
  <official_title>Reduced Intensity Stem Cell Transplantation for Advanced Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia Followed by Vaccination With Lethally Irradiated Autologous Tumor Cells Admixed With Granulocyte Macrophage-colony Stimulating Factor Secreting K562 Cells</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to assess the safety and immune activity of a vaccine
      made from the participant's own cancer cells, when administered after a reduced intensity
      transplant. In recent years, researchers at Dana-Farber Cancer Institute have discovered that
      vaccines made from a patients's own cancer cells, that have been engineered in the laboratory
      to produce a protein called GM-CSF, can be effective in stimulating a powerful immune
      response specific to that cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  This study can be divided into four phases: 1) Screening; 2) Reduced intensity
           transplant phase; 3) Vaccinations (cycle 1 and cycle 2:each cycle lasts 7 weeks) and 4)
           Vaccine completion.

        -  Screening Phase: After signing the consent form, participants will be asked to undergo
           some screening tests and procedures to find out if they are eligible to participate in
           the study. These tests and procedures are likely to be part of regular cancer care and
           may be done even if the patient does not take part in the research study. It is
           important to note that if insufficient numbers of the participant's leukemia cells to
           generate vaccine were collected on the CLL collection and banking study (DF/HCC study
           06-200), then they will not be eligible to participate in this study.

        -  Allogeneic reduced intensity stem cell transplant phase: The transplant phase of the
           study will begin when the participant is admitted to the hospital to receive
           chemotherapy and stem cell transplant. The minimum duration of hospitalization for the
           procedure is approximately 8 days. Undergoing transplant involves the following
           procedures and treatments: Central intravenous catheter; chemotherapy; medications to
           prevent graft versus host disease (GVHD); medication to prevent infections; physical
           exams; blood tests and bone marrow biopsy and aspirate.

        -  Vaccination Phase: Vaccinations will be given in two cycles, of seven weeks each, that
           are identical with the exception of when they are administered. Cycle 1 vaccination will
           begin approximately one month after the stem cells have been infused, provided there is
           no significant evidence of GVHD. Cycle 2 vaccination will be being approximately one
           month after discontinuing tacrolimus, provided there is no evidence of severe acute or
           chronic GVHD. The vaccine will be given 6 times over a period of two months. The
           participant will receive vaccination shots once weekly for 3 vaccines and then every
           other week for 3 vaccines.

        -  Skin biopsies will be done after the first and after the fifth vaccinations. Current
           status of the participants CLL will be assessed to determine how the disease has
           responded to transplant and vaccination. These tests include analysis of bone marrow and
           blood tests.

        -  Vaccine completion phase: After one cycle of vaccination is completed, the participant
           will return to the outpatient clinic monthly for check-ups for 6 visits, to monitor the
           effects of the vaccine.

        -  Since this trial involves the use of genetically modified cells, it is recommended that
           participants on this trial undergo annual checkups for at least 20 years, in order to
           monitor for long term effects of the vaccination treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the safety and toxicity of vaccination with lethally irradiated autologous CLL cells admixed with GM-562 cells following reduced intensity allogeneic stem cell transplant for CLL patients with advanced disease.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To characterize the biologic activity in response to vaccination with lethally irradiated autologous CLL cells admixed with GM-562 cells, following reduced intensity allogeneic stem cell transplant</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>to estimate duration of disease response, disease free and overall survival.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Lymphocytic Leukemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GM-K562 Vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Biological/Vaccine: GM-K562 vaccine The vaccine will be administered over 1 cycle of 7 weeks, that begins 1 month after stem cell transplant. The vaccine will be given 6 times over 2 months -- once a week for three weeks then every other week for 3 vaccines.
Procedure/Surgery: stem cell transplantation Participants will be admitted to the hospital for approximately 8 days to receive chemotherapy and stem cell transplantation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GM-K562 vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>The vaccine will be administered over 1 cycle of 7 weeks, that begins 1 month after stem cell transplant. The vaccine will be given 6 times over 2 months -- once a week for three weeks then every other week for 3 vaccines.</description>
    <arm_group_label>GM-K562 Vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>stem cell transplantation</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be admitted to the hospital for approximately 8 days to receive chemotherapy and stem cell transplantation</description>
    <arm_group_label>GM-K562 Vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Advanced CLL, defined as no response or progressive disease during standard nucleoside
             analogue based regimen; or, evidence of progressive disease within 24 months of
             completion of nucleoside analogue regimen; or, intolerance to fludarabine; or, failure
             to achieve complete remission following salvage regimen.

          -  no sites of adenopathy &gt; 5cm

          -  (8/8) HLA matched related or unrelated donor available.

          -  Must have prior banked tumor, collected by peripheral blood draw, leukapheresis, bone
             marrow biopsy or by lymph node dissection, per DF/HCC protocol 06-200

          -  ECOG performance status 0-2

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Serum creatinine greater than or equal to 2.0mg/dl

          -  ALT or AST greater than or equal to 3x ULN

          -  Total bilirubin greater than or equal to 2.0mg/dl (except for patients with Gilbert's
             syndrome)

          -  Cardiac ejection fraction greater than or equal to 30%

          -  HIV infection

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Catherine J. Wu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 27, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 27, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 1, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 25, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 25, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Catherine Wu, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GM-CSF</keyword>
  <keyword>GM-K562</keyword>
  <keyword>vaccine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphocytic, Chronic, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

