<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00448318</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>WKG_07_BB</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00448318</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the Effects of Music Interventions on Hospitalised People With Dementia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluating the Effects of Music Interventions on Hospitalised People With Dementia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Ageing Research Institute, Australia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Ageing Research Institute, Australia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Dementing syndromes are, for the most part, incurable. People with dementia become highly
      dependent and frequently have to move from their homes into residential aged care facilities.

      Medications aimed at reducing the severity of a number of symptoms associated with the
      different types of dementia have had only modest success.

      Increasingly, people with dementia, their families and carers are turning to supplementary or
      alternative approaches to the management of their symptoms. There are many published reports
      describing the successful use of music therapy in reducing the severity of many symptoms of
      dementia. These include reports of improved memory, improved language skills, reduced anxiety
      and depression, reductions in agitation and disruptive behaviours and better social
      relationships with family, peers and carers. However, the quality of evidence they provide
      for the most part fails meet the standards of evidence required by health care providers.
      This clinical trial will examine the effects of a music therapy intervention.

      The study will recruit 180 patients in sub-acute hospital wards. Participants will be
      randomly placed in groups that receive either occupational therapy or music therapy. Before
      the therapy programs begin, we will use questionnaires to measure memory function, language
      ability, orientation and mood. We will also record brain activity from the surface of the
      scalp, blood pressure and pulse to examine physiological responses. The same measures will be
      repeated after the 3 weeks of therapy to determine whether there has been any improvement in
      the symptoms of the participants and whether the group that had music therapy showed greater
      improvement than the group that had occupational therapy. We will make a video recording
      during one therapy session to allow us to observe levels of engagement and to assess changes
      in facial expressions. This will provide information about the immediate effects of music on
      mood and social interaction. The information we collect about brain activity and blood
      pressure will help us to understand how music therapy might bring about changes in the
      symptoms of dementia. This understanding will be useful in developing better applications of
      music therapy. It will also add to our current knowledge about how the various diseases cause
      the problems they do.

      In summary, the primary aim of the project is to determine whether the reported effects of
      music therapy are supported by objective evidence.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Dementia presents a significant health problem throughout the world. We will
      compare the effects of a music therapy intervention and an occupational therapy intervention
      in a randomised controlled trial conducted with hospitalised older people with dementia.

      The study will employ physiological, psychometric and observer-rated measures to monitor
      change over time in a range of parameters including cognitive and behavioural responses, mood
      and agitation, CNS function, facial expression and blood pressure. The battery of
      psychometric instruments consists of well-validated and reliable measures. Cognitive status
      will be measured using The Mini-Mental State Exam (Folstein et al, 1975) and the Hierarchic
      Dementia Scale (Cole and Dastoor, 1996) Mood will be assessed using the Geriatric Depression
      Scale (Yesavage et al., 1983). A wide range of behaviours will be assessed with the
      Cohen-Mansfield Agitation Inventory (CMAI) (Cohen-Mansfield, J., 1986). To monitor changes
      related to the music and non-music interventions, we will employ the EEG methods that will
      detect changes in dementia-related generalised, global slowing of the EEG as well as more
      localised changes at sites in anterior and posterior regions of both cerebral hemispheres.
      EEG-coherence methods will be used to assess intrahemispheric and interhemispheric functional
      interactions. We will also record auditory evoked potentials to evaluate changes in the
      attentional status of participants. This will provide data that will detect change over time
      in response to the interventions. The Facial Activation Coding System (Ekman &amp; Friesen, 1978)
      allows systematic analysis of facial expressions from video-taped recordings. It has been
      used with people with dementia to provide valid and reliable quantitative estimates of pain
      states (Hadjistavropoulos et al., 2000). It will be employed here to quantitatively evaluate
      changes in facial expression that occur during the intervention sessions. This will allow us
      to observe within group changes and between group differences in the range of expressive
      responses. Changes in blood pressure will provide a means of evaluating physiological
      responses to the interventions.

      AIMS: The primary aim of the present study is to determine whether the symptomatic
      improvements attributed to music therapy are supported by empirical evidence derived from a
      battery of psychometric and observational measures. A second aim is to determine whether
      neurophysiological measures (EEG frequency, EEG-coherence, EP) and vascular activity (blood
      pressure) reflect central nervous system and autonomic changes that directly correlate with
      reductions in dementia-related symptoms.

      Specifically, the study will investigate the following hypotheses –

        1. Music employed as a therapeutic medium will reduce symptomatic cognitive, behavioural,
           emotional and functional deficits associated with dementia.

        2. Symptomatic changes will correlate with physiological changes. METHODOLOGY: This study
           will take advantage of an established collaborative network between the Department of
           Psychiatry, The University of Melbourne, The National Ageing Research Institute, The
           Cognitive, Dementia and Memory Service (CDAMS) at The Royal Melbourne Hospital and the
           CDAMS at the St George’s Hospital campus of St Vincent’s Health. The research team
           covers several disciplines including aged psychiatry, neuropsychiatry, geriatric
           medicine, neuropsychology, behavioural neuroscience, electrophysiology, music and music
           therapy.

      SUBJECTS: One hundred and eighty sub-acute patients with mild, moderate and severe dementia
      will be recruited from RMH (Royal Park Campus) and St Georges Hospital over a period of 18
      months. There will be a potential pool of approximately 800 patients over the planned 18
      month data collection period. We anticipate that with ineligibility of 30%, an attrition rate
      of up to 20-25% and time lost to holidays and a participation rate of 70%, our total cohort
      will be approximately 260, leaving substantial redundancy over the numbers required to power
      the study.

      Testing will commence when each patient has settled for one week when the majority of
      illnesses are stabilised and medications adjusted. A full medical assessment will be
      available for all participants in order to evaluate medical comorbidity, cognitive status and
      dementia diagnosis. This information will include results of physical examination, blood
      tests, Ct scan, informant history and neuropsychological assessment which includes the
      administration of the MMSE (Folstein et al. 1975) and classification according to DSM-IV,
      ICD-10 and NINCDS-ARDRA criteria, the current research gold standard for dementia diagnosis
      (American Psychiatric Association, 1994). Consensus diagnosis with information available will
      be made by the clinicians involved in the study. Primary diagnoses, comorbidities and
      medications will be monitored. Recruitment will be undertaken in accordance with procedures
      approved by The Mental Health Research and Ethics Committee, Melbourne Health Network, the St
      Vincent’s Health Research Ethics Committee. Given the nature of our participants’ diagnoses,
      it is recognised that they cannot give informed consent.

      PROCEDURE: Participants will be randomly assigned to either the music intervention group or
      the control (occupational therapy) group. Both groups will undertake three 50 minute
      intervention sessions per week for three weeks giving a total of nine interventions. Each
      session will be conducted with groups of 4 - 6 participants.

      Pre and post measures will be made on the day prior to the therapy session and the day after
      the last therapy session. These measures are as follows:

        -  EEG recording made that will yield slow/fast ratio data and resting state and
           music-listening EEG-coherence data and auditory evoked potential data.

        -  Four blood pressure and pulse readings taken at hourly intervals to establish a mean
           baseline.

        -  Questionnaires - Mini Mental State Examination, Hierarchic Dementia Scale, Geriatric
           Depression Scale will be administered prior to the first intervention session and after
           the ninth intervention session.

      Pre and post testing involving will take approximately 90 minutes in total. Video recordings
      will be made using two cameras during the fifth therapy session. The first camera will be
      located on a tripod such that the whole group, including the therapist, will be continuously
      in frame to facilitate subsequent observations about participation and social interactions.
      The second camera will be hand held and will take film of the faces of each participant
      during the session for subsequent coding of changes in facial expressions using the Facial
      Activation Coding System.

      Further information will be compiled by members of the research team. This information, used
      to monitor comorbid conditions and pre and post changes, will be derived from patient
      records. It will be collected the following instruments

        -  The Clinical Dementia rating Scale (Hughes et al, 1982)

        -  The Barthel Index (Mahoney and Barthel, 1965)

        -  The Cumulative Illness Rating Scale (Linn et al 1968).

        -  The Neuropsychiatric Inventory (Cummings, 1997) Finally, The Cohen-Mansfield Agitation
           Inventory (Weiner et al, 1998) will administered pre and post intervention by a
           researcher in consultation with nursing staff.

      In addition to the above measures, the full range of treatments outside the music therapy
      interventions received by participants in both groups will be documented. This will enable
      the researchers to monitor the levels of therapist contact experienced by participants in
      both the music therapy and control groups. It will also provide data that may be used as
      covariates in a number of statistical analyses.

      INCLUSION CRITERIA:People with a clinical diagnosis of dementia who are currently in
      sub-acute aged care hospital wards; EXCLUSION CRITERIA: delirium; acute medical conditions
      (eg pneumonia and cardiac failure) where it is likely that participation is contra-indicated;
      primary psychiatric conditions; severe hearing impairment; RANDOMISATION PROCEDURES: A
      stratified randomization procedure will be used to ensure that both the experimental and
      control groups are at least broadly homogeneous with respect to cognitive status. The
      procedure will be applied separately within each of the two hospital facilities with
      allocation made progressively as people enter the study. After consent has been acquired and
      the pre-intervention measures taken, participants will be coded, stratified into two levels
      according to MMSE scores then allocated to treatment groups according to the computer
      generated random sequences. The sequences will be generated using research randomiser, an
      online web-based program (http://www.randomizer.org/form.htm). The person responsible for
      implementing the allocation sequence will be either a member of the hospital staff or a NARI
      staff member who has no involvement in any other aspect of the study. That person will be
      responsible for de-identifying participants using a conventional coding system. Baseline and
      post-intervention data collection procedures will be administered by persons who have no
      other role in the project procedures and will remain blind to treatment allocation. Baseline
      testing will take place before allocation. As they will have no contact with participants
      during the intervention procedures and because patient identification is coded by an
      independent person, the blind can be maintained. As added protection, psychometric
      instruments (MMSE, HDS and GDS) will be assessed only once by an assessor for each
      participant. That is, if Assessor A administers the instruments with Participant A for
      baseline testing, Assessor B will administer the instruments post-intervention for
      Participant A. This will avoid any unintended prior knowledge of individual participant
      performance and so help to ensure post-treatment blinding with respect to active versus
      control group assignment. The instruments to be used have clear and established
      implementation procedures with high inter-rater reliability. After the post-intervention
      assessments have been taken for each participant, the assessors will be asked to nominate
      which group they thought the participant was in. A simple statistical analysis will be able
      to detect whether there is a significant bias in group assignment or whether assignment is no
      better than chance. Bias may arise, for example, if one treatment group has an outcome that
      strongly differentiates it from the other.. It is noted that, while there are other potential
      stratification factors (eg age, gender, diagnoses), the use of more factors rapidly becomes
      unfeasible. Because current cognitive status has some prognostic relevance, particularly with
      regard to music therapy, it has been decided to use that measure as the sole stratification
      factor.

      STATISTICAL ANALYSES: Given the multiple dependent variables being monitored in this study, a
      MANOVA will be used to test for between-group differences with post-hoc univariate
      comparisons as required. Based on previous studies at NARI referred to above using similar
      measures we expect that 90 subjects per group will detect a 25% change in mean values with at
      least 80% power (alpha .05). For test-retest data, a two way repeated measures MANOVA (group,
      time) will be used to examine changes over the duration of the intervention, group effects
      and the interaction between these factors. Bivariate correlations and multiple regression
      analyses will be used to explore the relationships between the various measures (EEG, FACS,
      MMSE, HDS, self-report and observational measures). Similar comparisons can also be made for
      change scores within each domain of parameters (objective, psychometric, self-report) and the
      way they co-vary over time.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date>October 2008</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mini Mental State Examination: baseline cf. post intervention scores.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hierarchic Dementia Scale: baseline cf. post intervention scores.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Geriatric Depression Scale: baseline cf. post intervention scores.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Note: post intervention measures taken within 24 hours of final therapeutic intervention session</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EEG fast/slow ratio: baseline cf. post intervention scores.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EEG Coherence: baseline cf. post intervention scores.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EEG evoked potentials:baseline cf. post intervention scores.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Note: post intervention measures taken within 24 hours of final therapeutic intervention session</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>180</enrollment>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <condition>Alzheimer's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Dementia, Vascular</condition>
  <condition>Lewy Body Disease</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Music Therapy</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of dementia

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  delirium

          -  acute medical conditions (eg pneumonia, cardiac failure)

          -  primary psychiatric conditions (eg schizophrenia)

          -  severe hearing impairment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jonathan B Barber, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Ageing Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jonathan B Barber, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+61 3 8387 2638</phone>
    <email>b.barber@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>John W Barlow, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+61 3 83872296</phone>
    <email>j.barlow@nari.unimelb.edu.au</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Ageing Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Parkville</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3052</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>John W Barlow, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+61 3 8387 2296</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jonathan B Barber, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 14, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 14, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 16, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 14, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 14, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 16, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Controlled clinical trial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lewy Body Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dementia, Vascular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

