<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00446251</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>25668-A</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>04-0927-A 05</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00446251</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Rituximab and Mycophenolate Mofetil (MMF) on Highly Sensitized Patients Awaiting Renal Transplant</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Highly Sensitized Patients: Effects of Rituximab and Mycophenolate Mofetil (MMF) On Anti-Human Leukocyte Antigen (HLA) Antibody Levels In Patients Awaiting Cadaveric Renal Transplant.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Genentech, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Washington</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a 12-month phase 2, prospective, open label study to evaluate the effect of rituximab
      with mycophenolate mofetil (MMF)on the PRA of 14 highly sensitized patients who just
      completed an 8 month trial of MMF treatment alone. PRA values obtained at study enrollment
      and at 6 and 12 months on combined therapy as well as the rates of transplant will be
      compared and evaluated using descriptive analysis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND: Patients who have been exposed to human tissue by prior transplants, blood
      transfusion or pregnancy may develop and maintain anti-bodies against these foreign human
      cells (SENSITIZATION). As a result of sensitization these patients are more likely to reject
      an organ donated from an individual who possesses a similar human cell marker
      (ANTIGENIC)profile. These sensitized patients will remain on the kidney transplant waiting
      list up to twice as long as those who are not pre-sensitized.

      The Panel of Reactive Antibodies (PRA) is a test panel used to measure the patient reactivity
      to human leukocyte cell antigens (HLA). A PRA of 75% means the patient reacted to 75% of the
      antigens on the panel. A high PRA indicates that the subject already has antibodies and is
      highly SENSITIZED. Spontaneous decreases in PRA titers rarely occur. Thus the probability of
      transplantation in sensitized patients is significantly decreased.

      RATIONALE for use of Rituximab:

      By reducing specific B-cell populations Rituximab is currently used as a treatment in
      auto-immune diseases such as lupus erythematosus and rheumatoid arthritis and some cancers
      such as B-cell non-Hodgkin's lymphoma. It has been reported to have a potential roll in
      decreasing anti-human lymphocyte (HLA) antibodies post transplant. More studies are needed to
      assess its possible benefit among pre-transplant patients. Vierira et al. [&quot;Rituxan for
      reduction of anti-HLA antibodies in patients awaiting renal transplantation&quot;, Am J
      Transplantation 2002;2:A870] reported on the use of rituximab in sensitized patients. Nine
      patients on dialysis with a PRA &gt; 50% were treated with rituximab (n=3 per group) at 50, 150,
      or 375mg/m2. No significant change was seen in WBC, hemoglobin, platelet count, chemistry,
      liver enzymes or CMV IgG titers. At three days and 6 months after infusion there was a
      decline in the B cell count compared to pre-infusion levels. In 44%, a decline in PRA was
      seen. The patients receiving the higher doses had a larger decrement in antibody titers.

      GENENTECH, INC. will provide Rituximab, labeled for investigational use. Rituximab is
      formulated for IV administration as a sterile product as a sterile, preservative-free liquid
      concentrate for intravenous (IV) administration.

      STUDY DESIGN: This is a 12-month phase 2, prospective, open label study to evaluate the
      effect of rituximab with mycophenolate mofetil (MMF)on the PRA of 14 highly sensitized
      patients who just completed an 8 month trial of MMF treatment alone. PRA values obtained at
      study enrollment and at 6 and 12 months on combined therapy as well as the rates of
      transplant will be compared and evaluated using descriptive analysis.

      Primary Endpoints: The number of subjects who experience a decrement from baseline in their
      Panel of Reactive Antibody values (PRA I, PRA II) or cPRA (calculated PRA when available) at:
      baseline, 6 and 12 months of study initiation.

      Secondary Endpoints: The number of subjects who received a transplant The number of subjects
      with a negative crossmatch if transplanted.

      STUDY POPULATION: Patients on the kidney transplant waiting list who are currently receiving
      hemodialysis and who have a Panel of Reactive Antibodies (PRA) titer levels over 50% after
      completing 8 months of mycophenolate mofetil (MMF) treatment alone.

      SCREENING: Subjects will be consented, then screened clinically for occurrence of infection,
      Tuberculosis exposure and for protective antibodies in response to prior vaccination.

      RITUXIMAB DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION: The Rituximab dose is 1000mg (1gm) given as a single
      I.V. infusion for 2 doses (days 1 and 15). No extra dosing will be given. Rituximab may be
      administered in an outpatient setting. Hypersensitivity reactions may occur. Premedication,
      consisting of acetaminophen (1gm) and diphenhydramine (50mg or equivalent dose) by mouth 30
      to 60 minutes prior to the start of an infusion will be considered before each infusion of
      Rituximab. Rituximab will not be re-administered after initial dose regimen.

      (MMF) Mycophenolate mofetil DOSAGE AND ADMINISTRATION: Dosing of MMF will continue at the
      highest tolerated dose the subject was taking at the completion of the parent study: &quot;Highly
      Sensitized Patients: effects of mycophenolate mofetil (MMF) on anti- human lymphocyte
      antibody (HLA) levels in patients awaiting renal transplant&quot;. The dose will be adjusted
      according to standard practices, gastrointestinal tolerance and WBC count.

      CLINICAL AND LABORATORY SAFETY EVALUATIONS:

      SCREENING:

        -  Medical history and documentation of the rationale for treatment of the patient's
           disease with Rituximab.

        -  Pregnancy test (serum or urine) for women of childbearing potential must be done prior
           to initial Rituximab treatment date.

        -  Medical history to include: age, sex, prior transplant history, blood transfusion
           history, prior pregnancy history, history of autoimmune disease, infection history over
           the last 5 years, and immunization history.

        -  Physical examination, including vital signs, and performance status.

        -  Hematology (within 2 weeks of treatment): complete blood count (CBC) with differential
           and platelet count.

        -  Serum Chemistries: glucose, blood urea nitrogen, serum creatinine, uric acid, total
           bilirubin, alkaline phosphatase, low density lipoprotein, high density lipoprotein,
           total protein, albumin, aspartate aminotransferase(AST), alanine aminotransferase (ALT),
           and serum calcium.

        -  Serology Testing as appropriate: Hepatitis B, Hepatitis C, HIV

        -  IgG and IgM total antibody counts.

        -  Drug Monitoring: Baseline = pre-infusion. Serum drug levels for Ritux will also be
           measured for safety. Human Anti-Rituximab Antibody (HACA)is a test for presence of
           antibodies against rituximab.

        -  Lymphocyte Sub Group: A sub-group of type-B lymphocytes called 'CD-19 Cells' are
           specifically impacted by Rituximab and will be used as a marker of drug efficacy.

      ON GOING EVALUATIONS Post -Treatment:

      For safety the total IgG and IgM levels will be monitored and IgG supplemented if levels
      decrease below normal values. Additionally WBC counts that drop below 3.0 will result in
      changes in the MMF dose. If serious infections occur MMF will be discontinued. Patients will
      be followed for one year after initial rituximab infusion.

        -  Hematology: monitor CBC + differential weekly for 1 month then monthly

        -  Monthly: PRAs will be monitored monthly through the 12th month of the study. The
           standard PRA value is the sum of anti-bodies produced by 2 main groups of lymphocytes;
           Class I and Class II. We will have PRA I and PRA II antibody classes reported separately
           as well as PRA reporting using a calculation (cPRA).

        -  Quarterly: Serology Testing as appropriate: Hepatitis B, Hepatitis C, HIV, IgG and IgM
           total antibody counts.

        -  Monitor Serum Ritux and HACA levels at baseline, 6 months and 9 months.

        -  Monitor CD19+ B-cells at baseline, weeks 1, 2, 4, months 3, 6, 9 and 12.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>Yes</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The Number of Subjects Who Experience a Decrease in Their Panel of Reactive Antibodies (PRA) at 6 Months Post Rituximab Infusion.</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 6 from start of study</time_frame>
    <description>the number of subjects who experience a decrease in their Panel of Reactive Antibodies (PRA) at 6 months and 12 months post Rituximab infusion</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Number of Subjects Who Experience a Change From Baseline in Their Panel of Reactive Antibody (PRA) Titers at 12 Months Post Rituximab Infusion.</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 12 from start of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Number of Subjects With a Negative Crossmatch at the Time of Transplant.</measure>
    <time_frame>Month 12 from start of study</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Kidney Failure, Chronic</condition>
  <condition>Diabetic Nephropathies</condition>
  <condition>Glomerulonephritis, IGA</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension, Renal</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituximab</intervention_name>
    <description>Rituximab dose is 1,000 mg given as an IV infusion every two weeks for 2 doses (days 1 and 15).</description>
    <other_name>Rituxan, Rituximab</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mycophenolate mofetil (MMF)</intervention_name>
    <description>Cellcept is continued from prior study, taken 500 - 1,000 mg BID, P.O.</description>
    <other_name>mycophenolate mofetil, MMF, Cellcept</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age range 18 - 75, inclusive

          -  Able and willing to give written informed consent and comply with the requirements of
             the study protocol

          -  Outpatient status

          -  Patients with a Panel of Reactive Antibodies (PRA) over 10% after an 8-month trial of
             MMF monotherapy

          -  Patients with updated immunizations for tetanus, influenza, hepatitis B, pneumococcus

          -  Patients with a negative purified protein derivative(PPD ) screen for tuberculosis
             (TB)within the last 6 months. If subject has a prior history of TB or positive PPD,
             documentation of adequate treatment is required.

          -  Women who are of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test
             prior to being enrolled in the study and agree to use a medically acceptable method of
             contraception throughout the study and for twelve months (1 year) after completion of
             treatment.

          -  Men must agree to use an acceptable method of birth control during treatment and for
             twelve months (1 year) after completion of treatment.

          -  Liver enzymes ALT and AST less than 2 times the normal limit.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Active infection

          -  Receipt of live vaccine within 4 weeks prior to first infusion.

          -  Previous treatment with rituximab (MabThera® / Rituxan®)

          -  History of multiple recurrent infections defined as more than 3 urinary tract
             infections, 2 episodes of pneumonia or 3 episodes of otitis/sinusitis in one year, or
             more than two dialysis line or peritoneal infections within one year.

          -  Infection with hepatitis C virus (HCV) or hepatitis B virus(HBV) or human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV), lack of documentation of treatment of a positive PPD,
             pregnant or breast-feeding, baseline leukopenia, white blood cell count (WBC) less
             than 4.0, thrombocytopenia (platelet count less than 100,000/mm) or difficult to treat
             anemia, a hematocrit chronically less than 32 on intravenous iron and EPO
             (erythropoietin) therapy, history of severe allergic or anaphylactic reactions to
             humanized or murine monoclonal antibodies.

          -  Concomitant malignancies or previous malignancies within the last five years, with the
             exception of adequately treated basal or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin or
             carcinoma in situ of the cervix.

          -  History of psychiatric disorder

          -  Significant cardiac or pulmonary disease (including obstructive pulmonary disease)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Connie L Davis, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aranda JM Jr, Scornik JC, Normann SJ, Lottenberg R, Schofield RS, Pauly DF, Miles M, Hill JA, Sleasman JW, Skoda-Smith S. Anti-CD20 monoclonal antibody (rituximab) therapy for acute cardiac humoral rejection: a case report. Transplantation. 2002 Mar 27;73(6):907-10.</citation>
    <PMID>11923690</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dafoe DC, Bromberg JS, Grossman RA, Tomaszewski JE, Zmijewski CM, Perloff LJ, Naji A, Asplund MW, Alfrey EJ, Sack M, et al. Renal transplantation despite a positive antiglobulin crossmatch with and without prophylactic OKT3. Transplantation. 1991 Apr;51(4):762-8.</citation>
    <PMID>2014527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Garrett HE Jr, Groshart K, Duvall-Seaman D, Combs D, Suggs R. Treatment of humoral rejection with rituximab. Ann Thorac Surg. 2002 Oct;74(4):1240-2.</citation>
    <PMID>12400781</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gloor JM, Lager DJ, Moore SB, Pineda AA, Fidler ME, Larson TS, Grande JP, Schwab TR, Griffin MD, Prieto M, Nyberg SL, Velosa JA, Textor SC, Platt JL, Stegall MD. ABO-incompatible kidney transplantation using both A2 and non-A2 living donors. Transplantation. 2003 Apr 15;75(7):971-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12698082</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hack N, Angra S, Friedman E, McKnight T, Cardella CJ. Anti-idiotypic antibodies from highly sensitized patients stimulate B cells to produce anti-HLA antibodies. Transplantation. 2002 Jun 27;73(12):1853-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12131677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holechek MJ, Hiller JM, Paredes M, Rickard JC, Montgomery RA. Expanding the living organ donor pool: positive crossmatch and ABO incompatible renal transplantation. Nephrol Nurs J. 2003 Apr;30(2):195-204.</citation>
    <PMID>12736998</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jillella AP, Dainer PM, Kallab AM, Ustun C. Treatment of a patient with end-stage renal disease with Rituximab: pharmacokinetic evaluation suggests Rituximab is not eliminated by hemodialysis. Am J Hematol. 2002 Nov;71(3):219-22.</citation>
    <PMID>12410580</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Libetta C, Rampino T, Dal Canton A. Polarization of T-helper lymphocytes toward the Th2 phenotype in uremic patients. Am J Kidney Dis. 2001 Aug;38(2):286-95.</citation>
    <PMID>11479154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maloney DG, Grillo-López AJ, Bodkin DJ, White CA, Liles TM, Royston I, Varns C, Rosenberg J, Levy R. IDEC-C2B8: results of a phase I multiple-dose trial in patients with relapsed non-Hodgkin's lymphoma. J Clin Oncol. 1997 Oct;15(10):3266-74.</citation>
    <PMID>9336364</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miura S, Okazaki H, Satoh T, Amada N, Ohashi Y. Long-term follow-up of living donor renal transplant recipients sensitized after donor specific blood transfusion. Transplant Proc. 2001 Feb-Mar;33(1-2):1221-3.</citation>
    <PMID>11267267</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nitta K, Akiba T, Kawashima A, Kimata N, Miwa N, Nishida E, Uchida K, Honda K, Yumura W, Nihei H. Characterization of TH1/TH2 profile in uremic patients. Nephron. 2002 Jul;91(3):492-5.</citation>
    <PMID>12119483</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reff ME, Carner K, Chambers KS, Chinn PC, Leonard JE, Raab R, Newman RA, Hanna N, Anderson DR. Depletion of B cells in vivo by a chimeric mouse human monoclonal antibody to CD20. Blood. 1994 Jan 15;83(2):435-45.</citation>
    <PMID>7506951</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schweitzer EJ, Wilson JS, Fernandez-Vina M, Fox M, Gutierrez M, Wiland A, Hunter J, Farney A, Philosophe B, Colonna J, Jarrell BE, Bartlett ST. A high panel-reactive antibody rescue protocol for cross-match-positive live donor kidney transplants. Transplantation. 2000 Nov 27;70(10):1531-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11118102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Takeda A, Uchida K, Haba T, Tominaga Y, Katayama A, Kobayashi T, Oikawa T, Morozumi K. Acute humoral rejection of kidney allografts in patients with a positive flow cytometry crossmatch (FCXM). Clin Transplant. 2000;14 Suppl 3:15-20.</citation>
    <PMID>11092347</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yokoyama T, Nitta K, Futatsuyama K, Hayashi T, Honda K, Uchida K, Kawashima A, Yumura W, Nihei H. Identification of T helper cell subsets in continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis patients. Nephron. 2001 Oct;89(2):215-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11549905</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vieira CA, Agarwal A, Book BK, Sidner RA, Bearden CM, Gebel HM, Roggero AL, Fineberg NS, Taber T, Kraus MA, Pescovitz MD. Rituximab for reduction of anti-HLA antibodies in patients awaiting renal transplantation: 1. Safety, pharmacodynamics, and pharmacokinetics. Transplantation. 2004 Feb 27;77(4):542-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15084932</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 9, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 9, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 12, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>December 29, 2009</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2010</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">March 29, 2010</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 30, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 30, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 6, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Dr. Connie Davis</name_title>
    <organization>University of Washington</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Kidney</keyword>
  <keyword>Renal</keyword>
  <keyword>Nephropathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Glomerulonephropathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunosuppression</keyword>
  <keyword>Graft</keyword>
  <keyword>Compatibility</keyword>
  <keyword>Transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>Transplantation, Kidney</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Nephropathies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glomerulonephritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glomerulonephritis, IGA</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension, Renal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Subjects were recruited from the parent study: &quot;Highly Sensitized Patients: effects of mycophenolate mofetil (MMF) on anti-human lymphocyte antibody levels in patients awaiting renal transplant&quot; study&quot; at 8 months if the subject had not experienced a 10% or greater reduction in Panel of Reactive Anti-bodies(PRA.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>Single arm study: all subjects received 2 Rituximab infusions of 1,000 mg. Subjects were kept at their highest tolerated dose of mycophenolate mofetil(MMF)from parent study.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Rituximab Infusion and Mycophenolate Mofetil Group</title>
          <description>Rituximab was administered by IV infusion at a dose of 1000 mg (1 g) on Days 1 and 15 to subjects already on 8 months of oral mycophenolate mofetil mono therapy (@ 500 - 1,000 mg twice daily as tolerated).</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="14">14 subjects were enrolled in this Rituximab-mycophenolic mofetil group.</participants>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="9"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="5"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>On-study Transplants</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Rituximab Infusion Reaction</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Lost to Follow-up</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Rituximab Infusion and Mycophenolate Mofetil Group</title>
          <description>Rituximab was administered by IV infusion at a dose of 1000 mg (1 g) on Days 1 and 15 to subjects already on 8 months of oral mycophenolate mofetil mono therapy (@ 500 - 1,000 mg twice daily as tolerated).</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="14"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="14"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="41.3" spread="8.81"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="14"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>The Number of Subjects Who Experience a Decrease in Their Panel of Reactive Antibodies (PRA) at 6 Months Post Rituximab Infusion.</title>
        <description>the number of subjects who experience a decrease in their Panel of Reactive Antibodies (PRA) at 6 months and 12 months post Rituximab infusion</description>
        <time_frame>Month 6 from start of study</time_frame>
        <population>12 subjects received the full dose of Rituximab AND continued to month 6 post infusion.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Rituximab Infusion and Mycophenolate Mofetil Group</title>
            <description>Rituximab was administered by IV infusion at a dose of 1000 mg (1 g) on Days 1 and 15 to subjects already on 8 months of oral mycophenolate mofetil mono therapy (@ 500 - 1,000 mg twice daily as tolerated).</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>The Number of Subjects Who Experience a Decrease in Their Panel of Reactive Antibodies (PRA) at 6 Months Post Rituximab Infusion.</title>
          <description>the number of subjects who experience a decrease in their Panel of Reactive Antibodies (PRA) at 6 months and 12 months post Rituximab infusion</description>
          <population>12 subjects received the full dose of Rituximab AND continued to month 6 post infusion.</population>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="12"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>The Number of Subjects Who Experience a Change From Baseline in Their Panel of Reactive Antibody (PRA) Titers at 12 Months Post Rituximab Infusion.</title>
        <time_frame>Month 12 from start of study</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Rituximab Infusion and Mycophenolate Mofetil Group</title>
            <description>Rituximab was administered by IV infusion at a dose of 1000 mg (1 g) on Days 1 and 15 to subjects already on 8 months of oral mycophenolate mofetil mono therapy (@ 500 - 1,000 mg twice daily as tolerated).</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>The Number of Subjects Who Experience a Change From Baseline in Their Panel of Reactive Antibody (PRA) Titers at 12 Months Post Rituximab Infusion.</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="12"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>The Number of Subjects With a Negative Crossmatch at the Time of Transplant.</title>
        <time_frame>Month 12 from start of study</time_frame>
        <population>As per protocol each subject was entered with intention to treat.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Rituximab Infusion and Mycophenolate Mofetil Group</title>
            <description>Rituximab was administered by IV infusion at a dose of 1000 mg (1 g) on Days 1 and 15 to subjects already on 8 months of oral mycophenolate mofetil mono therapy (@ 500 - 1,000 mg twice daily as tolerated).</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>The Number of Subjects With a Negative Crossmatch at the Time of Transplant.</title>
          <population>As per protocol each subject was entered with intention to treat.</population>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="12"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Rituximab Infusion and Mycophenolate Mofetil Group</title>
          <description>Rituximab was administered by IV infusion at a dose of 1000 mg (1 g) on Days 1 and 15 to subjects already on 8 months of oral mycophenolate mofetil mono therapy (@ 500 - 1,000 mg twice daily as tolerated).</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="14"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Cardiac disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Chest pain</sub_title>
                <description>Chest pain ensuing after Rituximab infusion in subject with known coronary artery disease.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="14"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <default_assessment>Non-systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="14"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pancreatitis</sub_title>
                <description>7 days post infusion the subject developed acute pancreatitis.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="14"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Immune system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Leukopenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="14"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Infusion reaction</sub_title>
                <description>Two infusion reactions: shortness of breath and backpain with moderately increased body temp and blood pressure.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="14"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>The only disclosure restriction on the PI is that the sponsor can review results communications prior to public release and can embargo communications regarding trial results for a period that is more than 60 days but less than or equal to 180 days. The sponsor cannot require changes to the communication and cannot extend the embargo.</restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. Connie L. Davis</name_or_title>
      <organization>University of Washington</organization>
      <phone>206-598-6079</phone>
      <email>cdavis@u.washington.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

