<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00443326</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20060349</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00443326</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AMG 714 20060349 Multiple Dose Study in Moderate to Severe Psoriasis Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Ascending Dose Study to Evaluate the Safety, Pharmacokinetics, and Efficacy of AMG 714 After Multiple Dose Administration in Subjects With Moderate to Severe Psoriasis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Amgen</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Investigational drug AMG 714 will be given to 66 subjects with moderate to severe psoriasis
      to study safety, pharmacokinetics, and efficacy. Dose levels include 150mg and 300mg and will
      be given to each subject for a total of 6 doses. Each dose for each subject will be given
      once every 2 weeks. Subjects will followed for up to 300 days post the first dose of AMG 714.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Psoriatic Assessment Score Index</measure>
    <time_frame>First 85 Days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>Collected for 300 Days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">22</enrollment>
  <condition>Psoriasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AMG 714</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>AMG 714 will be given as a multiple dose regimen</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AMG 714</intervention_name>
    <description>Dosing Regimen is 6 Doses over 3 Months</description>
    <arm_group_label>AMG 714</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Active but clinically stable, plaque psoriasis.

          -  Psoriasis involving greater than or equal to 10% of the body surface area

          -  A minimum PASI score of 10 obtained during the screening period.

          -  Received at least one previous phototherapy or systemic psoriasis therapy or have been
             a candidate to receive phototherapy or systemic psoriasis therapy in the opinion of
             the investigator.

          -  At least 18 years of age.

          -  Heterosexually active men and women must be willing to practice an effective method of
             contraception (as outlined in section 6.7) as determined by the investigator and
             sponsor for the duration of the study. This includes any washout period and the
             follow-up period.

          -  ALT and AST less than or equal to 2 x the upper limit of normal; hemoglobin greater
             than or equal to 10 g/dL (greater than or equal to 100 g/L in SI units); platelet
             count greater than or equal to 125,000 mm3 (greater than or equal to 125 x109/L in SI
             units); white blood cell count greater than or equal to 3,500 cells/mm3 (greater than
             or equal to 3.5 x109/L in SI units); serum creatinine less than or equal to 2 mg/dL
             (less than or equal to 177 μmol/L in SI units).

          -  Negative for HIV antibodies, hepatitis B surface antigen, and hepatitis C antibodies.

          -  Capable of understanding and giving written, voluntary informed consent before study
             screening.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Active guttate, erythrodermic, or pustular psoriasis at the time of the screening
             visit.

          -  Evidence of skin conditions (eg, eczema) at the time of the screening visit or between
             the screening visit and study drug initiation that would interfere with evaluations of
             the effect of investigational product on psoriasis.

          -  Clinically significant adverse event, infection, or laboratory toxicity, at the time
             of the screening visit or between the screening visit and study drug initiation that
             in the opinion of Amgen or the Investigator would preclude participation in the study.

          -  Clinically significant infection less than or equal to 30 days before the screening
             visit that in the opinion of Amgen or the Investigator would preclude participation in
             the study.

          -  Known positive tuberculin skin test (if not treated with appropriate chemoprophylaxis)
             or recent (within 6 months) exposure to a patient with active tuberculosis.

          -  Any other known infectious process that would, in the investigator's discretion,
             interfere with the subject's ability to participate in the study.

          -  Significant concurrent medical conditions at the time of screening, including:

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension (defined as screening systolic blood pressure measurement of
             greater than 160 mm Hg or a screening diastolic blood pressure of greater than 100 mm
             Hg) confirmed by 2 separate measurements during the screening visit

          -  Myocardial infarction less than or equal to 52 weeks before the screening visit

          -  Unstable angina pectoris

          -  Congestive heart failure

          -  Steroid or oxygen dependent chronic obstructive pulmonary disease

          -  Diagnosis of multiple sclerosis or any other demyelinating disease

          -  Inadequately controlled diabetes mellitus, defined by glycohemoglobin greater than 7.0
             at screening

          -  History of cancer (other than resected and surgically cured cervical cancer, cutaneous
             basal cell, squamous cell carcinoma) less than or equal to 5 years before the
             administration of first dose of investigational product

          -  Open cutaneous ulcers

          -  Any condition that, in the judgment of the investigator, might cause this study to be
             detrimental to the subject.

          -  Any evidence during screening of cutaneous basal or squamous cell carcinoma, or
             melanoma.

          -  Current or history of psychiatric disease that would interfere with the ability to
             comply with the study protocol or give informed consent.

          -  History of alcohol or drug abuse that would interfere with the ability to comply with
             the study protocol.

          -  Previous receipt of etanercept or any other anti-TNF agent(s), alefacept, efalizumab,
             or other investigational biologic agent for psoriasis.

          -  Receipt of any investigational product(s) less than or equal to 30 days before the
             first dose of investigational product in this study.

          -  PUVA therapy less than or equal to 30 days before the first dose of investigational
             product.

          -  UVA therapy less than or equal to 14 days before the first dose of investigational
             product.

          -  UVB therapy less than or equal to 30 days before the first dose of investigational
             product.

          -  Receipt of any other systemic psoriasis therapy or oral or parenteral corticosteroids
             less than or equal to 14 days before the first dose of investigational product.

          -  Topical steroids, topical vitamin A or D analog preparations or anthralin less than or
             equal to 14 days before the first dose of investigational product (exception - topical
             steroids at no higher than moderate strength, according to the package insert, are
             permitted on the scalp, axillae, and groin).

          -  Topical cyclosporin or calcineurin inhibitors such as pimecrolimus (Elidel) and
             tacrolimus (Protopic) less than or equal to 14 days before the first dose of
             investigational product.

          -  Intravenous or oral calcineurin inhibitors such as tacrolimus (Prograf) less than or
             equal to 30 days before the first dose of investigational product.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Amgen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.amgentrials.com</url>
    <description>AmgenTrials clinical trials website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 1, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 1, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 5, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <disposition_first_submitted>December 16, 2015</disposition_first_submitted>
  <disposition_first_submitted_qc>December 16, 2015</disposition_first_submitted_qc>
  <disposition_first_posted type="Estimate">January 20, 2016</disposition_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 16, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 16, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 20, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Psoriasis</keyword>
  <keyword>PASI</keyword>
  <keyword>Skin Biopsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Human Monoclonal Antibody</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted, but a results disposition has been submitted           -->
</clinical_study>

