<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00442455</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ML 18729</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00442455</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Erlotinib,Radiation and Cisplatin in Patients With Complete Resected Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Head and Neck</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I/II Trial of Erlotinib, Radiation Therapy, and Cisplatin in Patients With Complete Resected Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Head and Neck</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Grupo de Investigación Clínica en Oncología Radioterapia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Grupo de Investigación Clínica en Oncología Radioterapia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to determinate the free-progression interval in patients with
      surgically resected locally advanced squamous cell carcinoma of head and neck treated with
      the maximum tolerated dose of the combination of erlotinib, radiation therapy and cisplatin,
      previously established in a safety trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Phase I:

      3 cohorts of 3-6 patients, patients will received:

        -  Erlotinib 100-150 mg/day po for 7 weeks.

        -  Cisplatin 30-40 mg/m2 iv weekly for 7 weeks.

        -  Radiation therapy 63 Gy, five days a week, for 7 weeks. Cohort 1: 3 patients will be
           included in cohort 1.

      If no DLT has been recorded in the first three patients during the 7-weeks treatment, the
      dose level of erlotinib will be escalated to 150 mg and enrollment of cohort 2 will be
      initiated.

      If DLT has been recorded in one out of the first three patients during the during the 7-weeks
      treatment, then the first cohort will be expanded to 6 patients.

        -  If no further DLT has been recorded in patients 4 to 6 of cohort 1 during the 7-weeks
           treatment cycle, the dose level of erlotinib will be escalated to 150 mg and enrollment
           of cohort 2 will be initiated, after patient 6 has completed the 7-weeks treatment.

        -  If DLT has been recorded in one out of the patients 4 to 6 of cohort 1 during the
           7-weeks treatment cycle, the dose level of erlotinib will be escalated to 150 mg and
           enrollment of cohort 2 will be initiated, after patient 6 has completed the 7-weeks
           treatment.

        -  If DLT has been recorded in 2 patients of the patients 4 to 6 of cohort 1, during the
           during the 7-weeks treatment, then the trial will be terminated and this dose level will
           be considered as the Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD).

      If DLT has been recorded in 2 patients of the first three patients during the during the
      7-weeks treatment, then the trial will be terminated and this dose level will be considered
      as the Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD).

      Cohort 2:

      If DLT has been recorded in one out of the first three patients or 1-2 of the 6 patients in
      cohort 1, 3 patients will be included in cohort 2.

      If no DLT has been recorded in the first three patients during the 7-weeks treatment, the
      dose level of cisplatin will be escalated to 40 mg/m2 and enrollment of cohort 3 will be
      initiated.

      If DLT has been recorded in one out of the first three patients during the during the 7-weeks
      treatment, then the second cohort will be expanded to 6 patients.

        -  If no further DLT has been recorded in patients 4 to 6 of cohort 2 during the 7-weeks
           treatment cycle, the dose level of cisplatin will be escalated to 40 mg/m2 and
           enrollment of cohort 3 will be initiated, after patient 6 has completed the 7-weeks
           treatment

        -  If DLT has been recorded in one out of the patients 4 to 6 of cohort 2 during the
           7-weeks treatment cycle, the dose level of cisplatin will be escalated to 40 mg/m2 and
           enrollment of cohort 3 will be initiated, after patient 6 has completed the 7-weeks
           treatment

        -  If DLT has been recorded in 2 patients of the patients 4 to 6 of cohort 2 during the
           during the 7-weeks treatment, then the trial will be terminated and this dose level will
           be considered as the Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD).

      If DLT has been recorded in 2 patients of the first three patients of cohort 2 during the
      during the 7-weeks treatment, then the trial will be terminated and this dose level will be
      considered as the Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD).

      Cohort 3:

      If DLT has been recorded in one out of the first three patients or 1-2 of the 6 patients in
      cohort 2, 3 patients will be included in cohort 2.

      If no DLT has been recorded in the first three patients during the 7-weeks treatment, then
      the Maximum Tolerated Dose has not been reached.

      If DLT has been recorded in one out of the first three patients during the during the 7-weeks
      treatment, then the third cohort will be expanded to 6 patients.

        -  If no further DLT has been recorded in patients 4 to 6 of cohort 3 during the 7-weeks
           treatment cycle, then the Maximum Tolerated Dose has not been reached.

        -  If DLT has been recorded in one out of the patients 4 to 6 of cohort 3 during the
           7-weeks treatment cycle, then the Maximum Tolerated Dose has not been reached.

        -  If DLT has been recorded in 2 patients of the patients 4 to 6 of cohort 3 during the
           during the 7-weeks treatment, then the trial will be terminated and this dose level will
           be considered as the Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD).

      If DLT has been recorded in 2 patients of the first three patients of cohort 3 during the
      during the 7-weeks treatment, then the trial will be terminated and this dose level will be
      considered as the Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD).

      Inclusion of the third patient of each cohort will not be allowed until the safety data from
      the two previous patients have been analyzed

      Inclusion of the third patient of each cohort will not be allowed until the safety data from
      the two previous patients have been analyzed

      DLT is defined as:

        -  Any clinically intolerable hematological or non-hematological grade 3-4 toxicity.

        -  Grade 3-4 diarrhoea.

        -  Grade 3-4 or clinically intolerable grade 2 skin rash.

        -  Grade 4 mucositis implying a temporary interruption of radiation therapy (for longer
           than 2 consecutive weeks).

        -  Grade 4 mucositis occurring within the first 3 weeks of treatment.

        -  Grade 3-4 mucositis accompanied by one of the following toxicities:

        -  Worsening of performance status, defined as ECOG ≥ 2 or a decrease of 40% in the
           Karnofsky performance status scale.

        -  Grade 3 Weight loss (corresponding to a weight loss of ≥ 20% with respect to baseline
           weight).

        -  Underlying pain (not including swallowing) VAS &gt; 7.

        -  Parenteral nutrition.

        -  Any clinically significant toxicity, involving treatment interruption for a period
           longer than two weeks.

      Maximum Tolerated Dose is defined as the dose level at which 2 patients of the first three
      patients of one cohort or ≥ 3 of the 6 patients of one cohort exhibit one DLT, during the
      7-weeks treatment.

      Phase II:

      75 patients will be treated at dose step below MTD to determinate:

        -  Progression Free Survival, defined as the period of time from the surgery until disease
           progression or death.

        -  Overall survival.

        -  Locoregional progression-free survival.

      A tumor assessment will be performed 30 days after the end of treatment and every 3 months
      until disease progression afterwards.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determinate the maximum tolerated dose (PHASE I)</measure>
    <time_frame>17/MAR/08</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PHASE II)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DLT (PHASE I)</measure>
    <time_frame>17/MAR/08</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival and locoregional progression free survival (PHASE II)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">53</enrollment>
  <condition>Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Head and Neck</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Erlotinib, radiotherapy.</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>There are three cohorts of patients in whom the dose of Erlotinib chlorhydrate(100 and 150 mg) and Cisplatin (30 and 40 mg / m2) will be increase, and the doses of Radiation therapy being fixed (63 Gy during 5 days a week during 7 weeks)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Erlotinib chlorhydrate</intervention_name>
    <description>150 mg/day for 7 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Erlotinib, radiotherapy.</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Erlotinib clorhidrate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cisplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>30 mg/m2 i.v. weekly for 7 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Erlotinib, radiotherapy.</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cisplatino</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiation therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>63 Gy, five days a week, for 7 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Erlotinib, radiotherapy.</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with histological proof of epidermoid carcinoma of the oral cavity,
             oropharynx, larynx, or hypopharynx, treated with surgical resection with curative
             intent.

          -  Surgical resection must have taken place within 8 weeks prior to the patient's
             inclusion in the study.

          -  In those patients having clinical regional lymph node involvement radical neck
             dissection is mandatory. However, radical neck dissection is not an inclusion
             criterion in patients staged as N0.

          -  Age 18-70 years.

          -  Anticipated life expectancy of ≥ 12 weeks.

          -  Patients should have at least one of the following criteria:

               1. Pathological T3-4 tumor stage, apart from T3N0 of the larynx with negative
                  margins

               2. Pathological N2-3 nodal stage.

               3. Unfavorable pathological findings such as extranodal spread, positive resection
                  margins, perineural and/or vascular involvement.

          -  Written informed consent given by the patient.

          -  Therapeutic compliance of the patient and geographical proximity to the hospital to
             facilitate appropriate follow-up.

          -  ECOG 0-1.

          -  No distant metastatic disease.

          -  Adequate organ function according to the following criteria:

               1. Adequate bone marrow reserve: ANC &gt; 1,5 x 10(9) cells/L; Platelet count &gt; 100 x
                  10(9) cells/L; Hemoglobin &gt; 9 g/dL

               2. Liver function: Bilirubin &lt; 1.5 x ULN; Alkaline phosphatase (AP), aspartate
                  transaminase (AST) and alanine transaminase (ALT) &lt; 3.0 x ULN

               3. Renal function: calculated creatinine clearance (CrCl) &gt; 60ml/min or Creatinine
                  (Cr) &lt; 1.5 ULN of the reference laboratory.

               4. Serum calcium and alkaline phosphatase must be normal.

          -  Women of child bearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test within the 48h
             prior to the start of the treatment.

          -  Patients of both genders at a fertile age must follow effective contraceptive
             measures.

          -  Absence of symptomatic coronary artery disease or acute myocardial infarction within 6
             months prior to study.

          -  Patients capable of oral deglutition or requiring gastrostomy.

          -  No problems of intestinal transit such as malabsorption syndrome, chronic inflammatory
             bowel disease and other diseases, which might impair drug absorption

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Histology other than squamous cell carcinoma.

          -  Presence of macroscopic residual disease.

          -  Previous treatment with chemotherapy or radiotherapy or EGFR-targeted agents.

          -  Incomplete resection of the primary tumor or incomplete neck dissection.

          -  Patients being diagnosed with any other malignant disease, excluding resected
             nonmelanoma skin cancer or resected uterine cervix carcinoma.

          -  Pregnant or nursing women.

          -  Active infection.

          -  Concomitant severe illness (according to the opinion of the investigator) or whose
             estimated survival for this concomitant pathology is lower than that estimated for the
             neoplasm disease.

          -  Uncontrolled psychiatric illness.

          -  Inability to take oral medication, requiring intravenous feeding or prior surgical
             procedures affecting absorption or having active peptic ulcer.

          -  Impossibility to appropriate follow-up.

          -  Evidence of any other disease, metabolic dysfunction, physical examination finding, or
             clinical laboratory finding suggesting a condition that contraindicates the use of the
             study medication (erlotinib, cisplatin, radiotherapy), which might interfere with the
             analysis of the results or increase the risk of treatment complications.

          -  Any known significant ophthalmologic abnormalities, including severe xerophthalmia,
             keratoconjunctivitis sicca, Sjögren syndrome, severe exposure keratopathy or other
             abnormalities, which may increase the risk of corneal epithelial damage (the use of
             contact lenses during the study may increase the risk of corneal damage and its use is
             strongly discouraged. Those patients still using contact lenses will need a closer
             ophthalmologic follow-up.

          -  Frequent vomiting or medical disorder impairing swallowing of drugs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Felipe Calvo Manuel, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañón</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alejandro de la Torre Tomás, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Universitario Clínica Puerta de Hierro</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Manuel de las Heras González, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Clínico San Carlos</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ismael Herruzo Cabrera, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Regional Universitario Carlos Haya</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fernando Arias de la Vega, Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital de Navarra</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de Navarra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pamplona</city>
        <state>Navarra</state>
        <zip>31008</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clínico San Carlos</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28003</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañón</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Clínica Puerta de Hierro</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Regional Universitario Carlos Haya</name>
      <address>
        <city>Málaga</city>
        <zip>29010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 1, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 1, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 2, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 23, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 23, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 26, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Grupo de Investigación Clínica en Oncología Radioterapia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Esther Prats</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Oncologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Head Neck Carcinoma Erlotinib</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cisplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Erlotinib Hydrochloride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

