<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00702962</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PSHCI 08-005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00702962</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Carboplatin and Etoposide in Combination With Vorinostat for Patients With Extensive Stage Small Cell Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I/II Study of Carboplatin and Etoposide in Combination With Vorinostat for Patients With Extensive Stage Small Cell Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Phase I portion of the study is to assess the maximum tolerated dose of vorinostat when
      combined with carboplatin plus etoposide. The Phase II portion is to determine
      progression-free survival among patients with extensive disease small cell lung cancer
      receiving carboplatin plus etoposide with vorinostat.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Vorinostat inhibits growth and induces apoptosis in various human carcinoma cells.
      Furthermore, it affects the expression of various genes that are necessary for proliferation
      of cancer cells. Vorinostat also appears to block angiogenic signaling. Pre-treating four
      human cancer cell lines (including a brain tumor line) with vorinostat increased the killing
      efficiency of etoposide, ellipticine, doxorubicin, or cisplatin, but not of the topoisomerase
      I inhibitor camptothecin 13. Topoisomerase II is a ubiquitous nuclear enzyme that is involved
      in DNA replication, transcription, chromosome segregation, and apoptosis. It is the target
      for several anti-cancer drugs including etoposide. Treatment with HDAC inhibitors induces
      expression of topoisomerase II in cancer cells and enhances the sensitivity to etoposide 14.

      Early phase clinical trials have demonstrated single agent anti-cancer activity with
      vorinostat. In our study, combination of vorinostat with carboplatin and paclitaxel,
      demonstrated promising anticancer activity against NSCLC, including histological subsets of
      patients whose tumors demonstrated neuroendocrine differentiation 8. For all these reasons,
      vorinostat is a rational choice to combine with the regimen of carboplatin and etoposide for
      evaluation in patients with SCLC-ED.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess maximum tolerated dose of vorinostat combined with carboplatin + etoposide for patients with extensive disease SCLC.</measure>
    <time_frame>An expected average of 2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate overall survival &amp; objective response rate among patients with extensive disease SCLC receiving carboplatin + etoposide with vorinostat.</measure>
    <time_frame>An expected average of 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5</enrollment>
  <condition>Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1 Vorinostat 200mg Carbo 6 (AUC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Vorinostat 200 mg PO QD D1-14; Carbo 6 (AUC) D3; Etoposide 100 mg/m2 D1,2,3 Vorinostat, Carboplatin, Etoposide, SAHA</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2 Vorinostat 300mg Carbo 6 (AUC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Phase 2 is to determine progression free survival among patients with extensive disease SCLC receiving carboplatin plus etoposide with vorinostat.Vorinostat, Carboplatin, Etoposide, SAHA</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vorinostat, Carboplatin, Etoposide</intervention_name>
    <description>Sequential cohorts of 3-6 patients will be entered to the following dose levels: Level 1 - Days 1-14: Vorinostat 200 mg po QD; Day 3: Carboplatin 6 AUC; Days 1,2,3: Etoposide 100 mg/m2. Level 2 - Days 1-14: Vorinostat 300 mg po QD; Day 3: Carboplatin 6 AUC; Days 1,2,3: Etoposide 100 mg/m2; Level 3: Days 1-14: Vorinostat 400 mg po QD; Day 3: Carboplatin 6 AUC; Days 1,2,3: Etoposide 100 mg/m2. Treatment cycles will be repeated every 3 weeks. A maximum of 4 cycles will be administered to each patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1 Vorinostat 200mg Carbo 6 (AUC)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SAHA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SAHA</intervention_name>
    <description>Once the recommended phase II dose has been established and additional 15 patients will be enrolled. Days 1-4 Vorinostat recommended phase II dose po QD;Day 3 Carboplatin 6 AUC; Days 1,2,3 Etoposide 100 mg/m2. Treatment cycles will be repeated every 3 weeks. A maximum of 4 cycles will be administered to each patient. An additional 35 patients on the phase II portion of the trial will be required to achieve the outlined objectives.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2 Vorinostat 300mg Carbo 6 (AUC)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Vorinostat, Carboplatin, Etoposide</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically confirmed small cell lung cancer.

          -  Patients must have measurable disease, defined as at least one lesion that can be
             accurately measured in at least one dimension (longest diameter to be recorded) as &gt;20
             mm with conventional techniques or as &gt;10 mm with CT scan.

          -  Patients must be chemotherapy naive.

          -  Previous radiotherapy is allowed only if &lt; 30% of marrow bearing bones were irradiated
             and if radiotherapy was completed at least 2 weeks prior to enrollment and the patient
             has recovered from all adverse effects of prior radiotherapy.

          -  Age &gt;18 years.

          -  Life expectancy of greater than 3 months.

          -  ECOG performance status &lt;2 (Karnofsky &gt;60%).

          -  Adequate organ and marrow function.

          -  Women of childbearing potential and men must agree to use adequate contraception
             (hormonal or double barrier method of birth control) prior to study entry and for the
             duration of study participation.

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document.

          -  Both men and women of all races and ethnic groups are eligible for this trial.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have had chemotherapy or any other investigational agent for any
             indication within 30 days of study enrollment.

          -  Patients who have had radiotherapy within 2 weeks, prior to entering the study or
             those who have not recovered from adverse events due to these therapies.

          -  Patients with known brain metastases are excluded.

          -  Patients who have been previously treated with an HDAC inhibitor (use of valproic acid
             is allowed with a 30-day washout).

          -  Patients with peripheral neuropathy CTC grade &gt;2 are excluded.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

          -  Any major surgery within 2 weeks prior to enrollment. Minimally invasive procedures
             for the purpose of diagnosis or staging of the disease are permitted.

          -  History of another malignancy in the last 5 years. Patients with prior history of in
             situ cancer, basal or squamous cell skin cancer are eligible. Patients with other
             malignancies are eligible if they were cured by surgery alone and have been
             continuously disease free for at least 5 years.

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study because irinotecan and paclitaxel are
             antineoplastic agents with the potential for teratogenic or abortifacient effects.
             Because there is an unknown but potential risk for adverse events in nursing infants
             secondary to treatment of the mother with agents used in this trial, breastfeeding
             should be discontinued if the mother is treated with these agents.

          -  Patients with known HIV, Hepatitis B, Hepatitis C or active Hepatitis A are excluded.

          -  Patients on any systemic steroids for any indication, with doses that have not been
             stabilized to the equivalent of &lt; 10 mg/day prednisone during the 30 days prior to
             study enrollment. This does not include short courses of steroids administered at high
             doses.

          -  Patients with the inability to absorb oral vorinostat.

          -  Patients with known allergy or hypersensitivity to any component of any of the study
             therapies.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chandra P Belani, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Penn State College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn State College of Medicine, Penn State Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hershey</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>17033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 19, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 20, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Milton S. Hershey Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Chandra P. Belani</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>lung cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>small cell lung cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Small Cell Lung Carcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Etoposide phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vorinostat</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etoposide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>To determine if data is valuable</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>July 24, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>August 25, 2017</returned>
    <submitted>September 7, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>October 3, 2017</returned>
    <submitted>October 4, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>November 2, 2017</returned>
    <submitted>November 22, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>December 6, 2017</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

