<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00706810</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HCI25089</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00706810</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Combination of Hydroxyurea and Verapamil for Refractory Meningiomas</brief_title>
  <official_title>Combination of Hydroxyurea and Verapamil for Refractory Meningiomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Utah</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Utah</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Meningiomas account for 20% of primary adult brain tumors, occurring at an annual incidence
      of 6 per 100,000 (Louis, Scheithauer et al. 2000). Complete surgical resection is the
      treatment of choice but may not possible when the tumor invades critical structures (e.g.,
      skull base, sagittal sinus) (Mirimanoff, Dosoretz et al. 1985; al-Rodhan and Laws 1990;
      Al-Rodhan and Laws 1991; Newman 1994; De Monte 1995; Levine, Buchanan et al. 1999; Barnett,
      Suh et al. 2000; Ragel and Jensen 2003). Up to 20% of meningiomas exhibit a more aggressive
      phenotype that does not respond to standard therapies (Kyritsis 1996). Adjuvant therapies are
      critical for patients with this subset of meningiomas. Radiation therapy and stereotactic
      radiosurgery are good adjuvant therapies but are limited by radiation neurotoxicity, tumor
      size constraints, and injury to adjacent vascular structures or cranial nerves (Goldsmith,
      Wara et al. 1994; Barnett, Suh et al. 2000; Goldsmith and Larson 2000). Standard
      chemotherapeutic treatments have been disappointing (Kyritsis 1996). Even drugs like
      temozolomide that have shown efficacy against malignant brain tumors have failed to inhibit
      the growth of refractory meningiomas in a phase II study (Chamberlain, Tsao-Wei et al. 2004).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators have demonstrated previously that the calcium channel antagonists (CCAs)
      verapamil, nifedipine, and diltiazem can block in vitro and in vivo meningioma growth at
      clinically relevant doses (Jensen, Lee et al. 1995; Jensen, Petr et al. 2000; Jensen and
      Wurster 2001). However, only modest growth inhibition was exhibited in the tumors in these
      studies with CCAs alone. Many authors have shown augmented growth inhibition by adding CCAs
      to traditional chemotherapies in other tumor types (Tsuruo, Iida et al. 1981; Tsuruo, Iida et
      al. 1983; Helson 1984; Robinson, Clutterbuck et al. 1985; Ince, Appleton et al. 1986; Merry,
      Fetherston et al. 1986; Cano-Gauci and Riordan 1987). For instance, the combination of
      verapamil and 1,3-bis (2-chloroethyl)-1-nitrosourea (BCNU) is better than BCNU alone in
      inhibiting the growth of human gliomas in vitro and in vivo (Bowles, Pantazis et al. 1990).
      Calcium antagonists seem to exert the majority of their anti-tumor effects by inhibiting
      calcium dependent secondary messenger systems (Metcalfe, 1986 #74; Jensen, 2000 #15).
      Furthermore, the investigators have more recently demonstrated that the addition of a
      verapamil or diltiazem with HU enhances the growth inhibition seen with these drugs in vitro
      and in vivo.

      Hydroxyurea inhibits DNA synthesis by inhibition of ribonucleotide diphosphate reductase and
      is a well-known drug used for the treatment of a number of tumor types including head and
      neck tumors and chronic myelogenous leukemia. It has also been used as an adjuvant for
      antiretroviral treatment for patients with HIV and as a treatment for polycythemia vera,
      essential thrombocythemia and sickle cell disease.

      Hydroxyurea is well absorbed after oral administration with the peak serum concentration
      achieved in two hours. The drug is excreted primarily in the urine, either as urea or as the
      unchanged compound. The drug is supplied as 500 mg capsules in a white crystalline powder. It
      is stored at room temperature. Dosing is usually in the range of 20 mg/kg/day with
      adjustments necessary for patients with renal insufficiency. In the current study population
      patients would be usually treated with 500mg twice a day. It is contraindicated in patients
      with myelosuppression or severe anemia.

      Verapamil is another commonly used medication. It is used for the treatment of angina,
      hypertension, supraventricular arrhythmias, and migraine prophylaxis. Dosing with standard
      verapamil is 80-120 mg pox three times a day but the sustained release form can be given
      120-480mg once or twice each day. It is contraindicated in patients with left ventricular
      dysfunction, congestive hart failure, hypotension (systolic &lt;90bpm) 2nd or 3rd degree
      atrioventricular block (except in patients with a functioning artificial pacemakers), or sick
      sinus syndrome and atrial flutter or atrial fibrillation and an accessory bypass tract
      (Wolff-Parkinson-White Syndrome, Lown-Ganong-Levine Syndrome). Serious adverse reactions
      associated with Verapamil use are congestive heart failure, hypotension, bradycardia, 2nd or
      3rd degree AC block, angina, myocardial infarction, syncope and GI obstruction.

      STUDY PROCEDURES:

      Screening and pretreatment assessments: Written informed consent is obtained before
      study-specific screening evaluations are performed. After receiving a subject's agreement to
      participate in the study and verifying that the subject meets eligibility criteria, the
      following will be performed: Medical and surgical history, prior cancer therapy (including
      prior chemotherapy and radiation therapy), complete physical examination, orthostatic vital
      signs, blood pressure, heart rate, temperature, weight, height, Karnofsky performance status
      (See appendix), neurological evaluation, current medications, and drug allergies. The
      following laboratory evaluations will be obtained: complete blood count (including
      differential, hemoglobin, and platelet count), serum chemistries (BUN, creatine, sodium,
      potassium, bicarbonate, chloride, calcium, glucose, LDH, total protein, total bilirubin, ALT,
      AST, alkaline phosphatase, albumin), serum pregnancy test (for woman of childbearing age, for
      all other women - documentation in the medical history will confirm that the subject is not
      of childbearing potential). All subjects will undergo an ECG test at screening. Patients with
      incomplete bundle branch or first degree AV conductions problems that don't exclude them from
      the study will be monitored with serial monthly ECG exams or more frequently if symptoms
      occur. All subjects will undergo an MRI of the brain (or CT with contrast if unable to do
      MRI) with and without Gadolinium contrast to assess tumor measurements within three to four
      weeks prior to beginning treatment. Patients will also undergo Positron Emission Tomography
      (PET) with metabolic FDG (radiopharmaceutical fluorodeoxyglucose) markers to assess tumor
      activity. Baseline FDG/PET scans will be given to all enrolled patients at screening and
      every 6 months, thereafter.

      Assessments during treatment phase: Patients receive oral hydroxyurea twice daily for 2 years
      in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Responders may continue
      beyond the 2 years of protocol treatment at the discretion of the physician. If the therapy
      is stopped for any reason, therapy may be reinstituted if the discontinuance does not exceed
      4 consecutive weeks. The dose is 20 mg/kg/day divided in twice daily doses. The calculated
      dose will be rounded up or down to the nearest multiple of 500 mg. Patients will typically
      receive either 1,000 mg/day or 1,500 mg/day. If the dose is 1,500 mg/day, it should be
      divided as 500 mg po every morning and 1,000 mg po. at bedtime. Verapamil sustained release
      tablets will begin at a dose of 120 mg each day for two weeks, then 240 mg each day for two
      weeks, then 360 mg each day for two weeks, then 240 mg twice a day. If the baseline SBP is
      &lt;110 mmHg then the initial Verapamil sustained release dose will be 60 mg (1/2 of a 120 mg
      tablet) each day for two weeks. Patients will have blood pressure and heart rate measurements
      done weekly for the first month and them monthly thereafter. Other clinical and laboratory
      evaluations will be performed at 1 month intervals and include: limited physical examination,
      orthostatic vital signs, blood pressure, heart rate, temperature, Karnofsky performance
      status, neurologic evaluation, serum chemistries (BUN, creatine, sodium, potassium,
      bicarbonate, chloride, calcium, glucose, LDH, total protein, total bilirubin, ALT, AST,
      alkaline phosphatase, albumin). Concomitant medications and adverse events will also be
      collected. Complete blood counts (including differential, hemoglobin, and platelet count),
      will be done weekly throughout the study until counts stabilize for two months, and then labs
      will be done every two weeks thereafter to closely monitor the side-effect of
      myelosuppression.

      Patients with incomplete bundle branch or first degree AV conduction abnormalities that don't
      exclude them from the study will be monitored with monthly ECG exams or more frequently if
      symptoms occur. Subjects will undergo MRI with gadolinium (or CT with contrast if unable to
      do MRI) every three months after beginning treatment. Measurements will be made of the image
      slice with the largest cross sectional area. Two orthogonal measures will be made to
      determine maximal AP and lateral dimensions. PET imaging will be done at baseline and every 6
      months and proliferative and metabolic activity will be compared to baseline images. Tumor
      location and tumor size will be obtained by CT/MRI. Treatment response and clinical
      progression can frequently be difficult to measure directly. Serial neurological exams,
      CT/MRI and PET scans may provide a guide to the actual course of response and progression.
      Deterioration in neurological status and tumor regrowth on CT/MRI and PET must be sustained
      over time to declare clinical progression. The time interval until progression will be
      measured from the day of last CT/MRI before treatment and every 3-4 months until
      deterioration is documented. The patient should consistently be followed with the same
      diagnostic imaging study and formal evaluation of radiological tumor progression and tumor
      response will be done post study

      Patients will be treated for up to two years on the study. Progression of disease will be
      defined as a greater than 25% increase of largest cross sectional area by two orthogonal
      measurements. Patients will be discontinued for illness that prevents further treatment
      including unacceptable toxicity (Grade 3 or 4 that fails to resolve with dose medication per
      protocol) of study drugs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>Open Label</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants Experiencing Serious Adverse Events Including But Not Limited to Hospitalizations, Deaths Related to Treatment, or Other Incapacitating Conditions.</measure>
    <time_frame>two years</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse Events assessed in accordance with CTCAE (NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events) Version 3.0.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median Progression-free Survival Rates of the Treatment Population.</measure>
    <time_frame>31 months</time_frame>
    <description>Response and progression will be evaluated in this study using measurements from the MRI/CT scans. Measurements will be made of the image slice with the largest cross sectional area. Two orthogonal measures will be made to determine maximal AP and lateral dimensions. Progression of disease will be defined as a greater than 25% increase of largest cross sectional area by two orthogonal measurements, taking as reference the smallest sum recorded since the treatment started or the appearance of one or more new lesions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">8</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Brain Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Meningioma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All participants</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hydroxyurea</intervention_name>
    <description>Hydroxyurea inhibits DNA synthesis by inhibition of ribonucleotide diphosphate reductase and is a well-known drug used for the treatment of a number of tumor types including head and neck tumors and chronic myelogenous leukemia. It has also been used as an adjuvant for antiretroviral treatment for patients with HIV and as a treatment for polycythemia vera, essential thrombocythemia and sickle cell disease.</description>
    <arm_group_label>All participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Verapamil</intervention_name>
    <description>Verapamil is another commonly used medication. It is used for the treatment of angina, hypertension, supraventricular arrhythmias, and migraine prophylaxis. Dosing with standard verapamil is 80-120 mg pox three times a day but the sustained release form can be given 120-480mg once or twice each day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>All participants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        1. Must be age &gt; 18 years

          2. Patient able to provide written informed consent

          3. Histologically confirmed meningioma of any WHO grade (written pathology report from
             surgery required)

          4. Radiographic demonstration of at least 25% increase in tumor cross sectional area
             measured on CT/MRI within last 6 months

          5. Patients refusing or for which there is no further surgical or radiation therapy
             options

          6. WBC at least 2,500/mm3

          7. Platelet count of at least 100,000/mm3

          8. Hemoglobin &gt; 8.0 g/dL

          9. Renal insufficiency (glomerular filtration rate (GFR) &lt; 60 as estimated by the
             Cockcroft-Gault equation) are ineligible

         10. Hepatic disease (ALT, AST, bilirubin, or alkaline phosphatase &gt; 3 times upper limit of
             normal) or known cirrhosis are ineligible

         11. Clinically significant cardiovascular disease specifically those patients with the
             following conditions are ineligible:

               -  congestive heart failure

               -  known bundle branch or AV conduction problems

               -  2nd or 3rd degree atrioventricular block (except in patients with artificial
                  pacemaker),

               -  sick sinus syndrome

               -  atrial flutter or atrial fibrillation with an accessory bypass tract
                  (Wolff-Parkinson-White Syndrome, Lown-Ganong-Levine Syndrome),

               -  history of myocardial infarction in the past 6 months

               -  currently taking beta-blockers, digoxin, or neuromuscular blocking agents

               -  Bradycardia (resting heart rate &lt; 60 beats per minute)

         12. Hypotension (resting blood pressure &lt; 90 systolic)

         13. Altered neuromuscular transmission (Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy, myasthenia gravis)

         14. Karnofsky performance score 50-100%

         15. Life expectancy more than 6 months

         16. Pregnant or nursing females are ineligible. Fertile patients must use an effective
             contraception

         17. Received prior investigational agents in the past 6 months are ineligible
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Randy Jensen, MD, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Huntsman Cancer Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Huntsman Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 26, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 30, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>October 12, 2016</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>March 1, 2017</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2017</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Brain cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Meningioma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Meningioma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brain Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hydroxyurea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Verapamil</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>All Participants</title>
          <description>Hydroxyurea: Hydroxyurea inhibits DNA synthesis by inhibition of ribonucleotide diphosphate reductase and is a well-known drug used for the treatment of a number of tumor types including head and neck tumors and chronic myelogenous leukemia. It has also been used as an adjuvant for antiretroviral treatment for patients with HIV and as a treatment for polycythemia vera, essential thrombocythemia and sickle cell disease.
Verapamil: Verapamil is another commonly used medication. It is used for the treatment of angina, hypertension, supraventricular arrhythmias, and migraine prophylaxis. Dosing with standard verapamil is 80-120 mg pox three times a day but the sustained release form can be given 120-480mg once or twice each day.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="8"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="7"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>All Groups</title>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="7"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="50" lower_limit="25" upper_limit="76"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex/Gender, Customized</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Number of Participants Experiencing Serious Adverse Events Including But Not Limited to Hospitalizations, Deaths Related to Treatment, or Other Incapacitating Conditions.</title>
        <description>Adverse Events assessed in accordance with CTCAE (NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events) Version 3.0.</description>
        <time_frame>two years</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>All Groups</title>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Participants Experiencing Serious Adverse Events Including But Not Limited to Hospitalizations, Deaths Related to Treatment, or Other Incapacitating Conditions.</title>
          <description>Adverse Events assessed in accordance with CTCAE (NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events) Version 3.0.</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="7"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Median Progression-free Survival Rates of the Treatment Population.</title>
        <description>Response and progression will be evaluated in this study using measurements from the MRI/CT scans. Measurements will be made of the image slice with the largest cross sectional area. Two orthogonal measures will be made to determine maximal AP and lateral dimensions. Progression of disease will be defined as a greater than 25% increase of largest cross sectional area by two orthogonal measurements, taking as reference the smallest sum recorded since the treatment started or the appearance of one or more new lesions.</description>
        <time_frame>31 months</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>All Participants</title>
            <description>Hydroxyurea: Hydroxyurea inhibits DNA synthesis by inhibition of ribonucleotide diphosphate reductase and is a well-known drug used for the treatment of a number of tumor types including head and neck tumors and chronic myelogenous leukemia. It has also been used as an adjuvant for antiretroviral treatment for patients with HIV and as a treatment for polycythemia vera, essential thrombocythemia and sickle cell disease.
Verapamil: Verapamil is another commonly used medication. It is used for the treatment of angina, hypertension, supraventricular arrhythmias, and migraine prophylaxis. Dosing with standard verapamil is 80-120 mg pox three times a day but the sustained release form can be given 120-480mg once or twice each day.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Median Progression-free Survival Rates of the Treatment Population.</title>
          <description>Response and progression will be evaluated in this study using measurements from the MRI/CT scans. Measurements will be made of the image slice with the largest cross sectional area. Two orthogonal measures will be made to determine maximal AP and lateral dimensions. Progression of disease will be defined as a greater than 25% increase of largest cross sectional area by two orthogonal measurements, taking as reference the smallest sum recorded since the treatment started or the appearance of one or more new lesions.</description>
          <units>months</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="7"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="8.0" lower_limit="5" upper_limit="31"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>All Participants</title>
          <description>Hydroxyurea: Hydroxyurea inhibits DNA synthesis by inhibition of ribonucleotide diphosphate reductase and is a well-known drug used for the treatment of a number of tumor types including head and neck tumors and chronic myelogenous leukemia. It has also been used as an adjuvant for antiretroviral treatment for patients with HIV and as a treatment for polycythemia vera, essential thrombocythemia and sickle cell disease.
Verapamil: Verapamil is another commonly used medication. It is used for the treatment of angina, hypertension, supraventricular arrhythmias, and migraine prophylaxis. Dosing with standard verapamil is 80-120 mg pox three times a day but the sustained release form can be given 120-480mg once or twice each day.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>anemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>leukopenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>neutropenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>thrombocytopenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Cardiac disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>heart palpatations</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Eye disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>decreased eye acuity</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>proptosis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>abdominal pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>constipation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>parotitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>fatigue</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>ear infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>sinus infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>strep throat</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>urinary tract infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Investigations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>weight gain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Metabolism and nutrition disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>hypocalcemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>hyponatremia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>back pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>wrist sprain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Nervous system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>dizziness</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>headache</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>lightheaded</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>syncope</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>vasovagal</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Vascular disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>edema</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="7"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. Randy Jensen</name_or_title>
      <organization>Huntsman Cancer Institute</organization>
      <phone>801-581-6908</phone>
      <email>randy.jensen@hci.utah.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

