<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00709982</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR002380</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00709982</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Drug Interaction Study of Folic Acid and Oral Contraceptive Tablets Containing Norgestimate (NGM) /Ethinyl Estradiol (EE) in Healthy Women.</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-label Pharmacokinetic Drug Interaction Study of Folic Acid and 250 Mcg NGM/35 Mcg EE (ORTHO-CYCLEN) in Healthy Women..</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to assess the effect of folic acid administration on the blood
      level and the breakdown products of OC study drug (250 mcg norgestimate[NGM]/35 mcg Ethinyl
      Estradiol [EE]) tablets. The effect of study drug tablet intake on the blood level of folic
      acid is also determined.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-center, open-label, pharmacokinetic drug interaction study between folic
      acid (1 mg) and study drug (250 mcg NGM/35 mcg EE) in 2 groups of at least 20 healthy women
      each. In Group 1, a single oral dose of 250 mcg NGM/35 mcg EE study drug was administered to
      the healthy volunteers at the study site on Days 1 and 17 and folic acid 1 mg was
      administered orally on Days 4 to 18; in Group 2, folic acid 1 mg was administered orally on
      Days 1 and 17 at the study site and 1 tablet of study drug was administered on Days 2 to 17.
      Blood samples were collected at specified times for 72 hours postdose on Days 1 and 17 for
      the healthy volunteers in Group 1 for determination of blood levels of norelgestromin (NGMN),
      and norgestrel (NG) [the active breakdown product of NGM], and EE. For the healthy volunteers
      in Group 2, blood samples were collected for 24 hours after the folic acid dose on Days 1 and
      17 for determination of plasma levels of total folates. Safety was evaluated based on the
      following: the incidence, type and severity of adverse events; clinical laboratory tests;
      vital sign and electrocardiogram (ECGs) measurements; and physical examinations. Oral
      temperature, pulse, respiratory rate, and sitting blood pressure (BP) were taken before
      dosing on Days 1 and 17. For Group 1, measurements were taken before and at least 15 minutes
      after the 24-hour (Days 2 and 18), 48-hour (Days 3 and 19), and 72-hour (Day 4)
      pharmacokinetic blood draw; and at study completion (Day 20) or early withdrawal. For Group
      2, measurements were taken before and at least 15 minutes after the 24-hour pharmacokinetic
      blood draw on Days 2 and 18; and at study completion (Day 18) or early withdrawal. Physical
      and gynecologic examinations and 12-lead ECGs were performed at screening and at study
      completion or early withdrawal. Blood samples for blood chemistry, hematology, and urine
      samples for urinalysis were collected at the screening visit and at the follow-up visit or
      early withdrawal.

      Oral contraceptives tablet (250 mcg NGM/35 mcg EE); Folic acid tablet (1 mg). In Group 1, a
      single oral dose of (250 mcg NGM/35 mcg EE) study drug was administered on Days 1 and 17 and
      folic acid 1 mg was administered orally on Days 4 to 18; in Group 2, folic acid 1 mg was
      administered orally on Days 1 and 17 and 1 tablet of study drug was administered on Days 2 to
      17. Study drugs were taken with 240 mL (8 oz) of water at approximately 8:00 a.m.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2005</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the pharmacokinetic drug interaction between folic acid and the study drug (250 mcg NGM and 35 mcg EE) as measured by the pharmacokinetics of the active breakdown product of NGM, norelgestromin (NGMN), and EE.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure the pharmacokinetics of the active metabolite of NGM, norgestrel (NG). Evaluate the effect of the study drug on the pharmacokinetics of folic acid. Assess the safety.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">47</enrollment>
  <condition>Drug Interactions</condition>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Pharmacokinetics</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Norgestimate; Ethinyl Estradiol; Folic acid</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy, nonpregnant, nonlactating, nonsmoking women, weighing at least 110 pounds

          -  With regular menstrual cycles

          -  A body mass index between 16 and 29.9 kg/m2

          -  And having a hematocrit of at least 36%

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History or presence of disorders commonly accepted as contraindications to sex
             hormonal therapy including: thromboembolic disorders' cerebral vascular or coronary
             artery disease, chronic untreated hypertension, or migraines, benign or malignant
             liver tumor that developed during the use of OC

          -  Known or suspected estrogen-dependent neoplasia

          -  Presence of disorders commonly accepted as contraindications to combined OC including:
             undiagnosed abnormal vaginal bleeding, any neurovascular lesion of the eye or serious
             visual disturbance, or liver disease

          -  Intake any multivitamin or folic acid-containing supplements within 21 days before
             study admission

          -  Used a steroid hormone-containing intrauterine device within 3 months before study
             admission

          -  Used any medications that were known cytochrome P-450 enzyme inducers or inhibitors
             (e.g., St. John's Wort, cimetidine or rifampin), within 60 days before dosing
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research and Development, L.L.C. Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>http://filehosting.pharmacm.com/DownloadService.ashx?client=CTR_JNJ_6051&amp;studyid=475&amp;filename=CR002380_CSR.pdf</url>
    <description>A drug interaction study of folic acid and oral contraceptive tablets containing norgestimate (250 mcg)/ethinyl estradiol (35 mcg) in healthy women</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 30, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 2, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 3, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 6, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 6, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 8, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Norgestimate</keyword>
  <keyword>Contraceptives, Oral</keyword>
  <keyword>Ortho-Cyclen</keyword>
  <keyword>Folic Acid</keyword>
  <keyword>Ethinyl Estradiol</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Estradiol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Polyestradiol phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ethinyl Estradiol</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Estradiol 3-benzoate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Estradiol 17 beta-cypionate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Estradiol valerate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Contraceptive Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Norgestimate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Norgestrel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Folic Acid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin B Complex</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

