<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03214809</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NL61884.091.17</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03214809</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Use of a Point-of-care Thoracic Ultrasound Protocol for Hospital Medical Emergency Teams</brief_title>
  <acronym>METUS</acronym>
  <official_title>The Use of a Point-of-care Thoracic Ultrasound Protocol for Hospital Medical Emergency Teams</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rijnstate Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rijnstate Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study to assess the possible effects of the use of a point-of-care thoracic ultrasound
      protocol for hospital medical emergency teams (MET)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rationale: Study to assess the possible effects of the use of a point-of-care thoracic
      ultrasound protocol for hospital medical emergency teams Objective: Concordance between MET
      diagnosis with and without the use of ultrasound with the chart review definitive diagnosis
      will be studied. Also other secondary endpoints will be evaluated.

      Study design prospective, interventional study Study population: patients on the general
      wards in need treatment by the MET team Intervention (if applicable): When the MET team
      arrives first assessment will be done according to the abcde algorithm. If immediate
      interventions are needed (intubation, CPR etc) this will be done first (and noted). After the
      abcde assessment an initial diagnosis is noted. In the even weeks the thoracic ultrasound
      protocol will be done, in the uneven weeks not. After the use of ultrasound various variables
      are noted.

      Main study parameters/endpoints:

      Concordance between MET diagnosis with and without the use of ultrasound with the chart
      review definitive diagnosis will be studied.

      Also other secondary endpoints will be evaluated.

      Nature and extent of the burden and risks associated with participation, benefit and group
      relatedness:

      The use of ultrasound is without direct side effects in terms of radiation or other potential
      (non)physical disturbances.

      There are no data on the effects of the use of ultrasound during MET calls. The MET team will
      first deliver acute care if necessary, the ultrasound protocol can be done within 10-15
      minutes which is acceptable in terms of MET call care. The MET team physician can at any
      point decide to use the ultrasound if he/she thinks it is necessary.

      In other circumstances (e.g. emergency department or intensive care units) point-of-care
      ultrasound is considered to be part of standard care.

      The investigators will study the potential influence of ultrasound during MET calls in terms
      of accuracy of the initial diagnosis and whether ultrasound influences initial treatment,
      patients' disposition and so on, ultrasound is no treatment nor will be the use of ultrasound
      be decisive in the treatment of MET call patients in this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 14, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>When the MET team arrives first assessment will be done according to the abcde algorithm. If immediate interventions are needed (intubation, CPR etc) this will be done first (and noted). After the abcde assessment an initial diagnosis is noted. In the even weeks the thoracic ultrasound protocol will be done, in the uneven weeks not. After the use of ultrasound various variables are noted.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Concordance between MET diagnosis with and without the use of ultrasound with the chart review definitive diagnosis will be studied</measure>
    <time_frame>after 2-3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>final diagnosis will be determined by 2 independent experts on the basis of chart review and will be compared with the MET team diagnosis. There are 8 pre defined diagnosis categories. The difference in concordance between the MET diagnosis with and without the use of ultrasound with the definitive diagnosis will be tested with a chi-square or a Fisher Exact test in case of small expected frequencies.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Possible difference in diagnostic certainty</measure>
    <time_frame>direct after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>diagnostic certainty is measured on a scale 0-10. - Descriptive statistics will be presented as mean with standard deviation for normally distributed continuous data, median and inter-quartile range for skewed continuous variables. Differences between groups will be tested using the Students' T-test. In case of unevenly distributed variables, differences between groups will be tested using the Mann Whitney U Test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Possible differences in initial treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>direct after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>There are 11 pre-defined therapy categories. - Descriptive statistics will be presented as numbers and percentages for dichotomous and categorical variables. Differences between groups will be tested with a chi-square or a Fisher Exact test in case of small expected frequencies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Possible differences in patients' disposition</measure>
    <time_frame>direct after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>There are 4 pre-defined categories in patients' disposition. - Descriptive statistics will be presented as numbers and percentages for dichotomous and categorical variables. Differences between groups will be tested with a chi-square or a Fisher Exact test in case of small expected frequencies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Whether the use of ultrasound was considered to be helpful</measure>
    <time_frame>direct after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>The answer to this question is binary (yes or no). - Descriptive statistics will be presented as numbers and percentages for dichotomous and categorical variables. Differences between groups will be tested with a chi-square or a Fisher Exact test in case of small expected frequencies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>MET physicians characteristics</measure>
    <time_frame>direct after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>there are 5 pre-defined categories in MET physician characteristics. - Descriptive statistics will be presented as numbers and percentages for dichotomous and categorical variables. Differences between groups will be tested with a chi-square or a Fisher Exact test in case of small expected frequencies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Possible difference in the time needed to reach a diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>direct after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>time in minutes. - Descriptive statistics will be presented as mean with standard deviation for normally distributed continuous data, median and inter-quartile range for skewed continuous variables. Differences between groups will be tested using the Students' T-test. In case of unevenly distributed variables, differences between groups will be tested using the Mann Whitney U Test.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Possible difference in the need for supervisor attendance</measure>
    <time_frame>direct after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>the answer to this question is binary (yes or no). - Descriptive statistics will be presented as numbers and percentages for dichotomous and categorical variables. Differences between groups will be tested with a chi-square or a Fisher Exact test in case of small expected frequencies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of times ultrasound was used in te &quot;non-ultrasound weeks&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>direct after inclusion</time_frame>
    <description>answer to this question is a number. - Descriptive statistics will be presented as mean with standard deviation for normally distributed continuous data, median and inter-quartile range for skewed continuous variables. Differences between groups will be tested using the Students' T-test. In case of unevenly distributed variables, differences between groups will be tested using the Mann Whitney U Test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Dyspnea</condition>
  <condition>Coma</condition>
  <condition>Hypotension and Shock</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Thoracic ultrasound protocol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>ABCDE algorithm with Thoracic ultrasound protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No Thoracic ultrasound protocol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>ABCDE algorithm without Thoracic ultrasound protocol</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ultrasound protocol</intervention_name>
    <description>after first assessment and treatment by the MET team, an Multi-organ ultrasound protocol will be run by the MET doctor</description>
    <arm_group_label>Thoracic ultrasound protocol</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult patients on the general wards in need of treatment by the MET team.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  age (&lt;18 years),

          -  pregnancy:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Blans, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rijnstate Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rijnstate Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Arnhem</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 19, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 7, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 12, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 12, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 12, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>MET team</keyword>
  <keyword>Concordance</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Emergencies</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypotension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dyspnea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

