<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03218488</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR108277</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CNTO1275PSO4056</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03218488</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Safety Study of Ustekinumab in the Treatment of Pediatric Participants Aged 12 Years and Older With Moderate to Severe Plaque Psoriasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Observational Post-authorization Safety Study of Ustekinumab in the Treatment of Pediatric Patients Aged 12 Years and Older With Moderate to Severe Plaque Psoriasis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen-Cilag International NV</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen-Cilag International NV</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to monitor the long-term safety of ustekinumab in pediatric
      participants (aged greater than or equal to 12 years to less than 18 years inclusive) with
      moderate to severe plaque psoriasis, through monitoring for the following adverse events
      potentially related to immune modulation: serious infections, malignancies and autoimmunity;
      and to monitor the long-term effects of ustekinumab on growth (weight, height, body mass
      index) and development (sexual maturity based on the Tanner Scale).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 29, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2026</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to end of data collection (approximately 9 years)</time_frame>
    <description>An adverse event is any untoward medical occurrence in a patient administered a medicinal product. An adverse event does not necessarily have a causal relationship with the treatment. An adverse event can be any unfavorable and unintended sign, symptom, or disease temporally associated with the use of a medicinal product, whether or not related to that medicinal product.
All participants will be monitored for the long-term safety of ustekinumab for the frequency and severity of following adverse events potentially related to immune modulation and of clinical interest such as: serious infections, malignancies, and autoimmunity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of Growth: Height</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to end of data collection (approximately 9 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Growth will be based on height recorded at baseline and throughout the observational period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of Growth: Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to end of data collection (approximately 9 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Growth will be based on body weight recorded at baseline and throughout the observational period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of Growth: Body Mass Index (BMI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to end of data collection (approximately 9 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Growth will be based on body weight recorded at baseline and throughout the observational period. BMI is calculated by dividing the body weight (in kilogram) by the square of height (in meters).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sexual Maturity Based on the Tanner scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to end of data collection (approximately 9 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Tanner scale defined as a scale used to measure visible changes during puberty commonly referred to as &quot;Tanner stages&quot;. Female participants will be evaluated for breast development and pubic hair distribution and male participants are evaluated for development of external genitalia and pubic hair distribution, based on a 5-stage ordinal scale ranging from TS 1 (prepubertal/preadolescent characteristics) to TS 5 (mature or adult characteristics).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants Achieving Psoriasis Area and Severity Index (PASI) 50 Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to end of data collection (approximately 9 years)</time_frame>
    <description>The PASI is a system used for assessing and grading the severity of psoriatic lesions and their response to therapy. In the PASI system, the body is divided into 4 regions: the head, trunk, upper extremities, and lower extremities. Each of these areas is assessed separately for erythema, induration and scaling, which are each rated on a scale of 0 to 4. Total PASI score ranges from 0 to 72. A PASI 50 response represents participants who achieved at least a 50 percent improvement from baseline in the PASI score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants Achieving PASI 75 Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to end of data collection (approximately 9 years)</time_frame>
    <description>The PASI is a system used for assessing and grading the severity of psoriatic lesions and their response to therapy. In the PASI system, the body is divided into 4 regions: the head, trunk, upper extremities, and lower extremities. Each of these areas is assessed separately for erythema, induration and scaling, which are each rated on a scale of 0 to 4. Total PASI score ranges from 0 to 72. A PASI 75 response represents participants who achieved at least a 75 percent improvement from baseline in the PASI score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants Achieving PASI 90 Response</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to end of data collection (approximately 9 years)</time_frame>
    <description>The PASI is a system used for assessing and grading the severity of psoriatic lesions and their response to therapy. In the PASI system, the body is divided into 4 regions: the head, trunk, upper extremities, and lower extremities. Each of these areas is assessed separately for erythema, induration and scaling, which are each rated on a scale of 0 to 4. Total PASI score ranges from 0 to 72. A PASI 90 response represents participants who achieved at least a 90 percent improvement from baseline in the PASI score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants Achieving a Physician's Global Assessment (PGA) Score of 0 or 1</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to end of data collection (approximately 9 years)</time_frame>
    <description>The PGA documents the physician's assessment of the participant's psoriasis lesions at a given time point on a 5-point scale, where (0) = cleared, (1) = minimal, (2) = mild, (3) = moderate, (4) = marked, and (5) = severe. Overall lesions are graded for induration, erythema, and scaling. The sum of the 3 scores will be divided by 3 to obtain a final PGA score. Higher scores indicate greater severity of disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participant's Body Surface Area (BSA) Covered by Plaque-type Psoriasis</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to end of data collection (approximately 9 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of participant's body surface area covered by plaque-type psoriasis was estimated using the palm method: one of the participant's palm to proximal interphalangeal and thumb= 1 percent (%) of BSA. The total BSA affected was the summation of individual regions affected.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in Children's Dermatology Life Quality Index (cDLQI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to end of data collection (approximately 9 years)</time_frame>
    <description>The Children's Dermatology Quality Life Index (cDLQI) questionnaire will be used to assess the participant's perspective on the impact of skin disorders on daily living. It is a 10 item instrument with 4-item response options on a scale from 0 (Not at all) to 3 (Very much) and a recall period of 1 week. The total score ranges from 0 to 30, with lower scores indicating better quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Comorbidities</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline up to end of data collection (approximately 9 years)</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants will be assessed for the previous and current comorbidities other than pediatric plaque psoriasis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Psoriasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Participants With Moderate to Severe Plaque Psoriasis</arm_group_label>
    <description>All Participants diagnosed with moderate to severe plaque psoriasis who will either start therapy with ustekinumab within 30 days of baseline or have started therapy with ustekinumab in the 12-week period before enrollment as per routine clinical practice, will be monitored for the long-term safety of ustekinumab and long-term effects of ustekinumab on growth and development of pediatric participants. The primary data source for the study will be the medical records of participants and standardized questionnaires (completed by the physician and by the participant/parent).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ustekinumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will not receive any intervention as a part of this study. Participants with moderate to severe plaque psoriasis who are initiating treatment with ustekinumab within clinical practice (patients should either start therapy with ustekinumab within 30 days of baseline or have started therapy with ustekinumab in the 12-week period before enrollment for the treatment of psoriasis) will be observed for the long-term safety of ustekinumab and the long-term effects of ustekinumab on growth and development of pediatric participants.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participants With Moderate to Severe Plaque Psoriasis</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>STELARA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population will consist of pediatric participants (aged 12 years to less than 18
        years) with a diagnosis of moderate to severe plaque psoriasis who are initiating treatment
        with ustekinumab within clinical practice.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Have a confirmed diagnosis of moderate to severe chronic plaque psoriasis

          -  Either start therapy with ustekinumab within 30 days of baseline or have started
             therapy with ustekinumab in the 12-week period before enrollment for the treatment of
             psoriasis; a. the treatment decision must have been taken independently of and prior
             to a participants inclusion in the study; b. where participants have started therapy
             with ustekinumab before enrollment, appropriate baseline data including the disease
             activity score at the start of ustekinumab treatment must be documented

          -  Participant (and/or a legally-acceptable representative/guardian where applicable)
             must sign a participation agreement/informed consent form (ICF) allowing source data
             collection and verification in accordance with local requirements and the patient
             (and/or a legally-acceptable representative/guardian where applicable) must be able to
             understand and complete the requested patient-reported outcomes (PROs)

          -  Be willing to participate in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Is enrolled in an interventional clinical trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen-Cilag International NV Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen-Cilag International NV</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Study Contact</last_name>
    <phone>844-434-4210</phone>
    <email>JNJ.CT@sylogent.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCL Hopital Saint-Luc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bruxelles</city>
        <zip>1200</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UZ Leuven</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leuven</city>
        <zip>3000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU de Liège - Domaine Universitaire du Sart Tilman</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liege</city>
        <zip>4000</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grand Hôpital de Charleroi</name>
      <address>
        <city>Loverval</city>
        <zip>6280</zip>
        <country>Belgium</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gentofte Herlev Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hellerup</city>
        <zip>2800</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Odense Universitetshospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Odense C</city>
        <zip>5000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CH Victor Dupouy Argenteuil</name>
      <address>
        <city>Argenteuil</city>
        <zip>95107</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHRU Besançon -Hôpital Jean Minjoz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Besançon Cedex</city>
        <zip>25030</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Groupe Hospitalier Pellegrin CHU de Bordeaux</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bordeaux</city>
        <zip>33076</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ICH Hopital A. Morvan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brest Cedex 2</city>
        <zip>29609</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Le Bateau Blanc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Martigues</city>
        <zip>13500</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Necker Enfants Malades</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris Cedex 15</city>
        <zip>75743</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHU Saint-Etienne - Hôpital Nord</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint-Etienne Cedex 2</city>
        <zip>42055</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Klinikum der Johann Wolfgang Goethe -Universitaet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Frankfurt</city>
        <zip>60590</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitatsklinikum Schleswig-Holstein - Kiel</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kiel</city>
        <zip>24105</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Withdrawn</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Praxis Dr. med. Beate Schwarz - Germany</name>
      <address>
        <city>Langenau</city>
        <zip>89129</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Universitätsmedizin der Johannes Gutenberg-Universität Mainz</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mainz</city>
        <zip>55131</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Radboudumc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <zip>6525 EX</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oslo universitetssykehus HF, Rikshospitalet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oslo</city>
        <zip>0027</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Whipps Cross University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>E11 1NR</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Great Ormond Street Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>WC1N 3JH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Salford Royal Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salford</city>
        <zip>M6 8HD</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Denmark</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>Norway</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://pam.sylogent.com/cr/CR108277</url>
    <description>To learn how to participate in this trial please click here.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 13, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 13, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 19, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ustekinumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

