<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03212547</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ADBB Chile</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03212547</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Verbal Intervention on Late and Moderately Late Preterm Infants With Sustained Social Withdrawal</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Clinical Study on the Effects of Verbal Intervention on Late and Moderately Late Preterm Infants With Sustained Social Withdrawal Diagnosed by Means of the Alarm Distress Baby Scale</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Clinica Alemana de Santiago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Clinica Alemana de Santiago</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this project is to determine the effect of the verbal intervention on the
      decrease in sustained social withdrawal in late and moderately late preterm infants. The
      intervention will be performed by pediatricians trained in the Alarm Distress Baby Scale
      (ADBB). This scale has been applied to term and preterm newborns in multiple international
      studies, but it has not yet been applied in Chile, nor with moderately late and late preterm
      infants.

      Infants are social beings who are born with innate reciprocal communication skills that can
      be observed during the two first months after delivery in babies with normal development.
      These skills include abilities to make and maintain eye contact, to vocalize and to use
      facial expressions, body and head movements to start interactions. Micro-analytical studies
      have demonstrated the frequent appearance of short episodes of social withdrawal affecting
      the infant during mother-baby interactions, whose function is to regulate the interaction
      flow. This behavior can be perceived when the infant needs to calm down or when is tired, and
      as a reaction to transitory interaction disturbances. In contrast with these short episodes
      of social withdrawal, the occurrence of sustained social withdrawal in infants is
      significantly less and is frequently associated with pathological conditions, such as autism
      spectrum disorder, child depression, and severe or chronic pain. Additionally, sustained
      social withdrawal is a symptom of anxiety and post-traumatic stress disorders. Different
      studies have revealed a prevalence of 10-14% sustained social withdrawal in term infant
      populations and of 13-22% in pre-term infant populations. In addition, the increase in
      sustained social withdrawal has been related to deviations of the interaction skills,
      attachment, as well as to relational and behavioral disorders. The increase and
      chronification of sustained social withdrawal, used as a defensive conduct, imply a risk to
      the adequate development of an infant's potential and raise the probability of alterations in
      the development of his psychopathology.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients and methods: a prospective multicenter (Clínica Alemana de Santiago and Hospital San
      José) cohort study with comparative and explanatory elements. The study will comprise four
      periods (during hospitalization and at 2, 6 and 12 months of corrected gestational age). An
      experimental and a control group will be randomized when a MLP newborn is hospitalized. The
      experimental group will be composed of late and moderately late preterm infants (MLP) born
      between 32 to 366 weeks of pregnancy, who will be verbally intervened by the treating
      physician in outpatient well child consultations at 2, 6 and 12 months corrected age, trough
      interactive guidance with the aim of potentiating the interaction of the infant with the
      parents to reduce sustained social withdrawal. Likewise, an analysis of both institutions
      (Clinica Alemana de Santiago and Hospital San Jose) will be performed to assess the
      differences between them. The tools that will be applied are the ADBB scale, as dependent
      variable; the Edinburgh Post-natal Depression Scale to be applied to parents; the Modified
      Perinatal Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder Questionnaire and the Revised Impact of Events
      Scale. During the hospitalization of MLP infants, the painful and invasive procedures to
      which the infant is subjected will be quantified, as well as neonatal pain, hours of
      skin-to-skin contact, breastfeeding and parental visits. Results relevance and applicability:
      Efficient early detection and intervention in infants with sustained social withdrawal
      behavior is essential to prevent problems in their social and emotional development.
      Assessing sustained social withdrawal using a standardized and simple scale like the ADBB
      Scale will allow for monitoring the infant and implementing cost-effective interventions that
      will benefit him, his family and the society. Identifying the risk groups, i.e. with
      difficulties in the social and emotional development area, will allow us to optimize the
      follow-up and integral support programs according to the infants' health needs as well as to
      establish a care standard.

      Intervention Experimental group: the intervention consist in verbal interventions on infants
      (accompanied by their mothers) who presents sustained social withdrawal detected on the child
      consultations (at 2, 6 and 12 months of corrected gestational age). The sustained social
      withdrawal will be assessed by neonatologists certifieds in the assess of Alarm Distress Baby
      Scale (during the child consultation) and by certifieds external evaluator, by means of a
      video (8 to 12 minutes of extension) that will be recorder by the neonatologist and assessed
      by the external evaluator. If the trained neonatologist detect sustained social withdrawal he
      will perform the verbal intervention during the child consultation. If the neonatologist does
      not detect sustained social withdrawal during the pediatric check-up, but the certified
      external evaluator does when assessing the video, the patient will be contacted and will
      receive treatment within the time limits described (+- 30 days). Also, the verbal
      intervention is described in a guide for &quot;Promotion of verbal interventions for interaction&quot;
      , and will be supplemented with a written guideline for parents to promote adequate
      interaction between parents and infant.

      Control group: infants will assist at child consultations (at 2, 6 and 12 months of corrected
      gestational age) whit non trained neonatologists. These neonatologists will record a video
      that will be assessed by certifieds external evaluators. Infants in the control group won't
      receive the verbal intervention. However, they will receive a development stimulation guide
      adapted of the ministerial guides for the stimulation of development of the Ministry of
      Health of Chile.

      Infants will be randomized while they are hospitalized in the NICU of Clinica Alemana de
      Santiago or in the NICU of Hospital San Jose. At the time of randomization, it will be
      defined whether the infant should attend medical check-ups at 2, 6 and 12 months of corrected
      gestational age with a neonatologists trained in Alarm Distress Baby Scale, or with a
      physician not trained, who will not perform the treatment.

      Additionally, if during the experimental group medical check-ups at 2, 6 or 12 months of CGA,
      the physician trained in ADBB detects social withdrawal or finds any acute morbidity such as
      acute respiratory infection, fever, dehydration, hyperemesis, diarrhea, prolonged pain or
      irritability, or some acute condition that might affect the quality of the baby's
      interactions, he will perform a second assessment with the ADBB scale within 15 days.

      At the end of the clinical trial, all the infants who present sustained social withdrawal in
      the medical check-up at 12 months of corrected gestational age will be offered free
      assessment and intervention (3 sessions) by the research team of this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">September 20, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 20, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 20, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
    <masking_description>Simple blind masking method. A group of certified external evaluators will assess a video recorded to detect social withdrawal in moderate and late preterm infantes. The video will be recorded during the medical check-up at 2, 6 and 12 months of corrected gestational age.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sustained social withdrawal</measure>
    <time_frame>Neonatologists trained in the ADBB scale will apply the ADBB scale during the medical check-ups of moderate and late preterm infants at 2, 6 and 12 months of corrected age.</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative categorical variable, ordinal. Category according sum of obtained scores (0-4: No withdrawal, 5-9: moderate withdrawal, 10 or more: Severe withdrawal).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-partum depression</measure>
    <time_frame>The EPDS will be completed by the mothers of moderate and late preterm infants at 2, 6 and 12 months of corrected age.</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative categorical variable, nominal. Category obtained from scores lower or higher than 12 points in Edinburgh scale (&quot;No risk&quot; and &quot;risk&quot;).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-traumatic stress symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>The PPQ-m and IES-R will be completed by the mothers and fathers of moderate and late preterm infants at 6 and 12 months of corrected age.</time_frame>
    <description>Quantitative categorical variable, nominal. Category obtained from scores lower or higher than 19 points in Modified Perinatal Post-traumatic Stress Disorder Questionnaire (&quot;no risk&quot; and &quot;risk&quot;).
Category obtained from scores lower or higher than 24 (&quot;clinical concern&quot;) in Impact of Event Scale Revised (IES-R).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">140</enrollment>
  <condition>Social Withdrawal of Childhood or Adolescence</condition>
  <condition>Preterm Infant</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Verbal interventions made on infants (accompanied by their mothers) who presents sustained social withdrawal detected on the child consultations (at 2, 6 and 12 months of corrected gestational age), made by neonatologists certifieds in the assess of Alarm Distress Baby Scale. Theintervention is described in a guide for &quot;Promotion of verbal interventions for interaction&quot; , and will be supplemented with a written guideline for parents.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control group: infants will assist at child consultations (at 2, 6 and 12 months of corrected gestational age) whit non trained neonatologists. However, these group will receive a development stimulation guide adapted of the ministerial guides for the stimulation of development of the Ministry of Health of Chile.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Verbal Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Promotion of verbal interventions:
Detecting whether the infant has social withdrawal.
The physician will verbally intervene.
Positive response (+) from the infant, the evaluator will point out this to the parents.
Negative response (-) from the infant, the evaluator will include the parents in the interaction.
If he infant establishes positive contact (+) with the parents, he/she will point out this response to them.
If the infant does not establish positive contact (-)with the parents, repeat step 2.
If the infant offers a positive response (+) to the second attempt of verbal intervention, the evaluator will point out this response to the parents.
At the end of each medical check-up, give and explain the &quot;ADBB Intervention Sheet&quot;.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  32 to 36+6 week preterm newborn. Gestational age assigned by neonatologist at birth.

          -  Spanish speaking parents.

          -  Parents with stable cohabiting and both of them responsible for the care of the infant

          -  Double or single pregnancy (monochorionic or bichorionic).

          -  Born and hospitalized within the first 48 hours of life or with a stay of at least 48
             hours at Clínica Alemana de Santiago or at Hospital San José.

          -  Signed informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Mother with antecedents or confirmed exposure to cocaine, marihuana or cocaine crack
             during pregnancy

          -  Neurological pathology that impairs the infant development diagnosed during pediatric
             check-ups.

          -  Suspicion or confirmation of major malformations or genopathies prior to birth or at
             birth.

          -  Perinatal asphyxia: &lt;3 Apgar score at 1 minute or &lt; 5 at 5 minutes and/or cord pH &lt;7.0

          -  Infants from the control group treated by a neonatologist trained in ADBB scale before
             the infant attends the check-up at 12 months of CGA.

          -  Infants from the experimental group who do not attend one of the three medical
             check-ups (at 2, 6 or 12 months of CGA) with a neonatologist trained in ADBB.

          -  Infants who attend one of the three medical checkups (at 2, 6 or 12 months of CGA)
             without their mother.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>3 Days</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jorge Bustamante Loyola, Phd</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Clínica Alemana de Santiago</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Margarita Venegas, Phd</last_name>
    <phone>+56990207431</phone>
    <email>mvenegas@alemana.cl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Paola Henriquez Diaz</last_name>
    <phone>+56988049730</phone>
    <email>paola.sofias@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinica Alemana de Santiago</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santiago</city>
        <state>Region Metropolitana</state>
        <zip>7650568</zip>
        <country>Chile</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jorge Bustamante Loyola, Phd</last_name>
      <phone>+56999691389</phone>
      <email>jorbuslo@alumni.uv.es</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Marcela Perez Retamal, Md</last_name>
      <phone>+56996999846</phone>
      <email>mperezr@alemana.cl</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jorge Bustamante Loyola</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Chile</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 7, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 7, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 19, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 19, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 21, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Social withdrawal</keyword>
  <keyword>Preterm Infant</keyword>
  <keyword>Parent's mental health</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Premature Birth</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Not decided yet</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

