<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03212989</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-0468</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01HL132791-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03212989</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate Effects of Vorinostat and HXTC on Persistent HIV-1 Infection in HIV-Infected Subjects Started on ART</brief_title>
  <acronym>XTRA</acronym>
  <official_title>IGHID 11627 - A Phase I Study to Evaluate the Effects of Vorinostat and HIV-1 Antigen Expanded Specific T Cell Therapy (HXTC) on Persistent HIV-1 Infection in HIV-Infected Individuals Started on Antiretroviral Therapy (The XTRA Study)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase I, single-site, study to evaluate the effects of VOR and HIV-1 Antigen
      Expanded Specific T Cell Therapy (HXTC) on persistent HIV-1 Infection in HIV-infected
      individuals suppressed on cART. Twelve participants with durable viral suppression will be
      enrolled and will complete the study. All participants will receive the same treatment and if
      eligible, will be dosed with HXTC and VOR. Participants will continue their baseline cART
      regimen throughout the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Purpose: This study will test the use of special immune system cells called expanded
      HIV-specific T Cell (HXTC) Therapy to stimulate the immune system to respond better to HIV.
      HXTC Therapy will be given in combination with the drug Vorinostat (VOR) which has been shown
      to stimulate some cells infected with HIV to become active and start making HIV virus. The
      purpose of this study is to:

        1. Evaluate the safety of a series of HXTC infusions in combination with serial doses of
           VOR and

        2. Help scientists evaluate ways of re-activating latent (non-active) HIV virus and
           determine if the immune system can be made stronger to eliminate the activated HIV
           virus.

      Participants: HIV-infected men and women, ≥ 18 and &lt; 65 years of age, with durable viral
      suppression for ≥ 24 months as measured on standard HIV RNA assays. Eligible participants
      must be on stable cART and have a CD4 count ≥ 350 cells/mm3. We plan to enroll up to 12
      participants at UNC who complete all 6 Steps of this study.

      Procedures (methods):

      In Step 1 and prior to initiating the two series of VOR and HXTC combined therapies, all
      participants will undergo study screening where they will be required to: 1. Demonstrate a
      baseline measurement of the frequency of resting CD4 T cell infection ≥ 0.3 infected cells
      per million as determined by QVOA, as a further decrease from this low frequency of infection
      cannot be definitively measured given the QVOA assay threshold, and 2. Exhibit ex-vivo (Step
      1) response to VOR

      Participants progressing to Step 2 will receive 2 (two) doses of VOR 400 mg followed by a
      leukapheresis. If an increase in cell-associated HIV RNA (ca-RNA) is observed in-vivo
      following the single VOR dose, they will be eligible to donate cells for the manufacture of
      HXTC (Step 3). Successful manufacturing of the HIV-1 antigen expanded specific T cells will
      progress participants to combination treatment in Steps 4 and 5. In Steps 4 and Step 5,
      participants will receive two series of VOR dosing and HXTC infusions, for a total 20 doses
      of VOR 400 mg and 5 HXTC infusions.

      In the first series (Step 4), participants will receive VOR 400 mg PO every 72 hours for 10
      doses and 2 infusions of HXTC. The first HXTC infusion will be administered six hours after
      the first dose of VOR (HXTC #1) and the 2nd HXTC infusion (HXTC #2) will occur 6 hours after
      the 6th dose of VOR.

      In the second series in Step 5, participants will receive an additional 10 doses of VOR 400
      mg PO every 72 hours and 3 HXTC infusions. The first HXTC infusion in Step 5 (HXTC #3) will
      occur 6 hours after the 11th dose of VOR (1st dose in Step 5), the 2nd HXTC infusion (HXTC
      #4) will occur 6 hours after the 16th dose of VOR, and the 3rd HXTC infusion (HXTC #5) will
      occur 1 - 3 days after the 20th dose of VOR. If there are insufficient cells manufactured to
      allow 5 infusions, the first infusion in Step 5 (HXTC #3) will be omitted.

      Following the final HXTC infusion in Step 5, participants move into Step 6 for a minimum of
      six (6) additional visits: 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, and 26. The 3rd and final leukapheresis will
      occur at Visit 23 (Week 21), approximately 9 weeks after the last HXTC infusion to evaluate
      the effect of study treatment on IUPM by QVOA.

      All participants who receive greater than 8 doses of VOR in the study will be required to
      enter a study cancer registry where they will be contacted once a year for 5 years after
      completion of their study participation. The registry is created because of genotoxic
      findings that were associated with the use of VOR. All participants will be monitored for
      development of future malignancies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 27, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants w/ at least one ≥ Grade 3 adverse event including signs/symptoms, lab toxicities, and/or clinical events that is possibly or definitely related to VOR or HXTC any time from the first day of study treatment through the end of study</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to end of study, approximately 96 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Safety data will include local and systemic signs and symptoms, laboratory measures of safety/toxicity, and all adverse and serious adverse events. Safety data will be routinely collected throughout the duration of the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants demonstrating an HIV-specific immune response to the combination of VOR and HXTC therapy as well as a change in the frequency of latent HIV infection</measure>
    <time_frame>Through End of study, approximately 96 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">12</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV-1 Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VOR + HXTC arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This is an open label single arm study. All eligible participants receive the following interventions:
Step 2 - Single dose of Vorinostat (VOR) 400 mg PO
Step 4 - Vorinostat (VOR) 400 mg PO every 72 hrs x 10 doses and 2 HXTC infusions
Step 5 - Vorinostat (VOR) 400 mg PO every 72 hrs x 10 doses and 2 HXTC infusions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vorinostat</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants meeting criteria for Step 1 (exhibit ex-vivo response to VOR) will progress to Step 2 where they will receive a single dose of VOR 400 mg followed by a leukapheresis. If an increase in cell-associated HIV RNA (ca-RNA) is observed in-vivo following the single VOR dose, they will be eligible to donate cells for the manufacture of HXTC (Step 3). Successful manufacturing of the HIV-1 antigen expanded specific T cells will progress participants to combination treatment in Steps 4 and 5. In Steps 4 and Step 5, participants will receive two series of VOR dosing and HXTC infusions, for a total 20 doses of VOR 400 mg and 5 HXTC infusions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VOR + HXTC arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ZOLINZA</other_name>
    <other_name>MK-0683</other_name>
    <other_name>SAHA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HXTC</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants meeting criteria for Step 1 (exhibit ex-vivo response to VOR) will progress to Step 2 where they will receive a single dose of VOR 400 mg followed by a leukapheresis. If an increase in cell-associated HIV RNA (ca-RNA) is observed in-vivo following the single VOR dose, they will be eligible to donate cells for the manufacture of HXTC (Step 3). Successful manufacturing of the HIV-1 antigen expanded specific T cells will progress participants to combination treatment in Steps 4 and 5. In Steps 4 and Step 5, participants will receive two series of VOR dosing and HXTC infusions, for a total 20 doses of VOR 400 mg and 5 HXTC infusions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VOR + HXTC arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>HIV-1 antigen expanded specific T-cell</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. ≥ 18 years and &lt; 65 years of age at screening

          2. Ability and willingness of participant to give written informed consent. Note: Due to
             the lack of foreseeable benefit to study volunteers, the study will not enroll
             illiterate or mentally incompetent volunteers.

          3. Karnofsky performance status &gt; 70.

          4. Confirmation of HIV-1 infection HIV infection is defined as documentation by any
             licensed rapid HIV test or HIV enzyme or chemiluminescence immunoassay (E/CIA) test
             kit at any time prior to study entry and confirmed by a licensed Western blot or a
             second antibody test by a method other than the initial rapid HIV and/or E/CIA, or by
             HIV-1 antigen, plasma HIV-1 RNA viral load.

             NOTE: The term &quot;licensed&quot; refers to a US FDA-approved kit.

             WHO (World Health Organization) and CDC (Centers for Disease Control and Prevention)
             guidelines mandate that confirmation of the initial test result must use a test that
             is different from the one used for the initial assessment. A reactive initial rapid
             test should be confirmed by either another type of rapid assay or an E/CIA that is
             based on a different antigen preparation and/or different test principle (e.g.,
             indirect versus competitive), or a Western blot or a plasma HIV-1 RNA viral load.

          5. On antiretroviral therapy for at least 24 months and on potent antiretroviral therapy
             for greater than or equal to 6 months prior to Screening (Visit 1).

             Potent ART is defined by current treatment guidelines and consists of at least 2
             nucleoside/nucleotide reverse transcriptase inhibitors plus a non-nucleoside reverse
             transcriptase inhibitor, integrase inhibitor, or a protease inhibitor without
             interruption (defined as missing doses for more than two (2) consecutive days or more
             than four (4) cumulative days) in the 24 weeks prior to Screening (Visit 1).

             Other potent fully suppressive antiretroviral combinations will be considered on a
             case-by-case basis. Prior changes in or elimination of medications for easier dosing
             schedule, intolerance, toxicity, or other reasons are permitted if an alternative
             suppressive regimen was maintained.

          6. Ability and willingness of participant to continue cART throughout the study.

          7. Able and willing to adhere to protocol therapy, schedule, and is judged adherent to
             antiretroviral therapy (adherence defined in inclusion criterion 5.)

          8. Plasma HIV-1 RNA &lt; 50 copies/mL at two time points in the previous 12 months prior to
             study screening (one time point can be at screening) and never &gt; or equal to 50
             copies/mL on two consecutive time points in the last 24 months.

             NOTE: A single unconfirmed plasma HIV RNA &gt; or equal to 50 copies/mL but &lt; 1000 c/mL
             is allowed if a subsequent assay was &lt; 50 copies/mL; but none in the 6 months
             preceding the study screening visit.

          9. Plasma HIV-1 RNA &lt; 50 copies/mL at screening (Visit 1).

         10. CD4+ cell count ≥ 350 cells/mm3 at screening (Visit 1).

         11. No active HCV infection at or within 90 days of screening (Visit 1). Note: No active
             HCV defined as negative HCVAb or if HCVAb is positive, reflex HCV RNA is negative.

         12. No active HBV infection (measureable HBV DNA or HBVsAg+) at or within 90 days of
             screening (Visit 1).

         13. Women with written documentation of any of the following:

               1. prior hysterectomy OR bilateral oophorectomy (removal of both ovaries)

               2. bilateral tubal ligation or non-surgical permanent sterilization

               3. Women with intact uterus and ovaries who have not had a period for ≥ one year AND
                  have a documented FSH level indicating postmenopausal status.

         14. All male study volunteers must agree not to participate in a conception process (e.g.
             active attempt to impregnate, sperm donation, in vitro fertilization) and, if
             participating in sexual activity that could lead to pregnancy, the male study
             volunteer and his female partner must use two reliable methods of contraception
             (condoms, with or without a spermicidal agent; a diaphragm or cervical cap with
             spermicide; an IUD; or hormonal-based contraception) simultaneously while receiving
             the protocol-specified study products and for 6 weeks after stopping the study
             products. Participants must use a reliable barrier method of contraception (condom,
             cervical cap) along with another form of contraception.

             NOTE: For female partners who are receiving ritonavir, estrogen-based contraceptives
             are not reliable and an alternative method should be suggested.

         15. Ability and willingness to provide adequate locator information.

         16. Ability and willingness to communicate effectively with study personnel

         17. Adequate vascular access for HXTC infusion and leukapheresis.

         18. Able to swallow pills without difficulty.

         19. Potential participant must have adequate organ function as indicated by the following
             laboratory values:

        System Laboratory Value Hematological Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1,500 /mcL Platelets
        ≥125,000 / mcL Hemoglobin ≥ 12 g/dL (male) and ≥ 11.5 g/dL (females) System Laboratory
        Value Coagulation Prothrombin Time (PT) or INR ≤1.1x upper limit of normal (ULN) Chemistry
        K+ levels Within normal limits Mg++ levels ≥ 1.4 mEq/L Glucose Screening serum glucose ≤
        Grade 1 (fasting or non- fasting) Albumin ≥ 3.5 g/dL or ≥ LLN Renal Creatinine clearance
        determined by the CKD-Epi equation found at:
        https://www.qxmd.com/calculate/calculator_251/egfr-using-ckd-epi eGFR &gt; 60mL/min Hepatic
        Serum total bilirubin Total bilirubin &lt; 1.1 times the ULN range. If total bilirubin is
        elevated, direct bilirubin must be &lt; 2 times the ULN range.

        NOTE: If participant is on an atazanavir-containing therapy, then a direct bilirubin should
        be measured instead of the total bilirubin and must be ≤ 1.0 mg/dL.

        AST (SGOT) and ALT (SGPT) &lt; 1.25 X ULN Alkaline Phosphatase &lt; 1.25 X ULN Lipase &lt; 1.1 X ULN
        ULN = upper limit of normal LLN = lower limit of normal

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Known allergy or sensitivity to components of VOR and its analog or to components in
             the HXTC product.

          2. Women without written documentation of menopause (absence of a period for ≥ one year
             and FSH level indicating menopause), hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy,
             non-surgical permanent sterilization, or bilateral tubal ligation.

          3. Untreated syphilis infection (defined as a positive rapid plasma reagingain (RPR)
             without clear documentation of treatment).

             Note: In cases of untreated syphilis, participant may re-screen following
             documentation of adequate treatment of syphilis

          4. All male participants expecting to father children within the projected duration of
             the study.

          5. Receipt of compounds with HDAC inhibitor-like activity, such as valproic acid within
             30 days prior to screening.

          6. Use of any investigational antiretroviral agents within 30 days prior to screening
             (Visit 1).

          7. If the study PI (or designee) or protocol team is unable to construct a fully active
             alternative cART regimen based on previous resistance testing and/or treatment
             history.

          8. Use of the following medications that carry risk of torsade des pointes: amiodarone,
             arsenic trioxide, astemizole, bepridil, chloroquine, chlorpromazine, cisapride,
             clarithromycin, diopyramide, dofetilide, domperidone, droperidol, erythromycin,
             halofantrine, haloperidol, ibutilide, levomethadyl, mesoridazine, methadone,
             pentamidine, pimozidine, probucol, procanimide, quinidine, sotalol, sparfloxacxin,
             terfenadine, thioridizine.

          9. Use of any of the following within 90 days prior to screening (Visit 1):
             immunomodulatory, cytokine, or growth stimulating factors such as systemic
             corticosteroids, cyclosporine, methotrexate, azathioprine, anti-CD25 antibody, IFN,
             interleukin-2 (IL-2), coumadin, warfarin, or other Coumadin derivative anticoagulants.

         10. Prior use of any HIV immunotherapy or HIV vaccine within 12 months prior to Screening
             (Visit 1), except for prior HXTC infusions.

         11. Received any infusion blood product, immune globulin, or hematopoietic growth factors
             within 90 days prior to study screening (Visit 1).

         12. Pregnancy or breast-feeding.

         13. History or other clinical evidence of severe illness, malignancy, immunodeficiency
             other than HIV, or any other condition that would make the participant unsuitable for
             the study in the opinion of the investigator (or designee).

         14. Use of topical steroids over a total area exceeding 0.5mg/kg/day within 30 days prior
             to Screening (Visit 1).

         15. Treatment for an active AIDS-defining opportunistic infection within 90 days prior to
             Screening (Visit 1).

         16. Any active malignancy that may require chemotherapy or radiation therapy.

         17. Compulsorily detained (involuntarily incarcerated) for treatment of either a
             psychiatric illness or a physical illness, e.g., infectious disease. Prisoner
             recruitment and participation is not permitted.

         18. Known psychiatric or substance abuse disorders that would interfere with participant's
             ability to fully cooperate with the requirements of the trial as assessed by the study
             investigator (or designee).

         19. History or other clinical evidence, as assessed by the study PI (or designee), of
             significant or unstable cardiac disease (e.g., angina, congestive heart failure,
             recent myocardial infarction, significant arrhythmia) or clinically significant
             electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormalities. Any history of cardiac rhythm disturbance
             requiring medical or surgical therapy.

         20. Unable to have a person available to drive participant home at infusion visits. 21.
             Participation in another investigational clinical research study (with the exception
             of an antiretroviral treatment trial that uses FDA approved antiretroviral agents) or
             use of investigational agents within 30 days prior to screening (Visit 1).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julia Sung, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Margolis, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cynthia Gay, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>JoAnn Kuruc, MSN, RN</last_name>
    <phone>919-966-8533</phone>
    <email>joann_kuruc@med.unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Julia Sung, MD</last_name>
    <phone>919-843-1550</phone>
    <email>julia_sung@med.unc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina Health Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27514</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>JoAnn Kuruc, MSN, RN</last_name>
      <phone>919-966-8533</phone>
      <email>joann_kuruc@med.unc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Julia Sung, MD</last_name>
      <phone>919-843-1550</phone>
      <email>julia_sung@med.unc.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Julia Sung, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Margolis, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cynthia Gay, MD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joseph Eron, Jr., MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 29, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 6, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>HXTC</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiretroviral Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV-Infected</keyword>
  <keyword>Vorinostat</keyword>
  <keyword>AIDS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vorinostat</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

