<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03213600</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017-A01042-51</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03213600</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neurostimulation-enhanced Behavioral Remediation of Social Cognition in Schizophrenia</brief_title>
  <acronym>NSOCOG</acronym>
  <official_title>Neurostimulation-enhanced Behavioral Remediation of Social Cognition in Schizophrenia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hôpital le Vinatier</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hôpital le Vinatier</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Social cognition concerns the understanding of how people think about others and how that, in
      turn, influences our behavior, feelings, and social interactions. schizophrenia
      social-cognitive impairment is profound (effect size D&gt;1.2), medication resistant and
      critically limits functional well-being . Social cognition involves complex patterns of
      coordinated activity within numerous cortical and subcortical networks, making it a difficult
      target for clinical neuroscience investigation. Yet, prior research demonstrates that
      sensory-perceptual dysfunction in schizophrenia can upwardly generalize into higher-order
      social-cognitive impairment making perception a tractable and fruitful approach for studying
      social cognition in schizophrenia. Here, the investigators explore how distortions in
      perception of temporal coincidence can contribute to the aberrant inferences of physical
      causation and social agency.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Social cognitive deficits in these patients are robust and hinder their ability to maintain
      gainful employment as well as forge and sustain meaningful social relationships. Current
      antipsychotic medications are largely ineffective in treating these symptoms. The proposed
      protocol aims at utilizing Noninvasive Brain Stimulation (NIBS) and cognitive behavioral
      training to enhance core perceptual impairment in marking time that may contribute to both
      social and nonsocial cognitive dysfunction in schizophrenia.

      Cognitive behavioral training along the line investigators propose has no reported adverse
      effects.The transdirect current stimulation (tDCS) is a very safe method with encouraging
      results in previous works in which no severe adverse events where found. There are a few
      minor side effects including skin irritation, a phosphene at the start of stimulation,
      nausea, headache, dizziness, and itching under the electrode. A recent study of over 500
      subjects using the currently accepted protocol reported only a slight skin irritation and a
      phosphene as side effects. Patients can benefit from a significant improvement of invalidant
      symptoms but also of their quality of life. To ensure safety, patients will be accompanied
      throughout the protocol by professionals trained in the management of their disease. Besides
      the protocol procedure, patients will be supported, in all centers, according to the
      international recommendations in terms of safety and practice. Patients receiving placebo
      procedure after randomization will pursue pharmacological treatment and usual health care.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>The investigators will enroll 150 subjects comprising three population groups SZ, At Risk and HS.) Immediately after inclusion, participants will be randomized into 2 equal groups via random generation of two binary integer's reflecting tDCS-treatment condition or the tDCS control (sham) resulting in random allocation into one of 2 study arms. This randomization will be stratified per population group to insure that both conditions are equally reflected across all three groups.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Causation Task - testing time based causal judgments</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Primary metric: threshold defined as the smallest time difference (in 16.7ms increments) at which subject judge ball movement &quot;B&quot; to be caused by the impact of ball &quot;A&quot; 75% of the time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Triangle Task - measuring the extent to which temporal coincidence is used to infer causality in a social situation</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Primary metric: threshold of tolerated relational time delay (levels in 16.7ms increments) between interacting visual figures (i.e triangles), under which participants reliably (at 75%) perceive social agency or social interactions.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EEG Task 1, Time visual oddball task - for measuring electrophysiological markers of active temporal (time) deviance detection</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Primary metric: Mismatch negativity in the event related potentials of electrodes over the visual cortex with typical latency of 150-250ms after the onset of the deviant stimuli</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>EEG Task 2, Covert visual simultaneity task - an exploratory task designed to model the visual Simultaneity behavioral task</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Primary metric: Dependent measure: decibel change in Alpha and Beta power across bellow- threshold and above- threshold conditions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resting state oscillatory structure</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Primary metric: Dependent measure: decibel change in Alpha and Beta power during rest</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Behaviors and Mental Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>transcranial Direct Current Stimulation ( tDCS )</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intensity : 1,5mA Duration : 20 minutes stimulation over frontal (F3/F4) electrodes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>transcranial Direct Current Stimulation ( tDCS)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intensity : 1,5mA Duration : 20 minutes stimulation over parietal(CP3 CP4) electrodes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>transcranial Direct Current Stimulation tDCS</intervention_name>
    <description>75 participants will receive 20 minutes of active tDCS (1,5mA, 20 minutes stimulation over frontal (F3/F4) electrodes ); A group of 75 participants will receive 1,5mA 20 minutes of stimulation over parietal (CP3 CP4) electrodes. During this stimulation session and we will also measure your ability to perceive visual and auditory objects presented by a computer, while recording your brain activity using electroencephalography or EEG (a technique using electrodes that measures the electrical activity of your brain)</description>
    <arm_group_label>transcranial Direct Current Stimulation ( tDCS )</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>transcranial Direct Current Stimulation ( tDCS)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  be between 18 and 45-years-old

          -  have normal hearing assessed by the Five-minute hearing test

          -  have French as a first language

          -  be able to provide written informed consent

          -  be right handed as measured by the Edinburgh handedness scale

          -  covered by, or having the right to Social Security

          -  informed consent signed

          -  patients with diagnosis of schizoprenia or schizoaffective disorder-depressive type as
             determined by the SCID Diagnostic Interview for DSM-V and administered by a clinician

          -  clinically stable and on a stable medication regiment for the past 3 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  significant medical or neurological illness or history of fetal alcohol exposure that
             may increase risks of the study, significantly affect brain function, or impede
             participation

          -  substance dependence (except nicotine) or abuse not in remission within the past six
             months or recent use presenting the possibility of acute intoxication or withdrawal

          -  a history of any Axis I psychiatric disorder except those required in the inclusion
             criteria, any history of pervasive developmental disorder or mental retardation

          -  for Visit 3: If participating in tCDS Contraindications for tDCS (pacemaker or brain
             stimulator) and/or MRI (neurologic stimulator, pacemaker, cardiac defibrillator,
             cardiac prosthesis, vascular prosthesis, intracranial clips or clamps, cerebrospinal
             fluid derivation, metallic splinters in the eyes)

          -  patients under curatorship/guardianship and whose clinical condition requires
             inpatient procedure under constraint

          -  healthy controls must not be currently using psychoactive médications or have a
             first-degree relative with a psychotic disorder
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>POULET EMMANUEL, MD - PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>CH LE VINATIER</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>POULET EMMANUEL, MD - PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+33(0)4 37 91 55 65</phone>
    <email>emmanuel.poulet@chu-lyon.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>LEITMAN DAVID, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+33(0)4 37 91 55 65</phone>
    <email>david.leitman@ext.inserm.fr</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Le Vinatier</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bron</city>
        <zip>69678</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>emmanuel poulet, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>33437915565</phone>
      <email>emmanuel.poulet@chu-lyon.fr</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>VIAL VERONIQUE</last_name>
      <phone>+33(0)437915531</phone>
      <email>veronique.vial@ch-le-vinatier.fr</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>emmanuel poulet, md, phd</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 7, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 7, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 11, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

