<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03215927</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BMS: IM101-657</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03215927</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Abatacept for the Treatment of Myositis-associated Interstitial Lung Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>ATtackMy-ILD</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Controlled Pilot Trial to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Subcutaneous Abatacept in Treating Interstitial Lung Disease Associated With the Anti-synthetase Syndrome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rohit Aggarwal, MD</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bristol-Myers Squibb</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A randomized, controlled pilot trial to evaluate the efficacy and safety of subcutaneous
      Abatacept in treating interstitial lung disease associated with the anti-synthetase syndrome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a proof of concept study to evaluate the efficacy, safety and tolerability of ABT in
      Syn-ILD in a multi-center randomized, placebo-controlled 6-month (24-week) pilot study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 9, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A 1:1 randomization scheme for abatacept 125 mg vs. placebo as a weekly SQ injection for 24 weeks.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Only the site pharmacist is unblinded.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>FVC% Change</measure>
    <time_frame>24 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome criteria for efficacy will be the FVC% change from the baseline visit to week 24 between the 2 treatment arms (SOC/placebo vs. SOC/Abatacept).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to progression free survival where progression</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The first occurrence of any of the following: death or lung transplant or FVC ≥10% decline or FVC ≥5% decline with DLCO ≥15% decline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of change in patient reported dyspnea scores</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>measured by University of California San Diego Shortness of Breath Questionnaire (UCSD SOBQ) (range 0-120, higher score is worsening dyspnea).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to improvement in FVC% by ≥10</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of FVC% results from pulmonary function tests from baseline, 3 and 6 months. Improvement is defined as an FVC% change ≥10.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Myositis</condition>
  <condition>Interstitial Lung Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subcutaneous placebo injection weekly for 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Abatacept</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subcutaneous injection of abatacept 125 mg weekly for 24 weeks. 24 week optional follow up phase all subjects receive abatacept 125 mg weekly.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Abatacept</intervention_name>
    <description>Abatacept 125mg subcutaneous weekly</description>
    <arm_group_label>Abatacept</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Orencia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 18 years.

          2. Anti-synthetase syndrome defined as the patient possessing 1 antisynthetase
             autoantibody (Jo-1, PL-12, PL-7, KS, OJ, EJ, Zo) in the presence of autoimmune ILD.

          3. ILD defined by radiographic (HRCT chest) findings of reticulation, honeycombing or
             ground glass opacities (GGO) without another plausible explanation. HRCT chest
             defining ILD for inclusion criteria, should be within last 1 year done as SOC.

          4. Active ILD (see Section 4.2).

          5. Baseline FVC % &lt;80% as minimal threshold of ILD severity (PFT done within last 3
             months is acceptable for inclusion criteria determination).

          6. SOC immunosuppressive therapy (IS) therapy:

               1. Steroids (prednisone or other forms of steroid in equivalent doses) OR one of the
                  other immunosuppressive agent (either Mycophenolate (MMF) or Azathioprine) OR a
                  combination of steroid and an immunosuppressive agent. MMF (maximum of 3 gm/day)
                  or azathioprine (maximum of 200 mg/day).Goal is to start the trial drug (or
                  placebo) soon after starting SOC (MMF/AZA/Steroids) and their doses are stable.
                  Note that patients on steroids alone as well as not on steroids can be enrolled
                  in the trial as well.

               2. Desired dose of the SOC therapy should be reached 4 weeks prior to first study
                  visit (Visit 1). No dose changes are allowed 4 weeks prior to first study visit.

               3. Dose of concomitant therapy (SOC) cannot be changed during the 24 weeks of the
                  trial unless safety/toxicity issues supervene.

               4. If on steroid, the steroid dose must be stable for 2 weeks prior to Visit 1.

          7. No other concomitant IS medications including methotrexate, cyclosporine, IVIG,
             tacrolimus, cyclophosphamide or tofacitinib.

          8. No concomitant biologic agents (i.e. rituximab, anti-TNF agents, tocilizumab).

          9. Additional IS therapy: Patient cannot begin any new IS therapy or new steroid taper
             for the 24-week study period, except if severe clinical worsening (flare up) of the
             disease requiring rescue therapy occurs (i.e. documentation of worsening of PFT/HRCT
             and patient and physician determination of worsening). See section of rescue
             medication below for details.

         10. If the enrolling physician is planning to discontinue current IS agent or steroid
             before clinical trial, then following washout period is required prior to Visit 1.

             Medication Washout Period methotrexate 4 weeks Other IS agent (e.g. azathioprine,
             cyclosporine, tacrolimus, leflunomide, mycophenolate mofetil) 4 weeks IVIg or
             cyclophosphamide 3 months rituximab 6 months infliximab or adalimumab 8 weeks
             glucocorticoids 2 weeks etanercept 2 weeks anakinra 1 week

         11. Men and women of reproductive potential must agree to use an acceptable method of
             birth control during the trial period.

         12. Subject has provided written informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        A patient will be excluded if any of the following Exclusion Criteria are met:

          1. Severe end stage lung disease:

               1. FVC ≤30% or FEV1 ≤ 30% or

               2. Requirement of high O2 requirement ≥ 6 L/min at rest for &gt;1 month before the
                  study enrollment or

               3. Listed for lung transplantation or

               4. PI feels that ILD is severe and end stage fibrosis is such that there is low
                  potential for improvement with any disease modifying intervention.

          2. Subjects under the age of 18.

          3. Known active current or history of recurrent bacterial, viral, fungal, mycobacterial
             or other infections (including but not limited to tuberculosis and atypical
             mycobacterial disease, hepatitis B and C, and herpes zoster, but excluding fungal
             infections of nail beds).

          4. Any major episode of infection requiring hospitalization or treatment with IV
             antibiotics within 4 weeks of screening.

          5. Active TB requiring treatment within the previous 3 years. Patients should be screened
             for latent TB using PPD/or quantiferon gold within last 1 year and, if positive,
             treated following local practice guidelines prior to initiating ABT. Patients treated
             for active tuberculosis with no recurrence in 3 years are permitted.

          6. Primary or secondary immunodeficiency (history of or currently active) unless related
             to primary disease under investigation.

          7. Pregnant women or nursing (breast feeding) mothers.

          8. History of alcohol, drug or chemical abuse within 1 year prior to screening or any
             medical condition or physical or psychological state that the PI feels would not allow
             the subject to safely complete the study.

          9. Major surgery (including joint surgery) within 8 weeks prior to screening or planned
             major surgery within 6 months following randomization.

         10. Treatment with any other investigational agent within 4 weeks (or 5 half-lives of the
             investigational drug, whichever is longer) of screening.

         11. Previous treatment with the following cell-depleting therapies, including
             investigational agents or approved therapies: CAMPATH, anti-CD4, anti-CD5, and
             anti-CD3.

         12. Previous treatment with ABT.

         13. History of severe allergic or anaphylactic reactions to monoclonal antibodies.

         14. Evidence of serious uncontrolled concomitant cardiovascular, nervous system, renal,
             hepatic, endocrine (include uncontrolled diabetes mellitus) or gastrointestinal
             disease (including complicated diverticulitis, ulcerative colitis, or Crohn's
             disease.)

         15. Evidence of concomitant lung disease which PI feels may interfere with clinical
             assessment of ILD for example severe active COPD, asthma, occupational lung disease,
             pulmonary sarcoidosis, etc.

         16. Prisoners or subjects who are compulsory detained
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rohit Aggarwal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Courtney Ward</last_name>
    <phone>412-648-9989</phone>
    <email>cow24@pitt.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Diane Koontz</last_name>
    <phone>412-383-8674</phone>
    <email>dik4@pitt.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beverly Hills</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90211</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karla Alvarez</last_name>
      <phone>310-360-9197</phone>
      <email>karla@attunehealth.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Swamy Venuturupalli, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mallary Crow Adams</last_name>
      <phone>303-724-8403</phone>
      <email>Mallary.CrowAdams@ucdenver.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Aryeh Fischer, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Joyce Lee, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>John Hopkins Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sherry Leung</last_name>
      <phone>410-550-1741</phone>
      <email>sleung7@jhu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cheilonda Johnson, MD, MHS</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sonya Danoff, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham &amp; Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Luisa Quesada</last_name>
      <phone>617-525-7370</phone>
      <email>lquesadaarias@bwh.harvard.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul F. Dellaripa, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tracy J. Doyle, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15261</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Courtney Ward</last_name>
      <phone>412-648-9989</phone>
      <email>cow24@pitt.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Diane Koontz</last_name>
      <phone>412-383-8674</phone>
      <email>dik4@pitt.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rohit Aggarwal, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kurasawa K, Nawata Y, Takabayashi K, Kumano K, Kita Y, Takiguchi Y, Kuriyama T, Sueishi M, Saito Y, Iwamoto I. Activation of pulmonary T cells in corticosteroid-resistant and -sensitive interstitial pneumonitis in dermatomyositis/polymyositis. Clin Exp Immunol. 2002 Sep;129(3):541-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12197897</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Israël-Assayag E, Fournier M, Cormier Y. Blockade of T cell costimulation by CTLA4-Ig inhibits lung inflammation in murine hypersensitivity pneumonitis. J Immunol. 1999 Dec 15;163(12):6794-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10586079</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jiménez-Alvarez L, Arreola JL, Ramírez-Martínez G, Ortiz-Quintero B, Gaxiola M, Reynoso-Robles R, Avila-Moreno F, Urrea F, Pardo A, Selman M, Zuñiga J. The effect of CTLA-4Ig, a CD28/B7 antagonist, on the lung inflammation and T cell subset profile during murine hypersensitivity pneumonitis. Exp Mol Pathol. 2011 Dec;91(3):718-22. doi: 10.1016/j.yexmp.2011.09.010. Epub 2011 Sep 14.</citation>
    <PMID>21945736</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murata K, Dalakas MC. Expression of the costimulatory molecule BB-1, the ligands CTLA-4 and CD28, and their mRNA in inflammatory myopathies. Am J Pathol. 1999 Aug;155(2):453-60.</citation>
    <PMID>10433938</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nagaraju K, Raben N, Villalba ML, Danning C, Loeffler LA, Lee E, Tresser N, Abati A, Fetsch P, Plotz PH. Costimulatory markers in muscle of patients with idiopathic inflammatory myopathies and in cultured muscle cells. Clin Immunol. 1999 Aug;92(2):161-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10444360</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cutolo M, Soldano S, Montagna P, Sulli A, Seriolo B, Villaggio B, Triolo P, Clerico P, Felli L, Brizzolara R. CTLA4-Ig interacts with cultured synovial macrophages from rheumatoid arthritis patients and downregulates cytokine production. Arthritis Res Ther. 2009;11(6):R176. doi: 10.1186/ar2865. Epub 2009 Nov 23.</citation>
    <PMID>19930661</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buch MH, Boyle DL, Rosengren S, Saleem B, Reece RJ, Rhodes LA, Radjenovic A, English A, Tang H, Vratsanos G, O'Connor P, Firestein GS, Emery P. Mode of action of abatacept in rheumatoid arthritis patients having failed tumour necrosis factor blockade: a histological, gene expression and dynamic magnetic resonance imaging pilot study. Ann Rheum Dis. 2009 Jul;68(7):1220-7. doi: 10.1136/ard.2008.091876. Epub 2008 Sep 4. Erratum in: Ann Rheum Dis. 2011 Aug;70(8):1519.</citation>
    <PMID>18772191</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lumsden JM, Roberts JM, Harris NL, Peach RJ, Ronchese F. Differential requirement for CD80 and CD80/CD86-dependent costimulation in the lung immune response to an influenza virus infection. J Immunol. 2000 Jan 1;164(1):79-85.</citation>
    <PMID>10604996</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Platt AM, Gibson VB, Patakas A, Benson RA, Nadler SG, Brewer JM, McInnes IB, Garside P. Abatacept limits breach of self-tolerance in a murine model of arthritis via effects on the generation of T follicular helper cells. J Immunol. 2010 Aug 1;185(3):1558-67. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.1001311. Epub 2010 Jul 2.</citation>
    <PMID>20601593</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mitsui T, Kuroda Y, Ueno S, Kaji R. The effects of FK506 on refractory inflammatory myopathies. Acta Neurol Belg. 2011 Sep;111(3):188-94.</citation>
    <PMID>22141281</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ochi S, Nanki T, Takada K, Suzuki F, Komano Y, Kubota T, Miyasaka N. Favorable outcomes with tacrolimus in two patients with refractory interstitial lung disease associated with polymyositis/dermatomyositis. Clin Exp Rheumatol. 2005 Sep-Oct;23(5):707-10.</citation>
    <PMID>16173253</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ando M, Miyazaki E, Yamasue M, Sadamura Y, Ishii T, Takenaka R, Ito T, Nureki S, Kumamoto T. Successful treatment with tacrolimus of progressive interstitial pneumonia associated with amyopathic dermatomyositis refractory to cyclosporine. Clin Rheumatol. 2010 Apr;29(4):443-5. doi: 10.1007/s10067-009-1358-x. Epub 2010 Feb 4.</citation>
    <PMID>20130943</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Takada K, Nagasaka K, Miyasaka N. Polymyositis/dermatomyositis and interstitial lung disease: a new therapeutic approach with T-cell-specific immunosuppressants. Autoimmunity. 2005 Aug;38(5):383-92. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16227154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilkes MR, Sereika SM, Fertig N, Lucas MR, Oddis CV. Treatment of antisynthetase-associated interstitial lung disease with tacrolimus. Arthritis Rheum. 2005 Aug;52(8):2439-46.</citation>
    <PMID>16052580</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guglielmo S, Bertinaria M, Rolando B, Crosetti M, Fruttero R, Yardley V, Croft SL, Gasco A. A new series of amodiaquine analogues modified in the basic side chain with in vitro antileishmanial and antiplasmodial activity. Eur J Med Chem. 2009 Dec;44(12):5071-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ejmech.2009.09.012. Epub 2009 Sep 15.</citation>
    <PMID>19811859</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kerola AM, Nieminen TV, Kauppi MJ, Kautiainen H, Puolakka K, Virta LJ, Kerola T. Increased risk of levothyroxine-treated hypothyroidism preceding the diagnosis of rheumatoid arthritis: a nationwide registry study. Clin Exp Rheumatol. 2014 Jul-Aug;32(4):455-9. Epub 2014 Jun 6.</citation>
    <PMID>24959977</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arabshahi B, Silverman RA, Jones OY, Rider LG. Abatacept and sodium thiosulfate for treatment of recalcitrant juvenile dermatomyositis complicated by ulceration and calcinosis. J Pediatr. 2012 Mar;160(3):520-2. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2011.11.057. Epub 2012 Jan 13.</citation>
    <PMID>22244459</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maeshima K, Kiyonaga Y, Imada C, Iwakura M, Hamasaki H, Haranaka M, Ishii K. Successful treatment of refractory anti-signal recognition particle myopathy using abatacept. Rheumatology (Oxford). 2014 Feb;53(2):379-80. doi: 10.1093/rheumatology/ket251. Epub 2013 Aug 6.</citation>
    <PMID>23920268</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elhai M, Meunier M, Matucci-Cerinic M, Maurer B, Riemekasten G, Leturcq T, Pellerito R, Von Mühlen CA, Vacca A, Airo P, Bartoli F, Fiori G, Bokarewa M, Riccieri V, Becker M, Avouac J, Müller-Ladner U, Distler O, Allanore Y; EUSTAR (EULAR Scleroderma Trials and Research group). Outcomes of patients with systemic sclerosis-associated polyarthritis and myopathy treated with tocilizumab or abatacept: a EUSTAR observational study. Ann Rheum Dis. 2013 Jul;72(7):1217-20. doi: 10.1136/annrheumdis-2012-202657. Epub 2012 Dec 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23253926</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mera-Varela A, Pérez-Pampín E. Abatacept therapy in rheumatoid arthritis with interstitial lung disease. J Clin Rheumatol. 2014 Dec;20(8):445-6. doi: 10.1097/RHU.0000000000000084.</citation>
    <PMID>25417684</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khanna D, Mittoo S, Aggarwal R, Proudman SM, Dalbeth N, Matteson EL, Brown K, Flaherty K, Wells AU, Seibold JR, Strand V. Connective Tissue Disease-associated Interstitial Lung Diseases (CTD-ILD) - Report from OMERACT CTD-ILD Working Group. J Rheumatol. 2015 Nov;42(11):2168-71. doi: 10.3899/jrheum.141182. Epub 2015 Mar 1. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25729034</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 28, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 10, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 12, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 9, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 9, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 10, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rohit Aggarwal, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ILD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases, Interstitial</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myositis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Abatacept</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

