<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03210051</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RIC-AIS-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03210051</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Remote Ischemic Conditioning Paired With Endovascular Treatment for Acute Ischemic Stroke (REVISE-1)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study Assessing the Safety and Feasibility of Remote Ischemic Conditioning Paired With Endovascular Treatment for Acute Ischemic Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Capital Medical University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Capital Medical University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Currently, early reperfusion is considered as the most effective therapy for the treatment of
      acute ischemic stroke (AIS). Over the past 20 years, intravenous tissue plasminogen activator
      (IV tPA) has been demonstrated to be the only effective therapy for AIS. More recently,
      several large randomized clinical trials have concluded the superiority of endovascular
      mechanical thrombectomy for AIS. Furthermore, with the development of materials and
      techniques, the occluded artery can be recanalized with high percentage (60%-90%), and the
      rate of recanalization is still being improved. A great number of AIS patients are now
      eligible for revascularization therapy and there should be a good prognosis of AIS after
      recanalizing the occluded artery using mechanical thrombectomy. However, things are never as
      simple as wished to be. The rate of patients with functional independence is less than 50%
      and over 15% patients died at 3 months post thrombectomy. The discrepancy between the
      functional outcome and recanalization rates encourage researchers to explore strategies that
      further improving the functional outcome of AIS patients.

      Remote ischemic conditioning has been demonstrated to reduce cerebral infarct size in mouse
      model of focal cerebral ischemia. And clinical researches demonstrated the protective effects
      of remote ischemic conditioning in AIS patient treated with IV tPA,. However, whether remote
      ischemic conditioning is safe and effective in protecting patients with large-vessel ischemic
      stroke and undergoing endovascular treatment is still unknown.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the present study, the investigators will assess the safety and feasibility of remote
      ischemic condition paired with endovascular treatment for AIS. A single arm of AIS patients
      treated with endovascular therapy will be recruited, and remote ischemic conditioning will be
      applied prior to reperfusion therapy and in combination with post reperfusion therapy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 7, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 20, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 17, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Device Feasibility</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with any RIC-related adverse events.</measure>
    <time_frame>0-90 days after endovascular treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>For all participants, adverse events will be assessed by as assessed by CTCAE v4.0.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in cerebral artery blood flow velocity</measure>
    <time_frame>0-7 days.</time_frame>
    <description>Cerebral artery blood flow velocity is recorded continuously by Transcranial Doppler (TCD) during remote ischemic conditioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in vital signs</measure>
    <time_frame>0-7 days.</time_frame>
    <description>Vital signs are documented continuously during remote ischemic conditioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in intracranial pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>0-7 days.</time_frame>
    <description>Intracranial pressure is monitored by noninvasive intracranial pressure monitoring equipment during remote ischemic conditioning</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in plasma biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>0-7 days.</time_frame>
    <description>Plasma biomarkers include biochemical biomarkers (e.g.,creatine kinase), blood routine test and coagulation function (e.g., PT, APTT, TT).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Final cerebral infarct volume.</measure>
    <time_frame>5-9 days after endovascular treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>The final infarct volume of cerebral infarct is evaluated by cranial noncontrast CT.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects completing all the designed RIC procedures.</measure>
    <time_frame>0-7 days.</time_frame>
    <description>9 times (36 cycles) of RIC interventions are planned to be applied to each subject pre and post-endovascular treatment for 7 consecutive days.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The severity of global disability at 90 days, as assessed by modified Rankin scale (mRS).</measure>
    <time_frame>0-90 days.</time_frame>
    <description>The mRS is an ordinal, graded interval scale that assigns patients among 7 global disability levels, which ranging from 0 (no symptom) to 5 (severe disability) and 6 (death).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Symptomatic Intracerebral Hemorrhage.</measure>
    <time_frame>0-90 days.</time_frame>
    <description>Deterioration in NIHSS score of ≥4 points within 24 hours from treatment and evidence of hemorrhage in imaging scans.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Any adverse event.</measure>
    <time_frame>0-90 days.</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events related or not related to remote ischemic conditioning will be documented.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RIC &amp; ET</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Remote ischemic conditioning paired with endovascular treatment. RIC is a physical strategy performed by an electric autocontrol device with cuffs placed on bilateral arms and inflated to 200 mmHg for 5-min followed by deflation for 5-min, the procedures is performed repeatedly for 5 times. Endovascular treatment of acute ischemic stroke is performed by experienced neuroradiologist according to the latest guideline from American Heart Association and American Stroke Association. It includes thrombectomy, intra-arterial thrombolysis, thrombus aspiration, stenting and balloon angioplasty.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Remote ischemic conditioning</intervention_name>
    <description>RIC is a physical strategy performed by an electric autocontrol device with cuffs placed on bilateral arms and inflated to 200 mmHg for 5-min followed by deflation for 5-min, the procedures is performed repeatedly for 5 times.</description>
    <arm_group_label>RIC &amp; ET</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RIC</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endovascular treatment</intervention_name>
    <description>Endovascular treatment include strategies that used to recanalize the occluded artery. Strategies often used include thrombectomy, intra-arterial thrombolysis, stenting and balloon angiography.</description>
    <arm_group_label>RIC &amp; ET</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ET</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Acute ischemic stroke where patient is ineligible for intravenous thrombolytic
             treatment or the treatment is contraindicated, or where patient has received
             intravenous thrombolytic therapy without recanalization;

          2. No remarkable pre-stroke functional disability (mRS ≤ 1);

          3. Age ≥18 and ≤ 80;

          4. Patient treatable within six hours of symptom onset;

          5. Informed consent obtained from patient or acceptable patient's surrogate

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Identified hemorrhagic diathesis, coagulation factor deficiency, or oral anticoagulant
             therapy with INR &gt; 3.0;

          2. Baseline platelet count &lt; 30*109/L;

          3. Baseline blood glucose of &lt; 2.7mmol/L or &gt;22.2mmol/L;

          4. Renal insufficiency with creatinine ≥ 265 umol/L;

          5. Severe, sustained hypertension (SBP &gt; 185 mmHg or DBP &gt; 110 mmHg);

          6. Woman of childbearing potential who is known to be pregnant or lactating;

          7. Subject participating in a study involving other drug or device trial study;

          8. Patients with a pre-existing neurological or psychiatric disease that would confound
             the neurological or functional evaluations;

          9. Unlikely to be available for 90-day follow-up;

         10. Contraindication for remote ischemic conditioning: severe soft tissue injury,
             fracture, or peripheral vascular disease in the upper limbs;

         11. Hypodensity on CT or restricted diffusion amounting to an ASPECTS score of &lt;7 on
             noncontrast CT;

         12. CT or MRI evidence of hemorrhage;

         13. Significant mass effect with midline shift on CT or MRI scans;

         14. Subjects with artery occlusions in multiple vascular territories;

         15. Evidence of intracranial tumor.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Xuanwu Hospital, Capital Medical University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beijing</city>
        <zip>100053</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hausenloy DJ, Barrabes JA, Bøtker HE, Davidson SM, Di Lisa F, Downey J, Engstrom T, Ferdinandy P, Carbrera-Fuentes HA, Heusch G, Ibanez B, Iliodromitis EK, Inserte J, Jennings R, Kalia N, Kharbanda R, Lecour S, Marber M, Miura T, Ovize M, Perez-Pinzon MA, Piper HM, Przyklenk K, Schmidt MR, Redington A, Ruiz-Meana M, Vilahur G, Vinten-Johansen J, Yellon DM, Garcia-Dorado D. Ischaemic conditioning and targeting reperfusion injury: a 30 year voyage of discovery. Basic Res Cardiol. 2016 Nov;111(6):70. Epub 2016 Oct 20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27766474</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ren C, Wang P, Wang B, Li N, Li W, Zhang C, Jin K, Ji X. Limb remote ischemic per-conditioning in combination with post-conditioning reduces brain damage and promotes neuroglobin expression in the rat brain after ischemic stroke. Restor Neurol Neurosci. 2015;33(3):369-79. doi: 10.3233/RNN-140413.</citation>
    <PMID>25868435</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meng R, Asmaro K, Meng L, Liu Y, Ma C, Xi C, Li G, Ren C, Luo Y, Ling F, Jia J, Hua Y, Wang X, Ding Y, Lo EH, Ji X. Upper limb ischemic preconditioning prevents recurrent stroke in intracranial arterial stenosis. Neurology. 2012 Oct 30;79(18):1853-61. doi: 10.1212/WNL.0b013e318271f76a. Epub 2012 Oct 3.</citation>
    <PMID>23035060</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 4, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 6, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 22, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Capital Medical University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ji Xunming</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Professor, Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acute ischemic stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Endovascular treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Remote ischemic conditioning</keyword>
  <keyword>Reperfusion therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuroprotection</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

