<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03219294</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>988210-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03219294</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Does Deep Neuromuscular Blockade Improve Operating Conditions During Total Hip Replacements?</brief_title>
  <official_title>Does Deep Neuromuscular Blockade Improve Operating Conditions During Total Hip Replacements?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Craig Curry</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Maine Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Spectrum Medical Group Anesthesiology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Maine Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      During many surgeries, increased muscle tension makes it harder for the surgeon to expose the
      site of surgery and work within the incision. Neuromuscular blockade (NMB) drugs such as
      Vecuronium bind to neurotransmitter (acetyl choline) receptors at the neuromuscular junction,
      blocking their action and producing muscle relaxation. This muscle relaxation allows easier
      retraction of muscle tissues and manipulation of structures in the wound. Improved surgical
      conditions are likely to result in improved patient outcomes. While increased depths of NMB
      have been shown to optimize surgical conditions during intra-abdominal and retroperitoneal
      procedures, the impact of NMB depth has not been reported for orthopedic surgeries.1 To
      address this, we propose to study the effect of NMB depth on surgical conditions during total
      hip replacement (THR).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific Aims

        1. Assess difference in surgical conditions between moderate and deep NMB groups. Enrolled
           patients will be randomized to receive moderate (n=58) or deep (n=58) NMB. Difference in
           surgical conditions will be evaluated by:

             1. The number of requests from the surgeon for additional relaxation (NMB) during the
                procedure. At any time during the operation if the surgeon feels the muscle tension
                is interfering with ease of operation he will ask for additional muscle relaxation.
                If the patient is moderately relaxed they will be converted to deep relaxation with
                additional muscle relaxants. If they are already deeply relaxed no additional
                relaxants will be administered (as is our current practice). All requests will be
                recorded.

             2. Rating by the surgeon after each surgery using an internally developed satisfaction
                scale. The scale was developed by modifying a scale used in a previous study of
                muscle relaxation in intra-abdominal surgery1 to specify two key elements
                identified by our surgeon: ease of muscle retraction and femur manipulation.

        2. Assess the impact of deep vs moderate NMB on time of surgery, measured from the time of
           incision to joint reduction.

      SIGNIFICANCE If we identify improved surgical conditions with deeper relaxation we will
      incorporate deep NMB into our routine anesthesia practice for THR.

      Vecuronium will be used as NMB drug in all study patients; this agent is currently used in
      over 90% of THR cases at Maine Medical Center (MMC). As is currently routine Vecuronium will
      be given after initiation of general anesthesia with propofol to facilitate intubation and
      further doses of Vecuronium will be given throughout the case as noted below to maintain NMB
      at the desired depth until the femoral implant is reduced. After the intubating dose of
      Vecuronium, NMB depth will be monitored every 5 minutes and dosing will be adjusted as needed
      to maintain a constant depth of NMB according to our current routine practice.

      Group 1: Moderate NMB: Intubating dose of Vecuronium of 0.1 mg/kg (IBW) and re-dosing with
      0.0125 to 0.05 mg/kg as needed to achieve and maintain 1 to 2 train of four (TOF)
      contractions. Redosing in this manner is a current clinical practice.

      Group 2: Deep NMB: Intubating dose of Vecuronium of 0.2 mg/kg (IBW) and re-dosing with 0.025
      to 0.1 mg/kg to achieve and maintain zero twitches in the TOF, and post tetanic count (PTC)
      of 1 to 2 contractions. This level of blockade is new to the practice since approval of the
      drug for use at MMC but is in common use since the advent of Sugammadex.

      The surgeon may request additional relaxation at anytime for inadequate surgical conditions
      thought to be related to muscle tension. All requests will be recorded. Patients in the
      moderate NMB group will receive additional doses of vecuronium to achieve deep NMB (PTC of 1-
      2). In the deep NMB group with PTC of 1-2, a saline dose without NMB will be given.

      NMB reversal Sugammadex will be given for reversal of NMB after the prosthesis has been
      reduced, using routine dosing of 2 mg/kg for the moderate group and 4 mg/kg for the deep
      group, per package insert by Merck.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>The anesthesiologist will NOT be blinded, but the orthopedic surgeon performing the hip replacement surgery will be.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Surgical conditions</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 24 hours for each patient and up to one year for the whole study.</time_frame>
    <description>The surgeon will grade the overall surgical conditions on a 5 point Likert scale, that will be taken into account along with requests for additional muscle relaxation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 24 hours for each patient and up to one year for the whole study.</time_frame>
    <description>Time from incision to joint reduction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">116</enrollment>
  <condition>Arthropathy of Hip</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate NMB</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intubating dose of Vecuronium 0.1 mg/kg (IBW) and re-dosing with 0.0125 to 0.05 mg/kg as needed to achieve and maintain 1 to 2 TOF contractions. Redosing in this manner is a current clinical practice.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Deep NMB</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Deep NMB: Intubating dose of Vecuronium 0.2 mg/kg (IBW) and re-dosing with 0.025 to 0.1 mg/kg to achieve and maintain zero twitches in the TOF, and post tetanic count (PTC) of 1 to 2 contractions. This level of blockade is new to the practice since approval of the drug for use at MMC but is in common use since the advent of Sugammadex.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vecuronium 0.1 mg/kg</intervention_name>
    <description>Vecuronium will be administered to achieve and maintain 1 to 2 TOF contractions.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Moderate NMB</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>vecuronium bromide</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vecuronium 0.2mg/kg</intervention_name>
    <description>Vecuronium will be administered to achieve and 0 TOF/PTC 1-2.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Deep NMB</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>vecuronium bromide</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) Physical status 1-3

          -  age 50-75

          -  English speaking

          -  able to provide informed consent

          -  BMI equal to less than 30

          -  non-emergent THR by anterolateral minimally invasive non-cemented total hip
             arthroplasty

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Revision surgery

          -  Bilateral THR

          -  ASA 4+

          -  age less than 50 or greater than 75

          -  BMI greater than 30

          -  unable to provide informed consent

          -  women taking oral contraceptives (Sugammadex used for reversal interferes with their
             efficacy

          -  contraindications to general inhalation anesthesia (such as malignant hyperthermia)

          -  contraindications to NMB (known allergy to NMB)

          -  chronic kidney disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Craig Curry, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Maine Medical Center/Spectrum Medical Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Janelle Richard, BA</last_name>
    <phone>2076622862</phone>
    <email>richaj3@mmc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Maine Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Maine</state>
        <zip>04102</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Janelle Richard, BA, CCRP</last_name>
      <phone>207-662-2862</phone>
      <email>richaj3@mmc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Craig Curry, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Basad E, Ishaque B, Stürz H, Jerosch J. The anterolateral minimally invasive approach for total hip arthroplasty: technique, pitfalls, and way out. Orthop Clin North Am. 2009 Oct;40(4):473-8, viii. doi: 10.1016/j.ocl.2009.05.001. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19773052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brueckmann B, Sasaki N, Grobara P, Li MK, Woo T, de Bie J, Maktabi M, Lee J, Kwo J, Pino R, Sabouri AS, McGovern F, Staehr-Rye AK, Eikermann M. Effects of sugammadex on incidence of postoperative residual neuromuscular blockade: a randomized, controlled study. Br J Anaesth. 2015 Nov;115(5):743-51. doi: 10.1093/bja/aev104. Epub 2015 May 2.</citation>
    <PMID>25935840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Madsen MV, Staehr-Rye AK, Gätke MR, Claudius C. Neuromuscular blockade for optimising surgical conditions during abdominal and gynaecological surgery: a systematic review. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2015 Jan;59(1):1-16. doi: 10.1111/aas.12419. Epub 2014 Oct 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25328055</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paton F, Paulden M, Chambers D, Heirs M, Duffy S, Hunter JM, Sculpher M, Woolacott N. Sugammadex compared with neostigmine/glycopyrrolate for routine reversal of neuromuscular block: a systematic review and economic evaluation. Br J Anaesth. 2010 Nov;105(5):558-67. doi: 10.1093/bja/aeq269. Epub 2010 Oct 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20935005</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chambers D, Paulden M, Paton F, Heirs M, Duffy S, Craig D, Hunter J, Wilson J, Sculpher M, Woolacott N. Sugammadex for the reversal of muscle relaxation in general anaesthesia: a systematic review and economic assessment. Health Technol Assess. 2010 Jul;14(39):1-211. doi: 10.3310/hta14390. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20688009</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 11, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 13, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 17, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Maine Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Craig Curry</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Anesthesiologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>neuromuscular blockade</keyword>
  <keyword>sugammadex</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Joint Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bromides</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vecuronium Bromide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

