<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03211533</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RF-2013-02358095</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03211533</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Identification of Infants at Risk of Cerebral Palsy</brief_title>
  <official_title>CareToy Observational Study: Early Identification of Infants at Risk of Cerebral Palsy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>IRCCS Fondazione Stella Maris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>IRCCS Fondazione Stella Maris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This observational study aims to early identify, through a rigorous and standardized
      follow-up, infants at high risk for Cerebral Palsy. After the consent agreement firmed by the
      parents, infants born at term or preterm with ultrasonographic evidence of brain injury
      considered at risk for neurodevelopmental disorders will be strictly monitored during the
      first months of life performing a periodic neurological assessment (Prechtl's General
      Movement (GMA) and the Hammersmith Infant Neurological Examination) at term age and around 3
      months of post term age. Moreover, to study more accurately the brain injury early identified
      by ultrasonographic brain exam, around 6 weeks of post-term age the enrolled infants will
      perform, as recommended in infants at risk, brain Magnetic Resonance (RM).

      Thanks to the high predictability power of the combination of the clinical observation with
      the neuroimaging infants at high risk of CP will be early detect. Selected infants,
      considered at high risk for CP will have the opportunity to perform an home based and family
      centered early intervention later than 3 post term age.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Scientific literature review shows evidence that early intervention, especially when
      performed in the first months of life, when the brain plasticity shows its great
      expressivity, has positive effects on neurodevelopmental outcomes. In this framework the
      early identification of infants at risk for neurodevelopmental disorders is a major
      prerequisite to start very early an intervention programme. To families of infants, born in
      Neonatal Units involved in this study, will be asked with written informed consent, to
      participate in this observational study that aims to early identify, through a rigorous and
      standardized follow-up, infants at high risk for CP. Infants born at term or preterm with
      ultrasonographic evidence of brain injury considered at risk for neurodevelopmental disorders
      will be strictly monitored during the first months of development by the clinical team (Child
      Neurologists and Neonatologists) performing a periodic neurological assessment through
      examination of the Prechtl's General Movement (GMA) and the Hammersmith Infant Neurological
      Examination, at term age and around 3 months of post term age. Moreover, to study more
      accurately the brain injury early identified by ultrasonographic brain exam, within 6 weeks
      post-term age enrolled infants will perform, as recommended in infants at risk, brain
      Magnetic Resonance (RM). During the conventional RM examination, when possible, a fMRI
      perceptive task will be also performed to evaluate possible predictor factors to the
      responsiveness to the early intervention.

      Thanks to the high predictability power of the combination of the clinical observation with
      the neuroimaging infants at high risk of CP will be early detect. Selected infants,
      considered at high risk for CP will have the opportunity to perform an home based and family
      centered early intervention later than 3 post term age.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 22, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 10, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 10, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fidgety Movements at 12 weeks (post-term age)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks post-term age</time_frame>
    <description>The Prechtl's General Movements Assessment is a non-invasive and cost-effective way to identify neurological issues which may lead to cerebral palsy and other developmental disabilities. The Fidgety movements are usually assessed between 9-20 weeks post-term age, showing the best expression at 12 weeks post term age. Infants whose Fidgety movements are absent or abnormal are at higher risk of neurological conditions, in particular for cerebral palsy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Writhing Movements at 40 weeks (term age)</measure>
    <time_frame>40 weeks (term age)</time_frame>
    <description>The 'writhing movements' (described in the Prechtl's General Movements Assessment) are present from term age until 8 weeks post-term age. The evaluation at 40 weeks is a key point for the assessment both in preterm and at term infants. Infants whose writhing movements are abnormal could be considered at risk for neurodevelopmental disabilities; they have been carefully monitored in the fidgety period (see primary outcome measure).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Magnetic resonance imaging rating scale</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 weeks (post-term age)</time_frame>
    <description>Infants recruited will perform, according to gold standard clinical guidelines, a MRI study of the brain lesion previously identified with brain ultrasound. MRI will allow to better study the type of lesion. It will be quantified according to a validated visual semi-quantitative rating scale that uses a reliable and valid anatomical template for a graphical representation of abnormal MRI findings with detailed scoring of relative brain structures. During the MRI a task of fMRI will be performed to identify predictors of response to treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebral Palsy</condition>
  <condition>Preterm Infant</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        For this observational study will be enrolled infants, born a term or preterm, with very
        early neurological signs (at term age) and evidences of brain lesion during ultrasound
        brain screening that are considered at risk for the development of CP.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  neurological signs (Hammersmith Infant Neurological Examination/General Movement
             Assessment according Precthl's).

          -  signs of brain injury identified at ultrasound brain exam

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  brain malformations

          -  severe sensory deficits
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>5 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Giovanni Cioni</last_name>
    <phone>050886233</phone>
    <email>gcioni@fsm.unipi.it</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Giuseppina Sgandurra</last_name>
    <email>gsgandurra@fsm.unipi.it</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>IRCCS Fondazione Stella Maris</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calambrone</city>
        <state>Pisa</state>
        <zip>56128</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Giuseppina Sgandurra, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>g.sgandurra@fsm.unipi.it</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 28, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 5, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 7, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 23, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 23, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>infants at risk of cerebral palsy</keyword>
  <keyword>MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>general movements</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paralysis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cerebral Palsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

