<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03217240</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NHeartCentreS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03217240</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Integrated Computational modelIng of Right Heart Mechanics and Blood Flow Dynamics in Congenital Heart Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Integrated Computational modelIing of Right Heart Mechanics and Blood Flow Dynamics in Congenital Heart Disease (&quot;INITIATE&quot;)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart Centre Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ministry of Health, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart Centre Singapore</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Advances in paediatric cardiology and cardiac surgery have enabled the survival of most
      patients born with congenital heart disease (CHD) into adulthood. Many CHD patients have
      undergone palliative or reparative surgery earlier in life. As patients survive into
      adulthood, they may need intervention or surgery for residual haemodynamic lesions. This is
      because they are at risk of arrhythmias secondary to structure heart disease and are
      susceptible to acquired heart disease. In these patients, pre-operative and post-operative
      evaluation of right ventricular (RV) structure (shape and volume) and function is an
      essential component of clinical management.

      Advances have been made in cardiac imaging so that accurate assessment of the right heart
      chamber in terms of its structure, function and physiology is possible. However, this
      technology has as yet never been applied in an effort to comprehensively assess RV structure,
      function and physiology. Cardiac Magnetic Resonance (CMR) will be used in this comprehensive
      assessment of structure and function. Thus, this research will allow development of a
      comprehensive integrated biomedical engineering (BME) R&amp;D platform for in-depth study and
      clinical diagnosis of the RV structure-function relationship and physiology and its
      association with biomarker, and exercise capacity in CHD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The incidence of Congenital Heart Disease (CHD) in live new-borns is estimated to vary from
      4.1/1000 to 12.3/1000. The improvement in survival of CHD patients has led to burgeoning
      numbers of grown-up CHD.The majority of these CHD patients face a lifetime of problems
      including RV dilation, ventricular arrhythmias, and sudden cardiac death.Considering
      inflation to visit costs and added image technology for diagnosis, the cost of each patient
      is expected to increase .In contrast to adult patients with acquired heart disease,
      abnormalities of the RV are ubiquitous in children and adults with CHD.

      Currently, clinical evaluation includes ECG and pulse oximetry alongside clinical
      examination. Investigation of RV anatomy and physiology is evolving from a reliance on
      invasive studies (right heart catheterization or RHC) to non-invasive imaging techniques such
      as echocardiography, nuclear scintigraphy, computed tomography, and CMR .2D echocardiography
      is largely operator dependent and suffers from poor inter-study reproducibility.The complex
      geometry of the RV makes it difficult to accurately quantify remodelling before and after
      intervention. Nuclear scintigraphy and computed tomography (CT) are constrained by the need
      for ionizing radiation as well as the poor temporal resolution of the technique.Importantly,
      existing CMR analytics fail to exploit the full potential of the rich CMR image dataset, and
      do not yield information on regional RV remodelling, muscle stiffness and blood flow
      characterization.

      Due to the challenges mentioned above, other than RV volumes and ejection fraction, other
      changes in RV shape and haemodynamics have yet to be considered in the official guidelines
      used to define eligibility for surgery and to quantify risk of operation. It is plausible
      that incorporation of additional variables that more comprehensively characterizes fine
      alterations in RV structure, function and haemodynamics in large risk-stratification models,
      such as the EuroSCORE and the Society of Thoracic Surgeons' Risk Calculator, may enhance risk
      stratification and prognostication.

      Incorporating novel exploratory RV functional indices (e.g. curvedness, area strain) and
      computational methods (e.g. CFD, FSI simulations), and then correlating these with clinical
      and cardiopulmonary exercise test outcomes will allow investigators to have established an
      unprecedentedly sizeable and rich clinical imaging database that serves both as a touchstone
      for clinical reference, as well as a repository for future exploratory research.

      Investigators tend to develop a comprehensive (BME) Research and Development platform for
      in-depth study of RV mechanics, blood flow and function in Congenital Heart Disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 5, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Develop a comprehensive (BME) RnD platform for in-depth study of RV mechanics, blood flow and function in Congenital Heart Disease</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
    <description>This research will give an in-depth understanding of RV structure-function relationship, mechanics and haemodynamics. This is the foundation for rationale and physiologically-sound clinical decision-making in CHD monitoring and management. In addition, computational modelling of RV blood flow would be the best tool to optimize an individual solution to RV surgery and may ultimately improve surgical planning. This proposal is a pioneering study that can influence the research field and current management in preoperative, intraoperative, and post-operative interventions in CHD patients.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Congenital Heart Disease</condition>
  <condition>Pulmonary Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Congenital Heart Disease</arm_group_label>
    <description>Tetralogy of Fallot Repair/Pulmonary Hypertension Cardiac Magnetic Resonance - MRI Cardiopulmonary Exercise Test Blood Sampling for all participants</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Volunteer</arm_group_label>
    <description>Cardiac Magnetic Resonance - MRI Cardiopulmonary Exercise Test Blood Sampling for all participants</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cardiac Magnetic Resonance - MRI</intervention_name>
    <description>All participants will have to undergo CMR which uses interaction of the magnetic properties of body tissues with strong magnetic fields to create images. Participants will be asked to lie on a narrow bed placed inside of a large magnet for about 1 hour. Several sets of images are needed. Participants are required to stay very still and follow the instruction of the MRI technologist who operates the machine from a room next door.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Congenital Heart Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Volunteer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cardiopulmonary Exercise Test</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will be asked to undergo a cardiopulmonary exercise test (CPET). Participants will need to wear a mask. Several electrodes will be placed on the chest to record heart activity during exercise. Participants will need to pedal for at least 8-12 minutes. Pedalling will be instructed to report any symptoms such as chest discomfort, shortness of breath, leg fatigue or dizziness. A small probe will be placed on participant's finger during the test to measure the oxygen content in the blood. Immediately after exercising, participants will rest for 5-10 minutes while the blood pressure and electrocardiogram are monitored. The results will be read by a cardiologist.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Congenital Heart Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Volunteer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood Sampling for all participants</intervention_name>
    <description>Serum samples will be obtained before CMR. The sample will be stored at -80 degree until assay. Investigators will perform various tests related to participants heart function</description>
    <arm_group_label>Congenital Heart Disease</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Volunteer</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Serum samples will be obtained before CMR. The sample will be stored at -80 degree until
      assay. Investigators will perform various tests related to participants heart function
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study will recruit 200 patients and 200 Healthy volunteers from across 3 sites at the
        following institutions:

          -  National Heart Centre

          -  National University Hospital

          -  KK Women's and Children's Hospital

             200 Congenital Heart Disease Patients 200 Healthy Volunteer
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        For patients with repaired tetralogy of Fallot

          1. Survivors of TOF repair more than one year after repair

          2. Aged: 12-80

        For patients with pulmonary hypertension

          1. Signed informed consent prior to initiation of any study mandated procedure

          2. Age between 12 - 80 years

          3. Patient with clinically suspected or known primary PH belonging to one of the
             following subgroups of the Updated Dana Point Clinical Classification Group 1 (at
             least 1 of the following a)Idiopathic (IPAH), or b)Heritable (HPAH), or c)Drug or
             toxin induced, or d)Associated (APAH) with one of the following: i.Connective tissue
             disease ii.Congenital heart disease

        For Healthy volunteers

          1. Aged :12-80

          2. Asymptomatic and ambulant

          3. Resting blood pressure &lt;140/90 mmHg

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Non-cardiac illness with a life expectancy of less than 2 years

          2. Previous heart, kidney, liver or lung transplantation

          3. Contraindication to MRI examination

               1. Cardiac pacemaker

               2. Brain aneurysm or clips

               3. Electronic implants or prosthesis

               4. Eye metal foreign body injury

               5. Severe claustrophobia

               6. Severe renal impairment, glomerular filtration rate &lt;30ml/min/1.73m2

          4. Pregnancy

        Additional exclusion criteria for healthy volunteers:

          1. History of any major medical problems, any cardiovascular disease (such as
             hypertension or diabetes) or significant renal or lung disease (eg.COPD, Asthma,
             Pneumonia,Pulmonary embolism,Pulmonary edema,Respiratory tract
             infection,Bronchiolitis)

          2. Concurrently taking any medications for cardiovascular disease (including
             hypertension)

          3. Heavy smoking (over 5 sticks per day or who has quit smoking in less than 12 months
             and had smoked over 5 sticks per day)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dr Zhong Liang</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Researcher</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Zhong Liang</last_name>
    <phone>67042237</phone>
    <phone_ext>2237</phone_ext>
    <email>zhong.liang@nhcs.com.sg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Nurkhairunisah Abdul Rahim</last_name>
    <phone>67042263</phone>
    <phone_ext>2263</phone_ext>
    <email>nurkhairunisah.abdul.rahim@nhcs.com.sg</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>119074</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dr Chai Ping</last_name>
      <phone>67722165</phone>
      <phone_ext>2165</phone_ext>
      <email>ping_chai@nuhs.edu.sg</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dr Chai Ping</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Heart Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>169609</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nurkhairunisah Binte Abdul Rahim</last_name>
      <phone>67042263</phone>
      <phone_ext>2263</phone_ext>
      <email>nurkhairunisah.abdul.rahim@nhcs.com.sg</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Yin Siang Liaw</last_name>
      <phone>67042274</phone>
      <phone_ext>2274</phone_ext>
      <email>liaw.yin.siang@nhcs.com.sg</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dr Zhong Liang</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>KK Women's and Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>229899</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dr Tan Teng Hong</last_name>
      <phone>63941049</phone>
      <phone_ext>1049</phone_ext>
      <email>tan.teng.hong@singhealth.com.sg</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dr Tan Teng Hong</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26330417</url>
    <description>Clinical outcomes of fractional flow reserve.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22922562</url>
    <description>Diagnostic accuracy of fractional flow reserve from anatomic CT angiography</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22032711</url>
    <description>Diagnosis of ischemia-causing coronary stenoses by noninvasive fractional flow reserve computed from coronary computed tomographic angiograms.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22922698</url>
    <description>Guidelines on the management of valvular heart disease (version 2012): the Joint Task Force on the Management of Valvular Heart Disease of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and the European Association for Cardio-Thoracic Surgery (EACTS).</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=The+effects+of+pregnancy+on+right+ventricular+remodeling+in+women+with+repaired+tetralogy+of+fallot</url>
    <description>The effects of pregnancy on right ventricular remodeling in women with repaired tetralogy of Fallot</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Factors+associated+with+impaired+clinical+status+in+long-term+survivors+of+tetralogy+of+fallot+repair+evaluated+by+magnetic+resonance+imaging</url>
    <description>Factors associated with impaired clinical status in long-term survivors of tetralogy of Fallot repair evaluated by magnetic resonance imaging</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Adult+congenital+heart+disease+importance+of+the+right+ventricle.+J+Am+Coll+Cardiol+2009%3B</url>
    <description>Adult congenital heart disease importance of the right ventricle</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Recommendations+for+cardiovascular+magnetic+resonance+in+adults+with+congenital+heart+disease+from+the+respective+working+groups+of+the+European+Society+of+Cardiology</url>
    <description>Recommendations for cardiovascular magnetic resonance in adults with congenital heart disease from the respective working groups of the European Society of Cardiology</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18046031</url>
    <description>Computed tomography--an increasing source of radiation exposure</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Douglas PS, Pontone G, Hlatky MA, Patel MR, Norgaard BL, Byrne RA, Curzen N, Purcell I, Gutberlet M, Rioufol G, Hink U, Schuchlenz HW, Feuchtner G, Gilard M, Andreini D, Jensen JM, Hadamitzky M, Chiswell K, Cyr D, Wilk A, Wang F, Rogers C, De Bruyne B; PLATFORM Investigators. Clinical outcomes of fractional flow reserve by computed tomographic angiography-guided diagnostic strategies vs. usual care in patients with suspected coronary artery disease: the prospective longitudinal trial of FFR(CT): outcome and resource impacts study. Eur Heart J. 2015 Dec 14;36(47):3359-67. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehv444. Epub 2015 Sep 1.</citation>
    <PMID>26330417</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Min JK, Leipsic J, Pencina MJ, Berman DS, Koo BK, van Mieghem C, Erglis A, Lin FY, Dunning AM, Apruzzese P, Budoff MJ, Cole JH, Jaffer FA, Leon MB, Malpeso J, Mancini GB, Park SJ, Schwartz RS, Shaw LJ, Mauri L. Diagnostic accuracy of fractional flow reserve from anatomic CT angiography. JAMA. 2012 Sep 26;308(12):1237-45.</citation>
    <PMID>22922562</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koo BK, Erglis A, Doh JH, Daniels DV, Jegere S, Kim HS, Dunning A, DeFrance T, Lansky A, Leipsic J, Min JK. Diagnosis of ischemia-causing coronary stenoses by noninvasive fractional flow reserve computed from coronary computed tomographic angiograms. Results from the prospective multicenter DISCOVER-FLOW (Diagnosis of Ischemia-Causing Stenoses Obtained Via Noninvasive Fractional Flow Reserve) study. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2011 Nov 1;58(19):1989-97. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2011.06.066.</citation>
    <PMID>22032711</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vahanian A, Alfieri O, Andreotti F, Antunes MJ, Barón-Esquivias G, Baumgartner H, Borger MA, Carrel TP, De Bonis M, Evangelista A, Falk V, Lung B, Lancellotti P, Pierard L, Price S, Schäfers HJ, Schuler G, Stepinska J, Swedberg K, Takkenberg J, Von Oppell UO, Windecker S, Zamorano JL, Zembala M; ESC Committee for Practice Guidelines (CPG); Joint Task Force on the Management of Valvular Heart Disease of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC); European Association for Cardio-Thoracic Surgery (EACTS). Guidelines on the management of valvular heart disease (version 2012): the Joint Task Force on the Management of Valvular Heart Disease of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC) and the European Association for Cardio-Thoracic Surgery (EACTS). Eur J Cardiothorac Surg. 2012 Oct;42(4):S1-44. doi: 10.1093/ejcts/ezs455. Epub 2012 Aug 25.</citation>
    <PMID>22922698</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Egidy Assenza G, Cassater D, Landzberg M, Geva T, Schreier J, Graham D, Volpe M, Barker N, Economy K, Valente AM. The effects of pregnancy on right ventricular remodeling in women with repaired tetralogy of Fallot. Int J Cardiol. 2013 Oct 3;168(3):1847-52. doi: 10.1016/j.ijcard.2012.12.071. Epub 2013 Jan 28.</citation>
    <PMID>23369674</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Geva T, Sandweiss BM, Gauvreau K, Lock JE, Powell AJ. Factors associated with impaired clinical status in long-term survivors of tetralogy of Fallot repair evaluated by magnetic resonance imaging. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2004 Mar 17;43(6):1068-74.</citation>
    <PMID>15028368</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Warnes CA. Adult congenital heart disease importance of the right ventricle. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2009 Nov 17;54(21):1903-10. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2009.06.048. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19909869</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kilner PJ, Geva T, Kaemmerer H, Trindade PT, Schwitter J, Webb GD. Recommendations for cardiovascular magnetic resonance in adults with congenital heart disease from the respective working groups of the European Society of Cardiology. Eur Heart J. 2010 Apr;31(7):794-805. doi: 10.1093/eurheartj/ehp586. Epub 2010 Jan 11.</citation>
    <PMID>20067914</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brenner DJ, Hall EJ. Computed tomography--an increasing source of radiation exposure. N Engl J Med. 2007 Nov 29;357(22):2277-84. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18046031</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 11, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 11, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hypertension, Pulmonary</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Defects, Congenital</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

