<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01991405</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MCI Working Memory Training.</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01991405</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Memory Aid - Working Memory Training in Patients With Mild Cognitive Impairment.</brief_title>
  <acronym>MCI</acronym>
  <official_title>Memory Aid - Computer Based Working Memory Training in Elderly With Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI). A Randomized, Controlled Trial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sorlandet Hospital HF</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sorlandet Hospital HF</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Mild Cognitive Impairment (MCI) is a condition characterized by memory problems more severe
      than normal cognitive changes due to old age, and less severe than dementia. Reduced working
      memory (WM) is regarded as one of the core symptoms of an MCI-condition. Recent studies have
      indicated that WM can be improved trough computer based training.

      Objectives:

      The objective of the study is to evaluate if working memory training is effective in
      improving working memory in elderly MCI-patients. Further, to evaluate if cognitive training
      relates to structural changes in the white and gray matter of the brain, assessed by
      structural Magnetic Resonance Imaging. Cognitive phenotypes related to memory impairment and
      progression to dementia will also be investigated.

      Patients and Methods:

      The proposed study is a blinded, randomized and controlled trail that will include 90 elderly
      patients from a Memory Clinic diagnosed with MCI. The groups will be randomized to either
      training or a placebo version. The intervention is computerized working memory training
      performed for 45 minutes over 25 sessions. Neuropsychological assessment and structural MRI
      will be performed before, 6 and 12 months after training.

      Relevance:

      Currently there is no known treatment available for mild memory impairment/MCI, and few
      studies on specific cognitive training in MCI-patients have been performed. The proposed
      study has received funding from a Norwegian Health Region. If computer based training results
      in positive changes to memory functions in MCI patients this may represent a new,
      cost-effective treatment. Secondly, evaluation of training induced structural changes to grey
      or white matter may improve our understanding of the mechanisms behind effective cognitive
      interventions in MCI patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Working Memory function.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from baseline (3, 6 and 12 months after intervention).</time_frame>
    <description>The study seeks to assess changes in the patients working memory function after an intervention of working memory training.The construct of &quot;Working Memory&quot; is measured on several levels: by neuropsychological tests (cognitive level), assessment of daily living skills (ADL-level), and measures of changes in the brains white and gray matter in areas that are correlated with working memory function (brain level).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Episodic memory function.</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes from baseline (3, 6 and 12 months after intervention).</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure the patients results on a word list task, both immediate and delayed recall, as well as recognition. Low scores on word list learning is associated with progression to dementia. It is anticipated that patients with MCI are at risk for developing dementia. The study seeks to investigate if there is a correlation between the results on memory tests and progression to dementia in this patient group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Mild Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Computerized Working Memory Training.</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Working Memory Training, includes both auditive and visual tasks, administrated on a computer, under guidance. 5 x 45 minutes per week, for 5 weeks. The placebo group will train at an fixed level (non-adaptive), but with otherwise identical computer programs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Computerized Working Memory Training.</intervention_name>
    <description>Auditive and visual Working Memory tasks, administrated on a computer under guidance. 5 x 45 minutes per week, for 5 weeks. The intervention group will train at an &quot;adaptive&quot; level that is not to difficult nor to easy, which is hypothesized as optimal for learning and training effect. The placebo group will train with a &quot;sham&quot; program that is fixed (&quot;non-adaptive&quot; in difficulty level), but otherwise identical.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Computerized Working Memory Training.</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cogmed (r) from Pearson Assessment Inc.</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who meet the Peterson diagnostic criteria of MCI:

               1. memory complaints (preferably confirmed by an informant).

               2. memory impairment according to age and education.

               3. preserved general cognitive function.

               4. intact activities of daily living, absence of dementia.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  head trauma with post-traumatic loss of conscience for 30 minutes during lifespan.

          -  loss of senses (blindness, deafness).

          -  photo-sensitive epilepsy.

          -  unsuitability for Magnetic Resonance Imaging-examination due to metal foreign bodies
             or severe claustrophobia.

          -  drug and/or alcohol abuse.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>55 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Svein Gunnar Gundersen, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Head of research department</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gro C Løhaugen, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0047-95844805</phone>
    <email>gro.c.lohaugen@ntnu.no</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sorlandet Hospital HF</name>
      <address>
        <city>Arendal</city>
        <state>Aust-Agder</state>
        <zip>4838</zip>
        <country>Norway</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susanne S Hernes, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0047-48136020</phone>
      <email>susanne.sorensen.hernes@sshf.no</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Norway</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 18, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 18, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 25, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 23, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mild Cognitive Impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>Working Memory Training</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuropsychological function in MCI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

