<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01995097</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00044933</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01CA166149</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01995097</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BABY STEPS II: SMS Scheduled Gradual Reduction Text Messages to Help Pregnant Smokers Quit</brief_title>
  <official_title>SMS Scheduled Gradual Reduction Text Messages to Help Pregnant Smokers Quit</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Primary Aim: To test the efficacy of a SMS text-based scheduled gradual reduction (SGR) and
      counseling intervention to promote smoking cessation in the late third trimester.

      Hypothesis: The rate of smoking cessation in the late third trimester among women in the SGR
      Support Messages arm will be higher than among women in the Support Messages arm.

      Secondary Aim 1: To assess the effect of the SGR intervention on biochemically validated
      prolonged abstinence and smoking reduction during pregnancy.

      Secondary Aim 2: To assess the effect of the SGR intervention on smoking abstinence at three
      months postpartum.

      Secondary Aim 3: To assess the effect of the SGR intervention on the rate of preterm birth.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background and Significance:

      Smoking during pregnancy is associated with a plethora of negative effects on the fetus,
      including preterm birth, low birth weight, fetal growth restriction, placental abruption,
      fetal/neonatal death, sudden infant death syndrome, learning disabilities and attention
      deficit disorder. Quitting smoking improves the health of the fetus, and if the cessation is
      maintained, the health of the mother and other family members living in the household. Yet
      despite the commonly known evidence of the harms, as much as half of women who smoke continue
      to do so when becoming pregnant.

      Cognitive-behavioral cessation interventions for pregnant smokers have had modest success
      with quit rates that range from 10 to 30%. Interventions have included face-to-face
      counseling or telephone counseling, neither of which is easily disseminable in the health
      care setting. Using SMS (Short Message Service) text messaging to deliver counseling has the
      potential for efficacy and widespread dissemination. The only trial that used text messaging
      to target cessation during pregnancy found null results. Thus, a counseling intervention via
      SMS texting might not be potent enough to promote cessation; pregnant smokers might need more
      assistance. Scheduled gradual reduction (SGR) might be an effective strategy to supplement
      counseling. SGR first assesses smokers' patterns, then over the course of three or four
      weeks, gradually reduces the number of cigarettes smoked by lengthening the time interval
      between cigarettes. Thus, smokers might be prompted to smoke at a time when they do not want
      to smoke and might not be prompted to smoke at a time when they want to smoke. The smoking
      becomes unlinked from the cues (psychological and behavioral), and smokers must work through
      their times of craving (physiological). Therefore, when cigarettes get fewer and fewer in the
      last two weeks, smokers should have an easier time giving them up completely.

      Knowing whether an SMS text-messaging intervention plus a SMS text-based counseling
      intervention helps pregnant smokers quit could significantly improve the maternal and fetal
      health of any pregnant woman with a cell phone with texting ability. Most previous
      efficacious interventions that have helped pregnant smokers quit are not easily disseminated.
      A texting intervention could impact many pregnant women's health given the reach and
      disseminability.

      Design:

      The two-arm randomized controlled trial compares Arm 1, SGR via SMS text messaging plus SMS
      Support Messages to Arm 2, SMS Support Messages alone. The study team will conduct three
      face-to-face surveys, one at baseline (between 10 and 28 weeks of pregnancy), one in the late
      third trimester, and another at 3 months postpartum. The study team will biochemically
      validate smoking abstinence and reduction via saliva. Women randomized to Arm 1 will start to
      receive SGR messages one week after they enroll. They will receive these messages for 3-5
      weeks depending on the amount of cigarettes they smoke at time of enrollment. Women
      randomized to both arms will receive Support messages from the time of enrollment through 35
      weeks gestation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 20, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 13, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>biochemically validated seven-day point prevalence smoking abstinence</measure>
    <time_frame>late third trimester (35 weeks)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>prolonged smoking abstinence</measure>
    <time_frame>late third trimester (35 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>biochemically validated smoking reduction</measure>
    <time_frame>late third trimester (35 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>biochemically validated postpartum smoking abstinence</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postpartum</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>preterm birth</measure>
    <time_frame>delivery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">331</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking</condition>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SGR + Support Messages</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>scheduled gradual reduction text messages for first 3-5 weeks of participation; support text messages through 35th week of pregnancy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Support Messages Only</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>support text messages through 35th week of pregnancy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Scheduled Gradual Reduction Text Messages</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SGR + Support Messages</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Support Text Messages</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SGR + Support Messages</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Support Messages Only</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Women who:

          -  are between 10 and 28 weeks pregnant,

          -  have smoked at least 100 cigarettes in their lifetime,

          -  smoke 3 or more cigarettes per day in the prior 7 days,

          -  are current smokers,

          -  are willing to try to quit smoking,

          -  are enrolled in prenatal care at the clinics from which the study team is recruiting
             and plan to receive care there throughout their pregnancy,

          -  are age 18 or older,

          -  speak English

        Exclusion Criteria:

        - evidence of unstable cognitive or mental health problems who cannot properly provide
        consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathryn Pollak, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 20, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 25, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 26, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>smoking cessation</keyword>
  <keyword>smoking reduction</keyword>
  <keyword>scheduled gradual reduction</keyword>
  <keyword>pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>text message intervention</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

