<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01996137</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NHGDSRB_D_2013/01042</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01996137</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>VASSTII: An Exploratory Clinical Study on a VASST IITreadmill System for Post Stroke Gait Rehabilitation.</brief_title>
  <acronym>VASSTII</acronym>
  <official_title>An Exploratory Clinical Study on a Variable Speed and Sensing Treadmill (VASST II) System for Hemiparetic Gait Rehabilitation After Stroke</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tan Tock Seng Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ngee Ann Polytechnic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tan Tock Seng Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      An exploratory clinical study on a Variable Speed and Sensing Treadmill system(VASST) for
      hemiparetic gait rehabilitation after stroke.

      Building upon the positive results of VASST I conducted in 2012, VASST II will be an open
      label pilot trial of 11 subjects screened for eligibility by TTSH medical and rehabilitation
      team Study hypotheses : Training on VASST may result in a gain of +40% - 50% for distance
      walked and +10-20% of gait speed compared to baseline and response rate of 85% and serious
      adverse event rate of &lt;10%.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A recent collaboration with Ngee Ann Polytechnic's team from the Biomedical Engineering
      Centre, Electronic &amp; Computer Engineering Division, School Of Engineering Singapore yielded
      the VASST I; an innovative product, the result of co development between NP and TTSH
      rehabilitation centre's CART (Centre for Advanced Rehabilitation Therapeutics) was supported
      by a competitive grant. (EMBC paper ref, SIRF)

      VASST I incorporates the following features which enhance manual treadmill training:

        1. Sensing mechanisms to track user's self-activated actions during exercise.

        2. Automated speed‐control to adapt to a user's gait speed and pattern.

        3. Safety sensing to slow down the treadmill when the user is unable to sustain the
           treadmill speed in order to avert a potential fall.

        4. Overhead safety harness without body weight support for reduction of fall risk.

        5. Software tools to collect vital clinical data regarding ambulatory gait speed, distance
           and time walked during treatment.

      A recently completed proof of concept trial in June 2013 yielded encouraging results in 10
      chronic poststroke hemiplegic subjects. All subjects completed the trial without any adverse
      events. The clinical team was able to smoothly test-bed VASST in 10 subjects with good
      subjective feedback. Following 12 hour - long supervised training sessions over 4 weeks,
      there were significant gains from baseline for measures of gait quantity (+30.1%) and gait
      speed (+8.7%). These gains were maintained for up to 4 weeks after training ceased. The
      response rate was 80% and positive feedback was obtained in 80% of subjects. Objective
      measurements were obtained using independent kinematic gait analysis using the Gaitrite
      system.

      With these encouraging results, the combined TTSH and Ngee Ann medical and bioengineering
      teams have brought the co-development to a deeper level, leading to VASST II which is
      conceptualized as a pre-commercialisation prototype.

      Additional technological improvements include:

        1. Automated unweighting subsystem of up to 20% body weight support to benefit more
           severely impaired subjects in terms of reduction of physical fatigue during ambulation
           and to reduce destabilization or fall risk during higher gait training speeds.

        2. Hand grip sensors to intelligently guide progression of training speeds

        3. Instrumentation subsystem including sensors to record spatial and temporal gait
           measurements during gait training such as step and stride length, gait speed / distance
           walked. An anticipated sensor accuracy of +/- 1.27 cm similar to the Gaitrite system in
           measuring step length may potentially allow ambulatory gait monitoring, obviating the
           need for additional independent post-training analysis using a gait measurement
           instrument such as Gaitrite.

        4. Real-time feedback subsystem with graphical LCD display which is interactive and varied
           in order reduce boredom and motivate users.

        5. Wireless data transfer subsystem for data storage and analysis to a laptop computer for
           the treating therapist.

      Research objectives

        1. To provide clinical inputs into VASST II via systematic hazard analyses, in order to
           arrive at a prototype which may attract commercial interest for licensing and
           manufacture and eventual deployment to ambulatory rehabilitation clinics in hospitals
           and day rehabilitation centres.

        2. To conduct of a pilot clinical trial using VASST II for 11 subacute to chronic (&gt;3
           months) hemiplegic stroke patients in an ambulatory setting.

        3. To obtain pre and post outcomes using standardized clinical scales and objective
           measurements of gait parameters during exercise. (gait speed, quantity, cadence, step
           length)

        4. To obtain subjective feedback with regards to their experience after using VASST II from
           research subjects and therapists.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>1 hour of VASST II training</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>6 minute walk test</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>distance (metres) walked in 6 minutes</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gait speed</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>metres/second over 10 metre walk test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Functional ambulation categoryFAC</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The level of independence or aid needed for walking</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">11</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Hemiplegic Gait</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VASST II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Stroke patients selected to undergo VASST II treadmill training for 60 minutes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VASST</intervention_name>
    <description>Stroke patients with hemiparesis undergo gait training via VASST</description>
    <arm_group_label>VASST II</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. First ever stroke (ischaemic or haemorrhagic) confirmed on CT or MR imaging

          2. Aged 21 - 80 years

          3. Stroke duration of &gt; 3 months - 24 months (subacute -chronic stroke)

          4. Able to walk overground at a self-selected speed of &gt;0.2m/s with or without walking
             aids or lower limb orthoses for at least 150 meters with at most minimal aid or
             supervision.

          5. Functional ambulation category (FAC &gt;/= 2) (subject needs at most minimal assistance
             to walk)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Cardiovascular conditions such as uncontrolled hypertension/hypotension, angina
             pectoris, recent myocardial infarction, congestive cardiac failure, known
             echocardiographic ejection fraction &lt; 40%, chronic arrhythmias (e.g. atrial
             fibrillation), pacemaker, uncontrolled Diabetes Mellitus.; within 3 months of study
             screening

          2. Terminal illness such as advanced malignancy, end stage renal failure,
             neurodegenerative diseases with life expectancy of &lt; 6 months.

          3. Aphasia (inability to obey 2 step commands), cognitive impairment, untreated
             depression or psychiatric disorder.

          4. Severe hearing or visual impairment despite aids.

          5. Active lower limb arthritis, lower limb or joint pain (Visual Analogue Scale) &gt;5/10,
             fixed orthopaedic deformities and peripheral vascular disease of the lower limb which
             could be worsened by treadmill training.

          6. Moderate to severe lower limb spasticity or spasms (Modified Ashworth Scale &gt;2)

          7. Active trunk skin conditions, known abdominal aortic aneurysm, anticoagulation with
             warfarin precluding safe fit of unweighting gait harness.

          8. Body weight &gt; 130kg.

          9. Pregnancy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen SG Chua, MBBS,FRCP</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tan Tock Seng Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karen SG Chua, MBBS,FRCP</last_name>
    <phone>65 64506 164</phone>
    <email>Karen_Chua@ttsh.com.sg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>CJ Wong, MBBS,MRCP</last_name>
    <phone>6564506181</phone>
    <email>wong_chin_jung@ttsh.com.sg</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tan Tock Seng Hospital CART 5B</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>308433</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen S Chua, MBBS, FRCP</last_name>
      <phone>68894580</phone>
      <email>Karen_Chua@ttsh.com.sg</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>CJ Wong, MBBS,MRCP</last_name>
      <phone>64506181</phone>
      <email>Wong_chin_jung@ttsh.com.sg</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karen SG Chua, MBBS,FRCP</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chin Jung Wong, MBBS,MRCP</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 21, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 26, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 27, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tan Tock Seng Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Chua Sui Geok, Karen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Doctor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Treadmill</keyword>
  <keyword>Gait Speed</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gait Disorders, Neurologic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

