<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00078299</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>040128</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>04-EI-0128</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00078299</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Age-Related Eye Disease Study (AREDS) Clinical Lens Grading System</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Age-Related Eye Disease Study (AREDS) Clinical Lens Grading System</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Eye Institute (NEI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate a system developed to grade the severity of age-related cataract, a
      common cause of vision loss in older adults. Cataract research requires methods to simply and
      accurately determine the type and severity of cataracts in order to develop new, possibly
      non-surgical, treatments.

      Patients 50 years of age and older with one of the three major age-related cataract types
      (nuclear, cortical, and posterior subcapsular) may be eligible for this study. Participants
      will be recruited from among patients enrolled in other National Eye Institute protocols.

      Participants will have their eyes examined independently by two ophthalmologists with a
      biomicroscope, a magnifying device routinely used during eye examinations. The doctors will
      use the new grading system to record if a cataract is present, and if so, how severe it is.
      The examination includes measurement of visual acuity (vision chart test) and examination of
      the lens, retina, pupils and eye movements. Photographs of the eye will be taken using a
      special camera that flashes a bright light in the eye.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Standardized lens photography with centralized grading of photographs has been used in
      clinical trials and epidemiologic studies of cataract. While photographic grading systems
      have been shown to be reliable, they are too expensive and complex to use in many studies.
      For some large studies, especially those with many centers or those in which lens changes are
      of secondary concern, it would be useful to have a simple clinical lens grading system that
      is reliable and that can be used with minimal training of examiners. Several clinical lens
      grading systems have been developed and found to be reliable in the hands of dedicated lens
      researchers, but the systems have been difficult for other ophthalmologists to use reliably.

      The Age-Related Eye Disease Study (AREDA) has developed a simplified clinical cataract
      grading system to assess the severity of nuclear, cortical and posterior subcapsular
      cataracts, the 3 main types of age-related cataract. The system is designed to require
      minimal examiner training for persons already proficient in the use of the slit lamp. A total
      150 participants with cataracts of varying severity, who are already participating in other
      NEI protocols, will be recruited to evaluate the reliability of the system. After being
      dilated, each participant will have a lens grading performed independently by 2 examiners. To
      provide information on the validity of the clinical gradings, lens photographs will be taken
      and graded using the detailed AREDS system for grading photographs. The data will allow us to
      evaluate (1) the agreement between the AREDS clinical lens grading system and the AREDS
      photographic system of grading lens opacities, and (2) the agreement on assessment of
      cataract severity among opthalmologists (with varying subspecialty) using the AREDS clinical
      lens grading method.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date>April 2005</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>150</enrollment>
  <condition>Cataract</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Patient must understand and sign the informed consent.

          2. Patient must be at least 18 years of age.

          3. Pupillary dilation to at least 6 mm must be possible.

          4. Patients must have at least one natural lens present.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients below the age of 18 will be excluded from participation in this study of
        age-related cataract.

        1. Any condition such as corneal opacification that precludes adequate slit lamp
        examination and photography of the lens.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Eye Institute (NEI)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Steinberg EP, Javitt JC, Sharkey PD, Zuckerman A, Legro MW, Anderson GF, Bass EB, O'Day D. The content and cost of cataract surgery. Arch Ophthalmol. 1993 Aug;111(8):1041-9.</citation>
    <PMID>8352686</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Age-Related Eye Disease Study Research Group. The age-related eye disease study (AREDS) system for classifying cataracts from photographs: AREDS report no. 4. Am J Ophthalmol. 2001 Feb;131(2):167-75.</citation>
    <PMID>11228291</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chylack LT Jr, Leske MC, McCarthy D, Khu P, Kashiwagi T, Sperduto R. Lens opacities classification system II (LOCS II). Arch Ophthalmol. 1989 Jul;107(7):991-7.</citation>
    <PMID>2751471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2005</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 20, 2004</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 20, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 23, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Cortical</keyword>
  <keyword>Nuclear Sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Posterior Subcapsular</keyword>
  <keyword>Photographic Methods</keyword>
  <keyword>Reproducibility (intra and interobserver)</keyword>
  <keyword>Cataract</keyword>
  <keyword>Agreement</keyword>
  <keyword>Grading System</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cataract</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Eye Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

