<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00076609</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PHY906-2002-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00076609</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Botanical PHY906 Plus Capecitabine for Advanced Unresectable Hepatocellular Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II Study of Botanical PHY906 Plus Capecitabine for Advanced Unresectable Hepatocellular Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>PhytoCeutica</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>PhytoCeutica</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Capecitabine is a chemotherapeutic that has been approved for use in breast and colorectal
      cancers. The advantages of capecitabine are that (1) it is an oral drug; and (2) it is less
      toxic than many other chemotherapeutics. In an off-label hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC)
      clinical study, the response rate with capecitabine was 13%. The botanical drug
      PHY906--currently manufactured pursuant to GMP standards and regulations--has been used in
      China for over 1800 years to treat gastrointestinal-related ailments. Recently, preclinical
      studies demonstrated that PHY906 potentiates the anti-tumor effect of capecitabine. This
      trial will evaluate the safety and efficacy of PHY906 in enhancing the anti-tumor effects of
      capecitabine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2003</start_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor imaging and evaluation every 6 weeks</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Alphafetoprotein measurements every 3 weeks for first 3 courses, then every 6 weeks thereafter</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QoL assessment every 3 weeks</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survival follow-up every 2 months</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>31</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Liver Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PHY906</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>capecitabine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men or women 18 to 80 years of age with a histologic or cytologic diagnosis of HCC or
             who meet all of the following criteria: (a) a-fetoprotein levels &gt; 600 ng/mL; and (b)
             presence of cirrhosis or chronic hepatitis B or C; and (c) characteristic enhancement
             pattern of liver tumors on triphasic CT scan or MRI.

          -  All patients previously exposed to any prior anticancer treatments must have clear
             evidence of progressive disease after the most recent treatment regimen (see Exclusion
             Criteria).

          -  In the phase I (dose finding) and phase II (efficacy) portions of the study, patients
             may either have had no prior chemotherapy (chemotherapy naive), no prior capecitabine
             chemotherapy, or have been refractory to--or relapsed from--no more than two prior
             systemically administered treatment regimens. (Chemoembolization is not regarded in
             this context as a systemically administered treatment regimen.)

          -  All patients in both the phase I and phase II portions of this study must have at
             least one previously unirradiated, bidimensionally measurable lesion by computerized
             tomography (CT) or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan of &gt; 20 mm (if conventional
             CT scan) or more than or equal to 10 mm (if spiral CT scan). Triphasic spiral CT or
             MRI scans are preferred when such equipment is available. All CT scans should employ a
             “hepatoma protocol” image capture technique.

          -  Patients with central nervous system (CNS) involvement will have had appropriate
             treatment and will be free of progressive neurological deficits in the 28 days prior
             to enrollment.

          -  Patients with cirrhosis must have a Child-Pugh cirrhosis severity classification no
             greater than B.

          -  Baseline performance status must be Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) 0, 1, or
             2.

          -  Life expectancy must be reasonably estimated to be &gt; 12 weeks.

          -  Women patients who are known to be capable of conception should have a negative serum
             pregnancy test (beta-human chorionic gonadotropin [b-hCG]) within 2 weeks of starting
             the study; all patients should agree to use adequate non-estrogenic birth control
             methods, consistent with the institute’s standard form of contraception if conception
             is possible during the study.

          -  Provide written informed consent prior to screening.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with an estimated (Cockroft and Gault equation) to the power of 40 or
             calculated baseline creatinine clearance of 30-50 mL/min should have the starting dose
             of capecitabine reduced to 750 mg/m2 BID X 14 days; the dose of PHY906 remains
             unchanged. Patients with a baseline creatinine clearance of less than 30 mL/min should
             not be enrolled in this trial.

          -  Patients with Child-Pugh cirrhosis severity classification of C.

          -  Baseline abnormalities in hepatic tests (AST &gt; 5.0 X study center upper limit of
             normal (ULN); ALT &gt; 5.0 X study center ULN; albumin &lt; 2.8 g/dL; international
             normalized ratio for prothrombin time (INR) &gt; 1.5 X study center ULN; total bilirubin
             &gt; 3.0 x study center ULN).

          -  Baseline hemoglobin &lt; 10.0 g/dL; total WBC &lt; 2.0 X 10 to the power of 9/L; absolute
             neutrophil count (ANC) &lt; 1.0 X 10 to the power of 9/L; or platelet count &lt; 50.0 X 10
             to the power of 9/L.

          -  Patients who are pregnant or breastfeeding.

          -  Any prior radiation therapy (other than small portals used for the palliation of
             isolated, symptomatic, osseous metastases) must have been completed more than 21 days
             before entry into the study and evaluable lesions must not have been included in the
             radiation portal.

          -  Patients may be either treatment naive or have had previous anticancer treatment; if
             previously treated they may not have been exposed to capecitabine and no more than two
             prior systemically administered treatment regimens are allowed. It is required that
             all treatment be completed no less than 21 days prior to the patient being treated in
             this study. Chemoembolization or hepatic resection are not regarded as systemically
             administered treatment regimens.

          -  Any treatment-related toxicity must have resolved within the 21 days prior to study
             entry.

          -  Patients with previous or concurrent malignancy except for inactive non-melanoma skin
             cancer and/or in situ carcinoma of the cervix, or other solid tumor treated curatively
             and without evidence of recurrence within the last 3 years prior to study entry.

          -  Patients with known, untreated brain metastases are ineligible for this trial.
             Patients with treated (irradiated) brain metastases are eligible if treatment was
             completed more than 28 days prior to study entry and if clinical neurologic function
             is stable. No patient, however, may enroll in this trial if they are taking phenytoin
             (Dilantin). Patients with carcinomatous meningitis, treated or untreated, are excluded
             from the study.

          -  Patients with uncontrolled metabolic disorders or other nonmalignant organ or systemic
             diseases or secondary effects of cancer that induce a high medical risk.

          -  Patients receiving warfarin (Coumadin), or any of the coumarin-type anticoagulants at
             any dose, even “mini-dose,” are excluded from this study because of a possible
             interference in their metabolism by capecitabine.

          -  Known allergy or hypersensitivity to PHY906 or any of the components used in the
             PHY906 formulations, or to capecitabine.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City of Hope National Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Duarte</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford Hospital and Clinics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06520</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Connecticut Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06516</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Cancer Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 27, 2004</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 27, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 28, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2007</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2007</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 28, 2007</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>hepatocellular carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>advanced</keyword>
  <keyword>unresectable</keyword>
  <keyword>liver cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>systemic chemotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>botanical</keyword>
  <keyword>herbal</keyword>
  <keyword>alternative and complementary medicine</keyword>
  <keyword>capecitabine</keyword>
  <keyword>PHY906</keyword>
  <keyword>oral</keyword>
  <keyword>HCC</keyword>
  <keyword>traditional chinese medicine</keyword>
  <keyword>tcm</keyword>
  <keyword>QOL</keyword>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Capecitabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

