<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02063035</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012P000266</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012P000266</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02063035</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness Study of the Drug Tranexamic Acid to Reduce Post-surgery Blood Loss in Spinal Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Topical Application of Tranexamic Acid to Reduce Postoperative Blood Loss in Posterior Approach Spinal Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Hypothesis: Topical application of Tranexamic acid into the surgical wound during spine
      surgery will decrease the overall blood loss post-operatively. This reduction in blood loss
      will reduce the need for transfusion. In addition it will also significantly reduce the cost
      of the surgical procedure.

      Specific Aim 1: The goal of this study is to quantitatively assess whether topical
      application of tranexamic acid placed into the surgical wound during lumbar spine surgery
      will decrease post-operative blood loss, thus lowering the need for blood transfusions. By
      reducing the number of transfusions participants can avoid the well-known complications
      associated with them. The investigators do not plan on measuring serum tranexamic acid
      levels.

      Several meta-analyses and level I studies have shown that intravenous (IV) administration of
      tranexamic acid is effective in reducing postoperative blood loss and the need for
      transfusion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Tranexamic acid, an antifibrinolytic agent, has been studied at great length across a myriad
      of medical specialties to reduce blood lost during these surgeries. Topical tranexamic acid
      administration reduces postoperative blood loss and proved safe in multiple types of
      surgeries -e.g. cardiothoracic, oral and maxillofacial, eye, ear and throat.(References:
      Fawzy and others [et al], Wong et al, Zufferey et al, Wang et al, Ipema et al).

      Intravenous tranexamic acid administration has been shown to reduce postoperative blood loss
      and transfusion need in patients undergoing spinal surgery (Reference: Elwatidy et al). Some
      advocates have suggested that topical (i.e. local) administration might be preferred over
      intravenous application. Topical administration of tranexamic acid has some potential
      advantages as it leads to lower systemic absorption, and offers less concern over the risk of
      thromboembolic complications (References: Wong et al, Raveendran et al).

      While systemic (intravenous) use of tranexamic acid has been studied in spine surgery, there
      has been little studied to show its effectiveness at reducing blood loss when used topically.

      This study proposes to determine if the topical application of tranexamic acid into the
      surgical wound of posterior multi-level lumbar spine surgery will decrease postoperative
      blood loss, thus decreasing the need for potential transfusions. Tranexamic acid has been
      well documented for its safety and efficacy, the investigators believe that this agent will
      become an important tool to reduce the blood loss in spinal surgeries. It offers a reduction
      in blood loss and, ultimately, a decrease in the transfusion rates which pose risks to the
      subject and significant cost.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 22, 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 22, 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Hemoglobin Level From Preoperative Appointment to Postoperative Hospital Discharge</measure>
    <time_frame>From preoperative appointment approximately one week before surgery to end of hospital stay up to approximately 5 days after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Blood loss was calculated from the difference between the level of hemoglobin at the preoperative appointment and the lowest level during the postoperative hospitalization period. Reported here is the change in hemoglobin level after surgery. A negative number indicates a reduction in hemoglobin level.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood Loss Volume Following Surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>From end of surgery on Day 1 to end of hospital stay up to approximately 5 days</time_frame>
    <description>Blood loss following surgery was defined as the total amount of fluid collected from the drain in the wound site during the hospital stay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Length of Stay in Days</measure>
    <time_frame>From end of surgery on Day 1 to end of hospital stay up to approximately 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The number of days the participants stayed in the hospital after surgery was recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative Blood Transfusions During Hospitalization</measure>
    <time_frame>From end of surgery on Day 1 to end of hospital stay up to approximately 5 days</time_frame>
    <description>All units of blood transfused during the hospital stay after surgery were recorded. One red blood cell unit contains 300 to 360 mL of whole blood.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">29</enrollment>
  <condition>Lumbar Spinal Stenosis</condition>
  <condition>Thoracic Spinal Stenosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tranexamic acid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery will receive a single, topical dose of tranexamic acid. The surgeon will irrigate the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirate it after five minutes. Drains will be placed after the study drug has been aspirated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery will receive a single, topical dose of matching placebo. The surgeon will irrigate the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirate it after five minutes. Drains will be placed after the study drug has been aspirated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tranexamic Acid</intervention_name>
    <description>A single topical application of 3 grams (g) of Tranexamic acid in 100 milliliter (mL) saline.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tranexamic acid</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cyklokapron®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>A single topical application of matching placebo, which is 100 mL of normal saline.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18-85 years, both male and female

          -  Undergoing elective multi-level spinal surgery with a posterior approach to the
             thoracolumbar spine.

          -  Negative pregnancy test

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Allergy to tranexamic acid

          -  Preoperative anemia (Hemoglobin &lt;11 grams per deciliter [g/dL] )

          -  Coagulopathy (preoperative platelet count &lt;150,000, International Normalized Ratio
             &gt;1.4, or Partial Thromboplastin Time &gt; 1.5 times normal)

          -  History of deep vein thrombosis, stroke, or pulmonary embolism

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding

          -  Liver function tests 2 times the upper limit of normal, and those with creatine
             greater than 1.6 milligrams per deciliter (mg/dL)

          -  Infection

          -  Revision procedure in which the only procedure is removing instrumentation

          -  Renal impairment

          -  Dural tear
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kirkham B Wood, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital Orthopedic Spine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fawzy H, Elmistekawy E, Bonneau D, Latter D, Errett L. Can local application of Tranexamic acid reduce post-coronary bypass surgery blood loss? A randomized controlled trial. J Cardiothorac Surg. 2009 Jun 18;4:25. doi: 10.1186/1749-8090-4-25.</citation>
    <PMID>19538741</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gill JB, Chin Y, Levin A, Feng D. The use of antifibrinolytic agents in spine surgery. A meta-analysis. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2008 Nov;90(11):2399-407. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.G.01179. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18978408</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thompson GH, Florentino-Pineda I, Poe-Kochert C. The role of amicar in decreasing perioperative blood loss in idiopathic scoliosis. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2005 Sep 1;30(17 Suppl):S94-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16138073</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hynes MC, Calder P, Rosenfeld P, Scott G. The use of tranexamic acid to reduce blood loss during total hip arthroplasty: an observational study. Ann R Coll Surg Engl. 2005 Mar;87(2):99-101.</citation>
    <PMID>15826417</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elwatidy S, Jamjoom Z, Elgamal E, Zakaria A, Turkistani A, El-Dawlatly A. Efficacy and safety of prophylactic large dose of tranexamic acid in spine surgery: a prospective, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2008 Nov 15;33(24):2577-80. doi: 10.1097/BRS.0b013e318188b9c5.</citation>
    <PMID>19011538</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wong J, Abrishami A, El Beheiry H, Mahomed NN, Roderick Davey J, Gandhi R, Syed KA, Muhammad Ovais Hasan S, De Silva Y, Chung F. Topical application of tranexamic acid reduces postoperative blood loss in total knee arthroplasty: a randomized, controlled trial. J Bone Joint Surg Am. 2010 Nov 3;92(15):2503-13. doi: 10.2106/JBJS.I.01518.</citation>
    <PMID>21048170</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Raveendran R, Wong J. Tranexamic acid reduces blood transfusion in surgical patients while its effects on thromboembolic events and mortality are uncertain. Evid Based Med. 2013 Apr;18(2):65-6. doi: 10.1136/eb-2012-100872. Epub 2012 Aug 4.</citation>
    <PMID>22864370</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zufferey P, Merquiol F, Laporte S, Decousus H, Mismetti P, Auboyer C, Samama CM, Molliex S. Do antifibrinolytics reduce allogeneic blood transfusion in orthopedic surgery? Anesthesiology. 2006 Nov;105(5):1034-46. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17065899</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang H, Shen B, Zeng Y. Comparison of topical versus intravenous tranexamic acid in primary total knee arthroplasty: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled and prospective cohort trials. Knee. 2014 Dec;21(6):987-93. doi: 10.1016/j.knee.2014.09.010. Epub 2014 Oct 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25450009</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ipema HJ, Tanzi MG. Use of topical tranexamic acid or aminocaproic acid to prevent bleeding after major surgical procedures. Ann Pharmacother. 2012 Jan;46(1):97-107. doi: 10.1345/aph.1Q383. Epub 2011 Dec 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22202494</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 19, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 13, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 14, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>March 23, 2017</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>June 6, 2017</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">June 8, 2017</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 6, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 6, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kirkham Wood</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor at Harvard Medical School</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>lumbar spine surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>thoracic spine surgery</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Constriction, Pathologic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Spinal Stenosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tranexamic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Tranexamic Acid</title>
          <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery received a single, topical dose of 3 grams (g) tranexamic acid. The surgeon irrigated the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirated it after five minutes. Drains were placed after the study drug was aspirated.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Placebo</title>
          <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery received a single, topical dose of matching placebo. The surgeon irrigated the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirated it after five minutes. Drains were placed after the study drug was aspirated.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="12"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="17"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="12"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="17"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Tranexamic Acid</title>
          <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery received a single, topical dose of 3 g tranexamic acid. The surgeon irrigated the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirated it after five minutes. Drains were placed after the study drug was aspirated.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Placebo</title>
          <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery received a single, topical dose of matching placebo. The surgeon irrigated the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirated it after five minutes. Drains were placed after the study drug was aspirated.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="12"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="17"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="29"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Inter-Quartile Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="69" lower_limit="62" upper_limit="72"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="66" lower_limit="50" upper_limit="73"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="68" lower_limit="60" upper_limit="72"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="20"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Change in Hemoglobin Level From Preoperative Appointment to Postoperative Hospital Discharge</title>
        <description>Blood loss was calculated from the difference between the level of hemoglobin at the preoperative appointment and the lowest level during the postoperative hospitalization period. Reported here is the change in hemoglobin level after surgery. A negative number indicates a reduction in hemoglobin level.</description>
        <time_frame>From preoperative appointment approximately one week before surgery to end of hospital stay up to approximately 5 days after surgery</time_frame>
        <population>Only participants, for whom both preoperative and postoperative time points were collected, are reported in this outcome measure.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Tranexamic Acid</title>
            <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery received a single, topical dose of 3 g tranexamic acid. The surgeon irrigated the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirated it after five minutes. Drains were placed after the study drug was aspirated.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery received a single, topical dose of matching placebo. The surgeon irrigated the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirated it after five minutes. Drains were placed after the study drug was aspirated.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Change in Hemoglobin Level From Preoperative Appointment to Postoperative Hospital Discharge</title>
          <description>Blood loss was calculated from the difference between the level of hemoglobin at the preoperative appointment and the lowest level during the postoperative hospitalization period. Reported here is the change in hemoglobin level after surgery. A negative number indicates a reduction in hemoglobin level.</description>
          <population>Only participants, for whom both preoperative and postoperative time points were collected, are reported in this outcome measure.</population>
          <units>grams per deciliter (g/dL)</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>Inter-Quartile Range</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="11"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="15"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="-3.2" lower_limit="-4.6" upper_limit="-2.4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="-4.6" lower_limit="-5.3" upper_limit="-4.1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.1318</p_value>
            <method>Wilcoxon (Mann-Whitney)</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Blood Loss Volume Following Surgery</title>
        <description>Blood loss following surgery was defined as the total amount of fluid collected from the drain in the wound site during the hospital stay.</description>
        <time_frame>From end of surgery on Day 1 to end of hospital stay up to approximately 5 days</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Tranexamic Acid</title>
            <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery received a single, topical dose of 3 g tranexamic acid. The surgeon irrigated the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirated it after five minutes. Drains were placed after the study drug was aspirated.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery received a single, topical dose of matching placebo. The surgeon irrigated the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirated it after five minutes. Drains were placed after the study drug was aspirated.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Blood Loss Volume Following Surgery</title>
          <description>Blood loss following surgery was defined as the total amount of fluid collected from the drain in the wound site during the hospital stay.</description>
          <units>mL</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>Inter-Quartile Range</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="12"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="17"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="534" lower_limit="260" upper_limit="705"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="530" lower_limit="320" upper_limit="795"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Hospital Length of Stay in Days</title>
        <description>The number of days the participants stayed in the hospital after surgery was recorded.</description>
        <time_frame>From end of surgery on Day 1 to end of hospital stay up to approximately 2 weeks</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Tranexamic Acid</title>
            <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery received a single, topical dose of 3 g tranexamic acid. The surgeon irrigated the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirated it after five minutes. Drains were placed after the study drug was aspirated.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery received a single, topical dose of matching placebo. The surgeon irrigated the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirated it after five minutes. Drains were placed after the study drug was aspirated.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Hospital Length of Stay in Days</title>
          <description>The number of days the participants stayed in the hospital after surgery was recorded.</description>
          <units>days</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>Inter-Quartile Range</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="12"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="17"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="5" lower_limit="4" upper_limit="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="6" lower_limit="5" upper_limit="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Post-operative Blood Transfusions During Hospitalization</title>
        <description>All units of blood transfused during the hospital stay after surgery were recorded. One red blood cell unit contains 300 to 360 mL of whole blood.</description>
        <time_frame>From end of surgery on Day 1 to end of hospital stay up to approximately 5 days</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Tranexamic Acid</title>
            <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery received a single, topical dose of 3 g tranexamic acid. The surgeon irrigated the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirated it after five minutes. Drains were placed after the study drug was aspirated.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo</title>
            <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery received a single, topical dose of matching placebo. The surgeon irrigated the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirated it after five minutes. Drains were placed after the study drug was aspirated.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Post-operative Blood Transfusions During Hospitalization</title>
          <description>All units of blood transfused during the hospital stay after surgery were recorded. One red blood cell unit contains 300 to 360 mL of whole blood.</description>
          <units>units of blood</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>Inter-Quartile Range</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="12"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="17"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0" lower_limit="0" upper_limit="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0" lower_limit="0" upper_limit="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>From time of admission to hospital for surgery up to study completion (up to approximately 2.5 years).</time_frame>
      <desc>Participants were monitored only for the following serious adverse events from time of admission to hospital for surgery up to study completion: myocardial infarction, stroke, thrombosis, and postoperative infection. Non-serious adverse events were not collected in this study.</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Tranexamic Acid</title>
          <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery received a single, topical dose of 3 g tranexamic acid. The surgeon irrigated the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirated it after five minutes. Drains were placed after the study drug was aspirated.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Placebo</title>
          <description>Participants undergoing spinal surgery received a single, topical dose of matching placebo. The surgeon irrigated the study medication in the wound prior to closure, and aspirated it after five minutes. Drains were placed after the study drug was aspirated.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Cardiac disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Myocardial infaction</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Surgical and medical procedures</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Postoperative wound infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Postoperative wound infection after release from hospital</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="12"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="17"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="0"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="0"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. Kirkham B. Wood</name_or_title>
      <organization>Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston, MA, USA</organization>
      <phone>617-726-2000 ext +1</phone>
      <email>kbwood@stanford.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

