<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02060123</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UW 12-555</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02060123</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Qigong Intervention Program for Abused Chinese Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Wait-list Controlled Trial of a Qigong Intervention Program on Telomerase Activity and Psychological Stress in Abused Chinese Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the effect of a qigong intervention program on
      telomerase activity in Chinese women with a history of intimate partner violence.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Qigong is a mind-body exercise rooted in the paradigm of traditional Chinese medicine, aiming
      to achieve a harmonious flow of energy (qi) in the body through gentle movements and is thus
      considered as a holistic health practice towards promoting physical and mental well-being and
      improving longevity. It was suggested that qigong exercise, as a stress management strategy,
      could be effective in improving psychological symptoms, as well as enhancing cellular
      telomerase activity by reducing oxidative stress level and regulating immune response.

      The study is to evaluate the effects of a qigong intervention on telomerase activity and
      pro-inflammation cytokines, perceived stress, perceived coping, and depressive symptoms in
      Chinese women with a history of intimate partner violence. The study design is a randomized,
      wait-list controlled design with intervention and wait-list control groups. A total of 240
      Chinese abused women will be recruited. The qigong intervention program consists of: (i) a
      2-hr group qigong training twice a week for 6 weeks; (ii) weekly group follow-up of a 1-hour
      group qigong exercise for 4 months; and (iii) self-practice of qigong exercise for 30 minutes
      each day throughout the intervention period lasting 5.5 months. It is hypothesized that the
      participants in the intervention group will have higher levels of telomerase activity and
      perceived coping, and lower levels of pro-inflammation cytokines, perceived stress, and
      depressive symptoms, on completion of a qigong intervention program, compared to abused
      Chinese women in the wait-list control group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in telomerase activity</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-intervention (baseline) and post-intervention (5.5 months later)</time_frame>
    <description>For each participant, 10 ml of peripheral blood will be collected for measurements of telomerase activity at two time points: pre-intervention (T0) and post-intervention (T2) in the intervention group, as well as in wait-list control group before qigong training.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in level of pro-inflammatory cytokines</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-intervention (baseline) and post-intervention (5.5 months later)</time_frame>
    <description>The peripheral blood plasma will also be analyzed for pro-inflammation cytokines TNF-alpha and IL-6 levels.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in perceived stress</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-intervention (baseline), post-training (6 weeks later) and post-intervention (5.5 months later)</time_frame>
    <description>The 10-item Perceived Stress Scale (PSS), the most widely used psychological instrument for measuring the perception of stress, will be used to assess the degree to which situations in life are perceived by the participant as stressful during the past month.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in perceived coping</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-intervention (baseline), post-training (6 weeks later) and post-intervention (5.5 months later)</time_frame>
    <description>The Perceived Coping Scale (PCS) will be used to assess the types and perceived effectiveness of each of the 13 specific strategies used by the participant in dealing with violence perpetrated by her intimate partner.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in depressive symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-intervention (baseline), post-training (6 weeks later) and post-intervention (5.5 months later)</time_frame>
    <description>The Chinese version of the Beck Depression Inventory version II (BDI-II) will be used to assess depressive symptoms in the previous two weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in sleep disturbance</measure>
    <time_frame>pre-intervention (baseline), post-training (6 weeks later) and post-intervention (5.5 months later)</time_frame>
    <description>The Chinese version of the General Sleep Disturbance Scale (GSDS), a 21-item questionnaire, will be used to measure participants' sleep disturbance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">271</enrollment>
  <condition>Abused Women</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Qigong training</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>a total of 103 hours over a period of 5.5 months, consisting of:
Group learning and practice: a 2-hour qigong exercise training session will be provided by a qigong master twice a week for six consecutive weeks (24 hours),
Weekly group follow-up: a 1-hour qigong exercise will be conducted with reinforcement of learning and remedial teaching by a qigong master once a week for four consecutive months (16 hours) after the group learning and practice, and
Self-practice: participant will engage in qigong exercise for 30 minutes every day for the whole intervention period lasting 5.5 months (63 hours).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wait-list control- Health talks</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Monthly health education talks unrelated to qigong will be provided starting from the point when the intervention group starts the qigong weekly follow-up.Once the intervention group has completed the qigong intervention program, the wait-list control group will receive the qigong exercise training.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Qigong training</intervention_name>
    <description>a total of 103 hours over a period of 5.5 months, consisting of:
Group learning and practice: a 2-hour qigong exercise training session will be provided by a qigong master twice a week for six consecutive weeks (24 hours),
Weekly group follow-up: a 1-hour qigong exercise will be conducted with reinforcement of learning and remedial teaching by a qigong master once a week for four consecutive months (16 hours) after the group learning and practice, and
Self-practice: participant will engage in qigong exercise for 30 minutes every day for the whole intervention period lasting 5.5 months (63 hours).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Qigong training</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Wait-list control- Health talks</intervention_name>
    <description>Monthly health education talks unrelated to qigong will be provided starting from the point when the intervention group starts the qigong weekly follow-up.Once the intervention group has completed the qigong intervention program, the wait-list control group will receive the qigong exercise training.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Wait-list control- Health talks</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years of age or older,

          -  willing to undertake the qigong intervention program,

          -  available for all testing points,

          -  receptive to random allocation, and

          -  assessed to be abused by an intimate partner in the preceding year or longer, based on
             the Chinese Abuse Assessment Screen.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  had participated in qigong training or other mind body intervention within the
             previous 6 months, or

          -  have serious medical conditions that might limit their participation in qigong
             exercise (based on our previous experience, such conditions include cancer, severe
             obesity, narcolepsy, major depressive disorder, schizophrenia), or

          -  have psychiatric disorders, or

          -  use medication or other psychological intervention for stress, or

          -  are abused by someone who is not their intimate partner.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Agnes Tiwari, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>HKSKH Lady MacLehose Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ho RT, Chan JS, Wang CW, Lau BW, So KF, Yuen LP, Sham JS, Chan CL. A randomized controlled trial of qigong exercise on fatigue symptoms, functioning, and telomerase activity in persons with chronic fatigue or chronic fatigue syndrome. Ann Behav Med. 2012 Oct;44(2):160-70. doi: 10.1007/s12160-012-9381-6.</citation>
    <PMID>22736201</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhang GD. The impacts of 48-form tai chi chuan and yi qi yang fei gong on the serum levels of IgG, IgM, IgA, and IgE in human. Journal of Beijing Institute of Physical Education. 1990;4:12-4.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jahnke R, Larkey L, Rogers C, Etnier J, Lin F. A comprehensive review of health benefits of qigong and tai chi. Am J Health Promot. 2010 Jul-Aug;24(6):e1-e25. doi: 10.4278/ajhp.081013-LIT-248. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20594090</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 6, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 9, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 11, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 28, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 28, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 1, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Professor Agnes Tiwari</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor and Head</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Qigong</keyword>
  <keyword>Telomerase</keyword>
  <keyword>Perceived stress</keyword>
  <keyword>RCT</keyword>
  <keyword>Chinese</keyword>
  <keyword>Abused women</keyword>
  <keyword>intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Depression</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

