<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02067897</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>104906</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02067897</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Nonrandomized Assessment of Ingrown ToenaiLs Treated by Excision of Skinfold Rather Than Toenail</brief_title>
  <acronym>NAILTEST</acronym>
  <official_title>Nonrandomized Assessment of Ingrown ToenaiLs Treated by Excision of Skinfold Rather Than Toenail (NAILTEST): a Study of the Vandenbos Procedure in Children and Adolescents</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Michael Livingston</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Physicians' Services Incorporated Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Western University, Canada</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Ingrown toenails occur when the nail grows into the surrounding skin, resulting in pain and
      infection. The most common procedure to treat this problem is a wedge excision (removal of
      part of the toenail) and matricectomy (destruction of part of the nailbed with chemicals or
      surgical instruments). This study will evaluate the effectiveness of an alternative technique
      called the Vandenbos procedure (where the skin is removed and the toenail is left intact).
      This procedure is currently being used by some of the pediatric surgeons at our hospital and
      we want to evaluate our results up to 6 months after surgery. We believe that the true
      recurrence rate will be greater than 0% but that recovery time and morbidity will be
      acceptable to most patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Ingrown toenails are common among adolescents and young adults with the big toe being the
      most commonly affected. The exact incidence is unknown. An ingrown toenail occurs when the
      nail traumatizes the surrounding skin, resulting in swelling, infection, and the generation
      of granulation tissue. This cycle causes the nail to embed itself even further into the
      surrounding tissues, leading to additional swelling and infection.

      Many treatments have been proposed for this condition. Non-surgical options include soaking,
      wearing loose shoes, antibiotics, and specialized braces. While these treatments often
      provide short-term symptomatic relief, many people with ingrown toenails eventually need
      surgery. The most common surgical treatment is a wedge excision (removal of the ingrown part
      of the nail). Most clinicians perform a partial matricectomy at the same time (destruction of
      part of the underlying nailbed with chemicals or surgical instruments). This prevents
      recurrence (where the toenail becomes ingrown again). The rate of recurrence with the wedge
      excision and matricectomy is reported to be 12-50%.

      An alternative surgical technique is the Vandenbos procedure, where the skinfold is excised
      and allowed to heal by secondary intention over a period of approximately 6 weeks. This
      approach theoretically involves more pain, a higher risk of post-operative bleeding (because
      it is initially an open wound), and a longer recovery time. Proponents of this technique
      argue that these short-term morbidities are justified given the low rate of recurrence and
      excellent long-term results.

      The original case series published by Vandenbos in 1959 found a recurrence rate of 0%. Two
      recent case series published by doctors from Ontario reported the same finding, but it was
      unclear how many patients in their series were lost to follow-up. Other studies have reported
      positive results but with a recurrence rate of 7-20%. Thus, the true effectiveness of this
      procedure remains unclear. Furthermore, there is no high quality evidence to support one
      technique over the other. Even a recent Cochrane review of 24 randomized controlled trials
      could not reach any definitive conclusions as to which procedure (among other surgical
      options) is the most effective. Previous trials show significant heterogeneity and none have
      assessed the Vandenbos procedure specifically. As a result, many clinicians continue to use
      the wedge excision and matricectomy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Enrolling by invitation</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical signs of recurrence will be assessed 1 month, 2 months, and 6 months after surgery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain, functional status, and quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 month, 2 months, 6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Pain, functional status, and quality of life will be measured with the 5-item EuroQol-5D-5L.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction with the Vandenbos procedure will be measured with the 8-item Surgical Satisfaction Questionnaire (SSQ).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recovery time</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month, 2 months, 6 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Recovery time will be calculated in days off before returning to work, school, and normal footwear.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Nails, Ingrown</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vandenbos procedure (skinfold excision)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants in this cohort will undergo with Vandenbos procedure (skinfold excision) for one or more ingrown toenails. This surgery will be formed as an day procedure under general anesthetic.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population include children and adolescents aged 10 to 18 years with one or more
        ingrown toenails. They may have undergone previous surgical and/or non-surgical treatment
        for this condition.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  10 to 18 years old

          -  Undergoing Vandenbos procedure for one or more ingrown toenails

          -  Willing to complete assessments

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to understand English

          -  Severe medical co-morbidities
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sarah A Jones, MD, PhD, FRCSC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Division of Pediatric Surgery</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Western Ontario, London Health Sciences Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6A 5W9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yang G, Yanchar NL, Lo AY, Jones SA. Treatment of ingrown toenails in the pediatric population. J Pediatr Surg. 2008 May;43(5):931-5. doi: 10.1016/j.jpedsurg.2007.12.042.</citation>
    <PMID>18485969</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heidelbaugh JJ, Lee H. Management of the ingrown toenail. Am Fam Physician. 2009 Feb 15;79(4):303-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19235497</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eekhof JA, Van Wijk B, Knuistingh Neven A, van der Wouden JC. Interventions for ingrowing toenails. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2012 Apr 18;(4):CD001541. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD001541.pub3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22513901</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vandenbos KQ, Bowers WF. Ingrown toenail: a result of weight bearing on soft tissue. U S Arm Forces Med J 1959;10:1168-73.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chapeskie H, Kovac JR. Case Series: Soft-tissue nail-fold excision: a definitive treatment for ingrown toenails. Can J Surg. 2010 Aug;53(4):282-6.</citation>
    <PMID>20646404</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haricharan RN, Masquijo J, Bettolli M. Nail-fold excision for the treatment of ingrown toenail in children. J Pediatr. 2013 Feb;162(2):398-402. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2012.07.056. Epub 2012 Sep 10.</citation>
    <PMID>22974574</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Antrum RM. Radical excision of the nailfold for ingrowing toenail. J Bone Joint Surg Br. 1984 Jan;66(1):63-5.</citation>
    <PMID>6693479</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Persichetti P, Simone P, Li Vecchi G, Di Lella F, Cagli B, Marangi GF. Wedge excision of the nail fold in the treatment of ingrown toenail. Ann Plast Surg. 2004 Jun;52(6):617-20.</citation>
    <PMID>15167000</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mitchell S, Jackson CR, Wilson-Storey D. Surgical treatment of ingrown toenails in children: what is best practice? Ann R Coll Surg Engl. 2011 Mar;93(2):99-102. doi: 10.1308/003588411X12851639107674. Epub 2010 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>21073822</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 12, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 18, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 20, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 11, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 11, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 13, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Western University, Canada</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Livingston</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Resident, Division of General Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Nails, Ingrown</keyword>
  <keyword>Children</keyword>
  <keyword>Ambulatory Surgical Procedures</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nails, Ingrown</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

