<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02065414</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LAEBBA0005</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02065414</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Clinical Trial to Test the Effect of Experimental Mouth Rinse on Gum Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Four Weeks Clinical Efficacy of an Ethyl Lauroyl Arginate HCL (LAE) Mouth Rinse: Effect on Gingivitis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johnson &amp; Johnson Consumer and Personal Products Worldwide</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johnson &amp; Johnson Consumer and Personal Products Worldwide</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Participants will be given special instructions about taking care of their teeth during the
      18 hours before they come to the dentist's office for screening/baseline, 1 week, 2 weeks and
      4 weeks. At that first visit, they will be examined by a dentist, who will examine their
      mouths with a dental instrument to determine whether they qualify to participate in the
      trial. Someone who works for the dentist will also take some oral measurements.

      Participants who qualify to be in the study will receive a treatment for their gingivitis and
      have an equal chance of being assigned to one of three treatment groups. Participants in all
      three groups will be given toothpaste that is already available in stores. They will brush
      their teeth twice daily in their regular manner. After brushing, participants in one group
      will use an experimental mouth rinse that is not available in stores. Another group will be
      given a mouth rinse to use that is already available in stores, and the third group will use
      a placebo mouth rinse. After they receive their assigned products participants will be
      supervised while they brush their teeth and rinse to ensure they understand exactly how to
      use the products. Participants will be required to stay at the site 20 minutes after the
      first use of product during visit 1 to monitor any potential allergic reaction. All other
      brushing and rinsing over the next four weeks will be at home, but participants will be
      required to keep a diary to record their brushing and rinsing times twice each day.

      Participants will be required to bring their diaries and any left-over toothpaste and mouth
      rinse with them for three more scheduled appointments after about 1 week, 2 weeks, and 4
      weeks. At those appointments, the dentist will examine their mouths, make sure there are no
      safety concerns, and examine again to get the measurements needed. One of the dentist's staff
      members will take other measurements as well.

      The study will determine the measured effects of the experimental mouth rinse on bleeding as
      a result of gingivitis, and compare these results to the mouth rinse that is already
      available.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      At screening Participants will present to the clinical site having refrained from oral
      hygiene for at least 8 hours, but no more than 18 hours for baseline examinations (safety
      oral and hard soft tissue exam, MGI - Modified Gingival Index, BI - Bleeding Index and PI-
      Plaque Index and Extrinsic Staining. After the baseline oral examinations, qualifying
      participants will receive a whole-mouth supragingival dental prophylaxis and will be randomly
      assigned to one of three treatment groups.

      Participants randomly assigned to the negative control treatment group will brush twice daily
      with a marketed fluoride toothpaste in their usual manner and rinse with a placebo mouth
      rinse. Participants randomly assigned to the experimental treatment group will brush twice
      daily with a marketed fluoride toothpaste brush in their usual manner and use an experimental
      mouth rinse. The last treatment group randomly assigned to the positive control will brush
      twice daily with a marketed fluoride toothpaste in their usual manner and rinse with a
      marketed available mouth rinse. Participants will have an equal chance of being assigned each
      of the three groups. The first product use will be conducted under supervision of study
      personnel. Participants will be required to stay at the site 20 minutes after the first use
      of product during visit 1 to monitor any potential analytic reaction. All other brushing and
      rinsing will be unsupervised and the participants will be required to maintain a diary card
      to document twice-daily product use, brushing and rinsing times. Diaries along with product
      accountability will be used to check for subject compliance.

      Participants will return to the clinical site after 1 week (Day 7±1 day), 2 weeks (Day 14±2
      days) and 4 weeks (Day 28±3 days). Oral hard and soft tissue safety, Modified Gingival Index
      (MGI), Bleeding Index (BI), and Plaque Index (PI) will be assessed by the primary examiner 1
      at all visits Extrinsic stain will be assessed at baseline, 2 weeks and 4 weeks by the
      secondary examiner.

      At the end of the study, subjects will return all used and unused product to the clinical
      site.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Whole Mouth Mean Bleeding Index (BI) at 4 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Bleeding will be assessed by using a standard measurement called the Gingival Bleeding Index.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Whole Mouth Mean Bleeding Index (BI) at 1 week</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 2 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Bleeding will be assessed by using a standard measurement called the Gingival Bleeding Index</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Whole-mouth Mean Modified Gingival Index (MGI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Gingivitis will be assessed by scoring inflammation according to the Modified Gingival Index.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Turesky Modification of the Quigley Hein Plaque Index (PI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Plaque will be assessed using a standard scale called the Turesky Modification of the Quigley Hein Plaque Index</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Extrinsic Stain</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Stain will be assessed using the standard measurement called Macpherson Modification of the Lobene Stain Index</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">260</enrollment>
  <condition>Gingivitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neg Control Mouth Rinse W002194-0221-P</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Mouth rinse containing 5% Hydroalcohol
Twice each day, brush in usual manner with a fluoride-containing dentifrice, rinse mouth with water, and then rinse with 20 ml of mouth rinse W002194-0221-P for 30 seconds and spit it out.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: Mouth Rinse 19668-012</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Listerine Advance Gum Defense Twice each day, brush in usual manner with a fluoride-containing dentifrice, rinse mouth with water, and then rinse with 20 ml of mouth rinse 19668-012 for 30 seconds and spit it out - do not swallow.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active Comparator Mouth Rinse 5000347078873</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Mouth rinse containing Chlorhexidine Corsodyl ®Mouthwash
Twice each day, brush in usual manner with a fluoride-containing dentifrice, in the usual manner, rinse mouth with water, wait 5 minutes after brushing and then rinse with 10 ml of mouth rinse 5000347078873for 60 seconds and spit it out - do not swallow.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Listerine Advance Gum Defense</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: Mouth Rinse 19668-012</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mouth rinse containing Chlorhexidine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Active Comparator Mouth Rinse 5000347078873</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mouth rinse containing 5% Hydroalcohol</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Neg Control Mouth Rinse W002194-0221-P</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1. Males and females 18 years of age or older, in good general and oral health without
             any known allergy to commercial dental products or cosmetics.

          -  2. Evidence of a personally signed and dated informed consent document indicating the
             subject (or legally acceptable representative) has been informed of all pertinent
             aspects of the trial and all questions have been answered.

          -  3. Females of childbearing potential must be using a medically-acceptable method of
             birth control for at least 1 month prior to Visit 1 and agree to continue using this
             method during their participation in the study.

          -  4. Able to comprehend and follow the requirements of the study (including availability
             on scheduled visit dates) based upon research site personnel's assessment.

          -  5. A minimum of 20 natural teeth with scorable facial and lingual surfaces. Teeth that
             are grossly carious, extensively restored, orthodontically banded, abutments,
             exhibiting severe generalized cervical and/or enamel abrasion, or third molars will
             not be included in the tooth count.

          -  6. A mean gingival index ≥1.75 according to the Modified Gingival Index.

          -  7. A mean plaque index ≥1.95 according to the Turesky modification of the Quigley-Hein
             Plaque Index scored on six surfaces per tooth.

          -  8. Mean Bleeding Index ≥0.15

          -  9. Absence of significant oral soft tissue pathology, excluding plaque-induced
             gingivitis, based on a visual examination and at the discretion of the Investigator.

          -  10. Absence of moderate/advanced periodontitis based on a clinical examination (ADA
             Type III, IV).

          -  11. Absence of fixed or removable orthodontic appliance or removable partial dentures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  1. History of significant adverse effects, including sensitivities or suspected
             allergies, following use of oral hygiene products such as toothpastes and mouth rinses
             and red food dye.

          -  2. Dental prophylaxis within 2 weeks prior to Screening visit.

          -  3. History of medical conditions requiring prophylactic antibiotic coverage prior to
             invasive dental procedures.

          -  4. Antibiotic, anti-inflammatory or anticoagulant therapy during the study or within
             the one month prior to the baseline exam. Intermittent use of certain
             anti-inflammatory medication is acceptable at the discretion of the investigator.

          -  5. Daily use of aspirin.

          -  6. Known sensitivity to the investigational product ingredients.

          -  7. Self reported pregnancy or lactation (this criterion is due to oral tissue changes
             related to pregnancy and nursing which can affect interpretation of study results).

          -  8. Significant unstable or uncontrolled medical condition which may interfere with a
             subject's participation in the study, at the discretion of the Investigator.

          -  9. Participation in any clinical study within 30 days of Visit 1.

          -  10. Relative, partner or staff of any clinical research site personnel.

          -  11. Other severe acute or chronic medical or psychiatric condition or laboratory
             abnormality that may increase the risk associated with study participation or
             investigational product administration or may interfere with the interpretation of
             study results and, in the judgment of the Investigator, would make the subject
             inappropriate for entry into this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Lynch, DMD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Johnson &amp; Johnson Consumer and Personal Products Worldwide</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Research Ethics Committee Yorkshire &amp; Humber-Sheffield</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chester</city>
        <zip>M1 3DZ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 16, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 18, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 19, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 4, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 4, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 5, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gums</keyword>
  <keyword>Gingiva</keyword>
  <keyword>Gingival Inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>Gingival Bleeding</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gingivitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chlorhexidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chlorhexidine gluconate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Listerine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sodium Fluoride</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

