<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02064504</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201010</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02064504</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Determine the Pharmacokinetics of GSK961081 and Fluticasone Furoate When Administered Alone or in Combination</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open Label, Randomised, Six-way Crossover, Single Dose Study to Determine the Pharmacokinetics of GSK961081 and Fluticasone Furoate When Administered Alone or in Combination</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      GSK961081 is a novel bifunctional molecule that combines muscarinic antagonism and
      beta2-agonism in a single molecule and is in development for the treatment of chronic
      obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). This is a randomised, open-label, six-way crossover,
      single dose study. This study evaluates the drug delivery and systemic pharmacokinetics of
      GSK961081 following concurrent administration of GSK961081 and fluticasone furoate via dry
      powder inhaler (DPI) in comparison to GSK961081 DISKUS. There will be six treatment periods
      and 7 days washout period in the study. Subjects will attend the unit in the morning for
      dosing and will be resident until 12 hours post administration. All subjects will receive six
      treatments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 19, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 20, 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 20, 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>GSK961081 AUC(0-t')</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre dose, 5 minutes (min), 15 min, 30 min, 45 min, 1 hour (h), 2 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 10 h and 12 h for each treatment period</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected to estimate the area under the concentration-time curve from zero (pre-dose) to last common time of quantifiable concentration across all treatments for an analyte where t'=common time AUC(0-t') of GSK961081 following concurrent administration of GSK961081 and fluticasone furoate via DPI in comparison to GSK961081 DISKUS</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre dose, 5 min, 15 min, 30 min, 45 min, 1 h, 2 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 10 h and 12 h for each treatment period</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected to estimate the maximum observed concentration (Cmax) of GSK961081 following concurrent administration of GSK961081 and fluticasone furoate via DPI in comparison to GSK961081 DISKUS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC(0-t') and Cmax following single and dual strip administration of GSK961081</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre dose, 5 min, 15 min, 30 min, 45 min, 1 h, 2 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 10 h and 12 h for each treatment period</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected to estimate the AUC(0-t') and Cmax of GSK961081 following single and dual strip administration of GSK961081 alone via DPI in comparison to GSK961081 DISKUS</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AUC(0-t') and Cmax following concurrent administration of GSK961081 and fluticasone furoate</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre dose, 5 min, 15 min, 30 min, 45 min, 1 h, 2 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 10 h and 12 h for each treatment period</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected to estimate the AUC(0-t') and Cmax of GSK961081 following concurrent administration of GSK961081 and fluticasone furoate via DPI in comparison to single and dual strip GSK961081 via DPI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fluticasone furoate AUC(0-t') and Cmax</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre dose, 5 min, 15 min, 30 min, 45 min, 1 h, 2 h, 4 h, 6 h, 8 h, 10 h and 12 h for each treatment period</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be collected to estimate the AUC (0-t') and Cmax of fluticasone furoate following concurrent administration of GSK961081 and fluticasone furoate via DPI in comparison to dual strip fluticasone furoate via DPI</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Safety and tolerability as assessed by number of participants with Adverse Events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the study treatment in the following order: ABFCED in each period (one per period). Where A=GSK961081 administered from DISKUS, B=GSK961081 Single strip (SS) administered from DPI, C=GSK961081 Dual Strip (DS) administered from DPI with a filled (lactose) second strip (DS configuration), D=GSK961081/fluticasone furoate (GSK961081/FF) administered from DPI (GSK961081 higher dose), E=FF DS administered from DPI with a filled (lactose) second strip (dual strip configuration), F=GSK961081/FF administered from DPI (GSK961081 lower dose).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the study treatment in the following order: BCADFE in each period (one per period)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the study treatment in the following order: CDBEAF in each period (one per period)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the study treatment in the following order: DECFBA in each period (one per period)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the study treatment in the following order: EFDACB in each period (one per period)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 6</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the study treatment in the following order: FAEBDC in each period (one per period)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GSK961081</intervention_name>
    <description>Dry white to off white powder</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 6</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fluticasone furoate</intervention_name>
    <description>Dry white powder</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 4</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sequence 6</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male/females aged between 18 and 64 years of age inclusive, at the time of signing the
             informed consent.

          -  Healthy as determined by a responsible and experienced physician, based on a medical
             evaluation including medical history, physical examination and laboratory tests. A
             subject with a clinical abnormality or laboratory parameter(s) which is/are not
             specifically listed in the inclusion or exclusion criteria, outside the reference
             range for the population being studied may be included only if the Investigator
             determines that the finding is unlikely to introduce additional risk factors and will
             not interfere with the study procedures.

          -  Body mass index (BMI) within the range 18 to 29.0 kilogram (kg)/meter (m)^2
             (inclusive).

          -  A female subject is eligible to participate if she is of:

        Non-childbearing potential defined as pre-menopausal females with a documented tubal
        ligation or hysterectomy for this definition, &quot;documented&quot; refers to the outcome of the
        investigator's/designee's review of the subject's medical history for study eligibility, as
        obtained via a verbal interview with the subject or from the subject's medical records; or
        postmenopausal defined as 12 months of spontaneous amenorrhea in questionable cases a blood
        sample with simultaneous follicle stimulating hormone (FSH) greater than 40 MlU/mL and
        estradiol less than 40 picogram (pg)/mL (less than 147 pmol/L) is confirmatory. Females on
        hormone replacement therapy (HRT) and whose menopausal status is in doubt will be required
        to use the contraception methods if they wish to continue their HRT during the study.
        Otherwise, they must discontinue HRT to allow confirmation of post-menopausal status prior
        to study enrollment. For most forms of HRT, at least 2-4 weeks will elapse between the
        cessation of therapy and the blood draw; this interval depends on the type and dosage of
        HRT. Following confirmation of their post-menopausal status, they can resume use of HRT
        during the study without use of a contraceptive method.

        Child-bearing potential with negative pregnancy test as determined by serum human chorionic
        gonadotropin (hCG) test at screening or urine hCG test prior to dosing AND Agrees to use
        one of the contraception methods for an appropriate period of time (as determined by the
        product label or investigator) prior to the start of dosing to sufficiently minimize the
        risk of pregnancy at that point. Female subjects must agree to use contraception for 5
        terminal half-lives after the end of the study (i.e. until after the follow-up visit is
        complete).

        OR has only same-sex partners, when this is her preferred and usual lifestyle.

          -  Capable of giving written informed consent, which includes compliance with the
             requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT), alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin less than or equal
             to 1.5x upper limit of normal (ULN) (isolated bilirubin greater than 1.5xULN is
             acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and direct bilirubin less than 35%).

          -  Forced Expiratory Volume in 1 second (FEV1) greater than or equal to 85% predicted and
             a FEV1/ Forced Vital capacity (FVC) ratio greater than or equal to 0.7

          -  Based on single or averaged QTc values of triplicate Electrocardiograms (ECGs)
             obtained over a brief recording period:

        QT duration corrected for heart rate by Fridericia's formula (QTcF) less than 450
        millisecond.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or biliary abnormalities
             (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones).

          -  History of regular alcohol consumption within 6 months of the study defined as:

        An average weekly intake of greater than 21 units for males or greater than 14 units for
        females. In Australia one unit (= standard drink) is equivalent to 10 gram of alcohol: 270
        mL of full strength beer (4.8%), 375 mL of mid strength beer (3.5%), 470 mL of light beer
        (2.7%), 250 mL pre-mix full strength spirit (5%), 100 mL of wine (13.5%) and 30 mL of
        spirit (40%).

          -  History of sensitivity to any of the study medications, or components thereof or a
             history of drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of the investigator or GSK
             Medical Monitor, contraindicates their participation.

          -  A positive pre-study Hepatitis B surface antigen or positive Hepatitis C antibody
             result within 3 months of screening.

          -  Urinary cotinine/ Breath carbon monoxide (CO) levels indicative of smoking or history
             or regular use of tobacco- or nicotine-containing products within 6 months prior to
             screening and a pack year history of &lt;/=10 pack years.

          -  A positive pre-study drug/alcohol screen.

          -  A positive test for Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV) antibody.

          -  Where participation in the study would result in donation of blood or blood products
             in excess of 500 mL within a 56 day period.

          -  Lactating females.

          -  The subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received an investigational
             product within the following time period prior to the first dosing day in the current
             study: 30 days, 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of the
             investigational product (whichever is longer).

          -  Exposure to more than four new chemical entities within 12 months prior to the first
             dosing day
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Randwick</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2031</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</url>
    <description>Researchers can use this site to request access to anonymised patient level data and/or supporting documents from clinical studies to conduct further research.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://gsk-clinicalstudyregister.com/study/201010?search=study&amp;study_ids=201010#rs</url>
    <description>Results for study 201010 can be found on the GSK Clinical Study Register.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 13, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 13, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 17, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Respiratory</keyword>
  <keyword>GSK961081 (MABA)</keyword>
  <keyword>healthy subjects</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>GW685698 (fluticasone furoate)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chronic Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Disease, Chronic Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fluticasone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Patient-level data for this study will be made available through www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com following the timelines and process described on this site.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <study_docs>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>201010</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Study Protocol</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>201010</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Annotated Case Report Form</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>201010</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Statistical Analysis Plan</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>201010</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Informed Consent Form</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>201010</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Dataset Specification</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>201010</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Clinical Study Report</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>201010</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Individual Participant Data Set</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
  </study_docs>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

