<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02065505</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19284013.6.0000.5503</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02065505</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Method Pilates X Pilates in Water Postural Alignment and Its Correlation With Respiratory Capacity With Hemiparesis Spastic</brief_title>
  <official_title>METHOD PILATES x PILATES IN WATER POSTURAL ALIGNMENT AND ITS CORRELATION WITH RESPIRATORY CAPACITY WITH HEMIPARESIS SPASTIC</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidade do Vale do Paraíba</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade do Vale do Paraíba</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the efficacy of treatment with the Pilates Method in postural alignment and its
      correlation with the respiratory capacity of individuals with hemiparesis, with the aid of
      biomedical instrumentation, comparing the method performed in soil and therapy pool.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The hemiparesis, which corresponds to muscle weakness in hemisphere contralateral to injury,
      is the most common disorder after stroke Brain. The most obvious implication is postural
      asymmetry, having direct relation to respiratory pressures are also reduced due to muscle
      weakness, thus altering the respiratory capacity of these individuals. The Pilates Method is
      gaining prominence in clinical and scientific areas, contributing to restoring good posture
      and vertical alignment of the body. Therefore, this study aims assess muscle electrical
      activity, respiratory capacity and functionality of spastic hemiparetic patients before and
      after application the Pilates Method, soil and therapy pool. A randomized study where 60
      hemiparetic participate will be held with brachial predominance and 30 healthy subjects
      (Control Group), of both sexes, ages 40 to 70 years. Individuals with hemiparesis will be
      randomly assigned through a lottery and half held 10 consecutive sessions of Pilates in the
      soil and the rest will the same protocol adapted for therapy pool. The control group will be
      treated by the Pilates Method in the soil. The exercises will aim to lengthen musculature
      shortened due to postural pattern of pathology ; strengthen selected muscles that give
      support and postural musculature more important upper limb for activities of daily living.
      Participants will undergo postural assessment, activity EMG, muscle strength, respiratory
      capacity analysis and evaluation of the functionality of the upper limbs on the first day of
      treatment and after doing all sessions. The Student's t test will be used, with a
      significance level of 5 % to compare results obtained before and after treatment. After the
      tests, the Pearson correlation will also be made between the data obtained in soil and
      therapy pool. Thus, it is expected that Pilates can improve postural alignment and the
      breathable hemiparetic and the strengthening of specific muscles of the upper limbs assist in
      improving the functionality of them in their daily activities.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>October 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>muscle electrical activity before and after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The electrical activity of the postural muscles will be measured before and after treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>respiratory capacity before and after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured respiratory capacity of the participants (tidal volume, residual volume, etc.) before and after treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>higher functionality members before and after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured through a range of functionality, the functionality of the upper limbs of the subjects, seeking an improvement in their activities of daily living.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pilates Group Solo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>participate in this group 30 individuals who will be treated with the Pilates Method performing the exercises on the ground, using the Swiss ball and elastic bands. The exercises will aim to lengthen the musculature that are shortened due to the characteristic postural pattern of pathology (major and minor pectoral, shoulder adductors, biceps, wrist flexors, trunk side chain); strengthen the musculature that provide postural support (abdominal, middle trapezius, rhomboids, gluteus maximus, erector spinae and latissimus dorsi) and the upper limb musculature important for activities of daily living (triceps, biceps, internal rotators, external rotators and abductors of the shoulder).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Water Pilates Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>participate in this group 30 individuals who will be treated with the Pilates method, but doing the exercises in the therapy pool, with the aid of floats and weights. The protocol of stretches and exercises will work the same muscle groups than the G1, keeping the same decubitus whenever possible. The adaptations to the exercises are justified by the physical principles of water, which at one point may act for or against the activity being performed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mat Pilates</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Pilates Group Solo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Water Pilates</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Water Pilates Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Having suffered cerebrovascular accident for at least two years (chronic hemiparesis)
             with prevalence of upper limb (middle cerebral artery);

          -  Spasticity grade 1, 1 + 2 by the Modified Ashworth Scale;

          -  Good cognition;

          -  Get assume a standing position

          -  Sign the Consent form;

        Inclusion Criteria for Healthy individuals who will make up the control group:

          -  People who may be standing upright;

          -  Understand the activities that will be proposed

          -  Subscribe to the disclaimer conscentimento.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with severe cardiovascular disease;

          -  Patients with joint deformities;

          -  Patients with balance disorders;

          -  Patients with seizures;

          -  Patients with hypertension;

          -  Patients with uncontrolled diabetes;

          -  Individuals with a restriction in the liquid medium;

          -  Individuals with cognitive impairment that prevents an understanding of the proposed
             activities.

        Exclusion criteria for the control group:

          -  Individuals who do not meet the age range studied;

          -  Patients with uncontrolled hypertension and diabetes;

          -  Individuals with restrictions on liquid medium;

          -  Subjects with any neurological disorder;

          -  Individuals with severe respiratory diseases;

          -  Individuals who have been diagnosed with severe postural imbalance.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tamires de Souza Moreira Prianti</last_name>
    <phone>5512991394476</phone>
    <email>tamirescpv@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rehabilitation Engineering Laboratory of Sensory Motor</name>
      <address>
        <city>São José dos Campos</city>
        <state>São Paulo</state>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tamires de Souza Moreira Prianti</last_name>
      <phone>5512991394476</phone>
      <email>tamirescpv@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tamires de Souza Moreira Prianti</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 7, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 14, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 19, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 14, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 14, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 19, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Spastic hemiparesis</keyword>
  <keyword>Posture</keyword>
  <keyword>Pilates</keyword>
  <keyword>Respiratory Capacity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscle Spasticity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paresis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

