<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00050115</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>030051</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>03-H-0051</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00050115</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Collection of Biological Samples From Patients With Hepatitis-Associated Aplastic Anemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Collection of Blood, Stool, Bone Marrow and/or Tissue Samples From Subjects With Hepatitis-Associated Aplastic Anemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will collect samples of blood, stool, bone marrow, or other tissues from patients
      with hepatitis-associated aplastic anemia to investigate a possible association between
      exposure to viruses and the development of aplastic anemia in these patients. Cells from the
      samples obtained may be grown in the laboratory for future studies. Patients samples may be
      used to:

        -  Study abnormalities that occur in hepatitis-associated aplastic anemia;

        -  Test for various viruses;

        -  Test immune function;

        -  Measure factors related to the patients disease or diseases they may be at risk for;

        -  Evaluate the effectiveness of current therapies, refine treatment approaches, and
           identify potential new therapies;

        -  Identify possible measures for disease prevention;

        -  Identify possible genetic factors associated with hepatitis-associated aplastic anemia.

      Patients 2 years of age and older with severe aplastic anemia that developed within 6 months
      of an episode of hepatitis may be eligible for this study.

      Participants will complete questionnaires and provide tissue samples as described below.

      Questionnaires

      All patients (or another respondent for the patient) will fill out a questionnaire including
      demographic information (age, gender, race, ethnic group, education level, state of
      residence), current symptoms, medications, medical history, and history of possible exposures
      to toxins or viruses. A second questionnaire, which includes questions related to mental
      health, sexual behavior, alcohol and drug use, is optional for participants age 21 and older.
      These questionnaires are designed to uncover features of hepatitis-associated aplastic anemia
      and possibly reveal a common cause of the disease.

      Sample Collections

        -  Blood- will be collected at the time of the patient s initial evaluation or upon
           enrollment into the study and possibly periodically during the study. Blood will be
           drawn through a needle in an arm vein.

        -  Bone marrow- may be collected as part of the patient s standard medical care or
           specifically for research purposes of this study. For this procedure, the skin over the
           hipbone and the outer surface of the bone itself are numbed with an injection of a local
           anesthesia. Then, a larger needle is inserted into the hipbone and marrow is drawn into
           a syringe. Marrow cells are suctioned two to six times during the 15-minute procedure.

        -  Stool- will be provided by the patient.

      Liver- tissue may be biopsied as part of the patient s general medical care or for NIH
      patients, as part of their enrollment in a treatment protocol.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Our laboratory has a long-standing interest in viruses that affect the bone marrow,
      especially those causing bone marrow failure. One specific syndrome, hepatitis-associated
      aplastic anemia, suggests that the same agent is responsible for the severe and sometimes
      fulminate hepatitis as well as the profound bone marrow failure. This study is designed to
      collect clinical data, and samples from patients with hepatitis-associated aplastic anemia,
      in order to learn more about the clinical features of the disease, as well as to collect
      blood, liver, bone marrow and stool samples where possible for ongoing virological studies.
      For liver and bone marrow samples, material will only be obtained when the liver or bone
      marrow are biopsied for other medical indications, or during the removal of the liver at the
      time of transplantation. No additional risk to the patient should result from either
      procedure.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 18, 2002</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">9</enrollment>
  <condition>Aplastic Anemia</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA

        Presumptive clinical diagnosis of hepatitis-associated aplastic anemia. That is, aplastic
        anemia within 12 months of an episode of hepatitis

        Age equal to or greater than 2 years old

        Ability to comprehend the investigational nature of the study and provide informed consent.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

        Suspected cholestatic or obstructed liver disease

        Current diagnosis or past history of myelodysplastic syndrome, Fanconi s anemia,
        dyskeratosis congenita or other congenital forms of aplastic anemia.

        Diagnosis of Diamond-Blackfan anemia or a constitutional marrow failure disease.

        Underlying carcinoma, recent history of radiation or chemotherapy

        Age less than 2 years old
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Neal S Young, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2003-H-0051.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Böttiger LE, Westerholm B. Aplastic anaemia. 3. Aplastic anaemia and infectious hepatitis. Acta Med Scand. 1972 Oct;192(4):323-6.</citation>
    <PMID>5081070</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mary JY, Baumelou E, Guiguet M. Epidemiology of aplastic anemia in France: a prospective multicentric study. The French Cooperative Group for Epidemiological Study of Aplastic Anemia. Blood. 1990 Apr 15;75(8):1646-53.</citation>
    <PMID>2183887</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young NS, Issaragrasil S, Chieh CW, Takaku F. Aplastic anaemia in the Orient. Br J Haematol. 1986 Jan;62(1):1-6.</citation>
    <PMID>3942690</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 21, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 21, 2002</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 19, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 20, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 4, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bone Marrow Failure</keyword>
  <keyword>Seronegative Hepatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Fulminate Hepatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Aplastic Anemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis Associated Aplastic Anemia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Aplastic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

