<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00050362</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>030055</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>03-D-0055</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00050362</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rofecoxib and Bupivacaine to Prevent Pain After Third Molar (Wisdom Tooth) Extraction</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of a Long-Acting Local Anesthesia (Bupivacaine) and a Selective COX-2 Inhibitor (Rofecoxib) in Suppression of Central Sensitization</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (NIDCR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the ability of the drugs rofecoxib and bupivacaine to prevent pain
      following third molar (wisdom tooth) extraction. Rofecoxib is approved to treat pain of
      arthritis and menstrual cramps. Bupivacaine is a local anesthetic similar to lidocaine, but
      longer acting.

      Healthy normal volunteers between 16 and 35 years of age who are in general good health and
      require extraction of their two lower wisdom teeth may be eligible for this study.

      Participants will have their two lower wisdom teeth extracted, and a biopsy (removal of a
      small piece of tissue) will be taken from the inside of the cheek around the area behind one
      of the extraction sites. Ninety minutes before surgery, patients will take a dose of either
      rofecoxib, or a placebo (a pill with no active ingredient) by mouth. Just before surgery,
      they will receive an injection of either lidocaine or bupivacaine to numb the mouth and a
      sedative called midazolam (Versed® (Registered Trademark)) through an arm vein to cause
      drowsiness. After surgery, a small piece of tubing will be placed into one of the two
      extraction sites. Samples will be collected from the tubing to measure chemicals involved in
      pain and inflammation.

      Patients will remain in the clinic for up to 4 hours after surgery to monitor pain and drug
      side effects while the anesthetic wears off. During this time, they will complete pain
      questionnaires every 20 minutes. (Patients whose pain is unrelieved an hour after surgery may
      request and receive acetaminophen (Tylenol) and codeine.) The tubing then will be removed and
      they will be discharged with pain medicines (Tylenol, codeine and the study drug) and forms
      to record pain ratings. They will be given detailed instructions on how and when to take the
      medicines and how to record information in the pain diary.

      Patients will return to the clinic 48 hours after surgery with the pain diary and pain
      relievers. At this visit, another biopsy will be taken under local anesthetic (lidocaine).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Central sensitization refers to persistent post-injury changes in the central nervous system
      resulting in greater pain sensitivity. The concept of preemptive analgesia is defined as a
      treatment that prevents establishment of central sensitization by providing analgesic
      coverage during the perioperative period of surgery. Previous acute pain studies using the
      oral surgery model have shown that suppression of postoperative pain, not intra-operative
      nociceptive barrage, diminishes the development of sensitization at 24 to 48 hours
      post-surgery. During the intermediate postoperative period, the nociceptive input from both
      surgical insult and inflammation leads to central sensitization, yet their relative
      contributions have not been clearly evaluated. The proposed study is designed to evaluate the
      relative impact of surgical insult and the subsequent inflammation on postoperative pain. The
      relative contribution of each of these nociceptive processes provides a basis for
      postoperative pain management and the development of preemptive strategies.

      All subjects (N = 136) will be healthy volunteers scheduled for third molar extractions.
      Using a double-blinded, randomized, parallel study design, subjects will be randomized into
      four groups. All patients will receive local anesthesia injections preoperatively (either 2%
      lidocaine or 0.5% bupivacaine) to manage surgical pain in conjunction with a preemptive
      medication (either 50 mg of rofecoxib or placebo) to control postoperative inflammation. The
      first dose of preemptive medication will be taken by mouth 90 minutes prior to conscious
      sedation and extractions, and later self-administered once a day for the next 48 hours. The
      analgesic effect of the drugs will be assessed in the clinic every 20 minutes for the first
      four hours after extractions, and then self-assessed at 24, and 48 hours after surgery using
      two pain intensity assessment instruments: category scale and visual analog scale (VAS).
      Microdialysis will be performed with sample collection concurrent with pain report over the
      immediate postoperative period of four hours. Two biopsies will be performed: preoperatively,
      and postoperatively at 48 hours. The combination regimen with bupivacaine and rofecoxib is
      predicted to maximally suppress the onset and intensity of postoperative dental pain to a
      greater extent than all other groups through a blockade of the nociceptive input from both
      surgery and inflammation. It is hypothesized that this preemptive treatment will maximally
      inhibit the development of central sensitization following tissue injury which manifests as
      hyperalgesia at later time points. It is also hypothesized that the administration of
      rofecoxib (a cyclooxygenase-2 selective anti-inflammatory medication) will reduce
      post-surgical pain experienced at later time points to a greater extent than suppression of
      the intra-operative nociceptive barrage alone (by bupivacaine), suggesting that suppression
      of inflammation plays a more pivotal role than attenuating nociception due to tissue injury
      in diminishing central sensitization.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date>October 2004</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment>136</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Tooth Extraction</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rofecoxib and Bupivacaine</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Male or female volunteers referred for third molar extraction willing to undergo 3 visits:
        1 screening visit, 1 surgical appointment, and 1 follow-up research-related appointment.

        Between the ages of 16-35 years (based upon eruption patterns and age-related complications
        associated with surgical extraction of third molars).

        In general good health-American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA) status I or II (healthy
        subjects based upon criteria for safe administration of out-patient conscious sedation).

        Willing to undergo observation period for four hours postoperatively.

        Willing to complete a 100 mm visual analog scale and a category scale every 20 minutes for
        the first 4 postoperative hours, and later at 24 and 48 hours.

        Willing to have a microdialysis probe placed beneath the surgical flap over the first 4
        hours post-surgery.

        Willing to have a preoperative biopsy on the day of surgery and a postoperative biopsy at
        48 hours.

        Willing to return 48 hours post-operation to turn in completed pain diaries and for the
        postoperative biopsy.

        Must have two lower partial (rating&amp;eq;3) or fully impacted (rating&amp;eq;4) wisdom teeth
        (mandibular third molars).

        As assessed at the screening visit, the sum of the mandibular third molar surgical
        difficulty ratings must be between 6 to 8 in order to evaluate subjects experiencing
        similar pain levels.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Allergy to aspirin, NSAIDs, or sulfites, amide anesthetics.

        Pregnant or lactating females.

        History of peptic ulcers and/or GI bleeding.

        Chronic use of medications confounding the assessment of the inflammatory response or
        analgesia, for example, NSAIDS, COX-2 inhibitors, antihistamines, steroids,
        antidepressants.

        Presence of a clinical sign suggestive of infection, inflammation or pre-existing pain.

        Unusual surgical difficulty (determined from panoramic radiograph or during the actual
        surgery.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute of Dental And Craniofacial Research (NIDCR)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Woolf CJ. Evidence for a central component of post-injury pain hypersensitivity. Nature. 1983 Dec 15-21;306(5944):686-8.</citation>
    <PMID>6656869</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Woolf CJ, Wall PD. Morphine-sensitive and morphine-insensitive actions of C-fibre input on the rat spinal cord. Neurosci Lett. 1986 Feb 28;64(2):221-5.</citation>
    <PMID>3960401</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cook AJ, Woolf CJ, Wall PD, McMahon SB. Dynamic receptive field plasticity in rat spinal cord dorsal horn following C-primary afferent input. Nature. 1987 Jan 8-14;325(7000):151-3.</citation>
    <PMID>3808072</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 2004</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 4, 2002</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 4, 2002</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 5, 2002</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>NSAID</keyword>
  <keyword>Oral Surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Hyperalgesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Preemptive Analgesia</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bupivacaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rofecoxib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

