<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00054821</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P50AR048939</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P50AR048939</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NIAMS-082</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00054821</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prevention of Post-Traumatic Osteoarthritis (OA)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pathogenesis-Prevention of Post-Traumatic Osteoarthritis (OA): Effects of Distraction and Motion on OA</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ned Amendola</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases (NIAMS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Iowa</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Joint injury and trauma dramatically increase the risk of developing osteoarthritis (OA). The
      purpose of this study is to determine what factors lead to decreased pain, improved joint
      function, and repair of the joint surface in post-traumatic OA.

      Study hypotheses: 1) Ankle motion during distraction will result in clinically significant
      improvements in Ankle Osteoarthritis Scale scores, SF-36 scores, and improved cartilage
      thickness distribution over the habitually most heavily loaded portion of the articular
      surface, as compared to the use of distraction without ankle motion. 2a) Ankles with low
      geometric surface irregularity and greater range of motion will have better preservation of
      neo-chondroid tissue (increased normalized cartilage thickness and reduced longitudinal
      compressive strain in the habitually heavily regions of the articular surface) than those
      with high surface irregularity. 2b) Low geometric surface irregularity and greater range of
      motion will have reduced habitual focal or regional contact stress elevation. 3) Joints that
      have better improvements in Ankle Osteoarthritis Scale scores and improved cartilage
      thickness distribution over habitually heavily loaded portion of the articular surface will
      have improved normalization of synovial fluid markers of biosynthetic/degradative activity
      and oxidative stress.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Little work has been done on the pathogenesis and prevention of post-traumatic OA. The human
      ankle joint provides a unique opportunity for the study of post-traumatic OA because of the
      low risk of primary OA and the relatively high risk of post-traumatic OA. This study involves
      a multidisciplinary approach utilizing both laboratory and clinical research to improve
      understanding of OA and to develop innovative approaches for preventing and treating this
      disease. Mechanical distraction involves operative placement of specialized pins and rods to
      hold the joint in place. Some distraction allows for limited motion of the joint, while other
      distraction holds the joint immobile. The purpose of this study is to elucidate the
      mechanical factors that lead to restoration of a cartilaginous articular surface, decreased
      pain, and improved joint function after mechanical distraction of osteoarthritic joints.

      Participants in this study will be randomly assigned to one of two treatment groups. Group A
      will be treated with mechanical distraction with motion; Group B will be treated with
      mechanical distraction without motion. Participants will be followed for 28 months and will
      have 11 study visits. Most of the study visits will occur during the first half of the study.
      State-of-the-art techniques for clinical assessment, articular surface imaging, biomechanical
      modeling, and biochemical testing will be used in this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ankle Osteoarthritis Scale scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>CT data to measure cartilage distribution over the articular surface and synovial fluid markers of biosynthetic/degradative activity and oxidative stress in response to treatment and comparison to clinical and radiographic changes</measure>
    <time_frame>Two years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Improved joint function</measure>
    <time_frame>Two Years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group A participants will be treated with mechanical distraction with motion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group B participants will be treated with mechanical distraction without motion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ankle distraction permitting motion</intervention_name>
    <description>External fixator is applied to ankle joint for 85 - 95 days; ankle motion is permitted</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ankle distraction without motion</intervention_name>
    <description>External fixator is applied to ankel joint for 85 - 95 days; ankle motion is not permitted</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Symptomatic isolated ankle OA (unilateral Kellgren grade 3, 4, or 5)

          -  Skeletally mature (children included if they have no open growth plates)

          -  Failure of less than 1 year nonoperative treatment, including 3 months of continuous
             treatment with nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory agents and 3 months of unloading
             treatment (i.e., unloading brace, crutches, cane, walker)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph A. Buckwalter, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Iowa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas D. Brown, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Iowa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Orthopedics and Rehabilitation, University of Iowa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iowa City</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>52242</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buckwalter JA. Sports, joint injury, and posttraumatic osteoarthritis. J Orthop Sports Phys Ther. 2003 Oct;33(10):578-88. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14620787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buckwalter JA, Brown TD. Joint injury, repair, and remodeling: roles in post-traumatic osteoarthritis. Clin Orthop Relat Res. 2004 Jun;(423):7-16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15232420</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 11, 2003</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 12, 2003</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 13, 2003</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 16, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 16, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Iowa</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ned Amendola</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Osteoarthritis, Ankle</keyword>
  <keyword>Ankle Distraction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

