<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02617173</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SHEBA-15-2514-GR-CTIL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02617173</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Low Electrical Current on Testicular Spermatocyte Count</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Low Electrical Current on Testicular Spermatocyte Count</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sheba Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sheba Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Oligozoospermia, refers to a low concentration of sperm. A low sperm count or poor sperm
      quality is the cause of infertility in about 20% of couples with fertility problems, and a
      contributory factor in a further 25% of couples. In the majority of cases, no cause can be
      found. For mild male infertility, intra uterine insemination (IUI) is the procedure of choice
      with a pregnancy rate of 6.5%. In IUI, sperm is inserted using a thin, flexible catheter
      directly into a woman's uterus.

      Azoospermia affects 1% of the male population and 20% of male infertility situations. Over
      50% of azoospermic cases are due to testicular failure, including absence or failed
      production as well as low production and maturation arrest during the process of
      spermatogenesis. ICSI allows successful fertilization even with immature sperm obtained
      directly from testicular tissue. This is done through TESA (Testicular sperm aspiration) or
      TESE (Testicular sperm extraction). In cases of TESE small strips of testicular tissue are
      extracted with the intention of finding few viable sperm cells to be used for IVF or ICSI.
      Men with non-obstructive azoospermia have 0 to 3 mature spermatids per seminiferous tubule in
      contrast to 17-35 mature spermatids in men with normal spermatogenesis. TESE success rates
      are approximately 50% but differ according to etiology. Unfortunately, there is no method of
      pointing out where sperm may be found. TESE is accompanied with pain, tissue loss, reduced
      success in future TESE due to tissue scaring and testosterone deficiency.

      The complex process of spermatogenesis includes maturation of young spermatids into
      spermatozoas, a process which takes approximately 74 days. During spermatogenesis,
      spermatogonial stem cells are transformed into spermatids and released from the seminiferous
      tubule epithelium into its lumen. Non-motile spermatozoa are transported through the
      seminifreous tubules to the epididymis by testicular fluid secreted from the Sertoli cells
      with the aid of peristaltic contraction. During transport through the epididymis, sperm cells
      develop the ability to progress forward, undergo capacitation and attach and penetrate the
      egg.

      The electric charge of the spermatic cell has been termed zeta potential (electrokinetic
      potential) and is defined as the electric potential in the slip plane between the sperm
      membrane and its surroundings. Mature sperm possess an electric charge of −16 to −20 mV.

      In the animal study conducted, positive electrical current with a low amplitude bellow
      sensation level was situated around the scrotum of four normospermic and one oligospermic
      male pigs. At the end of the research the concentration of spermatocytes in the epididymis
      obtained in surgery was found to be 200 to 1600 percent above the baseline.

      Our intention is to evaluate if positive electrical current with a low amplitude bellow
      sensation level situated on the scrotum will increase the concentration of spermatocytes in
      the ejaculate.

      If our hypothesis is confirmed this may become a method for treating male infertility. The
      period of improvement is still unclear.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>November 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Spermatomcyte count in the ejaculate.</measure>
    <time_frame>One year.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate if positive electrical current with a low amplitude below sensation level situated on the scrotum will increase the concentration of spermatocytes in the ejaculate.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Oligozoospermia</condition>
  <condition>Azoospermia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Low current electrical stimulator</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Micro 400 Matrix Therapy Products</intervention_name>
    <description>Positive electrical current with a low amplitude bellow sensation level situated on the scrotum.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men with primary infertility defined as a state of Azoospermia.

          -  Men with pathological sperm tests indices as defined by the WHO.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Men with genetic syndromes, and states of Azoospermia secondary to chemotherapy, bone
             marrow transplantation or radiation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gil Raviv, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Urology Department, Sheba Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Gil Raviv, Prof</last_name>
    <phone>972-52-666-8285</phone>
    <email>Gil.Raviv@sheba.health.gov.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Male Fertility Clinic, Sheba Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ramat Gan</city>
        <zip>5265601</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gil Raviv, Prof</last_name>
      <phone>972-52-666-8285</phone>
      <email>Gil.Raviv@sheba.health.gov.il</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Shashar, Dr</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ishijima SA, Okuno M, Mohri H. Zeta potential of human X- and Y-bearing sperm. Int J Androl. 1991 Oct;14(5):340-7.</citation>
    <PMID>1794918</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chan PJ, Jacobson JD, Corselli JU, Patton WC. A simple zeta method for sperm selection based on membrane charge. Fertil Steril. 2006 Feb;85(2):481-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16595231</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 22, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 26, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 30, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 26, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 26, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 30, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Azoospermia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oligospermia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

