<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02616302</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TAK-390MR_204</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2014-004506-15</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1166-8748</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02616302</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 2 Study of Dexlansoprazole Delayed-Release Capsules to Treat Symptomatic Nonerosive Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease in Pediatric Subjects Aged 1 to 11 Years</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2, Double-Blind, 12 Week, Multicenter Study to Assess the Safety and Effectiveness of Daily Oral Administration of Dexlansoprazole Delayed-Release Capsules in Pediatric Subjects Aged 1 to 11 Years With Symptomatic Nonerosive Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the safety and effectiveness of treatment with once
      daily (QD) oral administration of dexlansoprazole capsules (15, 30, and 60 mg) in pediatric
      participants aged 1 to 11 years with symptomatic nonerosive gastroesophageal reflux disease
      (GERD).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The drug being tested in this study is called dexlansoprazole. Dexlansoprazole is being
      tested to treat children aged 1 to 11 years who have nonerosive gastroesophageal reflux
      disease (GERD). This study will look at the effectiveness and side effects of three different
      doses of dexlansoprazole in children with GERD.

      The study will enroll approximately 80 patients. Participants weighing ≤30 kg will be
      randomly assigned (by chance, like flipping a coin) to receive dexlansoprazole 15 or 30 mg,
      and participants who weigh &gt;30 kg will be randomized to receive dexlansoprazole 30 or 60 mg.

      All participants will be asked to take one capsule at the same time each day throughout the
      study. Parents/caregivers for participants ages 1 to 8 and participants ages 9 to 11 will be
      asked to record any time they have heartburn symptoms in an electronic diary.

      This multi-center trial will be conducted worldwide. The overall time to participate in this
      study is up to 16 weeks, which includes up to 4 weeks to screen for the study. Participants
      will make multiple visits to the clinic, plus a final phone call 5 to 10 days after last dose
      of study drug for a follow-up assessment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study start date has been delayed.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">November 1, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 13, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 13, 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Days Without Hurting or Burning in the Stomach, Chest or Throat Over the 12 Weeks of Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Daily electronic diaries (eDiaries) will be completed which contain Pediatric Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease Symptom Daily Diaries (PGSDD) questionnaires that document presence or absence of hurting or burning in the stomach, chest or throat vomiting, regurgitation and trouble eating. Parents or caregivers of participants aged 1 to 8 years will complete the PGSDD (parent) in the eDiary for their child and participants aged 9 to 11 years will complete PGSDD (child) in the eDiary themselves. The eDiaries will be completed on a daily basis reflecting a continuous 24-hour period.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Hetzel-Dent (HD) Grade 0 at Week 12 Among Participants With HD Classification Scale Grade 1 and Histologic Features of Reflux Esophagitis (HFRE) Grade ≤2 at Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Week 12</time_frame>
    <description>HD classification scoring: Grade 0=Macroscopically normal esophageal mucosa; Grade 1=No macroscopic erosions visible but erythema, hyperemia, and/or friability may be present; Grade 2=Superficial erosions or ulcers involving &lt;10% of mucosa of distal 5 cm of esophageal squamous mucosa; Grade 3=Superficial erosions or ulcers involving 10% to 50% of mucosal surface of distal 5 cm of esophageal squamous mucosa; Grade 4=Deep ulcers anywhere in esophagus or confluent erosion or ulceration of &gt;50% of mucosal surface of distal 5 cm of esophageal squamous mucosa.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Days Without Hurting or Burning in the Stomach, Chest or Throat in Children Aged 9 to 11 Years Over the 12 Weeks of Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Daily electronic diaries (eDiaries) will be completed which contain Pediatric Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease Symptom Daily Diaries (PGSDD) questionnaires that document presence or absence of hurting or burning in the stomach, chest or throat vomiting, regurgitation and trouble eating. Parents or caregivers of participants aged 1 to 8 years will complete the PGSDD (parent) in the eDiary for their child and participants aged 9 to 11 years will complete PGSDD (child) in the eDiary themselves. The eDiaries will be completed on a daily basis reflecting a continuous 24-hour period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Days Without Hurting or Burning in the Stomach, Chest or Throat in Children Aged 1 to 8 Years Over the 12 Weeks of Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Daily electronic diaries (eDiaries) will be completed which contain Pediatric Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease Symptom Daily Diaries (PGSDD) questionnaires that document presence or absence of hurting or burning in the stomach, chest or throat vomiting, regurgitation and trouble eating. Parents or caregivers of participants aged 1 to 8 years will complete the PGSDD (parent) in the eDiary for their child and participants aged 9 to 11 years will complete PGSDD (child) in the eDiary themselves. The eDiaries will be completed on a daily basis reflecting a continuous 24-hour period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Days Without Vomiting Over the 12 Weeks of Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Daily electronic diaries (eDiaries) will be completed which contain Pediatric Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease Symptom Daily Diaries (PGSDD) questionnaires that document presence or absence of hurting or burning in the stomach, chest or throat vomiting, regurgitation and trouble eating. Parents or caregivers of participants aged 1 to 8 years will complete the PGSDD (parent) in the eDiary for their child and participants aged 9 to 11 years will complete PGSDD (child) in the eDiary themselves. The eDiaries will be completed on a daily basis reflecting a continuous 24-hour period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Days Food Did Not Come Up from Stomach to Mouth Over the 12 Weeks of Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Daily electronic diaries (eDiaries) will be completed which contain Pediatric Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease Symptom Daily Diaries (PGSDD) questionnaires that document presence or absence of hurting or burning in the stomach, chest or throat vomiting, regurgitation and trouble eating. Parents or caregivers of participants aged 1 to 8 years will complete the PGSDD (parent) in the eDiary for their child and participants aged 9 to 11 years will complete PGSDD (child) in the eDiary themselves. The eDiaries will be completed on a daily basis reflecting a continuous 24-hour period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Days Without Trouble Eating Over the 12 Weeks of Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Daily electronic diaries (eDiaries) will be completed which contain Pediatric Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease Symptom Daily Diaries (PGSDD) questionnaires that document presence or absence of hurting or burning in the stomach, chest or throat vomiting, regurgitation and trouble eating. Parents or caregivers of participants aged 1 to 8 years will complete the PGSDD (parent) in the eDiary for their child and participants aged 9 to 11 years will complete PGSDD (child) in the eDiary themselves. The eDiaries will be completed on a daily basis reflecting a continuous 24-hour period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">80</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastroesophageal Reflux</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>≤30 kg: Dexlansoprazole 15 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dexlansoprazole 15 mg, capsules, once, daily, for 12 weeks. Participants weigh ≤30 kg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>≤30 kg: Dexlansoprazole 30 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dexlansoprazole 30 mg, capsules, once, daily, for 12 weeks. Participants weigh ≤30 kg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>&gt;30 kg: Dexlansoprazole 30 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dexlansoprazole 30 mg, capsules, once, daily, for 12 weeks. Participants weigh &gt;30 kg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>&gt;30 kg: Dexlansoprazole 60 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dexlansoprazole 60 mg, capsules, once, daily, for 12 weeks. Participants weigh &gt;30 kg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexlansoprazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Dexlansoprazole 15 mg, 30 mg, and 60 mg capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>≤30 kg: Dexlansoprazole 15 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>≤30 kg: Dexlansoprazole 30 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>&gt;30 kg: Dexlansoprazole 30 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>&gt;30 kg: Dexlansoprazole 60 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dexilant</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. In the opinion of the investigator, the participant (as age appropriate) and/or
             parent(s)/legal guardian is capable of understanding and complying with protocol
             requirements.

          2. Prior to any study-specific procedures being performed, the informed consent and the
             assent form (as applicable) must be signed and dated by parent(s) or legal guardian
             and by the participant respectively, if appropriate.

          3. Has a medical history of symptoms of gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD) for at
             least 3 months prior to Screening.

          4. Has a medical history of at least 1 failed attempted withdrawal of prior proton pump
             inhibitor (PPI)/acid suppressive therapy and a return of symptoms upon withdrawal.

          5. Has met the electronic diary (eDiary) qualification criteria as assessed by the
             Pediatric Gastroesophageal Reflux Disease Symptom Daily Diaries (PGSDD), defined as
             hurting or burning in the stomach, chest, or throat on at least 3 of any 7 consecutive
             days during the Screening Period.

          6. Has either (1) a positive endoscopy with both a Hetzel-Dent (HD) Grade 1 and a
             Histologic Features of Reflux Esophagitis (HFRE) Scale Grade &lt;2, OR (2) an endoscopy
             with HD Grade 0 and a documented pH-metry suggestive of acid-related disease. The
             pH-metry should be performed during Screening or within 6 months of signing informed
             consent and assent (as applicable) for GERD symptoms. An endoscopy performed within 1
             week prior to signing informed consent and assent (as applicable), is an acceptable
             replacement for the screening endoscopy if GERD is documented by the HD classification
             scale criterion previously described, protocol-required biopsies were collected and
             endoscopic pictures were obtained.

          7. Is male or female and age 1 to 11 years inclusive at Screening.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Has evidence of cardiovascular, pulmonary, central nervous system, hepatic,
             hematopoietic, renal, or metabolic disorder, severe allergy, asthma, or allergic skin
             rash that suggests any uncontrolled, clinically significant underlying disease or
             condition (other than the disease being studied), which may impact the ability of the
             participant to participate or potentially confound the study results.

          2. Has a coexisting disease affecting the esophagus (eg, esophageal varices, scleroderma,
             viral or fungal infection, or esophageal stricture), history of radiation therapy or
             cryotherapy to the esophagus, caustic or physiochemical trauma such as sclerotherapy
             to the esophagus.

          3. Has any findings in his/her medical history, physical examination, or safety clinical
             laboratory tests giving reasonable suspicion of underlying disease that might
             interfere with the conduct of the trial.

          4. Has a history of hypersensitivity or allergies to dexlansoprazole, any component of
             dexlansoprazole or any PPI (including lansoprazole, omeprazole, rabeprazole,
             pantoprazole, or esomeprazole) or antacids.

          5. Is required to take excluded medications or it is anticipated that the participant
             will require treatment with at least 1 of the disallowed concomitant medications
             during the study evaluation period.

          6. Has a condition that may require inpatient surgery during the course of the study.

          7. Has known history of Barrett's esophagus with dysplastic changes in the esophagus.

          8. Has history of eosinophilic esophagitis (EoE) endoscopic or histologic findings
             suggestive of EoE (&gt;15 eosinophils per high-powered field [HPF])

          9. Has history of celiac disease, tests positive for tissue transglutaminase (tTG)
             antibody or confirmed disease by histology.

         10. Has history of inflammatory bowel disease, or irritable bowel syndrome.

         11. Has active gastric or duodenal ulcers within 4 weeks prior to Day -1.

         12. Requires dilatation of esophageal strictures and/or strictures preventing passage of
             the endoscope during the screening endoscopy. Schatzki's ring (a ring of mucosal
             tissue near the lower esophageal sphincter) is acceptable.

         13. A female participant who has reached menarche.

         14. Is known to be positive for the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV).

         15. Has current or historical evidence of Zollinger-Ellison syndrome or other
             hypersecretory condition.

         16. Has a history of gastric, duodenal, or esophageal surgery except simple oversew of an
             ulcer. A history of gastric tube and/or percutaneous endoscopic gastrostomy (PEG)
             placement is allowed.

         17. Had an acute upper gastrointestinal hemorrhage within 4 weeks prior to endoscopy.

         18. Has donated or lost &gt;10% of the total blood volume, undergone plasmapheresis, or has
             had a transfusion of any blood product within 90 days prior to the first dose of study
             drug.

         19. Has a known history of alcohol abuse or illegal drug use within the past 12 months
             prior to the first dose of study drug.

         20. Has any screening abnormal laboratory value that suggests a clinically significant
             underlying disease or condition that may prevent the participant from entering the
             study; or the participant has: creatinine &gt;1.5 mg/dL, alanine aminotransferase (ALT)
             and/or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &gt;2 times the upper limit of normal (×ULN), or
             total bilirubin &gt;2.0 mg/dL with AST/ALT elevated above the limits of normal values.

         21. Is an immediate family member, study site employee, or is in a dependent relationship
             with a study site employee who is involved in the conduct of this study or may consent
             and assent (as applicable) under duress. Students of the institution/research facility
             who are under the supervision of, or in a subordinate role to, the investigator are
             also ineligible.

         22. The participant, in the opinion of the investigator, is unlikely to comply with the
             protocol or is unsuitable for any other reason.

         23. Has participated in another clinical study and/or has received any investigational
             compound within 30 days prior to Screening.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Director Clinical Science</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Louisville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Louisville</city>
        <state>Kentucky</state>
        <zip>40202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>Brazil</country>
    <country>Israel</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Mexico</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Portugal</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 24, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 24, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 26, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gastroesophageal Reflux</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexlansoprazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lansoprazole</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

