<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02617381</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>K140901</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02617381</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pre-operative Haemorrhagic Risk Screening, Using a Standardized Questionnaire Before Scheduled Surgeries</brief_title>
  <acronym>HEMORISQ</acronym>
  <official_title>Pre-operative Haemorrhagic Risk Screening, Using a Standardized Questionnaire Before Scheduled Surgeries.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      &quot;This is not a validation study of a questionnaire. This is a multicenter diagnostic study,
      assessing the sensitivity and specificity of a simple structured questionnaire, to identify
      patients requiring further haemostatic investigations, in pre-operative patients. This study
      will also allow for the assessment of the sensitivity and specificity of the routine care
      strategy.

      All patients are recruited during the pre-anaesthesia visit by an anaesthesiologist, in
      different anaesthetic sectors each day of the week, so that different types of surgery are
      represented.

      Each day (from Monday to Friday), the first 2 eligible patients will be offered to take part
      in the study.

      Routine care strategy is not modified by the study protocol. In addition, the simple
      structured questionnaire will be completed by the patient with a research assistant after the
      pre-operative consultation As recommended in diagnostic studies, the gold standard (see
      secondary endpoint paragraph) will be performed consistently in all patients to avoid
      verification bias.

      The improvement of screening for the need of further investigations by use of the
      questionnaire compared to routine care will be measured counting how many patients are
      adequately reclassified with the questionnaire compared to the routine care strategy,
      regarding the gold standard (using the Net Reclassification Index).&quot;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      &quot;Screening for the need of an extensive haematological investigation in order to determine
      the existence of inherited or acquired haemostatic abnormalities at the pre-anaesthesia visit
      is part of a routinely used strategy to prevent perioperative haemorrhagic complications. In
      France, this screening is mainly based on a basic set of haemostatic tests: prothrombin time
      (PT), activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) and platelet count (PC). When these tests
      are abnormal, the patient may undergo a more complete set of haemostatic tests and, if
      needed, be referred to a haematologist for advice. Nevertheless, all published studies have
      pointed out the scarce efficacy of preoperative PT/aPTT/PC testing for hemorrhagic risk
      assessment.

      Therefore, in 2011 several professional societies have advised AGAINST using this strategy
      and advocated its replacement by a structured questionnaire for the screening of the need of
      further haemostatic investigations (to validate or not an increased risk of perioperative
      haemorrhage). Nevertheless, the performance of a screening strategy relying on such a
      structured questionnaire has never been studied in the pre-anaesthesia context. This probably
      explains why many anaesthesiologists still continue to prescribe PT/aPTT/PC to detect
      haemostatic abnormalities and don't use any questionnaire.

      Thus, our hypothesis is that a validated structured and simple questionnaire is an accurate
      screening strategy to determine patients requiring further haemostatic investigations in the
      preoperative setting.

      One of the main reasons for the non compliance with the guidance advising against the use of
      screening haemostatic tests (PT/aPTT/PC) for the identification of patients with potential
      haemorrhagic risk is probably related to the fact that the alternative strategy proposed to
      anaesthesiologists (the use of a structured questionnaire) has never been investigated before
      in the context of the pre-anaesthesia visit. Therefore, the present project would estimate
      the diagnostic performance (sensitivity and specificity) of a simple structured questionnaire
      to identify patients requiring further haemostatic investigations (i.e. patients for whom
      further haemostatic investigations would conclude to an increase haemorrhagic risk). The
      innovative approach of the project is related to: (i) the choice of a simple structured
      questionnaire, specifically conceived to be used at the pre-anaesthesia visit; (ii) a study
      design that takes into account the needs of the final users (the anaesthesiologist and the
      surgical team).

      To estimate the diagnostic accuracy of a questionnaire at the pre-anaesthesia visit, to
      identify patients requiring further haemostatic investigations for haemorrhagic risk
      assessment as defined by a full haemostatic investigation (i.e. patients for whom full
      haemostatic investigations would conclude to an increase haemorrhagic risk)

        -  To estimate the diagnostic accuracy (specificity, sensibility and likelihood ratios) of
           the current routine care strategy at the pre-anaesthesia visit (i.e. no structured
           questionnaire, and prescription of further haematological tests at the sole discretion
           of the anaesthesiologist) to identify patients requiring further haemostatic
           investigations for HgR as defined by the gold standard (a full haemostatic
           investigation).

        -  To measure the improvement in the identification of patients requiring further
           haemostatic investigations for HgR assessment using a simple structured questionnaire,
           compared to usual care, in pre-operative patients (i.e. to describe how many patients
           are adequately reclassified by using the questionnaire).

        -  To describe how many patients had a major peri-operative bleeding event with respect to
           the answers to the simple structured questionnaire.&quot;
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 25, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Simple structured questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>To estimate the diagnostic accuracy (specificity, sensibility and likelihood ratios) of a simple structured questionnaire at the pre-anaesthesia visit, to identify patients requiring further haemostatic investigations for haemorrhagic risk (HgR) assessment as defined by the gold standard (a full haemostatic investigation), i.e. patients for whom further haemostatic investigations would conclude to an increase haemorrhagic risk.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of the Net Reclassification Improvement Index (NRI)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The diagnostic classification provided by the strategy based on the questionnaire compared to that based on hemostasis screening tests will be evaluated by Net Reclassification Improvement Index (NRI)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1500</enrollment>
  <condition>Pre-operative Haemorrhagic Risk</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>questionnaire</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>assessing the sensitivity and specificity of a simple structured questionnaire</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>questionnaire</intervention_name>
    <description>assessing the sensitivity and specificity of a simple structured questionnaire</description>
    <arm_group_label>questionnaire</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients seen at the pre-anaesthesia visit by an anaesthesiologist before any
             scheduled intervention (except for cardiac, vascular, hepatic, obstetrical surgery,
             since these procedures are associated with a high HgR; neurosurgery is also excluded,
             due to fatal or functional consequences in case of small volume blood loss).

          -  Age &gt; 18 years

          -  Signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients under long term antiplatelet and/or anticoagulant therapy

          -  Not French speaker

          -  Not affiliated to any social security covering
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dan LONGROIS, Pr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hopital Bichat-Claude Bernard</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75018</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 19, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 25, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 1, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

