<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02611128</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17633</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P50HD028934</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02611128</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Urinary DENND1A.V2 as a Predictor of Pubertal Hyperandrogenemia</brief_title>
  <acronym>DENND1A</acronym>
  <official_title>Urinary DENND1A.V2 as a Predictor of Pubertal Hyperandrogenemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Virginia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Penn State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Virginia Commonwealth University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Virginia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS) is a common disorder marked by hyperandrogenism,
      oligo-/anovulation, and subfertility. The precise causes of PCOS are unclear, but the
      pathophysiology involves complex genetic and environmental influences. Importantly, not all
      girls with obesity have HA, and free testosterone (T) concentrations are highly variable in
      this group. Luteinizing hormone (LH) and insulin concentrations are significant but only
      partial predictors of free T in girls with obesity; significant unexplained variability in
      free T suggests that additional factors contribute to HA in this population. Abnormalities of
      ovarian and adrenal steroidogenesis are likely contributors in this regard, but such
      abnormalities are difficult to quantify. Recent Genome Wide Association Studies have
      identified DENND1A as a PCOS susceptibility gene candidate. Preliminary in vitro data
      strongly implicate a DENND1A splice variant called DENND1A Variant 2 (DENND1A.V2) as a
      contributor to excessive theca cell androgen production in PCOS. The investigators' primary
      goal with the proposed pilot study is to determine the relationship between urinary exosomal
      DENND1A.V2 mRNA and free T concentrations in peripubertal girls. The investigators
      hypothesize that urinary exosomal DENND1A.V2 mRNA quantity is a significant and independent
      predictor of peripubertal hyperandrogenemia. In this study, the investigators will carefully
      phenotype peripubertal girls with and without hyperandrogenemia (primarily in the form of
      hormonal, maturational, and anthropometric measurements) in addition to measuring urinary
      exosomal DENND1A.V2 mRNA. As a primary analysis, the investigators will examine the
      relationship between morning free testosterone and urinary exosomal DENND1A.V2, controlling
      for previously-described partial predictors of free testosterone (LH, insulin) in addition to
      potential confounders (BMI z-score, bone age). These studies will provide important
      information regarding the etiology of HA in peripubertal girls. Ultimately, these data may
      lead to a non-invasive test of ovarian/adrenal steroidogenic activity and support the
      development of a diagnostic test for PCOS in high-risk peripubertal girls (e.g., those with
      obesity).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To date, the mechanisms underlying excess androgen production from steroid producing tissues
      have been unclear, but recent Genome Wide Association Studies (GWAS) have provided additional
      data in this regard. Initial GWAS data in a Han Chinese population identified some 12 loci as
      potential PCOS susceptibility gene candidates. One of these loci, the DENND1A locus at
      9q22.32, has been replicated in GWAS studies in both Asian and European populations. Strauss
      and colleagues recently demonstrated DENND1A expression in testes, ovarian theca cells, and
      H295 adrenal carcinoma cells — all androgen producing tissues/cells. DENND1A is therefore an
      exceedingly strong PCOS susceptibility gene candidate. However, it remains unclear how
      DENND1A may contribute to the PCOS phenotype.

      Importantly, there are two transcriptional forms of the DENND1A gene — a consequence of
      alternate splicing. The larger transcript (DENND1A Variant 1, or DENND1A.V1) encodes a 1009
      amino acid protein, while the smaller transcript DENND1A.V2 encodes a truncated 559 amino
      acid. The product of DENND1A.V2 contains the DENN domain and a clathrin-binding domain, but
      differs from the product of DENND1A.V1 in two ways: (1) it does not contain the proline-rich
      C-terminal domain present in Variant 1, and (2) DENND1A.V2 results from differential splicing
      and contains a unique 33 amino acid C-terminal sequence. Of significant interest, published
      studies by Drs. McAllister and Strauss (McAllister JM, et al. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA.
      2014;111:E1519-27) strongly implicate the DENND1A.V2 splice variant as a contributor to
      excessive theca cell androgen production in PCOS:

        -  Expression of DENND1A.V2 protein in cultured theca cells isolated from women with PCOS
           was over 3-fold elevated compared to normal ovarian theca cells. Similarly, DENND1A.V2
           mRNA abundance was elevated in PCOS theca and correlated with increased theca cell
           androgen (dehydroepiandrosterone [DHEA]) production.

        -  Forced expression of DENND1A.V2 in normal theca cells increased expression of CYP17A1
           and CYP11A1 (genes for key steroidogenic enzymes) along with androgen/androgen precursor
           (e.g., 17OHP4, DHEA, testosterone) and progesterone production.

        -  Knockdown of DENND1A.V2 in cultured PCOS theca cells reduced CYP17A1 and CYP11A1
           expression in addition to 17OHP4 and DHEA production.

        -  Treatment of cultured PCOS theca cells with anti-DENND1A.V2 IgG antibodies reduced
           expression of CYP17A1 and CYP11A1 mRNA expression as well as DHEA and 17OHP4 synthesis.

      These data provide strong support to the contention that the DENND1A.V2 splice variant is a
      major factor underlying the phenotype of cultured PCOS theca cells and, thus, the etiology of
      ovarian hyperandrogenemia in PCOS. By extension, the DENND1A.V2 splice variant may be a
      significant contributor to peripubertal hyperandrogenemia, and it may explain much of the
      variable hyperandrogenemia observed in obese peripubertal girls. The investigators propose
      that, in some peripubertal girls, increased expression of DENND1A.V2 in ovarian and/or
      adrenal cells promotes excess androgen secretion with the advent of puberty (when ovarian
      stimulation by LH increases) and/or in the presence of obesity (e.g., enhanced insulin
      secretion, augmenting LH-stimulated ovarian androgen synthesis and/or ACTH-stimulated adrenal
      androgen synthesis).

      Of great interest, preliminary data from 5 normal women and 6 women with PCOS suggested that
      urinary exosomal DENND1A.V2 mRNA was approximately 3-fold elevated in women with PCOS
      compared to normally-cycling controls (McAllister JM, et al. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA.
      2014;111:E1519-27). Exosomes are small vesicles (40-100 nm) that contain nucleic acids shed
      by cells into blood and urine, and they are known to be a stable source of RNA. Thus, urinary
      exosomal DENND1A.V2 quantity may serve as a marker of DENND1A.V2 activity in the
      ovary/adrenal.

      In these proposed studies, the investigators (including collaborators Drs. McAllister and
      Strauss) will obtain urine for exosomal DENND1A.V2 mRNA quantitation in addition to blood
      samples to measure androgen levels, LH and insulin (the latter two previously-demonstrated to
      predict free testosterone). The investigators will test the hypothesis that the quantity of
      urinary exosomal DENND1A.V2 mRNA is a strong and independent predictor of androgen levels in
      peripubertal girls.

      To the investigators' knowledge, no data exist that tie a PCOS susceptibility gene candidate
      to pubertal hyperandrogenemia. The investigators propose to evaluate a novel biomarker
      (urinary exosomal DENND1A.V2 mRNA) as a predictor of free testosterone in pubertal girls.
      Evaluation of this biomarker in adolescents is highly innovative.

      The present proposal will build on Aim 3 of Project 1 (NIH P50 HD28934), in which the
      investigators carefully assess the determinants of hyperandrogenemia in girls with
      peripubertal obesity. Specifically, Aim 3 is an intensive protocol involving (a) overnight
      frequent blood sampling for LH and insulin along with (b) ovarian and adrenal stimulation
      protocols over the subsequent 2 days. Some of the subjects participating in this proposed
      pilot study will also participate in Aim 3. Correlation between urinary exosomal DENND1A.V2
      mRNA and ovarian/adrenal stimulation protocols will allow a preliminary assessment of urinary
      exosomal DENND1A.V2 mRNA as a non-invasive measure of ovarian/adrenal steroidogenesis — a
      potentially important clinical tool.

      Peripubertal girls with hyperandrogenemia are believed to be at high risk for developing
      adolescent/adult PCOS, but since the manifestations of PCOS can overlap with the findings of
      normal puberty, the diagnosis of PCOS may be unreliable until later adolescence. If urinary
      exosomal DENND1A.V2 mRNA is a significant predictor of hyperandrogenemia in this cohort,
      future studies will determine the utility of urinary exosomal DENND1A.V2 as a diagnostic test
      to predict the development of PCOS across puberty. This is an innovative and exceedingly
      exciting prospect that may have significant potential implications for at-risk girls.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary exosomal DENND1A.V2</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of study (the study involves one outpatient visit)</time_frame>
    <description>Urinary exosomal DENND1A.V2</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum free testosterone</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of study (the study involves one outpatient visit)</time_frame>
    <description>Calculated free testosterone</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bone age</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of study (the study involves one outpatient visit)</time_frame>
    <description>A measure of maturational stage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>BMI z-score</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of study (the study involves one outpatient visit)</time_frame>
    <description>Body mass index normalized for age and gender</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Morning luteinizing hormone</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of study (the study involves one outpatient visit)</time_frame>
    <description>Serum luteinizing hormone (LH) measured at same time as free testosterone and fasting insulin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fasting insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of study (the study involves one outpatient visit)</time_frame>
    <description>Serum insulin measured at same time as free testosterone and morning LH</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">65</enrollment>
  <condition>Polycystic Ovary Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Hyperandrogenism</condition>
  <condition>Puberty</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Peripubertal girls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Peripubertal girls with varying androgen concentrations will have careful phenotype/genotype assessment, primarily to assess the relationship between urinary exosomal DENND1A.V2 and serum free testosterone concentrations.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Phenotype/genotype assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>The investigators will perform careful phenotyping in addition to hormonal assessments and assessments of DENND1A</description>
    <arm_group_label>Peripubertal girls</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Optional sample banking for later genetic analysis: At the time of study, the investigators
      will request consent/assent to bank saliva samples for later genetic analysis (e.g., if
      additional highly-promising gene candidates for adolescent hyperandrogenemia/PCOS are
      identified). If subjects and parents do not provide assent/consent that would allow specimens
      to be banked for later genetic analysis, the samples and the means of linking specimens to
      data will be destroyed (once analysis for all participants is completed).
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Peripubertal girls, Tanner breast stages 1-5
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        List of Inclusion Criteria

        • Peripubertal girls, Tanner breast stages 1-5

        List of Exclusion Criteria

          -  Age &lt; 8 or &gt; 17 y

          -  Men and boys are excluded

          -  Inability to obtain proper consent/assent

          -  Atypical obesity

          -  Underweight: Underweight is defined as a BMI-for-age percentile &lt; 5

          -  Positive pregnancy test or lactation

          -  Assessment during the luteal phase as suggested by a serum progesterone ≥ 1.5 ng/ml

          -  Virilization or a total testosterone &gt; 150 ng/dl

          -  Excessively elevated DHEA-S: This will be defined as a DHEA-S &gt; 1.5 times the
             age-appropriate upper limit of normal

          -  Congenital adrenal hyperplasia (CAH)

          -  Cortisol deficiency/excess

          -  Inadequately-treated or unstable thyroid dysfunction

          -  Significant hyperprolactinemia: Since mild elevations may be seen in girls with
             hyperandrogenemia or PCOS, elevations up to 30 (i.e., 1.5 times the upper limit of
             normal) will be accepted in such girls

          -  Significant chronic medical history: This includes a significant history of cardiac or
             pulmonary dysfunction (e.g., known or suspected congestive heart failure; asthma
             requiring intermittent systemic corticosteroids; etc.); history of renal insufficiency
             or durable electrolyte abnormalities; or a history of substantial liver disease. A
             history of liver test abnormalities will be allowed in two circumstances: (1) mild
             bilirubin elevations will be accepted in the setting of known Gilbert's syndrome; (2)
             mild transaminase (ALT, AST) elevations may be seen in obese girls, so stable
             elevations &lt; 1.5 times the upper limit of normal will be accepted in this group.

          -  Uncontrolled type 2 diabetes mellitus: This will be reflected by a hemoglobin A1c &gt;
             7.0%. Subjects with impaired glucose tolerance or a diagnosis of type 2 diabetes that
             is well-controlled with lifestyle management alone will be allowed to participate.

          -  Type 1 diabetes mellitus: Since subjects with type 1 diabetes invariably require
             exogenous insulin, they will not be allowed to participate.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>8 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher McCartney, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Virginia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Melissa Gilrain</last_name>
    <phone>434-243-6911</phone>
    <email>pcos@virginia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Christopher McCartney, MD</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Research in Reproduction</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charlottesville</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22908</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Melissa Gilrain</last_name>
      <phone>434-243-6911</phone>
      <email>pcos@virginia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christopher R McCartney, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>John C Marshall, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jan McAllister, PhD (Penn State)</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Jerome Strauss, MD, PhD (VCU)</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 12, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 18, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 20, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Virginia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Chris McCartney</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor of Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Polycystic Ovary Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperandrogenism</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We do not have current plans to share IPD</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

