<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02616237</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20131213002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02616237</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Facebook-based Weight Loss Programme for Obese Adults in Hong Kong</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of a Facebook-based Weight Loss Programme for Obese Adults in Hong Kong</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the feasibility and efficacy of a 6-month weight
      loss intervention program for obese working adults through a popular social networking site -
      Facebook.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Obese individuals often are at higher risk for developing non-communicable diseases such as
      diabetes and cardiovascular disease. The regular physical activity, healthy diet and social
      support have been shown to be beneficial for weight loss.

      This is a two-arm parallel design randomized controlled trial for 6 months. Participants who
      completed the baseline assessment will be randomly allocated, after stratified by gender, to
      either a control group or Facebook-based intervention group. The control group will receive
      information on healthy eating, physical activity, obesity and cancer via three government
      printed health pamphlets. In addition to the government health pamphlets, the intervention
      group will receive a programme delivered through Facebook.

      The interventions include participation in a private research group on Facebook for health
      education, self monitoring and social support. Participants will receive 12 weekly lessons
      related to nutrition, physical activity, Chinese food therapy, acupressure, weight loss. A
      registered nutritionist and a registered Chinese medicine practitioner will join the Facebook
      group as health partners. Both of them are also registered nurses.

      Data collection will be carried out at baseline, 3 months and 6 months. Each time, both
      groups will complete online questionnaires and attend in-person anthropometric measurements
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Measures are done in three time points: baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Weights will be taken in light clothes without shoes using a digital scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Body Mass Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Measures are done in three time points: baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Height will be taken at baseline using a wall-mounted stadiometer. BMI will be calculated as weight (kg)/height (m2)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in waist circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>Measures are done in three time points: baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Waist circumference will be measured by using an inelastic tape measure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Stages of Change</measure>
    <time_frame>Measures are done in three time points: baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>A 5-item questionnaire will be used to categorize participants into stages of change (pre-contemplation, contemplation, preparation, action, maintenance)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in weight self-efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Measures are done in three time points: baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-efficacy for weight loss will be assessed by using a 20-item Weight Efficacy Lifestyle Questionnaire (WEL).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in physical activity self-efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Measures are done in three time points: baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>A questionnaire of perceived confidence to engage in physical activity under a variety of circumstances on a 5-point Likert scale will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in weight decisional balance</measure>
    <time_frame>Measures are done in three time points: baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>A 20-item questionnaire of perceived pros and cons of weight loss on a 5-point Likert scale. The balance of the two scores &gt;0 indicate more advantages than disadvantages to weight loss</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in social support</measure>
    <time_frame>Measures are done in three time points: baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>A questionnaire will be used to measure the perceived support and sabotage from friends and family for healthy eating and physical activity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in dietary intake of fruits and vegetables</measure>
    <time_frame>Measures are done in three time points: baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>A questionnaire will be used to assess self-reported intake of fruits and vegetables in terms of portion size and frequency</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Measures are done in three time points: baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The International Physical Activity Questionnaire will be used to assess the changes in physical activity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">59</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Lifestyle Intervention: The interventions include participation in a private research group on Facebook for health education, self monitoring and social support. Participants will receive 12 weekly lessons related to nutrition, physical activity, Chinese food therapy, acupressure, weight loss. A registered nutritionist and a registered Chinese medicine practitioner will join the Facebook group as health partners. Both of them are also registered nurses.
Besides the Facebook contents, the participants will also receive government printed health information on healthy eating, physical activity, obesity and cancers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The participants randomized into the Control Group will only receive government printed health information on healthy eating, physical activity, obesity and cancers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lifestyle Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>East-meets-West Lifestyle Intervention elements include nutrition and exercise from the Western perspective, food therapy and acupressure from the Traditional Chinese Medicine perspective, self-monitoring, and motivational videos of successful stories from working colleagues. The group participants in the Facebook are encouraged to post their health behaviors and questions, self-monitor, pledge for weight loss, seek social support and interact with health partners and other participants.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  university full-time employees;

          -  age 18 to 60 years,

          -  BMI of 25 to 40 kg/m2,

          -  have access to Internet and Facebook;

          -  able to communicate in both English and Chinese at F.5 secondary school level or
             above.

          -  agree to communicate with Internet, email, Facebook group and respect privacy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Smoker;

          -  an unstable medical or mental status;

          -  history of myocardial infarction or stroke, or cancer in the past 5 years;

          -  orthopedic or joint problems that would prohibit exercise;

          -  in treatment for alcohol or drug dependency;

          -  an eating disorder;

          -  pregnant, breastfeeding, or planning on becoming pregnant within the next 6 months;

          -  use of medication that might affect body weight;

          -  a recent weight loss of more than 4.5 kg in the previous 6 months;

          -  currently participating in a weight loss program;

          -  organic obesity;

          -  unable to attend assessments or increase physical activity.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>WanChaw SHAE</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>Hong Kong</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Hong Kong</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 24, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 24, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 26, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 22, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 22, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 24, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>LAI Kam Wa</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Manager</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Chinese population</keyword>
  <keyword>acupressure</keyword>
  <keyword>physical activity</keyword>
  <keyword>nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>Facebook</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Weight Loss</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

