<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02614157</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>pLNR-201501</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02614157</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Lateral Lymph Node Dissection After Neoadjuvant Chemo-radiation in Advanced Low Rectal Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Lateral Pelvic Lymph Node Dissection After Neoadjuvant Chemo-radiation for Preoperative Enlarged Lateral Nodes in Advanced Low Rectal Cancer: a Phase III Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>West China Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>West China Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Lateral lymph nodes (LLD) metastasis is a major cause of local recurrence for advanced rectal
      cancer. As for the treatment strategies on LLN metastasis, there are huge controversies on
      whether lateral pelvic lymph nodes dissection (LLND) after neoadjuvant chemo-radiotherapy
      (nCRT) between Western and Eastern countries. Retrospective cohort evidences indicate that
      LLND following total mesorectal excision (TME) will bring benefit from cT3-4 rectal cancer,
      not regular predictive LLND, which will bring more side effects on the contrary. Existing
      reports tend to recommend LLND for specific individual with suspicious LLN metastasis.
      Moreover, there is a blank strict prospective randomized control study on the comparison of
      LLND+TME and LLND after nCRT. Therefore, our trial will compare the efficacy and safety of
      the two strategies for mid/low rectal cancer with suspicious LLN metastasis. The risk factors
      (such as radiologic factors, pathologic factors, and serum protein) to predict local
      recurrence and overall survival will be further investigated.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recently, the incidence and mortality of colorectal cancer have increased, leading the second
      prevalence after lung cancer. Local recurrence of mid/low rectal cancer is not only the poor
      prognostic factor but also the threat of terrible quality of life. Although universal usage
      of neoadjuvant chemo-radiotherapy (nCRT) and total mesorectal excision (TME) have decreased
      local recurrence to 5%-10%, the ratio of local recurrence has occupied almost 30% of total
      metastasis and recurrence incidences, which limited the therapeutic effect of rectal cancer.
      Increasing evidences have demonstrated lateral pelvic lymph nodes (LLN) metastasis as one of
      the prominent causes of local recurrence, accompanied with 10%-25% advanced rectal cancer.
      Published researches also reminder us preoperative LLN involvement may lead to high local
      recurrence and poor overall survival.

      As for the treatment strategies on LLN metastasis, there are huge controversies on whether
      lateral pelvic lymph nodes dissection (LLND) or LLND+TME after nCRT:

      Eastern countries especially Japan favors LLND following TME with the reasons: 1) the
      incidence of LLN metastasis reaches as high as 10%-25% and 27% of rectal patients who undergo
      TME solely (without LLND) will develop into local recurrence. And the predictive pelvic
      recurrence rate will decrease 50%; corresponding 5-year overall survival will increase 8%-9%.
      2) efficacy of LLND equals to resection of &quot;local lymph nodes metastases&quot;. A large cohort of
      11567 cases from Japan demonstrates resection of iliac lymph nodes metastasis does not show
      any difference from TME of cTxN2aM0 and resection of obturator and external iliac lymph nodes
      favors that of liver metastasis. 3) Japanese Guidelines for treatment of colorectal in 2014
      also recommends mid/low II/III rectal cancer under peritoneal reflex undergo regular
      TME+LLND.

      On the contrary, western countries favor sole TME after nCRT for LLN metastasis, holding
      that: 1) rate of lymph nodes metastasis is relatively low and LLN metastasis is regarded as
      systemic metastasis. 2) LLND experiences longer operative time, higher postoperative
      complications, and poor quality of life. 3) American NCCN and European ESMO guidelines
      recommend single TME for rectal cancer, if necessary, LLDN is added when LLN is indeed
      metastasis.

      However, there is a blank strict prospective randomized control study on the comparison of
      nCRT and LLND. Present existing retrospective cohort mainly focus on all the mid/low advanced
      cancer, not the specific individual of suspicious LLN metastasis. In fact, the results almost
      indicate no differences on local recurrence and overall survival, except for less operation
      time, blood loss, and perioperative complications in LLND. Although the latest researches
      start to report their preliminary outcomes, the patients sample sizes are small and they
      achieve varied recurrence and overall survival.

      In conclusion, the treatment strategy for colorectal cancer has focused on individual and
      precision. Massive of retrospective reports have indicated that rectal cancer patients with
      LLN metastasis will benefit from LLND, however, there is hot controversy on the treatment of
      whether TME+LLND or TME+nCRT for specific rectal patients with suspicious LLN metastasis.
      Therefore, our trial will compare the efficacy and safety of the two strategies for mid/low
      rectal cancer with suspicious LLN metastasis. The risk factors (such as radiologic factors,
      pathologic factors, and serum protein) to predict local recurrence and overall survival will
      be further investigated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>3-year local recurrence</measure>
    <time_frame>until local-recurrence (up to 3 years)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>disease free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of sexual and urinary dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>postoperative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">212</enrollment>
  <condition>Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>LLND+TME group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>advanced rectal cancer patients after neoadjuvant chem-radiation with suspicious lateral lymph nodes involvement undergo lateral lymph node dissection and total mesorectal excision(LLND+TME)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TME group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>advanced rectal cancer patients after neoadjuvant chem-radiation with suspicious lateral lymph nodes involvement undergo total mesorectal excision (TME)solely, without LLND</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>LLND</intervention_name>
    <description>advanced rectal cancer patients whose lymph nodes are suspiciously enlarged after neoadjuvant chemoradiation will undergo lateral lymph node dissection (LLND) and total mesorectal excision (TME)</description>
    <arm_group_label>LLND+TME group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lateral Lymph Node Dissection</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>labeled line</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>LLND+TME group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed rectal cancer (below the peritoneal reflection) Clinical
             stage I, II, or III

          -  No extramesorectal lymph node swelling (shorter diameter is less than 10 mm)

          -  No invasion to other organ (s)

          -  PS: 0, 1

          -  No past history of chemotherapy, pelvic surgery or radiation

          -  Written informed consent operative criteria:

          -  Mesorectal excision is performed

          -  Operative findings:

          -  Main lesion of the tumor is located at the rectum

          -  Lower tumor margin is below the peritoneal reflection

          -  R0 after resection

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  High rectal cancer

          -  Multiple cancer patients

          -  Pregnant patients

          -  Psychological disorder

          -  Steroid administration

          -  Cardiac infarction within six months

          -  Severe pulmonary emphysema and pulmonary fibrosis

          -  Doctor's decision for exclusion
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ziqiang Wang, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>West China Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ziqiang Wang, MD,PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+8618980602028</phone>
    <email>wangzqzyh@163.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mingtian Wei, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+8613198596090</phone>
    <email>m.weihx@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West China Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chengdu</city>
        <state>Sichuan</state>
        <zip>610000</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ziqiang Wang, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+8618980602028</phone>
      <email>wangzqzyh@163.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mingtian Wei, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+8613198596090</phone>
      <email>m.weihx@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baik SH, Kim NK, Lee YC, Kim H, Lee KY, Sohn SK, Cho CH. Prognostic significance of circumferential resection margin following total mesorectal excision and adjuvant chemoradiotherapy in patients with rectal cancer. Ann Surg Oncol. 2007 Feb;14(2):462-9. Epub 2006 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>17096053</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Quadros CA, Falcão MF, Carvalho ME, Ladeia PA, Lopes A. Metastases to retroperitoneal or lateral pelvic lymph nodes indicated unfavorable survival and high pelvic recurrence rates in a cohort of 102 patients with low rectal adenocarcinoma. J Surg Oncol. 2012 Nov;106(6):653-8. doi: 10.1002/jso.23144. Epub 2012 Apr 25.</citation>
    <PMID>22535617</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ueno M, Oya M, Azekura K, Yamaguchi T, Muto T. Incidence and prognostic significance of lateral lymph node metastasis in patients with advanced low rectal cancer. Br J Surg. 2005 Jun;92(6):756-63.</citation>
    <PMID>15838895</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yano H, Moran BJ. The incidence of lateral pelvic side-wall nodal involvement in low rectal cancer may be similar in Japan and the West. Br J Surg. 2008 Jan;95(1):33-49. doi: 10.1002/bjs.6061. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18165939</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kapiteijn E, Marijnen CA, Nagtegaal ID, Putter H, Steup WH, Wiggers T, Rutten HJ, Pahlman L, Glimelius B, van Krieken JH, Leer JW, van de Velde CJ; Dutch Colorectal Cancer Group. Preoperative radiotherapy combined with total mesorectal excision for resectable rectal cancer. N Engl J Med. 2001 Aug 30;345(9):638-46.</citation>
    <PMID>11547717</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kusters M, Marijnen CA, van de Velde CJ, Rutten HJ, Lahaye MJ, Kim JH, Beets-Tan RG, Beets GL. Patterns of local recurrence in rectal cancer; a study of the Dutch TME trial. Eur J Surg Oncol. 2010 May;36(5):470-6. doi: 10.1016/j.ejso.2009.11.011. Epub 2010 Jan 21.</citation>
    <PMID>20096534</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nagawa H, Muto T, Sunouchi K, Higuchi Y, Tsurita G, Watanabe T, Sawada T. Randomized, controlled trial of lateral node dissection vs. nerve-preserving resection in patients with rectal cancer after preoperative radiotherapy. Dis Colon Rectum. 2001 Sep;44(9):1274-80.</citation>
    <PMID>11584199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ueno H, Mochizuki H, Hashiguchi Y, Ishiguro M, Miyoshi M, Kajiwara Y, Sato T, Shimazaki H, Hase K. Potential prognostic benefit of lateral pelvic node dissection for rectal cancer located below the peritoneal reflection. Ann Surg. 2007 Jan;245(1):80-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17197969</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Watanabe T, Tsurita G, Muto T, Sawada T, Sunouchi K, Higuchi Y, Komuro Y, Kanazawa T, Iijima T, Miyaki M, Nagawa H. Extended lymphadenectomy and preoperative radiotherapy for lower rectal cancers. Surgery. 2002 Jul;132(1):27-33.</citation>
    <PMID>12110792</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yano H, Saito Y, Takeshita E, Miyake O, Ishizuka N. Prediction of lateral pelvic node involvement in low rectal cancer by conventional computed tomography. Br J Surg. 2007 Aug;94(8):1014-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17436337</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Georgiou P, Tan E, Gouvas N, Antoniou A, Brown G, Nicholls RJ, Tekkis P. Extended lymphadenectomy versus conventional surgery for rectal cancer: a meta-analysis. Lancet Oncol. 2009 Nov;10(11):1053-62. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(09)70224-4. Epub 2009 Sep 18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19767239</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim JC, Takahashi K, Yu CS, Kim HC, Kim TW, Ryu MH, Kim JH, Mori T. Comparative outcome between chemoradiotherapy and lateral pelvic lymph node dissection following total mesorectal excision in rectal cancer. Ann Surg. 2007 Nov;246(5):754-62.</citation>
    <PMID>17968166</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Suzuki K, Muto T, Sawada T. Prevention of local recurrence by extended lymphadenectomy for rectal cancer. Surg Today. 1995;25(9):795-801.</citation>
    <PMID>8555697</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sato H, Maeda K, Maruta M, Masumori K, Koide Y. Who can get the beneficial effect from lateral lymph node dissection for Dukes C rectal carcinoma below the peritoneal reflection? Dis Colon Rectum. 2006 Oct;49(10 Suppl):S3-12.</citation>
    <PMID>17106812</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim TH, Jeong SY, Choi DH, Kim DY, Jung KH, Moon SH, Chang HJ, Lim SB, Choi HS, Park JG. Lateral lymph node metastasis is a major cause of locoregional recurrence in rectal cancer treated with preoperative chemoradiotherapy and curative resection. Ann Surg Oncol. 2008 Mar;15(3):729-37. Epub 2007 Dec 5.</citation>
    <PMID>18057989</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim MJ, Kim TH, Kim DY, Kim SY, Baek JY, Chang HJ, Park SC, Park JW, Oh JH. Can chemoradiation allow for omission of lateral pelvic node dissection for locally advanced rectal cancer? J Surg Oncol. 2015 Mar 15;111(4):459-64. doi: 10.1002/jso.23852. Epub 2015 Jan 5.</citation>
    <PMID>25559888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fujita S, Akasu T, Mizusawa J, Saito N, Kinugasa Y, Kanemitsu Y, Ohue M, Fujii S, Shiozawa M, Yamaguchi T, Moriya Y; Colorectal Cancer Study Group of Japan Clinical Oncology Group. Postoperative morbidity and mortality after mesorectal excision with and without lateral lymph node dissection for clinical stage II or stage III lower rectal cancer (JCOG0212): results from a multicentre, randomised controlled, non-inferiority trial. Lancet Oncol. 2012 Jun;13(6):616-21. doi: 10.1016/S1470-2045(12)70158-4. Epub 2012 May 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22591948</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kobayashi H, Mochizuki H, Kato T, Mori T, Kameoka S, Shirouzu K, Sugihara K. Outcomes of surgery alone for lower rectal cancer with and without pelvic sidewall dissection. Dis Colon Rectum. 2009 Apr;52(4):567-76. doi: 10.1007/DCR.0b013e3181a1d994.</citation>
    <PMID>19404054</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Watanabe T, Itabashi M, Shimada Y, Tanaka S, Ito Y, Ajioka Y, Hamaguchi T, Hyodo I, Igarashi M, Ishida H, Ishiguro M, Kanemitsu Y, Kokudo N, Muro K, Ochiai A, Oguchi M, Ohkura Y, Saito Y, Sakai Y, Ueno H, Yoshino T, Fujimori T, Koinuma N, Morita T, Nishimura G, Sakata Y, Takahashi K, Takiuchi H, Tsuruta O, Yamaguchi T, Yoshida M, Yamaguchi N, Kotake K, Sugihara K; Japanese Society for Cancer of the Colon and Rectum. Japanese Society for Cancer of the Colon and Rectum (JSCCR) guidelines 2010 for the treatment of colorectal cancer. Int J Clin Oncol. 2012 Feb;17(1):1-29. doi: 10.1007/s10147-011-0315-2. Epub 2011 Oct 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22002491</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dharmarajan S, Shuai D, Fajardo AD, Birnbaum EH, Hunt SR, Mutch MG, Fleshman JW, Lin AY. Clinically enlarged lateral pelvic lymph nodes do not influence prognosis after neoadjuvant therapy and TME in stage III rectal cancer. J Gastrointest Surg. 2011 Aug;15(8):1368-74. doi: 10.1007/s11605-011-1533-7. Epub 2011 May 2.</citation>
    <PMID>21533959</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akiyoshi T, Ueno M, Matsueda K, Konishi T, Fujimoto Y, Nagayama S, Fukunaga Y, Unno T, Kano A, Kuroyanagi H, Oya M, Yamaguchi T, Watanabe T, Muto T. Selective lateral pelvic lymph node dissection in patients with advanced low rectal cancer treated with preoperative chemoradiotherapy based on pretreatment imaging. Ann Surg Oncol. 2014 Jan;21(1):189-96. doi: 10.1245/s10434-013-3216-y. Epub 2013 Aug 21.</citation>
    <PMID>23963871</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Akiyoshi T, Matsueda K, Hiratsuka M, Unno T, Nagata J, Nagasaki T, Konishi T, Fujimoto Y, Nagayama S, Fukunaga Y, Ueno M. Indications for Lateral Pelvic Lymph Node Dissection Based on Magnetic Resonance Imaging Before and After Preoperative Chemoradiotherapy in Patients with Advanced Low-Rectal Cancer. Ann Surg Oncol. 2015 Dec;22 Suppl 3:S614-20. doi: 10.1245/s10434-015-4565-5. Epub 2015 Apr 21.</citation>
    <PMID>25896145</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 23, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 24, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 25, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 11, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 11, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 14, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>West China Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ziqiang Wang,MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>rectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>lateral lymph node dissection</keyword>
  <keyword>neoadjuvant chemoradiation</keyword>
  <keyword>total mesorectal excision</keyword>
  <keyword>surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>recurrence</keyword>
  <keyword>metastasis</keyword>
  <keyword>overall survival</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

