<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02614690</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SRC118</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02614690</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Is Univalving or Bivalving of Long Arm Casts for Forearm Fractures Necessary?</brief_title>
  <official_title>Is Univalving or Bivalving of Long Arm Casts for Forearm Fractures Necessary?</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Connecticut Children's Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Connecticut Children's Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to examine the need for univalve or bivalve splitting of casts in pediatric
      patients with forearm fractures following closed reduction and cast application in a
      randomized, prospective fashion.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Following cast application, little is known regarding the need to split the cast, either in a
      univalve (a split along a single side of the cast) or bivalve (a split along both sides of
      the cast) fashion. Theoretically, the splitting of the cast allows for expansion and soft
      tissue swelling. However, review of the literature yields a paucity of evidence demonstrating
      the efficacy of splitting a cast. In a study by Nietosvaara et. al, a retrospective
      examination of 109 pediatric patients initially treated with closed cylindrical casting for
      closed forearm fractures were evaluated. Of these 109 patients, one-sixth required the
      initial cast to be split, trimmed, or removed secondary to post-traumatic swelling.

      However, the splitting of a cast is not without risks in itself. Once the initial swelling
      dissipates, a univalved or bivalved cast can become excessively loose. This loosening has
      been associated with a loss of reduction. If the loss or reduction is substantial, it may
      require a re-reduction or operation to correct. In addition, with every use of the cast saw a
      patient is placed at risk for iatrogenic cast saw injury. Thermal burns and abrasions from
      cast saws can cause lifelong emotional and physical scars for a patient. They can also be an
      inciting event for litigation against the hospital and or provider, with settlements
      averaging greater than $12,000 per centimeter of cast saw injury.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>January 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications for patients who are casted following a forearm fracture</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>This data will be able to help physicians and ER personnel help this patient population with the least number of cast complications and therefore allow for a more efficient use of resources since cast modifications could be minimized. Metrics used to characterize compliations are the radiograhic union used to determine speed of healing and the number of unplanned ER or clinic visits for cast modifications.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Fracture of Shaft of Radius and/or Ulna</condition>
  <condition>Metaphyseal Fracture of Bone of Upper Limb</condition>
  <condition>Fracture of Upper Limb, Level Unspecified</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No split Cast of forearm fractures</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient will have a &quot;No split cast&quot; long arm cast applied after a closed reduction of forearm fractures. The cast will not be split. 20 patients will be randomized to this arm.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Univalve Split Cast of forearm fractures</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will have a &quot;Univalve Split Cast&quot; long arm cast applied after undergoing closed reduction of of forearm fractures. This is a cast that is split on only one side of the cast. 20 patients will be randomized to this arm</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bivalve Split Cast of forearm fractures</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will have a &quot;Bivalve Split Cast&quot; long arm cast applied after they have undergone a closed reduction of of forearm fractures. This is a cast that will be split on both sides of the cast. 20 patients will be randomized to the bivalve split arm cast.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No Split Cast of forearm fractures</intervention_name>
    <description>Enroll 20 patients per arm: patients who present for long arm casts after closed reduction of forearm fractures will be randomized to one of 3 arms. Patients randomized to &quot;No Split Cast&quot; will have a cast that is not split, this is known as closed cast. The cast will be applied according to our Standard of Care casting. Patients will be then undergo follow-up for clinical and radiographic examinations based on the routine fracture management protocol for approximately 3 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>No split Cast of forearm fractures</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Univalve Split Cast of forearm fractures</intervention_name>
    <description>Enroll 20 patients per arm: patients who present for long arm casts after closed reduction of forearm fractures will be randomized to one of 3 arms. Patients randomized to &quot;Univalve Cast&quot; will have a cast that is split on only one side of the cast, this is known as univalve cast. The cast will be applied according to our Standard of Care casting. Patients will be then undergo follow-up for clinical and radiographic examinations based on the routine fracture management protocol for approximately 3 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Univalve Split Cast of forearm fractures</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bivalve Split Cast of forearm fractures</intervention_name>
    <description>Enroll 20 patients per arm: patients who present for long arm casts after closed reduction of forearm fractures will be randomized to one of 3 arms. Patients randomized to &quot;Bivalve Cast&quot; will have a cast that is split on both sides of the cast, this is known as bivalve cast. The cast will be applied according to our Standard of Care casting. Patients will be then undergo follow-up for clinical and radiographic examinations based on the routine fracture management protocol for approximately 3 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bivalve Split Cast of forearm fractures</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  A closed isolated radial and/or ulna fracture of the forearm inclusive of metaphyseal
             and/or shaft level fractures.

          -  Forearm fractures that require closed reduction (with or without conscious sedation)

          -  Patients between the ages of 3 and 12 years old

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Specific exclusions

               -  Age less than 3 or greater than 12

               -  Patients presenting with an associated neurological or vascular injury caused by
                  the fracture

               -  Patients presenting with an open fracture

               -  Patients requiring operative treatment following the initial fracture evaluation

               -  Ipsilateral upper extremity fracture

               -  Patients intubated or with a pre-existing condition that prevents them from
                  verbalizing symptoms of discomfort

          2. Generic exclusion: &quot;Subjects not meeting all inclusion criteria.&quot;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>3 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Lee, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Connecticut Children's Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mark Lee, MD</last_name>
    <phone>860-545-9100</phone>
    <email>Mlee01@connecticutchildrens.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Matt Solomito</last_name>
    <phone>(860) 284-0208</phone>
    <email>Msolomito@connecticutchildrens.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Connecticut Children's Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hartford</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Matt Solomito</last_name>
      <phone>860-284-0208</phone>
      <email>mailto:msolomito@ccmckids.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mark Lee, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 26, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 23, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 25, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 23, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 23, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 25, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Connecticut Children's Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mark Lee, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Orthopaedic Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fracture of the upper limb</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Calpastatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>April 20, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>July 13, 2017</returned>
    <submitted>January 23, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

