<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02617420</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15-0211</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02617420</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Monitoring Adherence Using Mobile Technology</brief_title>
  <official_title>Monitoring Adherence Using Mobile Technology</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study plans to learn more about how children use their asthma medicines. The
      investigators would like to see if special electronic monitoring devices that connect to
      smartphones and computers can help children to better manage their asthma
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patient participants that rate the devices as easy to use</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measuring the feasibility and acceptability of monitoring devices for children ages 6-17 who are at high risk for asthma exacerbation, by having children use the devices and having children/parents answer survey questions regarding their impressions of the product at the beginning of use and after 1.5 and 3 months of use.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of provider participants that rate the devices as easy to use</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measuring the feasibility and acceptability of monitoring devices for children ages 6-17 who are at high risk for asthma exacerbation, by having children use the devices and having providers answer survey questions regarding their impressions of the product at the beginning of use and after 1.5 and 3 months of use.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients/parents that exhibit behavioral changes with respect to taking asthma medications as a result of information gained from the monitoring devices.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>How many parents/patients of high risk asthmatic children change behavior regarding how they administer their medications as a result of information that they gained from the devices regarding their adherence to their treatment regimen, gained via phone surveys at 1.5 and 3 months after using the devices. Patients are surveyed if children are greater than 12 years old. Parents are surveyed if children are 6-12 years old.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of pediatric pulmonary providers that exhibit behavioral changes with respect to prescribing asthma medications as a result of information gained from the monitoring devices.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of healthcare providers (physicians, nurse practitioners and physician assistants) that feel that their decision-making is affected regarding medication regimens for asthma based on information that they receive on patient adherence from the devices based on survey data gathered at study entry and 3 months after initiation of the devices will be measured.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation of lung function to percent use of controller medications as measured by adherence devices.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate correlation of markers of lung function (spirometry, fractional exhaled nitric oxide (FeNO), with percent adherence as measured by the monitoring devices.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <description>All patients will be enrolled in one arm. These patients will have monitoring devices placed on their asthma controller and rescue medication, with data transmitted both to their smartphones and a dashboard accessed by their primary pediatric pulmonary provider.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Propeller Health Monitoring Device</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study subjects would be drawn from the list of high risk asthma patients and by pre-clinic
        chart review done by study investigator.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age 6-17 years and their parents

          -  either 2 emergency department visits/prednisone bursts in the last 12 months or at
             least 1 asthma related hospitalization in the last 12 months

          -  requiring daily controller therapy with either inhaled corticosteroids or combination
             corticosteroids/long acting beta agonist (LABA).

          -  Patients using metered dose inhaler therapy would be eligible. Patients may also be on
             leukotriene antagonists,

          -  Must be made aware that they will have to read and accept to the terms of the User
             Agreement prior to enrollment in the study. If they do not agree they will not be able
             to continue participation. The User agreement will be read agreed to electronically
             when they begin using the device, however a paper version will be provided at the time
             of consent upon request.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Primary language other than English or Spanish

          -  Presence of other significant chronic lung disease including cystic fibrosis,
             interstitial lung disease, tracheostomy status.

          -  Patients using diskus therapy.

          -  Patients only on leukotriene antagonists.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stanley Szefler, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 24, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 25, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 1, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 14, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 14, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 16, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

