<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02617056</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>N1932-P</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>RX001932-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02617056</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Objective Assessment of Behavioral Associations of Patients With Dementia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Objective Assessment of Behavioral Associations of Patients With Dementia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VA Office of Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VA Office of Research and Development</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      It is generally acknowledged that patients with dementia are best cared for at home. However,
      outbursts of various behavioral disturbances, e.g., combativeness, appear in most cases and
      often necessitate institutionalization. These outbursts are often without apparent warning,
      which limits preventive interventions. The measurement of the electrical activity of the skin
      is well-studied as an indicator of stress or agitation. The investigators propose to monitor
      the electrical activity of skin in patients with dementia in order to determine whether any
      sign of agitation may occur before the outburst. If skin electrical activity gives sufficient
      warning, then preventive interventions may be tried. If successful, the ability to predict
      and prevent outbursts of behavioral disturbances will allow patients to be cared for at home
      for longer periods. It is the primary aim of this project to determine whether skin
      electrical activity gives such a warning; possible preventive measures will be the subject of
      future studies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Objective(s): The key goal of this project is to develop methods for objectively
           monitoring and, ultimately, predicting outbursts of aberrant behaviors commonly seen
           among patients with a variety of neuropsychiatric conditions: dementia, PTSD, TBI, and
           schizophrenia. This initial study will be on patients with dementia. The analytic focus
           is on the measurement of electrodermal activity (EDA), a widely-studied physiological
           recording that indicates sympathetic tone; the central hypothesis in this approach is
           that sympathetic tone will increase prior to an outburst and, therefore, may allow
           therapeutic interventions to prevent it. Alterations of sympathetic activity have been
           implicated in the literature for each of these four conditions. Here, EDA recording
           holds the advantages of requiring neither effort nor communication on the part of the
           subject, and of being a noninvasive procedure. These factors make EDA potentially useful
           for the clinical assessment of arousal among patients with dementia, which will be the
           first of the specific groups studied under this protocol.

        2. Research Design: The general design of all of these studies is the monitoring of EDA in
           subjects with a small device that can be worn on the wrist, ankle or arm; patterns of
           spontaneous EDA will then be assessed for features that may predict the occurrence of an
           outburst. In the initial study of dementia patients, the investigators will first survey
           EDA responses in commonly used paradigms (e.g., visual stimulus, EDA response).
           Currently, little is known about EDA in this population, and the investigators redress
           this by (1) establishing behavioral and physiological baselines for each subject in the
           study, (2) determining how these two classes of dependent measures cohere, and (3)
           evaluating whether patterns of EDA differ as a function of aberrant behaviors that are
           often seen in dementia: wandering, combativeness, and &quot;sundowning&quot; (agitation that
           typically develops late in the day). These behaviors are often grouped in the literature
           under the term &quot;disorders of arousal&quot;, and are clinically well known to present as signs
           of disorientation and in some cases, distress. (4) Moreover, quantitative assessment of
           EDA change conceivably may reveal patterns that may signal the onset of problem
           behaviors.

           Each subject will serve as his/her own control, providing within-subject measures of EDA
           signal over time and its correlation with aberrant behaviors. It is worth noting that
           the key EDA measures are not subject to bias based on experimenter ratings. Further, the
           aberrant behaviors will also be rated over time, using quantitative rating scales for
           each of them. In a second class of analyses, the investigators will perform group
           contrasts of subjects with and without these aberrant behaviors, as operationally
           defined by rating scales, to determine if patients with these problem behaviors are
           distinctive as a group with respect to EDA patterns. All statistical analysis will be
           performed on anonymized data, blind to group membership.

        3. Methodology: EDA will be measured by standard techniques in all subjects: electrodes may
           be placed on the hands, feet, ankles, wrists, or arm according to preference and
           configured to measure conductivity or potential. In one portion of the study, a wearable
           device to measure EDA will be used to determine whether EDA predicts the occurrence of
           an outburst. In the study with dementia patients, assessments will be performed at an
           inpatient dementia care facility at the Bedford VAMC (GRECC). Over a two-year period,
           the investigators anticipate enrolling 60 subjects. Recruitment criteria include
           toleration of the EDA recording device worn on the wrist (similar to a watch) or the
           ankle. Skin potential, skin conductance, and membrane electrical power will be monitored
           and data recorded electronically. Data will be de-identified by assigning the serial
           subject number to each patient; a table linking the number to the subject's identity
           will be kept on a secure VA server, allowing re-identification after data analysis.

        4. Findings: If successful, EDA may predict an outburst of aberrant behavior with enough
           lead time to permit a preventive intervention.

        5. Clinical Relationships: The investigators hypothesize that: (a) stable physiologic
           baselines can be obtained for EDA measures, (b) EDA signals are altered as a function of
           aberrant behaviors (&quot;disorders of arousal&quot;) on a within-subject basis, and (c) group
           differences will emerge between samples of patients with and without these aberrant
           behaviors.

        6. Impact/Significance: If the EDA were borne out as a sensitive measure of disorders of
           arousal, this measure may find application in the assessment and treatment of dementia.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 1, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 29, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 29, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Ecologic or Community</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Electrodermal activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Continuously over a period of 4-6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>The purpose of this trial is to determine whether a signal of electrodermal activity (EDA) will precede an outburst of a behavioral disturbance by enough time to permit an intervention to prevent that behavior. This is a pilot project to test this hypothesis; subsequent studies will test the effectiveness of interventions. Therefore, the primary outcome sought is the detection of such a signal. EDA includes skin potential and skin conductivity. The time course of these two measurements form electrical signals. The shape of these signals will be characterized by mean value, spectral analysis and principle component analysis. The three analyses of two signals lead to six categories of information about the subject that will be examined as predictors of an outburst. Each subject will serve as his own control. More specifically, a successful outcome of this pilot project is that information from these six categories, alone or in combination, can predict an outburst.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association of behaviors with electrodermal activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Continuously over a period of 4-6 hours</time_frame>
    <description>While observing a subject to detect a signal for measure 1 above, we expect to detect minor variations of electrodermal activity that may correlate with objects in the environment, indicating a stress response that may not be apparent from the subject's demeanor. This may reveal unsuspected stress factors in the environment, the reduction of which may improve the subject's well being.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <condition>Psychomotor Agitation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Observational group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects with dementia</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        patients in dementia unit have advanced dementia; a small number of young adult controls
        will be studied to validate electrodermal measurements
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  any patient admitted to dementia unit at Bedford VAMC

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  inability to cooperate with electrodermal measurements
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Frank Greco, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Edith Nourse Rogers Memorial Veterans Hospital, Bedford, MA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Frank Greco, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(781) 687-3265</phone>
    <email>Frank.Greco2@va.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Edith Nourse Rogers Memorial Veterans Hospital, Bedford, MA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bedford</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01730</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joseph Squicciarini</last_name>
      <phone>781-687-2926</phone>
      <email>Joe.Squicciarini@va.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>P. B Cipolloni, MD</last_name>
      <phone>(781) 687-2838</phone>
      <email>pb.cipolloni@va.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Frank Greco, MD PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 25, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 25, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 30, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>electrodermal response</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychomotor Agitation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Upon request after publication.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

