<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02919748</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NUS-IRB: B-14-304</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02919748</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Choral Singing For the Prevention of Dementia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Choral Singing For the Prevention of Dementia: A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National University, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Agency for Science, Technology and Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nanyang Technological University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Cambridge</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ministry of Health, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National University, Singapore</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the efficacy of choral singing in the prevention of dementia and examine the
      underlying mechanisms using Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) technique and a panel of
      peripheral biomarkers in venous blood and urine. The investigators hypothesize that Choral
      singing could prevent cognitive decline among community-dwelling elderly who are at high risk
      of dementia. The underlying neural mechanisms involve the changes in brain structure and
      function that can be quantified using MRI technique. The changes in cognitive outcomes will
      be accompanied by observable changes from a panel of carefully selected peripheral
      biomarkers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cognitive function declines with advancing age and the prevalence and incidence of dementia
      rises dramatically in later life. Impaired cognitive function limits one's ability to work,
      live and socialize, and represent a major obstacle for active aging. Data from Asian
      countries showed a clear role of cognitive function in contributing to functional disability
      independent of physical health. How to maintain good cognitive health in the later stage of
      life is an important and challenging question that requires well-founded research with good
      applicability. With no cure for dementia in sight presently, it is vitally important to find
      effective preventive measures. Candidates and potential avenues for intervention should be
      carefully evaluated in well-designed randomized controlled trials (RCT). Here the
      investigators propose choral singing as a novel approach for the prevention of cognitive
      decline and dementia; the investigators plan to test the hypothesized efficacy in a RCT based
      on a selected group of senior Singaporeans from the Jurong Area. This proposed research is
      built on a growing body of research evidence on the role of choral singing in health
      promotion and psychological wellbeing; and the fact that no trial has tested the potential
      effectiveness of choral singing in delaying cognitive decline and the onset of dementia.

      The plasticity of the brain forms the scientific basis for the potential efficacy of choral
      singing in preventing cognitive decline and the incidence of dementia. It is well known that
      participating in various cognitive, social and productive activities is associated with
      improved cognitive function and lower risk of dementia. The protective effects on cognition
      may be particularly effective for certain subgroups. For example, analysis of local data
      showed that among the single and widowed elderly, an increase in social engagement was
      associated with a lower risk of cognitive impairment: compared with subjects in the lowest
      tertile of social engagement scores, the adjusted Odds Ratio (OR) of cognitive impairment was
      0.50 for subjects in the second or the third tertile.

      Data from previous clinical trials support that cognitive training is effective in improving
      cognitive function or delaying cognitive decline in the elderly. Functional gains from
      cognitive training have been reported to last up to five years, with a meta-analysis
      demonstrating that the protective effects of cognitive training on cognition in healthy
      elderly can persist years after training. In Singapore, a brain-computer interface based
      cognitive training system showed promise in improving memory and attention in healthy
      elderly. Specifically, the training led to significant improvement in immediate memory (p =
      0.038), visuospatial/constructional (p = 0.014), attention (p = 0.039), and delayed memory
      (p&lt;0.001) scores. However, cognitive training based on human trainer or brain-computer
      interface are expensive and hence the applicability as a preventive in real world setting for
      the general population is largely limited. Participants of such trainings also may not be
      able to maintain lasting interest and motivation. Given those considerations, relatively
      cost-effective and captivating methods are urgently needed and we believe choral singing is a
      promising candidate.

      In Singapore, there are more than 200 school choirs. Most universities and tertiary education
      institutions have choirs developed as an expressive art form. Furthermore, there are numerous
      church choirs who sing with spiritual passion, and the professional choruses who are selected
      to sing and to perform. The existing resource can be tapped on in the future for large scale
      interventional initiative once solid data of its efficacy are produced from rigorously
      designed clinical studies.

      In this collaborative research project that involves experts from multiple disciplines, the
      investigators propose to conduct a randomized clinical trial to examine the clinical efficacy
      of choral singing in the prevention of cognitive decline and dementia. As a cognitive
      stimulating activity, choral singing involves cognitive processes such as attention, memory,
      executive function and language. As a social activity, choral singing consists of group
      interactions which cultivate the feeling of being part of a meaningful community. Prior
      studies have demonstrated that situations and activities involving synchrony with others
      induces feelings of closeness and affiliation, and bolsters coordination with synchronization
      partners. Increased prosociality and conformity produced by synchrony may also be applied to
      other people more generally, even those who were not synchronization partners. Moreover,
      synchrony and affiliative orientations also share a bi-directional relationship, such that
      individuals who are more prone to prosocial tendencies are more likely to synchronize with
      others. As a physical exercise, choral singing requires the involvement of more than 100
      muscles; it helps to improve lung function and circulation, promotes superior posture, and
      boost balance and resistance. Choral singing also requires the choristers to cooperate with
      each other, the discipline of listening to blend with fellow singers and need persistently
      hard work to stay on par with the level of other singers. All the above may contribute to
      long term cognitive benefits of choral singing.

      Although theoretically plausible, the effectiveness of choral singing in preventing cognitive
      decline and dementia has not been studied scientifically. This proposed study will fill an
      important knowledge gap. The investigators aim to produce firm data on two year efficacy of
      choral singing in preventing cognitive decline and this will form the evidence base for
      further research and future interventional initiative.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in cognitive performance</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using a composite cognitive test score based on results from a battery of 6 cognitive tests that measures the performance on multiple cognitive domains. The composite cognitive test score (CCTS) will be calculated as the average of Z scores standardised to the baseline mean and standard deviation of trial participants, with higher scores representing better cognitive performance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in brain structure and function</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in biological markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using biological sampling</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depressive symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 month, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using the Geriatric Depression Scale (GDS-15)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 month, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using the Geriatric Anxiety Inventory (GAI)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 month, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using the Perceived Stress Scale (PSS)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 month, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using the Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index (PSQI)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropsychiatric symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 month, 1 year, 2 year.</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using the Neuropsychiatric Inventory (NPI)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using Rey Auditory Verbal Learning Test (RAVLT)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Digit Span</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using Digit Span Task</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Block Design</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using Block Design Test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Color Trails</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using Color Trails tests</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Symbol Digit Modality</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using Symbol Digit Modality Test (SDMT)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Boston Naming</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using Boston Naming Test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of symptoms of dementia</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using the Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Mini-Mental State Examination</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 month, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using the Mini-Mental State Examination (MMSE)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in Montreal Cognitive Assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 month, 1 year, 2 year</time_frame>
    <description>Measured using the Montreal Cognitive Assessment (MoCA)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">360</enrollment>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <condition>Cognitive Decline</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Choral Singing</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>General Health Education Program and Group Activities</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Choral Singing</intervention_name>
    <description>Weekly sessions at 1 hour of choral singing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Health Education Program</intervention_name>
    <description>Weekly session at 1 hour of health education talk and group activities</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Community-living elderly aged 60 years and above, and

          2. Subjective cognitive complaints based on self-report, or

          3. Objective cognitive impairment based on neuropsychological test scores (Z score &lt; 0
             and &gt;-1.5), or

          4. Multiple risk factors of dementia such as family history, depression, etc., and

          5. Not demented: Clinical Dementia Rating (CDR) global score=0

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any terminal illness, OR

          2. Stroke, OR

          3. Aphasia, OR

          4. Marked hearing impairment, OR

          5. Participating in another interventional study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lei Feng, Medicine</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National University, Singapore</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lei Feng, Medicine</last_name>
    <phone>65-67723491</phone>
    <email>pcmfl@nus.edu.sg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Elisabeth Ow, Nursing</last_name>
    <phone>65-67910134</phone>
    <email>pcmokte@nus.edu.sg</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>TaRA@JP</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>648886</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Elisabeth Ow, Nursing</last_name>
      <phone>65-67910134</phone>
      <email>pcmokte@nus.edu.sg</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lei Feng, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feng L, Ng TP, He Y, Li C, Kua EH, Zhang M. Physical Health and Cognitive Function Independently Contributed to Functional Disability among Chinese Older Adults: Data from Two Asian Metropolises. J Aging Res. 2011;2011:960848. doi: 10.4061/2011/960848. Epub 2011 Sep 14.</citation>
    <PMID>21941656</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Feng L, Ng XT, Yap P, Li J, Lee TS, Håkansson K, Kua EH, Ng TP. Marital Status and Cognitive Impairment among Community-Dwelling Chinese Older Adults: The Role of Gender and Social Engagement. Dement Geriatr Cogn Dis Extra. 2014 Oct 14;4(3):375-84. doi: 10.1159/000358584. eCollection 2014 Sep.</citation>
    <PMID>25473404</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu DX, Feng L, Yao SQ, Tian XF, Mahendran R, Kua EH. The early dementia prevention programme in Singapore. Lancet Psychiatry. 2014 Jun;1(1):9-11. doi: 10.1016/S2215-0366(14)70233-0. Epub 2014 Jun 4.</citation>
    <PMID>26360390</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 19, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 27, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 29, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National University, Singapore</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Feng Lei</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>cognitive decline</keyword>
  <keyword>choral singing</keyword>
  <keyword>health education program</keyword>
  <keyword>randomized controlled trial</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

