<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02915939</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>R01AG048931</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02915939</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Residential Care Transition Module</brief_title>
  <acronym>RCTM</acronym>
  <official_title>The Residential Care Transition Module</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>New York University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Benjamin Rose Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Emerging research on family caregiving and institutionalization has emphasized that families
      do not disengage from care responsibilities following a relative's admission to residential
      long-term care settings. The Residential Care Transition Module (RCTM) provides 6 formal
      sessions of consultation (one-to-one and family sessions) over a 4-month period to those
      family caregivers who have admitted a cognitively impaired relative to a residential
      long-term care setting (nursing home, assisted living memory care unit). The proposed mixed
      method, randomized controlled trial will determine whether and how the RCTM decreases family
      caregivers' emotional and psychological distress, placement-related strain, and increases
      relative's transitions back to the community. The RCTM will fill an important clinical and
      research gap by evaluating a psychosocial intervention designed for families following RLTC
      placement to determine whether and how this approach can help families better navigate the
      residential care transitions of relatives with Alzheimer's disease or a related dementia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Emerging research on family caregiving and institutionalization has found that families do
      not disengage from care responsibilities following relatives' admissions to residential
      long-term care settings. Families instead remain involved in a spectrum of care activities
      ranging from instrumental activities of daily living to emotional support. Perhaps for these
      reasons, a number of studies have noted that caregiving stress, depression, or other key
      outcomes remain stable or sometimes increase following residential long-term care (RLTC)
      entry for certain types of caregivers. A few interventions have attempted to increase family
      involvement after institutionalization, but no rigorous studies have demonstrated that these
      interventions are effective in helping families navigate transitions to RLTC environments.

      The Residential Care Transition Module (RCTM) provides 6 formal sessions of consultation
      (one-to-one and family sessions) over a 4-month period to those family caregivers who have
      recently admitted a relative to a RLTC setting. In this randomized controlled trial, family
      members who have admitted a cognitively impaired relative to a RLTC setting will be randomly
      assigned to the RCTM [(n = 120)] or a usual care control condition [(n = 120)]. A mixed
      methods analysis will be used to pursue the following aims: Specific Aim 1: Assess whether
      the RCTM yields statistically significant reductions in family members' primary subjective
      stress and negative mental health outcomes; Specific Aim 2) Determine whether family members
      who receive the RCTM will indicate statistically significant decreases in secondary role
      strains over a 12-month period when compared to usual care controls; Specific Aim 3)
      Determine whether RCTM family members report statistically significant decreases in
      residential care stress when compared to family members in the usual care control group; and
      Specific Aim 4) Delineate the mechanism of action of RCTM under conditions of high and low
      success by &quot;embedding&quot; qualitative components (30 semi-structured interviews) at the
      conclusion of the 12-month evaluation.

      The proposed project will fill an important clinical and research gap by evaluating a
      psychosocial intervention designed for families following RLTC placement that determines
      whether and how the RCTM can help families better navigate the residential care transitions
      of cognitively impaired relatives.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in care-related strain</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>A 7-item measure of care-related strain that assesses the stress family caregivers perceive as a result of having a relative in residential care</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in burden: Zarit Burden Interview</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>A 7-item version of the Zarit Burden Interview</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in stress: Perceived Stress Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Perceived Stress Scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer Disease</condition>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Residential Care Transition Module (RCTM) includes six in-person consultation sessions over a 4-month period conducted by a trained Transition Counselor (TC) with a primary family caregiver (self-identified as the person most responsible for providing on-going assistance to the care recipient in a residential long-term care setting such (RLTC) such as a nursing home or assisted living memory care unit.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The usual care control group will adjust for the social engagement provided to the Residential Care Transition Module (RCTM )treatment condition. The Transition Counselor (TC) will provide quarterly contact calls and the research coordinator will send a bi-annual project newsletter to all participants. If caregivers in the control group initiate contact with the TC for care needs, the TC will provide information and referral support.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>The Residential Care Transition Module</intervention_name>
    <description>Residential Care Transition Module sessions focus on the experiences of the caregiver, the care recipient, and (potentially) other family members immediately following residential long-term care (RLTC) admission. The sessions are designed to establish a therapeutic rapport with the caregiver and the family; provide a safe environment to explore stressors; examine family relational dynamics as they relate to the RLTC placement decision itself as well as the roles different family members play in the life of the caregiver and relative in RLTC; identify new modes of communication to facilitate more effective interactions with other family members and care staff; and identify effective ways to advocate for improved quality of care for and quality of life of their relatives in RLTC.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Family caregivers who consider themselves the most involved in visiting and providing
             assistance to relatives experiencing a long-stay admission to a nursing home or memory
             care assisted living unit

          -  Family caregivers must be English speaking, 21 years of age or older

          -  Family caregivers on psychotropic medications, such as anti-depressants or
             anti-psychotics, will be eligible if they have remained on a stable dosage for the
             last 3 months

          -  Family caregivers of relatives who have received a physician's diagnosis of
             Alzheimer's disease or a related dementia (ADRD)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Family caregivers who are participating in any other type of service that provides
             one-to-one psychosocial consultation (support groups excluded)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joseph E. Gaugler, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Joseph E. Gaugler, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>612-626-2485</phone>
    <email>gaug0015@umn.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota, School of Nursing, 6-153 Weaver-Densford Hall</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Joseph E. Gaugler, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>612-626-2485</phone>
      <email>gaug0015@umn.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gaugler JE, Reese M, Sauld J. A Pilot Evaluation of Psychosocial Support for Family Caregivers of Relatives with Dementia in Long-Term Care: The Residential Care Transition Module. Res Gerontol Nurs. 2015 Jul-Aug;8(4):161-72. doi: 10.3928/19404921-20150304-01. Epub 2015 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>25751083</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 19, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 26, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 27, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Family caregiving</keyword>
  <keyword>Institutionalization</keyword>
  <keyword>Residential long-term care</keyword>
  <keyword>Placement</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychosocial support</keyword>
  <keyword>Dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>Caregivers</keyword>
  <keyword>Nursing homes</keyword>
  <keyword>Assisted Living Facilities</keyword>
  <keyword>Long-Term Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Intervention Study</keyword>
  <keyword>Psychosocial Support Systems</keyword>
  <keyword>Social Support</keyword>
  <keyword>Coping</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Public access to the research data generated from this study will be offered via de-identified data files maintained by the Principal Investigator, Dr. Gaugler. All personal identifiers of family caregivers of persons with Alzheimer's disease or a related dementia (ADRD) participating in the study will be removed and replaced with random identification numbers prior to distributing WinZip data files. Dr. Gaugler plans to keep all data from the proposed 5-year project on the secure School of Nursing shared server folder for at least 7 years following study completion. Potential external investigators will be asked to complete a data user agreement. Dr. Gaugler will oversee the distribution of public data during the course of the funding period and for an indefinite time thereafter.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

