<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02910180</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00045392</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02910180</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Genetic, Metabolic, and Growth Factor Repository for Cerebrovascular Disorders</brief_title>
  <official_title>Genetic, Metabolic, and Growth Factor Repository for Cerebrovascular Disorders</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study encompasses the maintenance and utilization of a repository of samples from
      patients with cerebrovascular disease and stroke. The types of tissue taken are blood,
      cerebrospinal fluid (CSF), tissue, and microdialysis samples. Future analysis of these
      samples can potentially help investigators to better categorize groups of patients,
      understand the underlying etiology of these pathologies, identify markers that are associated
      with favorable or poor outcomes, and track changes that occur during the natural course of
      the disease or with treatment. This is a prospective observational study which will use
      samples from such patients to create this library which can be used to explore these
      questions in the future.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Genetic and metabolic profiling has become an important means to evaluate various
      pathologies, their effects on patients, and their treatments. In regards to cerebrovascular
      disease and stroke, there are a number of hypotheses which have been proposed. The levels and
      types of various angiogenic factors in the blood and tissues have been proposed to be
      predictive of patient outcome after ischemic stroke and treatment for stroke. Likewise,
      genetic factors may predict outcome or response to various types of treatments.

      The role of biological samples in furthering our understandings about cerebrovascular disease
      and treatment are well documented. Muscle microdialysis samples have confirmed the presence
      of sublethal ischemia during the induction of remote ischemic preconditioning. The effects of
      remote ischemic preconditioning on the coagulation profile, DNA methylation, and cell cycle
      gene expression of patients with aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage have also been
      elucidated. Blood samples collected in patients with intracranial arterial stenosis have
      produced many insights. Inflammatory cell profiles in patient who receive
      encephaloduroarteriosynangiosis (EDAS) surgery have been characterized. Angiogenic factor
      measurements have been shown to predict the degree of neovascularization in patients
      post-EDAS. In patients with intracranial atherosclerosis, angiogenic factor profiles were
      found to strongly correlate with failure of medical management and poor outcomes.

      It is clear that genetic and metabolic profiling are effective tools in evaluating the
      effects of cerebrovascular disease and their treatments. This study encompasses the
      maintenance and utilization of a repository of samples from patients with cerebrovascular
      disease and stroke. For every patient enrolled in the study, relevant patient information
      such as age, gender, diagnosis, medical history, family history, procedures/treatments
      received, radiological reports, and patient outcomes are recorded. This information is
      updated upon every follow-up during the study. The types of tissue taken are blood,
      cerebrospinal fluid (CSF), tissue, and microdialysis samples.

      Future analysis of these samples can potentially help investigators to better categorize
      groups of patients, understand the underlying etiology of these pathologies, identify markers
      that are associated with favorable or poor outcomes, and track changes that occur during the
      natural course of the disease or with treatment. This repository serves as the groundwork to
      explore these questions in the future.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>6 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in modified Rankin Scale (mRS) score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 Month, 3 Months, and 6 Months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in NIH Stroke Scale score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 Month, 3 Months, and 6 Months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Barthel Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 Month, 3 Months, and 6 Months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Montreal Cognitive Assessment test score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 Month, 3 Months, and 6 Months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Angiographic Neovascularization</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Analyzed in digital subtraction angiography (DSA) images</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Angiogenic Factor Measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 1 Month, 3 Months, 6 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured in blood, CSF, microdialysis samples, and tissue</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">900</enrollment>
  <condition>Cerebrovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Ischemic Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Repository</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Repository Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>The Repository Group consists of patients which have donated tissue to the repository.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Blood samples, microdialysis samples, cerebral spinal fluid, and tissue.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients diagnosed with cerebrovascular disease. This includes both non-surgical
        patients (such medically managed ischemic stroke, aneurysms, moyamoya disease,
        arteriovenous malformation, hemorrhagic stroke, etc.) and surgically treated patients
        (patients with aneurysm coiling or clipping, arteriovenous malformation resection, direct
        or indirect revascularization procedures for ischemia, etc.).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients diagnosed with cerebral vascular disease, regardless of gender, age,
             ethnicity/race, stage of disease or treatment, are eligible.

          -  Expected availability of clinical follow up data

          -  Participants must be willing to provide written, informed consent obtained in
             accordance with institutional and federal guidelines.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nestor R Gonzalez, MD, MSCR</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Neurosurgery</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Nestor R Gonzalez, MD, MSCR</last_name>
    <phone>(310) 423-0783</phone>
    <email>Nestor.Gonzalez@cshs.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Patrick Lyden, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(310) 423-0894</phone>
    <email>patrick.lyden@cshs.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90048</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Nestor R Gonzalez, MD, MSCR</last_name>
      <phone>310-423-0783</phone>
      <email>Nestor.Gonzalez@cshs.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Antoinette Anderson, BS</last_name>
      <phone>(310) 423-0783</phone>
      <email>antoinette.anderson@cshs.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Nestor R Gonzalez, MD, MSCR</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Moise Danielpour, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Alexander, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Shouri Lahiri, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Patrick Lyden, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Asma Moheet, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Axel Rosengart, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Wouter Schievink, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Konrad Schlick, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Shlee Song, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mayor F, Bilgin-Freiert A, Connolly M, Katsnelson M, Dusick JR, Vespa P, Koch S, Gonzalez NR. Effects of remote ischemic preconditioning on the coagulation profile of patients with aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage: a case-control study. Neurosurgery. 2013 Nov;73(5):808-15; discussion 815. doi: 10.1227/NEU.0000000000000098.</citation>
    <PMID>23867300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nikkola E, Laiwalla A, Ko A, Alvarez M, Connolly M, Ooi YC, Hsu W, Bui A, Pajukanta P, Gonzalez NR. Remote Ischemic Conditioning Alters Methylation and Expression of Cell Cycle Genes in Aneurysmal Subarachnoid Hemorrhage. Stroke. 2015 Sep;46(9):2445-51. doi: 10.1161/STROKEAHA.115.009618. Epub 2015 Aug 6.</citation>
    <PMID>26251247</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ooi YC, Laiwalla AN, Liou R, Gonzalez NR. Angiographic Structural Differentiation between Native Arteriogenesis and Therapeutic Synangiosis in Intracranial Arterial Steno-Occlusive Disease. AJNR Am J Neuroradiol. 2016 Jun;37(6):1086-91. doi: 10.3174/ajnr.A4675. Epub 2016 Jan 21.</citation>
    <PMID>26797139</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bilgin-Freiert A, Dusick J, Etchepare M, Stein N, Vespa P, Gonzalez NR. Muscle Microdialysis to Confirm Subischemic Injury in a Clinical Trial of Remote Ischemic Preconditioning. Stroke; a journal of cerebral circulation. 2012; 43:A3028.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dusick J, Hamilton R, Bilgin-Freiert A, Vespa P, Hu X, Asgari S, Gonzalez NR. Immediate Cerebrovascular and Brain Metabolic Effects of Remote Ischemic Preconditioning. Stroke; a journal of cerebral circulation. 2012; 43:A2698.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gonzalez, N. R., Liou, R. J., Rao, N., Hinman, J. D., Restrepo, L., Ali, L., … Saver, J. (2016). Abstract TP119: Angiogenic Factor Profiling in Medical Treatment of Intracranial Atherosclerosis (ICAS). Stroke, 47(Suppl 1), ATP119-ATP119.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gonzalez, N. R., Ooi, Y., Laiwalla, A., Restrepo, L., Ali, L., Liou, R., … Saver, J. (2016). Abstract TMP15: Circulating Antiangiogenic Profile Predicts Lower Degrees of Neovascularization After Indirect Revascularization With Encephaloduroarteriosynangiosis (EDAS) in Patients With Intracranial Atherosclerosis (ICAS). Stroke, 47(Suppl 1), ATMP15-ATMP15.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gonzalez, N. R., Connolly, M. J., Ooi, Y. C., Dusick, J., Bounni, F., Liebeskind, D. S., … Iruela-Arispe, L. (2015). Abstract 135: Angiogenic Factors and Response to Intensive Medical Management in Atherosclerotic Intracranial Arterial Stenosis. Stroke, 46(Suppl 1), A135-A135.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gonzalez, N. R., &amp; Iruela-Arispe, L. (2014). Abstract T P90: Characterization of Inflammatory Cells after EDAS Surgery in Patients with Intracranial Arterial Stenosis. Stroke, 45(Suppl 1), ATP90-ATP90.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gonzalez, N. R., Liou, R., Ooi, Y., Hinman, J. D., Rao, N., Toscano, J., … Saver, J. (2016). Abstract WP138: Effects of Intensive Medical Management (IMM) and Encephaloduroarteriosynangiosis (EDAS) On VEGFA165a/b Ratios in Patients With Intracranial Atherosclerosis (ICASi. Stroke, 47(Suppl 1), AWP138-AWP138.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 20, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 21, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 20, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 20, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 21, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nestor R. Gonzalez, MD, MSCR.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Neurosurgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tissue Repository</keyword>
  <keyword>Cerebrovascular Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>Aneurysm</keyword>
  <keyword>Arteriovenous malformation</keyword>
  <keyword>Fistula</keyword>
  <keyword>Intracranial Stenosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Registry</keyword>
  <keyword>Outcomes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cerebrovascular Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mitogens</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

