<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02910271</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PI464/15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02910271</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Features and Prevalence of Asymptomatic Peripheral Artery Disease in Patients With Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Features and Prevalence of Asymptomatic Peripheral Artery Disease in Patients With Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fundacion para la Investigacion Biomedica del Hospital Universitario Ramon y Cajal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fundacion para la Investigacion Biomedica del Hospital Universitario Ramon y Cajal</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      AIMS: Determining the clinical features and prevalence of peripheral artery disease (PAD) in
      asymptomatics patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus (T1DM) and checking the validity of the
      current recommendations regarding for PAD screening in T1DM.

      METHODOLOGY: An observational and cross-sectional prevalence study. The whole group of
      patients (sample size calculated: 299 patients) will make the Edinburgh Questionnaire for
      detecting classic symptoms of intermittent claudication, and after verifying the absence of
      symptoms and exclusion criteria, they will be included in the study. All patients will
      undergo assessment of clinical parameters related to T1DM and classic cardiovascular risk
      factors, as well as, an analytical assessment of the lipid profile, HbA1c level,
      proinflammatory profile and oxidative stress status. They will also undergo a comprehensive
      anthropometric assessment including office blood pressure (BP) monitoring and ambulatory
      24-hours BP monitoring in patients with an indication as routine clinical practice,
      assessment of cardioautonomic function, and lastly an ankle-brachial index (ABI) by Doppler
      ultrasound, in the context of routine clinical practice in patients with clinical indication,
      or as an extraordinary procedure for participating in the study in patients who do not meet
      criteria for screening according to current recommendations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      INTRODUCTION:

      PAD is a condition characterized by atherosclerotic occlusive disease of the lower
      extremities. While PAD is a major risk factor for lower-extremity amputation, it is also
      accompanied by a high likelihood for symptomatic cardiovascular and cerebrovascular disease.

      PAD is often more subtle in its presentation in patients with diabetes than in those without
      diabetes. In contrast to the focal and proximal atherosclerotic lesions of PAD found
      typically in other high-risk patients, in diabetic patients the lesions are more likely to be
      more diffuse and distal. Importantly, PAD in individuals with diabetes is usually accompanied
      by peripheral neuropathy with impaired sensory feedback, thus a classic history of
      claudication may be less common. Data from Framingham Heart Study revealed that 20% of PAD
      symptomatic patients had diabetes mellitus, but probably, this data greatly underestimates
      PAD prevalence. As well, it has been reported that of those with PAD, over one-half of
      patients are asymptomatic or have atypical symptoms, about one-third have claudication, and
      the rest have more severe disease. Also, patients with diabetes who have been identified with
      PAD are more prone to sudden ischemia secondary to arterial thrombosis or to have a pivotal
      event leading to neuroischemic ulceration or infection that rapidly results in an acute
      presentation with critical limb ischemia and risk of amputation.

      However, is important to note, that most clinical data about PAD and diabetes, are becoming
      from population studies and randomized clinical trials, made up exclusively with type 2
      patients, or more frequently, after analyzing all patients with diabetes diagnosis, without
      distinction between T1 to T2 subtypes. Thus, although much is known regarding PAD in the
      general population, the assessment and management of PAD in those with diabetes is less
      clear, especially in patients with T1DM diagnosis.

      In 2003, a Consensus Development Conference was held regarding PAD in diabetes. After a
      series of lectures by experts in the field of endocrinology, cardiology, vascular surgery,
      orthopedic surgery, podiatry, and nursing, a vascular medicine panel was asked to answer
      questions about the epidemiology and impact of PAD in people with diabetes, diagnosis and
      treatment of PAD, but always generalizing the management of T1 and T2 diabetes, under the
      unique same term of &quot;diabetes&quot;.

      PAD diagnosing in patients with diabetes is of clinical importance for two reasons:

      i) to identify patients at high risk of subsequent cardiovascular and cerebrovascular disease
      ii) to diagnose and treat PAD, which may be associated with functional disability and limb
      loss.

      Preventive measures in a patient with subclinical disease will make possible to avoid acute
      and chronic complications. Therefore, the knowledge about the true prevalence of PAD in T1DM
      is relevant for setting the screening indication in this patients, given that this is
      frequently asymptomatic and it might be clinically different at presentation compared to type
      2 diabetes patients.

      AIMS:

      The main objective of this works is determine the clinical features and prevalence of PAD in
      asymptomatics patients with T1DM and check the validity of the current recommendations
      regarding for PAD screening in T1DM.

      METHODOLOGY:

      Observational and cross-sectional prevalence study will be conducted. A consecutive
      population of type 1 patients from our clinics (sample size calculated: 299 patients) will be
      screened by the Edinburgh Questionnaire (Leng &amp; Fowkes 1992) for detecting classic symptoms
      of intermittent claudication, and after verifying the absence of symptoms and exclusion
      criteria, they will be included in the study.

        -  All patients will undergo assessment of clinical parameters related to T1DM (years of
           the initial diagnosis, insulin treatment, metabolic control, microvascular chronic
           complications), cardiovascular risk factors (hypertension, dyslipidemia, chronic
           smoking), prior cardiovascular disease (coronary and cerebrovascular disease), as well
           as, an analytical assessment including a lipid profile, HbA1c level, proinflammatory
           markers (C-reactive protein, homocysteine) and oxidative stress status.

        -  They will undergo a comprehensive anthropometric evaluation: weight, height, body mass
           index [BMI (kg / m2)], abdominal and hip circumference, and body fat percentage to total
           body weight by bioelectrical impedance.

        -  Office BP and ambulatory 24-hours BP monitoring in patients with an indication as
           routine clinical practice (Mancia G. et al 2013).

        -  Assessment of cardiovascular autonomic dysfunction: orthostatism systolic and diastolic
           BP, orthostatism heart rate, heart rate variability to expiration / inspiration,
           Valsalva and orthostatic.

        -  Diabetic foot exploration (including bilateral peripheral pulses, Neuropathy Symptoms
           Score questionnaire, monofilament exploration, and calibrated tuning fork).

        -  The ABI will be performed by Doppler ultrasound (HADECO® Minidop 8 Mhz), in the context
           of routine clinical practice in patients with clinical indication, or an extraordinary
           procedure for participating in the study in patients who do not meet criteria for
           screening according to current recommendations.

      The ABI will be measured in both posterior tibial and pedia arteries. Interpretation of ABI
      wil be as follows: Average: 0.90 to 1.20; mild arterial obstruction: 0.70 to 0.89; moderate
      arterial obstruction: 0.40 to 0.69; severe arterial obstruction &lt; 0.40; poorly compressible
      arteries &gt; 1.20.

      In patients with ABI &gt; 1.20 or &lt; 0.9, the examination will be completed as recommended
      guidelines about asymptomatic PAD diagnosis by assessing the graphic recording blood flow and
      assessment index finger-arm.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of PAD in asymptomatic patients with T1DM assessed by ankle-branchial index.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between anthropometric parameters and asymptomatic peripheral artery disease in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of anthropometric parameters among patients with and without peripheral artery disease.
Anthropometric evaluation includes:
Body mass index.
Waist circumference.
Body fat percentage with respect to total body weight assessed by bioelectrical impedance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between lipid profile and asymptomatic artery disease in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of lipids among patients with and without peripheral artery disease.
Lipid profile includes:
Total cholesterol.
LDL-cholesterol.
HDL-cholesterol.
Triglycerides.
Total cholesterol / HDL-cholesterol.
NonHDL cholesterol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between glycemic control and asymptomatic artery disease in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of glycosylated hemoglobin levels among patients with and without peripheral artery disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between C-reactive protein and asymptomatic artery disease in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of circulating C-reactive protein among patients with and without peripheral artery disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association between homocysteine and asymptomatic artery disease in patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of circulating homocysteine levels among patients with and without peripheral artery disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number and percentage of patients with pathological ankle-branchial index without screening criteria according to the current recommendations for subjects with type 1 diabetes mellitus.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of ankle-branchial index by doppler technique among patients with and without screening criteria according to the current recommendations for subjects with type 1 diabetes mellitus.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number and percentage of patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus, cardiovascular autonomic dysfunction and asymptomatic PAD.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Cardiovascular autonomic dysfunction will be assessed by orthostatism induced abnormal changes in systolic BP and diastolic BP.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number and percentage of patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus, cardiovascular autonomic dysfunction and asymptomatic PAD.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Cardiovascular autonomic dysfunction will be assessed by orthostatism induced abnormal changes in heart rate.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number and percentage of patients with type 1 diabetes mellitus, cardiovascular autonomic dysfunction and asymptomatic PAD.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Cardiovascular autonomic dysfunction will be assessed by RR interval variability response to expiration / inspiration, Valsalva maneuver and orthostatism.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of asymptomatic atherosclerotic carotid disease in patients with asymptomatic PAD.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Asymptomatic carotid atherosclerotic disease will be assessed by measuring the thickness of the intima by doppler technique.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">299</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <condition>Peripheral Artery Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with prior diagnosis of T1DM ≥ 18 years old, consecutively selected from T1DM and
        Insulin Pump clinics of a tertiary Hospital in Madrid.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous diagnosis of T1DM before 30 years of age.

        DM diagnostic criteria:

          -  DM cardinal symptoms (polyuria, polydipsia, unexplained weight loss) with plasma
             glucose ≥ 200 mg / dl, or diagnosis as diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA).

          -  fasting plasma glucose (≥ 8 h) ≥ 126 mg / dl.

          -  plasma glucose at 2 h in testing oral glucose tolerance test (75 g glucose) ≥ 200 mg /
             dl.

          -  glycosylated hemoglobin (HbA1c) ≥ 6.5% [as certified by the National method
             Glycohemoglobin Standardized Program (NGSP) and standardized according to the Diabetes
             Control and Complication Trial trial (DCCT)].

        The criteria b, c and d require confirmation, except in cases of hyperglycemia with acute
        decompensation (criteria a).

          -  Positive determination of a autoantibody serum markers of immune destruction against
             antigens cytoplasm of the islet cells (ICA), anti-insulin (AAI), and / or anti protein
             glutamate decarboxylase (GADA) at initial diagnosis time or during the course of the
             disease.

        Acceptance of participation in the study and sign the informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior diagnosis of PAD, diabetic foot, leg amputation or symptoms in line with PAD
             according to the Edinburgh questionnaire for intermittent claudication.

          -  Diagnosis of type 2 diabetes, gestational diabetes, latent autoimmune diabetes in
             adults (LADA) or maturity-onset diabetes of youth (MODY) diabetes.

          -  Current pregnancy, institutionalized or terminal illness subjects.

          -  Refusal to participate in the study or to sign the informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>María Lía Nattero Chávez</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Diabetes, Obesity and Human Reproduction Research Group, Department of Endocrinology and Nutrition, Hospital Universitario Ramón y Cajal, Universidad de Alcalá, Instituto Ramón y Cajal de Investigación Sanitaria (IRYCIS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>María Lía Nattero Chávez</last_name>
    <phone>0034913369029</phone>
    <email>lianattero@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Manuel Luque Ramírez, MD. PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0034913369029</phone>
    <email>manuel.luque@salud.madrid.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Diabetes, Obesity and Human Reproduction Research Group, Department of Endocrinology and Nutrition, Hospital Universitario Ramón y Cajal, Universidad de Alcalá, Instituto Ramón y Cajal de Investigación Sanitaria (IRYCIS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>María Lía Nattero Chávez</last_name>
      <phone>0034913369029</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Manuel Luque Ramírez</last_name>
      <phone>0034913369029</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Ferranti SD, de Boer IH, Fonseca V, Fox CS, Golden SH, Lavie CJ, Magge SN, Marx N, McGuire DK, Orchard TJ, Zinman B, Eckel RH. Type 1 diabetes mellitus and cardiovascular disease: a scientific statement from the American Heart Association and American Diabetes Association. Circulation. 2014 Sep 23;130(13):1110-30. doi: 10.1161/CIR.0000000000000034. Epub 2014 Aug 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25114208</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>American Diabetes Association. Peripheral arterial disease in people with diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2003 Dec;26(12):3333-41. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14633825</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murabito JM, D'Agostino RB, Silbershatz H, Wilson WF. Intermittent claudication. A risk profile from The Framingham Heart Study. Circulation. 1997 Jul 1;96(1):44-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9236415</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hirsch AT, Haskal ZJ, Hertzer NR, Bakal CW, Creager MA, Halperin JL, Hiratzka LF, Murphy WR, Olin JW, Puschett JB, Rosenfield KA, Sacks D, Stanley JC, Taylor LM Jr, White CJ, White J, White RA, Antman EM, Smith SC Jr, Adams CD, Anderson JL, Faxon DP, Fuster V, Gibbons RJ, Halperin JL, Hiratzka LF, Hunt SA, Jacobs AK, Nishimura R, Ornato JP, Page RL, Riegel B; American Association for Vascular Surgery; Society for Vascular Surgery; Society for Cardiovascular Angiography and Interventions; Society for Vascular Medicine and Biology; Society of Interventional Radiology; ACC/AHA Task Force on Practice Guidelines; American Association of Cardiovascular and Pulmonary Rehabilitation; National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute; Society for Vascular Nursing; TransAtlantic Inter-Society Consensus; Vascular Disease Foundation. ACC/AHA 2005 guidelines for the management of patients with peripheral arterial disease (lower extremity, renal, mesenteric, and abdominal aortic): executive summary a collaborative report from the American Association for Vascular Surgery/Society for Vascular Surgery, Society for Cardiovascular Angiography and Interventions, Society for Vascular Medicine and Biology, Society of Interventional Radiology, and the ACC/AHA Task Force on Practice Guidelines (Writing Committee to Develop Guidelines for the Management of Patients With Peripheral Arterial Disease) endorsed by the American Association of Cardiovascular and Pulmonary Rehabilitation; National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute; Society for Vascular Nursing; TransAtlantic Inter-Society Consensus; and Vascular Disease Foundation. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2006 Mar 21;47(6):1239-312.</citation>
    <PMID>16545667</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Standards of Medical Care in Diabetes-2016: Summary of Revisions. Diabetes Care. 2016 Jan;39 Suppl 1:S4-5. doi: 10.2337/dc16-S003. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26696680</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leng GC, Fowkes FG. The Edinburgh Claudication Questionnaire: an improved version of the WHO/Rose Questionnaire for use in epidemiological surveys. J Clin Epidemiol. 1992 Oct;45(10):1101-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1474406</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parati G, Stergiou G, O'Brien E, Asmar R, Beilin L, Bilo G, Clement D, de la Sierra A, de Leeuw P, Dolan E, Fagard R, Graves J, Head GA, Imai Y, Kario K, Lurbe E, Mallion JM, Mancia G, Mengden T, Myers M, Ogedegbe G, Ohkubo T, Omboni S, Palatini P, Redon J, Ruilope LM, Shennan A, Staessen JA, vanMontfrans G, Verdecchia P, Waeber B, Wang J, Zanchetti A, Zhang Y; European Society of Hypertension Working Group on Blood Pressure Monitoring and Cardiovascular Variability. European Society of Hypertension practice guidelines for ambulatory blood pressure monitoring. J Hypertens. 2014 Jul;32(7):1359-66. doi: 10.1097/HJH.0000000000000221.</citation>
    <PMID>24886823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 10, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 19, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 22, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 25, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 25, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 26, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Arterial Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

