<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02912000</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2016P000711/MGH</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02912000</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>TEACH: Technology Evaluation to Address Child Health</brief_title>
  <acronym>TEACH</acronym>
  <official_title>TEACH: Technology Evaluation to Address Child Health</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Massachusetts General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Academic Pediatric Association</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fonds de la Recherche en Santé du Québec</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Massachusetts General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed study is a pre- /post-implementation study in a pediatric practice with a
      control practice designed to test the feasibility and effectiveness of an electronic
      screening and service delivery tool for three modifiable health risk factors in pediatrics:
      parental tobacco use, sugar-sweetened beverages consumption, and poor dental care
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Key procedures of the study include:

        1. Practices will be contacted via letters, emails and in-person discussion with practice
           leaders.

        2. Among practices that say yes to recruitment, a total of 2 practices will be randomly
           assigned to one of two groups: 1) Implementation of the electronic screening tool 2)
           care as usual

        3. Control and intervention practices will be trained in integrating a Research Assistant
           (RA) who will be hired, trained, and paid by the research study. RAs will be through
           networking, temporary officeservice contractors, and other local resources.

        4. A notice to parents and teenagers will be posted where all can see it when registering
           for their pediatric visit. The notice will announce that the practice is participating
           in a research study and that parents/guardians and teenagers may be approached by a
           study RA. Practice staff will refer parents to the RA for the Eligibility Screener.

        5. In the control practice and in the pre-implementation phase of the intervention
           practice, after being seen by the pediatric clinician, the parent will be approached by
           the RA stationed near the exit of the clinic for an exit interview consisting of the
           Exit Survey. Alternatively, it the practice prefers to not have RAs directly approaching
           patients, practice staff will refer the potential participants to the RA after checkout.
           Parents who agree to study participation will learn about the study, sign the consent,
           and complete the Exit Survey for enrolled parents/guardians. Teenagers will not be
           invited or involved in this part of the study.

        6. In the post-implementation phase of the intervention practice, practice staff will
           follow a script at the check-in desk to refer parents to the RA. Parents will be
           approached by the RA after checking in for their appointment. Parents who agree to study
           participation will complete the Intake Survey. If they are accompanied by a teenager
           (aged 13-18 years old, the teenager will also be presented the study. Parents will be
           invited to consent to their child participate in the study. If the child is 13 years
           old, we will seek assent from the child to answer a portion of the intake survey. If
           he/she is 14 years or older, consent will be sought, and if obtained, the teenager will
           be asked to complete a section of the survey, on the same risk factors. We are asking
           that written documentation of these being waived and that consent/assent be inferred
           from survey participation, which will be documented in the research record. Teenagers
           will not be compensated for this section of the study that should take less than 5
           minutes to complete. After completion of the survey, the adult participants will
           receive, if they desire, an information sheet on the risk factors identified, as well as
           a summary of the screening questionnaire, to be handed to the clinician they are coming
           to see that day. If no risk factor is identified, no clinician handout will be given.
           Teenagers' response to the survey will not be shared with parents and will only be
           available to the principal investigator and co-investigator. Adult participants will
           also be asked to reach out to the RA after their appointment to complete the Exit
           Survey, following the procedure mentioned above.

        7. One month after the recruitment and completion of the Exit Survey, adult participants
           will be contacted by phone by the RA or the Principal Investigator (PI) to complete the
           Follow-up survey. Consent for this survey will be obtain as part of the study initial
           consent and preferred phone numbers will be obtained directly from the participants.
           After completion of the Follow-up Survey, participation in the survey will be complete.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reported screening and counseling by physicians about parental smoking, child dentist appointment, and sugar-sweetened beverages</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre-implementation (baseline) and Post-implementation</time_frame>
    <description>Higher rates of screening, counseling, and service delivery by clinicians in the period after implementation than at baseline (pre-implementation).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent report of behavior change intention related to parental smoking, child sugar sweetened beverage consumption and child's dental appointment</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and one month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Compared to the pre-implementation period, parents in the post-implementation period will have greater behavior change intention for each modifiable risk factor. This difference will be greater in the intervention practice than in the control practice.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reported behavior change related to parental smoking, child sugar sweetened beverage consumption and child's dental appointment</measure>
    <time_frame>one month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>At one month follow-up, the intervention group will have a greater increase in reported healthy behavior than the control group.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">650</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Dental Caries</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention group will receive the TEACH intervention - an electronic tablet screening in waiting room for the modifiable risk factors</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Care as usual: No electronic tablet in waiting room</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TEACH intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The TEACH intervention screens family for three modifiable behaviors ahead of the clinical encounter: parental tobacco use, children consumption of sugar-sweetened beverages and child dental health. The information from the screening is then shared with clinicians.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Parent of a child aged 0-18 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Parents under age 18

          -  Parents who have a child with a medical emergency (any condition requiring transfer
             for immediate medical intervention)

          -  Non-consenting individuals

          -  Non-English speakers
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jonathan P Winickoff, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 21, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 22, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 23, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Massachusetts General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jonathan P. Winickoff, MD, MPH</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dental Health Services</keyword>
  <keyword>Sugar-Sweetened Beverages</keyword>
  <keyword>Tobacco control</keyword>
  <keyword>Pediatrics</keyword>
  <keyword>Parents</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dental Caries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

