<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00576095</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2R01MH050604-10</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>MH50604</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00576095</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00048269</nct_alias>
    <nct_alias>NCT00185926</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical and Biological Characteristics of Psychotic Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>Hypothalamic-Pituitary-Adrenal (HPA)/ Dopamine Axis in Psychotic Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to investigate the relationships among findings in
      structural and functional neuroimaging, cognitive testing and HPA
      (hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal) axis dysregulation in psychotic depression.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Eligibility Procedures: Before entering the study and prior to any other procedures, you will
      be asked to read and sign this consent form. To determine if you are eligible for our study,
      you will then have a general medical (including menstrual cycle history on female patients)
      and psychiatric history taken, a physical examination your vital signs (blood pressure,
      pulse), height, weight, waist/hip ratio will be measured, and various psychiatric evaluations
      will be conducted. We will be video recording the psychiatric diagnostic assessment of every
      5th patient who enrolls in our study.

      On Day 1, your mood will be evaluated using a series of commonly used diagnostic instruments
      and rating scales. We will repeat the medical exam, blood and urine lab tests you had at your
      initial screening visit if it has been more than 4 weeks (30 days) since your eligibility
      screening.

      The rest of the study includes an MRI, neuropsychological testing, questionnaires, and blood
      draws.

      The MRI (called magnetic resonance imaging, MRI) involves having a picture of your brain
      taken using a magnet while a series of tasks is administered to you. The MRI scan procedures
      will take approximately 1 hour.

      The neuropsychological testing consists of a series of tests to assess your memory and
      concentration (neuropsychological means the way your brain processes and completes specific
      tasks.) This testing, including directions, will take approximately 3 hours of your time. You
      will also be asked to complete several questionnaires during your hospital stay. These
      questionnaires ask for your views about your personality, your childhood experiences your
      quality of life, your mood and a variety of aspects of your daily functioning. The
      questionnaires may be completed anytime during your stay and will take about 2.5 hours to
      finish

      The blood draws are done at the GCRC, where you will stay for 2 nights.

      The following blood draw procedures will be performed for all participants on Day 1: At 4pm
      on Day 1, an intravenous line (IV; needle inserted into a vein) will be placed in your arm to
      draw hourly blood samples used for the measure of adrenocorticotropin (ACTH) and cortisol.
      ACTH is a hormone that controls the release of cortisol (a stress hormone) in your system and
      both of these hormones levels change under stressful conditions. The blood samples are taken
      in small amounts (approximately 1/2 teaspoon) and will be collected at 2pm and 4pm on
      Baseline Day 1, and then on the hour, every hour, starting at 6pm and ending at 9am the next
      day. A total of 72 ml(approximately 5 tablespoons) of blood will be drawn. The IV line will
      be removed following the last blood draw. If you presently live in a time zone different from
      the Pacific Standard Time zone (for example, Eastern Standard Time zone), we may begin taking
      hourly blood samples as early as 3pm on Baseline Day 1 in order to more accurately measure
      your body's daily rhythm of hormones.

      The following blood draw procedures will be performed for all participants on Day 2: At 2pm
      on Baseline Day 2, you will have another IV line placed in your arm to draw hourly blood
      samples used for the measure of ACTH and Cortisol. At 3pm, you will be given 0.5mg (five
      0.1mg tablets) of Fludrocortisone. Cortisol and ACTH are taken in small amounts
      (approximately 1/2 teaspoon) and will be collected on the hour, every hour, starting at 2 pm
      and ending at 7pm, then every 30 minutes until 12 midnight. Melatonin will be collected at
      6:00pm, 7:00pm and then every 30 minutes until 12 midnight. Following the last blood draw, a
      blood sample will be taken for a clinical laboratory assessment to ensure your safety
      following Fludrocortisone administration. A total of 66ml's (4 1/2 tablespoons) of blood will
      be drawn. At 12 midnight, the IV line will then be removed and your vital signs will be
      taken.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cortisol</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Hourly serum cortisol</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive function</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Standard domains - including verbal memory, executive functioning, attention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">73</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Psychotic Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Depressive Disorder, Major</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PMD</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients diagnosed with major depression with psychotic features</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NPMD</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients diagnosed with major depression without psychotic features</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants with no psychiatric or depression history</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      serum
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Major depression with psychosis Major depression without psychosis Healthy controls
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:Inclusion criteria for PMD (individuals with Psychotic Major Depression)
        and NPMDs (individuals with Non-Psychotic Major Depression) are as follows:

          1. DSM IV diagnosis of Major Depressive Disorder with or without psychotic features,
             Bipolar II Disorder with or without psychotic features in a major depressive episode.

          2. 21-item HAM-D score greater than or equal to 21.

          3. Thase Core Endogenomorphic Scale score greater than or equal to 6 on the items
             included in the 21-item HDRS.

          4. Between 21 - 85 years of age.

          5. If currently taking antipsychotic, antidepressant, anticonvulsant, and/or
             mood-stabilizing medications, must be stable on the medication for at least one-week
             prior to entering the study.

          6. Pre-existing (current) primary treating psychiatrist for subjects with psychotic
             features.

          7. Any secondary diagnoses from the anxiety disorder spectrum is acceptable. Primary
             pre-existing chronic Obsessive-Compulsive Disorder(OCD) will be an exclusion criteria.

        Inclusion criteria for healthy controls are as follows:

          1. Between 21 - 85 years of age.

          2. Taking no medications

          3. Have a HAM-D score of less than or equal to 5.

        Exclusion Criteria:Exclusion criteria for PMDs and NPMDs are as follows:

          1. ECT in the 4 months prior to the study.

          2. Abuse of drugs or alcohol in the 6 months prior to study.

          3. Unstable or untreated hypertension, or cardiovascular disease.

          4. If participating in the blood draw portion of the protocol, endocrine disorders are
             exclusionary.

          5. Use of additional prescription medications, street drugs, or alcohol during the week
             before the study.

          6. Any Axis II diagnosis or traits which would make participation in the study difficult.

          7. Current pregnancy or lactation.

        Exclusion criteria for healthy controls:

          1. Personal history of Axis I or Axis II disorders.

          2. Active unstable medical problems.

          3. Abuse of drugs or alcohol in the 6 months prior to study.

          4. Use of additional prescription medications, street drugs, or alcohol during the week
             before the study.

          5. Currently pregnant or lactating.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alan Schatzberg</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer Keller</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 14, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 14, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 18, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 14, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

