<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00579111</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>19386</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>FAB</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00579111</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00625144</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reduced Intensity Preparative Regimen Followed by Stem Cell Transplant (FAB)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Reduced-Intensity Preparative Regiment With Fludarabine, Busulfan, And Alemtuzumab (Campath 1H) Followed By Allogeneic Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplant For Malignant And Non-Malignant Hematological Diseases</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Center for Cell and Gene Therapy, Baylor College of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Methodist Hospital System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Baylor College of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Blood disorders such as leukemia or lymphoma or hemoglobinopathies can benefit from receiving
      an allogeneic (meaning that the cells are from a donor) stem cell transplant. Stem cells are
      created in the bone marrow. They grow into different types of blood cells that the body
      needs, including red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets. In a transplant, the
      body's stem cells would be killed and then replaced by stem cells from the donor. Usually,
      patients are given very high doses of chemotherapy (drugs which kill cancer cells) prior to
      receiving a stem cell transplant. However, patients that are older, have received several
      prior treatments, or have other organ diseases are at a high risk of getting life-threatening
      treatment-related side effects from high doses of chemotherapy. Over the past several years,
      some doctors have begun to use lower doses of chemotherapy for preparing patients for a stem
      cell transplant.

      A condition that can occur after a stem cell transplant from a donor is Graft Versus Host
      Disease (GVHD). It is a rare but serious disorder that can strike persons whose immune system
      is suppressed and have received either a blood transfusion or a bone marrow transplant.
      Symptoms may include skin rash, intestinal problems similar to inflammation of the bowel and
      liver dysfunction.

      This research study uses a combination of lower-dose chemotherapy agents that is slightly
      different from those that have been used before.

      The medicines that will be used in this study are Fludarabine, Busulfan, both chemotherapy
      medicines, and Campath. Campath is a monoclonal antibody (a type of substance produced in the
      laboratory that binds to cancer cells). It helps the immune system see the cancer cell as
      something that needs to be destroyed.

      This research study will help us learn if using Fludarabine, Busulfan and Campath prior to an
      allogeneic stem cell transplant can provide treatment for blood disorders while decreasing
      the incidence of side effects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Allogeneic stem cell transplantation with high-dose chemotherapy affords a better chance of
      cure of malignant and non-malignant hematological diseases compared to autologous
      transplantation, because of the lack of stem cell contamination and the immune mediated graft
      vs. leukemia effect. Unfortunately, high-dose chemotherapy and allogeneic stem cell
      transplantation has a substantial treatment related mortality, that is particularly high in
      older patients (greater than 50 yrs of age), or in those with co-morbidities such as
      congestive heart disease and pulmonary disease. Patients who have pre-existing infections or
      who have had multiple relapses with prior chemotherapy are also at high risk. In all these
      groups, treatment related mortality may exceed 50%, making them ineligible for high-dose
      chemotherapy and allogeneic stem cell transplantation.

      Recently interest has increased in using less toxic chemotherapy protocols that are termed
      submyeloablative. The intent is to allow partial engraftment of a donor immune and
      hemopoietic systems with subsequent progressive replacement of the host's own hemopoiesis and
      immunity. As the donor immune system becomes established, patients may develop full donor
      chimerism, without passing through the period of prolonged aplasia associated with
      conventional conditioning regimens, and with less of the associated toxicity. Preliminary
      results in high-risk patients have shown treatment related mortality (TRM) of 15-20%, versus
      50% expected, with an overall survival rate of 70-80% at 1-2 years post transplant.

      As might be anticipated, the major problem with sub-ablative conditioning is that the graft
      failure rate is increased, with published figures of 5-30% versus 1-5% predicted in fully
      ablated patients. The incorporation of lymphodepleting antibodies in the preliminary
      conditioning regimen may allow these rejection rates to be diminished. Moreover, a highly
      efficient lymphodepleting MAb or MAb combination might be successfully substituted in part or
      in whole for cytotoxic and immunosuppressive drugs, further increasing the safety and
      efficacy of the subablative approach to stem cell transplantation. Our own data using the
      crude polyclonal mixture of antibodies in ATG as a component of pre-transplant conditioning
      revealed an improvement in engraftment during matched unrelated donor transplantation.The
      lymphodepleting monoclonal antibody Campath IH has many of the properties desired for this
      application, and we propose to incorporate it in our conditioning regimen. Since CAMPATH1H
      persists after infusion, we would expect it to have additional anti-GvHD effector function,
      further reducing treatment related mortality (TRM).

      The following preparative regimen will be delivered to all patients:

        1. Busulfan 3.2 mg/kg/day IV daily for 2 days, infused over 3 hours, on Day -5 and Day -4

        2. Fludarabine 30mg/m2/day IV daily for 4 days on Day -5 to D -2

        3. Campath 10 mg/day IV daily for 3 days on days -6 to D-4.

      Because CAMPATH-1H infusions will provide a persisting level of antibody over the transplant
      period, it will contribute to anti-GvHD activity. Additional Graft vs. host disease
      prophylaxis will consist of FK506 administered from Day-2.

      The stem cells will be infused on day 0.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    slow accrual
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>June 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Patients With Successful Donor Engraftment</measure>
    <time_frame>100 days</time_frame>
    <description>Each patient will be classified as a success or failure. A success will be defined as engraftment of at least 35% of cells 100 days after transplant.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Patients With Treatment Related Grade III or IV Non-hematological Toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>100 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">4</enrollment>
  <condition>Myelodysplastic and Myeloproliferative Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Acute Myelogenous Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia</condition>
  <condition>Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Plasma Cell Dyscrasia</condition>
  <condition>Lymphoproliferative Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Hematologic Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HLA-identical sibling transplant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Recipients of HLA identical sibling stem cell transplants</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Unrelated Matched or Single Antigen Mismatched transplant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Recipients of unrelated matched or single antigen mismatched donor stem cell transplant or single antigen mismatched family donor stem cell transplants</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Campath</intervention_name>
    <description>10 mg/day IV daily for 3 days on days -6 to D-4. Campath may be omitted from the conditioning regimen for patients with malignant diseases and matched related donor transplants</description>
    <arm_group_label>HLA-identical sibling transplant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Unrelated Matched or Single Antigen Mismatched transplant</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Alemtuzumab</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Busulfan</intervention_name>
    <description>3.2 mg/kg/day IV daily for 2 days, infused over 3 hours, on Day -5 and Day -4</description>
    <arm_group_label>HLA-identical sibling transplant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Unrelated Matched or Single Antigen Mismatched transplant</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fludarabine</intervention_name>
    <description>30mg/m2/day IV daily for 4 days on Day -5 to D -2</description>
    <arm_group_label>HLA-identical sibling transplant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Unrelated Matched or Single Antigen Mismatched transplant</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hematopoietic stem cell infusion</intervention_name>
    <description>Peripheral blood stem cells when possible. Bone marrow cells will be used if peripheral blood cells are insufficient or unavailable.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HLA-identical sibling transplant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Unrelated Matched or Single Antigen Mismatched transplant</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FK-506</intervention_name>
    <description>FK-506 at a dose of 0.03 mg/kd/day will be administered via continuous infusion over 24 hours from 4pm on Day -2 until engraftment or when the patient is able to take PO, then 0.03 mg/kg PO every 12 hours.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HLA-identical sibling transplant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Unrelated Matched or Single Antigen Mismatched transplant</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Tacrolimus</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Diagnosis of myelodysplastic and myeloproliferative disorders, acute myelogenous
             leukemia, acute lymphoblastic leukemia, chronic myelogenous leukemia, multiple
             myeloma, plasma cell dyscrasia, lymphoproliferative disorders (non-Hodgkin lymphoma,
             hairy cell leukemia, chronic lymphocytic leukemia, and Hodgkin's disease) and non
             malignant hematologic diseases considered treatable with an allogeneic transplant
             including but not limited to bone marrow failure syndrome, hemoglobinopathy and severe
             immunodeficiency states.

          2. Performance status 0-2 on Zubrod scale

          3. Ejection fraction &gt; 30%

          4. AST/ALT and bilirubin not &gt; 4 times normal

          5. FEV1 greater than 1.0 and diffusion capacity &gt; 40%

          6. Age birth to 70 years of age

          7. Conditions that increase treatment related mortality (need more than one to be
             eligible):

               -  Age &gt; 35 years

               -  EF of less than 45%

               -  DLCO less than 50% or FEV1 50-75% of predicted value

               -  Diabetes mellitus

               -  Renal insufficiency, defined by increase in serum creatinine level of 1.5 times
                  ULN or decrease in GFR by 25%

               -  Prior recent history of systemic fungal infection

               -  3rd or greater remission of AML or ALL

               -  More than 1 year of diagnosis (CML or myeloma patients only)

               -  Multiple types of treatment regimens (equal to or more than 3)

               -  Prior autologous or allogeneic stem cell transplantation

               -  Significant Grade III or IV neurologic or hepatic toxicity as defined by NCI CTC
                  toxicity from previous treatment

               -  No matched sibling donor

          8. Available healthy donor without any contraindications for donation

               -  5/6 or 6/6 related

               -  5/6 or 6/6 unrelated (molecular typing for DRB1)

          9. Patient and/or responsible person able to understand and sign consent

         10. For women of childbearing potential, negative pregnancy test

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant and lactating women or women unwilling to use contraception.

          2. HIV positive patient.

          3. Uncontrolled intercurrent infection.

          4. Refractory AML or ALL.

          5. Untreated blast crisis for CML.

          6. Uncontrolled high-grade lymphoproliferative disease/lymphoma.

          7. Unstable angina and uncompensated congestive heart failure (Zubrod of 3 or greater).

          8. Severe chronic pulmonary disease requiring oxygen (Zubrod of 3 or greater).

          9. Hemodialysis dependent.

         10. Active Hepatitis or cirrhosis with total bilirubin, SGOT, and SGPT greater than 3 x
             normal.

         11. Serum creatinine &gt;2x ULN.

         12. Unstable cerebral vascular disease and recent hemorrhagic stroke (less than 6 months).

         13. Active CNS disease from hematological disorder.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Rammurti T Kamble, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Texas Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Methodist Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 19, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 20, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 21, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>July 3, 2012</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>July 3, 2012</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">August 9, 2012</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 29, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 29, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 4, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Baylor College of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Rammurti Kamble</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Myelodysplastic and Myeloproliferative Disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Myelogenous Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Lymphoblastic Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Myelogenous Leukemia</keyword>
  <keyword>Multiple Myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>Plasma Cell dyscrasia</keyword>
  <keyword>Lymphoproliferative disorders</keyword>
  <keyword>Hematologic Diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Fludarabine</keyword>
  <keyword>Busulfan</keyword>
  <keyword>Campath</keyword>
  <keyword>Alemtuzumab</keyword>
  <keyword>allogeneic stem cell transplant</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Precursor Cell Lymphoblastic Leukemia-Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Lymphoid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myelogenous, Chronic, BCR-ABL Positive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myeloproliferative Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoproliferative Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hematologic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Paraproteinemias</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fludarabine phosphate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Alemtuzumab</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Busulfan</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tacrolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vidarabine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>HLA-identical Sibling Transplant</title>
          <description>Recipients of HLA identical sibling stem cell transplants</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Unrelated Matched or Single Antigen Mismatched Transplant</title>
          <description>Recipients of unrelated matched or single antigen mismatched donor stem cell transplant or single antigen mismatched family donor stem cell transplants</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="3"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="1"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>HLA-identical Sibling Transplant</title>
          <description>Recipients of HLA identical sibling stem cell transplants</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Unrelated Matched or Single Antigen Mismatched Transplant</title>
          <description>Recipients of unrelated matched or single antigen mismatched donor stem cell transplant or single antigen mismatched family donor stem cell transplants</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="3"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="1"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="4"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age, Customized</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Between 50 and 65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Number of Patients With Successful Donor Engraftment</title>
        <description>Each patient will be classified as a success or failure. A success will be defined as engraftment of at least 35% of cells 100 days after transplant.</description>
        <time_frame>100 days</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>HLA-identical Sibling Transplant</title>
            <description>Recipients of HLA identical sibling stem cell transplants</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Unrelated Matched or Single Antigen Mismatched Transplant</title>
            <description>Recipients of unrelated matched or single antigen mismatched donor stem cell transplant or single antigen mismatched family donor stem cell transplants</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Patients With Successful Donor Engraftment</title>
          <description>Each patient will be classified as a success or failure. A success will be defined as engraftment of at least 35% of cells 100 days after transplant.</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="3"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="1"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Number of Patients With Treatment Related Grade III or IV Non-hematological Toxicity</title>
        <time_frame>100 days</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>HLA-identical Sibling Transplant</title>
            <description>Recipients of HLA identical sibling stem cell transplants</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Unrelated Matched or Single Antigen Mismatched Transplant</title>
            <description>Recipients of unrelated matched or single antigen mismatched donor stem cell transplant or single antigen mismatched family donor stem cell transplants</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Patients With Treatment Related Grade III or IV Non-hematological Toxicity</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="3"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="1"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>HLA-identical Sibling Transplant</title>
          <description>Recipients of HLA identical sibling stem cell transplants</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Unrelated Matched or Single Antigen Mismatched Transplant</title>
          <description>Recipients of unrelated matched or single antigen mismatched donor stem cell transplant or single antigen mismatched family donor stem cell transplants</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="3"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="1"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Blood/Bone Marrow - Other: Engraftment Failure</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="3"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="1"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Infection (documented clinically or microbiologically) with Grade 3 or 4 neutrophils (ANC &lt;1.0 x 10e</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" events="2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="3"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" events="0" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="1"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="3"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="1"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Rammurti Kamble, MD</name_or_title>
      <organization>Baylor</organization>
      <phone>713-394-6252</phone>
      <email>rtkamble@tmhs.org</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

