<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00579358</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OCRT07001</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HS# 2007-5805</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00579358</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Molecular Basis of Congenital Heart Defects</brief_title>
  <official_title>Molecular Basis of Congenital Heart Defects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Irvine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Irvine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Congenital heart disease is one of the most common malformations in newborns. About 1% of
      newborns have cardiac malformations. Many need open heart surgery, which contributes
      substantially to pediatric mortality and morbidity. Recent advances in genetics suggest that
      many congenital heart defects are caused by mutation of genes. So far, half a dozen genes are
      found to be associated with congenital heart diseases, such as TBX5, NKX2.5, and GATA4, to
      name a few. In the near future, more genes will be identified.

      This study will evaluate the role of mutation of genes in congenital heart diseases and study
      the genotype-phenotype correlation. The central hypothesis is that a significant percentage
      of congenital heart disease is caused by mutation of genes involved in heart development, and
      the phenotype with missensed mutations is milder than nonsense mutation. Another hypothesis
      is that a significant proportion of patients with cardiac malformations will have mutations
      in their genes. The specific aim is to test the mutations of these genes in patients with
      congenital heart diseases. The study will provide substantial information to understand how
      the human heart develops. In the future, prenatal diagnosis could be developed based on this
      study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Purpose:

      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the role of mutation of genes in congenital heart
      diseases and study the genotype-phenotype correlation.

      Hypothesis:

      The central hypothesis is that a significant percentage of congenital heart disease is caused
      by mutation of genes involved in heart development, and the phenotype with missensed
      mutations is milder than nonsense mutation. Another hypothesis is that a significant
      proportion of patients with cardiac malformations will have mutations in their genes. The
      specific aim is to test the mutations of these genes in patients with congenital heart
      diseases.

      Study Design and Procedures:

      This is a pilot study on mutation of genes in congenital heart diseases and
      genotype-phenotype correlation. Probands and family members are initially evaluated by a
      local physician or at the UCI Medical Center. A clinical diagnosis is made based on clinical
      information, echocardiography, EKG, and/or cardiac catheteration.

      We would like to correlate the mutation the specific type of congenital heart defect. For
      example, if mutations of TBX5 more likely cause atrial-septal defects, ventricular-septal
      defects; mutations PTPN11 is more likely cause pulmonary stenosis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>November 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2010</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Congenital Heart Defects</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      blood samples
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The characteristics of the proposed subject population include:

          -  Children (male or female) who are able to give assent

          -  Subjects diagnosed with congenital heart defects

          -  Adults (male or female) who are competent to give informed consent

          -  Subjects who are unable to read or speak English

          -  Individuals of any ethnic origin
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults and children (both parent's signature required) who are able to give informed
             consent

          -  Adults or children who are prior diagnosed with congenital heart disease and/or who
             has immediate family member(s) with congenital heart disease (immediate family members
             include: subject's parents, siblings, and subject's children)

               -  If subject is the only one affected and subject does not disclose of any family
                  member being affected, than only subject will be enrolled

               -  If subject is affected and disclose that a family member is affected, that family
                  member will be contacted (with permission) to participate in the study

          -  Patients of all ethnical origin

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients diagnosed with no congenital heart disease (as determined by their medical
             assessment); (if subjects who are unaffected disclose that a family member is
             affected, with permission, that family will be contacted for participation)

          -  Patients who are unable to provide informed consent/assent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Taosheng Huang, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Irvine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Taosheng Huang, M.D., Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>(949) 824-9346</phone>
    <email>huangts@uci.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Taosheng Huang</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orange</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92868</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Taosheng Huang, M.D., Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>949-824-9346</phone>
      <email>huangts@uci.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 18, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 18, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 24, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 5, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 5, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 8, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Taosheng Huang, M.D., Ph.D.</name_title>
    <organization>University of California, Irvine</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Congenital heart defects</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Defects, Congenital</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

