<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00577018</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRU-USA-25</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00577018</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy and Safety Study of the Effect of Dose-Titration of Prucalopride for The Treatment of Chronic Constipation</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Trial to Evaluate the Effect of Dose-Titration on the Safety and Efficacy and R108512 Tablets in Subjects With Chronic Constipation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Movetis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Movetis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the safety profile of 4 mg prucalopride in the
      treatment of chronic constipation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the potential differences in the adverse event (safety) profile between 4 mg of
      prucalopride daily for 4 weeks; titration up to a 4-mg total daily dose of prucalopride by
      starting at 1 mg for 2 days, 2 mg for 2 days, to 4 mg thereafter; and placebo given as oral
      tablets once daily for 4 weeks in patients with chronic constipation
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 1998</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 1999</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 1999</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with an average of ≥3 SCBM/week</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with an average increase of ≥1 SCBM/week</measure>
    <time_frame>4 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">755</enrollment>
  <condition>Constipation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prucalopride</intervention_name>
    <description>4 mg o.d.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Resolor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prucalopride</intervention_name>
    <description>1 mg o.d. for 2 days, 2 mg o.d. for 2 days and 4 mg o.d. thereafter</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Resolor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>o.d.</description>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male and non-pregnant, non-breast feeding female subjects at least 18 years of age (no
             upper age limit);

          -  History of constipation. The subject reported having on average, 2 or fewer
             spontaneous bowel movements per week that resulted in a feeling or sensation of
             complete evacuation, as well as the occurrence of one or more of the following for at
             least 6 months before the selection visit: very hard (little balls) and/or hard stools
             for at least a quarter of the stools; sensation of incomplete evacuation following at
             least a quarter of the stools; or straining at defecation at least a quarter of the
             time. The above criteria only applied to spontaneous bowel movements, (i.e., not
             preceded within a period of 24 hours by the intake of a laxative or use of an enema).
             A subject who never had spontaneous bowel movements was considered to be constipated
             and therefore eligible for the trial;

          -  Constipation that was functional (i.e., not secondary to other causes);

          -  Willingness and ability to fill out own diary and questionnaires;

          -  Written informed consent, signed by the subject or legally acceptable representative
             and by the investigator; and

          -  Availability for follow-up during the trial period, as determined in the protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects in whom constipation was thought to be drug-induced or who were using any
             disallowed medication;

          -  Subjects suffering from secondary causes of chronic constipation. For example:

        Endocrine disorders: insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus; hypopituitarism; hypothyroidism;
        hypercalcemia; pseudo-hypoparathyroidism; pheochromocytoma; or glucagon-producing tumors.
        Endocrine disorders controlled by appropriate medical therapy were not excluded, with the
        exception of insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus Metabolic disorders: porphyria; uremia;
        hypokalemia; or amyloid neuropathy. Metabolic disorders controlled by appropriate medical
        therapy were not excluded

        • Exclusion criteria (cont'd): Neurologic disorders: Parkinson's disease; cerebral tumors;
        cerebrovascular accidents; multiple sclerosis; meningocele; aganglionosis;
        hypoganglionosis; hyperganglionosis; autonomic neuropathy; spinal cord injury; Chagas'
        disease; or major depression

          -  Presence of megacolon/megarectum or a diagnosis of pseudo-obstruction;

          -  Constipation as a result of surgery;

          -  Known or suspected organic disorders of the large bowel (i.e., obstruction, carcinoma,
             or inflammatory bowel disease). Results of a barium enema with flexible sigmoidoscopy
             or of a colonoscopic examination performed within the last 12 months were needed to
             rule out organic disorders. An examination performed within the last 3 years was
             acceptable, if the examination had been performed for an evaluation of constipation,
             if there was no history or evidence of weight loss, anemia, or rectal bleeding, and if
             the subject had had three consecutively negative stool occult blood tests at
             screening. Subjects with polyps discovered by colonoscopy that were untreated (i.e.,
             by polypectomy) were to be excluded;

          -  Presence of severe and clinically uncontrolled cardiovascular, liver or lung disease,
             neurologic or psychiatric disorders (including active alcohol or drug abuse);

          -  Clinically significant cancer within the past 5 years;

          -  Known HIV-positive status or AIDS;

          -  Impaired renal function;

          -  Clinically significant abnormalities of hematology, urinalysis or blood chemistry;

          -  Females of child-bearing potential without adequate contraceptive protection during
             the trial. Oral contraceptives, Depo-Provera®, or Norplant®) must have been used for
             at least 3 months prior to randomization. I.U.D.'s, sterilization, or a double-barrier
             method were other acceptable methods of birth control;

          -  Treatment with an investigational drug in the 30 days preceding the run-in phase of
             the trial; and

          -  Previous treatment with either R093877 (prucalopride hydrochloride) or R108512
             (prucalopride succinate).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John F Johanson, MD, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Private Practice</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>December 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 17, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 18, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 19, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 28, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 28, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 29, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Renate Specht Gryp</name_title>
    <organization>Movetis</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Constipation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

