<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00575315</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VCU03488</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>K23-DK-066578-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00575315</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>HIV-HCV Coinfection: Impact of Immune Dysfunction</brief_title>
  <official_title>HIV-HCV Coinfection: Impact of Immune Dysfunction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Virginia Commonwealth University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Virginia Commonwealth University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Effective therapy for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection has markedly prolonged
      survival in infected individuals. As a result, other diseases are now becoming clinically
      significant. Approximately 30% of HIV infected patients are co-infected with hepatitis C
      virus (HCV) which is now the leading co-morbid disease in co-infected individuals. The
      histologic severity and natural history of HCV has been reported to be accelerated in those
      co-infected with HIV. It is hypothesized that 1) the severity and progression of HCV disease
      is related to the immune competence of the individual, 2) immune restoration associated with
      HIV therapy may further accelerate the progression of HCV disease which may explain the
      marked increase in HCV related morbidity and mortality observed in recent years, and 3) the
      virologic response to anti-HCV treatment is directly related to the degree of immunologic
      competence. The specific aims of the proposal are: 1) To obtain, through multi-disciplinary
      didactic teaching, the necessary skills of clinical research design, data collection, data
      analysis, and biostatistical methods and 2) To study the impact of HIV disease on HCV, the
      effect of the immune function and immune restoration during HIV therapy on the natural
      history of HCV, and the efficacy of HCV treatment in HIV co-infection.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Approximately 30% of HIV infected patients are co-infected with hepatitis C virus (HCV) which
      is now the leading co-morbid disease in co-infected individuals. The histologic severity and
      natural history of HCV has been reported to be accelerated in those co-infected with HIV. It
      is hypothesized that 1) the severity and progression of HCV disease is related to the immune
      competence of the individual, 2) immune restoration associated with HIV therapy may further
      accelerate the progression of HCV disease which may explain the marked increase in HCV
      related morbidity and mortality observed in recent years, and 3) the virologic response to
      anti-HCV treatment is directly related to the degree of immunologic competence. The specific
      aims of the proposal are: 1) To obtain, through multi-disciplinary didactic teaching, the
      necessary skills of clinical research design, data collection, data analysis, and
      biostatistical methods and 2) To study the impact of HIV disease on HCV, the effect of the
      immune function and immune restoration during HIV therapy on the natural history of HCV, and
      the efficacy of HCV treatment in HIV co-infection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in liver histology</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessing the effect of confounding variables on hepatic fibrosis.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">634</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <condition>Hepatitis</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Sera
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        HIV-HCV Coinfection
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HIV antibody positive

          -  Positive HCV-RNA

          -  Age &gt; 18 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Coagulopathy (prothrombin time prolonged &gt; 2 seconds from control)

          -  Presence of ascites

          -  Thrombocytopenia (platelet &lt; 70,000)

          -  Active or recent (within 3 months) opportunistic infection related to HIV

          -  Advanced HIV disease with life expectancy less than 1 year

          -  Renal failure

          -  Hepatitis B surface antigen positive

          -  Inability to give informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard K Sterling, MD MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>VCU</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virgnia Commonwealth University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23298</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shah AG, Smith PG, Sterling RK. Comparison of FIB-4 and APRI in HIV-HCV coinfected patients with normal and elevated ALT. Dig Dis Sci. 2011 Oct;56(10):3038-44. doi: 10.1007/s10620-011-1710-2. Epub 2011 Apr 28.</citation>
    <PMID>21526398</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sterling RK, Wegelin JA, Smith PG, Stravitz RT, Luketic VA, Fuchs M, Puri P, Shiffman ML, Contos MA, Mills AS, Sanyal AJ. Similar progression of fibrosis between HIV/HCV-infected and HCV-infected patients: Analysis of paired liver biopsy samples. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2010 Dec;8(12):1070-6. doi: 10.1016/j.cgh.2010.08.004. Epub 2010 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>20728569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sterling RK, Contos MJ, Smith PG, Stravitz RT, Luketic VA, Fuchs M, Shiffman ML, Sanyal AJ. Steatohepatitis: Risk factors and impact on disease severity in human immunodeficiency virus/hepatitis C virus coinfection. Hepatology. 2008 Apr;47(4):1118-27. doi: 10.1002/hep.22134.</citation>
    <PMID>18366118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sterling RK, Chiu S, Snider K, Nixon D. The prevalence and risk factors for abnormal liver enzymes in HIV-positive patients without hepatitis B or C coinfections. Dig Dis Sci. 2008 May;53(5):1375-82. Epub 2007 Oct 16.</citation>
    <PMID>17939038</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith JO, Sterling RK. Hepatitis C and HIV. Curr Gastroenterol Rep. 2007 Mar;9(1):83-90. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17335682</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sterling RK, Lissen E, Clumeck N, Sola R, Correa MC, Montaner J, S Sulkowski M, Torriani FJ, Dieterich DT, Thomas DL, Messinger D, Nelson M; APRICOT Clinical Investigators. Development of a simple noninvasive index to predict significant fibrosis in patients with HIV/HCV coinfection. Hepatology. 2006 Jun;43(6):1317-25.</citation>
    <PMID>16729309</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sterling RK, Brown RS Jr, Hofmann CM, Luketic VA, Stravitz RT, Sanyal AJ, Contos MJ, Mills AS, Smith V, Shiffman ML. The spectrum of chronic hepatitis C virus infection in the Virginia Correctional System: development of a strategy for the evaluation and treatment of inmates with HCV. Am J Gastroenterol. 2005 Feb;100(2):313-21.</citation>
    <PMID>15667488</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stravitz RT, Shiffman ML, Sanyal AJ, Luketic VA, Sterling RK, Heuman DM, Ashworth A, Mills AS, Contos M, Cotterell AH, Maluf D, Posner MP, Fisher RA. Effects of interferon treatment on liver histology and allograft rejection in patients with recurrent hepatitis C following liver transplantation. Liver Transpl. 2004 Jul;10(7):850-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15237368</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sterling RK, Wilson MS, Sanyal AJ, Luketic VA, Stravitz RT, Contos MJ, Mills AS, Shiffman ML. Impact of highly active antiretroviral therapy on the spectrum of liver disease in HCV-HIV coinfection. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2004 May;2(5):432-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15118983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sterling RK, Contos MJ, Sanyal AJ, Luketic VA, Stravitz RT, Wilson MS, Mills AS, Shiffman ML. The clinical spectrum of hepatitis C virus in HIV coinfection. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2003 Jan 1;32(1):30-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12514411</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 14, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 17, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 18, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 19, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 19, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 20, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV-HCV Coinfection</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>Histology</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coinfection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Immune System Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

