<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00578123</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>04-094</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00578123</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical and Quality of Life Outcomes After Open or Robotic-Assisted Laparoscopic Radical Prostatectomy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Assessment of Clinical and Quality of Life Outcomes After Open or Robotic-Assisted Laparoscopic Radical Prostatectomy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Cleveland Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of the study is to look at surgical recovery and quality of life for men who have an
      open versus robotic-assisted laparoscopic radical prostatectomy (RP). RP is a procedure that
      removes the prostate gland. We want to see how long it will take you to return to health and
      strength after surgery. Quality-of-life (QOL) means how you feel about your life and your
      treatment of prostate cancer. The QOL surveys ask questions about your sexual, urinary and
      bowel functions. We will also ask questions about your use of health care services,
      out-of-pocket-spending on medical care and about your return to work, in order to learn about
      the financial impact of prostate cancer treatment. We hope that the surveys will help show
      how prostate cancer treatments affect your daily life after surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study will prospectively assess clinical outcomes in health-related quality of life
      (HRQOL) in men undergoing open, or robotic-assisted laparoscopic radical prostatectomy. Open
      radical prostatectomy is a frequently performed treatment for patients with clinically
      localized (cT1-T2) prostate cancer. The open technique stands as a benchmark against which
      all other treatments, including new surgical techniques, must be compared. Robotic-assisted
      and laparoscopic radical prostatectomy is considered an alternative surgical option for
      clinically localized prostate cancer. While this minimally invasive technique is more
      frequently being performed in the United States, a detailed comparison of the open and
      robotic-assisted laparoscopic techniques has not been performed. The relative risks and
      benefits of these surgical treatment options have not been explored in a contemporary group
      of patients treated at the same center by surgeons experienced in the open and
      robotic-assisted laparoscopic techniques. This study will address this deficiency in that
      follow-up information will be collected prospectively in consecutive patients undergoing open
      or robotic-assisted laparoscopic radical prostatectomy. While a prospective, randomized trial
      might be considered a more appropriate methodology to conduct such a comparative study, we
      have no baseline information, no guidelines to assess robotic-assisted laparoscopic
      competence, and a lack of skilled robotic-assisted laparoscopic pelvic surgeons to justify a
      lengthy and expensive trial. We will also collect information on health service utilization
      and employment during the 12-month postoperative period in order to assess the economic
      impacts of the different surgical approaches. While results from our proposed study will not
      necessarily be generalizable to all surgeons and may very well be a comparison of surgeons
      rather than techniques, the results will provide an initial assessment comparing experts in
      the open and robotic-assisted laparoscopic techniques. To date, no such comparison has been
      published. To our knowledge, no other center has expert surgeons in these techniques where
      such a study would be feasible. Because open techniques have improved dramatically over the
      past several years, and because the baseline data to be recorded in this proposal is not
      currently collected, use of historical controls for open radical prostatectomy would be
      inappropriate.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To compare robotic-assisted radical prostatectomy (RALP), and open radical prostatectomy (ORP) with respect to potency function at 1 year, after adjusting for known confounding variables measured at baseline.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the recovery of continence after RALP or ORP.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate patient convalescence after RALP or ORP.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate operative details.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Including operative time, blood loss, intraoperative fluid requirements, type of anesthesia, number and type of surgical drains, status of the neurovascular bundles including whether or not nerve grafting was performed, incision length, and other ancillary procedures for RALP or ORP</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate inpatient (hospital) details</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Including time in the post-anesthesia care unit, hospital convalescence, day of oral intake, day of ambulation, analgesia requirements, daily weights, length of time and output from surgical drains, hemoglobin and creatinine, complications, and length of hospital stay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate post-discharge (home) details.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Including analgesic use, return to normal activities/work, time of urinary catheterization, need for catheter replacement, hemoglobin, complications, visit to emergency room or unscheduled clinic visits, and biochemical outcomes (serum PSA levels) following surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate health service utilization, out-of-pocket spending and changes in employment following RALP or ORP.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">959</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1 Questionnaire</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Quality of Life Questionnaires</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quality of Life Questionnaires</intervention_name>
    <description>Three surveys you will need to complete. We will give you the surveys during your regularly scheduled clinic visits at three, six, and twelve months after surgery. You will NOT be asked to make additional appointments just for the study. You will have the option of completing some of the surveys in an easy to use computer format in the clinic waiting area or on paper.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1 Questionnaire</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Biopsy proven adenocarcinoma of the prostate

          -  Clinical stage T1-T2, NX or N0, Mx or M0

          -  Life expectancy greater than or equal to 10 years

          -  Planned radical prostatectomy

          -  Patients must be able to read and speak English, be free of cognitive impairment, and
             be reachable by telephone

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Prior hormonal therapy for prostate cancer

          -  Prior pelvic radiation

          -  Prior chemotherapy for prostate cancer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>James Eastham, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mskcc.org</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 18, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 19, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 20, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 3, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 3, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 4, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prostate</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of Life</keyword>
  <keyword>Questionaires</keyword>
  <keyword>04-094</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

