<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00573027</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB 8221</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00573027</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Heart Disease of the Small Arteries in Women and Men</brief_title>
  <official_title>Coronary Microvascular Disease and Endothelial Function in Women and Men</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Women suffer disproportionately than men from Cardiac Syndrome X ( chest pain in the absence
      of flow limiting coronary artery stenosis). Coronary microvascular disease is hypothesized to
      mediate chest pain in this syndrome. This disorder of the small heart vessels (arterioles)
      compared to the large vessels (arteries) is not diagnosed during routine heart
      catheterization. This results in delays in diagnosis, missed opportunities for treatment, and
      likely contributes to the increased death rate from coronary heart disease in women compared
      to men.

      Current testing for small vessel disease is performed in the cardiac catheterization
      laboratory using specialized testing and is not performed routinely. Accordingly, women with
      this condition are either falsely reassured, or misdiagnosed as another non-cardiac
      condition. Unnecessary healthcare costs related to re-hospitalization and repeat angiography
      are incurred, while women are often not initiated on appropriate lifesaving treatment. We and
      others have demonstrated in randomized controlled trials that therapies that target the
      endothelium, e.g. statins, ACE inhibitors, and exercise are effective in this condition.

      Majority of women with Cardiac Syndorme X go undiagnosed. Recent studies have shown
      significant increased health care costs, morbidity and mortality related to this disease. It
      is becoming more important to further characterize this group of patients and we hope to do
      that with our study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Aims:

        1. To establish prevalence of microvascular disease in women and men with Cardiac Syndrome
           X

        2. To study the predictive value and utility of noninvasive tests like Peripheral Artery
           Tonometry (PAT) and Cardiac Magnetic Resonance (CMR) in diagnosing Cardiac Syndrome X.

        3. To establish prognosis in women and men with Cardiac Syndrome X.

        4. To elucidate the risk factors, clinical features, diagnostic methods, treatment, and
           prognosis of patients with microvascular angina (MVA).

      With this research study, we want to specifically study a group of patients who have chest
      pain or other signs or symptoms suggestive of heart disease but don't have visible blockages
      in the large heart arteries. Patients with chest pain who undergo heart catheterization but
      have no blockages of large heart arteries will be consented and enrolled. Patients will be
      asked to fill out questionnaires about their medical history, including family, reproductive
      and, social histories. They will also be asked to undergo testing during heart
      catheterization that would test for abnormalities in their small heart arteries using
      medications, acetylcholine and adenosine. This testing is a standard of care procedure given
      at the discretion of the treating physician. Patients would receive this test whether they
      participate in the research or not. The test is performed by infusing acetylcholine and
      adenosine through the same catheter that is used for routine heart catheterization. This test
      may add an additional 15 minutes to the heart catheterization procedure.

      In addition, patients will be asked to undergo a non-invasive test called Peripheral Arterial
      Tonometry or PAT for research purposes and in some cases, if clinically indicated a Cardiac
      Magnetic Resonance (CMR) imaging test as a standard of care. Patients will be followed up
      using phone questionnaires at 6 months and than annually thereafter. It is proposed that
      problems with the function of the large and small arteries may be responsible for giving some
      patients their symptoms of chest pain and put them at risk for heart attacks. PAT may help us
      more easily and non-invasively measure this function by testing the arteries in the arm.
      Selected patients will also undergo CMR imaging that may be useful to detect abnormalities in
      the inner layer of the heart muscle resulting from the abnormal function of the large and
      small heart arteries. These non-invasive tests will be corroborated with results from
      invasive testing during heart catheterization, which is considered the gold standard for
      testing for function of the large and the small heart arteries.

      The three tests (heart catheterization with adenosine coronary flow reserve testing,
      acetylcholine provocative vasomotor testing during heart catheterization, cardiac MRI) are
      performed for standard care.

      Blood and urine collection have been added to this protocol as a secondary outcome for future
      tests and for testing whether impaired Endothelial Progenitor Cell (EPC) number is related to
      the presence and severity of microvascular disease.

      Results from our study will help confirm the need to test patients with chest pain and open
      large arteries during heart catheterizations for abnormalities in the function of the large
      and small heart arteries, and to validate the usefulness of using non-invasive techniques
      like PAT and CMR for detecting this problem. The study will also help confirm the increased
      risk of heart attack associated with the abnormal function in the large and small arteries in
      these patients.

      Subjects will be asked if they are interested in receiving information on Pro00015124
      (repository/collection). If they are interested, they will be consented under Pro00015124. No
      specimens collected as part of this study will be forwarded to Pro00015124.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>noninvasive Peripheral Artery Tonometry (PAT) testing and Cardiac Magnetic Resonance (CMR) imaging for the outcome of coronary endothelial dysfunction</measure>
    <time_frame>120 minutes</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>clinically indicated coronary angiography with adenosine coronary flow reserve measurement and acetylcholine provocative testing</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">634</enrollment>
  <condition>Heart Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>fill out baseline demographic and health/medical history questionnaires, CV risk factors, reasons of diagnosis of ischemia, information of coronary artery, and medication use
undergo clinically indicated coronary angiography with adenosine coronary flow reserve measurement and acetylcholine provocative testing in the cardiac catheterization laboratory (Appendix);
undergo noninvasive Peripheral Artery Tonometry (PAT) testing (Appendix);
undergo clinically indicated Cardiac Magnetic Resonance (CMR) imaging (Appendix) to detect subendocardial ischemia (if indicated and referred by the treating physician). The three tests (heart catheterization with adenosine coronary flow reserve testing, acetylcholine provocative vasomotor testing during heart catheterization, cardiac MRI) are performed for standard care.
have blood and urine testing.
fill out health questionnaires
be followed prospectively 6-week, 6-month, and annually for clinical status</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>noninvasive tests</intervention_name>
    <description>clinically indicated coronary angiography with adenosine coronary flow reserve measurement and acetylcholine provocative testing in the cardiac catheterization laboratory; Peripheral Artery Tonometry (PAT) testing; Cardiac Magnetic Resonance (CMR) imaging.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Women and men with signs and symptoms of myocardial ischemia and angina or angina
             equivalent (chest pain, abnormal stress testing, abnormal noninvasive testing) or
             microvascular angina (MVA) which is defined as angina and ischemic ECG changes without
             organic obstructive stenosis or epicardial spasm of the coronary arteries

          2. No obstructive coronary artery disease performed within the previous 24 months (&lt;50%
             luminal obstruction in one or more coronary arteries on angiography).

          3. Age &gt; 18 years old

          4. Competent to give informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Obstructive CAD ≥ 50% luminal diameter stenosis in ≥ 1 epicardial coronary artery,

          2. Acute coronary syndrome (defined by the ACC/AHA criteria, Braunwald 2000),

          3. Primary valvular heart disease clearly indicating the need for valve repair or
             replacement;

          4. Patients with concurrent cardiogenic shock or requiring inotropic or intra-aortic
             balloon support;

          5. Prior or planned percutaneous coronary intervention or CABG or prior acute MI in prior
             30 days;

          6. Prior non-cardiac illness with an estimated life expectancy &lt;4 years;

          7. Unable to give informed consent;

          8. Chest pain with a non-ischemic etiology (e.g.,pericarditis, pneumonia, esophageal
             spasm);

          9. Contraindications to adenosine or Regadenoson (Lexiscan)

         10. Women and men with intermediate coronary stenoses (&gt;20% but &lt;50% luminal diameter
             stenosis assessed visually at the time of angiography) will undergo clinically
             indicated IVUS testing based on the judgment of the operator; those determined to have
             flow FFR or obstructing stenosis will be excluded from the overall study.

         11. Heart failure (NYHA Class III or IV on treatment)

         12. LV dysfunction (ejection fraction &lt;40%)

         13. Documented obstructive myocardiopathy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>C.Noel Bairey-Merz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ying Mou, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>310-248-7669</phone>
    <email>Ying.Mou@cshs.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sophie Yoo, MS</last_name>
    <phone>424-315-4306</phone>
    <email>Jihye.Yoo@cshs.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cedars-Sinai Women's Heart Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90048</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ying Mou, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>310-248-7669</phone>
      <email>ying.mou@cshs.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Sophie Yoo, MS</last_name>
      <phone>424-315-4306</phone>
      <email>Jihye.Yoo@cshs.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Noel Bairey-Merz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Saibal Kar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Raj Makkar, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dan Berman, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Leslee Shaw, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Louise Thompson, MBChB</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rola Saouf, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 12, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 12, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 13, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Noel Bairey Merz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>microvascular dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>Microvascular</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adenosine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acetylcholine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

