<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00579956</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>OXTREC 018-06</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00579956</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Randomized Double Blinded Comparison of Ceftazidime and Meropenem in Severe Melioidosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>ATOM</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Double Blinded Comparison of Ceftazidime and Meropenem in Severe Melioidosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mahidol University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Wellcome Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Melioidosis, an infection caused by the bacterium Burkholderia pseudomallei, is a major cause
      of community-acquired septicaemia in northeast Thailand. Common manifestations include
      cavitating pneumonia, hepatic and splenic abscesses, and soft tissue and joint infections.
      Despite improvements in diagnostic procedures and treatment, the mortality of severe
      melioidosis remains unacceptably high - approximately 35% with currently used antibiotics
      (ceftazidime or co-amoxiclav). There is clear evidence that antibiotics can affect mortality;
      the use of ceftazidime rather than previous regimens (doxycycline + chloramphenicol +
      co-trimoxazole) led to a 50% reduction in mortality from 80% to 35%. However, the mortality
      in the first 48 hours has not been altered by any treatment regimen. A key question is
      whether alternative antibiotics could improve early outcome. The hypothesis tested is that
      meropenem is superior to ceftazidime in terms of mortality for the treatment of melioidosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Mortality rate of patients with severe melioidosis is still unacceptably high. Response to
      high dose parenteral ceftazidime treatment in survivors is also slow, as median time to
      abatement of fever is approximately 9 days. B. pseudomallei is susceptible to ceftazidime,
      imipenem, co-amoxiclav (Augmentin®), piperacillin and doxycycline, but unlike most other
      pseudomonads it is resistant to aminoglycosides, apart from kanamycin which has borderline
      activity. The fluoroquinolone compounds also have borderline activity. Two large published
      in-vitro studies have shown that the carbapenem group are the most active antibiotics against
      B. pseudomallei, with an MIC90 of 0.5 or 1.0 mg/L, and an MBC90 of 1 mg/L. We have tested the
      susceptibility to meropenem of 100 recently isolated strains of B. pseudomallei, all of which
      were assessed as susceptible (MIC90 = 0.5 mg/L; range 0.125-1 mg/L). Furthermore, 13 isolates
      in our collection assessed as resistant to ceftazidime were susceptible to meropenem. Using
      time-kill kinetic studies, ceftazidime did not show &quot;significant&quot; bactericidal activity
      whereas meropenem was bactericidal (99.9% kill) within 6 hours. Previous treatment trials
      have demonstrated the importance of the choice of antibiotic at the time of presentation. A
      study that compared a four-drug combination of chloramphenicol, doxycycline, and
      trimethoprimsulfamethoxazole (TMP-SMX) with ceftazidime alone demonstrated a 50% reduction in
      the mortality rate from 80% to 35%. Several previous randomized controlled trials have been
      conducted to determine whether the administration of alternative antimicrobial drugs are
      associated with further improvements in outcome. A comparison of TMP-SMX plus ceftazidime
      versus ceftazidime alone demonstrated that the addition of TMPSMX did not reduce the acute
      mortality rate. A previous study comparing ceftazidime and imipenem/cilastatin in the
      treatment of severe melioidosis was performed in Ubon Ratchathani between 1994 and 1997. This
      showed that &quot;treatment failure&quot; rate (a potentially subjective endpoint in this open-labelled
      trial) in the imipenem/cilastatin group was lower than in the ceftazidime group. Endotoxin
      release, believed to be important to the pathogenesis of severe sepsis, was also lower in the
      imipenem group than the ceftazidime group. No difference in mortality was observed, but this
      study was underpowered following early termination due to a lack of imipenem supply from the
      manufacturer. As a result, ceftazidime has remained the treatment of choice for melioidosis,
      but the question remains as to whether a carbapenem drug would be more effective. A second,
      sufficiently powered clinical trial would address this important question.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>December 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>All cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>In hospital</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>All cause mortality in patients culture positive for melioidosis</measure>
    <time_frame>In hospital</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Switch of antimicrobial therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>In hospital</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse drug reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fever clearance time (time to body temperature of less than 37.5°C for at least 48 hours)</measure>
    <time_frame>In hospital</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of hospital stay</measure>
    <time_frame>months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">750</enrollment>
  <condition>Melioidosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Meropenem</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Meropenem</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ceftazidime</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ceftazidime</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Meropenem</intervention_name>
    <description>Meropenem 1gm, diluted with 50ml normal saline solution IV every 8 hours for at least 10 days. The dose will be adjusted according to the creatinine clearance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Meropenem</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ceftazidime</intervention_name>
    <description>Ceftazidime 120mg/kg/day divided into 3 equal doses (maximum dose 2 gram/dose), diluted with 50ml normal saline solution IV every 8 hours for at least 10 days The dose will be adjusted according to the plasma creatinine level</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ceftazidime</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria (all criteria must be satisfied)

        A. Community acquired sepsis, and melioidosis is suspected:

        Suspected melioidosis (12): all of the following are defined as 'clinically probable'
        melioidosis

          -  A history of frequent contact with soil or surface water in the endemic area

          -  At least one of the following risk factors: diabetes mellitus, chronic renal failure
             or renal calculi, thalassaemia, aplastic anaemia or steroid abuse

          -  An illness compatible with melioidosis, including the presence of sepsis, acute
             pneumonia, acute pyelonephritis, septic arthritis, parotid disease or skin or soft
             tissue infection, or

          -  An evidence of intra-abdominal suppuration (hepatic or splenic abscesses) regardless
             of risk factors or exposure history

        Sepsis: defined as patients who have Systemic Inflammatory Response Syndrome (SIRS) - two
        or more of the following, clinically ascribed to infection:

          -  Fever: temperature &gt;38°C or &lt;36°C

          -  Tachycardia: heart rate &gt;90 beats/min

          -  Tachypnoea:

               1. Respiratory rate &gt;20 breaths/minute; or

               2. PaCO2 &lt;32 mmHg; or

               3. Mechanical ventilation

          -  White cell count &gt;12,000 cells/mL or &lt;4,000 cells/mL or &gt;10% band forms B. Age &gt; 14
             years. C. Need hospitalisation and intravenous antibiotic administration. D.
             Willingness to participate in the study and written, informed consent obtained from
             the patient.

        Exclusion Criteria (any one of the following):

        A. Pregnant or lactating women. B. Known hypersensitivity to meropenem or ceftazidime. C.
        Previous isolate with known resistance to ceftazidime or meropenem. D. Patients not
        expected to remain in hospital for treatment. E. Patients with community-acquired sepsis
        with cultures positive for other organisms.

        F. Patients treated with antibiotics active against B. pseudomallei (including ceftazidime,
        amoxicillin-clavulanate, meropenem) for this episode for greater than 24 hours.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wirongrong Chierakul, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mahidol University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Wirongrong Chierakul, MD</last_name>
    <phone>6689 1058571</phone>
    <email>kae@tropmedres.ac</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sappasithiprasong Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ubonratchathani</city>
        <state>Ubon</state>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Direk Limmathurotsakul, MD</last_name>
      <phone>6681 6149551</phone>
      <email>direk@tropmedres.ac</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Udon Thani General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Udon Thani</city>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Prapit Teparakkul, MD</last_name>
      <phone>6681 8779864</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 18, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 18, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 24, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 4, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Nick Day</name_title>
    <organization>Oxford University</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Melioidosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Meropenem</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thienamycins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ceftazidime</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

