<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02582827</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>QUILT-3.014</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02582827</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>QUILT-3.014: A Trial of ABI-011 Administered Weekly in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors or Lymphomas</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Trial of ABI-011 Administered Weekly in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors or Lymphomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NantBioScience, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NantBioScience, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of study CA601.2 is to determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) or
      recommended phase 2 dose (RP2D) of ABI-011 when administered by intravenous (IV) infusion on
      Days 1, 8, and 15, followed by a week of rest, in patients with advanced solid tumor
      malignancies or lymphomas. The MTD will be determined using a standard 3+3 design. The
      secondary objectives are to evaluate the safety and toxicity profile, to evaluate the plasma
      pharmacokinetics (PK), to assess the biological activity and pharmacodynamics, and to make a
      preliminary assessment of tumor response in patients with advanced solid tumors or lymphomas.
      The exploratory objectives are to determine the genomic and proteomic profile of patients'
      tumors to identify gene mutations, gene amplifications, levels of protein expression, and
      pinpoint oncoproteins. Correlations between genomic/proteomic profiles and efficacy outcomes
      will be assessed and principal metabolites of ABI-011 will be determined, if possible.

      Approximately 45-60 patients will be treated to determine dose limiting toxicities (DLTs),
      the MTD, and/or RP2D of ABI-011. Once the RP2D is identified, expansion of this cohort (up to
      10 patients) will occur.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      ABI-011 is a novel, albumin-bound formulation of a potent thiocolchicine analog, IDN 5404,
      with a mean particle size of approximately 100 nanometers (nm). The active drug, IDN 5404, is
      related to the colchicine family of tubulin-binding compounds that have been found to have
      vascular-disrupting activity in vivo. Studies are ongoing to determine whether IDN 5404 has
      vascular-disrupting activity. As a dimer, IDN 5404 has an additional activity as an inhibitor
      of topoisomerase I, a critical enzyme in deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) repair mechanisms.
      Although the active compound has limited solubility, IDN 5404 formulated as ABI-011 is
      soluble in saline, facilitating IV dosing and delivery of the active agent to tumors and the
      tumor vasculature.

      The primary objective of study CA601.2 is to determine the MTD or RP2D of ABI-011 when
      administered by IV infusion on Days 1, 8, and 15, followed by a week of rest, in patients
      with advanced solid tumor malignancies or lymphomas. The MTD will be determined using a
      standard 3+3 design. The secondary objectives are to evaluate the safety and toxicity
      profile, to evaluate the plasma PK (elimination rate constant, elimination half-life, volume
      of distribution, maximum serum concentration (Cmax), time to maximum concentration (tmax),
      and area under the time-concentration curve to time infinity (AUCinf), to assess the
      biological activity and pharmacodynamics, and to make a preliminary assessment of tumor
      response in patients with advanced solid tumors or lymphomas. The exploratory objectives are
      to determine the genomic and proteomic profile of patients' tumors to identify gene
      mutations, gene amplifications, levels of protein expression, and pinpoint oncoproteins.
      Correlations between genomic/proteomic profiles and efficacy outcomes will be assessed and
      principal metabolites of ABI-011 will be determined, if possible.

      Approximately 45-60 patients will be treated to determine DLTs, the MTD, and/or RP2D of
      ABI-011. Once the RP2D is identified, expansion of this cohort (up to 10 patients) will
      occur.

      Patients with cytologically or histologically confirmed solid tumor malignancies or lymphoma
      for which no curative standard approved therapy is available with an Eastern Cooperative
      Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status ≤ 2 will be included. In the dose-escalation phase
      of the study, patients can have measurable or non-measurable disease as defined by Response
      Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST), Version 1.1, criteria. In the dose-expansion
      phase of the study, only patients with measurable disease will be enrolled. No anti-cancer
      therapies (inclusive of investigational therapies) are allowed 5 half-lives/4 weeks
      (whichever is longer) prior to study drug administration (6 weeks for nitrosoureas or
      mitomycin C).

      ABI-011 will be administered via IV infusion for 30 minutes weekly on Days 1, 8, and 15 of a
      28-Day cycle. The starting dose will be 2 mg/m2. Patients will be allowed to continue
      treatment until they experience progressive disease or unacceptable toxicity, withdraw
      consent, or their physician feels it is no longer in their best interest to continue on
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">February 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine maximum tolerated dose (MTD) of ABI-011</measure>
    <time_frame>During Cycle 1 and each 28-Day treatment cycle, End of Study, Follow-up, approximately up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Determine the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) for repeated dosing of ABI-011</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate safety and toxicity profile of ABI-011</measure>
    <time_frame>During Cycle 1 and each 28-Day treatment cycle, End of Study, Follow-up, approximately up to 2 years total</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate safety and toxicity profile for repeated dosing of ABI-011. Number of subjects with adverse events (AEs), laboratory, electrocardiogram (ECG), echocardiogram, and ophthalmologic assessments, tumor pain and vital signs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate pharmacokinetics (PK) analysis; elimination rate constant</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 (Days 1,2,3); Cycle 2 (Days 1, 2, 3); Cycle 3 (Days 1, 2, 3)</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate drug concentration time data by individual subject for repeated dosing of ABI-011.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate pharmacokinetics (PK) analysis; elimination half-life</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 (Days 1,2,3); Cycle 2 (Days 1, 2, 3); Cycle 3 (Days 1, 2, 3)</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate drug concentration time data by individual subject for repeated dosing of ABI-011.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate pharmacokinetics (PK) analysis; volume of distribution</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 (Days 1,2,3); Cycle 2 (Days 1, 2, 3); Cycle 3 (Days 1, 2, 3)</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate drug concentration time data by individual subject for repeated dosing of ABI-011.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate pharmacokinetics (PK) analysis; maximum plasma drug concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 (Days 1,2,3); Cycle 2 (Days 1, 2, 3); Cycle 3 (Days 1, 2, 3)</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate drug concentration time data by individual subject for repeated dosing of ABI-011.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate pharmacokinetics (PK) analysis; time to maximum concentration (tmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 (Days 1,2,3); Cycle 2 (Days 1, 2, 3); Cycle 3 (Days 1, 2, 3)</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate drug concentration time data by individual subject for repeated dosing of ABI-011.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate pharmacokinetics (PK) analysis; area under the time-concentration curve (AUC)</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 (Days 1,2,3); Cycle 2 (Days 1, 2, 3); Cycle 3 (Days 1, 2, 3)</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluate drug concentration time data by individual subject for repeated dosing of ABI-011.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor response</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Every 8 weeks through Cycle 6, then every 12 weeks, approximately up to 2 years total</time_frame>
    <description>Tumor response based on assessment of target and non-target lesions according to response evaluation criteria in solid tumors (RECIST) criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Neoplastic Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ABI-011</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>IDN 5404 protein-bound particles for injectable suspension</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ABI-011</intervention_name>
    <description>ABI-011 is a novel, albumin-bound formulation of a potent thiocolchicine analog, IDN 5404, with a mean particle size of approximately 100 nm.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ABI-011</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IDN 5404 protein-bound particles for injectable suspension</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Each patient must meet all of the following criteria to be enrolled in this study.

          1. Patients ≥ 18 years of age (male and female).

          2. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status ≤ 2.

          3. Patients must be willing and able to sign an informed consent.

          4. Cytologically or histologically confirmed solid tumor malignancy or lymphoma for which
             no curative standard approved therapy is available.

          5. Patient agrees and is willing to provide 1 serial tumor biopsy (biopsies are
             mandatory), which would not put the patient or their treatment at significant risk.

          6. During the dose-escalation phase, measurable or non-measurable disease as defined by
             RECIST criteria (Version 1.1); during the dose- expansion phase only; disease must be
             measurable by RECIST criteria (Version 1.1) (clinical or radiological).

          7. Life expectancy of ≥ 12 weeks in the opinion of the investigator and medical monitor.

          8. All adverse events (AEs) (except alopecia) of any prior chemotherapy, surgery, or
             radiotherapy must have resolved to Grade ≤ 1.

          9. The following laboratory results must be present within the 14 days prior to the first
             administration of ABI-011:

               1. Hemoglobin ≥ 9 g/dL.

               2. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥1.5 x 109/L.

               3. Platelet count ≥ 100 x 109/L.

               4. Serum bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN).

               5. Aspartate transaminase (AST) and alanine transaminase (ALT) ≤ 2.5 ULN (except if
                  liver metastases are present, then values must be ≤ 5 x ULN).

               6. Potassium, ionized calcium, and magnesium within normal limits (WNL).

               7. Creatine kinase WNL.

               8. Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 x ULN.

               9. Activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) and prothrombin time (PT), or
                  International Normal Ratio (INR) WNL.

              10. WNL levels of troponin I.

         10. Women of child bearing potential and male patients who are not surgically sterile must
             be willing to practice contraceptive methods for the duration of the study and for
             30-days following the last dose of study medication. Female patients must be
             postmenopausal (greater than 12 months from onset of menopause) or surgically sterile
             (have undergone bilateral oophorectomy or hysterectomy). Women of child bearing
             potential and women &lt; 12 months since onset of menopause must agree to use an
             acceptable contraception method. If employing contraception, 2 of the following
             precautions must be used: vasectomy of partner, tubal ligation, vaginal diaphragm,
             intrauterine device, oral contraceptives (same oral contraceptive for a minimum of 3
             months prior to screening), birth control injections, birth control implant, condom
             and spermicidal (gel/foam/cream/vaginal suppository). Male patients must be surgically
             sterile or agree to use a condom and acceptable contraception method with partner.

         11. Women of childbearing potential and women &lt; 12 months since onset of menopause must
             have a negative serum pregnancy test (ß-hCG) within 24 hours prior to the first
             administration of study drug

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Patients who meet any of the following criteria will be excluded from the study:

          1. Inability to comply with study and follow-up procedures.

          2. Women who are pregnant or breastfeeding (lactating).

          3. Treatment with chemotherapy, hormonal therapy for cancer treatment (except leuprolide
             for prostate cancer), immunotherapy, biologic therapy, or radiation therapy as cancer
             therapy within 4 weeks or 5 half-lives, whichever is longer. Six weeks should have
             elapsed if prior chemotherapy treatment included nitrosoureas or mitomycin C.

          4. Patients who have received antibody-based therapies within 28 days or 5 half-lives of
             the agent, whichever time period is longer.

          5. Major surgery within 6 weeks before the first administration of study drug; needle
             aspirations, bone marrow biopsy and other similar procedures are allowable; minor
             surgery may be allowable following discussion and approval by Medical Monitor.

          6. Prior treatment with tumor vascular disrupting agents (VDAs).

          7. Any uncontrolled medical or psychiatric risk factors that would contraindicate the use
             or impair the ability of the patient to receive therapy per protocol or that may
             impose excessive risk to the patient.

          8. Central nervous system (CNS) metastases. Patients who have a history of CNS metastases
             or who display signs or symptoms of CNS metastases should be imaged with magnetic
             resonance imaging (MRI) or computed tomography (CT) within 2 months of screening; if a
             patient has current symptoms, the MRI or CT should be performed at screening. Should
             active metastases be detected, these patients will not be enrolled. Patients with
             previously treated brain metastases will not be enrolled if taking steroids or
             anti-convulsants.

          9. History of vascular neuropathy.

         10. History of vasculitides (autoimmune or idiopathic).

         11. History of retinopathy, including diabetic retinopathy. All patients must be evaluated
             by an ophthalmologist prior to study treatment.

         12. Current use of medications that may cause corrected QT interval (QTc) prolongation. If
             the need to use these medications arises during the study, a discussion with and
             approval by the Medical Monitor is required.

         13. History of allergy or hypersensitivity to any of the constituents of the ABI-011
             formulation.

         14. Active uncontrolled bacterial, viral, or fungal infection, requiring systemic therapy.

         15. Known infection with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) or known chronic active
             hepatitis B or hepatitis C virus (HBV/HCV) infection, unless a co-morbidity in
             patients with hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC).

         16. Inability to be venipunctured and/or tolerate venous access.

         17. Concurrent active second malignancy for which the patient is receiving therapy,
             excluding non-melanomatous skin cancer or carcinoma in situ of the cervix.

         18. Patients requiring therapeutic anticoagulation (e.g. warfarin, low-molecular weight
             heparin, or other anticoagulant) or with history of any bleeding diathesis. Aspirin or
             low-dose warfarin for catheter maintenance is allowed.

         19. Centrally-located lung tumors originating in the lungs and situated in the carinal
             bifurcation, the lung hila, or the main bronchi.

         20. Cardiovascular exclusion criteria:

               1. Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction (LVEF) &lt; 50% as measured by echocardiography.

               2. History (within prior 24 months) of either myocardial infarction or unstable or
                  poorly controlled angina.

               3. Electrocardiogram findings suggestive of significant current or previous ischemic
                  heart disease, or left bundle branch block.

               4. A cumulative doxorubicin dose of 550 mg/m2 or more; if patient has had radiation
                  to the chest and the heart was in the radiation field the maximum cumulative
                  doxorubicin dose is 300 mg/m².

               5. Class III or IV heart failure as defined by the New York Heart Association (NYHA)
                  functional classification.

               6. Congenital or acquired long QT syndrome.

               7. Uncontrolled hypertension: Blood pressure (BP) which when assessed on two
                  different occasions (e.g. screening and baseline) is greater than 150 millimeters
                  of mercury (mmHg) systolic and 90 mmHg diastolic despite receipt of
                  antihypertensive medication.

               8. Any current or past history of clinically significant arrhythmias, including
                  treatment with anti-arrhythmics.

               9. QTc prolongation defined as a QTc interval according to Bazett's formula of ≥ 450
                  msec for male patients or ≥470 msec for female patients at Baseline. Interval
                  determination will be based on a mean value obtained from 3 sequential baseline
                  electrocardiographs (ECGs) obtained at least 5 minutes apart.

              10. History of symptomatic peripheral vascular disease (venous or arterial) requiring
                  surgical intervention or chronic therapy (other than aspirin).

         21. Seizure disease requiring current anticonvulsant treatment.

         22. History of previous head trauma, cerebrovascular accident or transient ischemic attack
             within 24 months of enrollment.

         23. History of inflammatory bowel disease (active or past), or active peptic ulcer disease
             (prophylaxis with H2 blockers and proton pump inhibitors is acceptable).

         24. History of previous, whole abdomen radiation therapy or Grade ≥ 1 residual toxicity
             from previous radiation therapy.

         25. Administration of palliative radiotherapy for pain control within 7-days of planned
             administration of ABI-011.

         26. Transfusion of blood products [red blood cells (RBC), white blood cells (WBC) or whole
             blood] or Hematopoietic growth factors or other hematologic support, such as
             erythropoiesis-stimulating agents, granulocyte-colony stimulating factor (G-CSF), or
             platelet transfusion(s) within 14 days of screening.

         27. Participation in an investigational drug or device study within 30 days of screening
             for this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patrick Soon-Shiong, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Chief Medical Officer</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jacqueline Ongwenyi</last_name>
    <phone>(310) 853-7876</phone>
    <email>Jacqueline.Ongwenyi@NantKwest.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chan Soon-Shiong Institute for Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>El Segundo</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90245</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 14, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 19, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 21, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Advanced Solid Tumors</keyword>
  <keyword>solid tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>lymphoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

