<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02586389</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SQNM-CA-101</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02586389</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Specimen Collection From Patients With Non-Hematologic Cancer for Use in Development of a Liquid Biopsy Assay</brief_title>
  <official_title>Collection of Whole Blood and Tissue Specimens From Patients Diagnosed With Non-Hematologic Cancer for Use in Development of a Noninvasive Liquid Biopsy Assay to Determine the Tumor Genomic Profile in Circulating Cell-Free Tumor DNA</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sequenom, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sequenom, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This specimen collection is designed to obtain whole blood and tumor tissue from subjects
      diagnosed with cancer for the purpose of the development of a noninvasive liquid biopsy assay
      using next generation sequencing (NGS).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a non-significant risk multicenter, longitudinal specimen collection study. At the
      Baseline Visit, whole blood will be collected to be paired with either a previously collected
      tumor biopsy tissue sample or a prospectively collected tumor tissue sample. Whole blood
      samples will also be collected longitudinally at Interim visits for up to 5 years. Interim
      visits will be on a schedule dictated by their physician's standard-of-care management
      protocol. No more than 100mL of blood will be collected per month. Tumor tissue from
      recurrences will be collected for the duration of subject participation (after the Baseline
      Visit).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>biospecimen sample collection for liquid biopsy assay development</measure>
    <time_frame>After cancer diagnosis through 5 years of standard of care follow-up visits</time_frame>
    <description>Analysis of circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) in whole blood will be compared to baseline tumor DNA for concordance of mutations related to cancer.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3000</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-hematologic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Non-hematological Cancer Cohort</arm_group_label>
    <description>Eligible subjects will have been previously diagnosed with a non-hematological cancer with tumor present at baseline blood draw.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Whole blood samples and tissue samples will be collected for DNA extraction.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Male or female patients at least 18 years of age who have been diagnosed with
        non-hematologic cancer (Stages I-IV) and who meet all study inclusion criteria and no
        exclusion criteria. Primarily subjects with breast, colorectal, lung, or melanoma cancer
        (90%) will be enrolled. The remaining subjects (10%) diagnosed with other cancer types may
        be enrolled on a case by case basis.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is 18 years of age or older;

          -  Subject is willing to provide written informed consent;

          -  Subject has a diagnosis of a non-hematologic cancer, has tumor in the body, and has
             either;

               1. residual tumor tissue available for testing by the Sponsor; or

               2. genomic profiling results from an IVD or LDT assay performed on tumor biopsy
                  tissue; or

               3. an invasive procedure (biopsy, surgery) scheduled following the Baseline Visit
                  from which residual tumor tissue can be available for testing by the Sponsor.

          -  Subject is able, in the professional opinion of the investigator, to provide whole
             blood at the Baseline Visit and at the Interim Visits.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Underwent curative-intent surgery for management of the presently diagnosed tumor, at
             any time prior to the Baseline Visit.

          -  Underwent targeted or non-targeted chemotherapy, hormone receptor blocking therapy, or
             radiation therapy prior to the Baseline Visit.

          -  Underwent an invasive procedure (biopsy, surgery, thermal ablation) in the 7 days
             prior to any blood collection (baseline or follow-up).

          -  Any medical or mental condition that would interfere with the subjects' ability to
             willingly give written informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sue Beruti, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Sequenom, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Graham McLennan</last_name>
    <phone>(858) 202-9162</phone>
    <email>gmclennan@sequenom.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Compassionate Care Research Group, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Riverside</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92501</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Corina King, CCRP</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 21, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 22, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 26, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 19, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

