<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02583048</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A5343</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12005</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02583048</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the Safety, Tolerability, and Pharmacokinetics of Bedaquiline and Delamanid, Alone and in Combination, For Drug-Resistant Pulmonary Tuberculosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Trial of the Safety, Tolerability, and Pharmacokinetics of Bedaquiline and Delamanid, Alone and in Combination, Among Participants Taking Multidrug Treatment for Drug-Resistant Pulmonary Tuberculosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will evaluate the safety, tolerability, and pharmacokinetics of the
      anti-tuberculosis (TB) drugs bedaquiline (BDQ) and delamanid (DLM), alone and in combination,
      among participants (with or without HIV co-infection) taking multidrug treatment for
      multidrug-resistant tuberculosis (MDR-TB) or rifampin-monoresistant TB (RR-TB).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Bedaquiline (BDQ) and delamanid (DLM) are two newly approved anti-TB drugs and are both well
      tolerated. However, the combined effects of these two drugs have not been studied. Combining
      these two drugs, together with other anti-TB drugs, may improve outcomes for people with
      MDR-TB or RR-TB. The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety, tolerability, and
      pharmacokinetics of BDQ and DLM, alone and in combination, among participants (with or
      without HIV co-infection) taking multidrug treatment for MDR-TB or RR-TB. Researchers will
      specifically evaluate the effect of these drugs on the heart.

      Participants will be randomly assigned to one of three arms: participants in Arm 1 will
      receive BDQ, participants in Arm 2 will receive DLM, and participants in Arm 3 will receive
      BDQ and DLM. All participants will receive their assigned study drugs for 24 weeks together
      with multidrug background treatment (MBT) for MDR-TB or RR-TB (not provided by the study).
      HIV-infected participants will also receive dolutegravir, to be used in combination with two
      nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NRTIs) until study completion. NRTIs will not be
      provided by the study. All participants are expected to be hospitalized for 2 weeks starting
      at study entry. Participants may also be hospitalized for longer than 2 weeks.

      Study visits will occur at entry, each week for 8 weeks after study entry, every other week
      until week 24, and 8 additional visits between weeks 25 and 128. Visits may include physical
      examinations, blood collection, urine collection, sputum sample collection, hair sample
      collection, chest x-rays, electrocardiograms (ECGs), and adherence questionnaires.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm-specific mean change from baseline in QTcF</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 0, 8, 10, 12, 14, 16, 18, 20, 22 and 24</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in arm-specific mean change from baseline in QTcF, Arm 3 minus Arm 1, and Arm 3 minus Arm 2</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 0, 8, 10, 12, 14, 16, 18, 20, 22 and 24</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm-specific proportions of participants exhibiting QTcF above 500 ms at any time during study treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14, 16, 18, 20, 22 and 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm-specific proportions of participants exhibiting QTcF increase from baseline of more than 60 ms at any time during study treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14, 16, 18, 20, 22 and 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm- and visit-specific QTcF changes from baseline during study treatment, and at week 28</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 0, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14, 16, 18, 20, 22, 24 and 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm-specific proportions of participants exhibiting each of the following, at any time during study treatment: (a) absolute QTcF &gt;480 and ≤500 ms and (b) QTcF increase from baseline of &gt;30 and ≤60 ms</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 0, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14, 16, 18, 20, 22, 24 and 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In Arms 1 and 3, arm- and visit-specific means of PK parameters for BDQ and its metabolite, estimated using noncompartmental methods applied to concentrations from intensive PK sampling, and visit-specific geometric mean ratios (Arm 3 relative to Arm 1)</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 2, 8 and 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In Arms 2 and 3, arm- and visit-specific means of PK parameters for DLM and its metabolite, estimated using noncompartmental methods applied to concentrations from intensive PK sampling, and visit-specific geometric mean ratios (Arm 3 relative to Arm 2)</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 2, 8 and 24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Arm-specific proportions of participants exhibiting: (1) grade 3 or higher adverse events of any type at any time while on study TB drug (safety); (2) discontinuation of study TB drug(s) for any reason (tolerability); (3) death</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 0-24</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">84</enrollment>
  <condition>Tuberculosis</condition>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: Bedaquiline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 400 mg of bedaquiline once a day for 2 weeks followed by 200 mg of bedaquiline three times a week for 22 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Delamanid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 100 mg of delamanid twice a day for 24 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3: Bedaquiline and Delamanid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive 400 mg of bedaquiline once a day and 100 mg of delamanid twice a day for 2 weeks. They will then receive 200 mg of bedaquiline three times a week and 100 mg of delamanid twice a day for 22 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bedaquiline</intervention_name>
    <description>Bedaquiline will be administered as four 100 mg tablets (400 mg) by mouth once a day for 2 weeks, followed by two 100 mg tablets (200 mg) by mouth three times a week for 22 weeks, for all study arms involving the use of this drug.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: Bedaquiline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3: Bedaquiline and Delamanid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Delamanid</intervention_name>
    <description>Delamanid will be administered with food as two 50 mg tablets (100 mg) by mouth twice a day for 24 weeks, for all study arms involving the use of this drug.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Delamanid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3: Bedaquiline and Delamanid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dolutegravir</intervention_name>
    <description>For HIV-positive participants only: dolutegravir will be administered at a dose of one 50 mg tablet once daily, to be used in combination with two NRTIs until study completion. (NRTIs will not be provided by the study.)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1: Bedaquiline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2: Delamanid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3: Bedaquiline and Delamanid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men and women 18 years of age and older

          -  Documented pulmonary infection due to strains of MTB with (a) resistance to isoniazid
             (INH) and rifampin (RIF) (MDR-TB) or (b) resistance to RIF but not INH (RR-TB) from a
             sputum sample collected within 60 days prior to entry. Must be lab confirmed by either
             genotypic (eg, Hain GenoType MTBDRplus) or phenotypic (susceptibility testing on
             liquid or solid culture) methods. NOTE: MDR- or RR-TB diagnosis for purposes of
             meeting the inclusion criterion can be from a study testing laboratory or from an
             outside laboratory, as long as it is from a sputum sample collected within 60 days
             prior to entry.

          -  Laboratory confirmation of infection with an MTB strain that is susceptible to
             fluoroquinolones and aminoglycosides by either genotypic testing (such as Hain
             GenoType MTBDRsl) or phenotypic testing (susceptibility testing on liquid or solid
             culture) within 60 days prior to entry. NOTE: Fluoroquinolone and aminoglycoside
             susceptibility testing for purposes of meeting the inclusion criterion can be from a
             study testing laboratory or from an outside laboratory, as long as it is from a sputum
             sample collected within 60 days prior to entry.

          -  HIV-1 infection status must be documented as either absent or present, as defined
             below:

               -  Absence of HIV-1 infection, as documented by any licensed rapid HIV test or HIV-1
                  enzyme or chemiluminescence immunoassay (E/CIA) test kit, within 60 days prior to
                  entry. OR

               -  HIV-1 infection, documented by any licensed rapid HIV test or HIV-1 E/CIA test
                  kit at any time prior to entry and confirmed by a licensed Western blot or a
                  second antibody test by a method other than the initial rapid HIV and/or E/CIA,
                  or by HIV-1 antigen or plasma HIV-1 RNA viral load.

               -  NOTE: The term &quot;licensed&quot; refers to a U.S. FDA-approved kit, which is
                  recommended. For sites that are unable to obtain an FDA-approved kit, a kit that
                  has been certified or licensed by an oversight body within the country and
                  validated internally is acceptable.

               -  World Health Organization (WHO) and Centers for Disease Control and Prevention
                  (CDC) guidelines mandate that confirmation of the initial test result must use a
                  test that is different from the one used for the initial assessment. A reactive
                  initial rapid test should be confirmed by either another type of rapid assay or
                  an E/CIA that is based on a different antigen preparation and/or different test
                  principle (e.g., indirect versus competitive), or a Western blot or a plasma
                  HIV-1 RNA viral load.

          -  For HIV-positive participants only: CD4+ count greater than or equal to 100 cells/mm^3
             within 60 days prior to entry. CD4+ count must be obtained from a laboratory certified
             for protocol testing by the Division of AIDS (DAIDS) Immunology Quality Assurance
             (IQA) Program

          -  For HIV-positive participants only: for those who have been on ART for greater than or
             equal to 6 months and have an HIV-1 viral load greater than 500 copies/mL within 60
             days prior to entry, an HIV-1 genotype within 60 days prior to entry must show that at
             least one fully active NRTI is available to the participant within the country
             program.

          -  For females of reproductive potential, negative serum pregnancy test within 48 hours
             prior to entry

          -  Female and male participants of reproductive potential who are participating in sexual
             activity that could lead to pregnancy must agree to use one of the following forms of
             birth control while receiving TB study medications and for 6 months after stopping TB
             study medications:

               -  male or female condoms

               -  diaphragm or cervical cap with spermicide, if available

               -  intrauterine device (IUD)

               -  oral contraceptives or Depo-Provera

               -  NOTE A: Female participants who are not of reproductive potential are eligible
                  without requiring the use of contraceptives. Participant-reported history is
                  acceptable documentation of menopause (i.e., at least one year amenorrheic),
                  hysterectomy, or bilateral oophorectomy or bilateral tubal ligation; these
                  participants are all considered not of reproductive potential.

               -  NOTE B: Male participants who are not of reproductive potential (i.e., documented
                  azoospermia) or whose female partner/s are not of reproductive potential (as
                  defined above) are eligible without requiring the use of contraceptives.

          -  Chest x-ray performed within 60 days prior to entry to classify participant as having
             cavitary or non-cavitary disease

          -  Documentation of Karnofsky performance score greater than or equal to 50 within 14
             days prior to study entry

          -  Ability and willingness of participant or legally authorized representative to provide
             informed consent

          -  Willingness to be hospitalized for the required inpatient component of the study

          -  Taking MBT for a minimum of 7 days within the 10 days prior to entry

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of clinically relevant, currently active or underlying gastrointestinal,
             hepatic, cardiovascular, nervous system, psychiatric, metabolic (e.g., untreated
             hypothyroidism), renal, respiratory (other than due to TB), inflammatory, neoplastic,
             skin, immunological or infectious disease, which is not stable and controlled, that in
             the opinion of the investigator would preclude safe participation in the trial

          -  Current clinically relevant extrapulmonary TB, in the opinion of the site
             investigator, including but not limited to central nervous system (CNS) TB or TB
             osteoarthritis

          -  Previous treatment for MDR- or RR-TB, other than for the qualifying episode, at any
             time in the past

          -  Receipt of BDQ or DLM at any time in the past

          -  Breastfeeding

          -  QTcF interval greater than 450 ms within 72 hours prior to entry

          -  Clinically significant ECG abnormality in the opinion of the site investigator within
             60 days prior to entry, including but not limited to second or third degree
             atrioventricular (AV) block, prolongation of the QRS complex over 120 ms (in both male
             and female participants), or clinically important arrhythmia

          -  Current clinically relevant cardiovascular disorder in the opinion of the site
             investigator, including but not limited to heart failure, coronary heart disease,
             arrhythmia, or tachyarrhythmia

          -  Known family history of Long QT Syndrome in a first-degree relative (i.e., parent,
             offspring, or sibling)

          -  Requirement or expected requirement for protease inhibitors (PIs), efavirenz (EFV), or
             any other medication that is a moderate to strong inhibitor or inducer of CYP3A and
             CYP3A4 over the 24 weeks of study treatment. Drug information may be found on the AIDS
             Clinical Trials Group (ACTG) Drug Interactions Database, located at:
             http://tprc.pharm.buffalo.edu/home/di_search/. NOTE: Participants taking a PI or EFV
             can be switched to a treatment that is allowed in the study, but the PI must be
             stopped at least 2 days prior to starting study MDR- or RR-TB drugs and EFV must be
             stopped at least 7 days prior to starting study MDR- or RR-TB drugs.

          -  Requirement or expected requirement for a medication that significantly prolongs QTc,
             including but not limited to moxifloxacin (levofloxacin is acceptable), from 72 hours
             prior to study entry through 4 weeks after discontinuation of study treatment (week
             28)

          -  Requirement or expected requirement of clofazimine, a drug that might cause QT
             prolongation at current treatment doses on its own and can potentiate QT prolongation
             when given together with BDQ for prolonged periods, from 7 days prior to study entry
             through week 24 (discontinuation of study treatment).

          -  For individuals receiving the WHO short course regimen that contains clofazimine,
             receipt of more than 21 cumulative days of clofazimine at any time prior to, or at the
             time of, study entry.

          -  Known allergy/sensitivity or any hypersensitivity to components of study TB drugs or
             their formulation or to the nitroimidazole class of antibiotics

          -  Active drug or alcohol use or dependence that, in the opinion of the site
             investigator, would interfere with adherence to study requirements

          -  Any of the following laboratory abnormalities within 14 days prior to entry at any
             network-approved non-U.S. laboratory that operates in accordance with Good Clinical
             Laboratory Practices (GCLP) and participates in appropriate external quality assurance
             programs.

               1. Serum creatinine greater than 1.4 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

               2. Lipase greater than 1.6 x ULN

               3. Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) greater than 2.5 x ULN

               4. Total bilirubin greater than 1.6 x ULN

               5. Potassium less than 3.4 or greater than 5.6 mmol/L; magnesium less than 0.59
                  mmol/L; calcium less than 1.75 mmol/L

          -  Known current hepatitis B or C infection, current treatment for hepatitis B or
             hepatitis C infection, or positive for hepatitis B surface antigen or hepatitis C
             antibodies within 60 days prior to entry

          -  Among participants with HIV infection, in whom use of dolutegravir (DTG) is
             anticipated, any of the following:

               1. Unstable liver disease (as defined by the presence of ascites, encephalopathy,
                  coagulopathy, esophageal varices, or persistent jaundice), known biliary
                  abnormalities (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic
                  gallstones)

               2. History or presence of allergy to DTG or its components

               3. Severe hepatic impairment (Class C) as determined by Child-Pugh classification

               4. Previous use of raltegravir

          -  Documentation of any new and/or unstable AIDS-defining illness (other than TB) as
             defined by the CDC within 60 days prior to entry

          -  Acute or serious illness (other than TB) requiring systemic treatment and/or
             hospitalization within 60 days prior to entry
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kelly Dooley, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Johns Hopkins Adult AIDS CRS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Gary Maartens, MBChB, MMed</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Cape Town</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Barranco CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lima</city>
        <zip>04</zip>
        <country>Peru</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Fanny Rosas, R.N.</last_name>
      <phone>51-1-2067800</phone>
      <phone_ext>401</phone_ext>
      <email>frosas@impactaperu.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Task Applied Science (TASK) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <state>Western Cape Province</state>
        <zip>7530</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christelle v. Niekerk</last_name>
      <phone>27-21-9171044</phone>
      <email>christelle@task.org.za</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>South African Tuberculosis Vaccine Initiative (SATVI) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cape Town</city>
        <state>Western Cape Province</state>
        <zip>7705</zip>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chris Hikuam</last_name>
      <phone>27-21-4066228</phone>
      <email>chris.hikuam@uct.ac.za</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Peru</country>
    <country>South Africa</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 20, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 20, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 21, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 7, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis, Pulmonary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dolutegravir</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bedaquiline</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diarylquinolines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

