<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02587676</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EC13-006</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02587676</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Deterioration of Resilient Denture Liners and Patient Characteristics</brief_title>
  <official_title>Changes in the Hardness of Resilient Denture Liners Embedded in Maxillary Complete Dentures and Their Association With Patient Characteristics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nihon University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nihon University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Thirty complete maxillary denture wearers were recruited after obtaining informed consent.
      One investigator measured the Shore D hardness of the commercially available RDLs using a
      Vesmeter®. The salivary flow rates and pH values and the occlusal force were measured for all
      patients before initiation of the study.

      T-tests and Pearson's correlation coefficients were used for statistical analyses.

      A p-value of &lt;0.05 was considered statistically significant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. Participants This study was approved by the Human Ethics Committee of Nihon University
           School of Dentistry, Matsudo (EC 13-006). Thirty wearers of complete maxillary dentures
           (12 men; mean age, 71.8 ± 9.2 years and 18 women; mean age, 70.2 ± 10.7 years) who
           visited the Department of Removable Prosthodontics at our institute were recruited for
           this study. The volunteers were enrolled only after they provided written informed
           consent. Complete maxillary denture wearers who had been treated with a tissue
           conditioner, RDLs, and denture adhesives were excluded. Before starting the clinical
           trial, the participants were asked about the following environmental factors in a
           questionnaire: smoking, drinking, denture wearing during sleeping, and denture cleanser
           usage.

           After specimen making, all participants were instructed to wear their dentures as per
           their normal routine.

        2. Specimen Preparation A cylinder shapes six places with a 4-mm diameter and 2-mm depth ,
           that was drilled into the inner surface of the denture base. Then, the RDL materials
           were mixed by each product, packed into the cavity, and polymerized at room temperature
           . The six commercial RDLs used in this study:Evatouch Super (EVA; Neo Dental Chemical
           products, Washington, USA), GC RELINE (GCR; GC Dental Products Corp, Tokyo, Japan),
           Mucopren soft (MCP; Kettenbach GmbH &amp; Co KG, California, USA) Soften (SFT; KAMEMIZU
           CHEM, Osaka, Japan), FD Soft (FDS; KAMEMIZU CHEM, Osaka, Japan), and Bio Liner (BIO;
           Nissin Dental Products, Kyoto, Japan).

           Hardness was measured using a Vesmeter® (WaveCyber Corp, Saitama, Japan). When the
           probe, which included a built-in position sensor connected to a personal computer, was
           placed in a perpendicular orientation to an RDL, the indenter of the probe was depressed
           onto the RDL at a constant speed through electromagnetic power. Simultaneously, the path
           of the indenter was constantly traced by the position sensor. The computer processed
           electrical signals from the measuring device and calculated the Shore D hardness, which
           was the primary outcome in the present study. The same investigator measured the
           hardness at each appointment. The original hardness and the hardness at 1 month after
           oral exposure were used for analysis. Each specimen was measured five times, and the
           highest and lowest values were eliminated from the calculation of the mean
           representative value for each specimen. The specimens embedded in the dentures were
           measured on a hot plate to maintain the temperature at 37°C or as close to the oral
           temperature as possible.

        3. Statistical Analyses Before other statistical analyses, the normality of the data was
           tested using the Kolmogorov - Smirnov test, and then parametric statistical methods were
           applied.Two-way repeated measures analysis of variance ( ANOVA ) with the material type
           (EVA, MCP, GCR, FDS, SFT, and BIO) and time period (baseline and one month after) as
           factors was used to assess changes in the hardness of the six RDLs over time. The
           Tukey-Kramer test was used as a post hoc test after the two-way repeated measures ANOVA
           .The effects of categorical variables such as sex, smoking, drinking, denture wearing
           during sleeping, and denture cleanser usage on the hardness of the RDLs were analyzed
           using a two-way ANOVA without a post hoc test; we were not interested in comparing each
           RDL but rather in analyzing the effects of categorical variables on the RDLs. The
           effects of continuous variables, including age, salivary flow rate, and occlusal force,
           were analyzed using Pearson's correlation coefficients. All statistical analyses were
           performed using IBM® SPSS® Statistics 21 (IBM, Armonk, NY, USA). A p-value of &lt;0.05 was
           considered statistically significant.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>hardness</measure>
    <time_frame>10 min</time_frame>
    <description>Denture liners's hardness was measured using a Vesmeter® (WaveCyber Corp, Saitama ,Japan) at the out of oral cavity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Salivary flow test(Unstimulated saliva)</measure>
    <time_frame>5 min</time_frame>
    <description>The participants were instructed to sit in an upright position with their heads inclined forward, which facilitated saliva collection at the floor of the mouth and overflow from the lip. The saliva was allowed to drip into a measuring cup for 5 min, and the flow rate was calculated in mL/min .</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Salivary flow test(Stimulated saliva)</measure>
    <time_frame>2min</time_frame>
    <description>The participants were instructed to chew a piece of paraffin gum until it became soft. The first collection of saliva was swallowed, the timer was set, and chewing was continued for another 2 min .The participants spat out the saliva at short intervals into a measuring cup. The participants were instructed not to eat anything (drinking water was allowed), smoke, or take snuff at least two hours before the tests.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>pH measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>5 min</time_frame>
    <description>The pH values of the resting and stimulated saliva were obtained using a pH testing device (pH Spear, Eutech Instruments Pte Ltd, Ayer Rajah Crescent, Singapore). The investigator dipped the electrode approximately 2 to 3 cm into the saliva in a measuring cup and recorded the digitally obtained value.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Occlusal force measurement</measure>
    <time_frame>5 min</time_frame>
    <description>A GM10 occlusal force meter (Nagano Keiki, Tokyo, Japan) was used to measure the occlusal force. The maximum occlusal force applied by the functioning left and right first molars was measured three times, and the mean was used as a representative value.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>10 min</time_frame>
    <description>Before starting the clinical trial, the participants were asked about the following environmental factors in a questionnaire: smoking, drinking, denture wearing during sleeping, and denture cleanser usage.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Xerostomia</condition>
  <condition>Menopause</condition>
  <condition>Kidney Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>denture liners</arm_group_label>
    <description>Evatouch Super (EVA; Neo Dental Chemical products, Washington, USA), GC RELINE (GCR; GC Dental Products Corp, Tokyo, Japan), Mucopren soft (MCP; Kettenbach GmbH &amp; Co KG, California, USA) Soften (SFT; KAMEMIZU CHEM, Osaka, Japan), FD Soft (FDS; KAMEMIZU CHEM, Osaka, Japan), and Bio Liner (BIO; Nissin Dental Products, Kyoto, Japan).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Evatouch Super</intervention_name>
    <description>The deterioration of RDLs may differ between in vitro conditions and the conditions encountered in denture wearers. We conducted an in vivo study to investigate how resilient denture liners (RDLs) changed in hardness when embedded in complete maxillary dentures worn by patients for one month in a clinical setting. We hypothesized that the hardness one month after application of the RDLs would be affected by the age, the condition of the saliva, the occlusal force, type of denture used, the patients habits related to smoking, drinking, wearing dentures while sleeping, and using a denture cleanser.</description>
    <arm_group_label>denture liners</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GC RELINE</other_name>
    <other_name>Mucopren soft</other_name>
    <other_name>Soften</other_name>
    <other_name>FD Soft</other_name>
    <other_name>Bio Liner</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The patient of wearing complete maxillary dentures who visited the Department of Removable
        Prosthodontics at our institute were recruited for this study.

        The volunteers were enrolled only after they provided written informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  wearing maxillary complete dentures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  had been treated with a tissue conditioner, RDLs, and denture adhesives were excluded

          -  showed obvious cognitive impairment

          -  could not understand written or spoken Japanese
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>95 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Akina Ogawa</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Depertment of removable prosthodontics Nihon University School of Dentistry at Matsudo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kimoto S, So K, Yamamoto S, Ohno Y, Shinomiya M, Ogura K, Kobayashi K. Randomized controlled clinical trial for verifying the effect of silicone-based resilient denture liner on the masticatory function of complete denture wearers. Int J Prosthodont. 2006 Nov-Dec;19(6):593-600.</citation>
    <PMID>17165299</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 26, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 26, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 27, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 26, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 26, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 28, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Nihon University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Yasuhiko Kawai</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor Dr.Yasuhiko kawai</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Xerostomia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

