<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02589873</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CN-15-2318-H</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02589873</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Getting in Balance: A Workplace Diabetes Prevention Intervention Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>GIBW</acronym>
  <official_title>A Workplace Intervention Trial Comparing Two Diabetes Prevention Programs - In-person and Online - Delivered in a Large Urban Workplace Environment.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kaiser Permanente</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kaiser Permanente</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates two group-based Diabetes Prevention Program (DPP) lifestyle
      interventions delivered in the workplace to individuals at risk for pre-diabetes: 1) an
      in-person group-based lifestyle intervention; and 2) an internet-based intervention delivered
      using an online platform with lifestyle coaching support. Eligible participants will be
      randomized equally to each intervention program (120 participants in each).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study seeks to compare weight loss, changes in physical activity and dietary fat intake,
      and participant engagement in two Diabetes Prevention Program (DPP) interventions derived
      from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) curriculum: an in-person and an
      internet-based intervention program.

      We hypothesize that the internet-based intervention will be more effective in achieving
      weight loss than the in-person intervention, given its convenience for participants to
      complete sessions and therefore greater potential engagement in the program.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Body weight lost</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percentage of body weight lost and the amount of weight lost (in pounds) on average over the 12 month follow-up, and at 6 and 12 months compared to baseline, by intervention arm. Body weight will be collected at baseline, 6 months, and 12 months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in minutes of physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in physical activity duration per week - measured using the International Physical Activity Questionnaire (IPAQ);</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in dietary fat intake</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in daily dietary fat intake - measured using the Block Fat Screener</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Participant engagement</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participant engagement - measured by the number of intervention sessions completed by 6 months, as well as the number of maintenance sessions completed between 6 and 12 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Stress and well-being</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in well-being - measured using SF-8 Health Survey</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">157</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <condition>Overweight</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>In-Person Diabetes Prevention Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>An in-person group delivery modality of a CDC recognized Diabetes Prevention Program (DPP), delivered by the Young Men's Christian Association (YMCA). This group receives lifestyle coaching in a group setting, meeting weekly for 16 weeks followed by 3 biweekly sessions, and 5 monthly maintenance sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Online Diabetes Prevention Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>An online delivery modality of a CDC recognized Diabetes Prevention Program (DPP), delivered by Canary Health's Virtual Lifestyle Management program. This group completes online learning sessions weekly for 16 weeks followed by 8 monthly maintenance sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>In-Person Diabetes Prevention Program</intervention_name>
    <description>Lifestyle intervention program involving group-based educational sessions, diet and physical activity tracking, and weekly weigh ins. Participants complete the intervention over 12 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>In-Person Diabetes Prevention Program</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>YMCA DPP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Online Diabetes Prevention Program</intervention_name>
    <description>Lifestyle intervention program involving web-based educational videos, diet and physical activity tracking, and recording weight. Participants complete the intervention over 12 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Online Diabetes Prevention Program</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Virtual Lifestyle Management</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ethnicity: All ethnic groups;

          -  Sex: all genders;

          -  Age (as of date of enrollment): Lower age limit: 18 years; Upper age limit: NONE;

          -  Body mass index ≥ 25.0 kg/m2; ≥23 kg/m2 if Asian

          -  Having pre-diabetes based on a score of 9+ on the CDC pre-diabetes screener

          -  Able and willing to enroll and provide written, informed consent, i.e., to:

          -  meet the time and data collection requirements of the study;

          -  be randomized to one of the two intervention programs;

          -  adhere to the recommendations of the study intervention as assigned; and

          -  participate in follow-up for 12 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Does not work at one of the participating employer work locations/departments;

          -  Inability to speak, read, or understand English;

          -  No regular access to a computer with internet capabilities;

          -  Diagnosis of Type 1 or Type 2 diabetes mellitus;

          -  Systolic blood pressure ≥ 180 mm Hg or diastolic blood pressure ≥ 100 mm Hg on more
             than one occasion during the last year;

          -  Having a medical or physical condition that make moderate intensity physical activity
             (like a brisk walk) difficult or unsafe, such as exercise induced asthma or chronic
             obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD);

          -  Use of weight-loss medications in the past 3 months;

          -  Regular use (&gt; 5 days/month) of medications that affect appetite or weight (e.g., oral
             corticosteroids, insulin, oral hypoglycemics etc.);

          -  Currently enrolled in a weight loss program;

          -  Planning to undergo bariatric surgery during the study period;

          -  Heart disease (angina, heart attack (myocardial infarction), congestive heart failure
             (CHF)), stroke;

          -  Renal insufficiency;

          -  Diagnosis of cancer (other than non-melanoma skin cancer) that was active or treated
             with radiation or chemotherapy within the past 2 years;

          -  Pregnant, lactating or planning to become pregnant during the study period;

          -  Already enrolled or planning to enroll in a research study that would limit full
             participation in this study or confound the observation and interpretation of the
             study's findings;

          -  Planning to transfer to another department location during the study period;

          -  Planning to move out of the area during the study period;

          -  Investigator discretion for clinical safety or protocol adherence reasons.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Assiamira Ferrara, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kaiser Permanente</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>City and County of San Francisco</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 26, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 26, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 28, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lifestyle Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Workplace</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes Prevention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

