<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02586519</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PINUP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02586519</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pressure-Sensing Insoles in the Neuropathic Ulcer Treatment Pathway</brief_title>
  <acronym>PINUP</acronym>
  <official_title>Pressure-Sensing Insoles in the Neuropathic Ulcer Treatment Pathway (PINUP): A Randomized Controlled Trial for Active Neuropathic Ulcer Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Calgary</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Calgary</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Diabetic foot ulceration (DFU) is a common complication with a 25% lifetime risk in patients
      with diabetes. While most of these ulcers can be treated successfully on an outpatient basis,
      some will persist and become infected. Nearly one fifth of patients with lower-extremity
      diabetic ulcers will require amputation of the affected limb, resulting in staggering costs
      for both the patient and the healthcare system. Therapies that promote rapid and complete
      healing and reduce the need for expensive surgical procedures impact these costs
      substantially.

      The standard of care for the treatment of diabetic foot ulcers is the removable cast walker
      (RCW). RCW use has demonstrated plantar pressure reduction yet is typically perceived as
      having compliance issues due to its removable nature. In addressing this limitation, a
      modified version of the RCW has been developed by wrapping it in a layer of cohesive or
      plaster bandage. This technique has been termed the &quot;instant&quot; total contact cast (iTCC)
      derived from the seldom-used, gold standard treatment, the total contact cast (TCC). While
      ease of application and potential clinical equivalence are clear benefits, the iTCC carries
      disadvantages on account of its irremovability. For example, frequent dressing changes
      impractical, yet may be necessary for complex wound care. The goal of this research is to
      continue inquiry and innovation in this most basic aspect of care, whilst addressing the
      limitations of past research and failures in this domain.

      The investigators propose examining the capability of the SurroSense Rx® smart insole and
      smartwatch system (Orpyx Medical Technologies Inc., Calgary AB) in managing and monitoring
      adherence to plantar pressure offloading through alert-based feedback. The insoles are
      embedded with pressure sensors, which wirelessly communicate with a smartwatch that provides
      feedback on modifying activity or pressure profile over time. This smartwatch transmits
      audio, visual, and tactile notifications when excessive pressure-time thresholds under
      plantar regions of interest have been met. This feedback allows patients to be educated on
      their plantar pressure, and engages them and their caregivers to manage adherence to
      offloading. The investigators also propose comparing the healing rates of active neuropathic
      ulcers using RCWs coupled with the SurroSense Rx® smart insole system to assess whether
      adjunctive use of the two interventions improves the efficiency of neuropathic ulcer
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pressure offloading is the lynchpin of neuropathic ulcer care. Multiple methods of statically
      reducing pressure have been employed, with various degrees of success, in the ulcer care
      continuum. Traditional offloading interventions redistribute the load on the plantar surface,
      and include: non-removable devices (total contact casts, removable walkers rendered
      non-removable, and cast shoes), and removable devices (walkers, forefoot offloading shoes,
      half shoes, bivalve total contact casts, and therapeutic shoes)1,2,3.

      A Cochrane Review on the use of offloading in the treatment of uncomplicated neuropathic
      plantar ulcers gives the efficacy of each device type in terms of percentage of ulcers healed
      and time required for healing4. The total contact cast has been found to be more effective
      than removable devices in many randomized controlled trials, for both the percentage of
      neuropathic ulcers healed and the time required for healing5,6,7. Ninety-two percent of
      neuropathic ulcers healed in an average of 6 weeks8. Removable walkers made non-removable may
      be as effective as total contact casts9,10,11. The effectiveness of forefoot offloading
      shoes, half-shoes, and cast shoes in the healing of neuropathic forefoot ulcers needs to be
      confirmed by prospective trials12. The lower efficacy of prescribed removable devices could
      be attributable to a lower adherence to recommended use13.

      The effectiveness of offloading interventions is intimately linked to the skin reperfusion
      that is seen when persistent external pressure is alleviated. Key modifiable parameters in
      mitigating tissue damage to the neuropathic foot are pressure and time. Kosiak reported in
      1959 that &quot;microscopic pathologic changes were noted in tissues subjected to as little as 60
      mmHg for only one hour&quot;14,15. More recently, exposures from 15 min to one hour at pressures
      greater than 240 mmHg, and from two hours or more at pressures greater than 67 mmHg, were
      found to cause cell death in rat muscle tissue16. Despite this, there is limited information
      regarding the efficacy of interventions aimed at preventing pressure ulcers; a comprehensive
      review of the literature did not find enough evidence to recommend a repositioning
      frequency17. A consensus document from an international review on pressure ulcer prevention
      states that &quot;patients confined to wheelchairs should be taught to reposition every 15
      minutes&quot;18.

      While established pressure offloading interventions are able to statically reduce pressure on
      the active ulcer, they provide no dynamic relief of pressure. Since neuropathy is
      characterized by a loss of protective sensation (LOPS), the patient is often unaware of
      sustained pressure on a specific anatomic region over time. Even with static offloading
      instruments, it is conceivable that critical pressure and time thresholds can be dynamically
      exceeded without the patient's knowledge or ability to address the problem.

      Taken together, the literature provides support for the development of a system that monitors
      pressure over time at key locations, and provides alert-based feedback to guide as-needed,
      patient-based offloading for use in patients with active ulceration.

      The SurroSense Rx system (Orpyx Medical Technologies Inc., Calgary, AB) is a patent pending
      (US Publication #20120109013 and PCT WO/2012/055029) footwear system designed to aid in the
      prevention of plantar pressure ulceration and re-ulceration and the treatment of active
      ulcers in neuropathic patients. It comprises two pressure-sensing inserts and a smartwatch
      display device. The device alerts the user when &quot;safe&quot; pressure and time thresholds have been
      exceeded; the current thresholds are based on the general clinical understanding of pressure
      ulcer formation, which indicates that a conservative threshold would be &gt;30-50mmHg for &gt;15
      minutes. For a review of the literature, please refer to Appendix 4. As more plantar pressure
      and outcome data are collected over time, these thresholds may be modified for future
      iterations of the product. These thresholds will be kept constant for the duration of the
      study in question. The device measures plantar pressures at discrete points corresponding to
      bony prominences that would be considered to be at higher risk for ulceration: the first
      metatarsal head (1), the lateral metatarsal heads (2), the great toe (1), the lateral toes
      (1), the lateral foot (2), and the heel (1). These areas were selected based on the inherent
      high risk of neuropathic ulceration at these anatomic locations. This data is tracked, with
      analysis being performed on those that have been collected over the last 15 minutes. If &gt; 95%
      of the measurements taken by a pressure sensor over a 15-minute scanning window exceed 30-50
      mmHg, an alert is sent to the user via the smartwatch to guide them to appropriately offload
      that area.

      The proof of concept of the designed platform as a supplement in the management of the
      diabetic foot ulcer (DFU) will be assessed in the context of a randomized clinical trial
      (RCT) pilot. Our hypotheses are that the proposed technology will:

        1. Accelerate the wound healing process (i.e. success of complete wound healing within 16
           weeks, time to heal, rate of wound size change, and complication rate);

        2. Improve adherence with RCW use (measured in hours of use per day); and

        3. Improve offloading (i.e. in terms of pressure-time intervals).

        4. Upon wound closure, prevent the incidence of plantar ulcer recurrence.

      Eligible subjects will be randomized to the Experimental Arm, Control Arm A or Control Arm B
      (25 per arm). The experimental group will be provided with an active (alerting) SurroSense
      Rx® device fitted into a standardized RCW* (Rebound® Diabetic Walker, Össur, Iceland).
      Control Group A will be provided with an inactive (non-alerting) version of the SurroSense
      Rx® device fitted into a standardized RCW. Control Group B will be provided with an inactive
      version of the SurroSense Rx® device fitted into a standardized RCW and secured with a
      device-specific tie; this will act as an iTCC device for the purposes of this trial. Patients
      in all arms will be provided with a New Balance 928 shoe to wear on their contralateral foot
      so as to ensure optimal device performance. All patients will be assessed at baseline and
      every week until successful wound healing or 16 weeks, whichever comes first. Following wound
      resolution, patients will be followed with their assigned device, being used in a pair of New
      Balance 928 shoes to be provided to the patient, for 6 months for ulcer recurrence. After 6
      months, the device will be discontinued, at which time the patients will be followed for an
      additional 12 months for further ulcer recurrence. Should a patient's wound remain unresolved
      after 16 weeks, they will continue using their assigned device into the subsequent 6-month
      period. If wound resolution occurs during this 6-month period, patients will switch to the
      New Balance 928 shoes for the remainder of the period; however, if wound resolution does not
      occur during this time, the patient will be withdrawn from the study prior to the
      commencement of the subsequent 12-month observation period. For all research subjects wearing
      the SurroSense Rx®, the device will measure plantar pressure and adherence to prescribed
      offloading. All groups will be fit with Jawbone UP Activity Trackers (or an equivalent
      activity tracker) so as to monitor their activity throughout the study.

      *The removable Rebound® Diabetic Walker insole is heat-moldable: it can be heated (3 minutes
      at 110°C/230°F) and formed to the patients' foot (the patient stands in socks on the heated
      insole for 1 minute - then the hexagons should be removed as appropriate). This method should
      improve the weight distribution of the plantar foot and provide better offloading at the
      ulcer sites, and is recommended for optimal treatment.

      Primary aims of the study:

        -  This pilot study will investigate the efficacy of the SurroSense Rx® system in
           expediting the healing of active neuropathic ulcers in terms of rate of wound area
           reduction.

        -  It will also investigate the system's potential to improve healing rates in the
           treatment of active neuropathic ulcers using the more practical RCWs.

        -  It will also investigate the system's potential to prevent recurrent ulceration post
           ulcer resolution. To achieve this, following wound resolution, patients will be followed
           for 18 months (the first 6 months with their assigned device) to monitor for ulcer
           recurrence.

      Secondary aims of the study:

        -  Compare complete wound healing at 16 weeks in the experimental versus control groups

        -  Compare the healing times and rates as a function of the patient's baseline Michigan
           Neuropathy Screening Instrument (MNSI) and Modified Neuropathy Disability Score (MNDS)19
           in the experimental versus control group

        -  Compare the change in the MNDS over the course of the study

        -  Performance of a cost-effectiveness analysis of the experimental versus control group's
           methods of treating diabetic ulcers

        -  Elucidate pressure data and adherence parameters (activity data—including step count and
           type of activity, peak pressures, number of alerts, measures of central tendency for
           time to offload, areas of alert generation, hours of use per day) for all patients, and
           compare those data for patients in the experimental versus control groups

        -  Compare area of ulceration to areas of SurroSense Rx® device alert generation (active
           devices) or would-be alert generation (inactive devices)

        -  Compare pressure data and adherence parameters (activity data—including step count and
           type of activity, peak pressures, number of alerts, measures of central tendency for
           time to offload, areas of alert generation, hours of use per day) to MNSI and MNDS
           Scales

        -  Examine the ability of pressure data and adherence parameters to predict healing

        -  Comparison of complication rates in the experimental versus control groups
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Wound Closure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of Wound Closure (mm2 per day)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Wound Resolution</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of Wound Closure (Complete) over first 12 weeks</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrence of Ulcer</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Rate of ulcer recurrence in 6 months post complete wound closure (epithelialization)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost Utility</measure>
    <time_frame>Wound Healing Period (up to 12 weeks) + 6 Months Post-Wound Closure</time_frame>
    <description>Cost of care over assessed period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>Wound Healing Period (up to 12 weeks) + 6 Months Post-Wound Closure</time_frame>
    <description>Change in activity (step count) over time period of assessment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complication Rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Wound Healing Period (up to 12 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Requirement for antibiotics and/or surgical intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Complications</condition>
  <condition>Neuropathy</condition>
  <condition>Peripheral Neuropathy</condition>
  <condition>Diabetic Foot Ulcer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active SurroSense Rx System + RCW</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to the experimental group will be fitted with an active (alerting) version of the SurroSense R® smart insole System. This device will be placed in the RCW, underneath the liner. The device tab will be fed up the instep, through a hole in the liner, and affixed to the dorsum of the RCW by way of a tie.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inactive SurroSense Rx System + RCW</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to this group will be fitted with an inactive (non-alerting) version of the device in an identical fashion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Inactive SurroSense Rx System + iTCC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this group will be fitted with an inactive (non-alerting) version of the device in an identical fashion. The RCW will be further secured using a device specific tie such that it acts as an iTCC.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SurroSense Rx System</intervention_name>
    <description>The SurroSense Rx system (Orpyx Medical Technologies Inc., Calgary, AB) is a smart insole system designed to aid in the prevention of plantar pressure ulceration and re-ulceration, and the treatment of active ulcers in neuropathic patients. It comprises two pressure-sensing inserts and a smartwatch display device. The device alerts the user when &quot;safe&quot; pressure and time thresholds have been exceeded so that on-demand offloading can occur.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active SurroSense Rx System + RCW</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Inactive SurroSense Rx System + RCW</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Inactive SurroSense Rx System + iTCC</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SurroSense Rx Smart Insole System</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Diabetes (according to AAFP diagnostic criteria )

          -  Presence of neuropathy with Loss of Protective Sensation (LOPS), as defined by any
             loss of sensation as per the assessments included in the Modified Neuropathy
             Disability Score (MNDS)

          -  Active plantar diabetic foot ulcer (Grade 1A, according to the University of Texas
             Wound Classification System , )

               -  A minimum size ulcer ≥1cm2 and ≤ 12 cm2 post debridement at time of randomization

               -  If the subject has more than one ulcer, they should be identified and at least 2
                  cm apart

          -  Age &gt;18

          -  At least one palpable foot pulse

          -  Ability to understand all of the study requirements

          -  Life expectancy greater than the duration of the study

          -  Toe pressure (plethysmography) &gt; 50mm Hg

          -  Subject or responsible caregiver is willing and able to maintain the required
             offloading (as applicable for the location of the ulcer) and applicable dressing
             changes

          -  Doppler Ultrasound positive for at least one pedal pulse in each foot

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Weight &gt; 400 lb (182 kg)

          -  Uncorrected visual impairment

          -  Active Infection

          -  Non-plantar ulcers on the ankle, posterior heel, or other location

          -  More than one active plantar ulcer

          -  Presence of severe ischemia (any of: absence of foot pulses, Ankle Brachial Index 0.6
             &gt; [ABI] &gt; 1.2, capillary refill time &gt; 5 seconds; see Appendix 3)

          -  Current participation in another clinical investigation of a medical device or a drug;
             or has participated in such a study within 30 days prior to this study

          -  Current smokers

          -  Active abuse of alcohol

             o Subject has a history of any of the following intercurrent illnesses or conditions
             that would compromise the safety of the subject or the normal healing process:

          -  End-stage renal disease

          -  Immunosuppression

          -  Severe malnutrition

          -  Liver disease

          -  Aplastic anemia

          -  Scleroderma

          -  Acquired immune deficiency disease (AIDS) or HIV positive

          -  Connective tissue disorder

          -  Exacerbation of sickle cell anemia

          -  Active Charcot foot

          -  Excessive lymphedema

          -  Osteomyelitis and gangrene

          -  Subjects with ulcers secondary to a disease other than diabetes (e.g. vasculitis,
             neoplasms or haematological disorders)

             o At the end of the run-in period and prior to randomization, the subject be excluded
             if the following conditions are not met:

          -  Subject does not continue to meet the entrance criteria (inclusion and exclusion)

          -  The size of the study ulcer, following debridement, has decreased by more than 30%
             from the baseline assessment measured at screening.

          -  Abnormal toe and/or ankle range of motion

          -  Metatarsal ray amputation(s) (although transmetatarsal ray amputation is not an
             exclusion criteria)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karim Manji, DPM, AACFAS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Calgary</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karim Mani, DPM, AACFAS</last_name>
    <phone>4032292273</phone>
    <email>karim.manji@ucalgary.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Breanne Everett, MD, MBA, BSc</last_name>
    <phone>4034729949</phone>
    <email>breanne.everett@med.ucalgary.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Diabetic Foot &amp; Limb Preservation Centre- Peter Lougheed Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T1Y 6J4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karim Manji, DPM, AACFAS</last_name>
      <phone>4032292273</phone>
      <email>karim.manji@ucalgary.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cavanagh PR, Bus SA. Off-loading the diabetic foot for ulcer prevention and healing. J Vasc Surg. 2010 Sep;52(3 Suppl):37S-43S. doi: 10.1016/j.jvs.2010.06.007. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20804932</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bus SA, Valk GD, van Deursen RW, Armstrong DG, Caravaggi C, Hlavácek P, Bakker K, Cavanagh PR. The effectiveness of footwear and offloading interventions to prevent and heal foot ulcers and reduce plantar pressure in diabetes: a systematic review. Diabetes Metab Res Rev. 2008 May-Jun;24 Suppl 1:S162-80. doi: 10.1002/dmrr.850. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18442178</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bus SA. Priorities in offloading the diabetic foot. Diabetes Metab Res Rev. 2012 Feb;28 Suppl 1:54-9. doi: 10.1002/dmrr.2240. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22271724</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lewis J, Lipp A. Pressure-relieving interventions for treating diabetic foot ulcers. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2013 Jan 31;(1):CD002302. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD002302.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23440787</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>KOSIAK M. Etiology and pathology of ischemic ulcers. Arch Phys Med Rehabil. 1959 Feb;40(2):62-9.</citation>
    <PMID>13618101</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Linder-Ganz E, Engelberg S, Scheinowitz M, Gefen A. Pressure-time cell death threshold for albino rat skeletal muscles as related to pressure sore biomechanics. J Biomech. 2006;39(14):2725-32. Epub 2005 Sep 30.</citation>
    <PMID>16199045</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reddy M, Gill SS, Rochon PA. Preventing pressure ulcers: a systematic review. JAMA. 2006 Aug 23;296(8):974-84. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16926357</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chawla A, Bhasin G, Chawla R, &quot;Validation Of Neuropathy Symptoms Score (NSS) And Neuropathy Disability Score (NDS ) In The Clinical Diagnosis Of Peripheral Neuropathy In Middle Aged People With Diabetes.&quot; The Internet Journal of Family Practice; 12(1).</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Armstrong DG, Lavery LA, Harkless LB. Validation of a diabetic wound classification system. The contribution of depth, infection, and ischemia to risk of amputation. Diabetes Care. 1998 May;21(5):855-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9589255</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lavery LA, Armstrong DG, Harkless LB. Classification of diabetic foot wounds. J Foot Ankle Surg. 1996 Nov-Dec;35(6):528-31.</citation>
    <PMID>8986890</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mueller MJ, Diamond JE, Sinacore DR, Delitto A, Blair VP 3rd, Drury DA, Rose SJ. Total contact casting in treatment of diabetic plantar ulcers. Controlled clinical trial. Diabetes Care. 1989 Jun;12(6):384-8.</citation>
    <PMID>2659299</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ganguly S, Chakraborty K, Mandal PK, Ballav A, Choudhury S, Bagchi S, Mukherjee S. A comparative study between total contact casting and conventional dressings in the non-surgical management of diabetic plantar foot ulcers. J Indian Med Assoc. 2008 Apr;106(4):237-9, 244.</citation>
    <PMID>18828342</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Armstrong DG, Lavery LA, Wu S, Boulton AJ. Evaluation of removable and irremovable cast walkers in the healing of diabetic foot wounds: a randomized controlled trial. Diabetes Care. 2005 Mar;28(3):551-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15735186</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahn C, Salcido RS. Advances in wound photography and assessment methods. Adv Skin Wound Care. 2008 Feb;21(2):85-93; quiz 94-5. doi: 10.1097/01.ASW.0000305411.58350.7d. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18349736</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thomas GB, Finney RL. Calculus and Analytic Geometry. 9th ed. Reading, MA: Addison Wesley; 1995.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 22, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 23, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 26, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Calgary</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Karim Manji</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Lecturer, Department of Surgery, University of Calgary, Cumming School of Medicine, Diabetic Foot &amp; Limb Preservation Centre Peter Lougheed Centre</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>wearable technology</keyword>
  <keyword>Orpyx</keyword>
  <keyword>SurroSense Rx</keyword>
  <keyword>smart insole</keyword>
  <keyword>TCC</keyword>
  <keyword>total contact cast</keyword>
  <keyword>insole</keyword>
  <keyword>removable cast walker</keyword>
  <keyword>RCW</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Foot</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Foot Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peripheral Nervous System Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Complications</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

