<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01074190</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STU00007275</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01074190</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Neuraxial Analgesia on Maternal Breastfeeding</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Neuraxial Analgesia on Maternal Breastfeeding</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Northwestern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Northwestern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A previous randomized trial showed a possible negative association with labor neuraxial
      analgesia with high compared to low doses of fentanyl, and breastfeeding at 6 weeks
      postpartum. The significance of this study would be to validate or refute these findings. In
      addition, we hope to better evaluate the impact of cumulative dose of fentanyl on
      breastfeeding success in the initial postpartum period as well as at 6 weeks and 6 months
      post delivery. In order to better assess the quality of breastfeeding, we will utilize a
      validated breastfeeding assessment tool, LATCH (Latch, Audible swallowing, Type of Nipple,
      Comfort, and Help). This validated tool can assess maternal and infant variables, define
      areas of needed intervention, and determine priorities in providing patient teaching. The
      LATCH assessment has been shown to be a predictor of breastfeeding duration. We also plan to
      vary the dosage of fentanyl analgesia to determine the relationship between doses below 150
      micrograms and changes in breastfeeding assessments. If a clear association between decreased
      breastfeeding and total fentanyl is identified, then regimens to reduce cumulative doses of
      fentanyl can be developed to improve the likelihood of breastfeeding success in mothers that
      desire to breastfeed.

      Prior observational studies have inferred epidurals negatively affect breastfeeding by
      decreasing maternal plasma oxytocin release which may adversely affect infant neurobehavioral
      development. In a study by Beilin et al., it was reported that mothers receiving a high
      cumulative dose (&gt; 150 microgram) epidural fentanyl were more likely to have stopped nursing
      6 weeks postpartum compared with groups receiving no fentanyl or those receiving &lt; 150
      microgram. The study however, was underpowered to detect differences in breastfeeding prior
      to hospital discharge. In addition, the breastfeeding assessment tool utilized resulted in
      binary assessments, and therefore, a global rating of the quality of breastfeeding was not
      available.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants in this study will be asked to complete a questionnaire called the Intrinsic
      Motivation Inventory (IMI).

      Subjects will be randomized at the time they request neuraxial analgesia to one of three
      groups: Group 1: patient controlled epidural analgesia (PCEA) with bupivacaine 1mg/mL; Group
      2: PCEA with fentanyl 1 mcg/mL plus bupivacaine 0.8 mg/mL; Group 3: PCEA with fentanyl 2
      mcg/mL plus bupivacaine 0.625 mg/mL. Labor analgesia will be initiated in all groups using
      fentanyl 15 mcg plus bupivacaine 2.5 mg administered intrathecally. A basal infusion rate for
      the PCEA will be set at 8 mL/h with patient administered boluses of 8 mL every 10 minutes and
      a one hour limit of 32 mL. Breakthrough pain in all groups will be managed using
      anesthesiologist administered boluses of bupivacaine 1.25 mg/mL without fentanyl.

      The patient as well as individuals who evaluate the study patient will be blinded to the
      group assignment. Samples of maternal venous blood ½ teaspoon (2 mls) and cord blood 2ml (1/2
      teaspoon) will be collected after the delivery of the fetus. Blood concentrations of fentanyl
      and bupivacaine will be ascertained using high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC)
      analysis. Success of breastfeeding using the LATCH assessment tool will be measured by the
      lactation nurses within 24 hrs of delivery. At 6 weeks and at 3 months postpartum, follow-up
      phone calls by the anesthesia service will be made to assess for duration of breastfeeding.
      Also, the patient's obstetrician will be contacted to obtain the patient's Edinburgh
      Postnatal Depression Score to assess for postpartum depression, which may be a variable in
      decreasing breastfeeding success.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Effect of neuraxial analgesia with fentanyl on maternal-fetal breastfeeding</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">345</enrollment>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Breastfeeding</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>spinal fentanyl 15 micrograms plus bupivacaine 2.5 mg followed by a patient controlled epidural analgesia (PCEA) maintenance infusion of bupivacaine 1mg/mL</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>spinal fentanyl 15 micrograms plus bupivacaine 2.5 mg spinal followed by a PCEA infusion of fentanyl 1 micrograms/mL plus bupivacaine 0.8 mg/mL</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>spinal fentanyl 15 micrograms plus bupivacaine 2.5mg followed by a PCEA infusion of fentanyl 2 micrograms/mL plus bupivacaine 0.625 mg/mL</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Group 1</intervention_name>
    <description>A basal infusion rate for the PCEA will be set at 8 mL/h with patient administered boluses of 8 mL every 10 minutes and a one hour limit of 32 mL. Breakthrough pain in all groups will be managed using anesthesiologist administered boluses of bupivacaine 1.25 mg/mL without fentanyl.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>bupivacaine 1mg/ml</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Group 2</intervention_name>
    <description>A basal infusion rate for the PCEA will be set at 8 mL/h with patient administered boluses of 8 mL every 10 minutes and a one hour limit of 32 mL. Breakthrough pain in all groups will be managed using anesthesiologist administered boluses of bupivacaine 1.25 mg/mL without fentanyl.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>fentanyl 1mcg/ml plus bupivacaine 0.8 mg/ml</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Group 3</intervention_name>
    <description>A basal infusion rate for the PCEA will be set at 8 mL/h with patient administered boluses of 8 mL every 10 minutes and a one hour limit of 32 mL. Breakthrough pain in all groups will be managed using anesthesiologist administered boluses of bupivacaine 1.25 mg/mL without fentanyl.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>fentanyl 2mcg/ml plus bupivacaine 0.625 mg/ml</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 and above

          -  English speaking

          -  Term gestation (&gt; 38 weeks)

          -  Parous parturients presenting for attempted vaginal delivery with a cervical dilation
             less than 8 cm

          -  They must request neuraxial labor analgesia

          -  Have previously successfully breastfed their child postpartum for at least 6 weeks

          -  Are expressing an interest in exclusively breastfeeding postpartum

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Under 18 years of age

          -  Parturients who have received parental opioids during labor or have taken opioids
             prenatally

          -  Patients whose neuraxial analgesia failed due to abnormal spinal anatomy including
             scoliosis or previous spinal instrumentation

          -  Supplemental epidural opioids during labor

          -  Had an expedited labor with the delivery of the fetus less than 90 minutes from the
             placement of the neuraxial anesthestic

          -  Underwent cesarean delivery

          -  Received general analgesia for an unanticipated postpartum procedure

          -  Dropout criteria include patients who wished to be taken out of the study or were lost
             to follow-up
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cynthia Wong, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Northwestern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwestern University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baumgarder DJ, Muehl P, Fischer M, Pribbenow B. Effect of labor epidural anesthesia on breast-feeding of healthy full-term newborns delivered vaginally. J Am Board Fam Pract. 2003 Jan-Feb;16(1):7-13.</citation>
    <PMID>12583645</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Riordan J, Gross A, Angeron J, Krumwiede B, Melin J. The effect of labor pain relief medication on neonatal suckling and breastfeeding duration. J Hum Lact. 2000 Feb;16(1):7-12.</citation>
    <PMID>11138228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rahm VA, Hallgren A, Högberg H, Hurtig I, Odlind V. Plasma oxytocin levels in women during labor with or without epidural analgesia: a prospective study. Acta Obstet Gynecol Scand. 2002 Nov;81(11):1033-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12421171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beilin Y, Bodian CA, Weiser J, Hossain S, Arnold I, Feierman DE, Martin G, Holzman I. Effect of labor epidural analgesia with and without fentanyl on infant breast-feeding: a prospective, randomized, double-blind study. Anesthesiology. 2005 Dec;103(6):1211-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16306734</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jensen D, Wallace S, Kelsay P. LATCH: a breastfeeding charting system and documentation tool. J Obstet Gynecol Neonatal Nurs. 1994 Jan;23(1):27-32.</citation>
    <PMID>8176525</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 22, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 23, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 24, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 31, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 31, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 1, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Northwestern University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cynthia Wong</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Anesthesiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Epidural Labor Analgesia</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Infant</keyword>
  <keyword>Breastfeeding</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bupivacaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fentanyl</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>June 6, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>July 5, 2017</returned>
    <submitted>September 13, 2017</submitted>
    <returned>October 13, 2017</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

