<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01072994</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>691</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>P20HL101434</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01072994</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fish Oil In Heart Transplantation</brief_title>
  <acronym>FOHMC</acronym>
  <official_title>Fish Oil Effect on Heart Muscle Cells in Heart Transplant Patients (FOHMC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Despite aggressive treatment, patients with heart failure have a poor prognosis.
      Docosahexaenoic acid (DHA), an omega-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids found in fish oils, may
      prevent the progressions of heart failure through mechanisms that are not addressed with
      current drugs.

      The omega-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids Docosahexaenoic Acid (DHA) and Eicosapentaenoic acid
      (EPA) favorably impact mitochondrial dysfunction and chronic inflammation in heart failure
      (HF). Treatment with DHA-t-EPA alters cardiac phospholipid composition by decreasing
      arachidonic acid (a pro-inflammatory fatty acid) and increasing DHA and the mitochondrial
      phospholipid cardiolipin, with is associated with improved Left Ventricular (LV) function.

      Fish oil supplements contain a mix of DHA and EPA, however we postulate that DHA is superior
      to EPA in improving mitochondrial function and suppressing inflammation, and thus DHA should
      be used to treat HF.

      Cardiac phospholipid fatty acid composition (i.e. DHA, EPA, and arachidonic acid) and
      cardiolipin (CL) content will be measured in biopsies from stable heart transplantation
      patients that are obtained as part of standard clinical care in heart transplant patients
      before and after treatment with DHA alone or DHA+EPA. We will compare cardiac phospholipid
      composition from biopsies obtained at study entry and at 6 months follow-up (allowable range
      +/- two months, depending on patients' clinical conditions).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      50 adult heart transplant recipients (18-75 years of age) entered the maintenance phase (&gt;6
      months after heart transplantation), remaining clinically quiescent (See Inclusion criteria)
      and undergoing regularly scheduled myocardial biopsies (as part of standard clinical care)
      for allograft rejection will be recruited.

      Half of the subject will be receive DHA and half DHA+EPA administered orally which will be
      administered in two capsules in the morning and two in the evening. Each patient will serve
      as their own control, and comparisons will be made between pre and post treatments within
      each patient.

      Prior to assignment to treatment, a septal biopsy (10 to 20 mg) will be obtained during a
      routine biopsy procedure and immediately frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at -80 until
      analysis. Therapy will continue for at least 6 months and until completion of the primary end
      point of paired cardiac biopsy acquisition. Cardiac biopsies obtained during regularly
      scheduled myocardial biopsies for clinical evaluation for allograft rejection will also be
      analyzed for phospholipid fatty acid composition.

      The study completion date listed in this record was obtained from the &quot;Completed Date&quot;
      entered in the Query View Report System (QVR).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac phospholipid fatty acid composition and cardiolipin (CL) content in myocardium</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Cardiac phospholipid fatty acid composition (i.e. DHA, EPA, and arachidonic acid) and cardiolipin (CL) content will be measured in biopsies from stable heart transplantation patients that are obtained as part of standard clinical care before and after treatment with DHA alone or DHA+EPA. We will compare cardiac phospholipid composition from biopsies obtained at study entry and at 6 months follow-up (allowable range +/- two months, depending on patients' clinical schedule).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Myocardial Tissue in Heart Transplantation</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fish Oil</intervention_name>
    <description>Differential proportional doses of DHA versus DHA and EPA</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 18-75 years of age at time of cardiac transplantation;

          2. Absence of cardiac allograft rejection on the index cardiac biopsy

          3. No treatment for cardiac allograft rejection within 30 days of enrollment

          4. Absence of restrictive physiology or cardiac allograft dysfunction on hemodynamic
             assessment

          5. Stable immunosuppression and other background medications for past 30 days with no
             planned modulation in therapy for 6 months

          6. All women of childbearing potential must have a negative urine pregnancy test prior to
             treatment and agree to use adequate contraception (defined as oral or injectable
             contraceptives, intrauterine devices, surgical sterilization or a combination of a
             condom and spermicide) or limit sexual activity to vasectomized partner for 3 months
             after administration of therapy;

          7. Ability to sign Informed Consent Form and Release of Medical Information Form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Regular use of u)-3 PUFA supplements (fish oil or flax seed oil).

          2. Alcoholism or drug abuse;

          3. Poorly controlled diabetes (defined as a Hb A1C &gt;8);

          4. Fasting triglycerides &gt;250 mg/dl.

          5. Pregnancy and Lactation

          6. Persons with known sensitivity or allergy to fish;
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mandeep R. Mehra, MBBS, FACC</last_name>
    <phone>410-706-8246</phone>
    <email>mmehra@medicine.umaryland.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>February 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 19, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 19, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 22, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 28, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 28, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 29, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Mandeep R. Mehra, Professor and Head of Cardiology</name_title>
    <organization>University of Maryland School of Medicine</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Myocardium</keyword>
  <keyword>Phospholipid</keyword>
  <keyword>Fish oil</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiolipin</keyword>
  <keyword>Transplantation</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

