<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01075737</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>200077-501</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01075737</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Observational Study to Assess the Quality of Life of the Patients With Multiple Sclerosis and Their Caregivers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Observational Study to Assess the Quality of Life of the Caregivers of Patients With Multiple Sclerosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck KGaA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck KGaA</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is an observational, non controlled, non-interventional, multicentric, prospective study
      planned to be conducted in 450 subjects diagnosed with MS and their caregivers in 20 centres
      of Argentina. The observations from this study will contribute to the awareness of the impact
      on the Quality of Life (QoL) of the caregivers and, eventually will also provide measures for
      helping the subjects with multiple sclerosis (MS) without leaving aside the care of the
      physical and psychic health of those who work as caregivers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Caregivers of subjects diagnosed with MS have to take care of many activities of MS subjects
      that they cannot perform themselves, because of their lack of autonomy. The fact of aiding a
      person with some degree of disability due to a chronic disease in an intense way and for a
      long time could generate a high level of satisfaction in the caregiver; but at the same time
      the emotional and physical exhaustion of the caregiver increases as the disease progresses.
      The QoL of the person who is emotionally bonded to the MS subject as a caregiver has a great
      chance to be affected; and this is for sure more likely than in the case when the caregiver
      is a hired professional.

      OBJECTIVES

      Primary objective:

        -  To identify the impact of MS on the QoL of the MS subjects and their caregivers

      Secondary objectives:

        -  To establish the correlation between the QoL of the subjects with MS and their
           caregivers

        -  To identify the predictors of the QoL in the caregiver group

      This is an observational, prospective and non-interventional study planned to be conducted in
      20 centers in Argentina. The subjects with diagnosed MS will be managed with the clinical and
      therapeutic elements that their treating doctors considered appropriate, without modifying
      their decisions due to the subjects' inclusion into the study. The caregivers will be asked
      to complete the QoL questionnaire as a part of the normal interview on each and every visit.
      The total duration of the study is 24 months. A descriptive analysis will be performed for
      the demographic and clinical characteristics of the investigation subjects, as well as for
      the characteristics of the treatments they receive when they start their participation in
      this study. For the qualitative variables, treatment modifications, frequency tables and the
      percentages will be performed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of MS on QoL of subjects diagnosed with multiple sclerosis (MS) and their caregivers</measure>
    <time_frame>Each visit starting from the initial visit (Day 0) to end of the observation period (i.e. 24 months)</time_frame>
    <description>SF-36 will be administered to subjects diagnosed with MS and their caregivers; Beck depression inventory and MS-Functional system scores to subjects diagnosed with MS.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between QoL of subjects with MS and their caregivers</measure>
    <time_frame>During the observation period of 24 months starting from the initial visit (i.e. Day 0)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Predictors of QoL of caregivers</measure>
    <time_frame>During the observation period of 24 months starting from the initial visit (i.e. Day 0)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">141</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Subjects with Multiple Sclerosis</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects with diagnosed MS according to the revised Mc Donald criteria 2005; aged &gt;21 years.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Caregivers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Caregivers (aged &gt;21 years) for MS subjects.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects with diagnosed MS and their caregivers in Argentinean population.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  MS subjects and their caregivers, &gt;21 years of age of both sexes

          -  Subjects who have signed informed consent

          -  Subjects with established MS diagnosis according to the revised Mc Donald criteria -
             2005 with at least 1 year of evolution

          -  Subjects with MS that have an identified caregiver

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with other(s) associated neurological, psychiatric or systemic disease(s)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Miguel Jacobo, Neurologist</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>25 de Mayo 138 (Capital, Pcia. de Santiago del Estero) G4200AWD</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>25 de Mayo 138, Capital, Pcia. de</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santiago del Estero</city>
        <zip>G4200AWD</zip>
        <country>Argentina</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Argentina</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 24, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 24, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 25, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 14, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 14, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 17, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Sclerosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of life</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

