<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01678352</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11-136</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01678352</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Imiquimod and Tumor Lysate Vaccine Immunotherapy in Adults With High Risk or Recurrent Grade II Gliomas</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study to Evaluate the Effects of Imiquimod and Tumor Lysate Vaccine Immunotherapy for Adults With High Risk or Recurrent/Post-Chemotherapy WHO Grade II Gliomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Frank Lieberman</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Minnesota - Clinical and Translational Science Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot study of a vaccination regime that is designed to efficiently induce
      anti-tumor T-cell responses in patients with WHO grade II glioma. The proposed regime with
      BTIC Lysate in combination with imiquimod, an FDA-approved immune response modifier will
      induce potent anti-glioma immune response with minimal or no toxicity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      To determine the response rate and magnitude of CD8+ T-cell responses against the
      Imiquimod/BTIC lysate-based vaccines in post-vaccine PBMC using IFN- ELISPOT. ELISPOT assays
      indicate functional status of the antigen-specific T cells as cytokine-expression, and we are
      particularly interested in Type-1 (i.e. IFN expressing) T cell response. Therefore, IFN
      ELISPOT will be used as the primary assay for the immunological endpoint.

      Using flow-cytometry, we will also evaluate the numbers of lymphocyte subsets such as CD4+ T
      cells, CD4+/Foxp3+ regulatory T cells in an exploratory manner. In addition, in participants
      who undergo surgical debulking of the progressing tumor, if the tumor tissue is available,
      infiltration of antigen-specific CTLs will be evaluated by flow cytometry of
      tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes with the Imiquimod/BTIC lysate-based vaccine-targeted GAA
      specific MHC-tetramers. In addition, serological responses will be evaluated with
      flow-cytometry of BTIC cells as well as western blotting. These plans (in this paragraph) are
      immunological evaluations; however, do not compose the primary endpoints due to their
      exploratory nature.

      We will determine whether it is safe to administer Imiquimod/BTIC lysate-based vaccines in
      patients with grade II gliomas. Endpoints will therefore include incidence and severity of
      adverse events, using standard criteria as well as close clinical follow-up as would be
      performed normally in this group of participants following vaccinations. All reported or
      observed toxicities and adverse events at all clinic visits will be graded, documented and
      reported according to a standard toxicity table, the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse
      Events (CTCAE) version 4.0
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 8, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Two Years</time_frame>
    <description>The incidence and severity of adverse events associated with the vaccine regime will be assessed, with an early stopping rule based on the frequency of Dose Limiting Toxicity (DLT).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Induction of BTIC Lysate-specific T-cell response</measure>
    <time_frame>Two Years</time_frame>
    <description>We will determine the response rate and magnitude of immune response in post-vaccine peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) against the BTIC Lysate in response to this form of vaccine, using IFN-enzyme-linked immuno-spot (ELISPOT) assays.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">27</enrollment>
  <condition>High Risk WHO Grade II Glioma</condition>
  <condition>Recurrent/Post-Chemotherapy WHO Grade II Glioma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients must have undergone surgery or biopsy alone (no postoperative radiation or chemotherapy) and have a baseline MRI scan (within 4 weeks of the first vaccine) that shows stable disease or regression (no progression from the initial surgery/biopsy).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients received surgery or biopsy and radiation therapy (RT) (including fractionated external beam radiation therapy and/or stereotactic radiosurgery), which was completed ≥ 6 months prior to enrollment, and have a baseline MRI scan within 4 weeks prior to the first vaccine that shows stable disease or regression.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with recurrent WHO grade 2 glioma may have received prior external beam radiotherapy and/or chemotherapy. Patients with stable WHO grade 2 glioma must have had prior chemotherapy (at least one cycle of Temozolomide or PCV-based chemotherapy). With regard to the prior therapy in Cohort 3, patients may have had treatment for no more than 2 prior relapses. Relapse is defined as progression following initial therapy (i.e. radiation +/- chemo if that was used as initial therapy) or observation of stable disease. The intent therefore is that patients may have had 3 prior therapies (initial therapy and treatment for 2 relapses). If the patient had a surgical resection for relapsed disease, and no anti-cancer therapy was instituted for up to 12 weeks, and the patient undergoes another surgical resection, this is considered as 1 relapse.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tumor Lysate Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Cohort 1 Cohort 2 Cohort 3</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Imiquimod</intervention_name>
    <description>Cohort 1 Cohort 2 Cohort 3</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort 3</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Aldara</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Cohort 1 and 2: Age ≥18 year old with histologically diagnosed World Health
             Organization (WHO) grade II astrocytoma or oligoastrocytoma with &quot;high-risk&quot; factors -
             defined as:

               -  age ≥ 40 with any extent resection;

               -  age 18-39 with incomplete resection (post-op MRI showing &gt;1cm residual disease,
                  based on the maximum dimension of residual T2 or fluid-attenuated
                  inversion-recovery [FLAIR] abnormality from the edge of the surgical cavity
                  either laterally, anteroposteriorly, or superoinferiorly) or

               -  age 18-39 with neurosurgeon-defined gross total resection (GTR) but the tumor
                  size is ≥ 4 cm (the maximum preoperative tumor diameter, based on the axial
                  and/or coronal T2 or FLAIR MR images) Cohort 3: Age ≥18 year old with
                  histologically diagnosed WHO grade II glioma with recurrence

               -  Karnofsky performance status ≥ 60%

               -  Clinically stable and off corticosteroids for at least 4 weeks prior to study
                  enrollment

               -  Adequate organ function within 14 days of study registration including:

               -  Adequate bone marrow reserve: absolute neutrophil (segmented and bands) count
                  (ANC) ≥1.0 x 109/L, platelets ≥100 x 109/L; hemoglobin ≥ 8 g/dL

               -  Hepatic: - Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) for age and SGPT
                  (ALT) ≤ 2.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) for age

               -  Renal: Normal serum creatinine or creatinine clearance ≥60 ml/min/1.73 m2

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of immune system abnormalities such as hyperimmunity (e.g., autoimmune
             diseases) that required systemic immunosuppression therapy and hypoimmunity (e.g.,
             myelodysplastic disorders, marrow failures, AIDS, ongoing pregnancy, transplant
             immunosuppression)

          -  Any isolated laboratory abnormality suggestive of a serious autoimmune disease (e.g.
             hypothyroidism)

          -  Any conditions that could potentially alter immune function (AIDS, multiple sclerosis,
             diabetes, renal failure)

          -  Receiving ongoing treatment with immunosuppressive drugs, excluding those patients
             requiring dexamethasone for treatment of tumor-related edema

          -  Currently receiving any investigational agents or registration on another therapy
             based trial

          -  Pregnant or lactating
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Frank Lieberman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 30, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 4, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 5, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Frank Lieberman</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Glioma</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>WHO Grade II</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Imiquimod</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

