<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02753049</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1K23NR015970-02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02753049</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Adherence Connection for Counseling, Education, and Support</brief_title>
  <acronym>ACCESS</acronym>
  <official_title>Adherence Connection for Counseling, Education, and Support (ACCESS): A Proof of Concept Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>New York University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Mentored Patient-Oriented Research Career Development Award - (K23) seeks to provide the
      advanced knowledge, skills, and experience for the candidate's career transition to an
      independent nurse scientist. Her long term goal is to become a leading nurse scientist in
      designing, implementing, and evaluating technology supported behavioral interventions
      targeted for improved disease self-management (i.e. medication adherence, retention in care)
      among human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)-infected, ethnic minority adolescents and young
      adults. With an extensive background in pediatric HIV nursing and completed NIH funded pre
      and post-doctoral interdisciplinary research traineeships, the candidate has begun to develop
      the knowledge-base and skills necessary for this goal.

      This award details a 3-year scope of mentored career development through which she will gain
      the foundation for future research endeavors. Specifically, the goals of this proposal are
      to: 1) conduct a novel research project under the mentorship of an interdisciplinary team of
      expert researchers; 2) acquire expertise in health informatics for implementation of
      technology supported behavioral interventions, health disparities, and advanced qualitative
      and mixed methods design and analysis through firsthand experience, didactic interactions
      with mentors, and graduate level coursework; 3) build a network of colleagues and
      collaborators within New York University and elsewhere through this research and
      participation at national and international meetings; and 4) prepare and submit a federal
      research grant (R-21) based upon the skills and findings from this award period.

      The specific research project through which she will accomplish these goals is a proof of
      concept study, Adherence Connection for Counseling, Education, and Support (ACCESS), and
      addresses the challenge of adherence to antiretroviral treatment among HIV-infected
      adolescents and young adults. A mixed method design is proposed and the specific aims are to:
      1) Characterize the feasibility and acceptability of a peer led, mHealth cognitive behavioral
      intervention delivered via remote videoconferencing using smartphones; 2) Obtain initial
      estimates of the biobehavioral impact of ACCESS on HIV virologic outcomes and self-reported
      ART adherence, beliefs and knowledge about antiretroviral treatment, adherence self-efficacy,
      and healthcare utilization (retention in HIV care). In summary, the ACCESS adherence
      intervention is consistent with the National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR) call for
      the development of novel interventions to deliver personalized care and real-time health
      information for patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 23, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Serum HIV RNA quantitative viral load</measure>
    <time_frame>Serum HIV RNA quantitative viral load will be measured at baseline and at 8 weeks, 16 weeks, and 24 weeks post-intervention.</time_frame>
    <description>Serum HIV RNA quantitative viral load results will be available for medical record data extraction at four time points, baseline (pre-intervention), and weeks 8, 16 &amp; 24 post-intervention. The primary outcome variable of adherence as measured with serum HIV-RNA will be dichotomized as a binary variable (&lt; 48 copies/ml; &gt; 48 copies/ml), indicating viral suppression. An interval estimate of the odds ratio will indicate the potential impact of ACCESS on viral suppression, with Chi-Square or Fisher's Exact Test for statistical significance.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Beliefs about antiretroviral treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Beliefs about antiretroviral treatment will be measured at baseline and 24 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Beliefs about ART will be assessed with the Beliefs about Medication Scale (BAMS)- a 59 item health beliefs questionnaire using a 7-point Likert scale to assess perceived threat, positive outcome expectancy, negative outcome expectancy, and intent regarding oral medication adherence [Riekert K. et al. 2002; J Clinical Psychol Med Settings]. Changes in scores of beliefs about medications will be compared pre and post the ACCESS intervention using Chi-Square or Fisher's Exact Test for discrete variables, and paired t-tests for continuous variables.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Knowledge about antiretroviral treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Knowledge about antiretroviral therapy will be measured at baseline and 24 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Knowledge about antiretroviral treatment will be measured with the HIV Treatment Knowledge Scale. This 21 item instrument uses true and false questions to assess knowledge of adherence, side effects and antiretroviral resistance [Balfour L. et al. 2007; AIDS Care]. Changes in scores of knowledge about ART will be compared pre and post the ACCESS intervention using Chi-Square or Fisher's Exact Test for discrete variables, and paired t-tests for continuous variables.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Adherence Self-Efficacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Adherence self-efficacy will be measured at baseline and 24 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Adherence self-efficacy will be measured with the Adherence Self-Efficacy Scale - a 12 item survey measure that uses a 10 point scale (0=cannot do it all;10=completely certain can do it) to assess confidence in ability to carry out important treatment related behaviors [Johnson M. et al. 2007; J Behav Med].
Changes in scores of self-efficacy will be compared pre and post the ACCESS intervention using Chi-Square or Fisher's Exact Test for discrete variables, and paired t-tests for continuous variables.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in 3-day adherence estimate</measure>
    <time_frame>3-day adherence estimates will be measured at baseline, and 8 weeks, 16 weeks, and 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>An average missed dose calculation will be computed and operationalized as: # of doses missed per medication multiplied by dosing schedule during the past 3 days/ divided by total number of prescribed doses over past 3 days. This percentage will be subtracted from 100% to obtain the 3-day adherence estimate [Garvie P. et al. 2010; J Adol Health]</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in health care utilization (retention in care)</measure>
    <time_frame>Retention in care will be measured at baseline and 24 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>For the purposes of this proof of concept study, retention in HIV care will be calculated as a proportion of kept to scheduled visits (range 0-100%). Changes in scores of healthcare utilization (retention) will be compared pre and post the ACCESS intervention using Chi-Square or Fisher's Exact Test for discrete variables, and paired t-tests for continuous variables.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV-infection/AIDS</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Peer led mHealth adherence intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Eligible participants enrolled will receive five, weekly-60 minute, 'ACCESS' sessions, delivered by a peer adherence coach via remote videoconferencing, using smartphones. Cognitive behavioral strategies will be employed to target beliefs about antiretroviral treatment (ART), knowledge of ART, and adherence self-efficacy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Peer led mHelath behavioral intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>A trained peer adherence coach will schedule five, weekly-60 minute, 'ACCESS' sessions, delivered to participants via remote videoconferencing, using smartphones. Cognitive behavioral strategies will be employed to target beliefs about antiretroviral treatment (ART), knowledge of ART, and adherence self-efficacy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Peer led mHealth adherence intervention</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ACCESS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        1. HIV seropositive status (perinatally and behaviorally infected youth)

          2. Ages 16-29 years

          3. English speaking

          4. Current ART with a prescribed regimen

          5. Evidence of virologic failure or (detectable quantitative HIV serum viral load&gt;200
             copies/ml)

          6. No neuro-cognitive deficits which would impede participation in videoconferencing
             sessions or completion of study measures. [Screening with the Folstein Mini-Mental
             State Exam (MMSE) will be performed to assess for the presence of neurocognitive
             deficits. Participants with a score of 24 or greater will be eligible for study
             participation.]
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>29 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ann-Margaret Navarra, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>212-998-9009</phone>
    <email>amd363@nyu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gail Melkus, EdD</last_name>
    <phone>212-998-5356</phone>
    <email>gdm3@nyu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bellevue Hospital Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aditya Kaul, MD</last_name>
      <email>aditya.kaul@nyumc.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 8, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 26, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 27, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 10, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 10, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 12, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>New York University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ann-Margaret Dunn Navarra</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>AIDS</keyword>
  <keyword>Adolescent</keyword>
  <keyword>Adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>Retention</keyword>
  <keyword>mHealth</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

