<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02755610</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CLIP-SP</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02755610</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Check List to Improve Patient Self-care and Product Defect Report in Continuous Ambulatory Peritoneal Dialysis</brief_title>
  <acronym>CLIP-SP</acronym>
  <official_title>Check List to Improve Patient Self-care and Product Defect Report in Continuous Ambulatory Peritoneal Dialysis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chulalongkorn University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Research Council of Thailand</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chulalongkorn University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Peritoneal Dialysis (PD) has been the main method of treatment for Thai End-Stage Renal
      Disease (ESRD) patients under the &quot;PD First&quot; policy of the Universal Coverage (UC) scheme.
      The increased demand has resulted in not only supply chain logistical problems, but also
      product quality concerns. Peritonitis, the main complication and main cause of failure in
      Continuous Ambulatory Peritoneal Dialysis (CAPD) patients, could be caused by product defect.
      This cluster randomized trial will be conducted in participating Peritoneal Dialysis Outcomes
      and Practice Patterns Study (PDOPPS) centers in Thailand to assess if a check list
      intervention could reduce peritonitis rate and increase the number of product defect report.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Peritoneal Dialysis (PD) has been the main method of treatment for Thai End-Stage Renal
      Disease (ESRD) patients under the &quot;PD First&quot; policy of the Universal Coverage (UC) scheme.
      The increased demand has resulted in not only supply chain logistical problems, but also
      product quality concerns. Peritonitis, the main complication and main cause of failure in
      CAPD patients, could be caused by product defect.

      PD Product Check List was developed based on the 28 routine steps of standard orientation
      manual for new Thai PD patients. Of these, step 2 (weighting the PD solution bag), step 3
      (checking expiration date, volume, glucose concentration, clarity, and color, step 27
      (weighting the PD solution bag), and step 28 (recording time, volume, and any abnormality
      encountered) are relevant to product defect report.

      This cluster randomized trial will be conducted in 22 Thai participating PDOPPS centers
      (20-25 prevalent and 10-15 incidence PD cases per center) to answer the primary research
      question: is the check list intervention effective in reducing peritonitis rate? The
      secondary research questions will also be considered: does the check list help increase the
      number of product defect report?

      Peritonitis incidence rate is the primary outcome, defined based on International Society for
      Peritoneal Dialysis (ISPD) 2010 recommendation. Product defect incidence is the secondary
      outcome, measured by number of incidence of product defect reported by the patients. Given no
      standard definition, a PD solution product will be considered defective if it is expired on
      the day of use, incorrect glucose concentration, abnormal clarity or color, physical
      abnormality of the box and/or the bag, or loosen connector.

      Because of the nature of the intervention, blinding is not possible. The randomization list
      will be generated separately for each participating PD center by using the random permuted
      block method with block size of two. Patients will be randomly allocated to either the study
      or control groups in a 1:1 ratio. While all subjects will receive standard PD care, the study
      subjects will also receive the check list plus a 30-minute orientation of how to use the
      check list.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Peritonitis Incidence Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Product Defect Incidence</measure>
    <time_frame>through study completion, an average of 1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">880</enrollment>
  <condition>End-Stage Kidney Disease</condition>
  <condition>Peritonitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PD Product Check List</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>PD Product Check List was developed based on the 28 routine steps of standard orientation manual for new Thai PD patients. Of these, step 2 (weighting the PD solution bag), step 3 (checking expiration date, volume, glucose concentration, clarity, and color, step 27 (weighting the PD solution bag), and step 28 (recording time, volume, and any abnormality encountered) are relevant to product defect report.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PD Product Check List</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>PD Product Check List</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ESRD patients who start peritoneal dialysis not longer than one month and participate
             in PDOPPS study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  ESRD patients who receive only hemodialysis

          -  ESRD patients who receive emergency peritoneal dialysis

          -  Illiterate ESRD patients or their caregivers
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Krit Pongpirul, MD,MPH,PhD.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Chulalongkorn University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Krit Pongpirul, MD,MPH,PhD.</last_name>
    <phone>+66866055088</phone>
    <email>doctorkrit@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Talerngsak Kanjanabuch, MD.</last_name>
    <phone>+66891144966</phone>
    <email>golfnephro@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Faculty of Medicine, Chulalongkorn University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangkok</city>
        <zip>10330</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Krit Pongpirul, MD,MPH,PhD.</last_name>
      <phone>+66866055088</phone>
      <email>doctorkrit@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Talerngsak Kanjanabuch, MD.</last_name>
      <phone>+66891144966</phone>
      <email>golfnephro@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.dopps.org/PDOPPS/AboutthePDOPPS.aspx</url>
    <description>The Peritoneal Dialysis Outcomes and Practice Patterns Study</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dhanakijcharoen P, Sirivongs D, Aruyapitipan S, Chuengsaman P, Lumpaopong A. The &quot;PD First&quot; policy in Thailand: three-years experiences (2008-2011). J Med Assoc Thai. 2011 Sep;94 Suppl 4:S153-61.</citation>
    <PMID>22043584</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Praditpornsilpa K, Lekhyananda S, Premasathian N, Kingwatanakul P, Lumpaopong A, Gojaseni P, Sakulsaengprapha A, Prasithsirikul W, Phakdeekitcharoen B, Lelamali K, Teepprasan T, Aumanaphong C, Leerawat B, Pongpiyadej J, Srangsomvong S, Kanjanabuch T, Eiam-Ong S, Vareesaengthip K, Lumlertkul D. Prevalence trend of renal replacement therapy in Thailand: impact of health economics policy. J Med Assoc Thai. 2011 Sep;94 Suppl 4:S1-6.</citation>
    <PMID>22043559</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liu FX, Gao X, Inglese G, Chuengsaman P, Pecoits-Filho R, Yu A. A Global Overview of the Impact of Peritoneal Dialysis First or Favored Policies: An Opinion. Perit Dial Int. 2015 Jul-Aug;35(4):406-20. doi: 10.3747/pdi.2013.00204. Epub 2014 Jul 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25082840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wong HS, Ong LM, Lim TO, Hooi LS, Morad Z, Ghazalli R, Shaariah W, Lim YN, Ahmad G, Goh BL, Liaw L, Pee S, Lee ML. A randomized, multicenter, open-label trial to determine peritonitis rate, product defect, and technique survival between ANDY-Disc and UltraBag in patients on CAPD. Am J Kidney Dis. 2006 Sep;48(3):464-72.</citation>
    <PMID>16931220</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kanjanabuch T, Chancharoenthana W, Katavetin P, Sritippayawan S, Praditpornsilpa K, Ariyapitipan S, Eiam-Ong S, Dhanakijcharoen P, Lumlertgul D. The incidence of peritoneal dialysis-related infection in Thailand: a nationwide survey. J Med Assoc Thai. 2011 Sep;94 Suppl 4:S7-12.</citation>
    <PMID>22043560</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amornnimit W, Pongpirul K, Sampatanukul P, Tungsanga K, Tosukhowong P, Kanjanabuch T. Black-stained peritoneal dialysis tubing: a national survey. Perit Dial Int. 2013 Nov-Dec;33(6):704-7. doi: 10.3747/pdi.2012.00167.</citation>
    <PMID>24335129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pongpirul K, Pongpirul WA, Kanjanabuch T. Potential causes of black-stained peritoneal dialysis tubing: an analysis from nurse practitioner's prospect. BMC Res Notes. 2014 Jul 6;7:434. doi: 10.1186/1756-0500-7-434.</citation>
    <PMID>24997794</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Treamtrakanpon W, Katavetin P, Yimsangyad K, Keawsinark P, Sanganunttakan S, Pandon S, Buddeewong D, Prakot A, Khumsupo C, Thamsutee N, Yaibuaiam R, Khumwong S, Towannang P, Theerasin Y, Mahatnan N, Eiam-Ong S, Kanjanabuch T. From the &quot;PD First&quot; policy to the innovation in PD care. J Med Assoc Thai. 2011 Sep;94 Suppl 4:S13-8.</citation>
    <PMID>22043561</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bernardini J, Price V, Figueiredo A; International Society for Peritoneal Dialysis (ISPD) Nursing Liaison Committee. Peritoneal dialysis patient training, 2006. Perit Dial Int. 2006 Nov-Dec;26(6):625-32. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17047225</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perl J, Davies SJ, Lambie M, Pisoni RL, McCullough K, Johnson DW, Sloand JA, Prichard S, Kawanishi H, Tentori F, Robinson BM. The Peritoneal Dialysis Outcomes and Practice Patterns Study (PDOPPS): Unifying Efforts to Inform Practice and Improve Global Outcomes in Peritoneal Dialysis. Perit Dial Int. 2016 May-Jun;36(3):297-307. doi: 10.3747/pdi.2014.00288. Epub 2015 Nov 2.</citation>
    <PMID>26526049</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Li PK, Szeto CC, Piraino B, Bernardini J, Figueiredo AE, Gupta A, Johnson DW, Kuijper EJ, Lye WC, Salzer W, Schaefer F, Struijk DG; International Society for Peritoneal Dialysis. Peritoneal dialysis-related infections recommendations: 2010 update. Perit Dial Int. 2010 Jul-Aug;30(4):393-423. doi: 10.3747/pdi.2010.00049. Erratum in: Perit Dial Int. 2011 Sep-Oct;31(5):512.</citation>
    <PMID>20628102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vonesh EF. Modelling peritonitis rates and associated risk factors for individuals on continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis. Stat Med. 1990 Mar;9(3):263-71.</citation>
    <PMID>2188325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 9, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 26, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 29, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 26, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 26, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 29, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Peritoneal Dialysis</keyword>
  <keyword>Checklist</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Peritonitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

