<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02755740</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Girl Guide</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02755740</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Promoting Smoking Cessation for Female Smokers in Hong Kong Through Training Female Youth SCRA</brief_title>
  <official_title>Promoting Smoking Cessation for Female Smokers in Hong Kong Through Training Female Youth Smoking Cessation and Reduction Ambassadors (SCRA)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>The University of Hong Kong</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>The University of Hong Kong</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project aims to promote quitting, and reduction for those who do not want to quit, among
      female smokers through training female youth as smoking cessation and reduction ambassadors
      (SCRA). The objectives are to:

        1. Promote age and gender-specific smoking cessation and reduction to the female population

        2. Deliver a smoking cessation and reduction ambassador training workshop to equip and
           empower female youth with the knowledge on the adverse effects of smoking on female
           smokers and the skills in smoking cessation and reduction and in raising public
           awareness of the harmful effects of smoking on female smokers.

        3. Have the trained female youth to deliver a brief advice (AWARD) to female smokers to
           help them to quit or reduce smoking and refer them to the female-specific smoking
           cessation hotline or the Department of Health Quitline for further assistance if needed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Phase I: Increase public awareness of the beneficial effects of smoking cessation on female
      smokers Five thousand leaflets on woman smoking cessation will be distributed to the Girl
      Guide, the University of Hong Kong and 40 secondary schools. For those who are not ready to
      join the training, they will be encouraged to help to increase the awareness of the
      importance of promoting smoking cessation by disseminating the leaflets to others, especially
      female smokers in the population.

      Phase II: Deliver a smoking cessation training curriculum for the female youth recruited
      through the Hong Kong Girl Guides Association, the University of Hong Kong and 40 secondary
      schools.

      The investigators aim to train 120-150 female youth (with the priority given to the Hong Kong
      Girl Guides Association) to be SCRA with better understanding on the needs and feelings of
      female smokers.The investigators will deliver a half-day SCRA training workshop to the female
      youth. In addition to the leaflets above, the investigators shall publicize the training
      workshop and recruit participants via bulk emails, newsletters and the homepage of the Hong
      Kong Girl Guides Association, the University of Hong Kong and 40 secondary schools. The
      investigators will draw on our experience in conducting smoking cessation training programmes
      for our existing projects such as Youth Quitline and Quit to Win Contests. In addition, the
      investigators shall train and empower participants how to deliver a brief smoking cessation
      advice to female smokers. For those who do not want to quit, they will be advised to reduce
      smoking as the first step towards quitting. Throughout the training, participants will be
      taught to deliver the &quot;AWARD&quot; approach: 1) Ask about smoking, 2) Warn the smokers that at
      least half will be killed by smoking, and the female specific harms due to smoking, 3) Advise
      to quit (or reduce) as soon as possible, 4) Refer to a cessation clinic or hotline, and 5) Do
      it again until they quit.7 At the end of the training workshop, participants should be
      capable of delivering brief smoking cessation and reduction advice to female smokers, and a
      referral system will be set up so that women who accept more intensive counselling can be
      referred to our and other more specialised smoking cessation services. Upon completion of the
      training, a certificate of attendance will be awarded to the participants.

      The outcomes of the training will be evaluated before and immediately afterwards, and 3- and
      6-month post training. A smoking-, tobacco control-, and smoking cessation and
      reduction-related knowledge, attitudes and practice (KAP) survey, 15 using a modified version
      of previous questionnaires which have been used to assess other smoking cessation training
      workshop,16 will be conducted.

      Additionally, there is increasing evidence that the Health Action Process Approach (HAPA) is
      helpful in explaining the psychological mechanisms in bridging the gap between intention and
      actual change in health behaviour.17 According to HAPA model, an individual's intention
      either to engage in a preventive measure or to modify risky behaviour in favour of a healthy
      practice, action plans and action control help the individual to structure a strategy for
      maintaining healthy practices and defeating other conflicting ideas.18 Adopting the HAPA
      model,17 intention, self-efficacy, and planning to provide smoking cessation and reduction
      advice will also be assessed.

      Phase III: Deliver a age and gender-specific smoking cessation advice

      The trained female SCRA will be encouraged to deliver &quot;AWARD&quot; to at least 2 female smokers to
      advise them to reduce and quit smoking. Self-help smoking cessation booklet designed by Hong
      Kong Council on Smoking and Health, a partner of our smoking cessation research team, will be
      provided. The trained youth ambassadors can identify and reach the target female smokers in
      the following ways:

        1. from their family members, relatives, friends, peers, schoolmates, or colleagues in
           workplaces;

        2. If the trained youth ambassadors cannot identify and reach target female smokers from
           (1), the investigators can refer female smokers to them through our other smoking
           cessation projects, such as Youth Quitline or Quit to Win project with the consensus
           from the female smokers
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The self-reported quit rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>not smoke for at least 7 days</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>biochemical-validated quit rate</measure>
    <time_frame>6-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>measurement of exhaled (CO) and salivary cotinine level</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>smoking reduction rate</measure>
    <time_frame>1-, 3-, and 6-month follow-up</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>smoking quit attempt</measure>
    <time_frame>1-, 3-, and 6-month follow-up</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>KAP change of SCRA from baseline to 3- and 6-month follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>3- and 6-month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Use questionnaires to measure the change of smoking cessation and reduction-related knowledge, attitudes and practice of Smoking Cessation Ambassadors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking Cessation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>receiving age and gender-specific SC advice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>After delivering the &quot;AWARD&quot; advice, the trained SCRA will seek consent from and refer adult female smokers (aged over 25 years) to our intensive smoking cessation telephone or face-to-face counselling interventions, which has already counselled 509 female smokers with a quit rate of 29.7% at 6-month and 26.7% at 3-year follow up. Female youth smokers will give consent and be referred to our Youth Quitline (5111 4333), a smoking cessation telephone counselling for young people aged 25 or below which has counselled 1257 smokers with a quit rate of 21.9% at 6 months. If necessary, the female smokers can be referred to other smoking cessation services (e.g., the integrated smoking cessation hotline by the Department of Health (1833-183).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>receiving age and gender-specific SC advice</intervention_name>
    <description>After delivering the &quot;AWARD&quot; advice, the trained SCRA will seek consent from and refer adult female smokers (aged over 25 years) to our intensive smoking cessation telephone or face-to-face counselling interventions, which has already counselled 509 female smokers with a quit rate of 29.7% at 6-month and 26.7% at 3-year follow up. Female youth smokers will give consent and be referred to our Youth Quitline (5111 4333), a smoking cessation telephone counselling for young people aged 25 or below which has counselled 1257 smokers with a quit rate of 21.9% at 6 months. If necessary, the female smokers can be referred to other smoking cessation services (e.g., the integrated smoking cessation hotline by the Department of Health (1833-183).</description>
    <arm_group_label>receiving age and gender-specific SC advice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  be able to communicate with Cantonese

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  taking Psychiatric drugs
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>William LI, Phd</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>School of Nursing, the University of Hong Kong</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The University of Hong Kong</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hong Kong</city>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 17, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 26, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 29, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 26, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>The University of Hong Kong</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. LI William Ho Cheung</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>female</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

