<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02758639</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201502573</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02758639</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Wonders &amp; Worries: A Clinical Trial of a Psychosocial Intervention for Children Who Have a Parent With Cancer</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas at Austin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Wonders &amp; Worries</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas at Austin</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Parental cancer can cause substantial behavioral and emotional distress in both parent and
      child. Parents struggle with talking with their child about their cancer and supporting the
      child during treatment. Over 73% of patients with children desire information and services to
      support their children yet only 9% of these families report receiving this support. The
      purpose of this study is to evaluate the Wonders &amp; Worries psychosocial intervention designed
      for children ages 5-14 who have a parent diagnosed with early stage cancer.This study is a
      randomized controlled clinical trial (RCT) evaluating the Wonders &amp; Worries group and
      individual intervention for school age children (5 -14 years old) who have a parent with
      cancer. Families will be enrolled at the time of initial parent consultation, given informed
      consent, and then randomized either to the intervention group of 30 families or the
      wait-listed control group of 30 families. Both groups will be given a series of standardized
      validated assessment instruments including the Revised Children's Manifest Anxiety Scale
      (RCMAS), the Child Behavior Checklist (CBCL), and the Family Communication Scale FACES IV at
      baseline, post intervention, and 8 week follow up. Upon completion of the follow up measures,
      families in the wait-listed control group will be enrolled into the intervention. Parent exit
      interviews for both groups will be used to measure parent-reported child outcomes and program
      utility.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the Wonders &amp; Worries psychosocial intervention
      designed for children ages 5-14 who have a parent diagnosed with early stage cancer. The
      Wonders &amp; Worries program curriculum is a psychosocial intervention that was designed to
      address the communication and distress issues raised in prior descriptive research and to
      respond to the limitations of current research. The goals of the program are to improve
      children's behavioral-emotional adjustment to their parent's cancer, improve parenting
      behavior (parenting quality, skills and self-efficacy), and increase family communication
      about the illness. The aim of the current study is to evaluate the efficacy of the Wonders &amp;
      Worries program on child and parent outcomes within a randomized clinical trial.

      Wonders &amp; Worries is an Austin based non-profit agency. Wonders &amp; Worries works with families
      in all stages of survivorship, who are affected by any serious or chronic physical illness.

      The fully scripted intervention involves 6 group or individual sessions for the children,
      each of which is briefly summarized, in Table 1. Families will be enrolled at the time of
      initial parent consultation at Wonders &amp; Worries, given informed consent, and then randomized
      either to the intervention group of 30 families or the wait-listed control group of 30
      families. Both groups will be given a series of standardized validated assessment instruments
      including the Revised Children's Manifest Anxiety Scale (RCMAS), the Child Behavior Checklist
      (CBCL), the Family Communication Scale FACES IV, and the AMMI-EC3- About My Mommy's Illness
      at baseline, post intervention, and 8 week follow up. Upon completion of the follow up
      measures, families in the wait-listed control group will be enrolled into the intervention.
      Parent exit interviews for both groups will be used to measure parent-reported child outcomes
      and program utility.

      The intervention will be provided by Wonders &amp; Worries certified child life specialists.
      Child life specialists are professionals trained to help children and their families
      understand and manage challenging life events and stressful health care experiences. By using
      play, recreation, education, self-expression and theories of child development, these
      specialists help promote the psychological well-being and optimum development of children and
      families faced with stressful situations. At Wonders &amp; Worries all services are provided by
      master's prepared certified child life specialists.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Child's Anxiety level (RCMAS) from baseline to 6 weeks and 8 week follow up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 week, 8 week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Revised Children's Manifest Anxiety Scale - child self report</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Child's Emotional/Behavioral Status (CBCL) from baseline to 6 weeks and 8 week follow up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 week, 8 week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>Child Behavior Checklist - parent report</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Family Communication Scale FACES IV from baseline to 6 weeks and 8 week follow up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 week, 8 week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>parent &amp; child report</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in The Family Quality of Life Scale (FQOL) from baseline to 6 weeks and 8 week follow up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 week, 8 week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>parent &amp; child report</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Cancer Self-Efficacy Scale (CASE) from baseline to 6 weeks and 8 week follow up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 week, 8 week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>parent report of parenting self efficacy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Spielberger State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI) from baseline to 6 weeks and 8 week follow up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 week, 8 week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>parent self report of anxiety</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Depression scale (CES-D) from baseline to 6 weeks and 8 week follow up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 week, 8 week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>parent self report of depression</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Parenting Concerns Questionnaire (PCQ) for adults with cancer from baseline to 6 weeks and 8 week follow up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 week, 8 week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>parent self report</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in child's worries about their parent's illness from baseline to 6 weeks and 8 week follow up</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 6 week, 8 week follow up</time_frame>
    <description>child self report of worries related to parent's illness AMMI-EC3- About My Mommy's Illness</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Psychological Adjustment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>W &amp; W Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Wonders &amp; Worries Psychosocial intervention is a 6 week group or individual sessions for children who have a parent with cancer focusing on psycho-educational information about cancer, treatment and its side effects, feelings expression, positive coping strategies, and family communication about the illness.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wait list control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Wait list group will complete baseline, 6 week and 8 week follow up measures and then will be enrolled to receive W &amp; W intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Wonders &amp; Worries Psychosocial Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Session 1: Getting to Know Each Other The goal is to create a sense of safety within the group so that the children feel comfortable discussing difficult topics. Session 2: Cancer Education to provide developmentally appropriate education about the illness, treatment, and side effects. Session 3: Cancer Treatment Center Tour: This session consists of a treatment center tour and education about treatment plan involved in family's care in a safe environment. Session 4: Feelings: The focus of this session is expression and validation of all feelings the children may experience. Session 5: Stress and Coping: Goal is to emphasize the different ways individuals cope and differentiate positive vs. negative coping strategies. Session 6: Hopes for the Future/Closure: An emphasis is made on the idea that positive things may evolve from the most difficult circumstances.</description>
    <arm_group_label>W &amp; W Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Wait list control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Families with children ages 5-14 at time of study. Children have a parent with early
             stage cancer, and are English-speaking.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children are not living in the home with the ill parent at least 50% of the time.
             Non-English speaking families.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Farya Phillips, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Texas at Austin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas at Austin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78712</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phillips F, Prezio EA. Wonders &amp; Worries: evaluation of a child centered psychosocial intervention for families who have a parent/primary caregiver with cancer. Psychooncology. 2017 Jul;26(7):1006-1012. doi: 10.1002/pon.4120. Epub 2016 Mar 8.</citation>
    <PMID>26954773</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 25, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 27, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 2, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 10, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>parental cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>children psychosocial adjustment</keyword>
  <keyword>psychosocial intervention</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

