<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02758236</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>INA102</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02758236</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tuberculosis Research of INA-RESPOND On Drug Resistance</brief_title>
  <acronym>TRIPOD</acronym>
  <official_title>Tuberculosis Research of INA-RESPOND On Drug Resistance</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ina-Respond</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Health Research and Development (NIHRD), Indonesia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, United States</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ina-Respond</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a prospective observational cohort study of TB patients who are treated or
      evaluated at 10 study sites. Patients presenting with cough for 2 weeks or longer with at
      least one additional TB symptom and a chest X-ray suggestive of TB, will be invited to be
      enrolled in the study. The signed informed consent will designate their willingness to
      participate on this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a prospective observational cohort study of TB patients who are treated or
      evaluated at 10 study sites. Patients presenting with cough for 2 weeks or longer with at
      least one additional TB symptom and a chest X-ray suggestive of TB, will be invited to be
      enrolled in the study. The signed informed consent will designate their willingness to
      participate on this study. Enrolled subjects will produce the sputum for bacteriological
      examination of M. tuberculosis by AFB, culture and Xpert. The sputum will also be tested by
      Xpert for drug resistance test. If the culture is positive, conventional DST will be
      performed, and M. tuberculosis isolates will be stored for spoligotyping and for future
      research on TB. All bacteriologicaly confirmed subjects will be followed for outcome
      assessment.

      For all enrolled subjects chest X-ray results, demographic data, TB co-morbidities, symptoms,
      nutritional status, treatment regimens, compliance and outcome will be collected. In
      addition, sputum, blood and urine will also be collected for storage.

      To estimate the proportion of MDR-TB amongst new and previously treated TB cases.

        1. To evaluate accuracy of clinical diagnosis by comparing clinically defined TB to
           laboratory confirmed TB.

        2. To compare AFB and Xpert MTB/RIF as TB diagnostic tests against culture result.

        3. To estimate the sensitivity and specificity of Xpert MTB/RIF in detecting Rif
           susceptibility against DST.

        4. To estimate the proportion of cured, completed, failed, died and lost to follow up as
           treatment outcomes on DS-TB and DR-TB cases

        5. To evaluate the association of treatment success (cured or completed) with the following
           data:

             1. Demographics (age, sex)

             2. TB contact history

             3. Smoking habit

             4. Treatment seeking behavior

             5. Co-morbidities (HIV, DM)

             6. Primary and secondary drug resistance

             7. Symptoms

             8. Cavitary disease

             9. Nutritional status

            10. Treatment regimens

            11. Patient reported compliance

            12. Numbers of bacteria by AFB test

            13. TB strains (e.g Beijing)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 13, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reporting the rate of MDR-TB amongst new and retreated TB cases.</measure>
    <time_frame>4.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Proportions of MDR will be estimated, along with exact 95% confidence intervals based on a binomial distribution</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reporting the treatment outcomes (cured, failed, died, treatment completion, and lost to follow up)</measure>
    <time_frame>4.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Proportions of subjects within each category as mentioned below:
cured: number of subjects who have smear or culture negative in the last month of treatment and on at least one previous occasion.
failed: number of subjects who have sputum smear or culture is positive at month 5 or later during treatment
died: number of subjects who died from any cause during treatment
treatment completion: number of subjects who have completed treatment without evidence of failure but with no records to show that sputum smear or culture negative in the last month of treatment and on at least one previous occasion were negative, either because tests were not done or results are unavailable
lost to follow up: number of subjects who have did not start treatment or treatment was interrupted for two consecutive months or more.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reporting the protective factors for treatment success.</measure>
    <time_frame>4.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Reporting the protective factors for treatment success (cured or completed treatment vs failed or died or loss to follow up) with logistic regression models will be estimated to describe associations of treatment success with these protective factors.
Protective factors below will be collected by interview with the subject and this information will be captured in the medical record:
a. Record the subject's data demographics (age, sex), TB contact history, smoking habit, treatment seeking behavior, co-morbidities (HIV, DM), primary drug resistance, symptoms, no cavity in the lung, nutritional status, treatment regimens, bacteria and TB strains (e.g., Beijing). Logistic regression models will be estimated to describe associations of treatment success with these protective factors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reporting the risk factors of treatment interruption (loss to follow up vs other treatment outcome).</measure>
    <time_frame>4.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Reporting risk factors of treatment interruption (loss to follow up vs other treatment outcome).
Reporting the risk factors of treatment interruption (loss to follow up vs other treatment outcome). Risk factors below will be collected by interview with the subject and this information will be captured in the medical record: the subject's demographics (age, sex), the number of subjects with TB contact history, smoking habit, treatment seeking behavior, co-morbidities (HIV, DM), primary drug resistance, symptoms, cavity in the lung, nutritional status, treatment regimens, compliance, numbers of bacteria and TB strains (e.g., Beijing). Logistic regression models will be estimated to evaluate associations of treatment interruption with these risk factors.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reporting how many percent clinically defined TB subjects compare to bacteriologically confirmed TB (AFB, X-pert, sputum culture).</measure>
    <time_frame>4.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Record the number of subject has clinically diagnosed TB. The physician categorized subjects as clinically TB when they have cough &gt;= 2 weeks, have at least 1 other TB symptoms (fever, unexplained weight loss, loss of appetite, hemoptysis, shortness of breath, chest pain, night sweats, fatigue) and suggestive TB on chest x-ray based on pulmonologist or internist consultant of pulmonologist opinion.
The number of subject laboratory confirmed TB with positive Mtb result on AFB, and/or X-pert, and/or sputum culture.
The number of subject laboratory confirmed TB with positive AFB, Xpert and sputum culture result with Mtb bacteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measuring the sensitivity and specificity of AFB and Xpert MTB/RIF relative to culture results.</measure>
    <time_frame>4.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measuring the sensitivity AFB or Xpert MTB/RIF relative to sputum culture result: Number of subjects who have positive AFB and/or Xpert MTB/Rif result whose culture positive divide with subjects who have positive AFB and/or Xpert MTB/Rif result whose culture positive plus subjects who have negative AFB and/or Xpert MTB/Rif result whose culture positive.
Measuring the specificity of AFB or Xpert MTB/RIF relative to sputum culture result: The number subjects with negative AFB and/or Xpert MTB/RIF that are also negative Mtb sputum culture divide with number subjects with negative AFB and/or Xpert MTB/RIF that are also negative Mtb sputum culture plus number subjects with negative AFB and/or Xpert MTB/RIF positive Mtb sputum.
Sensitivity and specificity will be estimated along with 97.5% confidence intervals. McNemar's statistic will test whether the sensitivity and specificity differ between AFB and Xpert MTB/RIF.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measuring sensitivity and specificity of Rif susceptibility results in Xpert MTB/RIF against result in DST as gold standard along with 97.5% confidence intervals.</measure>
    <time_frame>4.5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Measuring the sensitivity Rif susceptibility results in Xpert MTB/RIF relative to sputum culture result: Number of subjects who have resistant to Rif in Xpert MTB/RIF that are also show resistancy on DST divide subjects who have resistant to Rif in Xpert MTB/RIF that also show resistancy on DST plus subjects with sensitive on Rif in Xpert MTB/RIF whose DST show resistancy 100% relative to sputum culture result: The number of subjects with sensitive of Rif in Xpert MTB/RIF that are also show no resistancy on DST divide subjects who sensitive to Rif in Xpert MTB/RIF that show no resistancy on DST plus subjects with sensitive to Rif in Xpert MTB/RIF whose DST show resistancy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1357</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Tuberculosis</condition>
  <condition>MDR TB</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>No Intervention</description>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Subjects must be willing to allow storage of sputum, Mtb isolate, whole blood (PAXgene blood
      , plasma, PBMC), and urine on baseline, month 1, month 2, and end of treatment visit, saliva
      on baseline and end of treatment visit for use in future studies (for example, host response,
      spoligotyping, and genetic tests). Serum and whole blood for DNA are collected on baseline
      visit only.

      All samples will be stored at the NIHRD, Mtb isolate, plasma, saliva and urine will also be
      stored at each site
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Presumptive TB patients, &gt;=18 years old. This study will analyze 500 subjects
        bacteriologically confirmed TB (250 new cases and 250 previously treated cases). To obtain
        the numbers, we estimate to enroll 1357 subjects presumptive TB (1000 new cases and 357
        previously treated cases). These numbers are made based on our estimation that 25% of
        presumptive new TB cases and 70% of presumptive previously treated TB cases will be
        bacteriologically confirmed.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients suspected of having pulmonary TB

          -  Cough ≥ 2 weeks

          -  At least one other TB clinical symptom

               -  Fever

               -  Unexplained weight loss

               -  Loss of appetite

               -  Hemoptysis

               -  Shortness of breath

               -  Chest pain

               -  Night sweats

               -  Fatigue

          -  Suggestive TB on chest x-ray based on pulmonologist or internist consultant of
             pulmonology opinion

          -  Age ≥ 18 years' old

          -  Willing to be treated or evaluated at study site

          -  Willing to have specimens stored for use in future studies

          -  Patient denies having TB treatment for more than 7 days in the last 1 month (30 days).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Pregnancy or any serious condition includes, but not limited to, liver disease, chronic
        kidney disease, and psychiatric illness that might interfere with study compliance (based
        on the clinician judgment).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dr. dr. Erlina Burhan, SpP(K), MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Persahabatan Hospital, Jakarta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Dr. Muhammad Karyana, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>+622142879189</phone>
    <email>m.karyana@ina-respond.net</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>dr. Herman Kosasih, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+622142879189</phone>
    <phone_ext>114</phone_ext>
    <email>hkosasih@ina-respond.net</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 520: University of Udayana/Sanglah Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denpasar</city>
        <state>Bali</state>
        <zip>80114</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Prof. Dr. Ketut Tuti Merati, SpPD-KPTI</last_name>
      <phone>+62361246274</phone>
      <email>tutiparwati@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>dr. Ida Bagus Suta, SpP(K)</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 560: University of Diponegoro/ Dr. Kariadi Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Semarang</city>
        <state>Central Of Java</state>
        <zip>50244</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Prof. dr. Muhammad Hussein Gasem, PhD, SpPD-KPTI</last_name>
      <phone>+62248446757</phone>
      <email>mhgasem@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>dr. Banteng Hanang Wibisono, SpPD-K-P</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 620: Gatot Subroto Army Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jakarta</city>
        <state>DKI Jakarta</state>
        <zip>10410</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dr. dr. Soroy Lardo, Sp.PD, FINASIM</last_name>
      <phone>+628121045570</phone>
      <email>soroylardo@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>dr. Dewi Puspitorini, Sp.P</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 540: Penyakit Infeksi Sulianti Saroso Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jakarta</city>
        <state>DKI Jakarta</state>
        <zip>14340</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dr. Vivi Lisdawati, Msi,Apt</last_name>
      <phone>+62216506559</phone>
      <phone_ext>3119</phone_ext>
      <email>viandrashakti@yahoo.co.id</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>dr. Pompini Agustina, SpP</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 590: Persahabatan Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jakarta</city>
        <state>DKI Jakarta</state>
        <zip>14340</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dr. dr. Erlina Burhan, SpP(K), MSc</last_name>
      <phone>+628161628471</phone>
      <email>erlina_burhan@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dr. dr. Erlina Burhan, SpP(K), MSc</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 570: University of Airlangga/ Dr. Soetomo Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Surabaya</city>
        <state>East Of Java</state>
        <zip>60286</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Prof. Dr. Suharto SpPD-KPTI</last_name>
      <phone>+631 5035975</phone>
      <email>divtropin@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>dr. Tutik Kusmiati, SpP</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 600 : Adam Malik Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Medan</city>
        <state>North Sumatra</state>
        <zip>20136</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>dr. Bambang Prabowo, MARS</last_name>
      <phone>(+6261) 8360143</phone>
      <email>prabowob14@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>dr. Parluhutan Siagian, SpP(K)</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 510: University of Padjajaran/ Dr. Hasan Sadikin Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bandung</city>
        <state>West Java</state>
        <zip>40161</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>dr. Bachti Alisjahbana, PhD, SpPD-KPTI</last_name>
      <phone>+62222030776</phone>
      <email>b.alisjahbana@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dr. Arto Yuwono Soeroto, Sp.PD-KP</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 550: University of Hassanudin/ Dr. Wahidin Sudirohusodo Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Makassar</city>
        <zip>90245</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Prof. Dr. Mansyur Arif, PhD, SpPK (K)</last_name>
      <phone>+6411-582678</phone>
      <email>mansyur_arief@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dr. dr. Irawaty Djaharuddin, SpP(K)</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Site 580: University of Gadjah Mada/ Dr. Sardjito Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Yogyakarta</city>
        <zip>55284</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>dr. Abu Tholib Aman, MSc, PhD, SpMK(K)</last_name>
      <phone>+6274560300</phone>
      <email>abutholibaman@ugm.ac.id</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>dr. Bambang Sigit Riyanto, SpPD,K-P, FINASIM</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Indonesia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 4, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 27, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 2, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tuberculosis, Pulmonary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>No plan to share data</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

