<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02752282</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>49648</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02752282</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Anticipatory Counseling on LNG-IUS Continuation, Utilization and Satisfaction: A Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>ACCCUSS</acronym>
  <official_title>Anticipatory Counseling on LNG-IUS Continuation, Utilization and Satisfaction: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bayer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>John H. Stroger Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Washington</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a counseling intervention for new LNG-IUS users. The study explores the use of
      video technology to deliver anticipatory counseling on LNG-IUS side-effects, adjustment
      periods and bleeding changes to women newly using the LNG-IUS for contraceptive purposes. The
      primary aim is to understand if anticipatory counseling delivered via video can increase
      LNG-IUS satisfaction and continuation of the device in the first 6 months of use.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Enhanced anticipatory counseling detailing side effects when initiating progestin-only
      injectable contraception improved its continued use among women.While continuation rates at
      one year among levonorgestrel intrauterine system (LNG-IUS) users are considerably higher
      than those for progestin-only injectable users in the United States (80% versus 56%),
      enhanced anticipatory counseling could have an impact on the 20% of LNG IUS users who choose
      to discontinue the method within one year of use. For this reason, the investigators propose
      a study that would develop and pilot-test an anticipatory counseling intervention detailing
      unscheduled bleeding and other side effects such as pelvic pain or cramping among new LNG IUS
      users and compare this with a &quot;control,&quot; using video technology. The investigators have
      chosen video technology for the counseling intervention to ensure that all participants
      receive the exact same information about LNG side effects, which would be not possible using
      a face-to-face clinician-participant counseling model.

      The investigators propose two phases for this study. In Phase 1, a systematic literature
      search evaluating effective components in videos used for contraceptive counseling and the
      development of two separate video scripts will lead to: (1) an intervention, detailing
      expected side effects and safety of the LNG IUS, and (2) a similar-looking &quot;control,&quot;
      detailing only recommended screening guidelines for women, as well as information about LNG
      IUS safety. This phase of the study uses focus groups prior to the development of the video
      interventions, initially with family planning experts for content accuracy and cultural
      sensitivity, and secondarily with new LNG IUS users for acceptability. Findings from this
      phase will be used to fine-tune the scripts prior to development of the videos.

      In Phase 2 of the study, the investigators will pilot a trial in the clinical setting to
      evaluate the anticipatory counseling video intervention and its impact on LNG-IUS knowledge,
      continuation, health care utilization, and satisfaction. After receiving comprehensive
      contraceptive counseling from their clinicians, women who choose to have the LNG IUS inserted
      will be given a brochure that asks them to participate in an online study. After signing-on
      to an innovative website, participants will be randomized to either an intervention or
      control video and complete short questionnaires related to demographics, baseline
      menstruation, satisfaction, and LNG IUS knowledge before and after viewing their assigned
      video. Women will be followed for six months. They will be asked to complete a short online
      survey at three and six months regarding LNG IUS continuation, health care utilization, and
      satisfaction. Findings from this study will serve to design a future, appropriately powered
      randomized controlled trial assessing LNG IUS continuation, utilization, and satisfaction
      rates at 12 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in LNG-IUS knowledge, satisfaction and continuation from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Using standardize questionnaires we will assess any significant differences in LNG-IUS knowledge, satisfaction or continuation after 6 months between control arm and intervention arm subjects.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent of subjects in Phase II who complete all 3 surveys on-time over 6 months compared by recruitment method and site</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assess what percent of study participants were successfully recruited via a brochure or email contact at Seattle and Chicago.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects reporting LNG-IUS discontinuation during the study time frame (6 months) by reason for LNG-IUS removal</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Track number of subjects who have their LNG-IUS removed during the study period by reason, including: bleeding, cramping, acne, weight gain, depression or other reasons.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>LNG-IUS user self-reported satisfaction with video counseling</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>A survey using modified likert scales and free text boxes, will ask participants how helpful the video was, how many times they watched the video, and any feedback they had about video elements to improve.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>LNG-IUS user self-reported LNG-IUS healthcare utilization during study period</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 months, 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Compare LNG-IUS user self-reported healthcare utilization at baseline (before the LNg-IUS was placed) with 3 and 6 months after LNG-IUS use. This include number of phone calls and office visits and the user reported helpfulness of these interactions with their healthcare providers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Vaginal Bleeding</condition>
  <condition>Uterine Cramping</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Video</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this study arm will be assigned to watch a short educational video about new pap screening guidelines for women. Intervention: Cancer Screening Guidelines.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Video</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this group will be assigned to watch a short educational video providing anticipatory counseling on their LNG-IUS' side effects and expected changes in bleeding. Intervention: Anticipatory Counseling</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Anticipatory Counseling</intervention_name>
    <description>Anticipatory Counseling provides information on expected side-effects that may change or go away over time, or stay for the duration of the treatment. Anticipatory counseling can also help patients understand when their side-effects are normal and when to seek medical attention.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention Video</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cancer Screening Guidelines</intervention_name>
    <description>Anticipatory Counseling on United States Preventative Services Task Force (USPSTF) updated pap screening guidelines</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Video</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Women aged 18 and over who are deemed appropriate candidates be their healthcare
             providers and choose to use LNG-IUS, either Mirena or Skyla.

          2. Within five days of FIRST using either Mirena or Skyla

          3. Willing to answer online questions before and after watching the assigned video
             (intervention or control)

          4. Willing to complete short online questionnaire at three and six months

          5. Has working email and/or phone number

          6. Able to understand verbal and written English

          7. Appropriate LNG-IUS candidates whoa re being treated for other pre-existing medical
             disorders while using the LNG IUS may continue to take their medications as directed
             by their healthcare provider.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Women aged less than 18 years old

          2. Initiated LNG-IUS method more than five days from enrollment date.

          3. Within six weeks postpartum

          4. Breastfeeding

          5. Using LNG-IUS for treatment other than contraception

          6. Do not have access to the Web

          7. Have neither working email or phone number

          8. Does not understand written or verbal English

          9. Inappropriate candidates for LNG IUS as deemed by healthcare provider
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Emily Godfrey, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stroger Hospital of Cook County</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington Medical Centers</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 15, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 21, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 26, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Washington</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Emily Godfrey</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor, Family Medicine</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Family Planning</keyword>
  <keyword>LNG-IUS</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Education</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Hemorrhage</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

