<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02757105</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RHB-102-02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02757105</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled Phase 2 Trial of BEKINDA (Ondansetron 12 mg Bimodal Release Tablets) for Diarrhea Predominant Irritable Bowel Syndrome (IBS-D)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Phase 2 Trial of BEKINDA (Ondansetron 12 mg Bimodal Release Tablets) for Diarrhea Predominant Irritable Bowel Syndrome (IBS-D)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>RedHill Biopharma Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>RedHill Biopharma Limited</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, 2-arm parallel group study. After
      qualifying for the study and signing informed consent, patients will undergo a two-week
      observation period during which stool consistency and frequency data and symptom data will be
      collected. Patients will then be randomized 60:40 to RHB-102 12 mg (BEKINDA) or placebo.
      Patients will continue on treatment for 8 weeks. Each medication will be given once daily.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All patients will undergo baseline evaluation including full history and physical, with
      particular attention to gastrointestinal symptomatology and findings, a standard set of
      safety laboratory examinations (CBC and platelet count, biochemical profile, urinalysis,
      serum TSH and free T4, INR), and 12-lead ECG. In addition, the following studies will be
      performed to exclude other causes of gastrointestinal symptoms:

        -  Serum testing for C-reactive protein and gluten sensitivity

        -  Colonoscopy if required per protocol

        -  Patients with a history of positive tests for ova, parasites or Clostridium difficile
           must undergo repeat testing, which must be negative, during the screening period.
           Starting during the baseline observation phase, all patients will keep diaries of
           symptomatology and stool frequency and consistency. Stool consistency will be assessed
           according to the Bristol Stool Form scale (Lewis and Heaton, 1997).

      Patients will keep diaries of stool frequency and consistency, symptoms, study medication
      compliance, and use of all medications, including rescue medications, throughout the study.

      Serum electrolyte assays (bicarbonate, calcium, chloride, magnesium, potassium, and sodium)
      will be performed at week 3 on study. Safety laboratory examinations will be performed during
      and after the treatment period in accordance with the study procedures schedule below.

      Patients will be questioned periodically regarding concomitant medication use and the
      occurrence of adverse events.

      Patients must complete at least 12 days of all baseline diary entries within the 14 day
      screening period to be eligible to participate in the study. Patients completing fewer than
      12 days of diary entries may, at the investigator's discretion, repeat the screening period
      diary. As long as the patent can complete and enter the study within 6 weeks, baseline
      laboratory studies need not be repeated. If repeating the 2 weeks' baseline diary will result
      in a period longer than 6 weeks from consent to start of treatment, the medical monitor must
      be consulted prior to randomization.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 19, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 14, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 16, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients in each treatment group with stool consistency response in the absence of increase in pain (&lt;10% increase in weekly average of worst daily pain).</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A weekly stool consistency responder is defined as a patient who experiences during a week ≥50% reduction in the number of days per week with at least one stool that has a consistency of Type 6 or 7 compared with baseline, and abdominal pain is unchanged or improved in comparison with baseline.
A patient will be characterized as an overall stool consistency responder if the patient was a weekly responder for ≥50% of the weeks of treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients in each treatment group who are pain responders, per FDA guidance definition.</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Abdominal pain intensity weekly responder: patient who experiences a decrease in the weekly average of worst abdominal pain in the past 24 hours score ≥30% compared with baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients in each treatment group who are overall responders, per FDA guidance definition.</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A patient is characterized as an overall weekly responder if the patient meets both the stool consistency and pain response definitions for a given week.
A patient is characterized as an overall study responder if the patient meets the criteria for overall weekly response for at least half the planned study weeks.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Exploratory: Decrease in Urgency</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Urgency is the feeling of a need to defecate and inability to control or incomplete control over defecation. Urgency over the course of the day, is measured on an 11-point Likert scale ranging from 0 (no urgency) to 10 (as bad as can be imagined).</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Irritable Bowel Syndrome With Diarrhea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BEKINDA 12 mg (Ondansetron Bimodal Release Tablets), once daily for 8 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Placebo, once daily for 8 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>BEKINDA</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RHB-102 12 mg</other_name>
    <other_name>Ondansetron Bimodal Release Tablet 12 mg</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male and female patients age≥18 years (with a minimum of 35% males in the study)

          2. Patient meets FDA guidance and Rome III criteria for IBS-D:

             a. Recurrent abdominal pain or discomfort over ≥6 months, with frequency ≥3 days/month
             in the last 3 months associated with ≥2 of the following: i. Improvement with
             defecation ii. Onset associated with a change in frequency of stool iii. Onset
             associated with a change in the form of stool b. Loose or watery stools (Bristol stool
             form scale 6 or 7) ≥2 days per week

          3. Average worst daily pain intensity ≥3.0 for each of the two baseline weeks

          4. Major laboratory parameters within the following limits (no worse than grade 1
             abnormalities per NCI-CTCAE v4):

             a. Adequate hematologic function, as demonstrated by i. Hemoglobin ≥10 g/dL ii. ANC
             1.5-10 x 10^9/L iii. Platelets ≥100 x 10^9/L b. Adequate liver and renal function as
             demonstrated by i. AST and ALT each ≤ 3.0 x ULN ii. Total bilirubin ≤1.5 x ULN iii.
             Creatinine ≤1.5 X ULN c. Euthyroid based on TSH and free T4 levels

          5. Patients on thyroid hormone replacement must be on a stable dose for at least one
             month prior to study entry.

          6. C-reactive protein ≤2 x upper limit of normal for lab

          7. Patients of childbearing potential and male patients with partners of childbearing
             potential must utilize effective contraceptive measures Women of childbearing
             potential are women who have menstruated in the past 12 months, with the exception of
             women who have undergone surgical sterilization

          8. All patients must sign informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Evidence of other cause for bowel disease:

               1. Relevant abnormalities seen on colonoscopy if previously performed or if required
                  per this protocol. These include but are not limited to Crohn's disease,
                  ulcerative colitis, diverticulitis, ischemic colitis, microscopic colitis.

               2. History of and/or positive serologic test for celiac disease

               3. Known or suspected lactose intolerance.

          2. History of abdominal surgery other than appendectomy or cholecystectomy at any time

          3. Any elective major surgery (of any organ) planned for the period of the study,
             including follow-up

          4. History of organic abnormalities of the GI tract including but not limited to
             intestinal obstruction, stricture, toxic megacolon, GI perforation, fecal impaction,
             gastric banding, adhesions or impaired intestinal circulation (e.g., aortoiliac
             disease)

          5. Current or previous diagnosis of neoplasia (except non-GI neoplasia in complete
             remission ≥5 years, squamous and basal cell carcinomas). With approval of the medical
             monitor patients with curatively treated neoplasm in complete remission &lt;5 years may
             be entered in the study.

          6. Patients with a history of positive tests for ova or parasites or Clostridium
             difficile must be retested during the screening period and tests for the relevant
             agents must be negative

          7. Use of any 5-HT3 antagonist within 4 weeks of the start of baseline data collection.

          8. Use of rifaximin within 4 months of the start of baseline data collection.

          9. Use of any other agent specific for IBS (such as alosetron or eluxadoline) or for
             symptomatic treatment of IBS (such as antispasmotics and antidiarrheals other than
             loperamide) within 2 weeks of the start of baseline data collection.

         10. Uses of any investigational agent for any indication within 4 weeks of the start of
             baseline data collection.

         11. Congestive heart failure, bradyarrhythmia (baseline pulse&lt;55/min), known long QT
             syndrome

         12. Patients who have QTc prolongation&gt;450 msec noted on screening ECG, or who are taking
             medication known to cause QT prolongation

             Note: For current list of medications known to cause QT prolongation see:

             https://www.crediblemeds.org/healthcare-providers/drug-list/ There are several risk
             categories. Use the list showing those drugs known to cause torsade de pointes (TdP)

         13. Hypersensitivity or other known intolerance to ondansetron or other 5-HT3 antagonists

         14. Patient has taken apomorphine within 24 hours of screening

         15. Pregnant or lactating

         16. Patients with other major illnesses, either physical or psychiatric, or social
             situations which may interfere with participation in the study or interpretation of
             results

         17. Patients with severe hepatic impairment, defined as Child-Pugh score ≥10 at baseline
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Endoscoopy Center of AR</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72212</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arkansas Gastroenterology, P.A.</name>
      <address>
        <city>North Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72117</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Prx Clinical</name>
      <address>
        <city>Garden Grove</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92840</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Providence Clinical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>North Hollywood</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91606</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shahram Jacobs MD, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sherman Oaks</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>91403</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Advanced Rx Clinical Research Group, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Westminster</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92683</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bristol Hospital Dba Connecticut Gastroenterology Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bristol</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PMG Research of Winston-Salem</name>
      <address>
        <city>Winston-Salem</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Great Lakes Medical Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mentor</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44060</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinsearch</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chattanooga</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37421</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New Phase Research &amp; Development</name>
      <address>
        <city>Knoxville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37909</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Aztec Medical Research, LLC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Channelview</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77530</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gastroenterology Research of San Antonio</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 27, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 27, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 29, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 15, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 15, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 17, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diarrhea</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Irritable Bowel Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ondansetron</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

