<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02754258</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15/10E</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02754258</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Methylphenidate on Energy Intake and Energy Expenditure</brief_title>
  <acronym>MPH</acronym>
  <official_title>The Effects of Methylphenidate on the Reduction of Food Energy Intake and on the Augmentation of Energy Expenditure</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Ottawa</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Problem: Obesity is one of the leading causes of chronic disease and death. The efficacy
      of diet and exercise to sustain weight loss over the long term is weak. While pharmacotherapy
      is more effective than behavior intervention in maintaining weight loss the effects are often
      not sufficient to achieve optimal health benefits. Current drug treatments may be sub-optimal
      because they do not directly target the rewarding value of food, drive to eat, food liking,
      and impulsivity for eating energy dense snack foods, all of which influences both quantity
      and quality of food intake and impacts adherence needed to maintain weight loss.

      The Solution: The limitations in current anti-obesity agents are potentially addressed by
      Methylphenidate (MPH). We showed that MPH reduces food intake, dietary fat intake, hunger and
      food reward, as increase resting energy expenditure in obese and non-obese adults;however, no
      controlled field trials have been conducted in obese individuals without ADHD.

      Objectives/Hypotheses: Primary: To test the effects of MPH on energy intake in obese men and
      women. Secondary: to examine the effects of MPH on energy expenditure, body weight,
      impulsivity, food reward, and olfaction. The investigators predict that compared to placebo,
      MPH will show reduced appetite, along with reduced impulsivity, food reward, and smell
      function.

      Deliverable: This study may be the first to establish the short-term efficacy and safety of
      using MPH for weight loss, and if successful, data will inform a larger trial that can
      potentially identify MPH as a novel therapeutic agent for treating obesity and related
      chronic diseases in a predisposed population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Research Objectives and Hypotheses

      Primary: The primary objective of this study is to examine whether Methylphenidate (MPH) at
      dose of 0.50 mg/kg (not exceeding 100 mg/day) can lead to a sustained reduction in energy
      intake in obese adolescents and adults. Based on the investigators' pilot data in adults, it
      is predicted that daily administration of MPH for 60 consecutive days will produce reductions
      in food intake (both in lab and free-living) compared to placebo, extending our previous
      findings to a longer period of time and to obese adolescents. Prior to beginning the
      intervention, both MPH and placebo treatment groups will receive lifestyle advice (eating and
      exercise guidelines for healthy living). The primary outcome measures will rely on the
      validated measurements of energy intake (in lab lunch buffet and out of lab 3 day food menu).

      Secondary objectives/hypotheses: The effects of MPH on all components of energy expenditure
      will be investigated. Based on the investigators' pilot data, it is predicted that from
      Baseline to 60 days, MPH will increase total energy expenditure (TEE) when compared with
      placebo, mostly through greater resting energy expenditure (REE) and thermic effects of food
      (TEF). It is hypothesized that after the 60-day intervention the MPH group will experience a
      significantly attenuated reduction in REE compared to placebo. We predict that the MPH group
      will lose body weight at 2 months, whereas, it is predicted that there will be no change in
      body weight for the placebo. The investigators will also explore the effects of MPH on
      macronutrient preference and consumption, and on the rewarding value of energy dense snack
      foods. Based on previous findings, the investigators predict that MPH will reduce consumption
      of energy dense, high fat/sugar foods but have little effect on consumption of foods low in
      calories, fats or sugars. In addition, it is predicted that the reduction in intake of energy
      dense, high fat/sugar foods will be mediated by reductions in the rewarding value of food and
      impulsivity as measured by well validated computerized simulations. Also explored will be the
      effects of MPH on olfaction and it is predicted that compared to placebo, individuals taking
      MPH will have reduced smell function. It is also predicted the MPH group will show reduced
      appetite sensations, reduced rewarding value of food, reduced impulsivity for snack food, and
      reduced palatability ratings of food compared to placebo at 2 months.

      Trial Design

      The trial design will consist of a randomized, double blind, placebo-controlled 2 parallel
      arm study. The two randomly assigned treatment groups will consist of administrating a
      placebo or short-acting MPH two-times daily 1 hour before meals for a period of 2 months (60
      consecutive days). Prior to being randomized into either the placebo group or the
      experimental (MPH) group, subjects will first have had to respond to a recruitment poster,
      newspaper advertisement. Once it is determined with that initial screening that the
      participant still meets inclusion criteria, they will be invited to come to the laboratory
      for a screening visit to determine whether they meet eligibility criteria, to sign informed
      consent, and to take a test dose of MPH in order for a nurse to closely monitor any potential
      side-effects prior to starting the 2-times daily dosing of MPH or placebo.

      Trial Procedures

      The proposed study will consist of six visits to the laboratory for a total of twenty-four
      hours, as follows: there will be an initial clinical screening visit (4 hrs), three repeated
      measures test days (6hrs each; two at baseline and one at 60 days), a mid-point visit (1hr),
      and a Lunch Box visit (10 minutes to obtain out of laboratory food). School-aged participants
      will not have to miss school to participate; if necessary, testing will be able to be
      performed over the course of the weekend. After the initial laboratory visit and informed
      consent (i.e. clinical screening visit), participants will be randomized at the Baseline 1
      visit to one of two treatment groups to either receive placebo or MPH two times daily for a 2
      month intervention period that starts at the Baseline 2 visit. In order to track physical
      activity energy expenditure, participants will be instructed to wear accelerometers for 1
      week between the in lab screening visit and the Baseline 1 visit, and then again while under
      MPH or placebo for 1 week between the mid-point visit and the Final repeated measures test
      day. Upon leaving the Baseline 1 test day (i.e. no drug or placebo) participants will receive
      a 3 day supply of food from which they will exclusively eat from until they return to the lab
      4 days later for the Baseline 2 repeated measures test day (i.e. under drug or placebo).
      Similarly, 4 days prior to the Final repeated measures test day, participants will again have
      to visit the laboratory for their &quot;Lunch Box&quot; visit to obtain their three days' supply of
      food from which they will eat exclusively from. Participants will return to the laboratory to
      complete the study at the Final (day 60) repeated measures test day after 3 days of eating
      from the &quot;Lunch Boxes&quot;. For the 1 hour mid-point visit (at day 30) participants will be
      weighed and will report any perceived side-effects from the MPH or placebo. At this mid-point
      visit participants will bring in their pill container to verify compliance and to receive
      final 30 day supply of drug or placebo. At this time participants will be asked if they have
      begun any new medication or have started any over-the-counter medication as part of the
      study's safety monitoring protocol. A side-effects check list will also be provided to the
      participants upon leaving the Baseline 2 testing session; participants will be informed to
      note any perceived side-effects nightly for the first 14 days being on the study medication
      and will be instructed to notify the study coordinator as soon as specific side-effects are
      noted as being Major.

      Consent and Clinical Screening

      Initial Screening Visit (4 hours)

      Before beginning the study, a meeting between the study coordinator and the participant will
      occur in order to get consent and in order for the participant to ingest a test dose of MPH
      under the supervision of a nurse. The study coordinator will contact the participant in order
      to arrange a time for the approximately 4 hour meeting. The weight and height (thus BMI) will
      be measured upon arrival. The participant will then have to respond to questionnaires, e.g.
      the Wender-Utah Rating Scale (to assess traits compatible with ADHD), the Beck Depression
      Inventory (to assess depressive symptoms), the &quot;Three-Factor Eating Questionnaire&quot; (to assess
      eating style) and the Drug Abuse Screening Test (to ensure no underlying drug problem). If
      the participant is a female they cannot be pregnant to be included in the study; thus a
      pregnancy test will be administered and if it is determined that they are pregnant they will
      be referred to visit their family physician and excluded from the study. If eligible, the
      participant will be asked to read and sign the consent form. Eligible participants will then
      see a nurse who will administer the all of the measures outlined in the Case Report Form,
      e.g., a physical exam, medical history assessment, baseline vital signs, electrocardiogram
      (ECG), etc. The nurse will then administer a test dose of 0.5mg/kg of MPH and for a period of
      three hours after the ingestion of MPH the nurse will closely monitor any potential
      side-effects of the drug by measuring heart rate, blood pressure, and by following a detailed
      side-effects check-list. If at any point the participant rates and of the side effects as
      &quot;Prohibitive&quot;, then he/she will be excluded from the study. The participant will also be
      excluded from entering the study if they demonstrate an abnormal ECG systolic or if blood
      pressure exceeds the baseline reading by 20mmHg or if diastolic blood pressure exceeds the
      baseline reading by 10mmHg, BP &gt; 160/100, or resting pulse increased by 20 beats/minute from
      the baseline. As part of the comprehensive safety assessment to determine eligibility, the
      ECG data file that is collected will be stored via a USB external hard drive and then sent to
      CHEO cardiology to be read by a cardiologist. Once it is determined by the cardiologist that
      the ECG rhythm is normal, both the cardiologist and the QI will sign off on the Case Report
      form, indicating that the participant is eligible for enrollment. If it is determined by the
      ECG reading that the participant is not eligible, they will be called up by the study
      coordinator and told of the incidental findings and subsequently informed to visit their
      family physician to follow-up. The participant may bring the consent form home to further
      study its content before signing it. Prior to leaving the initial screening visit
      participants will be instructed on how to strap on an omni-directional accelerometer and
      instructed on how to fill out the log sheet which gathers information on when the monitors
      are worn and when they are taken off, which is needed to evaluate wear time for a seven day
      period. Participants will be instructed to return the accelerometers at their next visit,
      Baseline 1.

      Free and informed Consent

      During the initial screening visit, if a candidate meets the inclusion criteria, the
      coordinator will explain the research protocol to the subject. This will be done in order to
      explain in detail the requirements of the protocol and to answer all the questions from
      potential participants. If potential participants are still interested to participate in the
      study, the coordinator will then distribute, explain and answer questions regarding the
      consent form to the participant. The participant will then be asked to sign the informed
      consent letter.

      Active Investigational Product Description

      pms-METHYLPHENIDATE (methylphenidate hydrochloride) is a racemate consisting of a 1:1 mixture
      of d-methylphenidate (d-MPH) and l-methylphenidate (l-MPH). pms-METHYLPHENIDATE is a mild
      central nervous system stimulant with more prominent effects on mental than motor activities.
      The mode of action in man is not completely understood, but its stimulant effects are thought
      to be due to cortical stimulation and possibly to stimulation of the reticular activating
      system. There is neither specific evidence which clearly establishes the mechanism whereby
      methylphenidate produces its mental and behavioural effects in children, nor conclusive
      evidence regarding how these effects relate to the condition of the central nervous system
      (CNS). Methylphenidate hydrochloride is rapidly and extensively absorbed from the tablets
      following oral administration; however, owing to extensive first-pass metabolism,
      bioavailability is low (approx. 30%) and large individual differences exist (11-52%). Peak
      plasma concentrations of 10.8 and 7.8 ng/mL were observed, on average, 2 hours after
      administration of 0.30 mg/kg in children and adults, respectively. Methylphenidate is
      eliminated from the plasma with a mean half-life of 2.4 hours in children and 2.1 hours in
      adults. The apparent mean systemic clearance after an oral dose is 10.2 and 10.5 L/h/kg in
      children and adults, respectively for a 0.3 mg/kg dose, and 0.565 L/h/kg after an intravenous
      dose of the racemate in healthy adult volunteers. These data indicate that the
      pharmacokinetics of methylphenidate in hyperactive children is similar to that in healthy
      adult volunteers. The apparent distribution volume of methylphenidate in children was
      approximately 20 L/kg, with substantial variability (11-33 L/kg). The volume of distribution
      after an intravenous dose (Vss) is 2.23 L/kg for the racemate in healthy adult volunteers.

      Following oral administration of methylphenidate, 78-97% of the dose is excreted in the urine
      and 1-3% in the feces in the form of metabolites within 48-96 hours. The main urinary
      metabolite is ritalinic acid (a-phenyl-2-piperidine acetic acid, PPAA); unchanged
      methylphenidate is excreted in the urine in small quantities (&lt;1%). Peak PPAA plasma
      concentrations occurred at approximately the same time as peak methylphenidate
      concentrations, however, levels were several-fold greater than those of the unchanged drug.
      The half-life of PPAA was approximately twice that of methylphenidate.

      Role of CHEO Pharmacy

      Section C.05.010 of the Division 5 Regulations pertains to the sponsor's (i.e. Children's
      Hospital of Eastern Ontario) obligations in regards to Good Clinical Practice. The CHEO
      pharmacy will have the following obligations—compliant with said Regulations—with respect to
      the drug/placebo management: drug acquisition and dispensing, maintenance of inventory and
      accountability and reconciliation of records, labelling of study medication, storage of
      inventory, and general records such as patient information forms and creating patient
      binders. Note that in Division 5, Health Canada mandates that records must be maintained for
      a period of 25 years, and the CHEO pharmacy will ensure the maintenance of such record
      keeping.

      Safety Assessments and Trial Monitoring

      Clinical Safety Assessments

      The following assessments will be performed to determine the safety of MPH Hydrochloride:
      vital signs (blood pressure and pulse); monitoring effects/symptoms (side effects checklist).
      Those who report or show heightened blood pressure or heart rate side effects from the test
      doss of MPH at the clinical screening visit, e.g., systolic blood pressure exceeding baseline
      reading by 20mmHg, diastolic blood pressure exceeding the baseline reading by 10mmHg, BP &gt;
      160/100, or resting pulse increased by 20 beats/minute from the baseline reading will be
      excluded from the study. Subjective side effects will be measured for 21 potential side
      effects (e.g., headache, nausea, nervousness, etc.) by having subjects rate the intensity of
      their symptoms using the following scale : 1 = none, 2 = mild, 3 = moderate, 4 = severe. A
      qualified registered nurse is present throughout the entire session. Furthermore, thorough
      emergency plans have been implemented in conjunction with the Children's Hospital of Eastern
      Ontario (e.g. code blue) and the University of Ottawa should a crisis arise. In addition, the
      research unit has been equipped with a complete first aid unit cart along with an automated
      external defibrillator in which all the employees have been trained to operate. All employees
      are also required to maintain a valid CPR-C.

      Each participant will be supplied with a &quot;study enrollment card&quot; that will have the study
      title, along with the emergency contact information for the CHEO pharmacy technician (in
      control of study blinding) and for the Qualified Investigator (Principal Investigator—PI ).
      This card will act as a safeguard if the participant seeks emergency medical help where it is
      required to know whether they have been taking drug or placebo, thereby acting as an aid in
      the clinical judgment to stop the treatment. The enrollment card will also act to tract
      if/when a participant needs to be unblinded to the treatment.

      Trial Management and Monitoring

      Management

      The Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario Clinical Research Unit (CHEO-CRU) will be the
      coordinating center for this study and the University of Ottawa will the other testing site.
      The Principal Investigator and the study coordinator, along with CHEO pharmacy, will be
      responsible for the day-to-day operations of the trial. CHEO-CRU will provide the CHEO
      pharmacy with the randomization table and will resultantly be the only persons who are
      unblinded. The randomization will take place once the Initial Screening Visit is completed
      and it is determined that the participant is eligible to participate. Therefore, each
      participant will have an equal chance of being randomized to drug or placebo using a computer
      generated random number program by a member of the CRU before entering into the Baseline 1
      test day.

      Treatment discontinuation

      In the event that the subject is withdrawn from the study due to an AE, the AE will be
      recorded and reported, and the subject will be followed and treated until the abnormal
      parameter or symptom has resolved or stabilized. It is up to the clinician and the Data &amp;
      Safety Monitoring Board to determine that the AE is either resolved or that it has reached a
      stable state, after which no further follow-up is necessary. Support for this determination
      will be documented. The reason for withdrawal from the study will be recorded on the
      appropriate case report form (CRF). If a subject is removed from the study, we will continue
      the scheduled follow-up with the subject's permission. There will be no changes to the
      follow-up schedule, except no study treatment/intervention will be administered. If at any
      point a subject no longer wishes to participate in follow-up, or after the three month
      follow-up telephone call, participation in the study will be complete. If new evidence
      emerges in the literature to indicate that our study dosage is unsafe, the study will be
      discontinued and all further qualifying patients will be offered the more effective/safer
      treatment.

      Data Safety and Monitoring Board

      The Data and Safety Monitoring Board (DSMB) is an independent group of experts who will
      function independently and at arm's length from the Study Investigators and the Steering
      Committee of the Study. The primary responsibilities of the DSMB are as follows:

        1. Review and evaluate the accumulated study data for participant safety

        2. Make recommendations to the Steering Committee based on these reviews regarding the
           continuation, modification or termination of the trial

        3. DSMB members must maintain strict confidentiality concerning all privileged trial
           results, and during all phases of DSMB review and deliberations.

        4. No member of the DSMB should have a direct involvement with the conduct of the study. No
           member should have financial, proprietary, professional or other interests that may
           affect impartial, independent decision-making by the DSMB.

           The DSMB will be notified of all serious unexpected adverse drug reactions and all
           deaths within 5 working days of knowledge of the SAE. It is the Qualified Investigator's
           responsibility to ensure that the DSMB is apprised of all new safety information
           relevant to the study.

           The DSMB will be scheduled on a regular basis and as often as necessary. Regular reviews
           will be conducted yearly and focused primarily on safety issues. A designated third
           party analysis (prepared by a study statistician) will be delivered to the DSMB two
           weeks prior to any scheduled review. Prior to study initiation, DSMB members will review
           study protocols, informed consents, Data and Safety Monitoring Plans and other relevant
           documents as needed (case report forms, manual of procedures, etc.). During the study,
           DSMB members will review all study protocol amendments.

           Adverse Events (AE's) and Serious Adverse Events (SAE's)

           Adverse Events

           Adverse events (AEs) are defined as any symptom, sign, illness or experience that occurs
           while participating in the study, including both during admission and as an outpatient.
           Abnormal clinical results will be considered to be adverse events if the abnormality:

             -  results in study withdrawal

             -  is associated with clinical signs or symptoms

             -  leads to additional treatment or to further diagnostic tests

             -  is considered by the investigator or Data &amp; Safety Monitoring Board to be of
                clinical significance.

           Serious Adverse Event (SAE)

           A SAE is any adverse event that at any dose:

             -  results in death

             -  is life-threatening

             -  requires inpatient hospitalization or prolongation of existing hospitalization

             -  results in persistent or significant disability or incapacity

             -  results in a congenital anomaly/birth defect

             -  other serious (important event)

             -  prolonged hospitalization, significantly beyond the expected length of stay

             -  important medical events

           Serious Unexpected Adverse drug Reactions are SAEs that are likely to be related to the
           study drug.

           Medical and scientific judgment should be exercised in deciding whether expedited
           reporting is appropriate in other situations such as important medical events that may
           not be immediately life-threatening or result in death or hospitalization but may
           jeopardize the patient or may require intervention to prevent one of the events listed
           above.

           Serious Adverse Event Reporting

           What to Report

             -  Any SAE that meets the definition of a Reportable Serious Adverse Event

             -  All life-threatening or fatal adverse events with an attribution of possible,
                probable, or definite

           The Sponsor Investigator will notify Health Canada (Office of Clinical Trials) for those
           events which meet regulatory requirements for expedited reporting, (i.e. events which
           are BOTH serious AND unexpected), AND which are thought to be related to protocol
           treatment (or for which a causal relationship with protocol treatment cannot be ruled
           out).

           Adverse Drug Reaction (ADR) report must be filed in the cases:

             -  where the ADR is neither fatal nor life-threatening, within 15 days after becoming
                aware of the information

             -  where it is fatal or life-threatening, immediately where possible and, in any
                event, within 7 days after becoming aware of the information

             -  within 8 days after having informed Health Canada of the ADR, submit as complete as
                possible, a report which an assessment of the importance and implication of any
                findings

           This includes all serious events that are unexpected and related (i.e. possibly,
           probably, or definitely) to protocol therapy. Investigators must notify their Research
           Ethics Boards (REBs) and documents related to submission must be retained in the study
           binder on site.

           The submission of these events to the local ethics board should be done as soon as
           possible (within 30 days) or per local REB requirements. REB submissions greater than 90
           days from the date of notification will be regarded as delinquent and a major deficiency
           will be assigned.

           Important medical events are those that may not be immediately life threatening, but are
           clearly of major clinical significance. They may jeopardize the subject, and may require
           intervention to prevent one of the other serious outcomes noted above.

           Monitoring of AE's/SAE's:

           Any AE that occurs between the time a study participant/parent signs the informed
           consent form and the time he/she completes the telephone follow-up (or at the time of
           early discontinuation of the subject from the study for any reason) will be captured and
           recorded. At each contact with the subject, the investigator (or designate) will seek
           information on adverse events by specific questioning and, as appropriate, by
           examination.

           The intensity of an AE is assessed as mild (usually transient in nature and generally
           not interfering with normal activities), moderate (sufficiently discomforting to
           interfere with normal activities), and severe (prevents normal activities).

           The maximum clinical intensity of all adverse events will be classified as:

             -  Mild: Signs and symptoms that can easily be tolerated or ignored.

             -  Moderate: Symptoms that cause discomfort but are tolerable; they cannot be ignored
                and affect concentration.

             -  Severe: Symptoms that affect usual daily activity.

           The attribution of all adverse events will be classified as:

             -  Unrelated to investigational agent/intervention

                  -  Not related The AE is clearly not related to the intervention

                  -  Doubtful The AE is not likely to be related to the intervention

             -  Related to investigational agent/intervention

                  -  Possible The AE may be related to the intervention

                  -  Probable The AE is likely related to the intervention

                  -  Definite The AE is clearly related to the intervention

           An adverse drug reaction (ADR) is any untoward medical occurrence that the PI determines
           is likely related to the study drug (attribution of possible, probably, or definite).

           Feasibility

           There are no field studies looking at the effects of MPH on food intake (neither as a
           main outcome nor secondary outcome). Therefore, our only way of estimating effects sizes
           is extrapolating from our previous laboratory studies. In a laboratory study by the
           investigators, an effect size of .93 was attained in 9 obese adult males for the primary
           outcome of food intake with mean energy intake in kilocalories for MPH (0.5 mg/kg) and
           placebo of 843.5 + 393.4 and 1095.9 + 271.1, respectively. In a second study in 14
           normal weight adult males and females, an effect size of .69 was attained, favouring MPH
           (0.5 mg/kg) for food intake in an ad libitum buffet meal with mean difference in kcals
           of -133 (1099 for MPH minus 1232 for placebo), with a standard deviation of 192.0 kcals
           for the paired differences based on t-tests. Based on the more conservative effect size
           of .69, it would be possible to detect a significant difference in kcals consumed over a
           60-day period between MPH and placebo using a paired t-test with an alpha of 0.05, power
           of 0.80, with 18 participants per group. Thus, the plan to include 40 participants per
           group should enable the investigators to look at trends on other energy balance
           (secondary outcome) variables, accounting for an expected drop-out of 5-10%. The plan is
           to run 3 new participants/month, thus the experimental part of the study should last
           approximately 14 months.

           Role of Investigators/Staff

           Philippe Robaey, as Principal Investigator, is a physician and child Psychiatrist and
           Director of the ADHD clinic at CHEO. He has many years of clinical and research
           experience with MPH. Dr. Robaey will be responsible for the medical aspects of the study
           such as prescribing the study medication under double blind conditions, as well as
           overseeing the evaluation of vital sign and side effects of MPH. Dr. Eric Doucet, as
           Co-Principal Investigator (C0-PI) is a Full Professor of Human Kinetics at University of
           Ottawa, Faculty of Health Sciences. Dr. Doucet is an expert in the measurement of energy
           balance measures using the proposed methods. The study of the adult population will be
           conducted in Dr. Doucet's Behavioural Metabolic Research Unit, where our previous MPH
           cross-over trial was done, and he will oversee the coordination and supervision of the
           experimental testing procedures. Dr. Gary Goldfield, as Co-Principal Investigator
           (CO-PI), is a clinical psychologist and Investigator with the Healthy Active Living and
           Obesity Research Group at the CHEO Research Institute. He will oversee the assessment of
           psychiatric inclusion criteria evaluated by questionnaire and structured clinical
           interview, as well as the measurement of the reinforcing (rewarding) value of food. Dr.
           Jameason Cameron, as co-Principal investigator, is a postdoc and a research coordinator
           at CHEO. He has extensive experience with feeding studies and weight loss trials, and
           measures of food reward and smell function. Dr. Cameron will be responsible for the
           day-to-day testing and to supervise the PhD student who will be co-coordinating the
           study.

           Statistical Analysis

           Differences between groups (MPH vs. placebo) in energy intake and energy expenditure
           variables, as well as body weight, impulsivity, olfaction, hunger, satiety, and the
           reinforcing value of food will be evaluated by paired t-tests and repeated measures
           analyses of variance (ANOVA). Hypotheses of mechanisms linking MPH and reduced food
           intake and weight loss via reduced food reward will be explored using multiple
           regression mediational analyses as described by Baron and Kenny.

           Data Management

           All &quot;source document&quot; data collected from the study visits, except data that would
           indicate randomization assignment, will be maintained in a secure location within the
           Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario. The investigator will verify that all data
           entries in the CRF are accurate and correct. Data collection is the responsibility of
           the research staff at the site under the supervision of the Principal Investigator.
           During the study the investigator will maintain complete and accurate documentation for
           the study and keep all original source documents. All adverse events will be graded,
           assessed by severity and causality and reviewed by the site investigator. Original
           subject records (source documents) will be reviewed during the course of the monitoring
           to verify the accuracy of the CRF's. This review will be conducted according to the peer
           monitoring plan. The Investigator(s) institutions(s) will permit trial-related
           monitoring, audits, REB(s) review and regulatory inspections(s) by providing direct
           access to source data and documentation. The medical (hospital/practice) records for
           each patient should contain information to provide a means by which study data can be
           verified. Patient information collected electronically will be available for review when
           the study site is monitored or audited. Entry of these data in SPSS will be performed
           primarily by the PhD student, but partly by the co-Principal investigators. Subjects
           will be assigned a code number to maintain blinding to data management staff, with the
           corresponding list of names associated with subject codes kept by the pharmacist in a
           secure filing cabinet. Databases will be stored on a secure server, with nightly backup.

           Publication Plan

           By the end of the second year of the study the investigators plan on publishing 2
           peer-review articles, one at the international journal Physiology and Behavior
           highlighting the secondary metabolic outcomes, and the other at the American Journal of
           Clinical Nutrition, highlighting the main outcome of the influence of MPH on appetite.

           Ethical Considerations

           This study will be conducted according to Canadian and international standards of Good
           Clinical Practice and the Health Canada, Food and Drug Act, Part C, Division 5, Drugs
           for clinical Trials Involving Human Subjects, and in full conformance with principles of
           the &quot;Declaration of Helsinki&quot;. The CHEO research institute policies and standard
           operating procedures will also be followed. This protocol and any amendments will be
           submitted to the CHEO REB for formal approval to conduct the study. The decision of the
           REB concerning the conduct of the study will be made in writing to the investigator. All
           participants for this study will be provided a consent form and assent form if
           applicable, describing this study and providing sufficient information for participants
           to make an informed decision about their participation in this study. The consent form
           will be submitted with the protocol for review and approval by the REB. The formal
           consent of a participant, using the REB-approved consent form, will be obtained before
           that participant is submitted to any study procedure. The consent form must be signed by
           the participant or legally acceptable surrogate, and the investigator-designated
           research professional obtaining the consent.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Energy Intake</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured three times over the course of 2 months (twice at baseline: once with and without study drug &amp; once at final visit).</time_frame>
    <description>Participant will be offered a lunch buffet that includes items they indicate are preferred. They will be able to eat as much or as little as they choose.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Energy Expenditure</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured three times over the course of 2 months (twice at baseline: once with and without study drug &amp; once at final visit).</time_frame>
    <description>Indirect calorimetry measure: participant lies supine on a bed while a neoprene mask is attached to their face. Expired breath is captured by the metabolic cart to assess resting energy expenditure and the thermic effect of feeding.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Body Weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured two times over the course of 2 months (once at baseline &amp; once at final visit).</time_frame>
    <description>Participant stands on a weight scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Height</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at baseline.</time_frame>
    <description>Participant stands next to a stadiometer; height will be used to determine BMI at baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Height</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at final visit; height will be used to determine BMI at the final visit.</time_frame>
    <description>Participant stands next to a stadiometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Body Mass Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured two times over the course of 2 months (once at baseline &amp; once at final visit).</time_frame>
    <description>This measure is a conglomerate of body weight (kg) divided by height (meters squared)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Impulsivity towards food and non-food reward as measured by reaction time on a computer task.</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured three times over the course of 2 months (twice at baseline: once with and without study drug &amp; once at final visit).</time_frame>
    <description>A &quot;go/no-go&quot;computer task that measures reaction time to food and non-food cues with simple button-presses on a keyboard.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Odour Detection Threshold measured with Sniffin' Sticks Odourized Pens</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured three times over the course of 2 months (twice at baseline: once with and without study drug &amp; once at final visit).</time_frame>
    <description>Odourized pens, called Sniffin Sticks, are used to measure odour detection threshold for a non-toxic odourant called n-butanol.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>60 day oral administration of sugar placebo twice per day before lunch and supper.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Methylphenidate (MPH)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>60 day oral administration of active study drug (methylphenidate) twice per day before lunch and supper.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MPH</intervention_name>
    <description>60 days on oral methylphenidate administered 2 times daily before lunch and supper.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Methylphenidate (MPH)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pms-Methylphenidate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>60 days on oral placebo administered 2 times daily before lunch and supper</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sugar Placebo</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  males and females 16 to 40 years old

          -  BMI in the obese category (above 29.9kg/m2)

          -  willing to comply with procedures, and sign informed consent forms

          -  able to swallow a placebo pill that will be used in the study (same size as study
             drug)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  smoker (the main outcome is energy intake and smoking is known to impact appetite)

          -  known serious food allergies, including lactose

          -  history of previous MPH use or allergy to MPH

          -  history of ADHD or current diagnosis of an axis 1 psychiatric disorder (e.g.,
             depression, panic disorder, schizophrenia) as measured by self-report, the Wender-Utah
             Rating Scale52-54 and the Beck Depression Inventory

          -  current use of antidepressants, thyroid medication, or any medication that could
             affect appetite

          -  high blood pressure

          -  pre-existing cardiovascular disorders including uncontrolled hypertension, angina
             pectoris, arterial occlusive disease, heart failure, cardiomypathies, myocardial
             infarction, and cardiac arrhythmia

          -  diabetes

          -  excessive use of alcohol or alcoholism, or current addictions to opiates, cocaine or
             stimulants as measured by the Drug Abuse Screening Test;

          -  not a restrained eater based on cut-score (11 or higher) on Three Factor Eating
             Questionnaire56

          -  glaucoma

          -  personal or family history of seizure disorders

          -  currently taking MAO inhibitors, pressor agents, coumarin, anticonvulsants,
             phenylbutazone, or tricyclic antidepressants

          -  history of thyroid disease

          -  personal or family history of motor tics or Tourettes's Syndrome

          -  not pregnant, as determined by commercially available pregnancy test taken by female
             participants prior to test dose of MPH.

          -  after the test dose of MPH, systolic blood pressure exceeding baseline reading by
             20mmHg, diastolic blood pressure exceeding the baseline reading by 10mmHg, BP &gt;
             160/100, or resting pulse increased by 20 beats/minute from the baseline.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eric Doucet, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Ottawa</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philippe Robaey, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Childrens Hospital of Eastern Ontario-Research Inst</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jameason D Cameron, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>613-737-7600</phone>
    <phone_ext>4103</phone_ext>
    <email>jcameron@cheo.on.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gary S Goldfield, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>613-737-7600</phone>
    <phone_ext>3288</phone_ext>
    <email>ggoldfield@cheo.on.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Of Eastern Ontario Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1H8L1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Children's Hospital Of E Ontario, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>6137377600</phone>
      <phone_ext>4103</phone_ext>
      <email>jcameron@cheo.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Ottawa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1N6N5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jameason Cameron, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>16137377600</phone>
      <phone_ext>4103</phone_ext>
      <email>jcameron@cheo.on.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 12, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 25, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 28, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 2, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 2, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 3, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Hospital of Eastern Ontario</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Phillippe Robaey</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Qualified Investigator, MD, PhD, FRCPC</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methylphenidate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We have not made a plan to make IPD available. We do plan on publishing the findings, but as per normal scientific reporting, with deidentified data.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

