<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01186302</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>WHO A65550</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01186302</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison of the Safety and Efficacy of Medical Abortion Provided by Physicians and Midlevel Providers in Nepal</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparison of the Safety, Efficacy, and Feasibility of Medical Abortion Provided by Physicians and Non-physicians in Nepal: a Randomized Controlled, Equivalence Trial.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>World Health Organization</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Center for Research and Environmental Health and Population Activities (CREHPA)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>World Health Organization</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to compare the safety, effectiveness, and acceptability of
      medical abortion provided by doctors and midlevel providers in a developing country where
      doctors are scarce, such as Nepal. This study is the first to evaluate the independent
      provision of medical abortion by trained nurses and auxiliary nurse midwives compared to
      doctors by assessing differences in safety, clinical outcomes, case management
      decision-making, and acceptability. This study provides scientifically valid data on the
      administration of medical abortion by midlevel providers working independently in a
      low-resource, developing country setting. The evidence generated by the study will assist
      policy makers in developing countries interested in expanding safe abortion services by
      eliminating the legal requirement limiting prescription of medical abortion to doctors where
      medical abortion is not restricted by law.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Each year, some 210 million women throughout the world become pregnant and nearly one in five
      chooses to terminate the pregnancy (Singh et al., 2009). Approximately, 22 million
      pregnancies are terminated unsafely; of these, the vast majority (98%) take place in
      developing countries (WHO, Forthcoming). Access to safe abortion services is a challenge for
      many women with unwanted pregnancies in developing countries because of restrictive
      legislation, a shortage of skilled staff or other barriers.

      Non-surgical methods of abortion, known as medical abortion, have been developed that use
      safe and effective drug-based methods for induced abortion. Prescribing authority is
      generally limited to doctors, however. As a result, medical abortion remains under-utilized
      and is often inaccessible for many women in developing countries seeking public sector
      providers trained in medical abortion in areas where there are no doctors.

      Midlevel providers (non-physician clinicians such as nurses and midwives) have the potential
      to provide accessible, low-cost, and safe abortion services in many countries, especially in
      the developing world. They are more cost-effective to employ than doctors and often work in
      areas where doctors are in short supply, providing much needed health services to
      under-served areas while conserving resources. Training midlevel providers in the independent
      provision of medical abortion with appropriate referral systems would expand access to safe
      abortion services to lower levels of the health care system where there is no doctor and
      complement a global health systems trend towards task-shifting where doctors are costly and
      scarce (WHO, 2007).

      The overall objective of the study is to obtain evidence on the safety and effectiveness of
      medical abortions performed by government trained and certified midlevel providers and
      physicians to inform policy makers interested in or committed to expanding and decentralizing
      medical abortion services.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete abortion</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measure was a successful (complete) abortion, defined as no ongoing pregnancy at clinical examination and no surgical intervention necessary.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications from medical abortion</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as life-threatening events requiring hospitalization: haemorrhage requiring a blood transfusion, hospitalization (iv fluids, iv antibiotics), or laparatomy for ectopic pregnancies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1104</enrollment>
  <condition>Medical Abortion</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Midlevel provider</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients were assigned to a midlevel provider (arm 1) or to a physician (arm 2) for their abortion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physician arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients were assigned to a midlevel provider (arm 1) or to a physician (arm 2) for their abortion.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Type of provider</intervention_name>
    <description>Different types of clinicians have different types of medical training. This study tested whether midlevel providers were as safe and effective in administering medical abortion as doctors. All types of providers underwent the same training in medical abortion and used the same medical abortion regimen.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Midlevel provider</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Physician arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Before randomization: Gestational age not more than 63 days as estimated by last
             menstrual period (LMP).

          -  After randomization: Gestational age not more than 63 days as estimated by abdominal
             and bimanual pelvic examination.

          -  Above national age of consent

          -  Willing to return to the clinic for misoprostol on Day 3 and for a follow-up visit on
             Day 10 to 14.

          -  Residence within the geographical area specified for each clinic and no more than one
             hour from emergency referral services.

          -  Willing to provide written informed consent to participate in the study and to be
             randomly assigned to a provider team.

          -  Able to understand the nature of the study, advice and instructions given by health
             providers.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous allergic reaction to one of the drugs in the medical abortion regimen

          -  Known or suspected ectopic pregnancy or undiagnosed adnexal mass

          -  Inherited porphyria (rare genetic blood diseases)

          -  Chronic adrenal failure

          -  Long term corticosteroid therapy

          -  Haemorrhagic disorder or anticoagulant therapy (blood thinner medications)

          -  IUD in utero that can not be removed before taking mifepristone

          -  Previous enrolment in the study (i.e. no repeat abortions; only one abortion per woman
             in the study)

          -  Unwilling or unable to return to clinic for follow-up visit.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kusum Thapa, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Paropakar Maternity and Women Hospital (Maternity Hospital), Kathmandu, Nepal</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ina Warriner, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>World Health Organization</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Center for Research and Environmental Health and Population Activities (CREHPA)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kathmandu</city>
        <country>Nepal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Nepal</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Warriner IK, Meirik O, Hoffman M, Morroni C, Harries J, My Huong NT, Vy ND, Seuc AH. Rates of complication in first-trimester manual vacuum aspiration abortion done by doctors and mid-level providers in South Africa and Vietnam: a randomised controlled equivalence trial. Lancet. 2006 Dec 2;368(9551):1965-72.</citation>
    <PMID>17141703</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 20, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 20, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 23, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 20, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 20, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 23, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Ina Warriner</name_title>
    <organization>World Health Organization</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>medical abortion</keyword>
  <keyword>Nepal</keyword>
  <keyword>midlevel providers</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

