<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01188135</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R01MH090160</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01MH090160</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01188135</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Antidepressant Adherence Via AD_IVR</brief_title>
  <acronym>AD_IVR</acronym>
  <official_title>Antidepressant Adherence Via Telephonic Interactive Voice Recognition (IVR)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Kaiser Permanente</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Kaiser Permanente</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Antidepressants are the most frequently prescribed class of psycho¬tropic medications and the
      most common treatment for depression and anxiety disorders—yet patient adherence is poor and
      is widely viewed as contributing to reduced effectiveness. However, traditionally-delivered
      adherence promotion programs are complex, staff-intensive, and costly—barriers to wider
      adoption, implementation, and maintenance of these programs in real-world settings. Our aim
      is to carry out a trial of a low-cost, IT-enabled Antidepressants adherence program,
      specifically a direct-to-patient, automated telephone interactive voice recognition (IVR)
      intervention to boost patient Antidepressants persistence. We will conduct a randomized
      clinical trial enrolling at least 6,000 Kaiser Permanente NW Region health plan members ages
      21 to 75, who had recently started on Antidepressants medications for depression and/or
      anxiety diagnoses. Participants will be randomized one of four arms;1. a no contact control
      arm, 2. a treatment as usual (TAU) control condition 3. to TAU plus the IVR automated
      telephone program and 4. a TAU plus the IVR automated telephone program plus receipt of
      psycho-education materials about antidepression medication use. Recruitment will continue for
      up to 18 months, with periodic participant-level follow-up assessment for the intervention
      participants for 40 weeks. The IVR intervention portion of the program will deliver reminder
      and/or tardy calls timed to projected Antidepressants refill dates. The intervention also
      optionally offers brief psycho-education, or transfer to a live pharmacist or the Kaiser mail
      refill pharmacy. The primary outcome will be the Estimated Level of Persistence with Therapy
      (continued us of Antidepressants medications). This will be based on prescription refill data
      abstracted from the Kaiser's electronic medical record (EMR). We hypothesize that
      participants in the IVR + psycho-education materials study arm will have a significantly
      higher rate of Antidepressants persistence than those in the TAU control condition ons only
      IRV call arms. We will also conduct cost-effectiveness analyses to assess the value-for-money
      (cost per depression free day gained, and cost per quality adjusted life year gained) of the
      IVR technology compared to TAU. Costs will include IVR development and implementation as well
      as EMR-derived healthcare utilization data (visits, medications, etc.), augmented with
      participant report of out-of-plan services.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Antidepressants (AD) are the most frequently prescribed class of psycho-tropic medications
      and the most common treatment for depression and anxiety disorders—yet patient adherence is
      poor and is widely viewed as contributing to reduced effectiveness. Fortunately, AD adherence
      can be improved via interventions consistent with the Chronic Care Model (CCM). However,
      traditionally-delivered adherence promotion programs are complex, staff-intensive, and
      costly—barriers to wider adoption, implementation, and maintenance of these programs in
      real-world settings. Our aim is to carry out a trial of a low-cost, IT-enabled AD adherence
      program, specifically a direct-to-patient, automated telephone interactive voice recognition
      (IVR) intervention to boost patient AD persistence. This intervention is consistent with the
      Chronic Care Model but is much more amenable to widespread dissemination over a large
      population. In an initial startup period the investigators will adapt and pilot existing IVR
      adherence calls and scripts, informed by formative focus groups and interviews with key
      informants (patients, providers). Following this, the investigators will conduct a pragmatic,
      randomized clinical trial at approximately 6,000 HMO members ages 21 to 75, recently started
      on an incident course of AD medications for associated unipolar depression and/or anxiety
      diagnoses. Participants will be randomized (1:1:1:1); 1. a no contact control arm, 2. a
      treatment as usual (TAU) control condition 3. to TAU plus the IVR automated telephone program
      and 4. a TAU plus the IVR automated telephone program plus receipt of psycho-education
      materials about antidepression medication use. Recruitment will continue for up to 18 months,
      with periodic participant-level follow-up for 40 weeks. The two IVR interventions will
      deliver reminder and/or tardy calls timed to projected AD refill dates. The intervention arms
      also optionally offers transfer to a live pharmacist or the HMO mail refill pharmacy. The
      primary outcome will be the Estimated Level of Persistence with Therapy (ELPT) for ADs, based
      on prescription refill data abstracted from the HMO's electronic medical record (EMR). We
      hypothesize that participants in the IVR study plus psycho-ed. arm will have a significantly
      higher rate of AD persistence than those in the TAU control condition or IVR only. Secondary
      medication adherence outcomes include continuous measure of medication acquisition (CMA) and
      continuous measure of medication gaps (CMG). Other secondary outcomes include self-report
      depression and anxiety symptoms, general health status, patient and provider satisfaction,
      and healthcare costs and usage. We will also conduct cost-effectiveness analyses (CEA) to
      assess the value-for-money (cost per depression free day gained, and cost per quality
      adjusted life year gained) of the IVR technology compared to TAU. Costs will include IVR
      development and implementation as well as EMR-derived healthcare utilization data (visits,
      medications, etc.), augmented with participant report of out-of-plan services. Finally,
      evaluative qualitative interviews will be conducted with key stakeholders to identify
      barriers/facilitators of intervention implementation—keys for future dissemination.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Participants in the IVR study arm will have a significantly higher rate of AD persistence (ELPT) than those in the TAU control condition</measure>
    <time_frame>assessments at 4, 8,12 and 40 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>A randomized controlled trial of adult members of a (HMO) starting an incident episode of antidepressant treatment, (a) nocontact control,(b) treatment as usual (TAU) versus (c) TAU plus the IVR automated telephone adherence program, (d)TAU plus the IVR automated telephone adherence program plus mailed psycho-education materials. The primary outcome will be antidepressant persistence, operationalized as the Estimated Level of Persistence with Therapy. Secondary outcomes will include patient and provider satisfaction, healthcare utilization, and patient self-reported depression and anxiety.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>cost-effectiveness analyses</measure>
    <time_frame>at the end of week 40</time_frame>
    <description>We will also conduct cost-effectiveness analyses comparing the arms of the study. We will employ healthcare utilization data (visits, medications, etc.) obtained from the electronic medical record, augmented with participant report of out-of-plan healthcare services. These will compare study conditions on the cost to achieve units of improvement in depression free days and quality-adjusted life years. We expect that costs per unit of improvementfor the IVR intervention will be within standard boundaries of decision-makers willingness to pay.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6058</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interactive Voice messaging</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive three kinds of interventions calls from the IVR phone system. (1) The first call is to orient the participant to the IVR system, ask permission to leave detailed messages in the future, and to encourage adherence in this initial period of great risk for premature discontinuation. (2) The Refill Reminder Call is to remind patients that a refill their antidepressant medications and occurs approximately 6 days before the prior dispense of medication is due to run out. (3) The &quot;Tardy&quot; Refill Call is made to participants for whom EMR records indicate that a scheduled refill was missed</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual care arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>usual care treatment with no interactive phone reminder calls phone</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IVR messaging w/ Psycho-ed. materials</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive three kinds of interventions calls from the IVR phone system. (1) The first call is to orient the participant to the IVR system, ask permission to leave detailed messages in the future, and to encourage adherence in this initial period of great risk for premature discontinuation. (2) The Refill Reminder Call is to remind patients that a refill their antidepressant medications and occurs approximately 6 days before the prior dispense of medication is due to run out. (3) The &quot;Tardy&quot; Refill Call is made to participants for whom EMR records indicate that a scheduled refill was missed. In addition, participants will receive educational material about antidepressant medication.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Interactive voice messaging or Interactive voice messaging + psycho ed materials</intervention_name>
    <description>Interactive voice telephone messages reminder participants to continue to take their antidepressive medications</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interactive Voice messaging</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>IVR messaging w/ Psycho-ed. materials</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must be Kaiser Permanente NW Region health plan members ages of 21 and 75
             and be members for at least 6 months prior to the initial antidepressive medications
             dispense.

          -  Participants must have an EMR chart diagnosis or presenting complaint of a unipolar
             mood diagnosis, anxiety disorder, or any subclinical or &quot;not otherwise categorized&quot;
             (NOC) variant of these.

          -  The participants' providers must give permission to study staff for their patients'
             enrollment in the study. There must be no indication of pending HMO disenrollment in
             the membership data.

          -  Participants must have an initial dispense of an antidepressant medication, with no
             dispense of any of these agents in the prior 6 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants must have no EMR chart diagnosis that is likely to impair participant
             ability to complete evaluations or take part in the intervention. These include
             psychiatric diagnoses such as bipolar disorder I (BP II is acceptable), schizophrenia,
             schizo-affective disorder, or similar diagnoses indicating psychosis.

          -  The investigators will also exclude individuals with any chart diagnosis indicating
             significant intellectual impairment, such as any dementia disorder, mental
             retardation, or profound developmental disorder such as autism.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Greg N Clarke, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Kaiser Permanente</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kaiser Permanente Center for Health Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97227</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 23, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 24, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 25, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 17, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>depression</keyword>
  <keyword>interactive voice messaging</keyword>
  <keyword>patient persistence with antidepressant medication treatment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antidepressive Agents</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

