<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01186588</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR017227</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01186588</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Canagliflozin in Study Participants With Various Degrees of Impaired Hepatic (Liver) Function</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label Study to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetics of a Single Oral Dose of 300 mg JNJ-28431754 (Canagliflozin) in Subjects With Various Degrees of Impaired Hepatic Function Compared With Subjects With Normal Hepatic Function</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to determine the concentration of canagliflozin in blood and
      urine samples after the administration of canagliflozin to study participants with mild or
      moderate hepatic (liver) impairment compared with study participants with normal hepatic
      function.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label (both study participant and investigator will know the name of the
      assigned treatment), pharmacokinetic (the study of how drugs are absorbed in the body, how
      they are distributed within the body, and how they are removed from the body over time) study
      of canagliflozin in adult study participants with mild or moderate hepatic (liver) impairment
      compared to study participants with normal hepatic function. Approximately 24 study
      participants who meet entry criteria for the study will be classified into 1 of 3 hepatic
      function groups: Group 1 (8 study participants with normal hepatic function), Group 2 (8
      study participants with mild hepatic impairment) and Group 3 (8 study participants with
      moderate hepatic impairment). The group allocation is based on the Child-Pugh score, an
      assessment of 5 clinical measures that is used to characterize the degree of hepatic
      impairment. At least 3 men and 3 women will be enrolled in each group and the 3 groups will
      be balanced with respect to an average age and body weight. Study participants will be
      required to stay overnight at the study center for 5 nights to receive study drug and have
      study procedures and safety assessments performed. All study participants will be
      administered a single 300-mg oral (by mouth) dose of canagliflozin after fasting (not eating
      food) for a period of at least 10 hours. After study drug administration, study participants
      will be provided with standardized meals (breakfast, lunch, and dinner). Blood and urine
      samples for analyses of canagliflozin and metabolites (M7 and M5) will be collected from
      study participants at specified time points up to 120 hours (blood) and 48 hours (urine)
      after study drug administration. After discharge from the study center, study participants
      will be required to return to the study center for 3 outpatient visits to have study
      procedures and safety assessments performed. Study participants will be monitored for safety
      during the study by evaluating adverse events reported and results from clinical laboratory
      tests, 12-lead electrocardiograms (ECGs), vital sign measurements, and physical examinations.
      On Day 1 of the study, a single 300 mg dose of canagliflozin will be orally administered to
      study participants after a fasting period of at least 10 hours followed 10 minutes later by a
      standardized breakfast that must be eaten within 30 minutes. Study participants are to remain
      standing or sitting for the first 4 hours after dosing. At 2 hours after dosing (but not
      earlier) all study participants must drink 1 glass of water; drinking of water is allowed
      from then onwards.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma concentrations of canagliflozin to evaluate protocol-specified pharmacokinetic parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>At protocol-specified time points before and after dosing on Day 1 through Day 6</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine concentrations of canagliflozin to evaluate protocol-specified pharmacokinetic parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>At protocol-specified time points after dosing on Day 1 through Day 3</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma concentrations of canagliflozin metabolites, (M5 and M7 to evaluate protocol-specified pharmacokinetic parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>At protocol-specified time points before and after dosing on Day 1 through Day 6</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine concentrations of canagliflozin metabolites (M5 and M7) to evaluate protocol-specified pharmacokinetic parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>At protocol-specified time points after dosing on Day 1 through Day 3</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events reported</measure>
    <time_frame>From Screening (up to 23 days prior to dosing) to 7 to 10 days after Day 6 or at the time of early withdrawal from the study.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital signs measurements and results from electrocardiograms</measure>
    <time_frame>From Screening (up to 23 days prior to dosing) to 7 to 10 days after Day 6 or at the time of early withdrawal from the study.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical examination findings</measure>
    <time_frame>From Screening (up to 23 days prior to dosing) to 7 to 10 days after Day 6 or at the time of early withdrawal from the study.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Laboratory test results</measure>
    <time_frame>From Screening (up to 23 days prior to dosing) to 7 to 10 days after Day 6 or at the time of early withdrawal from the study.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <condition>Hepatic Insufficiency</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>001</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Canagliflozin One 300-mg dose of canagliflozin on Day 1</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Canagliflozin</intervention_name>
    <description>One 300-mg dose of canagliflozin on Day 1</description>
    <arm_group_label>001</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All study participants must have a body mass index (ie, a measure of one's weight in
             relation to height) between 18 and 33 kg/m2 (inclusive)

          -  Study participants with normal hepatic function must have blood pressure at screening
             and before study drug administration between 90 and 160 mmHg systolic, inclusive, and
             55 and 100 mmHg diastolic, inclusive

          -  Study participants with normal hepatic function should be comparable to the groups
             with hepatic impairment with respect to mean (average) age (range of +/- 15 years) and
             mean weight (range of +/- 25%)

          -  Study participants with mild or moderate hepatic impairment must be otherwise in
             acceptable clinical condition on the basis results from prestudy assessments, have a
             total Child-Pugh score of 5 or 6 (mild hepatic impairment) or a score of between 7 and
             9, inclusive (moderate hepatic impairment)

          -  In study participants with mild or moderate hepatic impairment, concomitant therapy to
             treat underlying disease states or medical conditions related to hepatic insufficiency
             are allowed

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Study participants with normal hepatic function who have a history of or current
             medical illness deemed clinically significant by the investigator, use of any
             prescription or nonprescription medication, except for acetaminophen, oral
             contraceptives and hormonal replacement therapy within 14 days before the study drug
             administration, and have a positive test for drugs of abuse before study drug
             administration

          -  Study participants with mild or moderate hepatic impairment who have a positive test
             for drugs of abuse, have severe ascites or pleural effusion (accumulation of fluid in
             the abdomen and lungs, respectively), have a score of 3 or 4 for hepatic
             encephalopathy

          -  have acute exacerbation (worsening) of liver disease, as indicated by worsening
             clinical signs of hepatic impairment, or by an increase in total bilirubin (a liver
             function test) or prothrombin time (ie, the time it takes blood to clot) of more than
             50% in the 3 months prior to study entry
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L. C. Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Johnson &amp; Johnson Pharmaceutical Research &amp; Development, L.L.C.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Orlando</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Knoxville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://filehosting.pharmacm.com/DownloadService.ashx?client=CTR_JNJ_6051&amp;studyid=859&amp;filename=CR017227_CSR.pdf</url>
    <description>An Open-label Study to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetics of a Single Oral Dose of 300 mg JNJ-28431754 (Canagliflozin) in Subjects With Various Degrees of Impaired Hepatic Function Compared With Subjects With Normal Hepatic Function</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 19, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 19, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 23, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 27, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 27, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 29, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Canagliflozin</keyword>
  <keyword>JNJ-28431754</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatic impairment</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetic</keyword>
  <keyword>Normal hepatic function</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatic Insufficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Canagliflozin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

