<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01189955</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>harmonic total thyroidectomy</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01189955</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>the Use of Harmonic Scalpel Versus Knot Tying for Total Thyroidectomy</brief_title>
  <acronym>HS</acronym>
  <official_title>The Use of Harmonic Scalpel Versus Knot Tying for Total Thyroidectomy: A Prospective Randomized Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mansoura University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mansoura University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Consecutive patients treated for thyroid enlargement at our institution were evaluated for
      inclusion. Participants were randomly allocated to receive total thyroidectomy using harmonic
      scalpel HS or using ligature conventional thyroidectomy CT Follow-up visits were after 1
      week, 1 month, and 6 months, Study variables included operative time, length of incision,
      operative bleeding, postoperative drainage, hospital stay and complication.

      one hundred and thirty patients with thyroid enlargement were randomized and completed the
      study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients and method: Consecutive patients treated for thyroid enlargement at our institution
      were evaluated for inclusion. Participants were randomly allocated to receive total
      thyroidectomy using harmonic scalpel HS or using ligature conventional thyroidectomy CT
      Follow-up visits were after 1 week, 1 month, and 6 months, Study variables included operative
      time, length of incision, operative bleeding, postoperative drainage, hospital stay and
      complication.Preoperative preparation was performed for patients with thyrotoxicosis by
      antithyroid drug, and they were all euthyroid at the time of surgery. The routine
      pre-operative workup included measurement of thyroid-stimulating hormone and thyroid hormones
      (T3 and T4), as well as plasma levels of total calcium. In addition, a pre-operative
      laryngoscopy was performed.

      A prophylactic antibiotic in the form of a third-generation cephalosporin was administered 2
      hours before the operation. The operation was performed with the patient in the supine
      position under general anesthesia with endotracheal intubation. A Kocher incision, was made
      at the lower neck crease two finger above suprasternal notch.

      In the HS group, using the new harmonic scalpel device Focus (Ethicon Endo Surgery,
      Cincinnati, OH, USA) was used for cutting and coagulation . For closure of and division of
      superior and inferior arteries and veins we set the instrument at a power 2 i.e. more
      coagulation. And when smaller vessels like capsule veins we set it to the level 5 i.e. more
      cutting The superior artery and vein was divided close to the gland to avoid damage to
      superior laryngeal nerve. And control of any bleeding from the bed using the active blade of
      harmonic. Finally we insert drain.

      In the conventional group, mono- and bipolar coagulation, as well as ligatures, were allowed.

      In both groups, the Intra-operative bleeding was estimated by weighing the gauzes before and
      after use. Furthermore, blood from suction (when used) was also recorded. Operation time was
      recorded.

      Patients were discharged 24 hours after the procedure. Oral antibiotic coverage was
      recommended after discharge. Plasma levels of total calcium were measured on the first
      post-operative day. The need for oral substitution with calcium and/or vitamin D analogues
      during hospital stay and at patient discharge was recorded together with complications.

      Follow-up was performed on postoperative day 7, and then at 1 month, 3 months, and 6 months.
      . Patients were also seen at our clinic if they developed symptoms between follow-up visits.
      At follow-up, serum thyroid hormone concentrations and serum levels of total calcium were
      measured, and complications recorded. Postoperative laryngoscopy was performed within 4 weeks
      after surgery in all patients to evaluate vocal cord function.

      All assessments were conducted by investigators who were blinded to the experimental
      condition. The primary endpoint was operative time and secondary end points were operative
      bleeding, postoperative drainage, costs and complications.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>operative time</measure>
    <time_frame>3 hours</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>operative bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days postoperative</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>complications</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>costs</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">130</enrollment>
  <condition>Thyroid Swelling</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HS total thyroidectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the HS group, using the new harmonic scalpel device Focus (Ethicon Endo Surgery, Cincinnati, OH, USA) was used for cutting and coagulation . For closure of and division of superior and inferior arteries and veins we set the instrument at a power 2 i.e. more coagulation. And when smaller vessels like capsule veins we set it to the level 5 i.e. more cutting The superior artery and vein was divided close to the gland to avoid damage to superior laryngeal nerve. And control of any bleeding from the bed using the active blade of harmonic. Finally we insert drain.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>conventional total thyroidectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A prophylactic antibiotic in the form of a third-generation cephalosporin was administered 2 hours before the operation. The operation was performed with the patient in the supine position under general anesthesia with endotracheal intubation. A Kocher incision, was made at the lower neck crease two finger above suprasternal notch. In the conventional group, mono- and bipolar coagulation, as well as ligatures, were allowed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HS total thyroidectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>In the HS group, using the new harmonic scalpel device Focus (Ethicon Endo Surgery, Cincinnati, OH, USA) was used for cutting and coagulation . For closure of and division of superior and inferior arteries and veins we set the instrument at a power 2 i.e. more coagulation. And when smaller vessels like capsule veins we set it to the level 5 i.e. more cutting The superior artery and vein was divided close to the gland to avoid damage to superior laryngeal nerve. And control of any bleeding from the bed using the active blade of harmonic. Finally we insert drain.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HS total thyroidectomy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Group 1</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>conventional total thyroidectomy</intervention_name>
    <description>A prophylactic antibiotic in the form of a third-generation cephalosporin was administered 2 hours before the operation. The operation was performed with the patient in the supine position under general anesthesia with endotracheal intubation. A Kocher incision, was made at the lower neck crease two finger above suprasternal notch. In the conventional group, mono- and bipolar coagulation, as well as ligatures, were allowed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>conventional total thyroidectomy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Group 11</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Consecutive patients treated for thyroid enlargement

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients with one lobe pathology who need hemithyroidectomy, malignant thyroid
             previous neck operation, or a history of neck irradiation.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ayman El Nakeeb, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mansoura university, mansoura, Egypt</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ayman El Nakeeb</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mansoura, Egypt</city>
        <zip>335111</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mans.eun.eg/</url>
    <description>mansoura university</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hallgrimsson P, Lovén L, Westerdahl J, Bergenfelz A. Use of the harmonic scalpel versus conventional haemostatic techniques in patients with Grave disease undergoing total thyroidectomy: a prospective randomised controlled trial. Langenbecks Arch Surg. 2008 Sep;393(5):675-80. doi: 10.1007/s00423-008-0361-z. Epub 2008 Aug 2.</citation>
    <PMID>18677509</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Siperstein AE, Berber E, Morkoyun E. The use of the harmonic scalpel vs conventional knot tying for vessel ligation in thyroid surgery. Arch Surg. 2002 Feb;137(2):137-42.</citation>
    <PMID>11822946</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 25, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 26, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 27, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 26, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 26, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 27, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Mansoura University</name_title>
    <organization>Mansoura University</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>thyroidectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>harmonic</keyword>
  <keyword>RLN</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

