<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02328872</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Exec-PP-12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02328872</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Compass - Randomised Controlled Trial of Primary HPV Testing for Cervical Screening in Australia</brief_title>
  <acronym>Compass</acronym>
  <official_title>Compass - Randomized Controlled Trial of 5-yearly Cervical Screening With Primary HPV Testing Versus Cervical Screening With 2.5-yearly Liquid Based Cytology Testing, in HPV-Unvaccinated and HPV-Vaccinated Women in Australia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Victorian Cytology Service</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cancer Council New South Wales</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Victorian Cytology Service</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Compass is a randomised controlled trial of primary HPV testing for cervical cancer screening
      in Australia. A pilot study involving 5,000 women was carried out in 2013-2014. The trial
      will involve recruiting 121,000 women from primary health clinics. Women aged 25-69,
      attending for cervical screening or for routine follow-up will be invited to participate in
      the 2-arm trial. A liquid-based cytology (LBC) sample will be taken from consenting women and
      sent to VCS Pathology. Women will be randomised in a 1:2 parallel group allocation to LBC and
      HPV arms using randomisation with the minimisation procedure, with stratification by birth
      cohort according to whether offered HPV vaccination in Australia's national publicly-funded
      HPV vaccination program (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980). In the LBC
      (active control) arm, women will undergo 2.5 yearly image read cytology screening with reflex
      HPV triage testing for low grade cytology. In the HPV (intervention) arm women will undergo 5
      yearly HPV screening with partial genotyping enabling separate identification of HPV16 and
      HPV18 and referral of this group for diagnostic evaluation, and secondary randomisation of
      &quot;intermediate risk&quot; women testing positive for oncogenic HPV (but not HPV 16 or 18) to either
      image read LBC screening or dual-stained (DS) cytology testing with p16/Ki67. The laboratory
      reports issued to practitioners will specify the recommended management for women, according
      to study arm and test results.Participating women will be flagged on the Victorian Cervical
      Cytology Registry (VCCR) and clinical outcomes will be tracked via the VCCR. Data linkage
      between the VCCR and the National HPV Vaccination Program Register will be performed in order
      to integrate vaccination and screening histories for trial participants. Participants will be
      followed for an anticipated 5 years from the time of recruitment and the primary outcome is
      based on the total cumulative detection of CIN3+ after exit testing at 5 years.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Compass is a randomised controlled trial of primary HPV testing for cervical cancer screening
      versus cytology screening in Australia. A pilot study involving 5,000 women was carried out
      in 2013-2014. The main trial will involve recruiting 121,000 women from primary health
      clinics. Women aged 25-69, attending for cervical screening or for routine follow-up will be
      invited to participate in the 2-arm trial. A liquid-based cytology (LBC) sample will be taken
      from consenting women and sent to VCS Pathology. On receipt of a woman's first Compass sample
      at VCS Pathology she will be randomised in a 1:2 parallel group allocation to LBC and HPV
      arms using randomisation with the minimisation procedure, with stratification by birth cohort
      according to whether offered HPV vaccination in Australia's national publicly-funded HPV
      vaccination program (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and DOB &lt;1st July 1980).

      The screening and management algorithms for the two study arms will be as follows:

      Active control (LBC) Arm: 2.5 yearly image-read cytology screening with reflex HPV triage
      testing for low grade cytology.

      Intervention (HPV) Arm: 5 yearly HPV screening for potentially oncogenic types with partial
      genotyping enabling separate identification of HPV16 and HPV18 and referral of this group for
      diagnostic evaluation, and secondary randomisation of &quot;intermediate risk&quot; women testing
      positive for oncogenic HPV (but not HPV 16 or 18) to either image read LBC screening or
      dual-stained (DS) cytology testing with p16/Ki67.

      The laboratory reports issued to practitioners will specify the recommended management for
      women, according to study arm and test results.

      Participating women will be flagged on the Victorian Cervical Cytology Registry (VCCR) and
      invitation letters will be issued from the registry 3 months prior to the designated time for
      re-screening or follow-up. Clinical outcomes (screening test, colposcopy and histology
      results) will be tracked via the VCCR. Data linkage between the VCCR and the National HPV
      Vaccination Program Register will be performed in order to integrate vaccination and
      screening histories for trial participants. Participants will be followed for an anticipated
      5 years from the time of recruitment.

      Previous trials in unvaccinated populations have demonstrated increased detection of CIN2+ in
      HPV-screened (or co-tested) women vs. cytology-alone screened women in the baseline screening
      round, followed by decreased rates of incident CIN3+ in HPV-screened vs. Pap screened women
      thereafter. This potentially reflects (i) the increased detection of disease at the CIN2
      (treatment) threshold at baseline in HPV-screened women, leading to increased prevention of
      future CIN3 in the group of women treated for CIN2 at baseline; and (ii) the association,
      demonstrated in multiple cohort studies, between HPV positivity (especially for types 16/18)
      and the development of CIN3+ in the future. In the Compass trial, HPV-positive women without
      verified disease at baseline undergo increased surveillance until testing HPV negative.

      A total of 33,000 women in the birth cohorts not offered vaccination and 77,000 women in the
      cohorts offered vaccination, who are presenting for routine screening, will be recruited,
      along with additional women to bring the total number recruited to 121,000 (with the
      additional women representing those presenting for routine follow-up and those recruited for
      a safety monitoring sample). The sample size requirements for the trial are based on
      assessment of the cumulative proportion of CIN3+ (including CIN3 and invasive cervical
      cancer) in women who were screen-negative at baseline. A major impact of this study will be
      value of extended screening intervals in patients who are screen-negative at baseline.
      Logistically, it would be difficult to randomise patients after baseline screening and as
      such, the cumulative 5-year CIN3+ rates in baseline screen-negative patients may no longer be
      strictly comparative. However, this is a critical scientific question and so the trial is
      powered for this secondary outcome: the cumulative proportion of CIN3+ (including CIN3 and
      invasive cervical cancer) in screen-negative women, adjusted for censoring after CIN2+
      treatment.

      The primary outcome is based on the total cumulative detection of CIN3+. Because the primary
      outcome includes precancer, there remains a potential benefit from early detection in the
      baseline screening round, and although this benefit is not explicitly factored into the
      primary outcome it will be highlighted in the assessment of outcomes in baseline
      screen-negative women (i.e. in the analysis for Secondary Outcome 1). When assessing total
      cumulative rates of CIN3+, including both the baseline round and longitudinal follow-up in
      each arm, the follow-up duration is a critical determinant of the expected relative outcomes
      for CIN3+ when the two arms are compared. A second critical determinant is the disease
      ascertainment process at trial exit, and a consistent process using a sensitive screening
      test followed by equivalent referral and management processes must be performed in both arms.
      Therefore all women enrolled in Compass will be offered HPV exit testing at 5 years (since
      this will be the standard recommendation for cervical screening in Australia from December
      2017, the HPV exit test will also act as a routine cervical screening test).

      A Scientific Advisory Committee will advise the investigator team on issues related to
      protocol, operations and any other issues brought by the investigators to the Committee. An
      Independent Data Safety and Monitoring Committee (IDSMC) has been configured to monitor the
      safety of participants in the trial.

      Compass is sponsored by the Victorian Cytology Service (VCS), a government-funded health
      promotion charity. The VCS have received equipment and a funding contribution for the Compass
      trial from Roche Molecular Systems and Ventana Inc USA.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2023</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative CIN3+ (Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia Grade 3 or invasive cervical cancer) (ITT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Expected 5 year follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome will be cumulative CIN3+ at 5 years following a 5 year HPV exit testing round in both arms, in women randomised to the HPV arm vs. women randomised to the LBC arm, adjusted for censoring after CIN2+ treatment. For the primary outcome, intention to treat analysis will be performed with closed loop testing for non-inferiority and superiority if non-inferiority is declared. Assuming a total average CIN3+ rate in the LBC arm (across unvaccinated and vaccinated women) of 0.6%, and an absolute non-inferiority margin of 0.22%, the trial will have &gt;90% power with 97.5% confidence to detect non-inferiority for the HPV arm, allowing for a 10% non-compliance rate. This sample is adequately powered to detect this margin should the LBC rates be higher than the assumed 0.6%.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative CIN3+ in baseline screen-negative women (ITT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Expected 5 year follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative CIN3+ in women presenting for routine screening randomised to the HPV arm who were HPV-negative at baseline, vs. CIN3+ in those randomised to the LBC arm and who were LBC-negative at baseline, adjusted for censoring after CIN2+ treatment and stratified by recruitment group (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980). Intention to treat analysis will be performed with closed loop testing for non-inferiority and superiority if non-inferiority is declared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative CIN3+ in baseline screen-negative women (per protocol)</measure>
    <time_frame>Expected 5 year follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative CIN3+ in women presenting for routine screening randomised to the HPV arm who were HPV-negative at baseline, vs. CIN3+ in those randomised to the LBC arm and who were LBC-negative at baseline and at 2.5 years, adjusted for censoring after CIN2+ treatment and stratified by recruitment group (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980). Per-protocol analysis will be performed in women screened and followed up within a defined tolerance period according to protocol recommendations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative CIN2+ in baseline screen-negative women (ITT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Expected 5 year follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>Cumulative CIN2+ in women randomised to the HPV arm who were HPV-negative at baseline, vs. CIN2+ in women who were randomised to the LBC arm and were LBC-negative at baseline, adjusted for censoring after CIN2+ treatment and stratified by recruitment group (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Baseline CIN2+ and CIN3+</measure>
    <time_frame>Following recruitment</time_frame>
    <description>Cross-sectional outcomes for CIN 2+ and CIN3+ detection in each arm, stratified by recruitment group (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CIN2+ in women randomised to HPV testing at baseline with other oncogenic HPV</measure>
    <time_frame>Expected 12-24 month follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>CIN2+ in women randomised to HPV testing at baseline who have other HPV (not 16/18), stratified by recruitment group (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CIN2+ and CIN3+ in women who have an abnormal test result at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Expected 5 year follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>CIN2+ and CIN3+ in women who have an abnormal test result at baseline, adjusted for censoring after CIN2+ treatment and stratified by recruitment group (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>CIN2+ and CIN3+ in women who were in follow-management for a previous abnormality at baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>Expected 5 year follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>CIN2+ and CIN3+ in women who were in follow-management for a previous abnormality at baseline, adjusted for censoring after CIN2+ treatment and stratified by recruitment group (date of birth &gt;=July 1st 1980 and &lt;1st July 1980).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">121000</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer of the Cervix</condition>
  <condition>Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention (HPV Arm)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Molecular testing for HPV with partial genotyping for types 16/18, with referral of the HPV16/18-positive group for diagnostic evaluation, and secondary randomisation of women testing positive for other oncogenic HPV infection (not 16/18), to either image-read cytology screening or dual-stained (DS) cytology testing with p16/Ki67 - the &quot;HPV arm&quot;. Screening performed 5 yearly.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control (LBC Arm)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Image-read liquid based cytology (LBC) screening with reflex HPV triage testing for low grade smears, the &quot;LBC arm.&quot; Screening performed 2.5 yearly.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Molecular testing for HPV</intervention_name>
    <description>Molecular testing for HPV with a test allowing partial genotyping for separate identification of types 16/18 from cervical samples. The technology used in this trial will be approved by the Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA) Australia. It will identify the major HPV oncogenic genotypes in a pool and separately identify HPV 16 and 18. It will also satisfy performance criteria for relative sensitivity and specificity compared to Hybrid Capture 2 (HC2 ) as articulated by Meijer et al, 2009, Guidelines for human papillomavirus DNA test requirements for primary cervical cancer screening in women 30 years and older.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention (HPV Arm)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Liquid Based Cytology</intervention_name>
    <description>The liquid based cytology (LBC) used in this trial will be will be approved by the Therapeutic Goods Administration (TGA) Australia for LBC and appropriately validated and (TGA approved) to perform human papillomavirus testing from a cytology sample.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control (LBC Arm)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Australian female residents aged 25-69 years who are attending for routine cervical
             screening.

          -  Participants may have been previously enrolled in the Compass Pilot but must have been
             discharged to routine screening. Women may also be in follow-up management for a
             previous abnormality or unsatisfactory cytology.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous total hysterectomy (uterus and cervix).

          -  The presence of symptoms or signs for which cervical cancer must be excluded.

          -  Currently undergoing treatment for cervical cancer.

          -  Currently enrolled in the Compass Pilot Study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>69 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen Canfell, BE, D.Phil.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cancer Council New South Wales</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marion Saville, M.B., Ch.B</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Victorian Cytology Service</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karen Canfell, BE, D.Phil.</last_name>
    <phone>+61 2 9334 1726</phone>
    <email>karen.canfell@nswcc.org.au</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Chloe J Jennett, BSc,GC.PhMed</last_name>
    <phone>+61 2 9334 1418</phone>
    <email>chloe.jennett@nswcc.org.au</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Victorian Cytology Service</name>
      <address>
        <city>Carlton</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3053</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Marion Saville, M.B., Ch.B</last_name>
      <phone>+61 3 92500322</phone>
      <email>msaville@vcs.org.au</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Peter Di Sciascio</last_name>
      <phone>+61 92500356</phone>
      <email>pdiscias@vcs.org.au</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18973271</url>
    <description>Guidelines for human papillomavirus DNA test requirements for primary cervical cancer screening in women 30 years and older</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 18, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 24, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 31, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 3, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 3, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 5, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Victorian Cytology Service</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marion Saville</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>screening</keyword>
  <keyword>cervical screening</keyword>
  <keyword>Human Papillomavirus (HPV)</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer prevention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma in Situ</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

