<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02322619</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>054-12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02322619</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bio-equivalency Study of Moxifloxacin Tablets, 400 mg Under Fasting Conditions</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open Label, Balanced, Randomized, Two-treatment, Two-period, Two-sequence, Single Dose, Crossover, Oral Bioequivalence Study of Moxifloxacin Tablets, 400 mg of Dr. Reddy's Laboratories Limited, Comparing With Avelox® Tablets 400 mg of Bayer Healthcare Pharmaceuticals Inc. in Healthy, Adult Human Subjects Under Fasting Conditions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dr. Reddy's Laboratories Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dr. Reddy's Laboratories Limited</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      An open label, balanced, randomized, two-treatment, two-period, two-sequence, single dose,
      crossover, oral bioequivalence study in human subjects under fasting conditions.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      An open label, balanced, randomized, two-treatment, two-period, two-sequence, single dose,
      crossover, oral bioequivalence study of moxifloxacin tablets 400 mg of Dr. Reddy's
      Laboratories Limited, comparing with Avelox ® Tablets 400 mg of Bayer Healthcare
      Pharmaceuticals Inc. in healthy, adult, human subjects under fasting conditions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under curve</measure>
    <time_frame>0.167, 0.333, 0.500, 0.750, 1.000, 1.333, 1.667, 2.000, 2.333, 2.667, 3.000, 3.500, 4.000, 4.500, 5.000, 6.000, 8.000, 10.000, 12.000, 16.000, 24.000, 36.000 and 48.000 post-dose</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">26</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Moxifloxacin Tablets 400 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Moxifloxacin Tablets 400 mg of Dr. Reddy's Laboratories Limited</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Avelox Tablets 400 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Avelox® Tablets 400 mg of Bayer Healthcare Pharmaceuticals Inc.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Moxifloxacin Tablets 400 mg</intervention_name>
    <description>Moxifloxacin Tablets 400 mg of Dr. Reddy's Laboratories Limited</description>
    <arm_group_label>Moxifloxacin Tablets 400 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Avelox Tablets 400 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Avelox</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy adult human volunteers between 18 to 45 years of age (both inclusive) living
             in and around Ahmedabad city or western part of India.

          -  Having a Body Mass Index (BMI) between 18.5 to 24.9 (both inclusive), calculated as
             weight in kg / height in m2.

        Not having any significant diseases or clinically significant abnormal findings during
        screening, medical history, clinical examination, laboratory evaluations, 12- lead ECG and
        X-ray chest (postero-anterior view) recordings.

          -  Able to understand and comply with the study procedures, in the opinion of the
             investigator.

          -  Able to give voluntary written informed consent for participation in the trial.

          -  In case of female subjects:

               -  Surgically sterilized at least 6 months prior to study participation or

               -  If of child bearing potential is willing to use a suitable and effective double
                  barrier contraceptive method or intra uterine device during the study. and

               -  Pregnancy test must be negative.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known hypersensitivity or idiosyncratic reaction to Moxifloxacin, other Quinolones or
             any of the excipients or any related drug.

          -  History or presence of any disease or disorder known to influence bone metabolism,
             compromise the haemopoietic, renal, hepatic, endocrine, pulmonary, central nervous,
             cardiovascular, immunological, dermatological, gastrointestinal or any other body
             system.

          -  Ingestion of medicine [including vitamin, herbal supplements and any enzyme modifying
             drugs, including strong inhibitors of cytochrome P450 (CYP) enzymes and strong
             inducers of CYP enzymes] at any time within 14 days prior to check in of period-I. In
             any such case subject selection will be at the discretion of the Principal
             Investigator.

          -  If the QTc interval will be more than 450 ms on ECG measurement at the time of
             screening.

          -  Any history or presence of hypokalamia, QT prolongation including torsades de pointe.

          -  Any history or presence of asthma (including aspirin induced asthma) or nasal polyp or
             NSAIDs induced urticaria.

          -  A recent history of harmful use of alcohol(less than 2 years), i.e. alcohol
             consumption of more than 14 standard drinks per week for men and more than 7 standard
             drinks per week for women (A standard drink is defined as 360 ml of beer or 150 ml of
             wine or 45 ml of 40% distilled spirits, such as rum, whisky, brandy etc) or
             consumption of alcohol or alcoholic products within 48 hours prior to check in.

          -  Smokers, who smoke 10 or more than 10 cigarettes / day or inability to abstain from
             smoking during the study.

          -  The presence of clinically significant abnormal laboratory values during screening.

          -  Use of any recreational drugs or history of drug addiction or testing positive in pre
             study drug scans.

          -  History or presence of psychiatric disorders.

          -  A history of difficulty with donating blood.

          -  Donation of blood (1 unit or 350 mL) or receipt of an investigational medicinal
             product or participation in a drug research study within 90 days prior to receiving
             the first dose of study medicine.

        Note: In case the blood loss was less than or equal to 200 mL; subject may be enrolled 60
        days after blood donation or after the last sample of previous study

          -  A positive hepatitis screen including hepatitis B surface antigen and/or HCV
             antibodies.

          -  A positive test result for HIV antibody.

          -  Consumption of grape fruit or grape fruit products within 48 hours prior to check in.

          -  An unusual diet, for whatever reason (e.g. low-sodium), for four weeks prior to check
             in of Period I. In any such case subject selection will be at the discretion of the
             Principal Investigator.

          -  Nursing mothers (females).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dr. Shashikanth Sharma, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Lambda Therapeutic Research Ltd.,</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>December 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 18, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 18, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 23, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 18, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 18, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 23, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Moxifloxacin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fluoroquinolones</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Norgestimate, ethinyl estradiol drug combination</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

