<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02321813</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TUZ-QL-CRC-14</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>01GY1339</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02321813</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Direct Improvement of Quality of Life Using a Tailored Pathway With Quality of Life Diagnosis and Therapy: Randomised Trial in Colorectal Cancer Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>DIQOL</acronym>
  <official_title>Direct Improvement of Quality of Life Using a Tailored Pathway With Quality of Life Diagnosis and Therapy: Protocol of a Randomised Clinical Trial in Colorectal Cancer Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tumorzentrum Regensburg e.V.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>German Federal Ministry of Education and Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tumorzentrum Regensburg e.V.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to determine whether a quality of life pathway with defined
      diagnostic and therapeutic options improves quality of life in colorectal cancer patients
      during follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is a growing interest in using quality of life (QoL) data not only as relevant endpoint
      in clinical trials on cancer patients, but also in routine practice in order to improve
      patients` health during treatment. The investigators designed, implemented and evaluated an
      integrated quality of life diagnosis and therapy pathway (QoL pathway) for breast cancer
      patients (Klinkhammer-Schalke et al, 2008; 2012), guided by the UK Medical Research Council
      framework for developing and testing complex interventions. It could be demonstrated in a
      routine setting that breast cancer patients showed a benefit from tailored QoL diagnosis and
      therapy (Klinkhammer-Schalke et al, 2012).

      But there is also requirement for managing QoL deficits of patients with other cancers and to
      replicate findings of the previous trial. To achieve this aim, the QoL pathway has been
      modified for colorectal cancer patients. The Tumor Center Regensburg provides the
      infrastructure of the present project (quality circles, project groups).

      This is a two-arm randomised clinical trial with one intervention group and one control
      group. Patients` QoL is assessed with the EORTC QLQ-C30 and QLQ-CR29 at 0, 3, 6, 12, and 18
      months after surgery.

      In intervention group results of the QoL-measure are transferred to a QoL-profile including
      13 dimensions on scales of 0-100 (cutoff for &quot;diseased QoL &lt;50). Three experts with varying
      professional background use the individual patient`s QoL-profile and clinical and
      sociodemographic information in order to generate a QoL-report including therapy
      recommendation which is sent to the coordinating practitioner. Specific therapeutic options
      for the treatment of diseased QoL have been identified: pain therapy, psychotherapy, social
      support, nutrition counseling, stoma care, physiotherapy, fitness. To provide continuous
      medical education, quality circles for each therapy option have been founded. Coordinating
      practitioners receive a list with addresses of all quality circle members.

      In control group QoL is also measured but the coordinating practitioner neither receives a
      QoL-profile nor a QoL-report.

      The investigators expect that patients in the intervention group will experience a lower
      number of QoL-deficits (QoL &lt; 50 points) in the first year after surgery compared with
      patients in the control group
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>proportion of patients in both groups with diseased quality of life (&lt;50 points in at least one dimension)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year after the date of primary surgery for colorectal cancer</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>rates of patients with diseased quality of life in each dimension of the profile</measure>
    <time_frame>0 (0-2 days before clinical discharge), 3, 6, 12, and 18 months after primary surgery for colorectal cancer</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">220</enrollment>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <condition>Colorectal Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the quality of life pathway results of the quality of life (QoL) measure are transferred to a QoL-profile. Three experts with various professional background use the individual patient`s QoL-profile and clinical and sociodemographic information in order to generate a QoL-report including therapy recommendation which is sent to the coordinating practitioner. Specific therapeutic options for the treatment of diseased QoL have been identified: pain therapy, psychotherapy, social support, nutrition counseling, stoma care, physiotherapy, fitness. To provide continuous medical education, quality circles for each therapy option haven been founded. Coordinating practitioners receive a list with addresses of all quality circle members.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In control group QoL is also measured but the coordinating practitioner neither receives a QoL-profile nor a QoL-report.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>quality of life pathway</intervention_name>
    <description>Quality of life measurement, diagnosis and tailored therapy (pain therapy, psychotherapy, social support, nutrition, stoma care, physiotherapy, fitness)</description>
    <arm_group_label>intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo control</intervention_name>
    <description>Quality of life measurement</description>
    <arm_group_label>control group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  primary colorectal cancer

          -  operated in one of four participating certified cancer centres for colorectal cancer
             (Krankenhaus Barmherzige Brüder, Department of Surgery, Regensburg; Germany;
             Caritas-Krankenhaus St. Josef, Department of Surgery, Regensburg; Germany; Klinikum
             Neumarkt., Department of Surgery, Neumarkt; Germany; Klinikum St. Elisabeth Straubing,
             Department of Surgery, Straubing, Germany), documented in a population-based cancer
             registry (Tumor Center Regensburg e.V.)

          -  informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  coordinating practitioner not implemented

          -  patient from district outside the study region (rural districts Regensburg, Neumarkt,
             Straubing, Straubing-Bogen, Kelheim, Schwandorf)

          -  patient unable to fill out the questionnaire for physical, psychological or language
             reasons (including dementia)

          -  age under 18 years

          -  pregnancy

          -  QoL clinician unavailable

          -  refusal to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Monika Klinkhammer-Schalke, MD, Ass. Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Tumor Center Regensburg e.V., An-Institute of the University of Regensburg, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Koller, Ph.D., Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Center for Clinical Trials, University Regensburg, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Wilfried Lorenz, MD, Prof. Ɨ</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tumor Center Regensburg e.V., An-Institute of the University of Regensburg, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ferdinand Hofstädter, MD, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johannes Kepler University Linz, Medical Faculty, Austria</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeremy C Wyatt, MD, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Leeds Institute of Health Sciences, University of Leeds, UK</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tumor Center Regensburg e.V., An-Institute of the University of Regensburg</name>
      <address>
        <city>Regensburg</city>
        <state>Bavaria</state>
        <zip>93053</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klinkhammer-Schalke M, Koller M, Steinger B, Ehret C, Ernst B, Wyatt JC, Hofstädter F, Lorenz W; Regensburg QoL Study Group. Direct improvement of quality of life using a tailored quality of life diagnosis and therapy pathway: randomised trial in 200 women with breast cancer. Br J Cancer. 2012 Feb 28;106(5):826-38. doi: 10.1038/bjc.2012.4. Epub 2012 Feb 7.</citation>
    <PMID>22315052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klinkhammer-Schalke M, Koller M, Ehret C, Steinger B, Ernst B, Wyatt JC, Hofstädter F, Lorenz W; Regensburg QoL Study Group. Implementing a system of quality-of-life diagnosis and therapy for breast cancer patients: results of an exploratory trial as a prerequisite for a subsequent RCT. Br J Cancer. 2008 Aug 5;99(3):415-22. doi: 10.1038/sj.bjc.6604505.</citation>
    <PMID>18665187</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klinkhammer-Schalke M, Koller M, Wyatt JC, Steinger B, Ehret C, Ernst B, Hofstädter F, Lorenz W. Quality of life diagnosis and therapy as complex intervention for improvement of health in breast cancer patients: delineating the conceptual, methodological, and logistic requirements (modeling). Langenbecks Arch Surg. 2008 Jan;393(1):1-12. Epub 2007 Jul 28.</citation>
    <PMID>17661076</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 11, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 16, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 22, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tumorzentrum Regensburg e.V.</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ass. Prof. Dr. Monika Klinkhammer-Schalke</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PD Dr.med. Monika Klinkhammer-Schalke</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>quality of life</keyword>
  <keyword>colorectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>definitive RCT</keyword>
  <keyword>complex intervention</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

