<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01083134</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>98-4077B</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01083134</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Correlation of Heart Hemodynamic Status Between 320 Multidetector Computed Tomography, Echocardiography and Cardiac Catheterization in Patients With Coronary Artery Disease</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      With the advances in multidetector computed tomography (MDCT) technology, CT angiography
      (CTA) of the coronary arteries using 64-slice or dual-source CT systems has evolved into a
      robust, alternative, noninvasive imaging technique to rule out coronary artery disease (CAD).
      Reported sensitivities and specificities of coronary CTA can compete with those of catheter
      angiography.

      Because CT is the major source of ionizing radiation in medicine, dual isotope myocardial
      perfusion scintigraphy and coronary CTA 16-, 64-slice MDCT and DSCT scanners are associated
      with the highest amount of radiation dose. Recently, a new generation of MDCT machines with
      even more detector row (320) has become clinically available. The maximum detector width of
      16 cm enables the entire heart to be examined in a single rotation and within a single
      heartbeat and is expected to substantially reduce artifacts from breathing and body motion.
      Due to high volume coverage, 320-slice CT machines are able to perform a nonspiral, ECG-gated
      examination of the heart within a single breath-hold.

      The purpose of this study was to investigate the correlation of hemodynamic status of 320
      MDCT, echocardiography, and coronary catheterization in patients who suspected coronary
      artery disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>all cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>one year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>percentage of stenosis</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        According to Diamond and Forrester colleague, there are risks including age, gender,
        smoking, diabetes, and dyslipidemia for coronary artery disease.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Intermediate or high risk for coronary artery disease

          2. Healthy volunteers

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Unstable angina

          2. Acute myocardial infarction

          3. Active cancer status

          4. Renal failure(Creatinine &gt; 1.5 mg/dl)

          5. Contrast allergy history

          6. Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cheng Gung Memorial Hospital at Linkou</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tsang-Tang Hsieh, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+886 -3-3196200</phone>
      <phone_ext>3656</phone_ext>
      <email>tth3388@adm.cgmh.org.tw</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cheng Hung Lee, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Achenbach S, Ropers D, Kuettner A, Flohr T, Ohnesorge B, Bruder H, Theessen H, Karakaya M, Daniel WG, Bautz W, Kalender WA, Anders K. Contrast-enhanced coronary artery visualization by dual-source computed tomography--initial experience. Eur J Radiol. 2006 Mar;57(3):331-5. Epub 2006 Jan 19.</citation>
    <PMID>16426789</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoffmann U, Nagurney JT, Moselewski F, Pena A, Ferencik M, Chae CU, Cury RC, Butler J, Abbara S, Brown DF, Manini A, Nichols JH, Achenbach S, Brady TJ. Coronary multidetector computed tomography in the assessment of patients with acute chest pain. Circulation. 2006 Nov 21;114(21):2251-60. Epub 2006 Oct 30. Erratum in: Circulation. 2006 Dec 19;114(25):e651.</citation>
    <PMID>17075011</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson TR, Nikolaou K, Wintersperger BJ, Knez A, Boekstegers P, Reiser MF, Becker CR. ECG-gated 64-MDCT angiography in the differential diagnosis of acute chest pain. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2007 Jan;188(1):76-82.</citation>
    <PMID>17179348</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scheffel H, Alkadhi H, Plass A, Vachenauer R, Desbiolles L, Gaemperli O, Schepis T, Frauenfelder T, Schertler T, Husmann L, Grunenfelder J, Genoni M, Kaufmann PA, Marincek B, Leschka S. Accuracy of dual-source CT coronary angiography: First experience in a high pre-test probability population without heart rate control. Eur Radiol. 2006 Dec;16(12):2739-47. Epub 2006 Sep 19.</citation>
    <PMID>17031451</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Einstein AJ. Radiation risk from coronary artery disease imaging: how do different diagnostic tests compare? Heart. 2008 Dec;94(12):1519-21. doi: 10.1136/hrt.2007.135731.</citation>
    <PMID>19011135</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hausleiter J, Meyer T, Hadamitzky M, Huber E, Zankl M, Martinoff S, Kastrati A, Schömig A. Radiation dose estimates from cardiac multislice computed tomography in daily practice: impact of different scanning protocols on effective dose estimates. Circulation. 2006 Mar 14;113(10):1305-10. Epub 2006 Mar 6.</citation>
    <PMID>16520411</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yates SJ, Pike LC, Goldstone KE. Effect of multislice scanners on patient dose from routine CT examinations in East Anglia. Br J Radiol. 2004 Jun;77(918):472-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15151967</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hein PA, Romano VC, Lembcke A, May J, Rogalla P. Initial experience with a chest pain protocol using 320-slice volume MDCT. Eur Radiol. 2009 May;19(5):1148-55. doi: 10.1007/s00330-008-1255-8. Epub 2009 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>19137311</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Expert Panel on Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Cholesterol in Adults. Executive Summary of The Third Report of The National Cholesterol Education Program (NCEP) Expert Panel on Detection, Evaluation, And Treatment of High Blood Cholesterol In Adults (Adult Treatment Panel III). JAMA. 2001 May 16;285(19):2486-97.</citation>
    <PMID>11368702</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Diamond GA, Forrester JS. Analysis of probability as an aid in the clinical diagnosis of coronary-artery disease. N Engl J Med. 1979 Jun 14;300(24):1350-8.</citation>
    <PMID>440357</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 8, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 9, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 28, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 28, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 29, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CAD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

