<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01086566</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>08-0059</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>UR revax CMI</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01086566</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cellular and Humoral Immune Response to Primary and Secondary Immunization With Subvirion H5N1 Vaccines</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Safety and Cellular and Humoral Immune Response to Primary and Secondary Immunization With Subvirion H5N1 Vaccines Representing Different Clades</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to evaluate safety and compare how the body reacts to 2 different
      strengths of the Clade (specific type of H5N1 virus) 2 H5N1 flu vaccine when given as a
      single vaccination with a high dose (90 mcg) or low dose (15 mcg) to volunteers who have
      received at least 2 doses of the Clade 1 H5N1 vaccine, in a previous National Institute of
      Health study or who have never received a H5N1 vaccine (naïve). Previously vaccinated
      subjects (in studies 04-0063, 05-0090, 05-0127) will receive either 15 or 90 mcg of H5N1
      vaccine. Multiply boosted volunteers who participated study 05-0043 and received Clade 1 and
      3 vaccines, will receive the same dose (15mcg). Vaccine naïve subjects will receive 2 doses
      of vaccine (15 or 90 mcg) separated by 28 days. Blood samples will be collected. 115
      volunteers age 18-64 may participate in study related procedures for approximately 7 months.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In response to the steadily increasing number of reports of human infection with avian
      influenza A (H5N1) viruses, there is now a world-wide effort to develop and test potential
      candidate vaccines for this and other avian viruses with pandemic potential. The study will
      be conducted as a laboratory blinded assessment of the humoral and cellular immune response
      to A/Indonesia/5/05 vaccine in three populations: healthy adults who have previously received
      a clade 1 H5 vaccine in a Division of Microbiology and Infectious Diseases (DMID)-sponsored
      study; healthy adult recipients of prime-boost regimens representing two clades; and healthy
      adults with no previous H5 vaccination and who are not at risk for H5 exposures. Primed
      subjects are randomized to receive a single dose of either 15 mcg or 90 mcg of
      A/Indonesia/5/05 vaccine. Multiply boosted subjects are those who participated in study
      05-0043, and have previously received both A/HK/97 (Clade 3) and A/VN/04 (Clade 1) vaccines.
      Because only a small number of such subjects are available, they will not be randomized but
      will all receive the same dose of vaccine. Unprimed subjects are randomized to receive 2
      doses of 15 mcg or 90 mcg of A/Indonesia/5/05 vaccine separated by 28 days. In all groups,
      sera and peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMC) are obtained prior to and on days 3, 7,
      14, and 28 after each dose. Primed and multiply boosted subjects also have sera and PBMC
      obtained on day 56. All groups will make a final study visit at 6 months following the last
      dose of vaccine (day 180 for primed and boosted subjects and day 208 for unprimed subjects).
      Approximately 115 subjects between the ages of 18 and 64 will participate in this study. The
      primary objective is to determine the safety of administration of the A/Indonesia/05
      subvirion vaccine when administered to healthy, primed or unprimed adults. The secondary
      objective is to: determine the effects of priming with a clade 1 vaccine on antibody
      responses to revaccination with a clade 2 vaccine. The tertiary objectives are to determine
      the effects of priming on the repertoire and phenotypes of B and T cells generated in
      response to vaccination; to evaluate whether pre-existing immunity to seasonal influenza
      viruses impacts the specificity and magnitude of the cluster of differentiation marker (CD)4
      T cell response to H5 vaccination and to describe the kinetics of the cellualr immune
      response to subvirion H5N1 vaccinatin in primed and unprimed individuals. The primary
      endpoint is reactogenicity, adverse event (AE) and serious adverse event (SAE) information,
      solicited in-clinic and via memory aids. The secondary endpoints are: levels of HAI antibody
      recognizing A/Indonesia/05 (Clade 2), A/Vietnam/04 (Clade 1) and representative Clade 2
      subclade viruses, and levels of neutralizing antibody assessed by neutralization tests using
      the rgA/Indonesia/5/05 virus prior to and Days 3, 7, 14, and 28 after each vaccination. This
      study is linked to DMID protocols 04-063, 05-0090, 05-0043 and 05-0127.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reactogenicity: Occurrence of vaccine-associated unsolicited adverse events through Day 28 after the last vaccination</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 to Day 28 for primed and boosted subjects and Day 0 to Day 56 for unprimed subjects.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reactogenicity: Occurrence of vaccine-associated solicited local and systemic adverse events within 8 days post-vaccination (Day 0-7)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 8 days post-vaccination (Day 0-7)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reactogenicity: Occurrence of vaccine-associated unsolicited serious adverse events (SAEs) through the course of the study</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 0 through 6 months after last dose of vaccine (day 180 for primed and boosted subjects and day 208 for non-primed subjects)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of HAI antibody recognizing A/Indonesia/05 (Clade 2), A/Vietnam/04 (Clade 1) and representative Clade 2 subclade viruses prior to and Days 3, 7, 14, and 28 after each vaccination in primed and unprimed subjects.</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples taken prior to vaccination on Day 0, and approximately 3, 7, 14, and 28 days after each dose of vaccine in primed and unprimed subjects</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of neutralizing antibody assessed by neutralization tests using the rgA/Indonesia/5/05 virus prior to and Days 3, 7, 14, and 28 after each vaccination.</measure>
    <time_frame>Blood samples taken prior to vaccination on Day 0, and approximately 3, 7, 14, and 28 days after each dose of vaccine</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>5</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">95</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Multiple Boost Group-15 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>25 healthy adults who have previously received both Clade 1 and Clade 3 vaccines as a participant in study DMID 05-0043 will receive a single dose of 15 mcg of A/Indonesia/5/05.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Primed Group-15 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>30 healthy adults who have previously received H5N1 vaccine at any dose will receive a single dose of 15 mcg of A/Indonesia/5/05.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Unprimed Group-90 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>15 healthy adults with no previous receipt of H5N1 vaccine at any dose will receive 2 doses of 90 mcg of A/Indonesia/5/05 vaccine separated by 28 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Unprimed Group-15 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>15 healthy adults with no previous receipt of H5N1 vaccine at any dose will receive 2 doses of 15 mcg of A/Indonesia/5/05 vaccine separated by 28 days.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Primed Group-90 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>30 healthy adults who have previously received H5N1 vaccine at any dose will receive a single dose of 90 mcg of A/Indonesia/5/05.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Influenza Virus Vaccine, Monovalent A/H5N1 A/Indonesia/05/2005</intervention_name>
    <description>Inactivated monovalent subvirion H5N1 vaccine (HA of A/Indonesia/05/05) provided in unit-dose vials containing 0.5 mL of either 30 mcg/mL A/H5N1 HA or 180 mcg/mL A/H5N1 HA. Subjects will receive 1 of 2 dose levels of vaccine, 15 or 90 mcg.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Multiple Boost Group-15 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Primed Group-15 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Primed Group-90 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Unprimed Group-15 mcg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Unprimed Group-90 mcg</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  To participate in the primed group, the subject must have previously received at least
             2 doses via the intramuscular route of subvirion inactivated A/H5N1/VN/1203/04 (H5N1)
             vaccine as part of a Division of Microbiology and Infectious Diseases (DMID)-sponsored
             protocol.

          -  To participate in the multiple boost group, the subjects must have previously received
             both clade 1 and clade 3 vaccines as a participant in the DMID 05-0043 study.

          -  To participate in the unprimed group, the subject must not have received previous H5N1
             vaccine at any dose.

          -  The subject must be between the ages of 18 and 64 years, inclusive.

          -  Female subjects must fulfill one of the following: (i) not able to bear children
             because she has been surgically sterilized (tubal ligation or hysterectomy) for at
             least one year or is at least 1 year post-menopausal or (ii) agrees to practice
             effective methods of contraception that may include, but are not limited to
             abstinence, barrier methods, monogamous relationship with vasectomized partner, birth
             control pills, patches, hormonal shots or hormonal implants, NuvaRing and IUDs
             (intrauterine devices), from 30 days prior to study enrollment through 30 days
             following receipt of the last dose of vaccine.

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential must have a negative pregnancy test (urine
             or serum) within 24 hours prior each to vaccination.

          -  The subject must be in good health, as determined by: vital signs (heart rate &lt;100
             beats per minute (bpm); blood pressure: systolic greater than or equal to 90 mm Hg and
             less than or equal to 140 mm Hg; diastolic less than or equal to 90 mm Hg; oral
             temperature &lt;100.0 degrees Fahrenheit); medical history; and targeted physical
             examination, when necessary, based on medical history. Stable medical condition is
             defined as: no recent change in prescription medication, dose, or frequency of
             medication in the last 3 months and health outcomes of the specific disease are
             considered to be within acceptable limits in the last 6 months. Any change that is due
             to change of health care provider, insurance company, etc, or is done for financial
             reasons, as long as in the same class of medication, will not be considered a
             violation of the inclusion criterion. Any change to prescription medication due to
             improvement of a disease outcome will not be considered a violation of the inclusion
             criterion.

          -  The subject is able to understand and comply with the planned study procedures,
             including being available for all study visits.

          -  The subject has provided informed consent prior to any study procedures.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  The subject is allergic to eggs, egg products, chicken or egg proteins or other
             components of the vaccine (including gelatin, formaldehyde, octoxinol and thimerosal).

          -  The subject is a woman who is breastfeeding or intends to become pregnant during the
             study period between enrollment and 30 days following receipt of the last dose of
             vaccine.

          -  The subject is immunosuppressed as a result of an underlying illness or treatment with
             immunosuppressive or cytotoxic drugs, or use of anticancer chemotherapy or radiation
             therapy within the preceding 36 months.

          -  The subject has an active neoplastic disease (excluding non-melanoma skin cancer or
             prostate cancer that is stable in the absence of therapy) or a history of any
             hematological malignancy. For this criterion, &quot;active&quot; is defined as having received
             treatment within the past 5 years.

          -  The subject has long-term (&gt; 2 weeks) use of oral or parenteral steroids, or high-dose
             inhaled steroids (&gt;800 mcg/day of beclomethasone dipropionate or equivalent) within
             the preceding 6 months (nasal and topical steroids are allowed).

          -  The subject received immunoglobulin or another blood product within the 3 months prior
             to enrollment in this study.

          -  The subject has received an inactivated vaccine within the 2 weeks or a live vaccine
             within the 4 weeks prior to enrollment in this study or plans to receive another
             vaccine within the next 28 days (or 56 days for vaccine naïve recipients).

          -  The subject has an acute or chronic medical condition that, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would render vaccination unsafe or would interfere with the evaluation
             of responses. These conditions include, but are not limited to: solicited
             reactogenicity symptoms, history of significant renal impairment (dialysis and
             treatment for kidney disease, including diabetic and hypertensive kidney disease);
             subjects with diabetes mellitus, well-controlled with oral agents may enroll as long
             as there has been no dose adjustment with the past 6 months; insulin-dependent
             diabetes is excluded; cardiac insufficiency, if heart failure is present (New York
             Association Functional Class III or IV); an atherosclerotic event during the 6 months
             prior to enrollment (e.g., history of myocardial infarction, stroke, recanalization of
             femoral arteries or transient ischemic attack).

          -  The subject has a history of a severe reaction following receipt of an influenza virus
             vaccine.

          -  The subject has an acute illness or an oral temperature greater than 99.9 °F (37.7 °C)
             within 3 days prior to enrollment or vaccination. Subjects who had an acute illness
             that was treated symptoms resolved are eligible to enroll as long as treatment is
             completed and symptoms resolve &gt; 3 days prior to enrollment.

          -  The subject is currently participating or plans to participate in a study that
             involves an experimental agent (vaccine, drug, biologic, device, blood product, or
             medication) or has received an experimental agent within 1 month prior to enrollment
             in this study, or expects to receive another experimental agent during participation
             in this study, or intends to donate blood during the study period.

          -  The subject has any condition that would, in the opinion of the site investigator,
             place the subject at an unacceptable risk of injury or render the subject unable to
             meet the requirements of the protocol.

          -  The subject has a diagnosis of schizophrenia, bi-polar disease, or other severe
             (disabling) chronic psychiatric diagnosis.

          -  The subject has been hospitalized within the past 5 years prior to enrollment for
             psychiatric illness, history of suicide attempt or confinement for danger to self or
             others.

          -  The subject is receiving psychiatric drugs. Psychiatric drugs include, but are not
             limited to: aripiprazole, clozapine, ziprasidone, haloperidol, molindone, loxapine,
             thioridazine, thiothixene, pimozide, fluphenazine, risperidone, mesoridazine,
             quetiapine, trifluoperazine, trifluopromazine, chlorprothixene, chlorpromazine,
             perphenazine, olanzapine, carbamazepine, divalproex sodium, lithium carbonate or
             lithium citrate. Subjects who are receiving a single antidepressant drug and are
             stable for at least 3 months prior to enrollment without decompensation are allowed
             enrollment into the study.

          -  The subject has a history of alcohol or drug abuse in the 5 years prior to enrollment.

          -  The subject has a known human immunodeficiency virus, hepatitis B, or hepatitis C
             infection.

          -  The subject has a history of Guillain-Barré syndrome.

          -  The subject has any condition that the investigator believes may interfere with
             successful completion of the study.

          -  The subject has occupational exposure to live H5N1 viruses or has received an H5N1
             vaccine outside of the context of a DMID study. Subjects with a previous history of
             receipt of an H5N1 vaccine in an oil-in-water emulsion adjuvant are also excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester Medical Center - Strong Memorial Hospital - Infectious Diseases</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 11, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 11, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 15, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 31, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 31, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 1, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Influenza, H5N1, avian influenza, parent protocol</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Influenza in Birds</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

