<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01086540</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DAIT ASC01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01086540</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rituximab for Treatment of Systemic Sclerosis-Associated Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension (SSc-PAH)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Phase II Multicenter Trial of a Monoclonal Antibody to CD20 (Rituximab) for the Treatment of Systemic Sclerosis-Associated Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension (SSc-PAH)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Autoimmunity Centers of Excellence</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Systemic sclerosis-associated pulmonary arterial hypertension (SSc-PAH) is a serious,
      life-threatening manifestation of systemic sclerosis (SSc), an autoimmune disease of the
      connective tissue characterized by scarring (fibrosis) and atrophy of the skin, joints and
      tendons, skeletal muscles, and internal organs, and immunological disturbances. One-year
      survival for patients with SSc-PAH ranges from 50-81%. There is currently no cure for SSc-PAH
      and treatment is limited to vasodilator therapy used in all forms of PAH. In recent studies,
      immunotherapy was shown to be effective in treating SSc-interstitial lung disease, another
      serious, life-threatening manifestation of SSc. In addition, there are compelling
      pre-clinical data and anecdotal clinical reports that suggest modulation of the immune system
      may be an effective strategy for treating SSc-PAH. To test this approach, this trial will
      determine if rituximab, an immunotherapy, has a marked beneficial effect on clinical disease
      progression, with minimal toxicity, in patients with SSc-PAH when compared to placebo.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This prospective, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multi-center, randomized trial will
      evaluate the effect of rituximab on disease progression in subjects with SSc-PAH receiving
      concurrent stable-dose standard medical therapy with a prostanoid, endothelin receptor
      antagonist, and/or phosphodiesterase 5 (PDE-5) inhibitor. The study will focus on assessment
      of clinical response and safety measures longitudinally. In addition, the effects of
      treatment with rituximab on the underlying immune mechanisms associated with B-cell
      dysregulation and pathogenic autoantibody response in this disease will be investigated. 1000
      mg of rituximab or placebo will be administered as two IV infusions given two weeks apart.
      Clinical assessments and sample collection will occur at monthly visits through Week 48. If a
      participant has not recovered B cells by Week 48, B cell studies will be conducted quarterly
      until reconstitution is documented or for 2 years after initial treatment.

      This trial will include a sub-study, entitled &quot;Right Ventricular Response to Rituximab in
      Systemic Sclerosis-Associated Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension - A Magnetic Resonance Imaging
      Sub-study&quot; (RESTORE Sub-study). The objective of the RESTORE sub-study is to evaluate the
      therapeutic effect of rituximab on the right ventricle of patients with SSc-PAH. Changes in
      right ventricular end diastolic volume index (RVEDVI) and stroke volume (SV) determined by
      cardiac MRI will be used as surrogates of right ventricle function and prognosis. Enrollment
      for the RESTORE sub-study will parallel that of main trial. Twenty patients from each
      treatment arm, distributed among all participating sites, will be recruited for this
      sub-study. Each patient will be studied at baseline (i.e. prior to initiation of study drug)
      and after 24 weeks or at time of discontinuation. In addition to the data collection and
      testing specified in the main trial, participants in RESTORE will undergo comprehensive
      cardiac MRI evaluation. All main trial study inclusion and exclusion criteria apply, as well
      as additional exclusion criteria that pertain only to the RESTORE sub-study: 1) known
      hypersensitivity to Gadolinium; 2) inability to tolerate or cooperate with MRI; 3) morbid
      obesity; and 4) presence of metallic objects or pacemakers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pulmonary vascular resistance measured by right heart catheterization</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks after treatment initiation</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety and tolerability of rituximab therapy using the NCI-CTCAE</measure>
    <time_frame>Longitudinally over 48 weeks after treatment initiation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of time to clinical worsening</measure>
    <time_frame>Censored at 48 weeks after treatment initiation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Carbon Monoxide Diffusing Capacity (DLCO) and oxygen saturation at rest on room air</measure>
    <time_frame>Longitudinally over 48 weeks after treatment initiation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of new digital ulcers</measure>
    <time_frame>Longitudinally over 48 weeks after treatment initiation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of Raynaud phenomenon</measure>
    <time_frame>Longitudinally over 48 weeks after treatment initiation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Exercise capacity determined by 6 minute walking distance</measure>
    <time_frame>Longitudinally over 48 weeks after treatment initiation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of biomarkers as indicators of disease progression</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and longitudinally over 48 weeks after treatment initiation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in quality of life from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks and 48 weeks after treatment initiation</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">57</enrollment>
  <condition>Systemic Sclerosis-Associated PAH</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Rituximab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rituximab</intervention_name>
    <description>2 infusions, 1000 mg. each, 14 days apart</description>
    <arm_group_label>Rituximab</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>2 infusions 14 days apart</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has provided written informed consent.

          -  Subject must be between the ages of 18 and 75.

          -  Clinical diagnosis of systemic sclerosis (either limited or diffuse cutaneous
             disease).

          -  Diagnosis of SSc-PAH within the past 5 years, with a mean pulmonary arterial pressure
             of ≥ 25 mmHg at entry.

          -  Mean Pulmonary Vascular Resistance (PVR) of &gt; 3 Wood units.

          -  Screening 6-minute Walking Distance (6MWD) of at least 100 meters.

          -  New York Heart Association (NYHA) Functional Class II, III, or IV.

          -  Subject must be able to maintain O2 saturation ≥ 90% at rest (with or without oxygen).
             Oxygen use is permitted.

          -  Subject must be vaccinated with the pneumococcal vaccine at least one month prior to
             initiation of therapy, unless subject was vaccinated within 5 years of study entry.

          -  Subject must have been treated with background medical therapy for PAH (prostanoid,
             endothelin receptor antagonist, PDE-5 inhibitor, and/or guanylate cyclase stimulators)
             for a minimum of 8 weeks and have been on stable dose medical therapy for at least 4
             weeks prior to randomization with no expectation of change for 24 weeks after
             randomization.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Documented PAH for greater than 5 years at the time of randomization defined as:

               -  Measurement of a mean Pulmonary Artery Pressure (PAP) &gt; 25 mmHg by right heart
                  catheterization at least 5 years previously, OR

               -  Treatment with targeted background PAH therapy for &gt; 5 years.

          -  Pulmonary Capillary Wedge Pressure &gt; 15 mmHg or Left Ventricular End Diastolic
             Pressure &gt; 15 mmHg.

          -  Persistent hypotension with Systolic Blood Pressure (SBP) &lt; 90 mmHg.

          -  Treatment with cyclophosphamide within 4 weeks of randomization.

          -  Treatment with immunocompromising biologic agents within 4 weeks prior to treatment
             initiation or treatment with infliximab within 8 weeks prior to treatment initiation.

          -  If being treated with a non-biologic immunosuppressive or immunomodulating drug,
             changes in dosage within 4 weeks prior to randomization. Subjects taking prednisone or
             equivalent corticosteroid &gt; 10mg daily are excluded.

          -  Previous exposure to any lymphocyte or B cell depleting agent.

          -  PAH for any reason other than SSc.

          -  History of coronary artery disease, significant ventricular tachy-arrhythmia, stent
             placement, coronary artery bypass surgery, and/or myocardial infarction.

          -  Moderate or severe interstitial lung disease.

          -  Chronic infections.

          -  Positive serology for infection with hepatitis B or C.

          -  A deep space infection within the past 2 years.

          -  Evidence of active infection within 2 weeks of randomization

          -  Presence of a positive tuberculosis (TB) skin test (e.g., PPD test) or positive
             QuantiFERON®-TB blood test, an indeterminate QuantiFERON®-TB blood test, or latent
             tuberculosis (TB).

          -  Significant renal insufficiency.

          -  Active, untreated SSc renal crisis at the time of enrollment.

          -  Recent administration of a live vaccine (&lt; 8 weeks) or any other immunization within 4
             weeks of treatment.

          -  History of anaphylaxis or Immunoglobulin E (IgE) -mediated hypersensitivity to murine
             proteins or any component of rituximab.

          -  Pregnancy.

          -  Lactation.

          -  History of malignancy within the last 5 years, except for resected basal or squamous
             cell carcinoma, treated cervical dysplasia, or treated in situ cervical cancer Grade
             I.

          -  A woman of childbearing potential who is unwilling to use a medically acceptable form
             of birth control

          -  History of non-compliance with other medical therapies.

          -  History of alcohol or drug abuse within 1 year of randomization.

          -  Receipt of any investigational drug or device within 4 weeks before the Screening
             Visit, with the exception of investigational prostanoids, endothelin receptor
             antagonists, and PDE-5 inhibitors, and guanylate cyclase stimulators.

          -  Recipient of lung transplant.

          -  Laboratory parameters at the screening visit showing any of the following abnormal
             results: Transaminases &gt; 2x the upper limit of normal (ULN) and/or bilirubin &gt; 2x ULN;
             Absolute neutrophil count &lt; 1,500/mm3; Platelet count &lt; 100,000/mm3; Hemoglobin &lt; 9
             g/dL.

          -  Concurrent treatment in a clinical research study using a non-FDA approved agent with
             the exception of an open-label study/study extension of investigational prostanoids,
             endothelin receptor antagonists, and PDE-5 inhibitors, and guanylate cyclase
             stimulators, provided the open-label investigational drug will be available and dose
             will remain stable through the trial's primary outcome time point of 24 weeks after
             randomization in this study, ASC01 (NCT01086540).

          -  Any condition or treatment, which in the opinion of the investigator, places the
             subject at unacceptable risk as a participant in the trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Nicolls, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University Medical Service/VA Palo Alto Health Care System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David B. Badesch, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas A. Medsger, Jr., M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lorinda Chung, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robyn Domsic, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aryeh Fischer, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>National Jewish Health/University of Colorado School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roham Zamanian, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Palo Alto</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Health Sciences Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Iowa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iowa City</city>
        <state>Iowa</state>
        <zip>52242</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Johns Hopkins University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Boston University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02118</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Minnesota Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55455</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital for Special Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10021</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chapel Hill</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27599</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pittsburgh Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15261</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of South Carolina</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29425</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Southwestern</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas Houston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Utah</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84132</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.niaid.nih.gov/</url>
    <description>The National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.niaid.nih.gov/about/dait</url>
    <description>The Division of Allergy, Immunology, and Transplantation (DAIT)</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.autoimmunitycenters.org/mission.php</url>
    <description>Autoimmunity Centers of Excellence (ACE)</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 11, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 11, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 15, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Systemic Sclerosis-Associated Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension</keyword>
  <keyword>Autoimmune Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Systemic Scleroderma</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Familial Primary Pulmonary Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Scleroderma, Systemic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Scleroderma, Diffuse</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Rituximab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

