<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01087307</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>100063</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10-E-0063</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01087307</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sample Collection Registry for Quality Control of Biological and Environmental Specimens and Assay Development and Testing</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sample Collection Registry for Quality Control of Biological and Environmental Specimens and Assay Development and Testing</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences (NIEHS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Researchers are interested in developing a registry protocol to obtain biologic and
      environmental samples anonymously from adult volunteers for use in laboratory tests and
      studies. The samples will be used to determine if new tests are sufficiently valid and
      precise to be used in research studies and for quality control purposes.

      Objectives:

      - To provide a registry of samples for test development, validation, analysis, and quality
      control at the National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences.

      Eligibility:

      - Male and nonpregnant female volunteers at least 18 years of age.

      Design:

        -  Samples to be collected will include blood, urine, saliva, household dust, cheek cells,
           hair, nasal cells, stool, nail clippings, exhaled breath condensate, or sperm.

        -  Specimens may be collected during a one-time sample collection, or participants may be
           asked to provide specimens on several occasions over a specified period, not to exceed 1
           year.

        -  Eligible participants will be asked to come to the clinical research unit to have their
           blood drawn and any noninvasive samples retrieved. Prior to blood draw, researchers will
           administer a brief past 24-hour questionnaire for research purposes. Specimens will be
           collected using standard clinical protocols.

        -  Participants will receive monetary compensation for providing samples for this protocol.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      We propose a registry protocol for use in obtaining biologic and environmental samples
      anonymously from adult volunteers for use in laboratory assay evaluation. The samples will be
      used to determine if new tests are sufficiently valid and precise to be used in research
      studies and for quality control purposes. In studies involving the storage and analysis of
      laboratory specimens, it is essential to evaluate the performance of available assays and to
      actively assess the impact of storage and handling on the quality of samples and laboratory
      analyses. Specifically, it is essential to 1) demonstrate that an assay is sufficiently
      reproducible and stable over time such that differences in levels among individuals in the
      population can be detected; 2) evaluate assay reliability by sending blinded anonymous
      samples along with study samples to testing labs for quality control purposes; 3) test
      proposed laboratories or methods by using replicate samples from the population in order to
      choose the laboratory or method with the greater precision, and; 4) assess how sample
      collection, handling, and storage procedures affect measured levels of specific analytes to
      allow for informed decisions about whether to proceed with a specific analysis. Under this
      protocol, assays could include evaluation of immunologic parameters, genes and gene products,
      peptides, proteins, hormones, lipids, viability of cells, evaporation and dilution effects,
      chemical toxins and their metabolites, micronutrients, metals and more. For some samples,
      lymphocytes will be extracted for use in studies of lymphocytes and/or immortalized cells.
      Samples to be collected will include blood, urine, saliva, household dust, cheek cells, hair,
      nasal cells, stool, nail clippings, exhaled breath condensate, sperm samples, skin cells,
      and/or sputum. In addition, a pulmonary function test (PFT) may be conducted to collect lung
      function information. Since it is important to collect samples from the general population,
      this protocol covers collection of samples from non-pregnant adults (male and female, age
      18+). Specimens may be collected during a one-time sample collection, or participants may be
      asked to provide specimens on several occasions over a specified period, not to exceed one
      year.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 16, 2010</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To generate a pool of biological or environmental samples with which to develop and test specific laboratory assays.</measure>
    <time_frame>Two-three years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characterize vascular age related-other</measure>
    <time_frame>Two-three years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10000</enrollment>
  <condition>Biospecimen</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  ELIGIBILITY CRITERIA:

        All participants must be non-pregnant and 18 years of age or older. No children, fetuses,
        cognitively impaired persons, or prisoners will be enrolled.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stavros Garantziotis, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences (NIEHS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lisa B Barber, MEd</last_name>
    <phone>(919) 541-9847</phone>
    <email>murphylb@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Stavros Garantziotis, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(919) 541-9859</phone>
    <email>garantziotis@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NIEHS, Research Triangle Park</name>
      <address>
        <city>Research Triangle Park</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27709</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lisa Murphy</last_name>
      <phone>919-541-9839</phone>
      <email>murphylb@mail.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2010-E-0063.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 14, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 13, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 13, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 16, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Biospecimen</keyword>
  <keyword>Registry</keyword>
  <keyword>Assay Development</keyword>
  <keyword>Assay Validation</keyword>
  <keyword>Specimen Collection</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

