<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01082302</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CT 1022</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2007-005432-88</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01082302</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pharmacokinetic Study of Topically Applied Veregen 15% Compared With Oral Intake of Green Tea Beverage</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label, Single-Center Phase I (Phase IV/ USA) Study to Assess the Pharmacokinetic Profile of Topically Applied Veregen® 15% in Patients With External Genital and Perianal Warts Compared With Oral Intake of a Green Tea Beverage</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>MediGene</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Charité Research Organization GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>MediGene</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This open, monocentric study is designed to investigate plasma concentrations of certain
      catechins after topical application of Veregen 15% ointment to genital or perianal warts in
      comparison to catechin plasma concentrations after oral intake of a defined dose of green tea
      beverage. The study is intended to demonstrate that topical administration of Veregen 15%
      induces catechin plasma concentrations lower or equivalent to those that can be reached with
      normal consumption of green tea.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic profile of green tea catechins</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1/2 and Day 7/8</time_frame>
    <description>Cmax, tmax, t1/2, AUC(0-t), and AUC of EGCg, EGC, ECg, and EC</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">43</enrollment>
  <condition>Genital Warts</condition>
  <condition>Perianal Warts</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>oral intake of green tea beverage</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Healthy volunteers are asked to drink a defined amount of green tea beverage over 7 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Polyphenon E 15% ointment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>3 times daily application of Polyphenon E 15% ointment on genital and perianal warts over 7 days</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Polyphenon E (Veregen) 15% ointment</intervention_name>
    <description>3 times daily application on genital and perianal warts over 7 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Polyphenon E 15% ointment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Green Tea Beverage with defined catechin content</intervention_name>
    <description>3 times daily oral intake over 7 days</description>
    <arm_group_label>oral intake of green tea beverage</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        For both subject groups (treatment arms 1 + 2):

          1. Male and female subjects, 18 years of age or older at the time of enrollment. Subjects
             will be stratified by gender.

          2. Written informed consent.

          3. Ability to comply with the requirements of the study.

             For patients (treatment arm 1, additionally):

          4. Clinical diagnosis of external genital and perianal warts which can be located: in
             men: over the glans penis, foreskin, penis shaft, and scrotum; in women: on the vulva;
             in both gender: in the inguinal, perineal, and perianal areas.

          5. A total wart area of at least 100 mm² and a maximum of 2500 mm².

          6. For women of child-bearing potential: negative pregnancy test and willingness to use
             two effective methods of contraception throughout their study participation is
             mandatory (oral contraceptives, hormone containing intrauterine device, depot
             injection, hormone implant, or sterilization (for contraception) plus condom (for
             prevention of reinfection). For male patients and partners of male patients who are of
             childbearing potential: use of two methods of effective contraception during the
             treatment period is mandatory (oral contraceptives, hormone containing intrauterine
             device, depot injection, hormone implant, or sterilization (for contraception) plus
             condom (for prevention of reinfection).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        For both subject groups (treatment arms 1 + 2):

          1. Participation in an investigational trial within 30 days prior to enrollment and for
             the whole study duration.

          2. Any current uncontrolled infection.

          3. Current known acute or chronic infection with Hepatitis virus B or C.

          4. Known Human immunodeficiency virus infection.

          5. Subjects with known history of chronic (diabetes, hypertension, gastritis, etc.) or
             consuming diseases (cancer, multiple sclerosis, etc.), chronic inflammation, or liver
             or renal insufficiency.

          6. Any chronic or acute condition including the skin, susceptible, in the opinion of the
             investigator, of interfering with the evaluation of the drug effect.

          7. Laboratory data above the upper normal range.

          8. Systemic intake of virostatics within 30 days prior to enrollment and for the whole
             study duration, with the exception of acyclovir and the related drugs famciclovir and
             valaciclovir.

          9. Systemic intake of immunosuppressive or immuno-modulatory medication or vaccination
             within 30 days prior to enrollment and for the whole study duration.

         10. Organ allograft recipient.

         11. Medication intake, including over the counter products and dietary supplements such as
             iodine, fluoride, or vitamins, which would interfere with study results, except
             paracetamol and oral contraceptives, within one week before and during the study
             course. Subjects are not allowed to consume green, black or Oolong tea as well as red
             wine or any other beverages or foods containing green tea extract within three days
             before each blood sampling visit.

         12. For female patients: pregnancy or lactation.

         13. Blood transfusion within 30 days prior to enrollment.

         14. Subjects who are placed in an institution due to a judicial or official directive.

             For patients (treatment arm 1, additionally):

         15. Previous participation in a trial investigating sinecatechins in the treatment of
             external genital and perianal warts.

         16. Treatment of external genital warts within 30 days prior to enrollment and for the
             whole study duration.

         17. Current infection with Herpes genitalis or history of Herpes genitalis infection
             within the last 3 months prior to enrollment.

         18. Any current and/or recurrent pathologically relevant genital infections other than
             genital warts.

         19. Known allergies against any of the ingredients of the ointment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Frank Wagner, Md, PD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Charité Research Organisation, Berlin</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charité Research Organisation</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>D-10117</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 1, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 8, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 7, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 7, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 8, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Dr. Petra Weyrauch</name_title>
    <organization>MediGene</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>green tea extract</keyword>
  <keyword>Polyphenon E</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Warts</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Condylomata Acuminata</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

