<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01086696</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>100078</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10-C-0078</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01086696</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot Study of F-18 Paclitaxel (FPAC) PET for Evaluating Drug Delivery of Solid Tumors in Breast, Lung, Renal, and Adrenal Cancers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Pilot Study of F-18 Paclitaxel (FPAC) PET for Evaluating Drug Delivery of Solid Tumors in Breast, Lung, Renal, and Adrenal Cancers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Paclitaxel is a chemotherapy drug that is commonly used to treat different types of
           cancers. However, cancer tumors can become resistant to paclitaxel, and as a result they
           will fail to accumulate sufficient concentrations of paclitaxel to kill the cancer
           cells. Researchers are interested in studying whether tumors have become resistant to
           paclitaxel, but to do so it must be possible to see how much paclitaxel is absorbed by
           the tumor cells.

        -  18F-Fluoropaclitaxel (FPAC) is a form of paclitaxel that has been modified to be
           slightly radioactive in order to show up on positron emission tomography (PET) scans. By
           injecting a very small amount (much less that that used to treat tumors) of the
           radiolabeled drug into the body, researchers hope to use PET scans to evaluate the
           amount of the drug absorbed by solid tumors. Because FPAC is best used to study tumors
           located above the diaphragm, all subjects in the study will have tumors near or above
           the diaphragm.

      Objectives:

      - To determine the safety and effectiveness of FPAC as a radiological evaluation chemical.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals at least 18 years of age who have been diagnosed with breast, adrenal, renal,
      or lung cancer and have a tumor located someone in the body at least 1 centimeter above the
      diaphragm.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam, blood tests, and imaging studies as
           directed by the study researchers.

        -  Participants will receive a single dose of FPAC, followed by a series of PET scans.
           Regular scans will be performed for 3 hours after the dose of FPAC.

        -  Participants will also have a single dose of a more conventional radiotracer, followed
           by a series of PET scans. The results of the two sets of scans will be compared with
           information from previous imaging studies of participants' tumors.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Paclitaxel is a commonly used chemotherapeutic to which tumors can become resistant by
           failing to accumulate sufficient concentrations of the agent to be lethal to the cell.

        -  A noninvasive imaging test could determine the uptake of paclitaxel by tumors

        -  The ability to non-invasively predict chemotherapeutic uptake in solid tumors could help
           select patients likely to respond to treatment, estimate drug concentration within the
           tumor and possibly aid in the development improved of drug delivery systems and drug
           resistance evasion strategies.

        -  The PET department at the NIH developed an efficient procedure for fluorination of
           paclitaxel to [18F]-labeled paclitaxel (FPAC) and studied its biodistribution in rats
           and mice.

        -  Initial preclinical data shows the biodistribution of FPAC to be similar to that of
           paclitaxel. It is proposed that the uptake kinetics of FPAC in vivo using PET imaging
           will be representative of the uptake kinetics of paclitaxel

        -  First in human studies were performed by the PI (Kurdziel, KA) while at Virginia
           Commonwealth University, Richmond VA in three normal volunteers and three breast cancer
           patients with no adverse events. Human dosimetry estimates were obtained.

        -  PET/CT imaging with FPAC should permit quantitation of solid tumor uptake of the agent,
           which in turn should parallel paclitaxel solid tumor kinetics.

        -  The physiological distribution of the agent limits its use below the diaphragm. Thus,
           lung and breast cancers, which tend to be sensitive to taxanes, are the target tumors in
           this study. Adrenal and renal tumors, which tend to be insensitive to taxanes are being
           included as negative-control tumors.

      Primary Objectives:

        -  Determine if the FPAC uptake in tumors is different than the uptake in normal background
           tissues

        -  Determine safety of FPAC administration

      Eligibility:

        -  Subjects must be 18 years or older for inclusion in this study

        -  Subjects must have histologically proven breast, adrenal, renal or lung cancer with a
           lesion outside of the abdomen and pelvis greater than or equal to 1cm

        -  Subjects may not receive any other investigational agents 24 hours before or following
           FPAC injection.

        -  Subjects must have an ECOG performance status less than or equal to 2 (Karnofsky greater
           than or equal to 60%)

        -  Subjects must NOT be pregnant

        -  When applicable, a documented history of prior chemotherapy and radiation therapy and
           responses to those treatments must be available.

      Design:

      In this protocol, we plan to stratify enrollment into 2 groups, enrolling 15 subjects in each
      arm:

      subjects with tumor type historically sensitive to paclitaxel therapy (lung and breast
      cancers) and subjects with tumor generally not responsive to paclitaxel therapy (adrenal and
      renal). Subjects will undergo regional dynamic FPAC PET/CT followed by static whole body
      imaging. All participants will undergo FDG PET/CT (outside studies permitted if submitted in
      DICOM format) Follow-up FDG PET/CT may be performed. (following at least 1 cycle of therapy),
      if applicable. If the target lesion is surgically resected, the post-treatment scan will not
      be performed. Subject is then expected to progress to standard or investigational therapeutic
      intervention (not defined by this protocol). Data regarding clinical and or imaging response
      to therapy will be collected if available. If a previous biopsy specimen is available, IHC
      for known drug transporters will also be performed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 9, 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 11, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 20, 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Uptake of FPAC in tumors</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour post injection of FPAC</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety of FPAC</measure>
    <time_frame>1-3 days after FPAC injection</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Renal Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Adrenal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subjects with tumor types typically treatedwith taxanes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>subjects with tumor types typically treatedwith taxanes</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>FPAC</intervention_name>
    <description>Each subject will be administered 7 mCi of FPAC,over 10-20 seconds, followed by saline flush.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Subjects must have a history of histologically or cytologically confirmed breast,
             lung, adrenal or renal cancer with a tumor above the diaphragm greater than or equal
             to 1 cm

          -  Subjects must be 18 years or older for inclusion in this study.

          -  Subjects must sign a written informed consent document and in accordance with
             institutional guidelines.

          -  If female, the subject must be postmenopausal for a minimum of two years, be
             surgically sterile, or have a negative pregnancy test within the 24 hours prior to
             tracer injection

          -  There are no study related limitations regarding previous radiation or chemotherapy.

          -  Subjects must have an ECOG performance status less than or equal to 2 (Karnofsky
             greater than or equal to 60%)

          -  Subjects must have normal organ and marrow function as defined below:

          -  leukocytes greater than or equal to 3,000/mcL

          -  absolute neutrophil count greater than or equal to 1,500/mcL

          -  platelets greater than or equal to 100,000/mcL

          -  total bilirubin within less than or equal to 2.5 times institutional limits OR &lt; 3.0
             mg/dl in patients with Gilbert s syndrome

          -  AST(SGOT)/ALT(SGPT) less than or equal to 2.5 times the institutional upper limit of
             normal (&lt;5 times the ULN for patients with known hepatic metastases)

          -  When applicable, a documented history of prior chemotherapy and radiation therapy and
             responses to those treatments must be available.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Subjects may not receive any other investigational agents 24 hours prior to or
             following FPAC injection

          -  Subjects must NOT receive radiation therapy to the target lesion less than or equal to
             8 weeks prior to FPAC injection

          -  Subjects must NOT have had surgery near the target lesion less than or equal to 4
             weeks prior to FPAC injection

          -  Subjects with a history of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar
             chemical or biologic composition to F-18 fluoropaclitaxel (i.e. Taxol)

          -  Subjects with severe claustrophobia (not relieved by oral anxiolytics) or other
             condition that would make them unable to lie still for the duration of the study

          -  Subjects with uncontrolled intercurrent illness or psychiatric illness/social
             situations that would limit compliance with study requirements

          -  Subjects who are pregnant or lactating or who suspect they might be pregnant. Because
             there is an unknown but potential risk for adverse events in nursing infants secondary
             to treatment of the mother with FPAC, breastfeeding should be discontinued if the
             mother receives FPAC.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen A Kurdziel, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hsueh WA, Kesner AL, Gangloff A, Pegram MD, Beryt M, Czernin J, Phelps ME, Silverman DH. Predicting chemotherapy response to paclitaxel with 18F-Fluoropaclitaxel and PET. J Nucl Med. 2006 Dec;47(12):1995-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17138742</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Logan J. Graphical analysis of PET data applied to reversible and irreversible tracers. Nucl Med Biol. 2000 Oct;27(7):661-70.</citation>
    <PMID>11091109</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tang HZ. [The changes of monoamine metabolites in CSF of patients with cerebral stroke]. Zhonghua Shen Jing Jing Shen Ke Za Zhi. 1991 Jun;24(3):130-2, 186. Chinese.</citation>
    <PMID>1716195</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 11, 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 12, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 15, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>PET Imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>F-18 Paclitaxel (FPAC)</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Lung Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Renal and Adrenal Cancers</keyword>
  <keyword>Kidney Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Adrenal Cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Renal Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adrenal Gland Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Albumin-Bound Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Racepinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephryl borate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

