<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01080235</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CPS 485</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01080235</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Improving Quality of Care for Elderly Patients in the Educational Setting</brief_title>
  <acronym>MacyCoVE</acronym>
  <official_title>Improving Quality of Care for Elderly Patients in the Educational Setting: A Multicenter Exploratory Study of Quality Improvement</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>American Board of Internal Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Josiah Macy, Jr. Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>American Board of Internal Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-center exploratory study (each site got local IRB approval) of the impact of
      an educational toolkit combined with a practice-performance self-evaluation instrument (ABIM
      Care of the Vulnerable Elderly Practice Improvement Module) on trainee knowledge, skills, and
      attitudes about practice-based learning and improvement and systems-based practice in the
      care of elderly patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a longitudinal quasi-experimental study. Programs will be randomly assigned to either
      the comparison or intervention group, stratified based on program size, affiliation,
      geographic location, and presence of a geriatrics fellowship program.

      Faculty will be trained in use of the CoVE PIM and in the development and implementation of a
      quality improvement plan. Residents in the intervention group will perform the medical record
      audit portion of the CoVE PIM. Patient surveys will be distributed by the residency clinics.
      The goal will be to audit the medical records of patients who complete the patient survey.
      Residents in intervention groups will participate in completing the practice system survey as
      a group. Finally, the residents in the intervention group will use the data from the medical
      record audit, patient survey, and practice system survey, working with faculty, to develop a
      quality improvement project to improve care for their geriatric patients.

      Local medical record abstractors will be trained to perform a separate medical record audit
      of a random sample of the same patients identified by the residents for both the intervention
      and comparison groups. The abstractors will perform both a baseline and follow-up audit and
      will target the same patients who are still living from the baseline period. The follow-up
      audit will occur 12 months after completion of the initial PIM data collection phase, or
      approximately 18 months after the initiation of the study.

      Evaluation of study outcomes will occur on the program, resident, and patient level.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Practice Improvement Module (PIM) quality impact</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the impact of the Care of the Vulnerable Elderly (CoVE) Practice Improvement Module to improve the quality of care received by elderly patients in the residency ambulatory setting.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess resident and faculty satisfaction with the Care of the Vulnerable Elderly Practice Improvement Module.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess feasibility</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the feasibility of conducting surveys of elderly patients in the residency training setting.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess use of geriatric and quality improvement toolkit</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the use and impact of an educational toolkit for teaching geriatric quality of care. The analysis will specifically focus on what components of the toolkit are used by programs.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess effects of disparities on elder care</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the effects of health disparities on the care of elderly patients in a training setting.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess barriers in training setting</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess structural barriers to providing quality care for vulnerable elderly in diverse training settings</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Practice Improvement Module impact for knowledge, skills, and attitudes</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the impact of the Care of the Vulnerable Elderly Practice Improvement Module to improve the knowledge, skills, and attitudes of residents in the care of specific geriatric conditions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Practice Improvement Module impact vs traditional</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assess the impact of the Care of the Vulnerable Elderly Practice Improvement Module compared to a traditional educational intervention on residents' knowledge of and attitudes about practice-based learning and improvement, systems based practice, and geriatric care guidelines.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Elderly</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control. Forty-two residency programs randomly assigned and stratified according to size, affiliation, geographic location, and presence of geriatrics fellowship. Twenty-one in the control arm. This group will use PIM as a data collection tool during baseline and follow-up time (i.e. audit of 50-75 charts, survey from 50-75 patients, and one system survey). They will not see the summary results of the data collected; they will not be required to complete a quality improvement plan based on the summary data. Local researchers will collect the data. Individual trainees will not do data collection or audits. At both baseline and follow-up, trainees will complete pre and post test surveys of 1) geriatric and 2) quality improvement knowledge, skills, and attitudes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>There are 21 residency programs in intervention arm who will 1) use PIM as a data collection tool (local researchers will audit 50-75 charts, survey 50-75 patients, and complete one system survey); 2) Each trainee will audit of up to five patient charts; collect 5 patient surveys; and complete the system survey as a group; 3) Summary data from these data streams will be reviewed by group; then they will design and implement a quality improvement plan; 4) At follow-up, local researchers will re-audit same 50-75 charts, collect surveys from same 50-75 patients, and complete one system survey. At baseline and follow-up, trainees and faculty will complete surveys of geriatric and quality improvement knowledge, skills, and attitudes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ABIM Care of Vulnerable Elderly Practice Improvement Module</intervention_name>
    <description>The ABIM CoVE PIM is a practice-performance self-evaluation instrument. It is a web-based tool based on nationally recognized guidelines that uses chart abstraction, patient surveys, and a practice system survey in order to generate a performance report focused on a key aspects of care for vulnerable elderly.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Quality improvement module</other_name>
    <other_name>Practice improvemnet module</other_name>
    <other_name>Self-assesment in pratice based learning and improvement</other_name>
    <other_name>PIM in residency</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Geriatric and Quality Improvement toolkit</intervention_name>
    <description>A resource toolkit about geriatrics and quality improvement was given to both study arms.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>The Improvement Guide by Langley and Nolan</other_name>
    <other_name>Geriatrics at Your Fingertips</other_name>
    <other_name>ACOVE Physician Education Program DVD</other_name>
    <other_name>Online resources</other_name>
    <other_name>Membership to AGS teaching slides website</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All residents at a resident clinic site

          -  Preceptors that are selected by the Champion for a particular resident clinic site

          -  Patients age 65 years or older for whom any of the following measures would be
             appropriate: falls prevention, identifying urinary incontinence, screening for
             depression and cognitive impairment, and providing other preventive care.

          -  Patients who have been in the practice for at least one year

          -  Patients who are ambulatory

          -  Patients who have been seen at least once by the practice within the past 12 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients under age 65

          -  Patients who have a terminal illness

          -  Patients with a life expectancy of less than one-year
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eric S Holmboe, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>American Board of Internal Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.abim.org/</url>
    <description>ABIM website. Please go to &quot;Helpful Resources&quot; under &quot;Residency Training&quot; to see more information about the CoVE PIM.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 1, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 2, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 4, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Eric S. Holmboe, MD Senior Vice President for Quality Research and Academic Affairs</name_title>
    <organization>American Board of Internal Medicine</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>quality improvement</keyword>
  <keyword>geriatric care</keyword>
  <keyword>residency training</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

