<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02922439</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MD010368</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02922439</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Health Literacy Assessment and Intervention to Reduce Disparities: FLIGHT/VIDAS II</brief_title>
  <acronym>FV2</acronym>
  <official_title>Health Literacy Assessment and Intervention to Reduce Disparities: FLIGHT/VIDAS II</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nova Southeastern University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Miami</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nova Southeastern University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study will to be to evaluate the effects of a mobile intervention focused
      on improving the chronic disease self management skills of individuals with low health
      literacy. The intervention will provide information that culturally and linguistically
      tailored to participants' level of health literacy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Health literacy is a critically important skill that helps people to become active
      participants in their health care. The 2003 National Assessment of Adult Literacy showed that
      more than 75 million Americans had basic health literacy skills, indicating that as many as 1
      in 4 Americans can have difficulty understanding information about their healthcare. Persons
      in racial and ethnic minorities are likely to have even lower levels of health literacy.
      Twenty-four percent of blacks (9.5 million persons) and 41% of Hispanics (21 million persons)
      have below basic levels of health literacy. These persons have lower levels of health
      literacy and compelling evidence, including our own findings (see below), link race and
      ethnicity to disparities in health via health literacy. Members of minority groups and older
      adults are more frequently affected by chronic diseases such as cancer, high blood pressure,
      heart attack, stroke, diabetes, elevated cholesterol, asthma, hepatitis C, HIV infection,
      mental health disorders and many others. The twin burdens of chronic disease and low levels
      of health literacy thus fall disproportionately on those most in need - members of minorities
      and older adults, all of whom likely to experience one or more chronic conditions while often
      not having the health literacy skills to help them cope.

      Chronic disease self-management (CDSM) is a logical target for a general health literacy
      intervention. In an approach that cuts across specific diseases. CDSM targets problems and
      skills needed to cope with issues such as fatigue, pain, stress, depression, sleep
      disturbance and treatment adherence. Studies show that in-person CDSM classes improve
      patients' functioning and reduce healthcare utilization, but their availability is limited
      due to the lack of qualified personnel and cost. Similarly, while interventions have been
      developed to improve health literacy, they are difficult to scale to levels needed to meet
      the challenge of low health literacy (for more than 40 million persons) due to their cost.
      Effective interventions with the potential for wider dissemination at reasonable costs are
      urgently needed.

      In a previous study, the investigators showed that a computer-delivered tailored information
      intervention targeting health literacy that can deployed either as an information kiosk in a
      clinical office or on the Internet could be cost-effective in improving patients' health
      literacy and adherence. It is not clear, however, whether the same sort of
      computer-delivered, multimedia and interactive approach will be effective in improving CDSM
      skills in persons with low baseline levels of health literacy, and if it is, whether its
      effects will extend beyond health literacy to general health, self-efficacy, activation, and
      treatment adherence. In this follow-up study the investigators will evaluate this possibility
      by creating a personally relevant computer-delivered intervention targeting CDSM and health
      literacy among African-Americans, Hispanics, and white non-Hispanics:
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Literacy</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, six weeks, and three months.</time_frame>
    <description>Using the FLIGHT/VIDAS health literacy scale, change in health literacy will be assessed at baseline, 6 weeks and three months.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mood</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, six weeks, and three months.</time_frame>
    <description>Using the Center for Epidemiological Studies Depression scale, participant mood will be assessed at baseline, six weeks and three months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep quality</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, six weeks, and three months.</time_frame>
    <description>Using the Insomnia Severity Index, participant sleep quality will be assessed at six weeks and three months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Activattion</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, six weeks, and three months.</time_frame>
    <description>Using the Patient Activation Measure (scale), participant mood will be assessed at baseline, six weeks and three months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">520</enrollment>
  <condition>Fatigue</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <condition>Sleep Wake Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tailored Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals will interact with a chronic disease self-management application that provides information tailored to age, race, language (English or Spanish) and level of health literacy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Individuals will interact with a chronic disease self-management application that provides the same information as the experimental intervention but is not personally tailored to level of health literacy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tailored Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention will focus on improving the health literacy of low literacy individuals by providing chronic disease self-management information tailored to cultural and linguistic characteristics of participants.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tailored Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Control Intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>This intervention will provide information similar to that provided in the control condition, but will not utilize tailoring.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Have at least one chronic condition (cardiovascular disease,; arthritis; cancer; lung
             disease, osteoporosis, depression and others treated with at least one medication

          -  Health literacy at or below 8th grade level as assessed by screening measure

          -  Able to provide informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe cognitive disability that would preclude the ability to give informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raymond L Ownby, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nova Southeastern University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rosemary Davenport, RN</last_name>
    <phone>954-262-1804</phone>
    <email>rd667@nova.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Raymond L Ownby, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>954-262-1481</phone>
    <email>ro71@nova.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.flightvidas.org</url>
    <description>Central study website including links to presentations and publications as well as most up-to-date information on study progress.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ownby RL, Acevedo A, Waldrop-Valverde D, Jacobs RJ, Caballero J, Davenport R, Homs AM, Czaja SJ, Loewenstein D. Development and initial validation of a computer-administered health literacy assessment in Spanish and English: FLIGHT/VIDAS. Patient Relat Outcome Meas. 2013 Aug 19;4:21-35. doi: 10.2147/PROM.S48384. eCollection 2013.</citation>
    <PMID>23990736</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ownby RL, Acevedo A, Waldrop-Valverde D, Jacobs RJ, Caballero J. Abilities, skills and knowledge in measures of health literacy. Patient Educ Couns. 2014 May;95(2):211-7. doi: 10.1016/j.pec.2014.02.002. Epub 2014 Feb 16.</citation>
    <PMID>24637163</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ownby RL, Acevedo A, Jacobs RJ, Caballero J, Waldrop-Valverde D. Quality of life, health status, and health service utilization related to a new measure of health literacy: FLIGHT/VIDAS. Patient Educ Couns. 2014 Sep;96(3):404-10. doi: 10.1016/j.pec.2014.05.005. Epub 2014 May 14.</citation>
    <PMID>24856447</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 28, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 30, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 4, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 4, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>chronic disease</keyword>
  <keyword>multimorbidity</keyword>
  <keyword>chronic disease self-management</keyword>
  <keyword>tailored information</keyword>
  <keyword>mobile applications</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fatigue</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chronic Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Wake Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Parasomnias</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>At study conclusion a cleaned data set will be made available to interested researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

