<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02920814</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16/LO/0095</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02920814</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Time Intensive CBT for a Specific Phobia of Vomiting</brief_title>
  <official_title>Time Intensive Cognitive Behavioural Therapy for a Specific Phobia of Vomiting Using a Single Case Experimental Design</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>King's College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>South London and Maudsley NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>King's College London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aims of this project are to determine the effectiveness of a time intensive form of
      Cognitive Behavioural Therapy (CBT) for Specific Phobia of Vomiting (SPOV). Current research
      shows that this brief format can be effective in other specific phobias e.g. insects and
      animals. However, to date limited research has been conducted on the effectiveness of time
      intensive forms of CBT for SPOV. A single case experimental design will be used to analyse
      specific and idiosyncratic outcome measures in 6-8 cases of SPOV, referred to the Centre for
      Anxiety Disorders and Trauma (CADAT) for treatment. Specifically, the project will explore
      the effectiveness of CBT delivered in a time-intensive format and imagery rescripting
      elements of the treatment. This initial study will provide important information about which
      elements of CBT are most effective at reducing targeted symptoms and whether symptom
      reduction can be achieved in a shorter number of sessions. It represents a crucial step
      before this format of CBT can be more rigorously evaluated and compared to other treatment
      approaches by Randomised Controlled Trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Design A single case experimental design (ABACADA) will be used. A, B, C etc represents
      points of intervention and clinical contact with participants when standardised outcome
      measures will be administered by the treating clinician at each session. Phases A1, A2, A3
      represent time between contact during which participants will undertake daily monitoring of
      idiosyncratic symptoms on Visual Analogue Scales (VAS) e.g. degree of avoidance, degree of
      worry, degree of nausea etc, so change between phases across time can be measured.

      Participants will be randomly allocated to differing lengths of baseline phase (initial
      clinical assessment to first clinical session) with 4 potential arms (7, 10, 14, or 17 days).
      The first three clinical sessions (formulation, imagery rescripting and planning of intensive
      days) will take place weekly and last up to 1.5 hours. The two intensive days will last up to
      4 hours each and take place shortly after the planning session and within a few days of each
      other. Three additional follow up sessions will be offered within 10 days of the intensive
      days (2 within one week, and the final session one week after). Follow up data will be
      collected by phone or post 3, 6 and 12 months post intervention.

      Participants Participants will be recruited from consecutive referrals to CADAT for treatment
      of SPOV. Clients will have a diagnosis of SPOV as defined by the Diagnostic and Statistical
      Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM-V) as their main presenting problem. They will be drawn from
      the CADAT waiting list, and if necessary from Improving Access to Psychological Therapy
      (IAPT) services at Southwark, Lambeth and Lewisham. These cases will be picked up by and
      treated at CADAT by qualified clinicians.

      Participants are expected to be involved in the study for up to 8 weeks for the treatment
      phase, and 12 months for follow up data to be collected.

      Recruitment Consultant Psychiatrist for the team at the Centre for Anxiety Disorders and
      Trauma will identify potential participants from the waiting list at CADAT who meet the
      inclusion criteria to take part in the study. Potential participants will then be asked if
      they would like to participate at the initial clinical assessment. They will be provided with
      an information sheet and the opportunity to ask questions before making a decision and giving
      informed consent.

      Sample size It is estimated that 6-8 cases will be sufficient for a single case experimental
      design to demonstrate proof of concept. This is based on previous studies using a similar
      design.

      Procedure Patients identified from the CADAT waiting list and who meet the study criteria
      will be asked at assessment if they would like to participate in the study. Those who are
      interested in taking part will be given an information sheet, and the opportunity to ask
      questions before making a decision on their participation. They will then be asked to provide
      informed written consent by signing a consent form before continuing with the study
      procedure. Clinicians will remind all participants of their right to withdraw from the study
      at any time, which will not affect their care or right to treatment as usual. Participants
      will then receive the time intensive form of CBT for their SPOV.

      To ensure therapist adherence to the time intensive format of the treatment, a separate
      treatment protocol has been provided as part of Standard Operating Procedures. This protocol
      is as follows:

        -  Assessment and signing of consent form

        -  Session 1: Re-baseline &amp; Formulation (including a conversation about early memory of
           vomiting)

        -  Session 2: Imagery Rescripting of early memory of vomiting

        -  Session 3: Planning for Intensive Days

        -  Intensive Day 1

        -  Intensive Day 2

        -  3 short clinical follow up sessions

      Standardised outcome measures will be collected at baseline, intervention and follow up
      phases. Participants will also be asked to collect daily idiosyncratic measures in between
      the intervention phases. Participants will be randomly allocated to differing lengths of
      baseline to the time of the intervention with 4 potential arms (7 days, 10 days 14 days or 17
      days). This will be done using a simple spreadsheet by a Research Assistant at CADAT. The
      baseline discussion around the memory of vomiting, imagery re-scripting and treatment
      planning will consist of 1-1.5 hour sessions. Time intensive treatment will consist of two
      sessions over 2 days (4 hours each). Three additional follow up sessions will be
      administered, 2 within 1 week of the intensive days and a third 1 week after the second
      follow up session. The same standardised outcome measures will be collected at 3, 6 and 12
      months by phone or post.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2016</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific Phobia of Vomiting Inventory (SPOVI)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>A 14-item self-report measure that focuses on cognitive processes, safety seeking and avoidance behaviours (Veale et al, 2013). The total score ranges from 0 to 56. The scale has a two-factor structure, with one factor of 7 items characterized by avoidance (e.g. &quot;I have been trying to avoid or control any thoughts or images about vomiting&quot;) and a second factor of 7 items comprised of threat monitoring (e.g. &quot;I have been focused on whether I feel ill and could vomit rather than on my surroundings&quot;). Cronbach's α is .91.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Emetophobia Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>13-item self-report questionnaire that has good reliability and validity against a behavioural avoidance test (Boschen &amp; Riddel, unpublished observations). The range is 13-65. The EmetQ has 3 factors. Factor 1 had 6 items focused on avoidance of travel, movement, or locations. Factor II was comprised of 3 items, which centred on themes of dangerousness of exposure to vomit stimuli. Factor III consisted of 4 items that focus on avoidance of others who may vomit. Cronbach's α is 0.82.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>9-item measure of depressive symptoms, based on DSM-IV. The total score ranges from 0 to 27 and Cronbach's α was .86.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Generalised Anxiety Disorder (GAD7)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>7-item scale and is designed to measure the severity of symptoms of generalized anxiety disorder. The total score ranges from 0 to 21 and the Cronbach's α was 0.92.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Work and Social Adjustment Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>5 item scale that is designed to measure interference in life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>IAPT Employment Status Questions</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week</time_frame>
    <description>Questions relating to current employment status, Statutory Sick Pay and benefits.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8</enrollment>
  <condition>Specific Phobia of Vomiting</condition>
  <condition>Emetophobia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Time Intensive CBT for SPOV</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Time intensive CBT for SPOV involving 6 weekly sessions and 2 intensive days of 4 hours each (over 8 weeks in total).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cognitive Behavioural Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Time intensive CBT over 8 weeks, including 6 weekly sessions and two intensive days of 4 hours each.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Time Intensive CBT for SPOV</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adults aged 18 years or over with a diagnosis of SPOV as defined by DSM-5

          2. The individual describes the SPOV as their main psychological problem

          3. The individual is able to read materials written in English and answer written
             questions

          4. Individuals must have capacity to provide written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Involvement in active CBT (imagery rescripting and/or exposure) within 2 years or
             inactive CBT within 1 year previous to this study

          2. Individuals with a diagnosis of any other mental health disorder that required
             treatment in its own right

          3. Individuals currently taking anti-anxiolytic medication where the dose has not been
             stable over one month prior to entering the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alexandra Keyes, BSc MSc</last_name>
    <phone>02032282101</phone>
    <phone_ext>82101</phone_ext>
    <email>alexandra.keyes@kcl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>David Veale, FRCPsych, MPhil, BSc, MD</last_name>
    <phone>02032282101</phone>
    <phone_ext>82101</phone_ext>
    <email>david.veale@kcl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Anxiety Disorders and Trauma</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE5 8AZ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Veale, FRCPsych, MPhil, BSc, MD</last_name>
      <phone>02032282101</phone>
      <phone_ext>82101</phone_ext>
      <email>david.veale@kcl.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alicia Deale, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>02032282101</phone>
      <phone_ext>82101</phone_ext>
      <email>alicia.deale@slam.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 29, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 29, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 30, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 29, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 29, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 30, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vomiting</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Phobic Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

