<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02927093</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SMRU 1605</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02927093</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical and Developmental Outcomes of Babies Who Became Yellow in the First Month of Life</brief_title>
  <official_title>Neonatal, Clinical and Neurodevelopmental Outcome of Neonates Hospitalized for Neonatal Hyperbilirubinemia Reaching Exchange Transfusion Threshold in a Remote Setting Along the Thai-Myanmar Border</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The Shoklo Malaria Research Unit (SMRU) provides care to refugees and migrant populations
      along the Thai-Burma border since 1986. Services include antenatal and birthing care, with
      2,500 births per year and Special Care Baby Units (SCBU) set up in 2008; all medical records
      including clinical and laboratory data are archived. The treatment of neonatal jaundice is
      based on treatment thresholds adapted from the neonatal jaundice guidelines, published by the
      Royal College of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists, UK. Total serum bilirubin (SBR) is done at
      regular intervals to monitor neonatal hyperbilirubinemia (NH) evolution, following SMRU
      guidelines. The SCBU have been set up to provide intensive care for neonates in a resource
      constrained setting and don't have equipment for assisted ventilation other than oxygen
      therapy. Neonates presenting with high serum bilirubin levels and/or clinical signs of acute
      bilirubin encephalopathy (ABE) cannot receive exchange transfusion on site and have to be
      referred to the Thai general hospital one hour drive from the clinics; and, for those
      neonates surviving, there has not been a systematic follow-up of their growth and
      neurodevelopment.

      The study will consist of a matched case-control series and a retrospective review of SCBU
      charts of neonates with NH reaching exchange transfusion threshold. The SCBU database will be
      searched for neonates born at ≥ 28 weeks of gestation hospitalized for phototherapy between
      January 2009 and December 2014; charts will be manually researched to identify study
      participants which will be classified as NH reaching exchange transfusion threshold (cases)
      or as NH within moderate threshold (controls). Additionally neurological signs compatible
      with ABE will be searched in the clinical notes and coded as present/absent. Cases discharged
      alive from the SCBU will be traced back to evaluate their clinical and neurocognitive long
      term outcome. Each case will be matched with a moderate NH control from the same clinic, sex,
      gestational age and season of birth and hospitalized within the same month.

      The results of this study will help to improving the clinical care during the neonatal period
      and to developing a guideline for a better follow-up of children with NH reaching exchange
      transfusion threshold.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will consist of a matched case-control series and a retrospective review of SCBU
      charts of neonates with NH reaching exchange transfusion threshold.

      The SCBU database will be searched for neonates born at ≥ 28 weeks of gestation hospitalized
      for phototherapy between January 2009 and December 2014. The SCBU charts of these neonates
      will be manually researched to identify study participants which will be classified as NH
      reaching exchange transfusion threshold (cases) or as NH within moderate threshold
      (controls). Additionally neurological signs compatible with ABE that would likely be reported
      by the clinical staff will be searched in the clinical notes and coded as present/absent;
      those signs are: sleepiness, irritability, apnea, convulsions, abnormal position/tone, and
      abnormal cry. Those charts will be included into the cases.

      Cases discharged alive from the SCBU will be traced back to evaluate their clinical and
      neurocognitive long term outcome. Each case will be matched with a moderate NH control from
      the same clinic, sex, gestational age and season of birth and hospitalized within the same
      month.

      Both will be examined clinically and findings reported on a standardized forms, their visual
      function will be tested using the Cardiff acuity and contrast cards and their neurocognitive
      development will be assessed using the Griffiths Mental Development Scales-Extended revised.

      Maternal demographics and additional birth variables (i.e. birth asphyxia, type of delivery,
      breastfeeding) will be extracted from the antenatal care database and added to the selected
      cases; laboratory results (G6PD deficiency, ABO incompatibility, haematocrit) are stored in
      the SCBU database and will be retrieved. The general characteristics, the trajectory of SBR,
      and the neonatal outcome will be described.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 31, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 31, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual Function Scores</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The odds ratio of visual function scores between survivors of NH reaching exchange transfusion threshold and those with moderate NH</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurodevelopmental scores</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The odds ratio of neurodevelopmental scores between survivors of NH reaching exchange transfusion threshold and those with moderate NH</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical status</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The clinical status between survivors of NH reaching exchange transfusion threshold and those with moderate NH</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality rate</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The mortality rate among neonates with NH reaching exchange transfusion threshold</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of neonates with ABE</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of neonates with ABE among those with NH reaching exchange transfusion threshold</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of neonates with G6PD deficiency</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of neonates with G6PD deficiency present among neonates with NH reaching exchange transfusion threshold</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of neonates with ABO incompatibility</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of neonates with ABO incompatibility present among neonates with NH reaching exchange transfusion threshold</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of neonates with polycythaemia</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of neonates with polycythaemia present among neonates with NH reaching exchange transfusion threshold</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of neonates with birth trauma</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of neonates with birth trauma present among neonates with NH reaching exchange transfusion threshold</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of neonatal sepsis</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of neonatal sepsis present among neonates with NH reaching exchange transfusion threshold</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of neonates with prematurity</measure>
    <time_frame>8 years</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of neonates with prematurity present among neonates with NH reaching exchange transfusion threshold</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">78</enrollment>
  <condition>Neonatal Hyperbilirubinemia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Case</arm_group_label>
    <description>neonates with NH reaching exchange transfusion threshold</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <description>neonates with NH within moderate threshold of the phototherapy charts</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Liveborn, singleton, ≥28 weeks gestation, hospitalized at SMRU SCBU, from 1st January 2009
        to 31st December 2014 will be included.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Cases

        Liveborn, singleton, ≥28 weeks gestation, hospitalized at SMRU SCBU presenting one or more
        of the following criteria:

          -  Two consecutive SBR measures above the exchange transfusion threshold of the
             phototherapy charts for gestational age

          -  SBR levels rising &gt; 8.5 µmol/L per hour

          -  One or more neurological signs compatible with ABE in the absence of other known
             neurological condition and in the presence of confirmed NH

        Controls

        Liveborn singleton, ≥28 weeks gestation, hospitalized at SMRU SCBU presenting all of the
        following criteria:

          -  At least one SBR between the moderate and the severe threshold of the phototherapy
             charts for gestational age

          -  No SBR above the severe threshold at any time point

          -  No reported abnormal neurological signs (i.e. convulsions, abnormal cry or tone)

        Each case who has been discharged alive from the SCBU will be matched to one control from
        the same clinic, sex, gestational age, season of birth and hospitalized within the same
        month and the clinical and neurodevelopment of both children will be conducted once.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Stillborn

          -  Twins

          -  Liveborn &lt; 28 weeks gestation

          -  Major congenital malformation

          -  Liveborn singleton, ≥28 weeks gestation, hospitalized outside SMRU SCBU

          -  Liveborn singleton, ≥28 weeks gestation, hospitalized at SMRU SCBU without SBR done or
             with all SBR below the moderate threshold of the phototherapy charts for gestational
             age
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>28 Weeks</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 5, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 5, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 6, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hyperbilirubinemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperbilirubinemia, Neonatal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The data will be stored in the database and may be shared with other researchers in the future, however, data will be anonymous and the researchers will not know the participant identity.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

