<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02925156</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>200038</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01DK080763</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02925156</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Modeling the Epidemiologic Transition Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>METS</acronym>
  <official_title>Modeling the Epidemiologic Transition Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Loyola University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Loyola University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This project examines whether individuals' amount of activity energy expenditure (AEE) is
      related to adiposity and adiposity/diabetes-related hormones in a diverse sample of 2500, and
      to test the ecological hypothesis that a decline in levels of AEE is an important cause of
      the increases in obesity that are currently taking place in many societies.

      One goal is to use doubly labeled water and/or accelerometers to objectively measure activity
      energy expenditure in community samples from five adult populations across the spectrum of
      obesity risk. From each site, (i.e., Ghana, South Africa, Seychelles, Jamaica, and the US),
      500 black adults will be recruited. Among all participants, AEE will be measured using
      accelerometers and in a subset of 75 per site, AEE will also be measured by doubly labeled
      water.

      The doubly labeled water sample will be used to confirm site-specific concordance with the
      accelerometer measurements and to estimate population mean levels of AEE. Additionally, body
      composition, dietary intake, fasting glucose, insulin, adiponectin, leptin and ghrelin will
      be measured. The relationships between calories expended in activity and body composition,
      dietary intake, glucose, hormones and adipocytokines, both within and between each population
      using doubly labeled water and accelerometers will be examined. In this longitudinal study,
      weight will be measured at 12 and 24-months, and AEE by accelerometer will be assessed at
      enrollment and again at 2-years of follow-up; associations between change in AEE and change
      in weight will be estimated.

      The central purpose of this project is to test whether AEE or change in AEE can be identified
      as a contributory mechanism to population-wide weight gain and, if so, to quantify its
      importance. In addition, we seek to understand the interrelationships between the
      adipocytokines and the hormones ghrelin and insulin as well as AEE in the regulation of body
      weight across the continuum of body mass indices (BMI) represented by these five populations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Populations all over the world are experiencing rapid increases in the prevalence of obesity
      and diabetes. To date, the public health response to the emerging obesity epidemic has been
      almost totally ineffective. As a first line of response, professional bodies and government
      organizations have issued prevention guidelines, all of which include recommendations on
      levels of activity energy expenditure (AEE). However, even if fully implemented, it is not
      clear that the current recommendations on AEE would impact the trend in age-related weight
      gain. In fact, there is virtually no direct evidence that can be brought to bear on the
      question of whether the obesity epidemic has resulted primarily or even partially from
      society-wide declines in habitual physical activity (PA).

      To date, epidemiologic research on AEE has relied on very crude measurement tools—primarily
      questionnaires. These self-reported data capture only a small fraction of the total variance
      in activity and are potentially confounded when they focus on leisure-time PA. By contrast,
      direct measurement with doubly labeled water (DLW) provides a precise, unbiased estimate of
      all forms of non-resting energy expenditure. DLW has also been used to validate the new
      generation of accelerometers which are efficient measurement tools for larger studies.

      In this study, objective measurement tools will be used to examine the &quot;ecology of AEE&quot;. This
      study will take place in 5 countries spanning the range of the activity-obesity spectrum and
      will combine both within-population person-level and between-population ecological analyses.
      First, the study will examine whether an individual's amount or pattern of AEE is related to
      adiposity in a diverse sample of 2,500. Second, the study will evaluate whether a decline in
      levels of AEE is an important cause of the rapid increases in obesity that currently take
      place in many societies. As an exploratory aim we will examine the role of selected
      adipocytokines and the appetite hormone ghrelin.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in body weight index (BMI) between high and low activity energy expenditure (AEE) groups.</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Body mass index (BMI) measured in kg/m^2 will be compared between high and low activity energy expenditure (AEE) groups 24 months after baseline. AEE is initially measured in kilocalories per day (kcal/d) but will be dichotomized at its median value resulting in low and high AEE groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>5</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2506</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ghana</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants in the Ghana cohort are located at or near the the village of Nkwantakese which is approximately 20 kilometers outside of Kwame Nkrumah University of Science and Technology in Kumasi.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>South Africa</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants in the South Africa cohort are located at or near Khayelitsha, the 3rd largest township in South Africa, which is an adjacent town to the city of Cape Town. The population of Khayelitsha is about 500,000 people.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Seychelles</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants in the Seychelles cohort are located at or near The Republic of Seychelles, which is an archipelago with 81,000 inhabitants located approximately 1,500 km east of Kenya in the Indian Ocean and approximately 2,000 km north of the island of Mauritius.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Jamaica</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants in the Jamaica cohort are located at or near Spanish Town, Jamaica which is an urban area 25 km from the center of Kingston. The population of Spanish Town in 1991 was estimated at 92,000 people.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>United States</arm_group_label>
    <description>Participants in the United States cohort are located at or near Maywood, IL, which is an African-American working class community adjacent to the western border of Chicago, IL. The population of Maywood in 2010 was estimated at 24,090 people.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study is comprises a complex samples population based approach drawn from communities
        in 5 countries: Ghana, Seychelles, South Africa, Jamaica and the US. Approximately 500
        participants are enrolled per site for an unweighted total of 2500 participants.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Identify as African American or Black

          -  Age 18-50

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy, nursing, or planning to become pregnant

          -  Movement disorders or other disability that limits mobility
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amy Luke, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Loyola University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Loyola University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maywood</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60153</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zimmet P. The burden of type 2 diabetes: are we doing enough? Diabetes Metab. 2003 Sep;29(4 Pt 2):6S9-18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14502096</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scaglione R, Argano C, Di Chiara T, Licata G. Obesity and cardiovascular risk: the new public health problem of worldwide proportions. Expert Rev Cardiovasc Ther. 2004 Mar;2(2):203-12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15151469</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Popkin BM, Gordon-Larsen P. The nutrition transition: worldwide obesity dynamics and their determinants. Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord. 2004 Nov;28 Suppl 3:S2-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15543214</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kohn M, Booth M. The worldwide epidemic of obesity in adolescents. Adolesc Med. 2003 Feb;14(1):1-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12529186</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>James PT. Obesity: the worldwide epidemic. Clin Dermatol. 2004 Jul-Aug;22(4):276-80. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15475226</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pate RR, Pratt M, Blair SN, Haskell WL, Macera CA, Bouchard C, Buchner D, Ettinger W, Heath GW, King AC, et al. Physical activity and public health. A recommendation from the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and the American College of Sports Medicine. JAMA. 1995 Feb 1;273(5):402-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>7823386</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fletcher GF, Balady G, Blair SN, Blumenthal J, Caspersen C, Chaitman B, Epstein S, Sivarajan Froelicher ES, Froelicher VF, Pina IL, Pollock ML. Statement on exercise: benefits and recommendations for physical activity programs for all Americans. A statement for health professionals by the Committee on Exercise and Cardiac Rehabilitation of the Council on Clinical Cardiology, American Heart Association. Circulation. 1996 Aug 15;94(4):857-62.</citation>
    <PMID>8772712</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Physical activity and cardiovascular health. NIH Consensus Development Panel on Physical Activity and Cardiovascular Health. JAMA. 1996 Jul 17;276(3):241-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8667571</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morrow JR Jr, Jackson AW, Bazzarre TL, Milne D, Blair SN. A one-year follow-up to physical activity and health. A report of the Surgeon General. Am J Prev Med. 1999 Jul;17(1):24-30.</citation>
    <PMID>10429749</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trumbo P, Schlicker S, Yates AA, Poos M; Food and Nutrition Board of the Institute of Medicine, The National Academies. Dietary reference intakes for energy, carbohydrate, fiber, fat, fatty acids, cholesterol, protein and amino acids. J Am Diet Assoc. 2002 Nov;102(11):1621-30. Erratum in: J Am Diet Assoc. 2003 May;103(5):563.</citation>
    <PMID>12449285</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 3, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 4, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 5, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 24, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Loyola University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Amy Luke</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Activity Energy Expenditure</keyword>
  <keyword>Doubly Labeled Water</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical Activity</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Adiponectin</keyword>
  <keyword>Leptin</keyword>
  <keyword>Ghrelin</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>There is no plan to share data</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

