<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02921477</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>062016</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02921477</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study for the Use of TKIs for Treatment of Cognitive Decline Due to Degenerative Dementias</brief_title>
  <official_title>Open Label Study for the Use of Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitors for Treatment of Cognitive Decline Due to Degenerative Dementias</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Neurological Associates of West Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pfizer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Neurological Associates of West Los Angeles</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The present study is designed as an open label study of patients with mild cognitive
      impairment or dementia to evaluate longer term tolerability and potential efficacy of
      tyrosine kinase inhibitors. Baseline and outcome measures in this study utilize validated
      tests that are appropriate for repeated measures which are not affected by practice effects.
      Advantages of this study include the fact that the neuropsychological testing instruments and
      advanced MRI imaging protocols that have been in routine clinical deployment provide for a
      high degree of availability and reliability for diagnosis and for monitoring change of
      status. Quality assurance is tightly controlled. The study population is sufficiently broad
      and the conditions of interest are sufficiently prevalent so that recruitment of the
      projected numbers of subjects is not a limiting factor.

      For a Phase I trial there is a proposed 20 patient sample to determine the frequency of
      common side effects in the population that is being studied. Subjects will be administered
      the initial dose of bosutinib, with dosage progressively increased over the course of the
      study. The initial dose of bosutinib is 100 mg tablet, once per day. The dose will be
      increased as tolerated up to 300 mg per day.

      All subjects will be started at 100 mg/day and the dose will be increased by 100 mg each
      month if the lower dose is tolerated without significant side effects. That is to say, the
      subject will take 100 mg/day every day for the first month, 200 mg/day every day for the
      second month, and 300 mg/day every day for the third month and for the remainder of the
      study, provided that adverse reactions do not prohibit continuation at this dosage. The
      investigators will be using the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE)
      Version 4.0 to monitor, evaluate, and report adverse reactions on an ongoing basis. Stopping
      and dose reduction rules for reported adverse reactions have been taken from the package
      insert of bosutinib.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In order for a subject to be considered for this study, the following criterion is required:

      • Cognitive decline with mild cognitive impairment (Clinical Dementia Rating Stage 0.5)
      through moderate dementia (CDR Stages 1 and 2)

      All patients, according to routine best practices will have an evaluation including
      neurological interview and examination to screen for reversible causes of cognitive change
      such as depression, substance abuse, vitamin deficiency and systemic illness. All patients
      will have a Beck Depression scale and blood tests for B12 and thyroid hormone. Patients will
      have an EKG, in particular to screen for QT prolongation which is a relative
      counterindication for use of tyrosine kinase inhibitor therapy.

      According to the package insert for bosutinib, the investigators are proposing to use an age
      range and dosage route that is comparable and overlapping with routine application of this
      drug. In addition, the investigators are proposing dosage ranges that are substantially lower
      than usually recommended for treatment of leukemia.

      The QDRS scale will be given to all patients; a cut off score of 1.5 has been used qualify
      patients with a dementia score (CDR) of 0.5 (ref 19).

      All patients will have a lumbar puncture for ABeta 42 and Tau proteins for Alzheimer's
      Spectrum. This spinal fluid examination has been shown to be both sensitive and specific for
      Alzheimer's disease (ref 20). Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) tau levels are also elevated in alpha
      synucleinopathy and frontotemporal lobar degeneration (ref 21). The lumbar puncture is
      performed once at entry.

      All patients will have an advanced MRI of the brain to include volume measurement of the
      hippocampus (ref 22), arterial spin labeling (ASL) perfusion scan (ref 23) and MRS of
      prefrontal, precuneus, hippocampus and occipital lobe. Patients with cognitive decline have
      decreased perfusion in temporal parietal or frontal regions of the brain with ASL perfusion,
      or show characteristic change in MRS or volumetric evaluation compared to aged matched
      control subjects. MRI will also demonstrate if patients have tumors, hydrocephalus, subdural
      hematomas and other structural etiologies of cognitive decline.

      On entry, patients will have CDR stage of at least 0.5 and at least one abnormal imaging
      biomarker and none of the exclusion criteria below. Baseline, six months, twelve months,
      eighteen months and two year (completion) testing will include the Quick Dementia Rating
      System (QDRS) for staging and the following battery of tests:

        -  the Repeatable Battery for Assessment of Neuropsychological Status (RBANS),

        -  Standardized 25 foot timed gait test

        -  the Nine Hole Pegboard Test,

        -  Montreal Cognitive Assessment Test versions 1,2,3 (MOCA),

        -  Brain imaging will be repeated at one year and two years. CSF studies have demonstrated
           good sensitivity and specificity for mild cognitive impairment (MCI) and dementia of the
           Alzheimer's type (ref 5). MRI volumetrics, perfusion scans and magnetic resonance
           spectroscopy (MRS) have shown to be of excellent discriminating value among Alzheimer's
           dementia (AD), Parkinson's spectrum degeneration (PDD/DLB) and frontal temporal lobar
           degeneration (FTLD) subgroups and is responsive to change as patient's progress from MCI
           to dementia (ref 6).

      The rationale behind this criterion is supported by the importance that the subject is
      cognitively able to effectively speak, listen, and read in English, and has the cognitive
      capacity to give informed consent.

      All subjects will be started at 100 mg/day and the dose will be increased by 100 mg each
      month if the lower dose is tolerated without significant side effects. Adverse reactions will
      be scaled according to the CTCAE v.4. If the subject experiences severe adverse reactions at
      any dose, or if the subject requires dose reduction for toxicity from a dose of 100 mg/day,
      the subject will be removed from the study. If the subject experiences moderate adverse
      reactions at a dose &gt;100 mg/day, the dose will be reduced by 100 mg and maintained at the
      lower dose for 1 month. If the subject experiences moderate or severe adverse reactions at
      this lower dose, the subject will be removed from the study. After 1 month, the dose will
      again be increased by 100 mg. If the subject does not experience any adverse reactions at
      this elevated dose, he/she will resume with the original up-titration schedule (i.e. increase
      by 100 mg every month up to 300 mg/day). If the subject experiences moderate symptoms at this
      elevated dose, the dose will again be reduced by 100 mg and will be maintained at this lower
      dose as the maximally tolerated dose.

      The duration of treatment is 1 year. To minimize risk, subjects will be seen weekly for
      toxicity monitoring during the first month of treatment, and biweekly during the second month
      of treatment. On weeks when the subject is not in for a visit, subject status will be
      assessed on the basis of phone calls with the respective care taker. The care taker will be
      determined during the QDRS staging at the time of the initial consultation. The care taker is
      an individual who is intimately familiar and in close contact with the subject. After the
      first two months, visits will be on a monthly basis. Mild, moderate, and severe adverse
      reactions will be reported on an ongoing basis. The rationale for such extended
      administration is to allow for a more reliable assessment of tolerability. The primary
      endpoint in evaluating tolerability will be how many of the initial 20 subjects are
      discontinued due to adverse reactions. Subjects will be discontinued if they have moderate or
      severe adverse reaction ratings according to the CTCAE, which are not remediable by dosage
      reduction.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients who are discontinued due to tolerability issues related to treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Mild Cognitive Impairment</condition>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bosutinib Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will be administered the initial dose of bosutinib, with dosage progressively increased over the course of the study. The initial dose of bosutinib is 100 mg tablet, once per day. The dose will be increased as tolerated up to 300 mg per day. The dose will be increased by 100 mg each month if the lower dose is tolerated without significant side effects. That is to say, the subject will take 100 mg/day every day for the first month, 200 mg/day every day for the second month, and 300 mg/day every day for the third month and for the remainder of the study, provided that adverse reactions do not prohibit continuation at this dosage. Stopping and dose reduction rules for reported adverse reactions have been taken from the package insert of bosutinib. The duration of treatment is 1 year.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>bosutinib</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Bosutinib Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>bosulif</other_name>
    <other_name>TKA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Cognitive decline with mild cognitive impairment (Clinical Dementia Rating Stage 0.5)
             through moderate dementia (CDR Stages 1 and 2)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with a history of hypersensitivity to bosutinib

          -  Subjects with contraindications for lumbar puncture, such as bleeding abnormalities,
             use of anticoagulant medications, and local skin or spine abnormalities

          -  Reversible causes of cognitive impairment that explains the clinical status entirely,
             such as hypothyroidism, depression

          -  Advanced stages of any terminal illness or any active cancer that requires
             chemotherapy

          -  Pre-existing renal impairment

          -  Pre-existing hepatic impairment

          -  QT prolongation

          -  Significant cytopenia

          -  Cardiovascular, cerebrovascular, and peripheral vascular arterial thrombosis

          -  Women who are pregnant, may become pregnant, or are breastfeeding

          -  Women of child-bearing potential and male participants with female partners who are of
             child-bearing potential

          -  Subjects unable to give informed consent or in vulnerable categories, such as
             prisoners
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>89 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sheldon Jordan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Neurological Associates of West Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Neurological Associates of West LA</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santa Monica</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90403</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carneiro BA, Kaplan JB, Giles FJ. Tyrosine kinase inhibitor therapy in chronic myeloid leukemia: update on key adverse events. Expert Rev Hematol. 2015 Aug;8(4):457-79. doi: 10.1586/17474086.2015.1041910. Epub 2015 May 4. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25938861</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hebron ML, Lonskaya I, Moussa CE. Nilotinib reverses loss of dopamine neurons and improves motor behavior via autophagic degradation of α-synuclein in Parkinson's disease models. Hum Mol Genet. 2013 Aug 15;22(16):3315-28. doi: 10.1093/hmg/ddt192. Epub 2013 May 10.</citation>
    <PMID>23666528</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lonskaya I, Hebron M, Chen W, Schachter J, Moussa C. Tau deletion impairs intracellular β-amyloid-42 clearance and leads to more extracellular plaque deposition in gene transfer models. Mol Neurodegener. 2014 Nov 10;9:46. doi: 10.1186/1750-1326-9-46.</citation>
    <PMID>25384392</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tapiola T, Alafuzoff I, Herukka SK, Parkkinen L, Hartikainen P, Soininen H, Pirttilä T. Cerebrospinal fluid {beta}-amyloid 42 and tau proteins as biomarkers of Alzheimer-type pathologic changes in the brain. Arch Neurol. 2009 Mar;66(3):382-9. doi: 10.1001/archneurol.2008.596.</citation>
    <PMID>19273758</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Targosz-Gajniak MG, Siuda JS, Wicher MM, Banasik TJ, Bujak MA, Augusciak-Duma AM, Opala G. Magnetic resonance spectroscopy as a predictor of conversion of mild cognitive impairment to dementia. J Neurol Sci. 2013 Dec 15;335(1-2):58-63. doi: 10.1016/j.jns.2013.08.023. Epub 2013 Aug 27.</citation>
    <PMID>24035276</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hebron M, Moussa CE. Two sides of the same coin: tyrosine kinase inhibition in cancer and neurodegeneration. Neural Regen Res. 2015 Nov;10(11):1767-9. doi: 10.4103/1673-5374.165320.</citation>
    <PMID>26807110</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lonskaya I, Hebron ML, Selby ST, Turner RS, Moussa CE. Nilotinib and bosutinib modulate pre-plaque alterations of blood immune markers and neuro-inflammation in Alzheimer's disease models. Neuroscience. 2015 Sep 24;304:316-27. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroscience.2015.07.070. Epub 2015 Jul 30.</citation>
    <PMID>26235435</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hebron ML, Lonskaya I, Olopade P, Selby ST, Pagan F, Moussa CE. Tyrosine Kinase Inhibition Regulates Early Systemic Immune Changes and Modulates the Neuroimmune Response in α-Synucleinopathy. J Clin Cell Immunol. 2014 Sep 30;5:259.</citation>
    <PMID>25635231</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lonskaya I, Hebron ML, Desforges NM, Schachter JB, Moussa CE. Nilotinib-induced autophagic changes increase endogenous parkin level and ubiquitination, leading to amyloid clearance. J Mol Med (Berl). 2014 Apr;92(4):373-86. doi: 10.1007/s00109-013-1112-3. Epub 2013 Dec 13.</citation>
    <PMID>24337465</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hebron ML, Lonskaya I, Moussa CE. Tyrosine kinase inhibition facilitates autophagic SNCA/α-synuclein clearance. Autophagy. 2013 Aug;9(8):1249-50. doi: 10.4161/auto.25368. Epub 2013 Jun 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23787811</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lonskaya I, Hebron ML, Desforges NM, Franjie A, Moussa CE. Tyrosine kinase inhibition increases functional parkin-Beclin-1 interaction and enhances amyloid clearance and cognitive performance. EMBO Mol Med. 2013 Aug;5(8):1247-62. doi: 10.1002/emmm.201302771. Epub 2013 Jul 4.</citation>
    <PMID>23737459</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Folch J, Petrov D, Ettcheto M, Pedrós I, Abad S, Beas-Zarate C, Lazarowski A, Marin M, Olloquequi J, Auladell C, Camins A. Masitinib for the treatment of mild to moderate Alzheimer's disease. Expert Rev Neurother. 2015 Jun;15(6):587-96. doi: 10.1586/14737175.2015.1045419. Epub 2015 May 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25961655</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Galvin JE. THE QUICK DEMENTIA RATING SYSTEM (QDRS): A RAPID DEMENTIA STAGING TOOL. Alzheimers Dement (Amst). 2015 Jun 1;1(2):249-259.</citation>
    <PMID>26140284</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adamczuk K, Schaeverbeke J, Vanderstichele HM, Lilja J, Nelissen N, Van Laere K, Dupont P, Hilven K, Poesen K, Vandenberghe R. Diagnostic value of cerebrospinal fluid Aβ ratios in preclinical Alzheimer's disease. Alzheimers Res Ther. 2015 Dec 18;7(1):75. doi: 10.1186/s13195-015-0159-5.</citation>
    <PMID>26677842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Llorens F, Schmitz M, Ferrer I, Zerr I. CSF biomarkers in neurodegenerative and vascular dementias. Prog Neurobiol. 2016 Mar-May;138-140:36-53. doi: 10.1016/j.pneurobio.2016.03.003. Epub 2016 Mar 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27016008</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Teipel SJ, Cavedo E, Grothe MJ, Lista S, Galluzzi S, Colliot O, Chupin M, Bakardjian H, Dormont D, Dubois B, Hampel H; Hippocampus Study Group. Predictors of cognitive decline and treatment response in a clinical trial on suspected prodromal Alzheimer's disease. Neuropharmacology. 2016 Sep;108:128-35. doi: 10.1016/j.neuropharm.2016.02.005. Epub 2016 Feb 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26876309</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Trebeschi S, Riederer I, Preibisch C, Bohn KP, Förster S, Alexopoulos P, Zimmer C, Kirschke JS, Valentinitsch A. Diagnostic Potential of Pulsed Arterial Spin Labeling in Alzheimer's Disease. Front Neurosci. 2016 Apr 19;10:154. doi: 10.3389/fnins.2016.00154. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>27147946</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cortes JE, Kantarjian HM, Brümmendorf TH, Kim DW, Turkina AG, Shen ZX, Pasquini R, Khoury HJ, Arkin S, Volkert A, Besson N, Abbas R, Wang J, Leip E, Gambacorti-Passerini C. Safety and efficacy of bosutinib (SKI-606) in chronic phase Philadelphia chromosome-positive chronic myeloid leukemia patients with resistance or intolerance to imatinib. Blood. 2011 Oct 27;118(17):4567-76. doi: 10.1182/blood-2011-05-355594. Epub 2011 Aug 24. Erratum in: Blood. 2013 Oct 3;122(14):2524.</citation>
    <PMID>21865346</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jefferson AL, Beiser AS, Seshadri S, Wolf PA, Au R. APOE and mild cognitive impairment: the Framingham Heart Study. Age Ageing. 2015 Mar;44(2):307-11. doi: 10.1093/ageing/afu183. Epub 2014 Dec 11.</citation>
    <PMID>25497326</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Janofsky JS, McCarthy RJ, Folstein MF. The Hopkins Competency Assessment Test: a brief method for evaluating patients' capacity to give informed consent. Hosp Community Psychiatry. 1992 Feb;43(2):132-6.</citation>
    <PMID>1572608</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Appelbaum PS. Clinical practice. Assessment of patients' competence to consent to treatment. N Engl J Med. 2007 Nov 1;357(18):1834-40. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17978292</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 28, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 30, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 3, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 30, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 30, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 3, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Neurological Associates of West Los Angeles</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sheldon Jordan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Neurologist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

