<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02923765</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201601026B0</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02923765</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Stepper Aerobic Training on Fitness, Disability, Inflammation and Thrombosis in Stroke Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Efficacy of Stepper Aerobic Training on Cardiopulmonary Fitness, Disability, Systemic Inflammation and Thrombosis in Stroke Patients With Hemiplegia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Stroke rehabilitation of hemiplegics primarily lies in motor control and training of
      activities of daily life. Whole body aerobics is much less emphasized. Nonetheless,
      cardiopulmonary fitness of even ambulatory hemiparetics is only half compared with healthy
      people, which is prone to deconditioning. The present study aims to understand the efficacy
      of aerobic training in addition to the usual neuro-rehabilitation, including aerobic fitness,
      daily activities dependency, anti-inflammation and anti-thrombosis. This is a prospective and
      randomized design. The subjects will be recruited from the hospitalized patients in the
      rehabilitation ward of Chang Gung Memorial Hospital at Linkuo. 120 hemiplegic patients due to
      stroke will be enrolled and randomized into two groups: combined training (CT) and usual
      rehabilitation. Participants in CT will receive aerobics at moderate intensity in addition to
      the usual rehabilitation. The program has 35 minutes/session, 5 sessions/week and 4-5 weeks
      in total. A constant-power semi-recumbent stepper will be employed as the training modality.
      It uses bilateral reciprocal movement of the arm coupled with the opposite leg, which allows
      for a push and pull motion. Additional 20 healthy participants will also be recruited as the
      healthy control. Assessment before and after training includes: (I) graded cardiopulmonary
      exercise test using constant-load stepper. (II) Functional Independence Measure. (III)
      coagulation system assessment, using Thrombin generation assay and Ceveron alpha (Technoclone
      GmbH, Vienna, Austria) : Von Willebrand factor, tissue plasminogen activator, plasminogen
      activator inhibitor-1, D-dimer, factor VIII, etc. [the 1st year]; (IV) monocyte-platelet
      aggregation and its subtypes, using flow cytometry [the 2nd year]. ( V) systemic
      inflammation, platelet activation and prognostic biomarker：C-reactive protein, soluble
      P-selectin, asymmetric dimethylarginine, Lipoprotein-Associated Phospholipase A2, etc [the
      3rd year]. Statistical analysis will use ANOVA with post-hoc, two-way repeated measure ANOVA,
      etc. The investigation will start after approval and end in 2019, July. We hope this
      investigation will establish a more comprehensive rehabilitation program for clinical
      application.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In Taiwan, there are 220,00 stroke survivors and each year, 10,000 new suffers causing
      impairment in daily activities. This is the leading cause of disability and consumes 4.5
      billions of National Health Insurance yearly. More than half of them become hemi-paretics and
      hemi-plegics. Stroke leads to the adverse combination of reduced functional capacity and
      increased energy demands to perform routine activities Thereby, physiologic fitness reserve
      is diminished. Aerobic fitness is low in stroke survivors. Among ambulatory patients
      suffering from hemiparetic stroke, the VO2peak is approximately half that of age-matched
      individuals , a level that is near the minimum range required for activities of daily life.
      It may limit their ability to perform everyday activities and cause further complications,
      such as cardiopulmonary de-conditioning, muscular atrophy, joint stiffness, or even learned
      nonuse.

      Many patients are discharged from neurorehabilitation focusing on motor control and ADL
      (activity of daily life ) training, while aerobic fitness training is neglected, especially
      in non-ambulatory patients. Randomized exercise training studies using a wide variety of
      modalities and protocols have demonstrated an 8~23% improvement in VO2peak after 2-6 months
      of training . However, most research recruit patients with hemiparesis who have
      mild-to-moderate gait impairment . No specific training protocols has been adequately studied
      or can be suggested for hemiplegic patients. It is difficult for them to partake in aerobic
      exercise, like walking or biking. There is a need to develop a new aerobic exercise module
      suitable for the patients, especially for those with ambulation difficulty resulted from
      severe paralysis.

      In the current investigation, a semi-recumbent stepper with constant power design will be
      adopted as training modality. It accommodates motor function deficits by providing trunk and
      distal limb support . In addition, semi- recumbent stepper uses bilateral reciprocal movement
      of the arm coupled with the opposite leg, which allows for a push and pull motion.

      Aerobic fitness training has been proposed as a beneficial approach for people with stroke.
      Taking part in fitness training could have a range of other benefits important to people with
      stroke such as improving cognitive function, improving mood, and quality of life, and it
      could reduce the risk of recurrent stroke . In the present investigation, the outcome
      measurement will not only include cardiopulmonary fitness and the degree of daily activity
      dependency, but also prognostic biomarkers, thrombotic and inflammatory state.

      It is well-documented that exercise training has an anti-thrombotic effect . Increased
      physical activity and cardiorespiratory fitness are associated with a reduced risk of
      fatality from cardiovascular diseases. Moreover, increased studies have demonstrated that
      regular moderate-intensity physical activity is associated with health benefits, even when
      aerobic fitness (e.g., maximal oxygen uptake, VO2max) remains unchanged . For sedentary
      persons at risk for cardiovascular disease, adopting a moderately active lifestyle can induce
      important health benefits, such as reducing prothrombotic factors and lipid peroxidation ,
      increasing fibrinolytic activity and high-density lipoprotein levels , etc. One of the
      present investigation aims to understand whether 20~25 sessions of aerobic training at
      moderate intensity will induce these favorable adaptations that could contribute to decreased
      risk for ischemic event.

      This is a prospective randomized controlled study. Eighty stroke sufferers with unilateral
      weakness will be enrolled in Chang Gung Memorial Hospital at Linkuo. They will be randomized
      into two groups: combined training (CT) and usual rehabilitation (UR). Participants in the CT
      group will receive supervised aerobic training at moderate intensity in addition to usual
      neuro-rehabilitation, in which motor control and task-oriented ADL training are the major
      contents. Patients in the UR will undergo usual neuro-rehabilitation only. The aim of the
      present research is to evaluate the efficacy of an aerobic training program at moderate
      intensity for a total of 20~25 sessions using a semi-recumbent stepper with constant power
      design. Pre- and post-training measurement includes (I) cardiopulmonary fitness, (II) daily
      activities dependency, (III) coagulation and fibrinolysis profile. [the 1st year] (IV)
      monocyte subsets and its interaction with platelets [the 2nd year]. (V) Systemic
      inflammation, platelet activation and prognostic biomarker：C-reactive protein, soluble
      P-selectin, asymmetric dimethylarginine, Lipoprotein-Associated Phospholipase A2, etc. [the
      3rd year]. Venous blood will be sampled two times before and after rehabilitation.

      Hopefully, this clinical investigation will establish the model of incorporating aerobics in
      the hemiplegic patients following stroke, and its efficacy for clinical application.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 11, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Exercise capacity of all participants by Cardiopulmonary ExerciseTest (CPET) and Functional Independence Measure (FIM)</measure>
    <time_frame>three years</time_frame>
    <description>CPET</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Thrombosis and Coagulation Activities of Blood Samples of All Participants by Flow Cytometry,</measure>
    <time_frame>three years</time_frame>
    <description>detection of monocytes and platelets aggregation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Thrombosis and Coagulation Activities of Blood Samples of All Participants by Dynamic TG Assay</measure>
    <time_frame>three years</time_frame>
    <description>detection the amount and time of thrombin generation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Thrombosis and Coagulation Activities of Blood Samples of All Participants Enzyme-linked Immunosorbent Assay (ELISA)</measure>
    <time_frame>three years</time_frame>
    <description>ELISA</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">170</enrollment>
  <condition>Ischemic Stroke</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>combined training (CT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>additional aerobic training by a stepper : 35 minutes/session, 5 sessions/week and 4-5 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>usual rehabilitation (UR)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual rehabilitation, without additional aerobic training</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>healthy participant (HP)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>healthy control</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aerobic training by a stepper</intervention_name>
    <description>Aerobic training by a stepper: 35 minutes/session, 5 sessions/week and 4-5 weeks in total</description>
    <arm_group_label>combined training (CT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of ischemic stroke

          -  Must be able to ride the stepper

          -  No cardiovascular disease in the healthy control group

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Resting heart rate greater than 100 beats per minute

          -  Atrial fibrillation or flutter

          -  Poor control of high blood pressure or diabetes

          -  Patients with peripheral arterial occlusive disease

          -  Patients with end-stage renal disease

          -  Patients receiving anticoagulant therapy

          -  Neurological instability

          -  Confusion or cognitive dysfunction
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shu-Chun Huang, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Chang Gung Memorial Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Shu-Chun Huang, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+88633281200</phone>
    <phone_ext>5156</phone_ext>
    <email>mr7171@cgmh.org.tw</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shu-Chun Huang</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taoyuan</city>
        <zip>333</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shu-Chun Huang, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+88633281200</phone>
      <phone_ext>5156</phone_ext>
      <email>mr7171@cgmh.org.tw</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 3, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 3, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 5, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 6, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 6, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

