<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02923479</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CRMINAIL01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02923479</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Robot-assisted Rehabilitation of Ankle Fractures: Efficacy and Comparison With Traditional Methods</brief_title>
  <official_title>Robot-assisted Ankle Rehabilitation Using the High-performance Robotic Device IIT-ARBOT: A Pilot Randomised Controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Istituto Nazionale Assicurazione contro gli Infortuni sul Lavoro</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Istituto Italiano di Tecnologia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Istituto Nazionale Assicurazione contro gli Infortuni sul Lavoro</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this trial is to determine the effectiveness, safety and tolerability of
      robot-assisted rehabilitation using ARBOT in patients with ankle dysfunction resulting from
      work related ankle fractures, compared with conventional rehabilitation programs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      INTRODUCTION:

      Robotic devices for lower-limb rehabilitation have been mainly tested in neurologically
      injured patients. Up to now, clinical studies using robotic training in orthopedic conditions
      are few. A pilot study was carried out at INAIL Physical Rehabilitation Center of Volterra
      using ARBOT, a prototypal robotic system for ankle rehabilitation. This device has been
      developed by IIT - Italian Institute of Technology and it consists of a two-degree-of-freedom
      electromechanical platform which is able to perform most of the exercises foreseen by the
      standard rehabilitation programs. By virtue of its innovative motion system and control
      architecture, ARBOT integrates multiple rehabilitation equipment functions, performing also
      special exercise programs such as elastic and fluid-dynamic resistance.

      ARBOT allows training according to programmed sequences, in order to promote range of
      movement, muscular function and proprioceptive recovery. Exercises can be performed with or
      without bearing weight. Moreover, ARBOT is a powerful evaluation instrument for
      physiotherapists in order to verify and record the results of rehabilitative intervention.

      The primary aim of this trial was to determine the effectiveness, safety and tolerability of
      robot-assisted rehabilitation using ARBOT in patients with ankle dysfunction resulting from
      work related ankle fractures, compared with conventional rehabilitation programs. Secondary
      objectives was to investigate correlations among physical and disability parameters, to
      collect data in order to define further study protocols and improve ARBOT's performance and
      ergonomics, and ultimately to evaluate patient satisfaction with respect to robot assisted
      rehabilitation programs.

      METHODS:

      Thirty-two patients with work related injuries resulting in ankle and/or hindfoot fractures
      and subsequent to the immobilization phase was enrolled in an open randomized controlled
      trial over a 30 month period. Each participant was randomly allocated to experimental or
      control group and received a 4-week rehabilitation program (20 sessions, for 5 days/week from
      admission to discharge in the Rehabilitation Centre) and weekly robotic and clinical
      assessments.

      Subjects in the experimental group were treated using ARBOT with passive, active and active
      assisted range-of-motion exercises, resistive exercises in isometric, isotonic, isokinetic,
      elastic and fluid-dynamic conditions, and proprioceptive training. Control subjects were
      assisted by a physiotherapist during range of motion recovery exercises and performed
      resistive and proprioceptive training using Biodex System 3 dynamometer and ProKin PK254
      mobile electronic platform.

      The assessment sessions included measurements of dorsiflexion ROM, isometric and isokinetic
      plantar-flexion torque and proprioceptive performance with ARBOT and 2 minutes walking and
      timed stair climbing test, LEFS-Lower Extremity Functional Scale and AOFAS-Ankle-Hindfoot
      Scale.

      Site monitoring of the study has been conducted according to the standard ISO 14155.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Dorsiflexion Range of Motion</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 1, 2, 3 and 4 weeks intervention</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Isometric peak torque at 0° and 10° of plantar flexion</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 2 and 4 weeks intervention</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of Isokinetic plantar-flexion torque at speed of 30°, 60°, 120°/sec</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 2 and 4 weeks intervention</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change of 2 Minute Walk Test (2MWT)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 2 and 4 weeks intervention</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Side Effects using ARBOT</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, up to 4 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timed Stair Climbing Test (10 steps)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 2 and 4 weeks intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proprioceptive tests (time taking and accuracy)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after after 2 and 4 weeks intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain (VAS 0-10)</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 1, 2, 3 and 4 weeks intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>LEFS - The Lower Extremity Functional Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after after 4 weeks intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>AOFAS - Ankle-Hindfoot Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline and after 4 weeks intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Satisfaction (VAS 0-10)</measure>
    <time_frame>After 4 weeks intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Ankle Fractures</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: ARBOT Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients in the &quot;ARBOT Group&quot; underwent to following interventions:
General Rehabilitation
Specific ankle rehabilitation by ARBOT device</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The patients in the Control Group underwent to following interventions:
General Rehabilitation
Specific ankle rehabilitation performed by physiotherapist
Specific ankle rehabilitation by Biodex System 3 dynamometer
Specific ankle rehabilitation by ProKin PK254 platform.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Specific ankle rehabilitation by ARBOT device</intervention_name>
    <description>ARBOT is a programmable robotic device consisting in a two-degree-of-freedom electromechanical platform developed by Italian Institute of Technology - Advanced Robotics and Rehab Technologies. It is composed of a fixed base, a central strut, a moving platform supporting patient's foot and three actuated limbs with a universal-prismatic-spherical kinematic chain. A six-axis force/torque sensor mounted between the moving platform and the footplate senses the human-robot interaction force and torque. The device is interfaced to a standard all-in-one touch screen Personal Computer with graphic applications to give patients visual feedback in real time.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: ARBOT Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>General Rehabilitation</intervention_name>
    <description>All patients underwent general rehabilitation (gait training, aerobic conditioning), including - if necessary - an initial weight training phase before the functional full weight-bearing program.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Experimental: ARBOT Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Specific ankle rehabilitation performed by physiotherapist</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects in the control group underwent manually assisted range of motion exercises.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Specific ankle rehabilitation by Biodex System 3 dynamometer</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects in the control group performed non-robotic resistive training using a Biodex System 3 dynamometer</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Specific ankle rehabilitation by ProKin PK254 platform</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects in the control group performed non-robotic proprioceptive training using a ProKin PK254 mobile electronic platform.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Functional limitation following work-related ankle injuries, including:

               -  Malleolar and/or tibial shaft fractures, both surgically and conservatively
                  treated;

               -  Distal tibia and fibula fractures, both surgically and conservatively treated;

               -  Hindfoot (Calcaneus and Talus) fractures, both surgically and conservatively
                  treated.

          2. Post-immobilization phase;

          3. Time interval since fracture event of less than 12 months;

          4. Signed informed consent acquisition.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Non-compliance with study requirements;

          2. Pregnancy or breast feeding;

          3. Current or prior history of malignancy;

          4. Open skin at the level of the patient-device interface;

          5. Sensory deficit at the level of the patient-device interface;

          6. Ankle motor deficit secondary to peroneal or tibial neuropathy;

          7. Acute inflammatory arthritis of the ankle;

          8. Other pathological conditions inducing lower limb pain or disfunction.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paolo Catitti, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>INAIL - Centro di Riabilitazione Motoria di Volterra</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>INAIL - Centro di Riabilitazione Motoria di Volterra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Volterra</city>
        <state>Pisa</state>
        <zip>56048</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saglia JA, Tsagarakis NG, Dai JS, Caldwell DG. Control Strategies for Patient-Assisted Training Using the Ankle Rehabilitation Robot (ARBOT). IEEE ASME TRANSACTIONS ON MECHATRONICS 2013; PP (99): 1-10.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saglia JA, Tsagarakis NG, Dai JS, Caldwell DG. A high-performance redundantly actuated parallel mechanism for ankle rehabilitation. International Journal of Robotics Research 2009; 28 (9): 1216-1227.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Saglia JA, Tsagarakis NG, Dai JS, Caldwell DG. Inverse-Kinematics-Based Control of a Redundantly Actuated Platform for Rehabilitation. Journal of Systems and Control Engineering, IMechE Proceedings 2009; 223 (1): 53-70.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 28, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 1, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 4, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 1, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 1, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 4, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Rehabilitation</keyword>
  <keyword>Robotics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ankle Fractures</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

