<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02922127</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAAQ8498</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02922127</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Compare Daily Ulipristal Acetate and Combined Oral Contraceptive Effects on Breast Epithelial Cell Proliferation</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Randomized, Single-blind Study to Compare the Effects of Daily Ulipristal Acetate (UPA) 10mg With a Combined Oral Contraceptive (COC) Pill on Breast Epithelial Cell Proliferation in Reproductive Age Women</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Columbia University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Columbia University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Breast cancer accounts for almost a quarter of all cancers in women. In the United States
      (U.S.) in 2014, more than 230,000 women were diagnosed and 40,000 died of breast cancer.
      There is an urgent need to develop acceptable means of preventing breast cancer both for high
      risk and average risk women.

      The proposed study is a clinical trial in premenopausal women aged 18-39 to evaluate the
      capacity of daily Ulipristal Acetate (UPA) to reduce breast epithelial cell proliferation
      (increase in number of cells in the breast) and to measure its effect compared to that found
      with a combined estrogen-progestin oral contraceptive (COC). UPA is an anti-progestin in use
      as daily medication up to 12 months for the treatment of abnormally heavy bleeding at
      menstruation due to uterine fibroids, and is currently in trials in the U.S. to evaluate its
      use as a daily contraceptive.

      The investigators will use breast biopsies to compare breast cell proliferation, comparing
      biopsies at the end of 3 months treatment to biopsies taken at baseline in the 2 groups (UPA
      and COC). The investigators will also compare the changes in the 2 groups to each other. The
      comparison of the effect of UPA to that of a conventional COC is because of UPA's potential
      use as a daily contraceptive.

      Cell proliferation in the breast occurs throughout the menstrual cycle. The actions of
      hormones on the breast are rapid and an anti-progestin such as UPA, which will block the
      action of progesterone in the breast, would be predicted to quickly lower breast cell
      proliferation in premenopausal women. Effects of UPA on the uterus continue to be studied and
      are reassuring. COC use has not been found to lower breast cell proliferation and is not
      associated with any decrease in risk of breast cancer.

      The changes in breast cell proliferation will also be compared to changes seen on breast MRI.
      If the changes are highly correlated future studies will be able to be done without the need
      for breast biopsies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a randomized controlled parallel group clinical trial with blinded evaluation to
      be carried out at 2 academic medical centers: Columbia University Medical Center and Weill
      Cornell Medical College. The investigators will screen healthy women aged 18-39 who meet
      inclusion/exclusion criteria and will enroll them for the study.

      After the informed consent process and study enrollment, study participation will begin with
      a baseline cycle. The main goal of the baseline cycle is to identify the occurrence and the
      timing of ovulation. Starting at about day 6 of the baseline cycle, participants will undergo
      blood sampling for progesterone (P4) levels at intervals of every 2-3 days. An increase of P4
      to greater than 3 ng/mL, confirmed by a second such value, will indicate ovulation and
      eligibility to continue in the study. The participant's baseline breast MRI and biopsy (see
      below) will be scheduled to occur in the mid luteal phase, about 7 days after the first
      increase (&gt;3 ng/mL) in P4. The investigators will randomly assign which breast has the first
      biopsy, and women will return for a post-biopsy visit about 7 days later. At the post-biopsy
      visit, the investigators will assess acceptability of the MRI and biopsy to the participants
      using visual analog scales (VAS) as well as interview.

      At the beginning of the next menstrual period, women will begin the treatment phase of the
      study. They will receive random assignment to either UPA or COC at the study center and
      receive their first dose and a 4-week supply of study drug. During cycles 1 and 2 they will
      return to the study site every 2 weeks for assessment, blood draws and to receive the next
      cycle of study drug. During the third cycle, they will return to the study site twice weekly
      for more frequent testing and monitoring. Each cycle will be 28 days, corresponding to usual
      COC packaging. At day 75-77 of treatment women will undergo the second breast MRI,
      immediately followed by a biopsy of the contralateral breast to that biopsied at baseline. An
      end-of-study visit, including checking the incision site and a repeat assessment of
      acceptability of the MRI and biopsy to the participants, will occur about 7 days later.
      Participants will also be asked to rate their preference for an MRI versus a biopsy, were it
      possible to do a study with only one of these procedures.

      Participants will have up to 24 study visits, and at each visit, participants will be asked
      about adverse events and use of any concomitant medications. Participants will have a high
      sensitivity urine pregnancy test at baseline and immediately preceding each MRI and preceding
      the first dose of study medication. Any participant with a positive pregnancy test will be
      immediately withdrawn from the study.

      Breast Biopsies Breast biopsies will take place immediately following each breast MRI. Women
      will receive 24-hour telephone follow-up, and make a visit within one week following each
      breast biopsy to ensure that the biopsy site is healing without incident.

      MRI For each participant, the baseline and follow-up MRI will be done using the same machine.
      Each MRI study will undergo an immediate wet read to assure adequate quality and to identify
      any unexpected pathology that would mandate clinical evaluation and withdrawal from the
      study. A limited report indicating technical adequacy and absence of major clinical
      abnormalities will be recorded in the patient record.

      Breast MRI and breast biopsy visits will take place at the Center for Breast Imaging at
      Columbia University Medical Center.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 16, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in breast epithelial cell proliferation rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, three months</time_frame>
    <description>The breast biopsies will be analyzed (measured by Ki67) at end of study treatment, as compared with baseline before initiation of treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in breast epithelial cell proliferation rate in the UPA group compared to the change in the COC group</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months</time_frame>
    <description>The breast biopsies will be analyzed (measured by Ki67).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects using UPA who experience a categorical decrease in breast background parenchymal enhancement (BPE)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, three months</time_frame>
    <description>This will be measured with contrast MRI.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of subjects experiencing a categorical decrease in breast BPE in the UPA group compared to the change in the COC group</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months</time_frame>
    <description>This will be measured with contrast MRI.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">45</enrollment>
  <condition>Contraception</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ulipristal Acetate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 women will randomized to daily use of 10mg of ulipristal acetate</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combined Oral Contraceptive</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>20 women will be randomized to daily use of a combined oral contraceptive pill</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ulipristal Acetate</intervention_name>
    <description>Daily use of Ulipristal Acetate</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ulipristal Acetate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ella</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combined Oral Contraceptive Pill</intervention_name>
    <description>Daily use of Oral Contraceptive Pill</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combined Oral Contraceptive</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Portia</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Women between 18 and 39 years of age (inclusive).

          2. In good health, with regular menstrual cycles between 21 and 35 days and with
             intra-individual variation of less than or equal to 5 days.

          3. Volunteers who are postpartum or who aborted in the first or second trimester must
             have had two normal menstrual cycles (3 bleeding episodes) prior to screening.

          4. No use of any other hormonal contraception within two normal menstrual cycles (3
             bleeding episodes) prior to screening.

          5. If previous use of injectable Depo Provera, subject must have had two normal menstrual
             cycles (3 bleeding episodes) prior to screening.

          6. Not at risk for pregnancy:

               1. Using a copper intra uterine device (IUD), or

               2. Willing to protect all further acts of intercourse with condoms, or

               3. Not hetero-sexually active, or

               4. Having undergone previous tubal ligation, or

               5. Partner sterilized or vasectomized.

          7. Body Mass Index (BMI) &lt; 30 kg/m2 and not having previously undergone bariatric
             surgery.

          8. Diastolic blood pressure (BP) ≤ 90 mm Hg and systolic BP ≤ 140 mm Hg after at least 5
             minutes in a sitting position. Hypertensive subjects who are treatment controlled may
             obtain a waiver for participation.

          9. Willing and able to follow all study requirements, including use of the study
             medication and willing to give information related to study medication use as required
             during the study, in the opinion of the investigator.

         10. Able to give informed consent to participate in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Currently pregnant as confirmed by positive high-sensitivity urine pregnancy test.

          2. Currently breast-feeding or within 30 days of discontinuing breast feeding at
             screening.

          3. Undiagnosed abnormal genital bleeding.

          4. Known hypersensitivity to an active substance or any of the excipients of the study
             treatments.

          5. Abnormal clinical breast examination at screening.

          6. Suspected hyperplasia or carcinoma of the endometrium.

          7. Ovarian cyst &gt; 25 mm observed on transvaginal or transabdominal ultrasound performed
             on the first visit of the Baseline cycle.

          8. History of any diagnostic or therapeutic breast biopsy

          9. Any of the known contraindications to COC use:

               1. History of or existing breast cancer, or other hormone sensitive neoplasia, or

               2. History of or current ischemic heart disease or stroke, or

               3. History of or current deep venous thrombosis or pulmonary embolism, or

               4. Systemic lupus erythematosus with positive or unknown antiphospholipid
                  antibodies, or

               5. History of or current benign or malignant liver tumor, or

               6. Severe (decompensated) cirrhosis.

               7. Headaches with focal neurological symptoms.

         10. Hereditary galactose intolerance, Lapp lactase deficiency, or glucose-galactose
             malabsorption.

         11. Known or suspected alcoholism or drug abuse.

         12. Known human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection.

         13. Smoking 15 cigarettes or more per day, if in the opinion of the investigator or
             medically qualified designee, this would increase the risk for cardiovascular disease
             and thromboembolism based on risk factors.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>39 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carolyn Westhoff, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Columbia University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Carolyn Westhoff, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-305-4805</phone>
    <email>clw3@columbia.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Margaret Polaneczky, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-746-3946</phone>
    <email>mpolanec@med.cornell.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ariel Allen, BA</last_name>
      <phone>212-305-8031</phone>
      <email>aa3975@cumc.colulmbia.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Claudia Roca, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>212-342-2986</phone>
      <email>cr479@columbia.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Carolyn Westhoff, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Weill Cornell Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Margaret Polaneczky, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 25, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 30, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 4, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 6, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 6, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Columbia University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carolyn L. Westhoff</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ulipristal Acetate (UPA)</keyword>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Combined Oral Contraceptive (COC)</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Contraceptive Agents</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Contraceptives, Oral</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Contraceptives, Oral, Combined</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

