<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01701141</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2009-P-001360</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01701141</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Depression and Dopamine Transporter Function Study Using C-11 Altropane</brief_title>
  <official_title>Depression and Dopamine Transporter Function: A Positron Emission Tomography Study Using C-11 Altropane</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mclean Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mclean Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Major depressive disorder (MDD) is often characterized by anhedonia and impaired ability to
      modulate behavior as a function of rewards. However, the neurobiology of anhedonia and
      reduced reward responsiveness remains largely unknown. Because dopamine (DA) plays a critical
      role in goal-directed behavior and reinforcement learning, DA dysregulation might play an
      important role. In fact, several lines of evidence suggest that down-regulation of DA
      transmission might characterize depression vulnerability and the emergence of depressive
      symptoms. The current study seeks to elucidate the role of DA dysfunction in MDD. We
      hypothesize that MDD subjects will show reduced DAT binding potential, reduced reward
      learning in the probabilistic reward task, and abnormal functional magnetic resonance imaging
      (fMRI) activation in dorsal and ventral striatal regions during an instrumental learning
      task.

      This study will include three sessions.

      The first will take place at Massachusetts General Hospital or at McLean Hospital's Center
      for Depression, Anxiety and Stress Research. The aims of this session will be to (a) explain
      the study; (b) collect written informed consent, and (c) assess the subject's eligibility.

      Following this, another session (either second or third in order) will take place at the MGH
      PET Imaging Laboratory. Participants will complete a PET scan and a probabilistic reward task
      designed to measure reward learning and sensitivity to reward. The radioactive tracer
      utilized is 11C-altropane.

      Another session (either second or third in order) will take place at the McLean Hospital
      Neuroimaging Center. Participants will complete an instrumental learning task while in the
      fMRI, followed by a social reinforcement learning task and an implicit learning serial
      reaction time task upon completion of the scan. In the instrumental learning task,
      participants have the opportunity to earn money but need to learn, by trial and error,
      stimulus-outcome associations. The social reinforcement learning task is designed to
      investigate whether learning deficits in MDD are specific to learning from monetary
      incentives or whether the learning deficits are more global and are affected when learning
      from social rewards and punishments. Participants will also complete an implicit learning
      serial reaction time task, designed to exclude the possibility of global learning deficits in
      MDD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>11C-Altropane Binding</measure>
    <time_frame>1 hour long PET scan during session 2</time_frame>
    <description>11C-altropane binding is recording during the positron emission tomography (PET) scan and is used to measure dopamine transporter levels.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral Performance in Probabilistic Reward Task</measure>
    <time_frame>20 minute task administered during session 2</time_frame>
    <description>The probabilistic reward task is designed to measure sensitivity to reward and reward learning.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Brain Activity during Instrumental Learning Task</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minute long fMRI scan during session 3</time_frame>
    <description>Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) data are acquired while participants perform the instrumental learning task. fMRI data allows us to measure aspects of brain activity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral Performance in Instrumental Learning Task</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minute task administered during session 3</time_frame>
    <description>The instrumental learning task is designed to measure participant learning from reward and punishment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral Performance in the Social Reinforcement Learning Task</measure>
    <time_frame>15 minute task administered during session 3</time_frame>
    <description>The social reinforcement learning task is designed to investigate whether learning deficits in MDD are specific to learning from monetary incentives or whether the learning deficits are more global and are affected when learning from social rewards and punishments.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Questionnaire Data</measure>
    <time_frame>Self-report measures are administered at all 3 sessions which take place within an average of 2-3 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>At all sessions participants will fill out self-report questionnaires regarding aspects of mood and affect, demographics, caffeine and alcohol consumption, etc.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral Performance in Implicit Learning Serial Reaction Time Task</measure>
    <time_frame>5 minute task administered during session 3</time_frame>
    <description>The implicit learning serial reaction time task is designed to exclude the possibility of global learning deficits in major depressive disorder.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Major Depressive Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Anhedonia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Individuals with MDD</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals with current MDD as determined by structured clinical interview for DSM-IV (SCID) at time of enrollment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Controls</arm_group_label>
    <description>Individuals with no psychiatric diagnosis as determined by structured clinical interview for DSM-IV (SCID) at time of enrollment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Community Sample
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Criteria for All Subjects

        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Written informed consent;

          2. Both genders and all ethnic origins, age between 18 and 45;

          3. Right-handed (Chapman and Chapman 1987);

          4. Absence of any medications for at least 3 weeks;

          5. Absence of pregnancy;

          6. Absence of current drug use (cocaine, cannabinoids, opiates, amphetamines,
             benzodiazepines and barbiturates) as assessed by urinary drug test.

          7. For women, completion of a negative urine pregnancy test prior to the MRI scan, as
             well as a negative STAT quantitative serum hCG test immediately prior to
             radiopharmaceutical exposure;

          8. Normal or corrected-to-normal vision and hearing.

        Exclusion Criteria

          1. Pregnant or currently breast-feeding women or any woman of childbearing potential who
             is seeking to become pregnant or suspects that she may be pregnant.

          2. History or current serious or unstable medical illness, including cancer,
             cardiovascular, hepatic, renal, respiratory, endocrine, neurologic or hematologic
             disease;

          3. History of seizure disorder;

          4. Failure to meet standard PET safety requirements;

          5. Failure to meet standard fMRI safety requirements;

          6. Students and employees supervised by the Investigators at MGH, McLean Hospital and
             Harvard University;

          7. Absence of fluency in written and spoken English;

          8. History of head injury;

          9. History or current use of cocaine, stimulants, or other dopaminergic drugs.

         10. Diabetes with poor glucose control;

         11. History or current diagnosis of dementia, or a score of &lt; 26 on the Mini Mental Status
             Examination (Folstein, 1975) at the screening visit;

         12. Clinical or laboratory evidence of hypothyroidism or currently taking thyroid
             medication;

         13. Currently taking medication that affects blood flow, e.g. certain blood pressure
             medications

         14. Evidence of significant inconsistencies in self-report.

        Criteria Specific to MDD subjects

        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. DSM-IV diagnostic criteria for MDD (diagnosed with the use of the SCID);

          2. A baseline HRSD score (Hamilton 1960) greater than or equal to 16 (17-item version);

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects with suicidal ideation where outpatient treatment is determined unsafe by the
             study clinician. These patients will be immediately referred to appropriate clinical
             treatment;

          2. History or current diagnosis of: learning and developmental disorders (including ADHD
             and autism spectrum disorders), anorexia nervosa, cognitive disorders, somatoform and
             factitious disorders, dissociative disorders, personality disorders, organic mental
             disorders, schizophrenia or other psychotic disorder, bipolar disorder, obsessive
             compulsive disorder; simple phobia, social anxiety disorder and generalized anxiety
             disorder are allowed if secondary to MDD.

          3. History of substance dependence lifetime or substance abuse within the last 12 months;

          4. History of bulimia nervosa or PTSD within the past 2 years;

          5. History or current diagnosis of dementia, or a score of &lt; 26 on the Mini Mental Status
             Examination (Folstein, 1975) at the screening visit;

          6. Current use of other psychotropic drugs;

          7. Patients with lifetime electroconvulsive therapy (ECT);

          8. Presence of any psychotropic medications for at least 2 weeks:

               -  6 months for dopaminergic drugs (including methylphenidate),

               -  6 weeks for fluoxetine,

               -  6 months for neuroleptics,

               -  2 weeks for benzodiazepines,

               -  2 weeks for any other antidepressants.

        Criteria Specific to Control subjects

        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Absence of medical, neurological, and psychiatric illness (including alcohol and
             substance abuse), as assessed by subject history and a structured clinical interview
             (SCID-I/NP);

          2. Absence of any medications for at least 3 weeks;

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History or current diagnosis of any of DSM-IV psychiatric illness;

          2. First degree relative with mood disorder or psychosis;

          3. History or current use of any psychiatric medication.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Diego Pizzagalli, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mclean Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McLean Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Belmont</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02478</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Massachusetts General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02114</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 2, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 3, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 4, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mclean Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Diego A. Pizzagalli</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor, Department of Psychiatry, Harvard Medical School</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Positron Emission Tomography (PET)</keyword>
  <keyword>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)</keyword>
  <keyword>reward</keyword>
  <keyword>stress</keyword>
  <keyword>learning</keyword>
  <keyword>Major Depressive Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Anhedonia</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anhedonia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dopamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

