<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00088751</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>040247</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>04-N-0247</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00088751</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment Study of Frontotemporal Dementia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Treatment Study for Frontotemporal Dementia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objectives. The proposed clinical study has two goals: First, to assess the efficacy of a
      central nervous system stimulant and an atypical antipsychotic in treating the behavioral
      symptoms of FTD and second, to further characterize the biological markers, including
      genetic, imaging, and CSF proteins, of FTD in relation to our existing group of Alzheimer's
      patients.

      Rationale. Frontotemporal dementia (FTD) is increasingly recognized as an important
      neuropsychiatric disorder. Symptoms of FTD include disinhibition, impulsivity, apathy,
      affective lability, and language dysfunction. The clinical syndrome is associated with
      frontal and/or anterior temporal atrophy on imaging and autopsy. Levels of the CSF proteins
      tau and (Beta)-amyloid 1-42, shown to have diagnostic utility in patients with Alzheimer's
      Disease (AD), have also been found to be abnormal in FTD. FTD is less associated with APOE
      genotype than AD, however some familial cases of FTD are associated with specific mutations
      in the gene encoding the tau protein. Currently, no treatments have been proven to be
      effective for altering the course or clinical symptoms of FTD.

      Design. Study subjects will include 50 male and female patients with mild-moderate
      frontotemporal dementia recruited from participants in NINDS protocol 02-N-0001. In a
      double-blinded crossover 11-week study without a placebo control, patients will be treated
      with a stimulant (dextroamphetamine) and an atypical antipsychotic (quetiapine). The primary
      outcome measures will be the Neuropsychiatric Inventory and the Clinical Global Impression of
      Change. Cerebrospinal fluid, cognitive and genetic measures, brain MRIs, and side effects
      scales will also be collected.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives. The goal of the proposed clinical study is to assess the efficacy of a central
      nervous system stimulant and an atypical antipsychotic in treating the behavioral symptoms of
      FTD.

      Rationale. Frontotemporal dementia (FTD) is increasingly recognized as an important
      neuropsychiatric disorder. Symptoms of FTD include disinhibition, impulsivity, apathy,
      affective lability, and language dysfunction. The clinical syndrome is associated with
      frontal and/or anterior temporal atrophy on imaging and autopsy. Currently, no treatments
      have been proven to be effective for altering the course or clinical symptoms of FTD.

      Design. Study subjects will include 20 male and female patients with mild-moderate
      frontotemporal dementia recruited from participants in NINDS protocols 02-N-0001 and
      81-N-0010. In a double-blinded crossover 11-week study without a placebo control, patients
      will be treated with a stimulant (dextroamphetamine) and an atypical antipsychotic
      (quetiapine). The primary outcome measures will be the Neuropsychiatric Inventory and the
      Clinical Global Impression of Change. Cognitive measures and side effects scales will also be
      collected.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 23, 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 1, 2009</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <enrollment>20</enrollment>
  <condition>Frontotemporal Lobar Degeneration</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. FTD as diagnosed by the Lund-Manchester criteria including patients with
                  diagnoses of Semantic Dementia or Primary Progressive Aphasia.

               2. Ages 45 to 95 years old.

               3. Mild-to-moderate (CDR 1 to 2) FTD with an assigned durable power of attorney.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Diagnosis of any form of dementia besides FTD, including AD, Lewy body dementia,
             vascular dementia, dementia associated with Parkinson's disease, Corticobasal
             Degeneration and Progressive Supranuclear Palsy.

          2. Severe dementia (CDR 3).

          3. Known allergy or serious adverse reaction to quetiapine or dextroamphetamine.

          4. Patient is already receiving a stimulant (methylphenidate, dextroamphetamine,
             pemoline, or modafinil), or an antipsychotic medication, typical or atypical,
             including prochlorperazine and metoclopromide.

          5. Patients taking any of the following medications because of their potential
             interaction with dextroamphetamine: MAO use currently or within 14 days prior to start
             of study, Furazolidone, Guanethidine, norepinephrine, sibutramine, tricyclic
             antidepressants, carbonic anhydrase inhibitors.

          6. Patients taking the following medications because of their potential interaction with
             quetiapine: Carbamazepine, clozapine, lithium, thioridazine.

          7. History of CVA, or at significantly increased risk for CVA (e.g., atrial fibrillation,
             recent TIA etc.).

          8. Symptomatic cardiovascular disease (i.e., angina, claudication, TIAs, syncope),
             uncontrolled hyper or hypotension, or a tic disorder.

          9. Any medical contraindication to performing the procedures involved in the study
             including blood draws or lumbar puncture.

         10. We will require a woman of child-bearing age to have a pregnancy test prior to
             starting the study medications and to use contraception during the course of the
             study.

         11. Patients with a previous negative trial of a stimulant.

         12. Patients with a history of severe psychosis.

         13. Patients with a history of recent substance abuse.

         14. Patients with QTc prolongation on a baseline EKG.

         15. A score of 2 or less on the Communication Functional Ratings - Swallowing Domain.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>45 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>95 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Woods SW, Tesar GE, Murray GB, Cassem NH. Psychostimulant treatment of depressive disorders secondary to medical illness. J Clin Psychiatry. 1986 Jan;47(1):12-5.</citation>
    <PMID>3941052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Satel SL, Nelson JC. Stimulants in the treatment of depression: a critical overview. J Clin Psychiatry. 1989 Jul;50(7):241-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2567730</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Galynker I, Ieronimo C, Miner C, Rosenblum J, Vilkas N, Rosenthal R. Methylphenidate treatment of negative symptoms in patients with dementia. J Neuropsychiatry Clin Neurosci. 1997 Spring;9(2):231-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9144102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 1, 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 31, 2004</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 31, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 2, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Frontotemporal Dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>Alzheimer's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Atypical Antipsychotic</keyword>
  <keyword>Stimulant</keyword>
  <keyword>Apathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Disinhibition</keyword>
  <keyword>Antipsychotic</keyword>
  <keyword>Biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>Dementia</keyword>
  <keyword>FTD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Frontotemporal Dementia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Aphasia, Primary Progressive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pick Disease of the Brain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Frontotemporal Lobar Degeneration</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

