<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00082420</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RETEQ (completed)</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>DK60021</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00082420</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT00072696</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Retinol Equivalence of Plant Carotenoids in Children</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To determine vitamin A value of beta-carotene in oil capsule, spinach, and golden rice.

      The experiments will be conducted in children (ages 7-9) with/without adequate vitamin A
      nutrition. As plant provitamin A carotenoids are a major and safe vitamin A source for a vast
      population in the world, it is essential to determine the efficiency of provitamin A
      carotenoid (mainly ß-C) conversion to vitamin A. By introducing ß-C into rice endosperm,
      Golden Rice may directly benefit consumers by providing vitamin A nutrition. Our
      investigation uses hydroponically grown, deca-deuterium labeled spinach and Golden Rice,
      synthetic ß-C-d10 and a vitamin A isotope reference, deca-deuterated retinyl acetate
      (RAc-d10), to evaluate the bioavailability and the bioconversion of plant provitamin A
      carotenes to retinol as compared with ß-C in oil capsules in vivo.

      Our objectives will be to test the following hypotheses and to make the following
      determinations: (1) The absorption and bio-conversion of provitamin A carotenes taken by
      children are different between spinach, Golden Rice, and ß-C in oil capsules. (2) The
      absorption of provitamin A carotenes and their bioconversion to vitamin A are different in
      children with or without adequate vitamin A nutrition. (3) To define the vitamin A
      equivalence(s) of dietary spinach, Golden Rice, and a ß-C in oil dose by using an isotope
      reference method in children with or without adequate vitamin A nutrition and to compare
      those values with values derived from model based compartmental analysis. (4) To determine
      the number and time of blood samples needed for future studies in various field settings on
      the retinol equivalence of a large number of plant sources.

      This study will be of importance in planning vitamin A deficiency prevention strategies and
      also will provide useful information regarding the potential efficacy of a bioengineered crop
      to provide vitamin A nutrition.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Seventy-two children each will take two meals, lunch and supper, containing equal amounts of
      ß-C in labeled spinach (along with white rice), or Golden Rice (along with light colored
      vegetables), or ß-C oil capsules (along with white rice and light colored vegetables), every
      day for 7 days. Before the two meals, the volunteers will take a breakfast with a RAc-d10
      dose as a reference for 7 days. The enrichment of labeled ß-C and labeled retinol in human
      circulation will be determined using advanced liquid chromatography / mass spectrometry and
      gas chromatography / mass spectrometry. Through the applications of these novel technologies,
      we will be able to determine the relative biological activities of endogenous carotenoids;
      that is, the vitamin A value of spinach, Golden Rice, and ß-C in oil capsules for children
      with/without vitamin A malnutrition.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2005</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Vitamin A Deficiency</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        healthy children with normal or marginal vitamin A nutrition
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  7-9 years old

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Parasitic infection
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>9 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lei Li, Yin Wang, Jieshu Wu, Ranfeng Zhu, Xianfeng Zhao, Zhixu Wang, Shi-an Yin. Biefficacy of β-carotene in Chinese children with marginal and normal vitamin A status (in Chinese). Hygiene Research, 2007;36(5):547-551.</citation>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lei Li, Yin Wang, Shi-an Yin, Michael A Grusak, Robert M Russell, Guangwen Tang. Bioconversion of spinach β-carotene in Chinese children with noemal or marginal vitamin A status. FASEB J. 2006 20:A1319</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 6, 2004</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 11, 2004</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 12, 2004</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 12, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 12, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 13, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Vitamin A malnutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>low vitamin A status</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamin A Deficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Night Blindness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamin A</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

