<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01492530</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AL04-DREW-840</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2P20MD000182</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01492530</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Men of African American Legacy Empowering Self</brief_title>
  <acronym>MAALES</acronym>
  <official_title>Reducing HIV Risk Behaviors and Psychosocial Stressors Among Bisexual African American Men</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Charles Drew University of Medicine and Science</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Minority Health and Health Disparities (NIMHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>California HIV/AIDS Research Program</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of California, Los Angeles</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Charles Drew University of Medicine and Science</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The MAALES Project is a community collaborative intervention designed to prevent HIV
      infection and transmission among African American men who have sex with both men and women.
      The investigators are a collaboration of researchers, community service providers and
      activists who are committed to developing and testing effective HIV prevention interventions
      that employ holistic and culturally relevant approaches. This includes recognizing the impact
      of forces such as racism, homophobia, heterosexism, sexism, and gender expectations on
      individual behavior and relationship dynamics in African American communities.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      HIV directly or indirectly related to male-to-male sexual intercourse is the largest
      contributor to HIV infection among Blacks (CDC 2002), accounting for approximately half of
      all US AIDS cases diagnosed among Black men and a substantial but unknown portion of cases
      diagnosed among Black women in 2001 (CDC 2002). The Men of African American Legacy Empowering
      Self (MAALES) Project is an intervention, designed to reduce HIV risk-related behaviors among
      African American men who have sex with men and women (MSMW) in Los Angeles.

      We propose to test the efficacy of the Men of African American Legacy Empowering Self
      (MAALES) Project, a newly developed, novel, and culturally congruent intervention designed to
      reduce HIV risk-related behaviors and improve psychosocial outcomes. The MAALES intervention,
      which originally pilot tested with 50 men using funds from the University of California's
      University wide AIDS Research Program (UARP), is guided by the Theory of Reasoned Action and
      Planned Behavior (9; 10), the Critical Thinking and Cultural Affirmation (CTCA) Model
      developed by a collaborating community-based organization (11), and the Empowerment Theory
      (12). The small group MAALES intervention was developed through an extensive formative
      research process and involves six two-hour group sessions held over three weeks and lead by
      two ethnically matched co-facilitators. In the proposed study, we will conduct a Phase 2a
      test of an enhanced version of the intervention with a total of 350-400 MSMW, evenly
      randomized to intervention and wait listed control conditions. The enhanced intervention
      includes two booster sessions conducted at 1.5- and 4.5-months post conclusion of the six
      sessions and dialogues regarding assumptions about prospective partners' HIV serostatus.
      Post-intervention survey assessments will occur immediately (for psychosocial outcomes and
      mediators) and at three and six months post conclusion of the intervention (for all outcomes
      and mediators). This project will be among the first to develop and test an HIV
      risk-reduction intervention designed specifically for African American MSMW.

      The Primary Specifics Aims are to:

        1. Determine the impact of the MAALES intervention on: (a) HIV-related sexual risk
           behaviors and (b) sex under the influence of drugs and alcohol among African American
           MSMW.

             1. Hypothesis: Compared to the control condition, the MAALES Intervention condition
                will be more effective in decreasing episodes of unprotected anal and vaginal
                intercourse and number of intercourse partners at the 3- and 6-month post
                assessments.

             2. Hypothesis: Compared to the control condition, the MAALES Intervention condition
                will be more effective in decreasing the number of episodes of drug and alcohol use
                prior to or during sex at the 3- and 6-month post assessments.

        2. Determine the impact of the MAALES intervention condition on psychosocial outcomes,
           including reducing HIV stigma and increasing racial/cultural pride among African
           American MSMW.

      Hypothesis: Compared to the control condition, the MAALES Intervention condition will be more
      effective in decreasing HIV stigma and improving racial/cultural pride at the immediate, 3-
      and 6-month post assessments.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduced HIV-related risk sexual behaviors</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Determine the impact of the MAALES Intervention on (a) HIV- related sexual risk behaviors and (b) sex under the influence of drugs and alcohol among African American MSMW.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Internalized Homophobia</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Examine whether reductions in internalized homophobia and gender role conflicts act as mediators of the effect of the MAALES Intervention condition on HIV risk behaviors (i.e., unprotected sexual intercourse and sex under the influence of drugs).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychological distress</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Examine whether psychological distress (i.e., depression and anxiety) predicts for risky sexual behaviors and moderates the MAALES intervention condition's efficacy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Psychosocial outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Determine the impact of the MAALES Intervention condition on psychosocial outcomes including reducing stigma and increasing racial/cultural pride among African American MSMW.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">437</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>6-session, small group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Men of African American Legacy Empowering Self (MAALES) Intervention, a six-session, theoretically grounded, small-group intervention held over 3 weeks. Includes an additional 2 booster sessions at 6 and 18 weeks following Session 6.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>HIV Education &amp; Risk Reduction Session</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>20-30 minute standard, client-centered HIV education and risk-reduction session administered over the phone or in person. Similar to that received during pre-test counseling for HIV testing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Men of African American Legacy Empowering Self</intervention_name>
    <description>Small group intervention. 6 main sessions + 2 booster sessions. Each session lasts 2 hours. Main sessions held over 3 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>6-session, small group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MAALES</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard HIV Education &amp; Risk Reduction</intervention_name>
    <description>Single, individual counseling and education session. Lasting 20-30 minutes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>HIV Education &amp; Risk Reduction Session</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Standard HERR Counseling Session</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Self-identified man of African descent (black)

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  English speaking

          -  Has had sex (oral, anal, mutual masturbation) with man or with a male-to-female
             transgender within the past 24 months.

          -  Has had sex (oral, anal, mutual masturbation) with a woman within the past 24 months.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Participated in another HIV prevention study, in a small-group HIV prevention program
             or HIV prevention case management in the prior 6 months.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nina Hawara, MPH, Ph. D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Charles Drew University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John K. Williams, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cleo Manago</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>AmASSI Health and Cultural Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sergio Avina</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>JWCH Institute, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kevin Pickett</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Palms Residential Care Facility</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>JWCH Institute, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90013</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charles Drew University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90059</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Williams JK, Ramamurthi HC, Manago C, Harawa NT. Learning from successful interventions: A culturally congruent HIV risk-reduction intervention for African American men who have sex with men and women. Am J Public Health. 2009 Jun;99(6):1008-12. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.2008.140558. Epub 2009 Apr 16.</citation>
    <PMID>19372517</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bingham TA, Harawa NT, Williams JK. Gender role conflict among African American men who have sex with men and women: associations with mental health and sexual risk and disclosure behaviors. Am J Public Health. 2013 Jan;103(1):127-33. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.2012.300855. Epub 2012 Nov 15.</citation>
    <PMID>23153143</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Harawa NT, Williams JK, McCuller WJ, Ramamurthi HC, Lee M, Shapiro MF, Norris KC, Cunningham WE. Efficacy of a culturally congruent HIV risk-reduction intervention for behaviorally bisexual black men: results of a randomized trial. AIDS. 2013 Jul 31;27(12):1979-88.</citation>
    <PMID>24180003</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 9, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 14, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 15, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 10, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 10, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 11, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Charles Drew University of Medicine and Science</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nina Harawa</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Men who have sex with Men and Women</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Behavioral Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Condom use</keyword>
  <keyword>African American MSMW</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

