<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01499316</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>426/11</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01499316</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Investigating the Effects of Hyperoxia on Fractional Flow Reserve</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigating the Effects of Hyperoxia on Fractional Flow Reserve in Patients With Moderate Coronary Artery Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bayside Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bayside Health</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Coronary artery disease (CAD) is a condition which refers to the narrowing of the small blood
      vessels that supplies blood and oxygen to the heart. It is a common cause of chest-pain
      related symptoms and as a result of a 'heart attack'. In most cases, to assess the severity
      of the disease is to use coronary angiography, which is a medical imaging technique that uses
      contrast (a dye) and x-ray to show the blood-flow supply of the coronary arteries.

      The optimal treatment for patients with symptomatic coronary disease is aggressive medical
      therapy. Current guidelines recommend patients with symptomatic CAD and severe disease on
      angiography undergo revascularisation therapy, which aims to restore blood flow to blocked
      arteries. This can be done by either percutaneous coronary intervention (feeding a small
      balloon or other device on a thin tube through blood vessels to the point of blockage and
      then inflate the balloon to open the artery), or coronary artery bypass grafting (open-heart
      surgery)2.

      For many symptomatic patients who have only moderate disease on angiography, further
      functional testing is required to assess the extent of the blockage. This can be achieved by
      placing a pressure wire to the artery of interest, to determine the likelihood that the
      blockage impedes oxygen delivery to the heart muscle, known as the Fractional Flow Reserve
      (FFR)3. FFR is commonly performed at the Alfred hospital in the assessment of such patients.
      During an FFR procedure, further information regarding the health of the small arteries of
      the heart can be obtained with the calculation of the index of micro-vascular resistance
      (IMR),

      Giving oxygen to patients with CAD is a common clinical practice, especially to all patients
      in the catheterisation laboratory whose had a 'heart attack' and often administered
      concurrently with light sedation during elective procedures.

      Recently, however, the safety of routine supplemental oxygen in patients with CAD has been
      questioned5. A research study analysed the outcomes of three small randomised studies on
      oxygen in patients who experienced a 'heart attack', while suggestive of harm, the findings
      of the study remain inconclusive.

      There may also be deleterious effects of supplemental oxygen, on more stable patients with
      CAD, who are not experiencing a 'heart attack'. Supplemental oxygen administered in the
      catheterisation laboratory to patients with stable CAD, has been shown to significantly
      reduce coronary artery blood flow and increase its resistance6-8. It has also been shown to
      reduce cardiac output and effect the relaxation phase of the heart cycle. Based on this data
      it is hypothesised that supplemental oxygen may affect FFR in patients with moderate CAD. The
      investigators therefore propose to undertake a study of the effects of supplemental oxygen on
      FFR in patients with moderate CAD.

      The patients enrolled into the study will be scheduled for an elective normal contrast
      diagnostic or interventional procedure as part of their clinically-indicated care. Once a
      moderate blockage of the artery has been identified, FFR and IMR will be measured. During the
      first phase of the FFR study, the patient will breathe room air and have a blood test to
      measure their oxygen level (blood gas). There is a 3 minute washout period, followed by the
      second phase, whereby the patient will be given 100% oxygen for 10 minutes and have another
      blood gas measured.

      The study will be conducted at Alfred Hospital with a total enrollment of 18 subjects. The
      estimated time to complete enrollment is 6-10 months.

      Data collected on each patient will include demographics, medical history, vital signs (heart
      rate, blood pressure, height, and weight), usage of cardiovascular medications, pathology
      results and procedural records. Any adverse events or serious adverse events related to the
      study procedure will also be recorded.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Fractional flow reserve</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of inpatient stay 2-3 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>index of micro-vascular resistance</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of inpatient stay 2-3 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High Flow oxygen</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>10 minute of 10/L min of inhaled oxygen with reservoir bag.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Room Air</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High Flow oxygen</intervention_name>
    <description>10 minute shigh flow oxygen</description>
    <arm_group_label>High Flow oxygen</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Room Air</intervention_name>
    <description>Room air breathing</description>
    <arm_group_label>Room Air</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults ≥ 18 years of age, AND

          -  Undergoing elective coronary angiography

          -  Evidence of moderate (40%-79%) stenosis, requiring further routine assessment with
             FFR.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute coronary syndrome

          -  Hypoxia with oxygen saturation measured on pulse oximeter &lt; 94% with the patient
             breathing air

          -  Altered conscious state

          -  Evidence of left ventricular failure or cardiogenic shock

          -  Unable to perform consent prior to procedure

          -  Known hypersensitivity to adenosine

          -  Sick sinus syndrome, second or third degree atrioventricular (A-V) block (except in
             patients with a functioning artificial pacemaker).

          -  Chronic Obstructive lung disease COPD or asthma

          -  Long QT syndrome

          -  Severe hypotension

          -  Concomitant use of dipyridamole
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Alfred Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Melbourne</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3004</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David M Kaye, MBBS PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>James Shaw, MBBS Phd</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Stephen Duffy, MBBS PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dion Stub, MBBS</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 5, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 22, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 26, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 6, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 6, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 10, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Coronary artery disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Fractional flow reserve</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperoxia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

