<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01493518</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20110105</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01493518</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, Pharmacodynamics, and Clinical Effects of AMG 557 in Adults With Psoriasis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Multiple-dose Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics, Pharmacodynamics, and Clinical Effects of AMG 557 in Subjects With Moderate to Severe Psoriasis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Amgen</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to study the safety, tolerability and immunogenicity of AMG 557
      following multiple subcutaneous dose administration in adults with moderate to severe
      psoriasis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Sponsor decision
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>November 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the number of adverse events per subject, including clinically significant changes in physical examinations, safety lab tests, ECG, vital signs, or immunogenicity to AMG 557</measure>
    <time_frame>28 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the efficacy of AMG 557 as measured by the proportion of subjects with a PASI 50, 75 and 90 at week 28</measure>
    <time_frame>28 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure the area under the serum concentration curve versus time of AMG 557 after multiple dose administration in subjects with moderate to severe psoriasis</measure>
    <time_frame>28 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure the peak serum concentration (Cmax) of AMG 557 after multiple dose administration in subjects with moderate to severe psoriasis</measure>
    <time_frame>28 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Psoriasis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PLACEBO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AMG 557</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AMG 557 or PLACEBO</intervention_name>
    <description>Multiple subcutaneous doses of AMG 557 or Placebo on Days 1, 8, 15, 29, 43, 57 and 71.</description>
    <arm_group_label>PLACEBO</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>AMG 557</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must sign an Institutional Review Board (IRB)-approved informed consent form
             (ICF) before any study specific procedures.

          -  Diagnosis of moderate to severe plaque PsO for at least 6 months prior to screening as
             defined by:

               -  A minimum PASI score of ≥ 10 obtained at screening;

               -  Psoriasis involving ≥ 10% of the Body Surface Area (BSA) at screening.

          -  Received at least 1 previous phototherapy or systemic PsO therapy (but not within the
             30 days before study drug administration), or has been a candidate to receive
             phototherapy or systemic PsO therapy in the opinion of the PI.

          -  Stable treatment without topical or systemic steroids, topical or systemic retinoids,
             vitamin D analogues (Dovenex), Psoralen Ultraviolet A (PUVA) therapy, Ultraviolet A
             (UVA) therapy or Ultraviolet B (UVB) therapy, methotrexate, or cyclosporine for at
             least 60 days prior to IP administration. Stable treatment of PsO involving scalp,
             axillae, or groin with topical corticosteroids of moderate strength will be allowed.

          -  Agrees to wear clothing that protects from sun exposure for the duration of the study.

          -  Agrees to use sunscreen (SPF of at least 30) on sun-exposed skin for the duration of
             the study.

          -  Male or female subjects between 18 and 55 years of age, inclusive at the time of
             screening.

          -  Body mass index (BMI) between 18 and 35 kg/m2, inclusive, at screening, unless
             considered by the PI and the Amgen Medical Monitor to be at an appropriate value in
             the context of other measured safety parameters.

          -  Able and willing to complete entire study (including skin biopsies) according to study
             schedule.

          -  Additional criteria per protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Diagnosis of guttate, pustular, or other non plaque forms of PsO.

          -  Evidence of skin conditions other than PsO (eg, eczema) during the screening period
             that would interfere with evaluations of the effect of IP on PsO.

          -  Previous receipt of any approved or investigational biologic agent for PsO or other
             medical conditions.

          -  Received PUVA therapy, UVA therapy or UVB therapy ≤ 30 days prior to IP
             administration.

          -  Treatment with any other systemic PsO therapy or oral or parenteral corticosteroids ≤
             30 days prior to IP administration.

          -  Use of high potency topical steroids, topical vitamin A or D analog preparations, or
             anthralin ≤ 30 days prior to IP administration (Note: stable doses &gt; 30 days of low or
             moderate strength topical steroids are permitted only on the scalp, axillae, and groin
             according to the package insert).

          -  Received topical cyclosporin or calcineurin inhibitors such as pimecrolimus (Elidel)
             and tacrolimus (Protopic) ≤ 30 days prior to IP administration.

          -  Received IV or oral calcineurin inhibitors such as tacrolimus (Prograf) ≤ 30 days
             prior to IP administration.

          -  Significant concurrent medical conditions at the time of screening or prior to
             randomization, including:

               -  Uncontrolled hypertension (defined as screening systolic blood pressure
                  measurement of greater than 140 mm Hg or a screening diastolic blood pressure of
                  greater than 90 mm Hg) confirmed by 2 separate measurements during the screening
                  visit;

               -  Unstable angina pectoris;

               -  Congestive heart failure;

               -  Steroid or oxygen dependent chronic obstructive pulmonary disease;

               -  Diagnosis of multiple sclerosis or any other demyelinating disease;

               -  Open cutaneous ulcers;

               -  Uncontrolled diabetes (HbA1c &gt; 7%).

          -  History of myocardial infarction.

          -  Subjects with two or more cardiovascular risk factors (defined as BMI &gt; 30, BP
             systolic &gt; 140 mm Hg, diagnosis of diabetes, history of cardiovascular event).

          -  Evidence of significant renal insufficiency during the screening period, defined by a
             glomerular filtration rate &lt; 50 mL/min using the Cockcroft and Gault equation:

             72 x Serum Creatinine (in mg/dL) / (140 - Age) x Body Weight (in kg) x [0.85 if
             female]

          -  Evidence of any bacterial, viral, parasitic, or systemic fungal infections during the
             30 days prior to study drug administration (eg, common cold, viral syndrome, flu like
             symptoms).

          -  Evidence of a recent (within 6 months of randomization) infection requiring in patient
             hospitalization or intravenous antibiotics.

          -  Positive test for HIV antibodies, hepatitis B surface antigen, or hepatitis C
             antibodies.

          -  Underlying condition that predisposes the subject to infections (eg, history of
             splenectomy; history of immunodeficiency).

          -  Evidence of past or active tuberculosis on chest x-ray performed during screening (or
             documented evidence on a chest x-ray performed within 6 months prior to planned
             dosing); known tuberculosis antecedents; known exposure (without adequate treatment)
             to a person with active tuberculosis; or positive protein purified derivative (PPD)
             Mantoux skin or serum quantiferon test at screening (without documented history of
             treatment). A positive result is defined as either induration greater than or equal to
             5 mm 48-72 hours after administration (Mantoux) or a positive serum quantiferon test
             result.

          -  History of malignancy.

          -  Evidence of liver disease (eg, serum ALT and AST &gt; 1.5 x the upper limit of normal)
             during screening period.

          -  Donated blood (including blood products) or experienced loss of blood ≥ 500 mL within
             2 months of screening.

          -  Additional criteria per protocol.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Amgen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Birmingham</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35233</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Reno</city>
        <state>Nevada</state>
        <zip>89511</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75231</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Research Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salt Lake City</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.amgentrials.com</url>
    <description>AmgenTrials clinical trials website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>November 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 18, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 14, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 16, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 15, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 15, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 19, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>SAFETY</keyword>
  <keyword>ADULT</keyword>
  <keyword>PSORIASIS</keyword>
  <keyword>INFLAMMATION</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Psoriasis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

