<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01494311</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2010/1046</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01494311</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rapydan Topical Anaesthesia for Arterial Cannulation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Lidocaine/Tetracaine Patch (Rapydan) for Topical Anaesthesia Before Arterial Access: A Double-blind, Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of Vienna</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Cleveland Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Population Health Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of Vienna</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Arterial catheterization is painful and is associated with patient stress and anxiety.
      Analgesia is usually provided by subcutaneous injection of local anesthetic. An alternative
      is topical anaesthesia, such as Rapydan which is a novel topical anesthetic patch containing
      70 mg each of lidocaine and tetracaine. We therefore tested the hypothesis that Rapydan patch
      analgesia is non-inferior to subcutaneous local anesthetic.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Many clinical procedures including arterial and venous punctures, percutaneous venous
      catheter insertion, lumbar puncture, and dermatological procedures are associated with pain
      and consequent patient discomfort.1-2 With the exception of venopuncture, arterial puncture
      is the most common invasive procedure performed on critically ill patients. Also, it is often
      necessary before induction of anaesthesia for invasive measurements of blood pressure and
      collection of arterial blood samples in patients undergoing major cardiac surgery. Injection
      of local anesthetics before insertion causes intra-dermal turgor and can trigger local
      vasoconstriction, both of which reduce puncture success rate.

      An alternative approach is to use topical anesthesia for percutaneous procedures. However,
      intact skin presents a significant barrier to topical anesthetic preparations. Therefore,
      topical anesthetic preparations typically must be applied under occlusive dressings for 45-60
      minutes before vascular access — which is often longer than is clinically practical.

      Rapydan (also known as Synera in the United States) is a novel topical anesthetic patch that
      contains 70 mg each of lidocaine and tetracaine. The central area of each Rapydan patch
      consists of a Controlled Heat Assisted Drug Delivery pod which is designed to allow for
      application just 20 minutes before percutaneous procedures. However, the efficacy of Rapydan
      topical analgesia has yet to be quantified for the more intense pain resulting from arterial
      puncture. We thus compared routine analgesia (subcutaneous injection with 0.5 ml of 1%
      lidocaine) with heated lidocaine/tetracaine patches. Specifically, we tested the hypothesis
      that lidocaine/tetracaine patch analgesia is non-inferior to that provided by subcutaneous
      lidocaine injection for insertion of arterial catheters.

      Ninty patients undergoing elective major cardiac surgery were included in this prospective,
      double blind clinical trial. Patients were randomly assigned to receive either a
      lidocaine/tetracaine patch, followed by subcutaneous injection 0.5 ml of normal saline
      solution or placebo patch, looking identically to the Rapydan patch and subsequent
      subcutaneous injection of 0.5 ml of lidocaine 1%. Pain during arterial catheterization using
      100-mm-long visual analog scale (VAS) was the primary outcome. Other outcomes were pain
      during anesthetic/saline injection and plasma tetracaine concentrations.

      VAS pain scores during arterial puncture were comparable in both groups and Rapydan was
      non-inferior to subcutaneous lidocaine. Pain scores at the time of subcutaneous injection
      were significantly lower (better) in patients assigned to the lidocaine/tetracaine patch than
      to lidocaine (P = 0.001). Plasma tetracaine concentrations never exceeded the detection limit
      of 25 ng/ml at any time in any patient.

      Both the lidocaine/tetracaine patch and subcutaneous injection of lidocaine provided
      comparable pain control during arterial catheter insertion. Subcutaneous lidocaine caused
      discomfort during injection whereas the lidocaine/tetracaine patch required placement 20
      minutes before the procedure. Given adequate time, the patch provided better overall
      analgesia by obviating the need for subcutaneous infiltration.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain during arterial catheterization</measure>
    <time_frame>During and minutes after arterial cannula insertion, day 1.</time_frame>
    <description>After finishing the puncture procedure, patients were asked to rate their worst pain during subcutaneous injection, during insertion of arterial cannula, and one minute after catheter insertion using a 100-mm-long visual analog scale (VAS). The use of a VAS to measure pain and discomfort has been validated in the several settings of chronic pain, acute postoperative pain, and acute non-surgical pain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain during annethetic/saline injection.</measure>
    <time_frame>During and minutes after injection, day 1.</time_frame>
    <description>After finishing the puncture procedure, patients were asked to rate their worst pain during subcutaneous injection, during insertion of arterial cannula, and one minute after catheter insertion using a 100-mm-long visual analog scale (VAS).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood concentration of plasma tetracaine</measure>
    <time_frame>Minutes before and after patch application, day 1.</time_frame>
    <description>Blood for measurement of plasma tetracaine concentrations sampled: 1) before patch application; 2) 15 minutes after patch application; 3) immediately after successful arterial puncture; 4) 30 minutes after patch application; and, 5) 60 minutes after patch application. Only blood samples from patients assigned to the tetracaine/lidocaine patch were analyzed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>At conclusion of procedure, day 1.</time_frame>
    <description>Patients also subjectively rated their procedure-related satisfaction on a four-point scale: 0 = unsatisfied; 1 = moderately satisfied; 2 = satisfied; and, 3 = very satisfied.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Investigator's evaluatuion of pain during catheter insertion</measure>
    <time_frame>At conclusion of procedure, day 1.</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators who were unaware of the randomization estimated each patient's pain intensity at the time of catheter insertion on a four-point scale with 0 indicating no pain and 3 indicating severe pain.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difficulty of puncture</measure>
    <time_frame>During catheter insertion, day 1.</time_frame>
    <description>The difficulty of the puncture was assessed using a 5-point scale with 1 being insertion at first attempt through 5 which indicated failure to insert the catheter.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of punctrue attempts</measure>
    <time_frame>During catheter insertion, day 1.</time_frame>
    <description>The number of puncture attempts were documented by the investigator.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of edema and erthema at the patch site</measure>
    <time_frame>Evaluated immediately after patch removed, day 1.</time_frame>
    <description>After the patches were removed an investigator, blinded to the study randomization, evaluated the treatment sites for skin reactions including edema and erythema using a 5-point Likert scale (1 = none; 5 = vigorous).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">90</enrollment>
  <condition>Arterial Catheterization</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo patch and lidocaine injection</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fourty-five patients were randomly assigned to receive a placebo patch, looking identically to the Rapydan patch and subsequent subcutaneous injection of 0.5 ml of lidocaine 1%.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lidocaine/tetracaine patch</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fourty-five patients were randomly assigned to receive a lidocaine/tetracaine patch, followed by subcutaneous injection 0.5 ml of normal saline solution.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lidocaine/tetracaine patch</intervention_name>
    <description>The lidocaine/tetracaine patch topical anesthetic patch contains 70 mg each of lidocaine and tetracaine. The central area of each patch consists of a Controlled Heat Assisted Drug Delivery pod which is designed to warm the skin to 26-34°C, theoretically enhancing drug absorption and allowing application just 20 minutes before percutaneous procedures. A active or placebo patch was placed on each patient's wrist in the region of the maximum radial artery pulsation. After 20 minutes, the patch was removed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lidocaine/tetracaine patch</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Rapydan</other_name>
    <other_name>Synera, 76667213</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Patch</intervention_name>
    <description>A placebo patch was placed on each patient's wrist in the region of the maximum radial artery pulsation. After 20 minutes, the patch was removed.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo patch and lidocaine injection</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Subcutaneous injection of 0.5 ml Lidocain 1%</intervention_name>
    <description>After removing the patch, a blinded investigator injected 0.5 ml of 1% lidocaine solution. Three minutes after injection, an attempt was made to cannulate the radial artery with a 20-gauge catheter.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo patch and lidocaine injection</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Subcutaneous injection of saline</intervention_name>
    <description>After removing the patch, a blinded investigator injected 0.5 ml saline solution. Three minutes after injection, an attempt was made to cannulate the radial artery with a 20-gauge catheter.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lidocaine/tetracaine patch</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients having elective valve-replacement or coronary artery bypass grafting
             requiring arterial access before induction of anaesthesia.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  analgesic use within 24 hours before surgery

          -  injury or infection at the planned puncture site

          -  known allergy to local anesthetics

          -  drug abuse

          -  alcoholism or psychiatric disorders

          -  childbearing potential without adequate birth control

          -  abnormal Allen's test
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cleveland Clinic Department of Outcomes Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cleveland</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44195</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of Vienna</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Population Health Research Institute, McMaster University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 15, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 15, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 16, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 15, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 15, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 18, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of Vienna</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kurt Rutzler</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Arterial catheter</keyword>
  <keyword>arterial cannula</keyword>
  <keyword>Rapydan</keyword>
  <keyword>lidocaine/tetracaine patch</keyword>
  <keyword>topical anaesthesia</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lidocaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tetracaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

