<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02338193</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RP-14-012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02338193</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dapagliflozin and Metformin,Alone and in Combination, in Overweight/Obese Prior GDM Women</brief_title>
  <acronym>DAPA-GDM</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized Study Evaluating Dapagliflozin and Metformin, Alone and in Combination, in Overweight Women With a Recent History of Gestational Diabetes Mellitus: Effects on Anthropometric Measurements and Cardiometabolic Abnormalities</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Woman's</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>AstraZeneca</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Woman's</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Women with a history of gestational diabetes (GDM) are at substantially increased risk of
      type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM). Compared with the general population, these women are more
      likely to be overweight or obese. Moreover, weight gain after GDM is significantly associated
      with T2DM, independent of baseline body weight. Weight gain, particularly increased central
      adiposity after delivery, is strongly associated with deterioration of β-cell compensation
      for insulin resistance. Taken together, our findings and other studies support increased
      abdominal fat as the strongest factor associated with declining B-cell compensation for
      insulin resistance in prior GDM women at high risk for T2DM. Dapagliflozin is a novel highly
      selective SGLT2 inhibitor that improves glycemic control by reducing renal glucose
      reabsorption leading to urinary glucose excretion. Its efficacy and safety has been studied
      in multiple randomized controlled trials including an add-on to metformin compared with a
      placebo. To the extent that glucotoxicity contributes to the demise in β-cell function in
      subjects with impaired glucose, SGLT2 inhibitors also may prove useful in the treatment of
      &quot;prediabetes.&quot; An additional secondary benefit of SGLT2 inhibition is the elimination of
      calories in the form of glucose. The loss of glucose with attendant caloric loss contributes
      to weight loss; in addition, improvements in β cell function have been seen. Weight loss seen
      with SGLT2 inhibitors is similar to that seen with glucagon-like peptide 1 analogs, and may
      be more acceptable because they are oral agents. A consistent finding in all dapagliflozin
      studies has been a reduction in blood pressure. The investigators hypothesize that
      combination dapagliflozin -metformin treatment over a 24-week period will have a greater
      positive impact on body weight, anthropometric measurements and glycemic and cardiometabolic
      parameters than dapagliflozin or metformin monotherapy in overweight/obese at-risk women with
      a history of GDM.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Following written consent, all study patients will undergo the following clinical, metabolic
      and laboratory evaluations before and during treatment. To ensure that patients remain
      unidentified, all study subjects will be assigned an individual study identifier which
      includes the study acronym, patient initials, and unique number. All blood samples will be
      obtained and results identified and reported using this unique study identifier. A full
      physical examination will be performed and vital signs (blood pressure, respiration and
      temperature) determined. Trained personnel using standardized protocols at the baseline and
      follow-up examination will obtain anthropometric measurements and blood specimens. Absolute
      body weight, height, waist and hip circumference, body fat distribution (waist/hip {WHR}) and
      waist/height ratio ({WHtR}) and blood pressure (BP) will be determined. Body weight will be
      measured to the nearest 0.1 kg using a calibrated digital scale with participants in light
      clothing and no shoes. Height will be measured to the nearest centimeter. The total body
      adiposity (total fatness), defined as the accumulation of body fat without regard to regional
      distribution, will be expressed as BMI and calculated as weight (kg)/ height (m) 2. The
      circumference measurements will be taken in the upright position using a 15-mm width flexible
      metric tape held close to the body but not tight enough to indent the skin. Waist
      circumference (WC) will be measured at the narrowest level midway between the lowest ribs and
      the iliac crest and hip circumference measured at the widest level over the buttocks while
      the subjects are standing and breathing normally. The WHR and WHtR will be calculated for
      measure of body fat distribution.

      All patients will randomly be assigned to one of 3 medication treatment groups--
      dapagliflozin-metformin (DAP-MET; 5 mg DAP/ MET 1000 mg BID), metformin XR (MET 1000 mg BID)
      or dapagliflozin (DAP 10 mg QD); all subjects will be allocated to one of these 3 groups
      based on computer-generated random numbers using a block randomization method. Oral glucose
      tolerance tests (OGTTs) with glucose (G) and insulin (I) measured at 0, 30, 60, and 120 after
      glucose load to assess diabetes, fasting (FBG) and mean blood glucose (MBG) concentrations,
      insulin resistance and pancreatic ß-cell function will be performed prior to randomization
      and at 20-24 weeks after full doses of study medications are reached. Mean blood glucose
      (MBG) concentrations will be calculated by summing glucose values obtained at 0,30,60 and 120
      minutes during the OGTT and dividing by 4. At the initial lab evaluation, creatinine and
      calculated eGFR, TSH, and ß-hCG will be determined for study inclusion. Baseline blood
      samples will also be analyzed for lipid profiles and liver enzymes.

      All patients will receive the same counseling concerning the benefits of lifestyle
      modification through diet and exercise. The patients will be also encouraged to increase
      daily exercise (such as walking, using stairs), although this will not be formally assessed.
      The participants will receive further encouragement to adhere to the regime during follow-up
      phone calls. Side effects of the treatment and reason for any withdrawals from the study will
      be recorded.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 22, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change in body weight</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline (time 0) to study end (24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Change in percent body weight with combination therapy compared to monotherapy from baseline to week 24</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measures of insulin sensitivity and secretion</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in composite indexes from baseline (time 0) to study end (24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Surrogate measures of insulin action derived from OGTT [insulin sensitivity index (HOMA-IR, Matsuda index), corrected early insulin secretory response (insulinogenic index/HOMA-IR) and oral disposition index (product of Matsuda index and insulinogenic index; SIOGTT x Δinsulin30-0 min to glucose30-0 min)]</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma lipid fractions</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline (time 0) to study end (24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>measures of plasma lipid fractions</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Creatinine and calculated eGFR</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline (time 0) to study end (24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>renal function evaluation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glycemic control</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline (time 0) to study end (24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>fasting and glucose stimulated levels after an OGTT</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline (time 0) to study end (24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>measures of diastolic and systolic blood pressure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Waist circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline (time 0) to study end (24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>measure of truncal adiposity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Waist-to-height ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline (time 0) to study end (24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>measure of waist divided by height as measure of central adiposity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body mass index</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline (time 0) to study end (24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>measure of overall adiposity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Liver enzymes</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline (time 0) to study end (24 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>changes in ALT and AST levels with treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">72</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Prevention in Women After GDM Who Are at High-risk</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DAPA/MET XR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dapagliflozin plus metformin XR- 5 mg/1000 mg with meal for 4 weeks DAPA/MET XR- 5mg/1000 mg BID final dose for 20 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Dapaglifloxin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dapagliflozin- 10 mg once daily before first meal for 24 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Metformin XR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Metformin XR with 500 mg once a day for 2 weeks, followed by 500 mg twice a day for 2 weeks, followed by 500 mg in the AM, 1000 mg in the PM for 2 weeks, with 1000 mg twice a day as the final dose for 20 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DAPA/MET XR</intervention_name>
    <description>final dose- 5 mg dapagliflozin/1000 mg glucophage XR BID for 20-24 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>DAPA/MET XR</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Xigduo 5mg/1000 mg</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DAPA</intervention_name>
    <description>10 mg dapagliflozin QD for 20-24 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Dapaglifloxin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Farxiga 10 mg</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MET XR</intervention_name>
    <description>1000 mg Metformin XR BID for 20-24 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Metformin XR</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Glucophage XR 500 mg</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  • Overweight/obese (BMI &gt;25) females 18 years to 45 years of age, who experienced
             gestational diabetes (GDM) during recent (within 12 months) pregnancy

               -  postpartum metabolic abnormalities determined by a 75 g oral glucose tolerance
                  test (Inclusive of prior GDM women with impaired fasting glucose (IFG), impaired
                  glucose tolerance (IGT), or both (IFG/IGT) postpartum)

               -  Completed lactation

               -  Using adequate contraception during study period unless sterilized

               -  Written consent for participation in the study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cholestasis during the past pregnancy

          -  Any hepatic diseases in the past (viral hepatitis, toxic hepatic damage, jaundice of
             unknown etiology), gallstones, abnormal liver function tests or renal impairment
             (elevated serum creatinine levels or abnormal creatinine clearance

          -  Presence of significant systemic disease, heart problems including congestive heart
             failure, history of pancreatitis, or diabetes mellitus (Type 1 or 2)

          -  Renal impairment (e.g., serum creatinine levels ≥1.4 mg/dL for women, or eGFR &lt;60)

          -  Significantly elevated triglyceride levels (fasting triglyceride &gt; 400 mg %)

          -  Untreated or poorly controlled hypertension (sitting blood pressure &gt;160/95mm Hg)

          -  Prior history of a malignant disease requiring chemotherapy

          -  Known hypersensitivity or contraindications to use of insulin sensitizers such as
             metformin or thiazolidinediones

          -  History of hypersensitivity reaction to dapagliflozin or other SGLT2 inhibitors (e.g.
             anaphylaxis, angioedema, exfoliative skin conditions)

          -  Current use of metformin, thiazolidinediones, GLP-1 receptor agonists, DPP-4
             inhibitors, SGLT2 inhibitors or weight loss medications (prescription or OTC)

          -  Uncontrolled thyroid disease (documented normal TSH) or hyperprolactinemia

          -  Liver enzymes (serum AST and/or ALT ) levels exceeding more than twice normal lab
             values

          -  Use of drugs known to exacerbate glucose tolerance

          -  History of diabetes or prior use of medications to treat diabetes except GDM

          -  Currently lactating

          -  Eating disorders (anorexia, bulimia) or gastrointestinal disorders

          -  Suspected pregnancy (documented negative serum pregnancy test within 72 hours before
             first dose of study drug), desiring pregnancy in next 6 months, breastfeeding, or
             known pregnancy in last 2 months

          -  Active or prior history of substance abuse (smoke or tobacco use within past 3 years)
             or significant intake of alcohol or history of alcoholism

          -  Patient not willing to use adequate contraception during study period and up to 4
             weeks after last dose of study drug (unless sterilized).

          -  Debilitating psychiatric disorder such as psychosis or neurological condition that
             might confound outcome variables

          -  Inability or refusal to comply with protocol

          -  Not currently participating or having participated in an experimental drug study in
             previous three months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen E Elkind-Hirsch, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Woman's Hospital, Louisiana</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Renee Harris, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Woman's Hospital, Louisiana</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Karen E Elkind-Hirsch, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>225 231-5278</phone>
    <email>karen.elkind-hirsch@womans.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Renee Harris, MD</last_name>
    <phone>225-924-8247</phone>
    <email>renee.harris@womans.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Woman's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baton Rouge</city>
        <state>Louisiana</state>
        <zip>70815</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Karen Elkind-Hirsch, PhD.</last_name>
      <phone>225-231-5278</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ericka Seidemann, MS</last_name>
      <phone>225-231-5275</phone>
      <email>ericka.seidemann@womans.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Karen Elkind-Hirsch, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Renee Harris, M.D.</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 14, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 21, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Woman's</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Karen Elkind-Hirsch</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Research</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>GDM</keyword>
  <keyword>T2DM</keyword>
  <keyword>prediabetes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Overweight</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Will publish findings. Individual patient information will be revealed only to patient</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

