<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02332434</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014-15</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>RCAPHM14_0179</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02332434</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Various Bariatric Surgical Procedures on Intestinal TRL Metabolism in Obese Type 2 Diabetic Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>MISTRAL</acronym>
  <official_title>Effects of Various Bariatric Surgical Procedures on Intestinal Triglyceride-rich-lipoprotein (TRL) Metabolism in Obese Type 2 Diabetic Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique Hopitaux De Marseille</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique Hopitaux De Marseille</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Rational: The world and french epidemic of obesity and diabetes represents a major problem of
      public health. The prevalence in France, in the adult population, is 15 % corresponding to
      6.9 million people for obesity and 6 % corresponding to 3.9 million people for diabetes.
      Morbidly obesity (body mass index 40 kg/m²), the most serious, is more and more frequent.
      Cardiovascular diseases are the first cause of morbidity and mortality. The atherogenic
      dyslipidemia of these insulin-resistant obese type 2 diabetic patients characterized by the
      quartet: elevated plasma triglycerides, low high-density lipoprotein-cholesterol, increased
      proportion of small and dense low-density lipoproteins, is widely explained by the blood
      accumulation of TRL from the liver and the intestine, and represents a major cardiovascular
      risk factor. The overproduction of intestinal TRL (which apoprotein B48 is the specific
      tracer) is a constituent recently recognized of insulin-resistance and the atherogenous role
      of these intestinal TRL has been shown. In view of this important overmortality and the
      failures of the medical, nutritional, dietary and psychotherapeutic combined treatment, the
      bariatric surgery quickly developed. Two main procedures are performed: 1 based exclusively
      on the gastric restriction (the sleeve gastrectomy) and one associating a malabsorption (the
      gastric bypass).

      Objectives: The main objective of this study is to compare the effect of each surgical
      procedure and the differential effect of the 2 bariatric surgery procedures on the production
      and clearance rates of the intestinal TRL. The secondary objectives are to compare the effect
      of each surgical procedure and the differential effect of the 2 bariatric surgery procedures
      on the production and clearance rates of the hepatic TRL and to document the potential links
      between the expected reduction of these productions after the surgery and the loss of weight,
      the improvement of the insulin-sensitivity, the changes in hormones, the decrease of the
      inflammatory state, the changes in energy expenditure, body composition and energy intake.

      Methods: It is a multicentric, prospective, comparative study of cohorts. After
      identification of the eligible subjects, the kinetics (production and clearance rates) of
      intestinal and hepatic TRL will be performed in the hospital, using established stable
      isotope enrichment methodology (5,5,5-D3-L-Leucine), in 2 groups of obese patients (15
      patients per surgery procedure), before and 6 months after the surgery.

      Perspectives: A better understanding of the dyslipidemia of obese type 2 diabetic patients
      and the factors modulating this dyslipidemia may lead to develop new dietary and/or drugs
      and/or surgical treatments targeted at the enterocyte to improve the lipid profile of these
      patients and reduce the incidence of cardiovascular diseases. Moreover, a differential effect
      between the 2 surgical procedures could help to choose the best surgical procedure for obese
      type 2 diabetic patients depending on the lipid profile at baseline.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>production and clearance rates of intestinal and hepatic TRL, in 2 groups of obese patients (15 patients per surgery procedure), before and 6 months after the surgery.</measure>
    <time_frame>7 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>sleeve gastrectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>bariatric surgery procedure based exclusively on the gastric restriction (the sleeve gastrectomy).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>gastric bypass</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>bariatric surgery procedure associating a malabsorption (the gastric bypass).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>stable isotope enrichment methodology (5,5,5-D3-L-Leucine)</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>sleeve gastrectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>gastric bypass</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject with a body mass index between 35 and 60 kg / m²

          -  Subject with no contradiction to the 2 surgical techniques studied: Sleeve Gastrectomy
             and Gastric Bypass

          -  Subject with type 2 diabetes as defined

          -  Subject not having presented cardiovascular events (myocardial infarct, stroke,
             peripheral ischemia) in the previous 6 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Urielle Desalbres</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Assistance Publique Hôpitaux Marseille</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sophie Beliard, MD</last_name>
    <email>sophie.beliard@ap-hm.fr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Assistance Publique Hôpitaux Marseille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marseille</city>
        <zip>13005</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sophie BELIARD, MD</last_name>
      <email>sophie.beliard@ap-hm.fr</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 5, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 5, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 6, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 16, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 16, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 17, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

