<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02331238</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PRO14020618</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02331238</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of a Middle School Coach Gender Violence Prevention Program</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cluster-Randomized Trial of a Middle School Coach Gender Violence Prevention Program</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pittsburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pittsburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This cluster-randomized school-based study will examine the effectiveness of a program for
      the primary prevention of perpetration of teen dating violence and sexual violence among
      middle school male athletes. Engaging men and boys in preventing violence against women and
      girls is recognized by major global health organizations as a critical public health
      strategy. &quot;Coaching Boys into Men&quot; is a theory- and evidence based program intended to alter
      gender norms that foster teen dating violence/sexual violence perpetration, promote bystander
      intervention, and reduce teen dating violence/sexual violence perpetration. Coaches receive a
      60-minute training and biweekly check-in from a violence prevention advocate to administer
      the intervention to their athletes via 12 mini-lessons conducted weekly throughout a sport
      season. In a randomized trial of program effectiveness among high school athletes (Centers
      for Disease Control and Prevention CE001561-01, PI Miller), male athletes receiving the
      program demonstrated increased positive bystander intervention behaviors and less verbal
      abuse perpetration compared to controls. This project seeks to test the effectiveness of this
      program with younger male athletes in grades 6-8.The innovations are three-fold: (1) testing
      the efficacy of a novel teen dating violence/sexual violence prevention program for middle
      school male athletes; (2) training athletic coaches in Teen Dating Violence/Sexual Violence
      prevention thus implementing primary prevention that does not rely on teachers or classroom
      time; and (3) integrating the goal of changing gender norms with the technique of a bystander
      intervention approach to reduce teen dating violence/sexual violence prevention. The
      experimental design involves a 2-armed cluster randomized- controlled trial in 41 middle
      schools (38 clusters) in Pennsylvania. Schools will be randomly assigned to either
      intervention or control (standard coaching) condition. Coaches in intervention schools will
      receive Coaching Boys into Men training. Baseline surveys will be collected for all
      intervention and control site athletes entering grades 6-8 at the start of each sports
      seasons across Year 1 (Time 1; N= 973 athletes). Follow up surveys will be collected at the
      end of each sports season (Time 2). All participating athletes will be re-surveyed 12 months
      after baseline (Time 3).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 10, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Positive Bystander Behavior from Baseline to Follow Up</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of past 3 month positive bystander behavior in athletes when witnessing disrespectful and harmful behavior among peers comparing baseline and follow up summary scores. Athletes report if they have witnessed peers' abusive behaviors in the past 3 months and if witnessed, how they responded (whether they intervened to interrupt the behavior)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Recognition of Abusive Behavior from Baseline to Follow Up</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Recognition of disrespectful and harmful behaviors against girls as abusive comparing baseline and follow up mean scores on the recognition of abusive behavior scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Gender Equitable Attitudes Scale from Baseline to Follow Up</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of gender-equitable attitudes comparing baseline and follow up mean scores on the gender attitudes scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Intentions to Intervene from Baseline to Follow Up</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proclivity to intervene when witnessing disrespectful and harmful behaviors among peers comparing baseline and follow up mean scores on a scale assessing likelihood of trying to stop disrespectful behaviors among peers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in self-reported recent (past 3 month) perpetration of Teen Dating Violence/Sexual Violence at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of Teen Dating Violence/Sexual Violence perpetration comparing baseline summary score with follow up 12 month summary score (whether participants have perpetrated acts of Teen Dating Violence or Sexual Violence towards anyone)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">973</enrollment>
  <condition>Violence</condition>
  <condition>Abuse</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control School</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Control schools (where the coaches do not receive the &quot;Coaching Boys into Men&quot; training until following academic year ;wait list control)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention School</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention schools (where coaches receive the Coaching Boys into Men training at start of each sports season).
&quot;Coaching Boys into Men&quot; program consists of 60 minute training for high school coaches led by a violence prevention advocate to introduce coaches to the rational for Coaching Boys into Men and the Coaching Boys into Men Coaches Kit. The coaches use this Coaching Boys into Men toolkit to provide weekly discussions with their athletes (generally 10-15 minute mini-sessions) throughout their athletic season (11 weeks). Discussion topics include how to prevent disrespectful and harmful behaviors towards women and girls and how to promote healthy choices and relationships among youth.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>&quot;Coaching Boys into Men&quot; program</intervention_name>
    <description>&quot;Coaching Boys into Men&quot; program consists of 60 minute training for high school coaches led by a violence prevention advocate to introduce coaches to the rational for Coaching Boys into Men and the Coaching Boys into Men Coaches Kit. The coaches use this Coaching Boys into Men toolkit to provide weekly discussions with their athletes (generally 10-15 minute mini-sessions) throughout their athletic season (11 weeks). Discussion topics include how to prevent disrespectful and harmful behaviors towards women and girls and how to promote healthy choices and relationships among youth.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention School</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        School eligibility:

        Urban and suburban middle schools in the Pittsburgh, PA region with athletics program

        Athlete eligibility:

        Ages 11-14 (grades 6-8), student at a participating middle school, participating in an
        athletic program led by coach participating in the research study

        Exclusion Criteria:

        School Eligibility:

        Middle schools not in the Pittsburgh area

        Athlete eligibility:

        Outside age range, not participating on a sports team at the middle school in which they
        are enrolled
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>11 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Miller, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh, University of Pittsburgh Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15213</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller E, Tancredi DJ, McCauley HL, Decker MR, Virata MC, Anderson HA, Stetkevich N, Brown EW, Moideen F, Silverman JG. &quot;Coaching boys into men&quot;: a cluster-randomized controlled trial of a dating violence prevention program. J Adolesc Health. 2012 Nov;51(5):431-8. doi: 10.1016/j.jadohealth.2012.01.018. Epub 2012 Mar 25.</citation>
    <PMID>23084163</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller E, Tancredi DJ, McCauley HL, Decker MR, Virata MC, Anderson HA, O'Connor B, Silverman JG. One-year follow-up of a coach-delivered dating violence prevention program: a cluster randomized controlled trial. Am J Prev Med. 2013 Jul;45(1):108-12. doi: 10.1016/j.amepre.2013.03.007.</citation>
    <PMID>23790995</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 1, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 5, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 6, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pittsburgh</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Elizabeth Miller</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief, Division of Adolescent and Young Adult Medicine, Children's Hospital, University of Pittsburgh Medical Center</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

