<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02336893</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DI-I-0734-13</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02336893</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Semi-structured Interview PACIENTE Improves Communication With Family Members at the Intensive Care Unit</brief_title>
  <acronym>PACIENTE</acronym>
  <official_title>Result of an Intervention for the Group of Physicians Responsible for Providing Information on the Satisfaction of the Relatives of Patients Hospitalized in an Intensive Care Unit</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fundación Universitaria de Ciencias de la Salud</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fundación Universitaria de Ciencias de la Salud</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess whether a formal training strategy using an interview
      PACIENTE may improve physician's skills and quality of communication with family members at
      the ICU.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction: Effective communication with physicians is an important factor for families at
      intensive care unit. Although physicians should have adequate communication skills, training
      programs are not available that would enable them to enhance this competence. Formal training
      using a semi-structured interview to improve skills and quality of communication was provided
      to physicians in charge of supplying information to families at the intensive care unit
      (ICU).

      Objective: To assess whether a formal training strategy using an interview PACIENTE may
      improve physician's skills and quality of communication with family members at the ICU.

      Methods: A pre- and post- intervention study was designed for a university hospital mixed ICU
      (medical and surgical). Training was provided to 34 resident physicians in charge of giving
      information to families at the ICU using interview PACIENTE. The interview was done
      conjointly with participation in simulated difficult clinical cases with actors posing as
      family members.

      Patient registries: Family satisfaction was assessed with a validated survey, FS-ICU 24, in
      122 and 123 family members pre- and post-intervention training, respectively, on the fourth
      day after patient admission to the ICU. The surveys were identified with consecutive numbers
      and not collected data that would allow subsequent identification of patients or their
      families. After the intervention, structures of interviews were monitored with checklists
      designed for this purpose. The meetings were always in the same place for this activity.

      The surveys were answered on paper and the data included in an SPSS database by one of the
      researchers. Single questions in the 24-FS-ICU survey were analyzed according to the author's
      suggestions with minor modifications. Scores from items 1-6 in the published survey were
      transformed to scores from 0 to 100. The Mann-Whitney U test was used to determine any score
      differences between pre- and post-interventions. Differences of P&lt;0.05 were considered
      statistically significant.

      The sample size was calculated to be 122 participants for pre-intervention and 122
      participants for post-intervention to detect α coefficient of 0.05 and with a power of 0.90.
      The survey was performed in the waiting room and questionnaires were collected immediately;
      thus, there were no missing questionnaires.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Comprehension of the information, measured with the instrument FS-ICU 24. Third question, second part.</measure>
    <time_frame>Four months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the instrument FS-ICU 24. Third question, second part.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adequate time to address concerns and answer questions, measured with the instrument FS-ICU 24. Tenth question, second part.</measure>
    <time_frame>Four months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the instrument FS-ICU 24. Tenth question, second part.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall satisfaction with care, measured with the instrument FS-ICU 24.</measure>
    <time_frame>Four months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the instrument FS-ICU 24.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall satisfaction with decision-making measured with the instrument FS-ICU 24.</measure>
    <time_frame>Four months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the instrument FS-ICU 24.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global survey satisfaction measured with the instrument FS-ICU 24.</measure>
    <time_frame>Four months</time_frame>
    <description>Measured with the instrument FS-ICU 24.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">245</enrollment>
  <condition>Communication</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Family members of patients admitted to the ICU from August to December 2013 that consented to participate in the satisfaction survey and had been in the ICU for 72 h.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Post-intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Family members of patients admitted to the ICU from March to August 2014 that consented to participate in the satisfaction survey and had been in the ICU for 72 h.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Training</intervention_name>
    <description>The final training was provided to a group of 34 residents --from internal medicine, anesthesiology, gynecology, and intensive care-- in charge of giving information to the patient's family members in the ICU. They were trained in the semi-structured interview PACIENTE (Present oneself and greet, Attend and listen, Call diagnosis, Inform treatment, Expose prognosis, Name introductory phrases to bad news, Take time to provide empathetic comfort, Explain an action plan involving the family) conjointly while participating in simulated difficult clinical cases with family members-actors. Four training programs were performed from February to September 2014.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Post-intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  That consented to participate in the satisfaction survey

          -  That whom had been in the ICU for 72 h.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Family members with language barriers (requiring assistance to answer a question in
             writing)

          -  Previous ICU admission within the study period

          -  Patient's death by the fourth day of admission

          -  Proved reasons for risk of judicial proceedings.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Miguel H Coral, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fundación Universitaria de Ciencias de la Salud</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fumis RR, Nishimoto IN, Deheinzelin D. Families' interactions with physicians in the intensive care unit: the impact on family's satisfaction. J Crit Care. 2008 Sep;23(3):281-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jcrc.2007.04.004. Epub 2007 Jul 5.</citation>
    <PMID>18725030</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bailey JJ, Sabbagh M, Loiselle CG, Boileau J, McVey L. Supporting families in the ICU: a descriptive correlational study of informational support, anxiety, and satisfaction with care. Intensive Crit Care Nurs. 2010 Apr;26(2):114-22. doi: 10.1016/j.iccn.2009.12.006. Epub 2010 Jan 27.</citation>
    <PMID>20106664</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Karlsson C, Tisell A, Engström A, Andershed B. Family members' satisfaction with critical care: a pilot study. Nurs Crit Care. 2011 Jan-Feb;16(1):11-8. doi: 10.1111/j.1478-5153.2010.00388.x.</citation>
    <PMID>21199550</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Curtis JR, Engelberg RA, Wenrich MD, Nielsen EL, Shannon SE, Treece PD, Tonelli MR, Patrick DL, Robins LS, McGrath BB, Rubenfeld GD. Studying communication about end-of-life care during the ICU family conference: development of a framework. J Crit Care. 2002 Sep;17(3):147-60.</citation>
    <PMID>12297990</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Azoulay E, Pochard F, Chevret S, Lemaire F, Mokhtari M, Le Gall JR, Dhainaut JF, Schlemmer B; French FAMIREA Group. Meeting the needs of intensive care unit patient families: a multicenter study. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2001 Jan;163(1):135-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11208638</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Brown A, Hijazi M. Arabic translation and adaptation of Critical Care Family Satisfaction Survey. Int J Qual Health Care. 2008 Aug;20(4):291-6. doi: 10.1093/intqhc/mzn013. Epub 2008 Apr 10.</citation>
    <PMID>18403569</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Auerbach SM, Kiesler DJ, Wartella J, Rausch S, Ward KR, Ivatury R. Optimism, satisfaction with needs met, interpersonal perceptions of the healthcare team, and emotional distress in patients' family members during critical care hospitalization. Am J Crit Care. 2005 May;14(3):202-10.</citation>
    <PMID>15840894</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Alexander SC, Keitz SA, Sloane R, Tulsky JA. A controlled trial of a short course to improve residents' communication with patients at the end of life. Acad Med. 2006 Nov;81(11):1008-12.</citation>
    <PMID>17065871</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lorin S, Rho L, Wisnivesky JP, Nierman DM. Improving medical student intensive care unit communication skills: a novel educational initiative using standardized family members. Crit Care Med. 2006 Sep;34(9):2386-91.</citation>
    <PMID>16791111</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Back AL, Arnold RM, Baile WF, Fryer-Edwards KA, Alexander SC, Barley GE, Gooley TA, Tulsky JA. Efficacy of communication skills training for giving bad news and discussing transitions to palliative care. Arch Intern Med. 2007 Mar 12;167(5):453-60.</citation>
    <PMID>17353492</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sullivan AM, Lakoma MD, Billings JA, Peters AS, Block SD; PCEP Core Faculty. Teaching and learning end-of-life care: evaluation of a faculty development program in palliative care. Acad Med. 2005 Jul;80(7):657-68.</citation>
    <PMID>15980082</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fineberg IC. Preparing professionals for family conferences in palliative care: evaluation results of an interdisciplinary approach. J Palliat Med. 2005 Aug;8(4):857-66.</citation>
    <PMID>16128661</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Shaw DJ, Davidson JE, Smilde RI, Sondoozi T, Agan D. Multidisciplinary team training to enhance family communication in the ICU. Crit Care Med. 2014 Feb;42(2):265-71. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0b013e3182a26ea5.</citation>
    <PMID>24105452</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Baile WF, Buckman R, Lenzi R, Glober G, Beale EA, Kudelka AP. SPIKES-A six-step protocol for delivering bad news: application to the patient with cancer. Oncologist. 2000;5(4):302-11.</citation>
    <PMID>10964998</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Azoulay E, Pochard F, Chevret S, Arich C, Brivet F, Brun F, Charles PE, Desmettre T, Dubois D, Galliot R, Garrouste-Orgeas M, Goldgran-Toledano D, Herbecq P, Joly LM, Jourdain M, Kaidomar M, Lepape A, Letellier N, Marie O, Page B, Parrot A, Rodie-Talbere PA, Sermet A, Tenaillon A, Thuong M, Tulasne P, Le Gall JR, Schlemmer B; French Famirea Group. Family participation in care to the critically ill: opinions of families and staff. Intensive Care Med. 2003 Sep;29(9):1498-504. Epub 2003 Jul 10.</citation>
    <PMID>12856124</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wall RJ, Engelberg RA, Downey L, Heyland DK, Curtis JR. Refinement, scoring, and validation of the Family Satisfaction in the Intensive Care Unit (FS-ICU) survey. Crit Care Med. 2007 Jan;35(1):271-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17133189</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Heyland DK, Tranmer JE; Kingston General Hospital ICU Research Working Group. Measuring family satisfaction with care in the intensive care unit: the development of a questionnaire and preliminary results. J Crit Care. 2001 Dec;16(4):142-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11815899</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>January 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 8, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 12, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 13, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 12, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 12, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 13, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Communication Barriers</keyword>
  <keyword>Total Communication Methods</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality Improvement</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality of Health Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Critical Care</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

