<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02335528</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10-504 W74V8H-06-C-0002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02335528</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SimCoach Evaluation: A Virtual Human Intervention to Encourage Servicemember Help-seeking for PTSD and Depression</brief_title>
  <official_title>SimCoach Evaluation: A Virtual Human Intervention to Encourage Servicemember Help-seeking for PTSD and Depression</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>RAND</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>RAND</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      SimCoach, a computer program featuring a virtual human that speaks and gestures in a
      videogame-like interface, is designed to encourage servicemembers, especially those with
      signs or symptoms of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) or depression, to seek help to
      improve their psychological health. The assessment included a formative component assessing
      SimCoach's design, development, and implementation approaches, as well as a summative
      component assessing outcomes among participants in a user experience survey and a randomized
      controlled trial (RCT).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Help-seeking intentions</measure>
    <time_frame>within 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Participants were asked the following question: &quot;How likely is it that you will seek help for issues such as stress, emotional, alcohol, drug, or family problems from the following people in the next month?&quot; and responded using a Likert scale ranging from 1=extremely unlikely to 7=extremely likely.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Perceived barriers to care</measure>
    <time_frame>within 30 days</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects were asked about their perceptions of both stigma-related and practical barriers to seeking help.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>User experience</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately following their interaction with SimCoach or online form (up to 5 min)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants responded to questions about their experience with the tool or the online form.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">333</enrollment>
  <condition>Post-traumatic Stress Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SimCoach intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to the SimCoach intervention arm interacted with &quot;Bill Ford,&quot; a simulated human (avatar) enacted in the SimCoach program. This white male avatar representing himself as an Army veteran who spoke to participants in a conversational manner. Participants interacted with him using a chat interface, where they could type responses to him. Bill Ford asked participants a series of questions that corresponded to validated PTSD or depression screening questionnaires. SimCoach then provided personalized recommendations for a symptom if the user reported experiencing the symptom at one of the two highest frequencies on the response scale. These recommendations consisted of a behavioral recommendation with an accompanying link to a website or online article on the topic.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Content Matched Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants assigned to the Content Matched Control condition arm completed text-based versions of the PCL PTSD screening inventory and PHQ-9 depression screening inventory. These instruments used standard, validated language and did not use the modified conversational versions used in the SimCoach intervention condition. The same personalized recommendations provided to the SimCoach group were provided as conventional text and links. After receiving personalized recommendations, participants completed text versions of primary help-seeking, perceived barriers to seeking help, and secondary outcome (user experience) measures.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>No-Treatment Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants randomized to the No-Treatment Control arm completed measures of the primary outcome (intentions to seek help) prior to being given a choice of SimCoach or the conventional screening administered in the other two arms of the study. After the help-seeking intention questionnaire was administered, participants were told that they would be asked some questions about any PTSD or depression symptoms that they might be having and were given the choice between chatting online with a virtual human or using an online form (options were presented in random order to prevent any influence of ordering on selection of the tool). After either interacting with SimCoach or filling out an online form, participants completed a questionnaire assessing user experience.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SimCoach</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>SimCoach intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years of age and

          -  active duty or Reserve servicemember or National Guard servicemember and

          -  being off duty

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  under the age of 18 years

          -  retired servicemember or not a servicemember

          -  currently on duty

          -  currently incarcerated, on parole, or on probation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>January 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 7, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 8, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 9, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 8, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 8, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 9, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Traumatic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stress Disorders, Post-Traumatic</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

