<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02331082</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>hssnyaya</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02331082</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Integrating Pediatric Care Delivery in Rural Healthcare Systems</brief_title>
  <official_title>Integrating Pediatric Care Delivery in Rural Healthcare Systems</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Possible</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Possible</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Globally, over seven million children under the age of five die each year, although a suite
      of interventions—safe delivery care, neonatal care and resuscitation, and management of
      childhood diarrhea, malnutrition, and pneumonia—can prevent many of these deaths when
      implemented within functioning health systems. This study will include a quasi experimental,
      stepped wedge, cluster-controlled trial of a mobile health care coordination and quality
      improvement intervention designed to facilitate comprehensive health systems strengthening.
      It will do this through training and equipping community-level health care clinics to manage
      chronic diseases through use of the Chronic Care Model, structured quality improvement
      sessions to promote clinical mentorship, and use of an integrated electronic medical record
      to provide real-time data for disease surveillance. The investigators hypothesize that
      improving upon the health system in these ways will lead to a 25% reduction in under-two
      mortality through improved services for the citizens of Achham, Nepal.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Introduction: A central challenge in the delivery of evidence-based interventions to promote
      under-five child survival is the coordination of care across the multiple tiers of the health
      system, from frontline health workers, to primary care clinics, to district hospitals, to
      specialty providers. Additionally, children who survive or avoid once-fatal diseases such as
      congenital and rheumatic heart diseases, prematurity, neurodevelopmental conditions, and
      disabilities sustained from traumatic injuries, are increasingly living well into
      adolescence, young adulthood, and beyond. Healthcare delivery systems in resource-limited
      settings, however, are ill-equipped to manage such patients' care. Mobile technologies,
      coupled with effective management strategies, may enhance implementation and coordination of
      evidence-based interventions, but few controlled trials exist to validate this. Particularly
      lacking are strategies that incorporate mobile technologies in an integrated manner across
      the health system.

      Intervention: We have developed a mobile health care coordination and quality improvement
      intervention within two rural district healthcare systems in Nepal, where the child mortality
      rate is an estimated 82 per 1,000, and coordination of child health care is poor. Firstly,
      the intervention aims to increase the timely engagement in acute care for children under the
      age of five to receive evidence-based World Health Organization protocols aimed at reducing
      child mortality—Integrated Management of Pregnancy and Childbirth, Integrated Management of
      Childhood Illness, Integrated Management of Emergency and Essential Surgical Care, and
      Community-based Management of Severe Acute Malnutrition. Secondly, the intervention aims to
      implement a Chronic Care Model for pediatric patients under the age of twenty suffering from
      a chronic disease (congenital and rheumatic heart disease, diabetes, depression, epilepsy,
      asthma, musculoskeletal and neurodevelopmental disabilities, and pre- and post-surgical
      conditions).

      Analysis: We will conduct a quasi-experimental, stepped-wedge, cluster-controlled trial. The
      primary outcome of this trial will be under-two mortality. We hypothesize a 25% reduction in
      under-two mortality rate during the intervention periods, relative to the control period. We
      hypothesize a 50% improvement in follow-up rates, a 30% improvement in global symptoms score,
      a 20% reduction in disability score, and a 20% reduction in inpatient days in hospital. We
      will use both quantitative and qualitative methods to assess the scalability of the
      intervention in terms of logistics, human resources, costs, and utilization.

      Impact: Rigorous evaluations of systems-level child healthcare interventions are needed to
      drive global healthcare policies and their implementation. The trial proposed here will
      inform the potential impact and scalability of health systems strengthening interventions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Under-two mortality rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
    <description>We expect the intervention will lead to a 25% decrease in under-two mortality in the experimental arm.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Infant mortality rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
    <description>We expect the intervention will lead to a 25% decrease in the infant mortality rate in the experimental arm.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Neonatal mortality rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
    <description>We expect the intervention will lead to a 25% decrease in the neonatal mortality rate in the experimental arm.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Institutional Birth Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
    <description>We expect the intervention will lead to a 25% increase in Institutional Birth Rate among reproductive-age women in the experimental arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antenatal Care Completion Percentage</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
    <description>We expect the intervention will lead to a 25% increase in number of pregnant women completing all 4 antenatal care visits in the experimental arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postpartum contraceptive prevalence rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
    <description>We expect the intervention will lead to a 20% increase in postpartum contraceptive prevalence rate among reproductive age women who have delivered in the past 2 years in the experimental arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preterm delivery rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
    <description>We expect the intervention will lead to 25% fewer preterm births in the experimental arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Low birthweight delivery rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
    <description>We expect the intervention will lead to a 25% reduction in babies born with low birthweights in the experimental arm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of stillbirths</measure>
    <time_frame>Five years</time_frame>
    <description>We expect the intervention will lead to 25% fewer stillbirths in the experimental arm.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">7000</enrollment>
  <condition>Infant Mortality</condition>
  <condition>Under-two Mortality</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Existing healthcare system</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Health System Improvement</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Structured Quality Improvement Chronic Care Model Integrated Electronic Medical Record Solar-powered electrical supply Performance-based financing</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Structured Quality Improvement</intervention_name>
    <description>For structured quality improvement, trained healthcare providers (primarily doctors from referral hospital) will serve as mentors to mid-level providers. The mentors will facilitate on-site trainings of primary care with mid-level providers at the district hospital. Mentors will also travel monthly to the healthcare facilities themselves to provide training both in the direct context of clinical care and to provide feedback based upon surveillance and monitoring data. The focus will be on the techniques from the Institute for Healthcare Improvement's Model for Improvement, including Plan-Do-Study-Act cycles, run charts, and root cause analyses. Finally, they will work with the clinical healthcare staff to identify resource needs from the local government for maintenance, water, electricity, and supplies. These resource needs will be addressed through an integrated supply chain management system across the tiers of the healthcare system.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Health System Improvement</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Clincal Mentorship</other_name>
    <other_name>Supply Chain Management</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Chronic Care Model</intervention_name>
    <description>Senior physicians trained in mentorship of non-physician mid-level providers will provide decision support for mid-level providers in the current district healthcare system with specific protocols for target conditions. We will add the following elements: focus on mid-level, non-physician providers as the primary clinicians within the intervention; intensive Community Health Worker (CHW) outreach for detection, screening, follow-up of patients, and encouragement of patient self-care and behavior change; and focused effort on the seamless care coordination of patients across the tiers of the system. Through trainings of CHWs, much of patient self-management comes in the form of home visits that reinforce clinic and hospital counseling, including risk management and prevention. CHWs will be trained in the counseling of each target condition, with counseling largely occurring in the patients' homes, where much of the challenges of chronic disease management and behavior change lie.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Health System Improvement</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Task-Shifting</other_name>
    <other_name>Healthcare Systems Strengthening</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Integrated Electronic Medical Record</intervention_name>
    <description>Clinical information systems. We are developing a system for tracking patients that integrates across each of the tiers using an electronic medical record. This is a key technology in supporting each of the above delivery system design elements.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Health System Improvement</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Electronic Medical Record</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Solar-powered electrical supply</intervention_name>
    <description>As a component of our comprehensive healthcare systems strengthening intervention, we are installing solar panels at community-level clinics to ensure continuous electrical supply for medical devices and technology.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Health System Improvement</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Solar Panel</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Performance-based financing</intervention_name>
    <description>As part of our healthcare systems strengthening intervention, we have established a performance-based financing agreement with the Government of Nepal that conditionally funds healthcare delivery based on population-level health outcomes and quality healthcare service delivery. In this arrangement, the Government serves as a regulator of healthcare delivery rather than a primary provider of healthcare services.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Health System Improvement</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Existing healthcare system</intervention_name>
    <description>This is the current rural, district-level public sector healthcare infrastructure of rural Nepal that is not strengthened during the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Control</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female

          -  Reproductive age, 15-49 years

          -  Resides within 14 village clusters that comprise experimental/control arms

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>15 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Citrin, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Possible</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Biraj Karmacharya, MBBS, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Duncan Maru, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>1-617-553-4256</phone>
    <email>duncan@possiblehealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Scott Halliday, MS</last_name>
    <phone>1-530-219-8807</phone>
    <email>scott@possiblehealth.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bayalpata Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sanfebagar</city>
        <state>Achham</state>
        <country>Nepal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aradhana Thapa, MPH</last_name>
      <email>aradhana@possiblehealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Bikash Gauchan, MBBS</last_name>
      <email>bikash@possiblehealth.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Citrin, PhD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charikot Primary Health Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bhimeshwor</city>
        <state>Dolakha</state>
        <country>Nepal</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Aradhana Thapa, MPH</last_name>
      <email>aradhana@possiblehealth.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Binod Dangal, MD-GP</last_name>
      <email>binod@possiblehealth.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Citrin, PhD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Nepal</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://possiblehealth.org/</url>
    <description>Possible</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://hsdg.partners.org/</url>
    <description>Healthcare Systems Design Group</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 8, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 31, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 6, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Infant Mortality</keyword>
  <keyword>Under-two mortality</keyword>
  <keyword>Maternal Mortality</keyword>
  <keyword>Implementation Research</keyword>
  <keyword>Health Systems Strengthening</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Disease Management</keyword>
  <keyword>Commuity Health Workers</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infant Death</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

