<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03297619</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>8694</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03297619</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Self-help Books for Social Anxiety</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Trial (RCT) Comparing Acceptance and Commitment Therapy (ACT) and Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT) Self-help Books for Social Anxiety</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Utah State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Utah State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to compare the efficacy and mechanisms of change of two self-help
      books for social anxiety in college students in a randomized controlled trial. One book is
      based on traditional cognitive behavioral therapy and one is based on acceptance and
      commitment therapy.

      This study will test the following hypotheses:

      Hypothesis 1: The CBT and ACT book conditions will both experience decreased social anxiety
      and distress. Life satisfaction and values progress will increase in both conditions.

      Hypothesis 2: The CBT condition will result in greater use of reappraisal, the ACT condition
      will not.

      Hypothesis 3: The ACT condition will result in greater use of defusion and decreased
      psychological inflexibility; the CBT condition will not.

      Hypothesis 4: Changes in experiential avoidance and defusion will predict changes in social
      anxiety and values progress in the ACT condition.

      Hypothesis 5: Changes in reappraisal will predict changes in social anxiety in the CBT
      condition. Change in values progress will be predicted by change in social anxiety in the CBT
      condition.

      Hypothesis 6: The association between social anxiety/negative affect and values progress will
      decrease or disappear in the ACT condition (i.e., decoupling), and remain the same in the CBT
      condition.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigators aim to recruit 100 participants for this RCT (50 per treatment condition).
      This will provide adequate power (0.80) to detect differences between groups of medium effect
      size (d=0.50). Eligibility criteria will include being 18 years of age or older, being a
      current Utah State University (USU) student, not having participated in previous self-help
      studies conducted by the USU Contextual Behavioral Science (CBS) Lab, being interested in
      self-help for social anxiety, and scoring at least a 6 on the Mini-SPIN, a screener for
      social anxiety symptoms. Participants will be recruited via SONA, flyers, online postings,
      classroom announcements, and through a general online screener for various USU CBS Lab
      studies.

      Total study participation will occur over approximately 8 weeks. All study procedures will be
      completed online, on a computer/mobile phone. After completing informed consent, participants
      will complete a baseline survey.

      At the end of the baseline survey, participants will be randomly assigned to use a book based
      on CBT (The Shyness and Social Anxiety Workbook) or on ACT (The Mindfulness and Acceptance
      Workbook for Social Anxiety and Shyness). Note that participants will be asked not to access
      other self-help books during the study duration. Participants will be provided with an 8-week
      reading schedule and a link to the assigned book. Participants will be asked to complete a
      midtreatment survey 4 weeks after the beginning of treatment. The midtreatment survey will
      include questions about adherence. Participants will be asked to complete a posttreatment
      survey 8 weeks after the beginning of treatment. This survey will also ask about adherence
      (reading, use of strategies taught in the book, and exposures). Researcher contact will
      involve reminders to complete assessments, a basic email assistance in identifying and
      responding to any barriers to using the self-help book, and twice-weekly reminders of the
      suggested reading schedule.

      After completing the initial assessment participants will be sent a link to The Mindfulness
      and Acceptance Workbook for Social Anxiety and Shyness if they are assigned to the ACT
      condition, or a link to the Shyness and Social Anxiety Workbook if they are in the CBT
      condition. They will be able to access the book online at any time. Participants will be
      asked to read assigned chapters on an 8-week schedule.

      The primary treatment components in the Mindfulness and Acceptance Workbook for Social
      Anxiety and Shyness are psychoeducation, values and goals, mindfulness, acceptance, defusion,
      and committed action. The book uses writing exercises to identify
      patterns/values/goals/committed action, guided and unguided mindfulness meditations, and
      acceptance exercises.

      The primary treatment components in The Shyness and Social Anxiety Workbook are
      psychoeducation (introducing the cognitive behavioral model), self-assessment (e.g., anxiety
      hierarchy, identifying beliefs, identifying avoidance), cognitive restructuring, situational
      exposure, exposure to physical symptoms, and maintenance/consolidation. The book also
      includes a chapter on motivation and treatment options and a chapter on medication, but these
      were omitted in a previous trial of the book and will also be omitted in the present study.
      There is also a chapter on social skills, which will be omitted in order to keep dosage
      similar between the two books. The book briefly mentions acceptance in the context of
      exposure (e.g., fear will stick around longer after fighting it) but includes no major
      acceptance or mindfulness components.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 16, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 15, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be randomly assigned to one of two active self-help interventions for the duration of the study.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale - Self Report (Fresco et al., 2001)</measure>
    <time_frame>Posttreatment (9 weeks after baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>A self-report measure of fear and avoidance of social situations.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>General Health Questionnaire-12 (Banks et al., 1980; Goldberg, 1978)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, midtreatment (5 weeks after baseline), and posttreatment (9 weeks after baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>A self-report measure of overall psychological distress.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-Reported Outcomes Measurement Information System (PROMIS) Satisfaction with Social Roles And Activities Short Form 8 v2.0 (Hahn et al., 2014)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, midtreatment (5 weeks after baseline), and posttreatment (9 weeks after baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>A self-report measure of social functioning</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Valuing Questionnaire - Progress subscale (Smout, Davies, Burns, &amp; Christie, 2014)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, midtreatment (5 weeks after baseline), and posttreatment (9 weeks after baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>A self-report measure of progress toward personal values.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Believability of Anxious Feelings and Thoughts Questionnaire (Herzberg et al., 2012)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, midtreatment (5 weeks after baseline), and posttreatment (9 weeks after baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>A self-report measure of cognitive fusion as it relates to anxiety.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive Fusion Questionnaire (Gillanders et al., 2014)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, midtreatment (5 weeks after baseline), and posttreatment (9 weeks after baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>A self-report measure of overall cognitive fusion.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Appraisal of Social Concerns Scale (Telch et al., 2004)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, midtreatment (5 weeks after baseline), and posttreatment (9 weeks after baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>A self-report measure of concern regarding negative social outcomes.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Reappraisal and mindfulness items (Goldin, Morrison, Jazaieri, Heimberg, &amp; Gross, 2017)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, midtreatment (5 weeks after baseline), and posttreatment (9 weeks after baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>These items will be used to measure use of cognitive reappraisal and mindful acceptance.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Social Anxiety</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ACT self-help book condition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this condition will be assigned to read The Mindfulness and Acceptance Workbook for Social Anxiety and Shyness by Fleming and Kocovski (2013), a self-help book based on acceptance and commitment therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CBT self-help book condition</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this condition will be assigned to read The Shyness and Social Anxiety Workbook by Antony and Swinson (2008), a self-help book based on cognitive-behavioral therapy for social anxiety.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mindfulness and Acceptance Workbook for Social Anxiety and Shyness</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants assigned to this condition will be asked to read this self-help book over an 8-week period.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ACT self-help book condition</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>The Shyness and Social Anxiety Workbook</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants assigned to this condition will be asked to read this self-help book over an 8-week period (with some chapters omitted).</description>
    <arm_group_label>CBT self-help book condition</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 18 or older

          -  Enrolled at Utah State University

          -  Have not participated in other self-help studies run by the USU CBS Lab

          -  Interested in using self-help book for social anxiety

          -  Scoring at least a 6 on the Mini Social Phobia Inventory (Mini-SPIN), a validated
             social anxiety screening measure

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Exclusion criteria mirror inclusion criteria: below the age of 18, not a student at
             Utah State University, have participated in previous self-help studies run by the CBS
             Lab, not interested in using a self-help book for social anxiety, or scoring a 5 or
             lower on the Mini-SPIN.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Levin, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Utah State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jennifer Krafft, BA</last_name>
    <phone>4359320291</phone>
    <email>jennifer.krafft@aggiemail.usu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Utah State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Logan</city>
        <state>Utah</state>
        <zip>84322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Levin, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>541-531-3892</phone>
      <email>mike.levin@usu.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Levin, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Twohig, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Connor KM, Kobak KA, Churchill LE, Katzelnick D, Davidson JR. Mini-SPIN: A brief screening assessment for generalized social anxiety disorder. Depress Anxiety. 2001;14(2):137-40.</citation>
    <PMID>11668666</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Antony, M. M., &amp; Swinson, R. P. (2008). The shyness and social anxiety workbook. Oakland, CA: New Harbinger Publications, Inc.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fleming, J. E., &amp; Kocovski, N. L. (2013). The mindfulness and acceptance workbook for social anxiety and shyness. Oakland, CA: New Harbinger Publications, Inc.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abramowitz JS, Moore EL, Braddock AE, Harrington DL. Self-help cognitive-behavioral therapy with minimal therapist contact for social phobia: a controlled trial. J Behav Ther Exp Psychiatry. 2009 Mar;40(1):98-105. doi: 10.1016/j.jbtep.2008.04.004. Epub 2008 Apr 26.</citation>
    <PMID>18514614</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fresco DM, Coles ME, Heimberg RG, Liebowitz MR, Hami S, Stein MB, Goetz D. The Liebowitz Social Anxiety Scale: a comparison of the psychometric properties of self-report and clinician-administered formats. Psychol Med. 2001 Aug;31(6):1025-35.</citation>
    <PMID>11513370</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Banks, M. H., Clegg, C. W., Jackson, P. R., Kemp, N. J., Stafford, E. M., &amp; Wall, T. D. (1980). The use of the General Health Questionnaire as an indicator of mental health in occupational studies. Journal of Occupational Psychology, 53, 187-194.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldberg, D. (1978). Manual of the GHQ. Windsor: NFER.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hahn EA, DeWalt DA, Bode RK, Garcia SF, DeVellis RF, Correia H, Cella D; PROMIS Cooperative Group. New English and Spanish social health measures will facilitate evaluating health determinants. Health Psychol. 2014 May;33(5):490-9. doi: 10.1037/hea0000055. Epub 2014 Jan 20.</citation>
    <PMID>24447188</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smout, M., Davies, M., Burns, N., &amp; Christie, A. (2014). Development of the Valuing Questionnaire (VQ). Journal of Contextual Behavioral Science, 3, 164-172. http://doi.org/10.1016/j.jcbs.2014.06.001</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herzberg KN, Sheppard SC, Forsyth JP, Credé M, Earleywine M, Eifert GH. The Believability of Anxious Feelings and Thoughts Questionnaire (BAFT): a psychometric evaluation of cognitive fusion in a nonclinical and highly anxious community sample. Psychol Assess. 2012 Dec;24(4):877-91. doi: 10.1037/a0027782. Epub 2012 Apr 9.</citation>
    <PMID>22486595</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gillanders DT, Bolderston H, Bond FW, Dempster M, Flaxman PE, Campbell L, Kerr S, Tansey L, Noel P, Ferenbach C, Masley S, Roach L, Lloyd J, May L, Clarke S, Remington B. The development and initial validation of the cognitive fusion questionnaire. Behav Ther. 2014 Jan;45(1):83-101. doi: 10.1016/j.beth.2013.09.001. Epub 2013 Sep 18.</citation>
    <PMID>24411117</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schultz LT, Heimberg RG, Rodebaugh TL, Schneier FR, Liebowitz MR, Telch MJ. The appraisal of social concerns scale: psychometric validation with a clinical sample of patients with social anxiety disorder. Behav Ther. 2006 Dec;37(4):392-405. Epub 2006 Aug 4.</citation>
    <PMID>17071216</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Telch MJ, Lucas RA, Smits JA, Powers MB, Heimberg R, Hart T. Appraisal of social concerns: a cognitive assessment instrument for social phobia. Depress Anxiety. 2004;19(4):217-24.</citation>
    <PMID>15274170</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldin PR, Morrison AS, Jazaieri H, Heimberg RG, Gross JJ. Trajectories of social anxiety, cognitive reappraisal, and mindfulness during an RCT of CBGT versus MBSR for social anxiety disorder. Behav Res Ther. 2017 Oct;97:1-13. doi: 10.1016/j.brat.2017.06.001. Epub 2017 Jun 3.</citation>
    <PMID>28654771</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 13, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 25, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 29, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Utah State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Levin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

