<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03291964</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17254</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03291964</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rapid MRI for Acute Pediatric Head Trauma</brief_title>
  <official_title>QuickBrain MRI for Acute Pediatric Head Trauma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Oregon Health and Science University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Oregon Health and Science University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pediatric head trauma is a leading cause of morbidity and mortality for children/adolescents.
      The current standard of care regarding imaging modality when concerned for an acute head
      injury is CT. This exposes children to radiation that may predispose to future malignancy.
      Rapid MRI is a test that eliminates radiation and has expanded uses in multiple other areas.
      This study is evaluating it for pediatric acute head trauma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Initial retrospective study suggests that QbMRI has adequate sensitivity to detect acute
      ciTBIs in children. This preliminary study included all pediatric trauma patients presenting
      to OHSU from 2/2010 through 12/2013 who had both a head CT and QbMRI. The current standard of
      care in the pediatric ICU at OHSU is for patients admitted with an acute head injury to
      undergo routine QbMRI follow up to assess status of the injury rather than a repeat head CT.
      Our study team collected clinical data on these patients that included clinical interventions
      and then de-identified all head CT and QbMRI images for this cohort. The images were then
      independently reviewed by 2 neuroradiology fellows at OHSU (Please refer to Figure 1). The
      sensitivity of QbMRI to detect any radiographic injury was 85% (95% CI: 73, 93), but
      increased when evaluating clinically important TBIs to 100% (95% CI: 89, 100). The largest
      limitation of this study was the variable and often long time interval between acquisition of
      the head CT and QbMRI. The average length of time between the initial head CT and QbMRI was
      27.5 hours with only 41% receiving both imaging tests within 12 hours of each other. Also,
      preliminary data was collected by retrospective review. As such, it is very promising that
      initial study had high sensitivity, but further prospective pilot data with a shorter
      interval between the index and reference test is needed to assess the discrepancy between the
      two types of lesions (radiographic vs clinically important) and feasibility of obtaining
      qbMRI in the setting of acute pediatric head trauma. While this study did not miss any
      clinically important TBIs, on further review of radiographic &quot;missed lesions&quot;, the study
      pediatric neurosurgeon noted signs of a healing bleed. This may suggest that they were
      &quot;missed&quot; because they were healed rather than present and not seen. All patients that did not
      have a lesion identified on QbMRI did not require significant clinical interventions and only
      underwent periods of observation in the hospital. However, this raises the need for a
      prospective trial to obtain QbMRI imaging within the same time frame sequentially after the
      initial head CT.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 3, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity-Specificity</measure>
    <time_frame>within 6 hours from the initial head CT</time_frame>
    <description>Sensitivity-Specificity of Rapid MRI for detection of an intracranial injury</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time from Order to obtaining MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>During initial ER stay within 3 hours from time of entry to the ER</time_frame>
    <description>minutes</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Need for anxiolysis medication (defined as benzodiazepenes for imaging indication)</measure>
    <time_frame>During initial ER stay within 3 hours from time of entry to the ER</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients requiring medication to obtain imaging</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Head Trauma</condition>
  <condition>Image, Body</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Diagnostic Test</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Rapid Brain MRI</intervention_name>
    <description>Children undergoing head CT for evaluation of acute head injury will also undergo rapid brain MRI with GRE sequence that is specific for blood. Their clinical care will not change at all based on the MRI.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All pediatric trauma patients being evaluated with a head CT for acute intracranial injury
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. The patient presents to the pediatric emergency department or trauma system at OHSU or
             is a trauma system transfer patient to OHSU

          2. Age 0-14 years.

          3. Being evaluated for a traumatic head injury and attending physician decides to obtain
             a head CT.

          4. Clinically stable for additional testing: provider deems it safe to obtain a QbMRI in
             the ED without deep sedation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject is from outside hospital and head CT was performed greater than 6 hours prior

          2. Subject is from outside hospital and initial head CT is not in our imaging system for
             review

          3. History of intracranial surgery

          4. History of metallic implants making MRI contraindicated

          5. Decompressive surgery prior to QbMRI
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>14 Years</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Sheridan, MD MCR</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Oregon Health and Science University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David Sheridan, MD MCR</last_name>
    <phone>5034941691</phone>
    <email>sheridda@ohsu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>OHSU</name>
      <address>
        <city>Portland</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97239</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David C Sheridan, MD</last_name>
      <phone>503-494-1691</phone>
      <email>sheridda@Ohsu.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 27, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 21, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 25, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 25, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Oregon Health and Science University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. David Sheridan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Emergency Medicine/Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Wounds and Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Craniocerebral Trauma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

