<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03295435</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>301916</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03295435</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Composition of Functional Tooth Units and Nutrient Intake in Older Men</brief_title>
  <acronym>CHAMP</acronym>
  <official_title>Associations Between the Composition of Functional Tooth Units and Nutrient Intake in Older Men: the Concord Health and Ageing in Men Project.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Sydney</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Sydney</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Various definitions of poor dentition in older adults has been linked with inadequate intake
      of nutrients and poor diet quality. This study aims to look at the associations between poor
      dentition as defined by the composition of functional tooth units, and dietary intake of
      nutrients in community dwelling older men.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Poor dentition, defined by numbers of teeth, functional tooth units or edentulism has been
      previously shown to be associated with poor intakes of nutrients in older adults, including
      but not limited to vitamin C, calcium, fibre, protein, zinc and folate. Similar findings have
      been found when poor dentition is defined by the presence of a prosthesis. Reasons for this
      inverse relationship include poor denture quality, reduced chewing capacity, or the
      inadequacy of prosthesis to replace natural teeth.

      However limited studies have looked at how the composition (natural verses prosthetic) of
      functional tooth units is associated with nutrient intake. A cross sectional analysis of a
      cohort of male older adults, participating in an ongoing longitudinal study, was conducted to
      investigate nutrition and oral health associations, including the relationship between the
      composition of functional tooth units and nutrient intake.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 5, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 13, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 13, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dietary intake of nutrients</measure>
    <time_frame>45 minute interview on 1 day (cross-sectional).</time_frame>
    <description>A diet history was performed, and data entered into a database which provided daily average nutrient intakes.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">781</enrollment>
  <condition>Oral Health of Older Men</condition>
  <condition>Dietary Assessment of Older Men</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Composition of functional tooth units</intervention_name>
    <description>Composition of functional tooth units measured by trained oral health therapists and was categorised into 3 groups:
Group A: Natural units only Group B: Natural &amp; Prosthetic units present Group C: No natural units present</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population is a subset of a ongoing longitudinal study, that start in 2005. Men
        over the age of 70 years on the electoral roll for geographical locations within the Canada
        Bay area of Sydney, NSW were invited to participate. The only exclusion criteria was living
        in an aged care facility at time of recruitment.

        The follow up this study is based on, invited participants to be involved in a fourth wave
        of assessments. Anyone who had moved into an aged care facility was included. However those
        who had moved outside of the Sydney, had died, previously withdrawn or refused to
        participate, (but remained active), were excluded.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Moved inter or intrastate (moved out of study area)

          -  Death

          -  Refused to participate

          -  previously withdrawn
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>78 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Cumming, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Sydney</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Centre for Education and Research on Ageing</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sydney</city>
        <state>New South Wales</state>
        <zip>2234</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.foodstandards.gov.au/science/monitoringnutrients/ausnut/Pages/ausnut2007.aspx</url>
    <description>Nutrient Database used to determine daily nutrient intakes of diet history</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Andrade FB, de França Caldas A Jr, Kitoko PM. Relationship between oral health, nutrient intake and nutritional status in a sample of Brazilian elderly people. Gerodontology. 2009 Mar;26(1):40-5. doi: 10.1111/j.1741-2358.2008.00220.x. Epub 2008 Feb 19.</citation>
    <PMID>18298586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hildebrandt GH, Dominguez BL, Schork MA, Loesche WJ. Functional units, chewing, swallowing, and food avoidance among the elderly. J Prosthet Dent. 1997 Jun;77(6):588-95.</citation>
    <PMID>9185051</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ervin RB, Dye BA. The effect of functional dentition on Healthy Eating Index scores and nutrient intakes in a nationally representative sample of older adults. J Public Health Dent. 2009 Fall;69(4):207-16. doi: 10.1111/j.1752-7325.2009.00124.x.</citation>
    <PMID>19453869</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shinkai RS, Hatch JP, Rugh JD, Sakai S, Mobley CC, Saunders MJ. Dietary intake in edentulous subjects with good and poor quality complete dentures. J Prosthet Dent. 2002 May;87(5):490-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12070511</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ueno M, Yanagisawa T, Shinada K, Ohara S, Kawaguchi Y. Masticatory ability and functional tooth units in Japanese adults. J Oral Rehabil. 2008 May;35(5):337-44. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2842.2008.01847.x.</citation>
    <PMID>18405269</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 24, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 24, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 24, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 24, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 27, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diet</keyword>
  <keyword>Oral Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Nutrition</keyword>
  <keyword>Dentition</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>De-identified data is be available for researchers.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

