<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03296566</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H16-03194</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03296566</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The SAFE Study: Satisfaction and Adherence to Follow-Up With Colposcopy Exams</brief_title>
  <official_title>The SAFE Study: Satisfaction and Adherence to Follow-Up With Colposcopy Exams</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>British Columbia Cancer Agency</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Women's Health Research Institute of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is intended to improve the patient experience of communication of colposcopy
      results and follow-up recommendations to patients. Current practice involves results being
      forwarded from the colposcopy clinic to the family or referring physician who then informs
      the patient. We are testing an intervention informed by focus groups in which a trained
      colposcopy nurse (patient liaison) directly contacts patients with their results and
      follow-up recommendations while providing education and support. We will examine whether this
      intervention improves patient satisfaction, reduces anxiety, and improves rates of adherence
      to follow-up and treatment appointments compared to the current practice.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cervical cancer is the second most commonly diagnosed cancer and third leading cause of
      cancer death in women worldwide. Pre-cancerous cells can be detected with regular Pap smear
      screening and diagnosed and treated with colposcopy. This process is limited by patient
      adherence to the follow-up and treatment recommendations. Currently at Vancouver General
      Hospital (VGH), the largest colposcopy clinic in the province, results are forwarded from the
      colposcopy clinic to the family or referring physician who informs patients of results and
      recommendations. Inefficiencies or errors in this step may cause patient dissatisfaction,
      missed appointments, increased costs, and compromise patient outcomes. The primary objective
      of this study is to examine whether having a trained colposcopy nurse directly contact
      patients with their results and follow-up recommendations while providing education and
      support will improve patient satisfaction and reduce anxiety, with the secondary aim being to
      assess the clinical effectiveness of this intervention in improving rates of adherence to
      follow-up and treatment appointments and potentially long-term clinical outcomes. The first
      phase of the study involves patient focus groups that will be interviewed about what elements
      of a patient liaison interaction are most important (separate Ethics submission). This
      information will inform the development of the patient liaison role and approaches to patient
      interaction to be utilized in the intervention in the second phase. The second phase will
      entail a randomized controlled trial comparing patient anxiety, satisfaction and adherence to
      follow-up between a control group (current practice) versus the intervention group exposed to
      the patient liaison at the VGH Colposcopy Clinic. For the primary aim, a questionnaire
      containing items pertaining to patient anxiety and satisfaction with their experience of
      receiving their colposcopy results will be administered both to the intervention and control
      groups and the mean scores pertaining to anxiety and satisfaction will be compared using
      two-tailed t-tests. For the secondary aim, a chart review at 6-12 months following the
      initial colposcopy visit will examine the rates of compliance with the recommended follow-up
      or treatment visits and histologic diagnoses, and comparisons will be sought between the
      intervention and control groups using z-score test.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 13, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Anxiety</measure>
    <time_frame>To be collected by questionnaire in 4-6 weeks following colposcopy visit</time_frame>
    <description>Mean state anxiety scores as measured by the State Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quantitative satisfaction with colposcopy visit experience including interactions with colposcopy professionals</measure>
    <time_frame>To be collected by questionnaire in 4-6 weeks following colposcopy visit</time_frame>
    <description>Patient satisfaction scores as measured by items in the questionnaire drawn from the VSQ-9 Inventory</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Qualitative satisfaction with colposcopy visit experience including interactions with colposcopy professionals</measure>
    <time_frame>To be collected by questionnaire in 4-6 weeks following colposcopy visit</time_frame>
    <description>Qualitative themes regarding the colposcopy and provider experience drawn from thematic analysis of open-ended questions in the questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Satisfaction with colposcopy information and diagnosis education</measure>
    <time_frame>To be collected by questionnaire in 4-6 weeks following colposcopy visit</time_frame>
    <description>Satisfaction with information and education received regarding colposcopy, patient diagnosis and follow-up recommendations measured by questionnaire items that measure these factors (PSQ-18 Inventory)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timeliness of colposcopy diagnosis results</measure>
    <time_frame>To be collected by questionnaire in 4-6 weeks following colposcopy visit</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure the time interval between colposcopy visit and communication of the results</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient knowledge of own colposcopy diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>To be collected by questionnaire in 4-6 weeks following colposcopy visit</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure the rate of accuracy between the participant self-reported colposcopy diagnosis and actual diagnosis</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to colposcopy treatment and follow-up instructions</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>We will measure rates of follow-up/treatment visit attendance</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Uterine Cervical Dysplasia</condition>
  <condition>Uterine Cervix Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Liaison Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The participants randomized to the intervention group will be exposed to the patient liaison in receiving their colposcopy report results and recommendations. Rather than receive results from their referring/family physician, an experienced colposcopy nurse will contact participants once the colposcopists complete the final colposcopy report. The colposcopy nurse will provide an explanation of the colposcopy results and subsequent follow-up or treatment recommendations, be available to answer patient questions (within her scope), offer educational or support resources to patients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>The control group will receive the standard of care for colposcopy results reporting via their referring physician. Following their colposcopy visit, control patients are given a slip of paper reminding them to call their family/referring physician for their colposcopy results in three weeks if they have not yet been contacted. Upon receipt of the final pathology, colposcopy reports are prepared by the colposcopists and forwarded to family/referring physicians typically within 2-3 weeks of the visit. Patients then receive the results of their colposcopy report from their family/referring physician by whatever method of communication preferred by that provider.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient Liaison</intervention_name>
    <description>An experienced colposcopy nurse will contact participants once the colposcopists complete the final colposcopy report. The colposcopy report will inform the referring provider that these patients will be informed of the results. The colposcopy nurse will provide an explanation of the colposcopy results and subsequent follow-up or treatment recommendations, be available to answer patient questions (within her scope), offer educational or support resources to patients. She will forward any patient questions beyond her scope to the patient's colposcopist who may then provide answers to the patient liaison or to the patient directly depending on the complexity and nature of the question.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Liaison Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Must be 19 years of age or older

          2. Must be patients presenting for an initial visit at the VGH Colposcopy Clinic

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Inability to speak conversational English- required to complete the questionnaire as
             well as provide informed consent to participate

          2. Inability or refusal to provide consent

          3. Pregnant - pregnant women do not usually have biopsies and their subsequent care may
             be much different than non-pregnant patients

          4. Do not have a family physician or referring physician who will provide continuity of
             care following colposcopy - these patients do not have the option of getting results
             from a family or referring physician, so they would bias results.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marette Lee, MD, MPH, FRCSC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marette Lee, MD, MPH, FRCSC</last_name>
    <phone>604-875-4268</phone>
    <email>Marette.Lee@vch.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Susan Keast</last_name>
    <phone>604-875-4111</phone>
    <phone_ext>67968</phone_ext>
    <email>Susan.Keast@vch.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vancouver General Hospital - Gordon and Leslie Diamond Health Care Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V5Z 1M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Susan Keast, RN</last_name>
      <phone>604-875-4111</phone>
      <phone_ext>67968</phone_ext>
      <email>Susan.Keast@vch.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marette Lee, MD, MPH, FRCSC</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Lori Brotto, PhD, R Psych</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sarah Mah, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Susan J Keast, RN</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Marguerite Bryce</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Balasubramani L, Orbell S, Hagger M, Brown V, Tidy J. Can default rates in colposcopy really be reduced? BJOG. 2008 Feb;115(3):403-8. doi: 10.1111/j.1471-0528.2007.01594.x.</citation>
    <PMID>18190379</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boone JD, Erickson BK, Huh WK. New insights into cervical cancer screening. J Gynecol Oncol. 2012 Oct;23(4):282-7. doi: 10.3802/jgo.2012.23.4.282. Epub 2012 Sep 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23094132</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brédart A, Kop JL, Efficace F, Beaudeau A, Brito T, Dolbeault S, Aaronson N; EORTC Quality of Life Group. Quality of care in the oncology outpatient setting from patients' perspective: a systematic review of questionnaires' content and psychometric performance. Psychooncology. 2015 Apr;24(4):382-94. doi: 10.1002/pon.3661. Epub 2014 Sep 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25196048</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Byrom J, Clarke T, Neale J, Dunn PD, Hughes GM, Redman CW, Pitts M. Can pre-colposcopy sessions reduce anxiety at the time of colposcopy? A prospective randomised study. J Obstet Gynaecol. 2002 Jul;22(4):415-20.</citation>
    <PMID>12521468</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dietrich AJ, Tobin JN, Cassells A, Robinson CM, Greene MA, Sox CH, Beach ML, DuHamel KN, Younge RG. Telephone care management to improve cancer screening among low-income women: a randomized, controlled trial. Ann Intern Med. 2006 Apr 18;144(8):563-71.</citation>
    <PMID>16618953</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lerman C, Hanjani P, Caputo C, Miller S, Delmoor E, Nolte S, Engstrom P. Telephone counseling improves adherence to colposcopy among lower-income minority women. J Clin Oncol. 1992 Feb;10(2):330-3.</citation>
    <PMID>1732434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Litchfield IJ, Bentham LM, Lilford RJ, McManus RJ, Greenfield SM. Patient perspectives on test result communication in primary care: a qualitative study. Br J Gen Pract. 2015 Mar;65(632):e133-40. doi: 10.3399/bjgp15X683929.</citation>
    <PMID>25733434</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nugent LS, Tamlyn-Leaman K, Isa N, Reardon E, Crumley J. Anxiety and the colposcopy experience. Clin Nurs Res. 1993 Aug;2(3):267-77.</citation>
    <PMID>8401241</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Connor M, Gallagher P, Waller J, Martin CM, O'Leary JJ, Sharp L; Irish Cervical Screening Research Consortium (CERVIVA). Adverse psychological outcomes following colposcopy and related procedures: a systematic review. BJOG. 2016 Jan;123(1):24-38. doi: 10.1111/1471-0528.13462. Epub 2015 Jun 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26099164</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Percac-Lima S, Ashburner JM, Zai AH, Chang Y, Oo SA, Guimaraes E, Atlas SJ. Patient Navigation for Comprehensive Cancer Screening in High-Risk Patients Using a Population-Based Health Information Technology System: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA Intern Med. 2016 Jul 1;176(7):930-7. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2016.0841.</citation>
    <PMID>27273602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Towler BP, Irwig LM, Shelley JM. The adequacy of management of women with CIN 2 and CIN 3 Pap smear abnormalities. Med J Aust. 1993 Oct 18;159(8):523, 526-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8412951</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 20, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 25, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 28, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 25, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 25, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 28, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of British Columbia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marette Lee</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Program Director, BC Provincial Colposcopy Program</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Dysplasia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cervical Intraepithelial Neoplasia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

