<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03294148</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-0544</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03294148</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mind-body Treatments for Chronic Back Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mind-body Treatments for Chronic Back Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Boulder</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Therapeutic Encounter Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Radiological Society of North America</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Psychophysiologic Disorders Society.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Boulder</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Participants with chronic back pain will complete an online prescreen. They will then be
      randomized to one of two different studies: a placebo vs. waitlist study or a psychotherapy
      vs. waitlist study, with randomization stratified on pain intensity, age, gender, and opioid
      use. Participants will then complete an in-person eligibility session, and eligible
      participants will be scheduled for the baseline assessment session. Following the baseline
      assessment session, participants will then be randomized to the treatment group or the
      waitlist group (with a ratio of 2:1 treatment:waitlist), using a computer-generated random
      sequence.

      This scheme will result in three equally sized groups—placebo, psychotherapy, and waitlist—as
      the investigators will collapse data from the waitlist arms in the two studies for analyses.
      The investigators do not use a standard three-way randomization because the investigators do
      not want placebo participants to think they are in a control condition. Thus, the
      investigators constrain participant's expectations to either injection vs. waitlist or to
      psychotherapy vs. waitlist.

      The placebo treatment is a subcutaneous injection of saline into the back. Participants will
      know that the treatment is a placebo, i.e., it is an &quot;open label&quot; placebo. Psychotherapy (8
      sessions) will be supervised by Alan Gordon and Howard Schubiner.

      Functional MRI brain imaging, self-reported clinical outcomes, and behavioral measures will
      be collected pre- and post-treatment. A brief follow-up survey will be sent at months 1, 2,
      3, 6, and 12 after the final assessment session. These will provide longer term data about
      the trajectory and durability of patient improvement.

      Additionally, a group of healthy controls, with no history of back pain, will complete the
      baseline assessment. They will serve as a comparison group to probe whether the patterns of
      observed brain activity is specific to CBP patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 7, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">November 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Participants will be randomized to one of two different studies: a placebo vs. waitlist study or a psychotherapy vs. waitlist study, with randomization stratified on pain intensity, age, gender, and opioid use. After an eligibility session, eligible participants will be randomized to the treatment group or the waitlist group (with a ratio of 2:1 treatment:waitlist), using a computer-generated random sequence. This scheme will result in three equally sized groups—placebo, psychotherapy, and waitlist—as the investigators will collapse data from the waitlist arms in the two studies for analyses. The investigators do not use a standard three-way randomization because the investigators do not want placebo participants to think they are in a control condition. Thus, the investigators constrain participant's expectations to either injection vs. waitlist or to psychotherapy vs. waitlist.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Researchers will not know which treatment the participants will be receiving (placebo or psychotherapy).</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Pain Inventory—short form (BPI-SF): Measuring change before and after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-treatment (5-7 weeks after baseline) and follow up surveys (1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 months after final assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>Pain intensity and interference</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Oswestry Low Back Pain Disability Questionnaire (OLBPD)- Measuring change before and after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-treatment (5-7 weeks after baseline) and follow up surveys (1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 months after final assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>Back pain disability questionnaire</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive and Negative Affect Scale short form (PANAS-SF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-treatment (5-7 weeks after baseline) and follow up surveys (1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 months after final assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire to rate positive and negative affect.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PROMIS short forms</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-treatment (5-7 weeks after baseline) and follow up surveys (1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 months after final assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>anger (5 items), sleep disturbance (8 items), anxiety (8 items), and depression (8 items)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tampa Scale of Kinesiophobia (TSK)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-treatment (5-7 weeks after baseline) and follow up surveys (1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 months after final assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire used to assess the subjective rating of kinesiophobia or fear of movement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain Catastrophizing Questionnaire (PCS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-treatment (5-7 weeks after baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire used to help quantify an individual's pain experience.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Timeline Follow-Back Measure for alcohol and drug use (TLFB)</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-treatment (5-7 weeks after baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>Questionnaire used to assess daily drinking and drug use.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Global Impression of Change (PGIC) scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-treatment (5-7 weeks after baseline) and follow up surveys (1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 months after final assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>Post-treatment-only outcome measure depicting a patient's subjective rating of overall improvement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment satisfaction questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-treatment (5-7 weeks after baseline) and follow up surveys (1, 2, 3, 6, and 12 months after final assessment)</time_frame>
    <description>Post-treatment-only outcome measure depicting the patient's satisfaction with the treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Willingness to experience pain task</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-treatment (5-7 weeks after baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>Pain auction measuring willingness to experience pain, adapted from Vlaev et al</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Progressive ratio task</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-treatment (5-7 weeks after baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>Participants click the mouse repeatedly to earn small amounts of money, to measure motivation</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Inflammatory markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-treatment (5-7 weeks after baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>Dried blood spots will be used to measure the immune markers IL-1, IL-6, and IL-10.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>fMRI</measure>
    <time_frame>Pre- and post-treatment (5-7 weeks after baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will respond to different pain related tasks during an fMRI scan.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">99</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <condition>Back Pain Lower Back Chronic</condition>
  <condition>Back Pain, Low</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The open-label placebo treatment the investigators will use is based on past open-label placebo trials (Kam-Hansen et al., 2014; Kaptchuk et al., 2010; Kelley et al., 2012). Prior to treatment administration, patients will view a brief (~3 min) video summarizing scientific findings regarding the therapeutic power of placebo treatments. The video will describe established findings regarding placebo and suggest that placebos may still work even when patients know the treatment is a placebo. The video will state that believing in the placebo is not necessary, and the investigators ask only that patients keep an open mind. Patients will then receive a subcutaneous injection of 1ml medical grade saline into the lower back. The injection will be administered near the location of the pain, as specified by the participant. The investigators will use a standard needle used in subcutaneous injections of 27 gauge with a length from 1in to 1.5in.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Psychotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Psychotherapy will consist of one initial medical history session with Co-I Schubiner, followed by twice weekly 50 minute psychotherapy sessions for 4 weeks with a therapist, for a total of 9 sessions maximum. The purpose of the initial medical history session is to help evaluate the likelihood that the patient's back pain is caused by structural conditions in the back. Dr. Schubiner will then speak with patients for a 1 hour session in which he collects their medical history and discusses different possible causes of their back pain with them. This session will be conducted by phone, by HIPAA-compliant Zoom, or by another HIPAA-compliant videoconferencing technology in consultation with the OIT team at Dr. Schubiner's hospital.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Waitlist</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Wait-listed patients will be asked not to change their treatment regime for the 4 weeks in between their two fMRI sessions. Wait-listed patients in the placebo injection arm will be offered the opportunity to receive the placebo treatment (optional). Waitlisted participants in the psychotherapy arm will be given a copy of Dr. Schubiner's book and free access to his online self-help program (optional to accept these).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Open-Label Placebo Treatment for Chronic Back Pain</intervention_name>
    <description>Subcutaneous injection of 1ml medical grade saline into the lower back.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Psychotherapy Treatment for Chronic Back Pain</intervention_name>
    <description>Twice weekly 50 minute psychotherapy sessions for 4 weeks, plus an initial medical history session</description>
    <arm_group_label>Psychotherapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants aged 21 to 70 with CBP will be enrolled.

          -  CBP will be defined according to the criteria established by a recent NIH task force
             (Deyo et al., 2014). Pain duration must be at least 3 months, with back pain being an
             ongoing problem for at least half the days of the last 6 months. That is, patients can
             meet criteria by either reporting pain every day for the past 3 months, or by
             reporting pain on half or more of the days for the past 6+ months. This will be
             determined by asking patients: (1) How long has back pain has been an ongoing problem
             for you? (2) How often has low back pain been an ongoing problem for you over the past
             6 months? A response of greater than 3 months to question 1 and a response of ''at
             least half the days in the past 6 months'' to question 2 would define CBP.

          -  Patients must rate pain intensity at 40/100 or greater on the Brief Pain
             Inventory-Short Form (BPI-SF), in keeping with inclusion criteria from previous CBP
             trials (Baliki et al., 2012; Cherkin et al., 2016; Hashmi et al., 2013; Seminowicz et
             al., 2011).

          -  Back pain must be elicited by our back pain device (see below).

          -  Participants must also be comfortable and able to communicate via email or text
             message, as several study measures are collected in this manner (see below).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Back pain associated with compensation or litigation issues as determined by
             self-report within the past year.

          -  Leg pain is greater than back pain. This suggests neuropathic pain, which may be less
             responsive to placebo or psychotherapy.

          -  Difficulty participating for technical/logistical issues (e.g., unable to get to
             assessment sessions).

          -  Self-reported diagnoses of schizophrenia, multiple personality disorder, or
             dissociative identity disorder.

          -  Self-reported use of intravenous drugs, due to concerns about infections and subject
             compliance with experimental protocols.

          -  Inability to undergo MRI as determined by MRI safety screen (e.g., pregnancy, metal in
             body, claustrophobia, using the standard screen conducted by the MRI imaging
             facility).

          -  Hypersensitive or hyposensitive to pressure pain: unable to tolerate 7kg/cm2
             stimulation or reporting no pain for 4kg/cm2 stimulation; see further details below.

          -  Current regular use of an immunosuppressant drug, such as steroids. Such drugs
             interfere with immunoassay results.

          -  Self-reported history of metastasizing cancers—cancer of the breast, thyroid, lung,
             kidney, prostate or blood cancers.

          -  Self-reported history of stroke, brain surgery, or brain tumor.

          -  Self-reported diagnosis of a specific inflammatory disorder: rheumatoid arthritis,
             polymyalgia rheumatica, scleroderma, Lupus, or polymyositis.

          -  Unexplained, unintended weight loss of 20 lbs. or more in the past year.

          -  Cauda Equina syndrome, as screened for by self-reported inability to control bowel or
             bladder function.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tor Wager</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Boulder</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tor Wager, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>303-492-7487</phone>
    <email>tor.wager@colorado.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jonathan Ashar</last_name>
    <email>jonathan.ashar@colorado.edu</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Boulder</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boulder</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80309</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tor Wager, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>303-492-7487</phone>
      <email>tor.wager@colorado.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jonathan Ashar</last_name>
      <email>jonathan.ashar@colorado.edu</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Annersten M, Willman A. Performing subcutaneous injections: a literature review. Worldviews Evid Based Nurs. 2005;2(3):122-30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17040533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ashar YK, Chang LJ, Wager TD. Brain Mechanisms of the Placebo Effect: An Affective Appraisal Account. Annu Rev Clin Psychol. 2017 May 8;13:73-98. doi: 10.1146/annurev-clinpsy-021815-093015. Epub 2017 Mar 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>28375723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Atlas LY, Bolger N, Lindquist MA, Wager TD. Brain mediators of predictive cue effects on perceived pain. J Neurosci. 2010 Sep 29;30(39):12964-77. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0057-10.2010.</citation>
    <PMID>20881115</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baliki MN, Petre B, Torbey S, Herrmann KM, Huang L, Schnitzer TJ, Fields HL, Apkarian AV. Corticostriatal functional connectivity predicts transition to chronic back pain. Nat Neurosci. 2012 Jul 1;15(8):1117-9. doi: 10.1038/nn.3153.</citation>
    <PMID>22751038</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Becker GM, DeGroot MH, Marschak J. Measuring utility by a single-response sequential method. Behav Sci. 1964 Jul;9(3):226-32.</citation>
    <PMID>5888778</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bicket MC, Gupta A, Brown CH 4th, Cohen SP. Epidural injections for spinal pain: a systematic review and meta-analysis evaluating the &quot;control&quot; injections in randomized controlled trials. Anesthesiology. 2013 Oct;119(4):907-31. doi: 10.1097/ALN.0b013e31829c2ddd. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24195874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blease C, Colloca L, Kaptchuk TJ. Are open-Label Placebos Ethical? Informed Consent and Ethical Equivocations. Bioethics. 2016 Jul;30(6):407-14. doi: 10.1111/bioe.12245. Epub 2016 Feb 3.</citation>
    <PMID>26840547</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bushnell MC, Ceko M, Low LA. Cognitive and emotional control of pain and its disruption in chronic pain. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2013 Jul;14(7):502-11. doi: 10.1038/nrn3516. Epub 2013 May 30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23719569</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cherkin DC, Sherman KJ, Balderson BH, Cook AJ, Anderson ML, Hawkes RJ, Hansen KE, Turner JA. Effect of Mindfulness-Based Stress Reduction vs Cognitive Behavioral Therapy or Usual Care on Back Pain and Functional Limitations in Adults With Chronic Low Back Pain: A Randomized Clinical Trial. JAMA. 2016 Mar 22-29;315(12):1240-9. doi: 10.1001/jama.2016.2323.</citation>
    <PMID>27002445</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chou R, Qaseem A, Snow V, Casey D, Cross JT Jr, Shekelle P, Owens DK; Clinical Efficacy Assessment Subcommittee of the American College of Physicians; American College of Physicians; American Pain Society Low Back Pain Guidelines Panel. Diagnosis and treatment of low back pain: a joint clinical practice guideline from the American College of Physicians and the American Pain Society. Ann Intern Med. 2007 Oct 2;147(7):478-91. Erratum in: Ann Intern Med. 2008 Feb 5;148(3):247-8.</citation>
    <PMID>17909209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen SP, Argoff CE, Carragee EJ. Management of low back pain. BMJ. 2008 Dec 22;337:a2718. doi: 10.1136/bmj.a2718. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19103627</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Colloca L, Petrovic P, Wager TD, Ingvar M, Benedetti F. How the number of learning trials affects placebo and nocebo responses. Pain. 2010 Nov;151(2):430-9. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2010.08.007.</citation>
    <PMID>20817355</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Delgado MR, Li J, Schiller D, Phelps EA. The role of the striatum in aversive learning and aversive prediction errors. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci. 2008 Dec 12;363(1511):3787-800. doi: 10.1098/rstb.2008.0161. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18829426</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Devilly GJ, Borkovec TD. Psychometric properties of the credibility/expectancy questionnaire. J Behav Ther Exp Psychiatry. 2000 Jun;31(2):73-86.</citation>
    <PMID>11132119</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deyo RA, Dworkin SF, Amtmann D, Andersson G, Borenstein D, Carragee E, Carrino J, Chou R, Cook K, DeLitto A, Goertz C, Khalsa P, Loeser J, Mackey S, Panagis J, Rainville J, Tosteson T, Turk D, Von Korff M, Weiner DK; National Institutes of Health task force on research standards for chronic low back pain. Report of the National Institutes of Health task force on research standards for chronic low back pain. J Manipulative Physiol Ther. 2014 Sep;37(7):449-67. doi: 10.1016/j.jmpt.2014.07.006. Epub 2014 Aug 12.</citation>
    <PMID>25127996</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dimidjian S, Goodman SH, Felder JN, Gallop R, Brown AP, Beck A. Staying well during pregnancy and the postpartum: A pilot randomized trial of mindfulness-based cognitive therapy for the prevention of depressive relapse/recurrence. J Consult Clin Psychol. 2016 Feb;84(2):134-45. doi: 10.1037/ccp0000068. Epub 2015 Dec 14.</citation>
    <PMID>26654212</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dimidjian S, Hollon SD. How would we know if psychotherapy were harmful? Am Psychol. 2010 Jan;65(1):21-33. doi: 10.1037/a0017299. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20063907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dimidjian S, Hollon SD, Dobson KS, Schmaling KB, Kohlenberg RJ, Addis ME, Gallop R, McGlinchey JB, Markley DK, Gollan JK, Atkins DC, Dunner DL, Jacobson NS. Randomized trial of behavioral activation, cognitive therapy, and antidepressant medication in the acute treatment of adults with major depression. J Consult Clin Psychol. 2006 Aug;74(4):658-70.</citation>
    <PMID>16881773</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eldar E, Hauser TU, Dayan P, Dolan RJ. Striatal structure and function predict individual biases in learning to avoid pain. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2016 Apr 26;113(17):4812-7. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1519829113. Epub 2016 Apr 11.</citation>
    <PMID>27071092</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Freburger JK, Holmes GM, Agans RP, Jackman AM, Darter JD, Wallace AS, Castel LD, Kalsbeek WD, Carey TS. The rising prevalence of chronic low back pain. Arch Intern Med. 2009 Feb 9;169(3):251-8. doi: 10.1001/archinternmed.2008.543.</citation>
    <PMID>19204216</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gatchel RJ, Peng YB, Peters ML, Fuchs PN, Turk DC. The biopsychosocial approach to chronic pain: scientific advances and future directions. Psychol Bull. 2007 Jul;133(4):581-624. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17592957</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Geuter S, Büchel C. Facilitation of pain in the human spinal cord by nocebo treatment. J Neurosci. 2013 Aug 21;33(34):13784-90. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2191-13.2013.</citation>
    <PMID>23966699</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Geuter S, Eippert F, Hindi Attar C, Büchel C. Cortical and subcortical responses to high and low effective placebo treatments. Neuroimage. 2013 Feb 15;67:227-36. doi: 10.1016/j.neuroimage.2012.11.029. Epub 2012 Nov 28.</citation>
    <PMID>23201367</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grace PM, Hutchinson MR, Maier SF, Watkins LR. Pathological pain and the neuroimmune interface. Nat Rev Immunol. 2014 Apr;14(4):217-31. doi: 10.1038/nri3621. Epub 2014 Feb 28. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24577438</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haake M, Müller HH, Schade-Brittinger C, Basler HD, Schäfer H, Maier C, Endres HG, Trampisch HJ, Molsberger A. German Acupuncture Trials (GERAC) for chronic low back pain: randomized, multicenter, blinded, parallel-group trial with 3 groups. Arch Intern Med. 2007 Sep 24;167(17):1892-8. Erratum in: Arch Intern Med. 2007 Oct 22;167(19):2072.</citation>
    <PMID>17893311</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hashmi JA, Baliki MN, Huang L, Baria AT, Torbey S, Hermann KM, Schnitzer TJ, Apkarian AV. Shape shifting pain: chronification of back pain shifts brain representation from nociceptive to emotional circuits. Brain. 2013 Sep;136(Pt 9):2751-68. doi: 10.1093/brain/awt211.</citation>
    <PMID>23983029</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hashmi JA, Baria AT, Baliki MN, Huang L, Schnitzer TJ, Apkarian AV. Brain networks predicting placebo analgesia in a clinical trial for chronic back pain. Pain. 2012 Dec;153(12):2393-402. doi: 10.1016/j.pain.2012.08.008. Epub 2012 Sep 15.</citation>
    <PMID>22985900</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hashmi JA, Baliki MN, Huang L, Parks EL, Chanda ML, Schnitzer T, Apkarian AV. Lidocaine patch (5%) is no more potent than placebo in treating chronic back pain when tested in a randomised double blind placebo controlled brain imaging study. Mol Pain. 2012 Apr 24;8:29. doi: 10.1186/1744-8069-8-29.</citation>
    <PMID>22531485</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoffman BM, Papas RK, Chatkoff DK, Kerns RD. Meta-analysis of psychological interventions for chronic low back pain. Health Psychol. 2007 Jan;26(1):1-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17209691</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hróbjartsson A, Gøtzsche PC. Placebo interventions for all clinical conditions. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2010 Jan 20;(1):CD003974. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD003974.pub3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20091554</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hsu MC, Schubiner H, Lumley MA, Stracks JS, Clauw DJ, Williams DA. Sustained pain reduction through affective self-awareness in fibromyalgia: a randomized controlled trial. J Gen Intern Med. 2010 Oct;25(10):1064-70. doi: 10.1007/s11606-010-1418-6. Epub 2010 Jun 8.</citation>
    <PMID>20532650</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hull SC, Colloca L, Avins A, Gordon NP, Somkin CP, Kaptchuk TJ, Miller FG. Patients' attitudes about the use of placebo treatments: telephone survey. BMJ. 2013 Jul 2;347:f3757. doi: 10.1136/bmj.f3757.</citation>
    <PMID>23819963</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irwin MR, Miller AH. Depressive disorders and immunity: 20 years of progress and discovery. Brain Behav Immun. 2007 May;21(4):374-83. Epub 2007 Mar 13. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17360153</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jensen MP, Ehde DM, Day MA. The Behavioral Activation and Inhibition Systems: Implications for Understanding and Treating Chronic Pain. J Pain. 2016 May;17(5):529.e1-529.e18. doi: 10.1016/j.jpain.2016.02.001. Epub 2016 Mar 24.</citation>
    <PMID>27052644</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kam-Hansen S, Jakubowski M, Kelley JM, Kirsch I, Hoaglin DC, Kaptchuk TJ, Burstein R. Altered placebo and drug labeling changes the outcome of episodic migraine attacks. Sci Transl Med. 2014 Jan 8;6(218):218ra5. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.3006175.</citation>
    <PMID>24401940</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaptchuk TJ. The placebo effect in alternative medicine: can the performance of a healing ritual have clinical significance? Ann Intern Med. 2002 Jun 4;136(11):817-25. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12044130</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaptchuk TJ, Friedlander E, Kelley JM, Sanchez MN, Kokkotou E, Singer JP, Kowalczykowski M, Miller FG, Kirsch I, Lembo AJ. Placebos without deception: a randomized controlled trial in irritable bowel syndrome. PLoS One. 2010 Dec 22;5(12):e15591. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0015591.</citation>
    <PMID>21203519</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kelley JM, Kaptchuk TJ, Cusin C, Lipkin S, Fava M. Open-label placebo for major depressive disorder: a pilot randomized controlled trial. Psychother Psychosom. 2012;81(5):312-4. Epub 2012 Aug 1.</citation>
    <PMID>22854752</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koban L, Wager TD. Beyond conformity: Social influences on pain reports and physiology. Emotion. 2016 Feb;16(1):24-32. doi: 10.1037/emo0000087. Epub 2015 Aug 31.</citation>
    <PMID>26322566</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kregel J, Meeus M, Malfliet A, Dolphens M, Danneels L, Nijs J, Cagnie B. Structural and functional brain abnormalities in chronic low back pain: A systematic review. Semin Arthritis Rheum. 2015 Oct;45(2):229-37. doi: 10.1016/j.semarthrit.2015.05.002. Epub 2015 May 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26092329</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee M, Manders TR, Eberle SE, Su C, D'amour J, Yang R, Lin HY, Deisseroth K, Froemke RC, Wang J. Activation of corticostriatal circuitry relieves chronic neuropathic pain. J Neurosci. 2015 Apr 1;35(13):5247-59. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3494-14.2015.</citation>
    <PMID>25834050</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Manchikanti L, Pampati V, Falco FJ, Hirsch JA. Growth of spinal interventional pain management techniques: analysis of utilization trends and Medicare expenditures 2000 to 2008. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2013 Jan 15;38(2):157-68. doi: 10.1097/BRS.0b013e318267f463.</citation>
    <PMID>22781007</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller FG, Kaptchuk TJ. The power of context: reconceptualizing the placebo effect. J R Soc Med. 2008 May;101(5):222-5. doi: 10.1258/jrsm.2008.070466. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18463276</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moore RC, Depp CA, Wetherell JL, Lenze EJ. Ecological momentary assessment versus standard assessment instruments for measuring mindfulness, depressed mood, and anxiety among older adults. J Psychiatr Res. 2016 Apr;75:116-23. doi: 10.1016/j.jpsychires.2016.01.011. Epub 2016 Jan 22.</citation>
    <PMID>26851494</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Müller M, Kamping S, Benrath J, Skowronek H, Schmitz J, Klinger R, Flor H. Treatment history and placebo responses to experimental and clinical pain in chronic pain patients. Eur J Pain. 2016 Oct;20(9):1530-41. doi: 10.1002/ejp.877. Epub 2016 Apr 7.</citation>
    <PMID>27062187</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ortiz R, Chandros Hull S, Colloca L. Patient attitudes about the clinical use of placebo: qualitative perspectives from a telephone survey. BMJ Open. 2016 Apr 4;6(4):e011012. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2015-011012.</citation>
    <PMID>27044586</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pedersen LM, Schistad E, Jacobsen LM, Røe C, Gjerstad J. Serum levels of the pro-inflammatory interleukins 6 (IL-6) and -8 (IL-8) in patients with lumbar radicular pain due to disc herniation: A 12-month prospective study. Brain Behav Immun. 2015 May;46:132-6. doi: 10.1016/j.bbi.2015.01.008. Epub 2015 Jan 31.</citation>
    <PMID>25653193</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roy M, Shohamy D, Daw N, Jepma M, Wimmer GE, Wager TD. Representation of aversive prediction errors in the human periaqueductal gray. Nat Neurosci. 2014 Nov;17(11):1607-12. doi: 10.1038/nn.3832. Epub 2014 Oct 5.</citation>
    <PMID>25282614</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schafer SM, Colloca L, Wager TD. Conditioned placebo analgesia persists when subjects know they are receiving a placebo. J Pain. 2015 May;16(5):412-20. doi: 10.1016/j.jpain.2014.12.008. Epub 2015 Jan 22.</citation>
    <PMID>25617812</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schistad EI, Espeland A, Pedersen LM, Sandvik L, Gjerstad J, Røe C. Association between baseline IL-6 and 1-year recovery in lumbar radicular pain. Eur J Pain. 2014 Nov;18(10):1394-401. doi: 10.1002/j.1532-2149.2014.502.x. Epub 2014 Apr 2.</citation>
    <PMID>24692238</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schwartz N, Temkin P, Jurado S, Lim BK, Heifets BD, Polepalli JS, Malenka RC. Chronic pain. Decreased motivation during chronic pain requires long-term depression in the nucleus accumbens. Science. 2014 Aug 1;345(6196):535-42. doi: 10.1126/science.1253994.</citation>
    <PMID>25082697</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seminowicz DA, Wideman TH, Naso L, Hatami-Khoroushahi Z, Fallatah S, Ware MA, Jarzem P, Bushnell MC, Shir Y, Ouellet JA, Stone LS. Effective treatment of chronic low back pain in humans reverses abnormal brain anatomy and function. J Neurosci. 2011 May 18;31(20):7540-50. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5280-10.2011.</citation>
    <PMID>21593339</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seymour B, O'Doherty JP, Koltzenburg M, Wiech K, Frackowiak R, Friston K, Dolan R. Opponent appetitive-aversive neural processes underlie predictive learning of pain relief. Nat Neurosci. 2005 Sep;8(9):1234-40. Epub 2005 Aug 21.</citation>
    <PMID>16116445</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shallcross AJ, Gross JJ, Visvanathan PD, Kumar N, Palfrey A, Ford BQ, Dimidjian S, Shirk S, Holm-Denoma J, Goode KM, Cox E, Chaplin W, Mauss IB. Relapse prevention in major depressive disorder: Mindfulness-based cognitive therapy versus an active control condition. J Consult Clin Psychol. 2015 Oct;83(5):964-75. doi: 10.1037/ccp0000050. Epub 2015 Aug 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26371618</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shpaner M, Kelly C, Lieberman G, Perelman H, Davis M, Keefe FJ, Naylor MR. Unlearning chronic pain: A randomized controlled trial to investigate changes in intrinsic brain connectivity following Cognitive Behavioral Therapy. Neuroimage Clin. 2014 Jul 23;5:365-76. doi: 10.1016/j.nicl.2014.07.008. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>26958466</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tilburt JC, Emanuel EJ, Kaptchuk TJ, Curlin FA, Miller FG. Prescribing &quot;placebo treatments&quot;: results of national survey of US internists and rheumatologists. BMJ. 2008 Oct 23;337:a1938. doi: 10.1136/bmj.a1938.</citation>
    <PMID>18948346</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tuttle AH, Tohyama S, Ramsay T, Kimmelman J, Schweinhardt P, Bennett GJ, Mogil JS. Increasing placebo responses over time in U.S. clinical trials of neuropathic pain. Pain. 2015 Dec;156(12):2616-26. doi: 10.1097/j.pain.0000000000000333. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26307858</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vachon-Presseau E, Tétreault P, Petre B, Huang L, Berger SE, Torbey S, Baria AT, Mansour AR, Hashmi JA, Griffith JW, Comasco E, Schnitzer TJ, Baliki MN, Apkarian AV. Corticolimbic anatomical characteristics predetermine risk for chronic pain. Brain. 2016 Jul;139(Pt 7):1958-70. doi: 10.1093/brain/aww100. Epub 2016 May 5.</citation>
    <PMID>27190016</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vlaev I, Seymour B, Chater N, Winston JS, Yoshida W, Wright N, Symmonds M, Dolan R. Prices need no preferences: social trends determine decisions in experimental markets for pain relief. Health Psychol. 2014 Jan;33(1):66-76. doi: 10.1037/a0030372. Epub 2012 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>23148449</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vlaev I, Seymour B, Dolan RJ, Chater N. The price of pain and the value of suffering. Psychol Sci. 2009 Mar;20(3):309-17. doi: 10.1111/j.1467-9280.2009.02304.x. Epub 2009 Feb 23.</citation>
    <PMID>19254237</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wager TD, Atlas LY. The neuroscience of placebo effects: connecting context, learning and health. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2015 Jul;16(7):403-18. doi: 10.1038/nrn3976. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26087681</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wager TD, Atlas LY, Leotti LA, Rilling JK. Predicting individual differences in placebo analgesia: contributions of brain activity during anticipation and pain experience. J Neurosci. 2011 Jan 12;31(2):439-52. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3420-10.2011.</citation>
    <PMID>21228154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wager TD, Atlas LY, Lindquist MA, Roy M, Woo CW, Kross E. An fMRI-based neurologic signature of physical pain. N Engl J Med. 2013 Apr 11;368(15):1388-97. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1204471.</citation>
    <PMID>23574118</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wager TD, Rilling JK, Smith EE, Sokolik A, Casey KL, Davidson RJ, Kosslyn SM, Rose RM, Cohen JD. Placebo-induced changes in FMRI in the anticipation and experience of pain. Science. 2004 Feb 20;303(5661):1162-7.</citation>
    <PMID>14976306</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Winston JS, Vlaev I, Seymour B, Chater N, Dolan RJ. Relative valuation of pain in human orbitofrontal cortex. J Neurosci. 2014 Oct 29;34(44):14526-35. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1706-14.2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25355207</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 13, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 25, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 26, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 25, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 25, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 26, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Placebo</keyword>
  <keyword>Back</keyword>
  <keyword>Pain</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic</keyword>
  <keyword>Mind-Body</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Low Back Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

