<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03297645</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HM20010240</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01HL138682</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03297645</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>RVA Breathes: A Richmond City Collaboration to Reduce Pediatric Asthma Disparities</brief_title>
  <official_title>RVA Breathes: A Richmond City Collaboration to Reduce Pediatric Asthma Disparities</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Virginia Commonwealth University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Virginia Commonwealth University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to evaluate a sustainable, community-engaged program to reduce
      asthma disparities among 5 to 11-year-old children in Richmond, Virginia. Richmond, an urban
      center, has been named the Asthma Capital, or &quot;most challenging place to live in the U.S.
      with asthma,&quot; by the Asthma and Allergy Foundation three times in the last 5 years. To date,
      however, the city has no comprehensive, community-engaged asthma care program for those
      children at highest risk for poor asthma outcomes. To address this disparity, the study team
      engaged with community partners and completed a mixed-methods needs assessment to enhance
      understanding of the barriers and supports to asthma care for children and their families
      living in Richmond. Several key priority areas emerged: peer support, advocacy, treating the
      home as a system, increased school nurse education, and coordination with schools and
      providers. Working together, the community-engaged team translated needs assessment findings
      to RVA Breathes, a program coordinating asthma care across 4 sectors: family, home,
      community, and medical care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      RVA Breathes includes family-based asthma self-management education (delivered by Community
      Health Workers [CHWs] with the Institute for Public Health Innovation), homeenvironmental
      remediation (with Richmond City Health Department's Healthy Homes Initiative), and a
      schoolnurse component (with elementary schools in the Richmond City Public School System).
      These interventions capitalize among existing resources and relationships with stakeholders
      in Richmond, each of which is committed to RVA Breathes. Three-hundred children with asthma
      and their caregivers will participate in a randomized clinical trial of RVA Breathes. After
      completing a baseline assessment, families will be randomized to one of three conditions: 1)
      asthma education + home remediation + school intervention, 2) asthma education + home
      remediation and 3) comparator condition (Enhanced Standard of Care, E-SOC). Families will
      participate in the program for 12 months and complete follow-up assessments (post-treatment
      and 3-, 6-, and 12-month) to measure changes in healthcare utilization and the impact of the
      program on child asthma outcomes. Conditions will be compared on the primary outcomes of
      healthcare utilization, including asthma specific ED visits and hospital admissions, school
      absences, and controller medication use; secondary outcomes include asthma control, symptoms,
      and quality of life. We will also evaluate the sustainability of RVA Breathes after 12 months
      (without active intervention), including a review of qualitative data from participants and
      stakeholders in the program. Findings from this trial will allow for dissemination and
      implementation of RVA Breathes as a sustainable program in the Richmond are.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Health care utilization</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported and from billing systems/insurance reports of frequency of emergency department visits and hospitalizations due to asthma. A composite variable of frequency of emergency department visits and hospitalizations will be generated to arrive at one health care utilization outcome variable.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication usage</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Refill data for each prescribed asthma medication will be used.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>School absences</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported missed school days due to asthma</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Asthma control</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-reported childhood asthma control test, which measures the frequency of daytime and nighttime asthma symptoms, activity limitations, and perception of disease control.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Asthma symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Caregivers will report number of symptom free days in the last 7 days.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Child quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Children will complete a measure that assesses their level of quality of life related to child asthma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parent quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Parents will complete a measure that assesses their level of quality of life related to child asthma.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>school + asthma education + home environment remediation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>asthma education + home environment remediation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>enhanced standard of care</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>School</intervention_name>
    <description>CHWs will ensure that families submit required health paperwork (e.g., asthma action plan, medication release form) and confirm with school nurses that children have the appropriate medications. School nurses will be given a standardized protocol to follow with clear guidelines for caring for students with asthma. The CHW assigned to the family will work with the school nurse to ensure that communication with the medical provider is occurring.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Asthma education</intervention_name>
    <description>CHWs will deliver evidence-based asthma education to parents and children. Content is drawn from existing asthma management programs, and adapted for families in Richmond. Between sessions, CHWs will call parents at least monthly to check in and assess family asthma management, including healthcare utilization since the last contact.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Home environmental remediation</intervention_name>
    <description>Healthy Homes will complete home-based environmental assessments using evidence-based protocols. Healthy Homes will provide real-time education and share information about their findings and recommendations for action. Families are provided with low-cost intervention materials (e.g., filters, pillow covers), as well as behavioral modifications to aid in the reduction of asthma triggers in the home.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Informational mail</intervention_name>
    <description>Family will be mailed publicly available asthma information every 3 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Enrolled in Richmond Public Schools

          -  Asthma-related emergency department visit/hospitalization within last year

          -  Physician-diagnosed asthma

          -  Richmond city resident

        Caregiver inclusion: child's legal guardian living in same home for the last 6 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe medical or psychiatric condition (child or caregiver)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>11 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robin Everhart, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Virginia Commonwealth University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Robin Everhart, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(804) 828-7249</phone>
    <email>reverhart@vcu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Commonwealth University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23298</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 8, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 25, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">September 29, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 9, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 9, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Shared data will be free of identifiers that could link findings with research participants or lead to deductive disclosure of individual subjects.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

