<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01564537</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C16010</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2011-005496-17</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CTR20130908</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1164-7646</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NL40132.018.12</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>12/LO/0949</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>JapicCTI-132345</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>1015042370</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>C16010CTIL</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01564537</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase 3 Study Comparing Oral Ixazomib Plus Lenalidomide and Dexamethasone Versus Placebo Plus Lenalidomide and Dexamethasone in Adult Patients With Relapsed and/or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 3, Randomized, Double-Blind, Multicenter Study Comparing Oral Ixazomib (MLN9708) Plus Lenalidomide and Dexamethasone Versus Placebo Plus Lenalidomide and Dexamethasone in Adult Patients With Relapsed and/or Refractory Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether the addition of oral ixazomib to the
      background therapy of lenalidomide and dexamethasone improves progression free survival (PFS)
      in participants with relapsed and/or refractory multiple myeloma (RRMM).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The drug being tested in this study is called Ixazomib. Ixazomib is being tested to treat
      people who have relapsed and/or refractory multiple myeloma (RRMM). This study will look at
      progression free survival (PFS), overall survival (OS) and safety in participants who take
      ixazomib in addition to lenalidomide and dexamethasone compared to placebo in addition to
      lenalidomide and dexamethasone.

      The study enrolled 722 patients. Participants were randomly assigned (by chance, like
      flipping a coin) to one of the two treatment groups—which will remain undisclosed to the
      patient and study doctor during the study (unless there is an urgent medical need):

        -  Ixazomib 4 mg + lenalidomide + dexamethasone

        -  Placebo (dummy inactive pill) - this is a tablet that looks like the study drug but has
           no active ingredient + lenalidomide + dexamethasone

      All participants will receive treatment in 28 day cycles until disease progression or
      unacceptable toxicity.

      This multi-center trial will be conducted worldwide. The overall time to participate in this
      study is approximately 80 months. Participants will make multiple visits to the clinic, and
      will be contacted every 4 weeks for PFS and every 12 weeks for OS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 1, 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 1, 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression Free Survival (PFS) as Assessed by the Independent Review Committee (IRC)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until disease progression or death up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Progression Free Survival (PFS) is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of first documentation of disease progression (PD) or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first. Response including PD was assessed by independent review committee (IRC) using the International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) response criteria. PD requires 1 of the following: Increase of ≥ 25% from nadir in: Serum M-component (absolute increase ≥ 0.5 g/dl); Urine M-component (absolute increase ≥ 200 mg/24 hours); In patients without measurable serum and urine M-protein levels the difference between involved and uninvolved free light chain (FLC) levels (absolute increase &gt; 10 mg/dl); Development of new or increase in the size of existing bone lesions or soft tissue plasmacytomas; Development of hypercalcemia (corrected serum calcium &gt; 11.5 mg/dl) attributed solely to plasma cell proliferative disease. Status evaluated every 4 weeks until disease progression (PD) was confirmed.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of randomization until death up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of death. Participants without documentation of death at the time of the analysis were censored at the date when they were last known to be alive.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Survival in High-Risk Participants Carrying Deletion 17 [Del(17)]</measure>
    <time_frame>At the time of screening; Day 1 of each cycle (every 4 weeks) until disease progression and thereafter every 12 weeks until death or study termination</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of death. The high-risk participants whose myeloma carried del(17) subgroup was defined as the cases reported as positive for del(17) by the central laboratory combined with those cases that lacked a central laboratory result but with known del (17) by local laboratory. Participants without documentation of death at the time of the analysis were censored at the date when they were last known to be alive.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall Response Rate (ORR) as Assessed by the IRC</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of each cycle (every 4 weeks) until disease progression up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
    <description>ORR was defined as the percentage of participants with Complete Response (CR) including stringent complete response (sCR), very good partial response (VGPR) and Partial Response (PR) assessed by the IRC using IMWG criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants With Complete Response (CR) and Very Good Partial Response (VGPR) as Assessed by the IRC</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of each cycle (every 4 weeks) until disease progression up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Response was assessed by the IRC using International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) Criteria. CR is defined as negative immunofixation on the serum and urine and; disappearance of any soft tissue plasmacytomas and; &lt; 5% plasma cells in bone marrow. VGPR is defined as Serum and urine M-protein detectable by immunofixation but not on electrophoresis or 90% or greater reduction in serum M-protein plus urine M-protein level &lt; 100 mg per 24 hours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of Response (DOR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of each cycle (every 4 weeks) until disease progression up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
    <description>DOR was measured as the time in months from the date of first documentation of a confirmed response of PR or better (CR [including sCR] + PR+ VGPR) to the date of the first documented disease progression (PD) among participants who responded to the treatment. Response was assessed by the investigator using International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) Criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Progression (TTP) as Assessed by the IRC</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1 of each cycle (every 4 weeks) until disease progression up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
    <description>TTP was measured as the time in months from the first dose of study treatment to the date of the first documented progressive disease (PD) as assessed by the IRC using IMWG criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants With Adverse Events (AEs) and Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>From the date of signing of the informed consent form through 30 days after the last dose of study drug up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance score, laboratory values, vital sign measurements and reported adverse events (AEs) were collected and assessed to evaluate the safety of therapy throughout the study. An AE is defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation participant administered a drug; it does not necessarily have to have a causal relationship with this treatment. An AE can therefore be any unfavorable and unintended sign (example, a clinically significant abnormal laboratory finding), symptom, or disease temporally associated with the use of a drug, whether or not it is considered related to the drug. A serious adverse event (SAE) is an AE resulting in any of the following outcomes or deemed significant for any other reason: death; initial or prolonged inpatient hospitalization; life-threatening experience (immediate risk of dying); persistent or significant disability/incapacity; or congenital anomaly; or a medically important event.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Participants Achieving Pain Response</measure>
    <time_frame>At screening; Day 1 of each cycle; and thereafter every 4 weeks until disease progression</time_frame>
    <description>Pain response was defined as 30% reduction from Baseline in Brief Pain Inventory-Short Form (BPI-SF) worst pain score over the last 24 hours without an increase in analgesic (oral morphine equivalents) use at 2 consecutive evaluations. The BPI-SF contains 15 items designed to capture the pain severity (&quot;worst,&quot; &quot;least,&quot; &quot;average,&quot; and &quot;now&quot; [current pain]), pain location, medication to relieve the pain, and the interference of pain with various daily activities including general activity, mood, walking activity, normal work, relations with other people, sleep, and enjoyment of life. The pain severity items are rated on a 0 to 10 scale where: 0=no pain and 10=pain as bad as you can imagine and averaged for a total score of 0 (best) to 10 (Worst).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Core Quality of Life (QOL) Questionnaire (EORTC-QLQ-C30)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Every 2 Cycles beginning with Cycle 2 during treatment period, End of Treatment (EOT), and every 4 Weeks in follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>The EORTC-QLQ-C30 is a 30-question tool used to assess the overall quality of life in cancer participants. It consists of 15 domains: 1 global health status (GHS) scale, 5 functional scales (Physical, Role, Cognitive, Emotional, Social), and 9 symptom scales/items (Fatigue, Nausea and Vomiting, Pain, Dyspnea, Sleep Disturbance, Appetite Loss, Constipation, Diarrhea, Financial Impact).The EORTC-QLQ-C30 Global Health Status/QOL Scale is scored between 0 and 100, where higher scores indicate better Global Health Status/QOL. Negative changes from baseline indicate deterioration in QOL or functioning and positive changes indicate improvement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change From Baseline in the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life Questionnaire Multiple Myeloma Module (QLQ-MY-20)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and Every 2 Cycles beginning with Cycle 2 during treatment period, End of Treatment (EOT), and every 4 Weeks in follow-up</time_frame>
    <description>The EORTC-QLQ-MY-20 is a patient-completed, 20-question quality of life questionnaire that has 4 independent subscales, 2 functional subscales (body image, future perspective), and 2 symptoms scales (disease symptoms and side-effects of treatment). The participant answers questions about their health during the past week using a 4-point scale where 1=Not at All to 4=Very Much. A negative change from Baseline indicates improvement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>OS in High-Risk Participants</measure>
    <time_frame>At the time of screening; Day 1 of each cycle; every 4 weeks until disease progression and thereafter every 12 weeks until death or study termination</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival (OS) is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of death. High-risk participants are defined as participants carrying cytogenic abnormalities: del(17), translocation t(4;14), or t(14;16) as reported by the central laboratory combined with those cases that lacked a central laboratory result but with known del (17), t(4;14), or t(14;16) by local laboratory. Cytogenetic abnormalities of del(13) and +1q are no longer considered to be high-risk abnormalities and are not included in the analysis. Participants without documentation of death at the time of the analysis were censored at the date when they were last known to be alive.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PFS in High-Risk Participants</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of randomization until disease progression or death up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
    <description>Progression Free Survival (PFS) is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of first documentation of disease progression or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first. Response was assessed by independent review committee (IRC) using IMWG response criteria. High-risk participants are defined as participants carrying cytogenic abnormalities: del(17), translocation t(4;14), or t(14;16) as reported by the central laboratory combined with those cases that lacked a central laboratory result but with known del (17), t(4;14), or t(14;16) by local laboratory. Cytogenetic abnormalities of del(13) and +1q are no longer considered to be high-risk abnormalities and are not included in the analysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic Parameters (Including Cmax, AUC and Tmax) of Ixazomib</measure>
    <time_frame>Days 1 &amp; 14 of Cycles 1 &amp; 2. Day 1 of Cycles 3 to 10</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Association Between Response or Resistance to Ixazomib Treatment and Proteasome and Nuclear Factor-kB (NF-kB)-Related Genes</measure>
    <time_frame>At the time of screening; Day 1 of each cycle; at EOT; every 4 weeks until disease progression and thereafter every 12 weeks until death or study termination</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">722</enrollment>
  <condition>Relapsed Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <condition>Refractory Multiple Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ixazomib + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ixazomib 4 mg, capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to end of treatment (EOT) projected at 80 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Ixazomib placebo-matching capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ixazomib</intervention_name>
    <description>Ixazomib capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ixazomib + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MLN9708</other_name>
    <other_name>NINLARO®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Lenalidomide capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ixazomib + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>Dexamethasone tablets</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ixazomib + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Ixazomib placebo-matching capsules</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Male or female participants 18 years of age or older.

          2. Multiple myeloma diagnosed according to standard criteria either currently or at the
             time of initial diagnosis.

             NOTE: The initial diagnosis must have been symptomatic multiple myeloma, although the
             relapsed disease did not need to be symptomatic.

          3. Must have had measurable disease, defined by at least 1 of the following 3
             measurements:

               -  Serum M-protein ≥ 1 g/dL (≥ 10 g/L).

               -  Urine M-protein ≥ 200 mg/24 hours.

               -  Serum free light chain (FLC) assay: involved FLC level ≥ 10 mg/dL (≥ 100 mg/L),
                  provided that the serum FLC ratio was abnormal.

          4. Participants with relapsed and/or refractory multiple myeloma (RRMM) who had received
             1 to 3 prior therapies.

             NOTE: population included the following 3 categories of participants:

               -  Participants who relapsed from their previous treatment(s) but were not
                  refractory to any previous treatment.

               -  Participants who were refractory to all lines of previous treatment(s) (ie,
                  participants who had never responded to any therapies received).

               -  Participants who relapsed from at least 1 previous treatment AND additionally
                  were refractory to at least 1 previous treatment. For the purposes of this study,
                  refractory disease was defined as disease progression on treatment or progression
                  within 60 days after the last dose of a given therapy.

             A line of therapy was defined as 1 or more cycles of a planned treatment program. This
             may have consisted of 1 or more planned cycles of single-agent therapy or combination
             therapy, as well as a sequence of treatments administered in a planned manner. For
             example, a planned treatment approach of induction therapy followed by autologous stem
             cell transplantation, followed by maintenance was considered 1 line of therapy.
             Autologous and allogenic transplants were permitted.

          5. Must have met the following clinical laboratory criteria:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1000/mm^3 and platelet count ≥ 75,000/mm^3.
                  Platelet transfusions to help participants meet eligibility criteria were not
                  allowed within 3 days prior to randomization.

               -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x the upper limit of the normal range (ULN).

               -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 3 x ULN.

               -  Calculated creatinine clearance ≥ 30 mL/min NOTE: Participants with a low
                  creatinine clearance ≤ 60 mL/min (or ≤ 50 mL/min, according to lenalidomide
                  prescribing information/local practice) were to receive a reduced lenalidomide
                  dose of 10 mg once daily (QD) on Days 1 through 21 of a 28-day cycle. The
                  lenalidomide dose may have been escalated to 15 mg QD after 2 cycles if the
                  participant was not responding to treatment and was tolerating the treatment. If
                  renal function normalized (ie, creatinine clearance &gt;60 mL/min or &gt;50 mL/min,
                  according to lenalidomide prescribing information/local practice) and the
                  participant continued to tolerate this treatment, lenalidomide may then have been
                  escalated to 25 mg QD.

          6. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0, 1, or 2.

          7. Participants who received prior allogenic transplant must have had no active
             graft-versus-host disease.

          8. Female participants who:

               -  Were postmenopausal for at least 24 months before the screening visit, OR

               -  Were surgically sterile, OR

               -  If they were of childbearing potential must have: had a negative pregnancy test
                  with a sensitivity of at least 25 mIU/mL within 10 to 14 days and again within 24
                  hours prior to starting Cycle 1 of lenalidomide; either agreed to practice true
                  abstinence, when this was in line with the preferred and usual lifestyle of the
                  participant. (Periodic abstinence [eg, calendar, ovulation, symptothermal,
                  post-ovulation methods] and withdrawal were not acceptable methods of
                  contraception.) OR begun 2 reliable methods of birth control (1 highly effective
                  method and 1 additional effective method) at the same time, at least 28 days
                  before starting study treatment through 90 days after the last dose of study
                  treatment; and agreed to ongoing pregnancy testing AND must have also adhered to
                  the guidelines of the RevAssist program (US participants), RevAid program
                  (Canadian participants), iAccess program (Australian participants), RevMate
                  program (Japanese participants) or The Lenalidomide Pregnancy Risk Minimisation
                  Plan as outlined in the Study Manual (all other participants who were not using
                  commercial supplies).

             Male patients, even if surgically sterilized (ie, status postvasectomy), who:

               -  Agreed to practice true abstinence, when this was in line with the preferred and
                  usual lifestyle of the participant. (Periodic abstinence [eg, calendar,
                  ovulation, symptothermal, post-ovulation methods] and withdrawal were not
                  acceptable methods of contraception.) OR

               -  Agreed to practice effective barrier contraception during the entire study
                  treatment period and 90 days after the last dose of study treatment if their
                  partner was of childbearing potential, even if they had a successful vasectomy,
                  AND

               -  Must have also adhered to the guidelines of the RevAssist program (US
                  participants), RevAid program (Canadian participants), iAccess program
                  (Australian participants), RevMate program (Japanese participants) or The
                  Lenalidomide Pregnancy Risk Minimisation Plan as outlined in the study Manual
                  (all other participants who were not using commercial supplies)

          9. Must have been able to take concurrent aspirin 81 to 325 mg daily (or enoxaparin 40 mg
             subcutaneously daily [or its equivalent] if allergic to aspirin), per published
             standard or institutional standard of care, as prophylactic anticoagulation.

             NOTE: For participants with prior history of deep vein thrombosis (DVT),
             low-molecular-weight heparin (LMWH) was mandatory.

         10. Voluntary written consent must have been given before performance of any study related
             procedure not part of standard medical care, with the understanding that consent may
             have been withdrawn by the participant at any time without prejudice to future medical
             care.

         11. Was willing and able to adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol
             requirements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Was refractory to lenalidomide or proteasome inhibitor-based therapy at any line.

             NOTE: Refractory disease was defined as disease progression on treatment or
             progression within 60 days after the last dose of a given therapy. Participants who
             progressed after 60 days from the last dose of a given therapy were considered
             relapsed and were eligible for inclusion in the study.

             Participants who were refractory to thalidomide-based therapy were eligible.

          2. Female participants who were breast feeding or pregnant.

          3. Failure to have fully recovered (ie, Grade 1 toxicity) from the effects of prior
             chemotherapy (except for alopecia) regardless of the interval since last treatment.

          4. Major surgery within 14 days before randomization.

          5. Radiotherapy within 14 days before randomization.

          6. Central nervous system involvement.

          7. Infection requiring systemic antibiotic therapy or other serious infection within 14
             days before randomization.

          8. Diagnosis of Waldenstrom's macroglobulinemia, polyneuropathy, organomegaly,
             endocrinopathy, monoclonal gammopathy, and skin changes (POEMS) syndrome, plasma cell
             leukemia, primary amyloidosis, myelodysplastic syndrome, or myeloproliferative
             syndrome.

          9. Evidence of current uncontrolled cardiovascular conditions, including uncontrolled
             hypertension, uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmias, symptomatic congestive heart failure,
             unstable angina, or myocardial infarction within 6 months before randomization in the
             study.

         10. Systemic treatment with strong inhibitors of cytochrome P450 (CYP) 1A2 (CYP1A2)
             (fluvoxamine, enoxacin, ciprofloxacin), strong inhibitors of CYP3A (clarithromycin,
             telithromycin, itraconazole, voriconazole, ketoconazole, nefazodone, posaconazole) or
             strong CYP3A inducers (rifampin, rifapentine, rifabutin, carbamazepine, phenytoin,
             phenobarbital), or use of Ginkgo biloba or St. John's wort within 14 days before
             randomization in the study.

         11. Ongoing or active systemic infection, active hepatitis B or C virus infection, or
             known human immunodeficiency virus positive.

         12. Comorbid systemic illnesses or other severe concurrent disease which, in the judgment
             of the investigator, would make the participant inappropriate for entry into this
             study or interfere significantly with the proper assessment of safety and toxicity of
             the prescribed regimens (eg, peripheral neuropathy that is Grade 1 with pain or Grade
             2 or higher of any cause).

         13. Psychiatric illness/social situation that would limit compliance with study
             requirements.

         14. Known allergy to any of the study medications, their analogues, or excipients in the
             various formulations of any agent.

         15. Inability to swallow oral medication, inability or unwillingness to comply with the
             drug administration requirements, or gastrointestinal condition that could interfere
             with the oral absorption or tolerance of treatment.

         16. Diagnosed or treated for another malignancy within 2 years before randomization or
             previously diagnosed with another malignancy and any evidence of residual disease.
             Participants with nonmelanoma skin cancer or carcinoma in situ of any type were not
             excluded if they had undergone complete resection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Medical Monitor</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Arkansas Medical Sciences</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pacific Cancer Medical Center Inc</name>
      <address>
        <city>Anaheim</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92801</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West Contra Costa Healthcare District</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berkeley</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94704</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Florida</name>
      <address>
        <city>Gainesville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32610</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cancer &amp; Blood Disease Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lecanto</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>34461</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Northwest Georgia Oncology Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Marietta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30060</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>John H. Stroger, Jr. Hospital of Cook County</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>2215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hackensack University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hackensack</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>7601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Roswell Park Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Buffalo</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14263</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Blood and Cancer Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fayetteville</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>28303</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Scranton Hematology Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scranton</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>18510</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MUSC Hollings Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29425</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West Virginia University Hospitals and Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Morgantown</city>
        <state>West Virginia</state>
        <zip>26506-9300</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical College of Wisconsin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milwaukee</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53226</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tom Baker Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T2N 4N2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cross Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 1Z2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vancouver General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V5Z 1M9</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saint John Regional Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint John</city>
        <state>New Brunswick</state>
        <zip>E2L 4L2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>CHUM Notre-Dame Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H2L 4M1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MUHC Glen Site Cedars Cancer Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H4A 3J1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
    <country>Austria</country>
    <country>Belgium</country>
    <country>China</country>
    <country>Czech Republic</country>
    <country>Denmark</country>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
    <country>Hungary</country>
    <country>Israel</country>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>Japan</country>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>New Zealand</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Portugal</country>
    <country>Romania</country>
    <country>Russian Federation</country>
    <country>Singapore</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>Sweden</country>
    <country>Turkey</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.tourmalinetrialmm1.com/</url>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 22, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 27, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 28, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>December 19, 2015</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>December 19, 2015</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">January 27, 2016</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Drug therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ixazomib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glycine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Participants enrolled in this study at 147 sites in Australia, Austria, Belgium, Canada, China, Czech Republic, Denmark, France, Germany, Hungary, Israel, Italy, Japan, Republic of Korea, Netherlands, New Zealand, Poland, Portugal, Romania, Russian Federation, Singapore, Spain, Sweden, Turkey, United Kingdom and US from 28 Aug 2012 to 27 May 2014.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>Participants with a diagnosis of relapsed and/or refractory multiple myeloma were enrolled in 1 of 2 treatment groups: Ixazomib 4 mg or Ixazomib placebo-matching tablets in combination with lenalidomide, and dexamethasone. Data cut-off for this first analysis was 30 October 2014. The study is continuing in a double-blind fashion.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Ixazomib+ Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
          <description>Ixazomib 4 mg, capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to end of treatment (EOT) projected at 80 months.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Placebo + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
          <description>Ixazomib placebo-matching capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="360"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="362"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>Safety Population: Received Study Drug</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="360"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="360"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="354">Completed=Participants who are ongoing as of 30 October 2014 or who have died on study.</participants>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="356">Completed=Participants who are ongoing as of 30 October 2014 or who have died on study.</participants>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="6"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="6"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Withdrawal by Participant</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="4"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="4"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Lost to Follow-up</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Other Miscellaneous Reasons</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="1"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <population>Intent-to-Treat (ITT) population was defined as all randomized participants.</population>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Ixazomib+ Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
          <description>Ixazomib 4 mg, capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Placebo + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
          <description>Ixazomib placebo-matching capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="360"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="362"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="722"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="65.5" spread="9.13"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="65.8" spread="9.70"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="65.7" spread="9.41"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age, Customized</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>≤65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="168"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="176"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="344"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt;65-≤75 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="145"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="125"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="270"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt;75 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="47"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="61"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="108"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="153"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="160"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="313"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="207"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="202"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="409"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race/Ethnicity, Customized</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>White</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="310"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="301"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="611"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Black or African American</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="13"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Native Hawaiian/Other Pacific Islander</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Asian</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="30"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="34"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="64"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>American Indian/Alaska native</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Other</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Not reported</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="15"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="22"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Race/Ethnicity, Customized</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Hispanic or Latino</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="21"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Not Hispanic or Latino</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="339"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="333"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="672"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Not Reported</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="15"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="25"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Missing</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Russian Federation</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="18"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="39"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Singapore</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="28"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="23"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="51"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Portugal</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="15"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Austria</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="5"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Netherlands</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Sweden</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="15"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="27"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>China</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Korea, Republic of</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Poland</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="20"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="41"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>France</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="36"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="45"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="81"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Romania</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="12"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Hungary</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="18"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="39"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>United Kingdom</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="12"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="20"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Spain</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="16"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="14"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="30"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>New Zealand</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="28"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="39"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="67"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Canada</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="26"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="45"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Czech Republic</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="15"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="36"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Turkey</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Belgium</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="14"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Denmark</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="17"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Italy</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="24"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="15"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="39"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Israel</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="19"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="14"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="33"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Australia</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="17"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Germany</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="15"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Japan</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="20"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="21"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="41"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Stratification Factor: Lines of Prior Therapy</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>1 Line</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="212"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="213"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="425"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>2 or 3 Lines</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="148"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="149"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="297"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Stratification Factor: Proteasome Inhibitor</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Exposed</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="250"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="253"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="503"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Naïve</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="110"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="109"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="219"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Stratification Factor: International Staging System (ISS) Stag at Screening</title>
          <description>Stage I: Serum beta2-microglobulin &lt;3.5 mg/L and albumin ≥3.5 g/dL; Stage II: Neither Stage I or III, meaning that either: beta2-microglobulin level ≥3.5 and &lt;5.5 mg/L (with any albumin level), OR albumin &lt;3.5 g/dL with beta2-microglobulin &lt;3.5 mg/L; Stage III: Serum beta2-microglobulin ≥5.5 mg/L. Normal serum beta2-microglobulin: &lt;3.0 mg/L; normal albumin: 3.5–5.0 g/dL.</description>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Stage I or Stage II</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="314"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="318"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="632"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Stage III</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="46"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="44"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="90"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Progression Free Survival (PFS) as Assessed by the Independent Review Committee (IRC)</title>
        <description>Progression Free Survival (PFS) is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of first documentation of disease progression (PD) or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first. Response including PD was assessed by independent review committee (IRC) using the International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) response criteria. PD requires 1 of the following: Increase of ≥ 25% from nadir in: Serum M-component (absolute increase ≥ 0.5 g/dl); Urine M-component (absolute increase ≥ 200 mg/24 hours); In patients without measurable serum and urine M-protein levels the difference between involved and uninvolved free light chain (FLC) levels (absolute increase &gt; 10 mg/dl); Development of new or increase in the size of existing bone lesions or soft tissue plasmacytomas; Development of hypercalcemia (corrected serum calcium &gt; 11.5 mg/dl) attributed solely to plasma cell proliferative disease. Status evaluated every 4 weeks until disease progression (PD) was confirmed.</description>
        <time_frame>From date of randomization until disease progression or death up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
        <population>Intent-to-Treat (ITT) population was defined as all randomized participants.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Ixazomib+ Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib 4 mg, capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib placebo-matching capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Progression Free Survival (PFS) as Assessed by the Independent Review Committee (IRC)</title>
          <description>Progression Free Survival (PFS) is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of first documentation of disease progression (PD) or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first. Response including PD was assessed by independent review committee (IRC) using the International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) response criteria. PD requires 1 of the following: Increase of ≥ 25% from nadir in: Serum M-component (absolute increase ≥ 0.5 g/dl); Urine M-component (absolute increase ≥ 200 mg/24 hours); In patients without measurable serum and urine M-protein levels the difference between involved and uninvolved free light chain (FLC) levels (absolute increase &gt; 10 mg/dl); Development of new or increase in the size of existing bone lesions or soft tissue plasmacytomas; Development of hypercalcemia (corrected serum calcium &gt; 11.5 mg/dl) attributed solely to plasma cell proliferative disease. Status evaluated every 4 weeks until disease progression (PD) was confirmed.</description>
          <population>Intent-to-Treat (ITT) population was defined as all randomized participants.</population>
          <units>months</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="360"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="362"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="20.6" lower_limit="17.02">Not estimable.</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="14.7" lower_limit="12.91" upper_limit="17.58"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.012</p_value>
            <method>Log Rank</method>
            <param_type>Hazard Ratio (HR)</param_type>
            <param_value>0.742</param_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>0.587</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>0.939</ci_upper_limit>
            <estimate_desc>HR is estimated from Cox Regression.</estimate_desc>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Overall Survival (OS)</title>
        <description>Overall survival is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of death. Participants without documentation of death at the time of the analysis were censored at the date when they were last known to be alive.</description>
        <time_frame>Date of randomization until death up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
        <population>ITT population was defined as all randomized participants.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Ixazomib+ Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib 4 mg, capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib placebo-matching capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Overall Survival (OS)</title>
          <description>Overall survival is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of death. Participants without documentation of death at the time of the analysis were censored at the date when they were last known to be alive.</description>
          <population>ITT population was defined as all randomized participants.</population>
          <units>months</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="360"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="362"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="NA">Not estimable; due to immaturity of survival results. Study is still being conducted in a double-blinded fashion to maintain integrity for long term endpoints.</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="NA">Not estimable; due to immaturity of survival results. Study is still being conducted in a double-blinded fashion to maintain integrity for long term endpoints.</measurement>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Overall Survival in High-Risk Participants Carrying Deletion 17 [Del(17)]</title>
        <description>Overall survival is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of death. The high-risk participants whose myeloma carried del(17) subgroup was defined as the cases reported as positive for del(17) by the central laboratory combined with those cases that lacked a central laboratory result but with known del (17) by local laboratory. Participants without documentation of death at the time of the analysis were censored at the date when they were last known to be alive.</description>
        <time_frame>At the time of screening; Day 1 of each cycle (every 4 weeks) until disease progression and thereafter every 12 weeks until death or study termination</time_frame>
        <posting_date>12/2020</posting_date>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Overall Response Rate (ORR) as Assessed by the IRC</title>
        <description>ORR was defined as the percentage of participants with Complete Response (CR) including stringent complete response (sCR), very good partial response (VGPR) and Partial Response (PR) assessed by the IRC using IMWG criteria.</description>
        <time_frame>Day 1 of each cycle (every 4 weeks) until disease progression up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
        <population>ITT population included all randomized participants.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Ixazomib+ Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib 4 mg, capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib placebo-matching capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Overall Response Rate (ORR) as Assessed by the IRC</title>
          <description>ORR was defined as the percentage of participants with Complete Response (CR) including stringent complete response (sCR), very good partial response (VGPR) and Partial Response (PR) assessed by the IRC using IMWG criteria.</description>
          <population>ITT population included all randomized participants.</population>
          <units>percentage of participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="360"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="362"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="78.3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="71.5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Percentage of Participants With Complete Response (CR) and Very Good Partial Response (VGPR) as Assessed by the IRC</title>
        <description>Response was assessed by the IRC using International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) Criteria. CR is defined as negative immunofixation on the serum and urine and; disappearance of any soft tissue plasmacytomas and; &lt; 5% plasma cells in bone marrow. VGPR is defined as Serum and urine M-protein detectable by immunofixation but not on electrophoresis or 90% or greater reduction in serum M-protein plus urine M-protein level &lt; 100 mg per 24 hours.</description>
        <time_frame>Day 1 of each cycle (every 4 weeks) until disease progression up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
        <population>ITT population included all randomized participants.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Ixazomib + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib 4 mg, capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib placebo-matching capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Percentage of Participants With Complete Response (CR) and Very Good Partial Response (VGPR) as Assessed by the IRC</title>
          <description>Response was assessed by the IRC using International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) Criteria. CR is defined as negative immunofixation on the serum and urine and; disappearance of any soft tissue plasmacytomas and; &lt; 5% plasma cells in bone marrow. VGPR is defined as Serum and urine M-protein detectable by immunofixation but not on electrophoresis or 90% or greater reduction in serum M-protein plus urine M-protein level &lt; 100 mg per 24 hours.</description>
          <population>ITT population included all randomized participants.</population>
          <units>percentage of participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="360"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="362"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="48.1"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="39.0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Duration of Response (DOR)</title>
        <description>DOR was measured as the time in months from the date of first documentation of a confirmed response of PR or better (CR [including sCR] + PR+ VGPR) to the date of the first documented disease progression (PD) among participants who responded to the treatment. Response was assessed by the investigator using International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) Criteria.</description>
        <time_frame>Day 1 of each cycle (every 4 weeks) until disease progression up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
        <population>Response-Evaluable population included all participants who received at least 1 dose of study drug, had measurable disease at baseline, and at least 1 post-baseline response assessment, all responders.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Ixazomib+ Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib 4 mg, capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib placebo-matching capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Duration of Response (DOR)</title>
          <description>DOR was measured as the time in months from the date of first documentation of a confirmed response of PR or better (CR [including sCR] + PR+ VGPR) to the date of the first documented disease progression (PD) among participants who responded to the treatment. Response was assessed by the investigator using International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) Criteria.</description>
          <population>Response-Evaluable population included all participants who received at least 1 dose of study drug, had measurable disease at baseline, and at least 1 post-baseline response assessment, all responders.</population>
          <units>months</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="279"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="255"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="20.5" lower_limit="16.62">Not estimable.</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="15.0" lower_limit="11.99">Not estimable.</measurement>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Time to Progression (TTP) as Assessed by the IRC</title>
        <description>TTP was measured as the time in months from the first dose of study treatment to the date of the first documented progressive disease (PD) as assessed by the IRC using IMWG criteria.</description>
        <time_frame>Day 1 of each cycle (every 4 weeks) until disease progression up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
        <population>ITT population included all randomized participants</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Ixazomib+ Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib 4 mg, capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib placebo-matching capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Time to Progression (TTP) as Assessed by the IRC</title>
          <description>TTP was measured as the time in months from the first dose of study treatment to the date of the first documented progressive disease (PD) as assessed by the IRC using IMWG criteria.</description>
          <population>ITT population included all randomized participants</population>
          <units>months</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="360"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="362"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="21.4" lower_limit="18.43">Not estimable.</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="15.7" lower_limit="13.21" upper_limit="18.27"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Number of Participants With Adverse Events (AEs) and Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)</title>
        <description>Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance score, laboratory values, vital sign measurements and reported adverse events (AEs) were collected and assessed to evaluate the safety of therapy throughout the study. An AE is defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation participant administered a drug; it does not necessarily have to have a causal relationship with this treatment. An AE can therefore be any unfavorable and unintended sign (example, a clinically significant abnormal laboratory finding), symptom, or disease temporally associated with the use of a drug, whether or not it is considered related to the drug. A serious adverse event (SAE) is an AE resulting in any of the following outcomes or deemed significant for any other reason: death; initial or prolonged inpatient hospitalization; life-threatening experience (immediate risk of dying); persistent or significant disability/incapacity; or congenital anomaly; or a medically important event.</description>
        <time_frame>From the date of signing of the informed consent form through 30 days after the last dose of study drug up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
        <population>Safety population included all randomized participants who received at least 1 dose of ixazomib.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Ixazomib+ Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib 4 mg, capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib placebo-matching capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Participants With Adverse Events (AEs) and Serious Adverse Events (SAEs)</title>
          <description>Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance score, laboratory values, vital sign measurements and reported adverse events (AEs) were collected and assessed to evaluate the safety of therapy throughout the study. An AE is defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a clinical investigation participant administered a drug; it does not necessarily have to have a causal relationship with this treatment. An AE can therefore be any unfavorable and unintended sign (example, a clinically significant abnormal laboratory finding), symptom, or disease temporally associated with the use of a drug, whether or not it is considered related to the drug. A serious adverse event (SAE) is an AE resulting in any of the following outcomes or deemed significant for any other reason: death; initial or prolonged inpatient hospitalization; life-threatening experience (immediate risk of dying); persistent or significant disability/incapacity; or congenital anomaly; or a medically important event.</description>
          <population>Safety population included all randomized participants who received at least 1 dose of ixazomib.</population>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="360"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="360"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>AEs</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="351"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="355"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>SAEs</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="143"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="158"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Percentage of Participants Achieving Pain Response</title>
        <description>Pain response was defined as 30% reduction from Baseline in Brief Pain Inventory-Short Form (BPI-SF) worst pain score over the last 24 hours without an increase in analgesic (oral morphine equivalents) use at 2 consecutive evaluations. The BPI-SF contains 15 items designed to capture the pain severity (“worst,” “least,” “average,” and “now” [current pain]), pain location, medication to relieve the pain, and the interference of pain with various daily activities including general activity, mood, walking activity, normal work, relations with other people, sleep, and enjoyment of life. The pain severity items are rated on a 0 to 10 scale where: 0=no pain and 10=pain as bad as you can imagine and averaged for a total score of 0 (best) to 10 (Worst).</description>
        <time_frame>At screening; Day 1 of each cycle; and thereafter every 4 weeks until disease progression</time_frame>
        <posting_date>12/2020</posting_date>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change From Baseline in the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Core Quality of Life (QOL) Questionnaire (EORTC-QLQ-C30)</title>
        <description>The EORTC-QLQ-C30 is a 30-question tool used to assess the overall quality of life in cancer participants. It consists of 15 domains: 1 global health status (GHS) scale, 5 functional scales (Physical, Role, Cognitive, Emotional, Social), and 9 symptom scales/items (Fatigue, Nausea and Vomiting, Pain, Dyspnea, Sleep Disturbance, Appetite Loss, Constipation, Diarrhea, Financial Impact).The EORTC-QLQ-C30 Global Health Status/QOL Scale is scored between 0 and 100, where higher scores indicate better Global Health Status/QOL. Negative changes from baseline indicate deterioration in QOL or functioning and positive changes indicate improvement.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline and Every 2 Cycles beginning with Cycle 2 during treatment period, End of Treatment (EOT), and every 4 Weeks in follow-up</time_frame>
        <posting_date>12/2020</posting_date>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Change From Baseline in the European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) Quality of Life Questionnaire Multiple Myeloma Module (QLQ-MY-20)</title>
        <description>The EORTC-QLQ-MY-20 is a patient-completed, 20-question quality of life questionnaire that has 4 independent subscales, 2 functional subscales (body image, future perspective), and 2 symptoms scales (disease symptoms and side-effects of treatment). The participant answers questions about their health during the past week using a 4-point scale where 1=Not at All to 4=Very Much. A negative change from Baseline indicates improvement.</description>
        <time_frame>Baseline and Every 2 Cycles beginning with Cycle 2 during treatment period, End of Treatment (EOT), and every 4 Weeks in follow-up</time_frame>
        <posting_date>12/2020</posting_date>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>OS in High-Risk Participants</title>
        <description>Overall survival (OS) is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of death. High-risk participants are defined as participants carrying cytogenic abnormalities: del(17), translocation t(4;14), or t(14;16) as reported by the central laboratory combined with those cases that lacked a central laboratory result but with known del (17), t(4;14), or t(14;16) by local laboratory. Cytogenetic abnormalities of del(13) and +1q are no longer considered to be high-risk abnormalities and are not included in the analysis. Participants without documentation of death at the time of the analysis were censored at the date when they were last known to be alive.</description>
        <time_frame>At the time of screening; Day 1 of each cycle; every 4 weeks until disease progression and thereafter every 12 weeks until death or study termination</time_frame>
        <posting_date>12/2020</posting_date>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>PFS in High-Risk Participants</title>
        <description>Progression Free Survival (PFS) is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of first documentation of disease progression or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first. Response was assessed by independent review committee (IRC) using IMWG response criteria. High-risk participants are defined as participants carrying cytogenic abnormalities: del(17), translocation t(4;14), or t(14;16) as reported by the central laboratory combined with those cases that lacked a central laboratory result but with known del (17), t(4;14), or t(14;16) by local laboratory. Cytogenetic abnormalities of del(13) and +1q are no longer considered to be high-risk abnormalities and are not included in the analysis.</description>
        <time_frame>From date of randomization until disease progression or death up to data cut-off: 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
        <population>Participants from the ITT population, all randomized participants, with cytogenic abnormalities.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Ixazomib+ Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib 4 mg, capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Placebo + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
            <description>Ixazomib placebo-matching capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>PFS in High-Risk Participants</title>
          <description>Progression Free Survival (PFS) is defined as the time from the date of randomization to the date of first documentation of disease progression or death due to any cause, whichever occurs first. Response was assessed by independent review committee (IRC) using IMWG response criteria. High-risk participants are defined as participants carrying cytogenic abnormalities: del(17), translocation t(4;14), or t(14;16) as reported by the central laboratory combined with those cases that lacked a central laboratory result but with known del (17), t(4;14), or t(14;16) by local laboratory. Cytogenetic abnormalities of del(13) and +1q are no longer considered to be high-risk abnormalities and are not included in the analysis.</description>
          <population>Participants from the ITT population, all randomized participants, with cytogenic abnormalities.</population>
          <units>months</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>95% Confidence Interval</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="75"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="62"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="21.4" lower_limit="15.67">Not estimable.</measurement>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="9.7" lower_limit="7.43" upper_limit="15.9"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Pharmacokinetic Parameters (Including Cmax, AUC and Tmax) of Ixazomib</title>
        <time_frame>Days 1 &amp; 14 of Cycles 1 &amp; 2. Day 1 of Cycles 3 to 10</time_frame>
        <posting_date>12/2020</posting_date>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Association Between Response or Resistance to Ixazomib Treatment and Proteasome and Nuclear Factor–kB (NF-kB)-Related Genes</title>
        <time_frame>At the time of screening; Day 1 of each cycle; at EOT; every 4 weeks until disease progression and thereafter every 12 weeks until death or study termination</time_frame>
        <posting_date>12/2020</posting_date>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>Randomization until data cutoff of 30 October 2014 (approximate median follow-up 15 months)</time_frame>
      <desc>The investigator had to document any occurrence of adverse events and abnormal laboratory findings. Any event spontaneously reported by the participant or observed by the investigator was recorded, irrespective of the relation to study treatment. Safety population includes all enrolled participants who received at least one dose of study drug.</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Ixazomib+ Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
          <description>Ixazomib 4 mg, capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Placebo + Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone</title>
          <description>Ixazomib placebo-matching capsules, orally, once, on Days 1, 8 and 15; plus lenalidomide 25 mg, orally, once, on Days 1 through 21; and dexamethasone 40 mg, orally, once, on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22 of a 28-day cycle for multiple cycles until progressive disease (PD) or unacceptable toxicity, whichever occurred first up to EOT projected at 80 months.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <default_vocab>MedDRA16.0</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="143" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="158" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Blood and lymphatic system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Thrombocytopenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Febrile neutropenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Neutropenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Anaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="8" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Disseminated intravascular coagulation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pancytopenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hyperviscosity syndrome</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Leukopenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Cardiac disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Atrial fibrillation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Atrial flutter</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cardiac failure</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the placebo treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cardiac failure congestive</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cardiac failure acute</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the placebo treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cardiogenic shock</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the placebo treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Myocardial infarction</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the ixazomib treatment arm and is not related to study treatment and one treatment-emergent death occurred in the placebo treatment arm and is not related to study treatment (related to lenalidomide).</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Angina pectoris</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Myocardial ischaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Acute myocardial infarction</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Acute coronary syndrome</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cardiac arrest</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the ixazomib treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cardio-respiratory arrest</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Diastolic dysfunction</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the ixazomib treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Left ventricular dysfunction</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Coronary artery disease</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Coronary artery thrombosis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Trifascicular block</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cardiovascular insufficiency</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the ixazomib treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Arrhythmia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Ear and labyrinth disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Acute vestibular syndrome</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Endocrine disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hyperthyroidism</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Eye disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Retinal vein thrombosis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Diarrhoea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nausea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Vomiting</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Constipation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Gastrooesophageal reflux disease</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dyspepsia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Ileus</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Intestinal obstruction</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Ileus paralytic</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Colitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pancreatitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Small intestinal obstruction</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Femoral hernia, obstructive</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Abdominal pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Oesophageal achalasia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Inguinal hernia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Haematochezia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Melaena</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Oesophageal ulcer</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>General disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pyrexia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="10" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="14" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Malaise</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Fatigue</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Asthenia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>General physical health deterioration</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Multi-organ failure</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the ixazomib treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Performance status decreased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Spinal pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Non-cardiac chest pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Oedema peripheral</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hyperthermia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Chills</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Death</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the placebo treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Soft tissue inflammation</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Hepatobiliary disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cholecystitis acute</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cholecystitis chronic</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hyperbilirubinaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="20" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="27" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bronchopneumonia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Lower respiratory tract infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Lung infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Lobar pneumonia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bronchitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Atypical pneumonia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Sepsis</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the placebo treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Septic shock</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Urosepsis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bacterial sepsis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Respiratory tract infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Postoperative wound infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Localised infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Influenza</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia influenzal</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>H1N1 influenza</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Gastroenteritis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Gastrointestinal infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Enterocolitis infectious</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Appendicitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Diarrhoea infectious</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Arthritis bacterial</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bronchitis bacterial</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Urinary tract infection bacterial</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cellulitis</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the placebo treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bacterial infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Herpes zoster</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pharyngitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Sinusitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Upper respiratory tract infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Chronic sinusitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Gastroenteritis viral</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Metapneumovirus infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Haemophilus infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia haemophilus</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Meningitis pneumococcal</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia pneumococcal</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the placebo treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumococcal infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumococcal sepsis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Staphylococcal bacteraemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Endocarditis staphylococcal</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Staphylococcal infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Campylobacter gastroenteritis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia moraxella</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Moraxella infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bronchopulmonary aspergillosis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Intervertebral discitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Candida pneumonia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia fungal</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the ixazomib treatment arm and is related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Salmonella sepsis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pulmonary tuberculosis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Urinary tract infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pyelonephritis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Skin infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dermo-hypodermitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pilonidal cyst</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Subcutaneous abscess</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pseudomonal sepsis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia pseudomonas aeruginosa</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Rhinovirus infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Parainfluenzae virus infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Respiratory syncytial virus infection</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Gastroenteritis caliciviral</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Endocarditis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Clostridium difficile colitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cytomegalovirus colitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Escherichia sepsis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Injury, poisoning and procedural complications</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Femur fracture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Femoral neck fracture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Foot fracture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Overdose</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Accidental overdose</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Spinal compression fracture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Spinal fracture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Thoracic vertebral fracture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Road traffic accident</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Fall</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Ligament rupture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Tendon rupture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Rib fracture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Sternal fracture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Procedural pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Concussion</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Humerus fracture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Investigations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Platelet count decreased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Weight decreased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Blood creatinine increased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Influenza A virus test positive</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Metabolism and nutrition disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypercalcaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hyponatraemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hyperglycaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypokalaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Gout</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Diabetes mellitus</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Diabetes mellitus inadequate control</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Decreased appetite</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pathological fracture</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Back pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pain in extremity</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Musculoskeletal pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Neck pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bone pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Osteolysis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Groin pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Arthritis reactive</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Arthralgia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Osteoarthritis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Neoplasms benign, malignant and unspecified (incl cysts and polyps)</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Plasma cell myeloma</sub_title>
                <description>Three treatment-emergent deaths occurred in the ixazomib treatment arm and are not related to study treatment and three treatment-emergent deaths occurred in the placebo treatment arm and are not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="8" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Plasmacytoma</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Plasma cell leukaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Adenocarcinoma of colon</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Myelodysplastic syndrome</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Metastatic gastric cancer</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Neoplasm malignant</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Prostate cancer metastatic</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Skin cancer</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Nervous system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Syncope</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Lethargy</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cerebrovascular accident</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Haemorrhagic stroke</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Ischaemic stroke</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cerebral haemorrhage</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the placebo treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Spinal cord compression</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Vascular encephalopathy</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Coma</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the ixazomib treatment arm and is not related to study treatment (related to lenalidomide) [participant also suffered from cerebrovascular accident].</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Neuralgia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Transient ischaemic attack</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Acute polyneuropathy</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Central nervous system lesion</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Convulsion</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Psychiatric disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Delirium</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Confusional state</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Psychotic disorder</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Completed suicide</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the placebo treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Renal and urinary disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Renal failure acute</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Renal failure</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Renal impairment</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Renal failure chronic</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nephrolithiasis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Urinary retention</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Urinary tract obstruction</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Reproductive system and breast disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Benign prostatic hyperplasia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Endometrial hyperplasia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Bartholin's cyst</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pulmonary embolism</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the ixazomib treatment arm and is not related to study treatment and one treatment-emergent death occurred in the placebo treatment arm and is not related to study treatment (both related to lenalidomide).</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="6" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="8" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pulmonary microemboli</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Interstitial lung disease</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Organising pneumonia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dyspnoea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="3" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Orthopnoea</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonia aspiration</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the ixazomib treatment arm and is not related to study treatment and one treatment-emergent death occurred in the placebo treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pneumonitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pulmonary congestion</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Acute respiratory distress syndrome</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Respiratory failure</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Haemoptysis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pleural effusion</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pulmonary hypertension</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Epistaxis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Lung disorder</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Psoriasis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cutaneous vasculitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Vascular disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Deep vein thrombosis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="4" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Thrombophlebitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Thrombophlebitis superficial</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypotension</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="2" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Orthostatic hypotension</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Aortic aneurysm</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Aortic dissection</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the placebo treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Haematoma</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Peripheral artery aneurysm</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Phlebitis superficial</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Aortic thrombosis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypovolaemic shock</sub_title>
                <description>One treatment-emergent death occurred in the placebo treatment arm and is not related to study treatment.</description>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Peripheral vascular disorder</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="1" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>5</frequency_threshold>
        <default_vocab>MedDRA16.0</default_vocab>
        <default_assessment>Systematic Assessment</default_assessment>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="335" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="322" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Eye disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Vision blurred</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="20" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="12" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Conjunctivitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="20" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="5" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Gastrointestinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dry mouth</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="15" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="23" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Abdominal pain upper</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="21" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="13" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Infections and infestations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Nasopharyngitis</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="71" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="66" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Investigations</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Neutrophil count decreased</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="20" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="20" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Metabolism and nutrition disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypocalcaemia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="20" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="16" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Muscle spasms</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="63" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="91" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Musculoskeletal chest pain</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="23" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="31" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Muscular weakness</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="16" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="18" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Nervous system disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Peripheral sensory neuropathy</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="67" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="50" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dizziness</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="48" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="34" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Headache</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="38" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="37" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Neuropathy peripheral</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="37" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="29" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dysgeusia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="30" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="27" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Tremor</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="21" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="33" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Paraesthesia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="28" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="14" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Psychiatric disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Insomnia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="70" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="90" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Anxiety</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="15" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="19" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Depression</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="18" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="14" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Cough</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="49" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="54" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dyspnoea exertional</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="12" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="20" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Dysphonia</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="7" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="18" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Pruritus</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="36" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="25" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Rash macular</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="22" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="22" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Rash maculo-papular</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="32" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="12" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
          <category>
            <title>Vascular disorders</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Hypertension</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="18" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="13" subjects_at_risk="360"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>In general, Investigators may publish clinical data after the earlier of (i) publication by the Sponsor or (ii) 12 months following the abandonment, early termination or database lock; provided a copy of the publication provided to Sponsor at least 30 days ahead of publication, the Sponsor's confidential information is removed as may be requested by Sponsor and Investigator defers publication for up to 60 days in the event Sponsor provides notice that it intends to file a patent application.</restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Medical Director, Clinical Science</name_or_title>
      <organization>Takeda</organization>
      <phone>+1-877-825-3327</phone>
      <email>trialdisclosures@takeda.com</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

