<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01562470</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10-104-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01562470</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Trial to Assess the Efficacy and Safety of a Novel Cellulite Cream</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Trial to Assess the Efficacy and Safety of a Novel Cellulite Cream in Reducing the Appearance of Cellulite in Human Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nutrasource Diagnostics Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nutrasource Diagnostics Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Study Hypothesis: That the test product will reduce thigh cellulite more that the placebo.

      This will be a double-blind, placebo-controlled study involving subjects with distinctive
      cellulite appearance on both thighs. Subjects will apply test cream to one thigh and placebo
      to the other, by random allocation, and cellulite appearance will be measured at week 0, 8
      and 16. Cellulite photographs will also be assessed by a (study blinded) trial researcher,
      who will assess cellulite appearance on a precisely-measured upper leg area. The subjects'
      own perception of cellulite appearance, from their diaries, will be numerically coded, and
      all three measures will be collated and analysed statistically.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Twenty subjects will be recruited through advertisements in local newspapers. Eligible
      subjects will be asked to visit the lab, where they will sign an information/consent form and
      answer a series of questions to determine their eligibility. If eligible, each subject will
      be asked to have their upper leg cellulite photographed, and thigh circumference will be
      measured. They will be given two containers of cream, labelled R (for right thigh) and L (for
      left thigh) which have been pre-weighed in their containers, and they will be instructed on
      how to apply the cream. They will record their perception of the amount of cellulite on a
      weekly basis, and they will also record any adverse events. At the two and four-month
      time-points, they will return to the lab with their diaries and cream. The cream in its
      container will be weighed to ensure compliance, and the diaries will be examined and returned
      to the participants. Thighs will again be photographed and circumference measured. At the
      four-month visit, subjects will return any remaining product for weighing, as well as their
      diaries for analysis.

      Photographs from each subject will be coded and cellulite marks assessed by arranging the
      photographs chronologically, i.e. timepoint 1, timepoint 2 and timepoint 3. They will also be
      assessed by a (blinded) trial researcher, who will assess cellulite appearance on a
      precisely-measured upper leg area in the photographs. The subjects' own perception of
      cellulite appearance, from their diaries, will be numerically coded, and all three measures
      will be collated and analysed statistically.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>thigh cellulite appearance</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction of cellulite appearance, as assessed by photographs, self-assessment and clinician assessment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Uper leg circumference and fat content</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction of upper leg circumference as measured by cm tape measure, and reduction of fat content of upper leg as measured using fat calipers</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence/absence of adverse reactions</measure>
    <time_frame>16 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Any incidence of an adverse event or events will be recorded in an Adverse Events Diary, and results collated and reported.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">23</enrollment>
  <condition>Thigh Cellulite</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>herbal-based cellulite cream</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Trial subjects will apply the treatment cream to one thigh and placebo to the other thigh, by random allocation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cellulite reduction cream</intervention_name>
    <description>1/8 tsp cellulite cream will be applied to the thigh twice daily - in the morning and at night, for a period of 16 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>herbal-based cellulite cream</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age: &gt;18 years

          -  Cellulite present equally on both thighs

          -  Willing to apply cream, as directed, for 16 weeks

          -  Willing to maintain habitual diet throughout the trial

          -  Willing to refrain from making any lifestyle changes during the life of the trial
             (exercise regimes, specific diets or cleanses)

          -  Will to refrain from making any changes to smoking habits during the study period

          -  Participant is in good health on the basis of medical history

          -  Participant understands the study procedures and provides informed consent (signed) to
             participate and authorizes the release of relevant protected health information to the
             study investigators

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of medications known to influence cellulite appearance

          -  Any leg surgical visit scheduled during trial

          -  Known intolerance or sensitivity to any ingredients in the study product

          -  Females who are pregnant, planning to be pregnant during the study period, lactating,
             or women of childbearing potential who are unwilling to commit to use of a medically
             approved form of contraception throughout the study period. The method of
             contraception must be recorded in the source documentation.

          -  Individual has a condition the Investigator believes would interfere with his or her
             ability to provide informed consent, comply with the study protocol, which might
             confound the interpretation of the study results, or put the subject at undue risk.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven Traplin, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Nutrasource Diagnostics Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maggie Laidlaw, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Nutrasource Diagnostics Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nutrasource Diagnostics Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guelph</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N1H1Y3</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 16, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 22, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 23, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 26, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cellulite</keyword>
  <keyword>reduction</keyword>
  <keyword>cream</keyword>
  <keyword>thighs</keyword>
  <keyword>women</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cellulite</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

