<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01569503</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DCIC11/12</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01569503</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vagus Nerve Stimulation a New Approach in the Treatment of Crohn's Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>VNS</acronym>
  <official_title>The Anti-inflammatory Effect of Vagus Nerve Stimulation (VNS): a New Approach in the Treatment of Crohn's Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Grenoble</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Université Joseph Fourier</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>CRSSA : Centre Recherche Service Santé Armée</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Grenoble</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether (VNS) Vagus Nerve Stimulation , is
      effective in the treatment of Crohn's disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Inflammatory bowel diseases or IBD (Crohn's disease and ulcerative colitis) are chronic
      inflammatory diseases involving the digestive tract, in particular the small bowel and/or the
      recto-colon. IBD represent a public health problem in Gastroenterology. The etiopathogeny of
      IBD is multifactorial involving immunological, genetic, infectious and environmental factors.
      An overarching hypothesis is that an unbalance of the autonomic nervous system, represented
      by the sympathetic and parasympathetic nervous system (e.g. the vagus nerve) is part of the
      mechanisms underlying the pathophysiology of IBD. A dysautonomia has been observed in IBD
      patients and we have recently demonstrated that this dysautonomia was linked to psychological
      coping, in particular in Crohn's disease. Classically, the vagus nerve, a mixed nerve, has an
      anti-inflammatory role through its central afferents which secondarily stimulate the
      hypothalamic-pituitary adrenal axis. Recent data have shown that the anti-inflammatory
      properties of the vagus nerve also involve peripheral efferents via an interaction of
      acetylcholine with nicotinic receptors leading to an inhibition of TNF release by
      macrophages. Vagus nerve stimulation (VNS) is currently used for the treatment of some forms
      of epilepsy in Human via a stimulation of vagal afferents. We have recently validated a model
      of chronic VNS (3h/d for 5 days) in freely moving rats by stimulating vagal efferents and we
      have studied the anti-inflammatory properties of VNS in an experimental model of colitis in
      rats. VNS significantly decreased body weight loss due to colitis and had an
      anti-inflammatory effect by decreasing a multivariate index of inflammation. To date, medical
      treatment of IBD (e.g. 5-aminosalicylates, corticosteroids, immunosuppressives or
      biotherapies i.e. anti-TNF) is only suspensive. The aim of our project is to propose another
      type of anti-inflammatory treatment based on neurostimulation of vagal efferents. For this
      purpose, we aim to perform a pilot study in 10 patients with moderate to severe Crohn's
      disease despite a reference treatment (corticosteroids and/or immunosuppressives) using the
      anti-inflammatory properties of VNS as an alternative to anti-TNF therapy. Central and
      peripheral effect of VNS will be also evaluated by electroencephalographic and sympatho-vagal
      (heart rate variability) recordings. The finality, at term, is to use VNS as an alternative
      to the conventional anti-TNF therapy not devoid of side effects, in particular infectious,
      with the advantage to use an intrinsic anti-inflammatory (anti-TNF) system and to take cover
      of problems of adherence to treatment which are frequently observed in the medical treatment
      of IBD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 30, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 30, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical remission 12 months after initiation of VNS</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after initiation of VNS</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical remission at 12 months :
Patient without corticoids or a dose of 20mg without dose adjustment (stable treatment) and without anti-TNF,
CDAI &lt;150 or CDAI has dropped by at least 70 or 100 points (Δ70, Δ100) compared with the baseline CDAI
Stable immunosuppressive therapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical remission 6 months after initiation of VNS</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months after initiation of VNS</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical remission at 6 months :
Patient without corticoids or a dose of 20mg without dose adjustment (stable treatment) and without anti-TNF,
CDAI &lt;150 or CDAI has dropped by at least 70 or 100 points (Δ70, Δ100) compared with the baseline CDAI
Stable immunosuppressive therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>VNS tolerance</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Description and frequency of adverse events</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of VNS effectiveness with biological markers</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of VNS effectiveness with biological markers of the pro-and anti-inflammatory status</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Endoscopic and ultrasound Assessment of VNS effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Endoscopy : CDEIS (Crohn's Disease Endoscopic Index of Severity) Ultrasound : score Migaleddu V. and al, 2009</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of the central effects of VNS</measure>
    <time_frame>At 6 weeks, at 6 months, at 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evolution of :
Sleep cycle : duration of sleep stages, sleep latency, latency between the different sleep stages.
High-resolution Electroencephalogram (EEG): Spatiotemporal evolution of the spectral density of EEG power in the different frequency bands
Correlation between high-resolution EEG markers of autonomic nervous system</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of peripheral effects of VNS on sympatho-vagal balance</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evolution of cardiac variability markers using time and frequency analysis of electrocardiogram :
Frequency Analysis : LH, HF, LF/HF
Time analysis : RMS-SD, pNN50, NN50, average cardiac rhythm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">9</enrollment>
  <condition>Crohn's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VSN</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>VNS therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>vagus nerve stimulation (VNS)</intervention_name>
    <description>VNS therapy consists of an implanted pacemaker-like device that delivers mild, intermittently pulsed signals to the patient's left vagus nerve. Roughly the size of a small pocket-watch and weighing less than one ounce, the pulse generator is implanted in the patient's left chest area. A thin thread-like wire, attached to the generator, runs under the skin to the left vagus nerve in the neck</description>
    <arm_group_label>VSN</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with CD involving the ileo-colon, diagnosed for at least 3 months prior to
             screening in flare (220&lt;CDAI&lt;450) of their disease despite a treatment reference
             (corticosteroids and/or immunosuppressives) with a stable dose will be included

          -  CRP&gt;5mg/l and/or fecal calprotectin &lt;100µg/l

          -  CDEIS &gt; 7 (Crohn's disease endoscopic index of severity)

          -  Consenting patient

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known cardiac pathology

          -  VNS contraindication

          -  Anoperineal CD only or associated with ileocolic lesion

          -  Diagnosis of indeterminate colitis, positive stool culture for enteric pathogens

          -  CD Surgery within 3 months before screening

          -  Short small intestine (&lt;1m)

          -  Koenig syndrome

          -  Intra-abdominal abscess

          -  Fistula with clinical or radiological abscess evidence

          -  Anoperineal CD with or without rectal involvement

          -  Ileostomy, colostomy, enteral or parenteral feeding

          -  Clinical condition medically or surgically unstable that, at the discretion of the
             investigator would not be compatible with the patient's participation in the study

          -  Any recent neoplasia, in the year prior to screening
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bruno BONAZ, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Grenoble university hsopital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grenoble university hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <state>Isere</state>
        <zip>38043</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meregnani J, Clarençon D, Vivier M, Peinnequin A, Mouret C, Sinniger V, Picq C, Job A, Canini F, Jacquier-Sarlin M, Bonaz B. Anti-inflammatory effect of vagus nerve stimulation in a rat model of inflammatory bowel disease. Auton Neurosci. 2011 Feb 24;160(1-2):82-9. doi: 10.1016/j.autneu.2010.10.007. Epub 2010 Nov 11.</citation>
    <PMID>21071287</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Borovikova LV, Ivanova S, Zhang M, Yang H, Botchkina GI, Watkins LR, Wang H, Abumrad N, Eaton JW, Tracey KJ. Vagus nerve stimulation attenuates the systemic inflammatory response to endotoxin. Nature. 2000 May 25;405(6785):458-62.</citation>
    <PMID>10839541</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 30, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 2, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 3, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Crohn's Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>VNS</keyword>
  <keyword>vagus nerve stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>inflammation</keyword>
  <keyword>Inflammatory bowel diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>TNF</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Crohn Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

