<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01567436</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10728</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01567436</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Prospective Field Study: Introducing the Shang Ring in Routine Clinical Settings</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective Study of Male Circumcision Using the Shang Ring in Routine Clinical Settings in Kenya &amp; Zambia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>FHI 360</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>EngenderHealth</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Weill Medical College of Cornell University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Kenya National AIDS &amp; STI Control Programme</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ministry of Medical Services, Kenya</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Teaching Hospital, Lusaka, Zambia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>FHI 360</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Male Circumcision (MC) is the only new biomedical method to demonstrate consistent efficacy
      as an HIV prevention intervention in randomized controlled trials (WHO and UNAIDS, 2007),
      based on three randomized controlled trials in Kenya, Uganda, and South Africa, that reported
      a protective effect of about 60%
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The World Health Organization, the Joint United Nations Programme on HIV/AIDS (UNAIDS), and
      other global reproductive health organizations have recognized the highly protective effect
      of male circumcision to prevent HIV infection in men. Male Circumcision (MC) is the only new
      biomedical method to demonstrate consistent efficacy as an HIV prevention intervention in
      randomized controlled trials, based on three randomized controlled trials in Kenya, Uganda,
      and South Africa, that reported a protective effect of about 60%. Subsequent studies have
      confirmed the value and persistence of MC's protection against HIV infection, and have
      demonstrated that MC also reduces the transmission of human papillomavirus.

      A wide variety of instruments, devices, and techniques are used around the world for male
      circumcision. The WHO, UNAIDS and JHPIEGO document entitled Manual for Male Circumcision
      under Local Anesthesia, includes step-by-step instructions for performing adult male
      circumcision using three different surgical procedures: the forceps-guided, dorsal slit, and
      sleeve resection methods. Procedure times for these techniques are approximately 20-30
      minutes excluding anesthesia and involve control of unavoidable bleeding and a significant
      amount of suturing, and can be associated with complications that include hematoma formation,
      infection, unsatisfactory cosmetic result, lacerations of the penile or scrotal skin and
      injury to the glans, particularly among inexperienced surgeons. Although training is
      necessary regardless of method, devices for MC have the potential to reduce both training
      time and surgical duration because neither hemostasis nor suturing is needed for most
      devices.

      The Shang Ring is an innovative device for adult male circumcision that has been on the
      Chinese market since 2005. The Shang Ring is manufactured by Wuhu SNNDA Medical Treatment
      Appliance Technology Co., Ltd (SNNDA).

      In the current African setting, only surgical circumcision is available for adults. Devices
      such as the Shang Ring have the potential to simplify and shorten surgery by eliminating the
      need for suturing and hemostasis. Data from two small studies in Kenya suggest that the Shang
      Ring has an acceptable safety profile. A randomized controlled trial was conducted in Kenya
      and Zambia to provide further data.

      Circumcision using the Shang Ring involves a few simple steps. First, a special measuring
      strip is used to determine which Shang Ring size to use. Following administration of local
      anesthesia, the inner ring is fitted at the base of the glans penis. Next, the foreskin is
      everted over the inner ring and the outer ring is secured (locked) over the inner ring, thus
      encasing the foreskin. The sterile device forms a tight seal. The foreskin is excised and
      several nicks are made in the foreskin on the underside of the device to prevent formation of
      a stiff, circumferential scab. Bleeding is minimal and no suturing or hemostasis is required.
      Finally, the participant returns in seven days for removal of the Shang Ring device. After
      removal, a bandage is applied to the wound. Men may be given a supply of bandages and told to
      change the bandaging daily or as needed.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Participants with Adverse Events as a Measure of Safety and Tolerability</measure>
    <time_frame>42 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of the Shang Ring Procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>42 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of men completely healed at 42 days</measure>
    <time_frame>42 Days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1200</enrollment>
  <condition>Male Circumcision</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Shang Ring</intervention_name>
    <description>The Shang Ring is a sterile device consisting of two concentric medical grade plastic rings: an inner ring with a silicone band and an outer, hinged ring. The inner ring fits inside the outer ring which will lock when snapped together. The Shang Ring comes in multiple sizes. The appropriate size is determined through use of a measuring strip. To ensure that men cannot remove the device prematurely, the locking mechanism must be broken open using a tool that is similar to a scalpel handle. Then, a pair of scissors is used to remove the inner ring, and a bandage or gauze dressing is applied.</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        All men enrolled in this research study must meet the following inclusion criteria:

          -  Must be aged 18 and 54 years;

          -  Must be uncircumcised (on examination);

          -  Must be in good general health;

          -  Must agree to HIV counseling and testing no more than one week before the procedure;

          -  Must be free of genital ulcerations or other visible signs of STI (on examination);

          -  Must be able to understand study procedures and requirements of study participation;

          -  Must agree to return to the healthcare facility for the full schedule of follow-up
             visits after his circumcision;

          -  Must freely consent to participate in the study and sign a written informed consent
             form;

          -  Must have a cell phone or access to a cell phone; and,

          -  Must agree to provide the study staff with an address, phone number, or other locator
             information while participating in the research study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  A man will be excluded from participation in this research study if he has any of the
             following exclusion criteria:

               -  Has a known allergy or sensitivity to lidocaine or other local anesthesia;

               -  Takes a medication that would be a contraindication for elective surgery, such as
                  an anticoagulant or steroid;

               -  Has known bleeding/clotting disorder (e.g. hemophilia); or

               -  Has an active genital infection, anatomic abnormality or other condition (e.g.
                  severe obesity, diabetes or sickle cell anemia), which in the opinion of the
                  surgeon, prevents the man from undergoing a circumcision as part of this study;

               -  Is currently participating in another biomedical study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>54 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marc Goldstein, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Cornell Medical College, NY, USA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark A Barone, DVM, MS</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>EngenderHealth, NY, USA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philip S Li, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Cornell Medical College, NY, USA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard Lee, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Weill Cornell Medical College, NY, USA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Perchal, MA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>EngenderHealth, NY, USA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jared Mogouche, MD ChB</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>EngenderHealth, Kisumu, Kenya</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Quentin Awori, MB ChB</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>EngenderHealth, Homa Bay, Kenya</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Raymond Simba, MB ChB MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Homa Bay District Hospital, Ministry of Health, Homa Bay, Kenya</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicholas Muraguri, MB ChB MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National AIDS/STD Control Programme, Nairobi, Kenya</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John M Wekesa, MB ChB MMed</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ministry of Medical Services, Nairobi, Kenya</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kasonde Bowa, MSc M. Med FRCS FACS FCS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Zambia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Zulu, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Teaching Hospital, Lusaka, Zambia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Homa Bay District Hospital male circumcision clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Homa Bay</city>
        <state>Nyanza</state>
        <zip>40300</zip>
        <country>Kenya</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Society for Family Planning Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lusaka</city>
        <country>Zambia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Kenya</country>
    <country>Zambia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 28, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 28, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 30, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 26, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 26, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 27, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

