<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01568710</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>120101</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>12-H-0101</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01568710</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Blood Flow and Pain Crises in People With Sickle Cell Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Measurement of the Reactive Hyperemia Index in Sickle Cell Patients During Pain Crisis and After Recovery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute (NHLBI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute for Biomedical Imaging and Bioengineering (NIBIB)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Many people with sickle cell disease have repeated episodes of severe pain that lasts for
      days, requiring hospital care. These episodes, called pain crises, may be caused by changes
      in blood flow. Researchers want to study blood flow in people with sickle cell disease who
      are having a pain crisis and compare it with their blood flow after the pain crisis has
      resolved. They also want to compare these measurements against blood flow in healthy people
      who do not have sickle cell disease.

      Objectives:

      - To study whether changes in blood flow cause pain crises in people with sickle cell
      disease.

      Eligibility:

        -  Individuals at least 18 years of age who have sickle cell disease and are being treated
           for a pain crisis.

        -  Individuals at least 18 years of age who have sickle cell disease and are not
           experiencing a pain crisis.

        -  Healthy volunteers matched by age and gender with the participants who have sickle cell
           disease.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Blood and urine
           samples will be collected.

        -  Participants having a sickle cell pain crisis will have two visits, one during the
           crisis and one about 4 weeks after the crisis has resolved.

        -  Participants not having a sickle cell pain crisis will have one or two study visits.
           Blood samples will be collected during at least one of these visits.

        -  Healthy volunteers will have one or two study visits. Blood samples will be collected
           during at least one of these visits.

        -  During each visit for all participants, cameras and blood flow monitoring equipment will
           be used to measure blood flow in the forearm.

      sickle cell disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Severe recurrent pain is the most common cause of acute morbidity in sickle cell disease1.
      The underlying pathogenesis was initially thought to be ischemia from obstruction of
      capillary beds by stiffened red blood cells; however, there is evidence that other factors
      contribute to the pathogenesis of sickle cell pain crisis, such as inflammation and
      coagulation, ischemia-reperfusion injury, angiogenesis balance, and vasomotor tone processes
      that are regulated by endothelial nitric oxide.

      Recent clinical data suggest that subjects with sickle cell disease suffer from chronically
      impaired nitric oxide bioavailability. This has been attributed to increased consumption of
      nitric oxide by hemoglobin and reactive oxygen species, or decreased production of nitric
      oxide by endothelial cells; however the roles of nitric oxide bioavailability and endothelial
      dysfunction during acute pain crisis are controversial and incompletely understood. Although
      there have been several studies of endothelial function in steady state sickle cell disease,
      there has been no comprehensive study of endothelial function during pain crisis.

      In this study, our primary objective is to measure the reactive hyperemia index (a measure of
      the endothelial response to shear stress) in twenty sickle cell subjects during acute pain
      crisis and to compare it with the reactive hyperemia index measured after recovery from pain
      crisis. This will identify whether there are acute changes in endothelial cell function
      during sickle cell pain crisis. Our secondary objective is to compare the reactive hyperemia
      index of thirty-five sickle cell subjects in steady state versus the reactive hyperemia index
      of thirty-five healthy control subjects. This will identify whether there are chronic
      differences in endothelial function between sickle cell subjects and healthy control
      subjects.

      This study will determine if there are defects in endothelium-dependent vasodilation in
      response to shear stress during sickle cell pain crisis. Moreover, this study provides an
      opportunity to evaluate new physiologic biomarkers of sickle cell pain crisis based on
      measurements of blood flow, temperature, and oxygenation in the skin. These measurements may
      serve as clinical endpoints in future studies of disease pathogenesis or therapeutic
      interventions for sickle cell disease.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 21, 2012</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Skin Blood Flood</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Skin Temperature</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tissue oxygenation</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">94</enrollment>
  <condition>Sickle Cell Disease</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA FOR SUBJECTS WITH SICKLE CELL DISEASE IN PAIN CRISIS:

               1. Age 18 years or older.

               2. Diagnosis of sickle cell anemia:

                    1. Diagnosis of sickle cell disease (electrophoresis or HPLC documentation of
                       hemoglobin SS, SC, S-beta-thalassemia or other hemoglobinopathies causing
                       sickle cell disease is required).

                    2. Acute onset pain crisis in a distribution typical for that subject, onset
                       within the last 7 days and for which hospitalization and parenteral narcotic
                       pain treatment are required.

               3. Ability to provide informed written consent.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA FOR SUBJECTS WITH SICKLE CELL DISEASE IN PAIN CRISIS:

          1. Pregnancy.

          2. History of non-trivial injury, burns, surgery or skin ulcers on the arms.

          3. Carrier of drug resistant bacteria that normally requires isolation while visiting a
             hospital.

          4. Administration of any of the following drugs within the last 14 days:

               -  Phosphodiesterase-5 inhibitors (sildenafil, vardenafil, tadalafil)

               -  Endothelin-1 receptor blockers (bosentan, sitaxentan, ambrisentan, tezosentan)

               -  Nitric oxide donors (nitroglycerin, nitroprusside, nitrates)

          5. Ingestion of caffeine within the 12 hours before the start of the study appointment,
             or tobacco use within the 30 days before the study appointment.

          6. Diagnosis with any of the following chronic diseases or conditions:

               -  Uncontrolled high blood pressure (systolic blood pressure must not be greater
                  than 160 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure greater than 90 mmHg)

               -  Uncontrolled high cholesterol (total cholesterol must not be greater than 240
                  mg/dL)

               -  Uncontrolled diabetes (must not have both a documented history of diabetes and
                  random blood glucose of greater than 200 mg/dL)

               -  Chronic kidney disease (serum creatinine must not be greater than 2 mg/dL)

               -  Coronary artery disease

               -  Peripheral vascular disease

          7. Received a blood transfusion within 7 days of the study procedure.

        SICKLE CELL DISEASE SUBJECTS IN STEADY STATE

        INCLUSION CRITERIA FOR SUBJECTS WITH SICKLE CELL DISEASE IN STEADY STATE:

          1. Age 18 years or older.

          2. Diagnosis of sickle cell anemia:

             a.Diagnosis of sickle cell disease (electrophoresis or HPLC documentation of
             hemoglobin SS, SC, S-beta-thalassemia or other hemoglobinopathies causing sickle cell
             disease is required).

          3. Ability to provide informed written consent.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA FOR SUBJECTS WITH SICKLE CELL DISEASE IN STEADY STATE:

          1. Pregnancy.

          2. History of non-trivial trauma, burns, surgery or skin ulcers on the arms.

          3. Carrier of drug resistant bacteria that normally requires isolation while visiting a
             hospital.

          4. Experience of an acute pain crisis requiring intravenous (IV) narcotics and hospital
             admission within the last 14 days.

          5. Ingestion of caffeine within the 12 hours before the start of the study appointment,
             or tobacco use within the 30 days before the study appointment.

          6. Administration of any of the following drugs within the last 14 days:

               -  Phosphodiesterase-5 inhibitors (sildenafil, vardenafil, tadalafil)

               -  Endothelin-1 receptor blockers (bosentan, sitaxentan, ambrisentan, tezosentan)

               -  Nitric oxide donors (nitroglycerin, nitroprusside, nitrates)

          7. Diagnosis of any of the following chronic diseases or conditions: &lt;TAB&gt;

               -  Uncontrolled high blood pressure (systolic blood pressure must not be greater
                  than 160 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure greater than 90 mmHg)

               -  Uncontrolled high cholesterol (total cholesterol must not be greater than 240
                  mg/dL)

               -  Uncontrolled diabetes (must not have both a documented history of diabetes and
                  random blood glucose of greater than 200 mg/dL)

               -  Chronic kidney disease (serum creatinine must not be greater than 2 mg/dL)

               -  Coronary artery disease

               -  Peripheral vascular disease

          8. Received a blood transfusion within 7 days of the study procedure.

        HEALTHY CONTROL SUBJECTS

        INCLUSION CRITERIA FOR HEALTHY CONTROL SUBJECTS

          1. Age 18 years or older.

          2. African, of African descent or Hispanic

          3. Ability to provide informed written consent.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA FOR HEALTHY CONTROL SUBJECTS

          1. Pregnancy.

          2. History of non-trivial injury, burns, surgery or skin ulcers on the arms.

          3. Carrier of drug resistant bacteria that normally requires isolation while visiting a
             hospital.

          4. Administration of any of the following drugs within the last 14 days:

               -  Phosphodiesterase-5 inhibitors (sildenafil, vardenafil, tadalafil)

               -  Endothelin-1 receptor blockers (bosentan, sitaxentan, ambrisentan, tezosentan)

               -  Nitric oxide donors (nitroglycerin, nitroprusside, nitrates)

          5. Ingestion of caffeine in the 12 hours before the start of the study appointment, or
             used tobacco in the 30 days before the study appointment.

          6. Diagnosis with any of the following chronic diseases or conditions:

               -  Sickle cell disease &lt;TAB&gt;

               -  Uncontrolled high blood pressure (systolic blood pressure must not be greater
                  than 160 mmHg or diastolic blood pressure greater than 90 mmHg)

               -  Uncontrolled high cholesterol (total cholesterol must not be greater than 240
                  mg/dL)

               -  Uncontrolled diabetes (must not have both a documented history of diabetes and
                  random blood glucose of greater than 200 mg/dL)

               -  Chronic kidney disease (serum creatinine must not be greater than 2 mg/dL)

               -  Coronary artery disease

               -  Peripheral vascular disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hans C Ackerman, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2012-H-0101.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Platt OS, Thorington BD, Brambilla DJ, Milner PF, Rosse WF, Vichinsky E, Kinney TR. Pain in sickle cell disease. Rates and risk factors. N Engl J Med. 1991 Jul 4;325(1):11-6.</citation>
    <PMID>1710777</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nagel RL. Sickle cell anemia is a multigene disease: sickle painful crises, a case in point. Am J Hematol. 1993 Jan;42(1):96-101. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8416304</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hebbel RP, Vercellotti GM. The endothelial biology of sickle cell disease. J Lab Clin Med. 1997 Mar;129(3):288-93. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9042813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 28, 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 30, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 30, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 2, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 14, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Blood Flow</keyword>
  <keyword>Endothelium</keyword>
  <keyword>Nitric Oxide</keyword>
  <keyword>Oximetry</keyword>
  <keyword>Laser Doppler</keyword>
  <keyword>Sickle Cell Disease</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anemia, Sickle Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

