<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01567033</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201103147</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01567033</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Healthy Eating and Active Living Taught at Home</brief_title>
  <acronym>HEALTH</acronym>
  <official_title>Translating a Weight Loss Intervention Through a National Home Visiting Program</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this research study is to evaluate two different Parents as Teachers
      curriculums taught by parent educators, during home visits. The control curriculum includes
      only the standard PAT lessons; the intervention curriculum includes the standard PAT lessons
      plus additional information about how families can live healthy and active lives while
      reaching a healthy weight. The investigators hypothesize the intervention lessons will change
      the way people eat and/or their activity level.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The primary aim is to test Healthy Eating &amp; Active Living Taught at Home (HEALTH), which
      adapts and integrates the Diabetes Prevention Program lifestyle intervention within Parents
      As Teachers (PAT), a national home visiting program on which many high needs populations rely
      for parent-child information and services. Specific aims 1 and 2 will evaluate the impact of
      HEALTH on lifestyle behaviors and weight of obese mothers and their overweight/obese
      preschool child across multiple PAT regions. Specific aims 3 and 4 will address elements of
      external validity through evaluation of factors that impact the uptake of HEALTH within the
      PAT organization.

      Specific aim 1. Using a group randomized, nested cohort design, evaluate the impact of HEALTH
      on obese women (BMI 30-45 kg/m2; age 18-45 y old) randomized to either control regions
      receiving the standard PAT program, or intervention regions receiving HEALTH.

      Hypothesis 1.1 The primary hypothesis is at the conclusion of the study, when compared to the
      control group, participants in HEALTH will achieve a 7% weight loss at 12 months and maintain
      a 5% weight loss at 24 months, which will be at least two-fold greater than that achieved in
      the control group.

      The secondary hypotheses are that at the conclusion of the study, when compared to the
      control group, participants in HEALTH will significantly:

      Hypothesis 1.2 Improve clinical outcomes of waist circumference and systolic and diastolic
      blood pressure; Hypothesis 1.3 Improve knowledge of evidence-based lifestyle behaviors and
      quality of life; Hypothesis 1.4 Decrease caloric intake Hypothesis 1.5 Increase moderate
      intensity walking.

      Specific aim 2. The secondary aim is to determine whether improvements in 'mother to child'
      behaviors of HEALTH participants will explain all or part of changes in the weight trajectory
      of the participant's overweight (&gt;85th percentile) or obese (&gt;95th percentile) preschool
      child. The hypotheses are that at the conclusion of the study, when compared to the control
      group:

      Hypothesis 2.1 There will be a significantly greater proportion of participants in the HEALTH
      group who improve child feeding practices with their preschool child; Hypothesis 2.2 There
      will be a significantly greater proportion of preschool children in the HEALTH group who
      maintain or reduce their weight as measured by BMI Z-score.

      Specific aim 3. The aim is to assess and provide information on the external validity of
      HEALTH to enhance research translation (e.g. reach and representativeness, program
      implementation or adaptation, decision making outcomes, and maintenance or
      institutionalization).

      Question 3.1 Are HEALTH adopters representative of control PAT participants and parent
      educators? Question 3.2 Are HEALTH parent educators effectively trained to deliver the
      intervention? Question 3.3 Is HEALTH implemented as designed or adapted for content,
      consistency, or intensity? Question 3.4 Is HEALTH maintained as an institutionalized
      component of PAT practice? Specific aim 4. The aim is to determine the cost-utility of HEALTH
      in decreasing obesity and risk for diabetes from two perspectives: the service provider and
      state health agencies.

      Question 4.1 Is the implementation and maintenance of HEALTH effective from a cost-utility
      perspective for the participants enrolled in the program and the agencies considering
      implementing these programs? Question 4.2 Is HEALTH effective in improving health quality,
      from the perspective of state agencies considering funding decisions for this and similar
      programs?
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 31, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 31, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Mass Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in BMI from baseline to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Body mass index (BMI) will be used to classify participants as &quot;obese&quot;. The investigators will calculate the BMI from weight and height measurements. Participants weight measurement will be obtained using a calibrated scale placed on a solid flat surface. The screener will record the weight in pounds. Height measurement will be the maximum vertical height measured using a stadiometer on a solid flat surface with a fixed vertical backboard and an adjustable headpiece or an approved portable stadiometer on a solid flat surface with an adjustable headpiece.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Waist Circumference</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in waist circumference from baseline to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Waist circumference will be used to estimate abdominal adiposity which is associated with risk of Type 2 diabetes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood Pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>Change in blood pressure from baseline to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>In accordance with American Heart Association guidelines, we will follow the recommendations and protocol for blood pressure measurement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>Changes in surveys from baseline to 24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Survey includes: dietary screener, International Physical Activity Questionnaire, SF-12 to assess quality of life, a knowledge test to reflect the HEALTH intervention, questions asking about lifestyle patterns, environmental questions, sleep, Preschooler Feeding Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">460</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes</condition>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Intervention participants received HEALTH, which embedded a lifestyle intervention derived from DPP within the standard PAT curriculum</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PAT Curriculum + Health Information</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants in the intervention group will receive the standard PAT curriculum plus information about healthy eating and an active lifestyle. This curriculum will be taught during up to 36 home visits in two years. Months 1-3 the visits are weekly; months 4-6 visits are biweekly; months 7-24 visits are monthly</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  female, obese (BMI 30 -45 kg/m2),have at least one overweight or obese preschool child
             (&gt;60th percentile) living in the home, plan to continue in the PAT program for two
             years, and able to give informed consent to participate in HEALTH.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  current pregnancy or plan to become pregnant in the next 24 months, inability to speak
             English, current enrollment in any weight loss program, a diagnosis and/or undergoing
             treatment for diabetes, cardiovascular disease, or eating disorders, or inability to
             exercise or engage in a walking program.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Debra Haire Joshu, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 14, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 27, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 30, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Home visiting</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

