<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01636999</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12-007</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01636999</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparing Sedara to Butorphanol in Early Labor</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparing Pain Relief in Early Labor: Nitrous Oxide Versus Butorphonol Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>West Penn Allegheny Health System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>West Penn Allegheny Health System</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Nitrous oxide (N2O) has been used for the treatment of labor pains for over 150 years. The
      longevity of its use in clinical practice can be attributed to its excellent safety profile,
      ease of administration, and familiarity of use among health-care providers. Sedara is a
      self-administered 50% N2O, 50% oxygen gas mixture with pain relieving and anxiety reducing
      properties recently available for use in the United States (US) to treat various painful
      clnical situations, including labor pains.

      In the US, epidural or intravenous administration of narcotic medications is one of the most
      common and frequently requested treatments for patients experiencing labor pains. Although
      generally considered safe, complications are common with epidurals, including fetal distress,
      low blood pressure in the mother, respiratory distress, and headache. In our hospital system,
      the use of the synthetic intravenous painkiller, Butorphanol, is a mainstay of treatment for
      labor pains. It too can have undesirable side effects in the mother, including low blood
      pressure and breathing problems.

      Because Sedara has until recently been unavailable in the US, studies comparing its efficacy
      with other agents for labor pain have been confined to Europe, predominantly in the United
      Kingdom. Several studies have investigated the efficacy of Sedara versus inhalation and
      intravenous anesthetics in various countries. We have obtained several Sedara devices for use
      in the West Penn Allegheny Health System (WPAHS) Department of Anesthesiology and would like
      to examine its efficacy in our target population of women experiencing pain during early
      labor.

      Hypothesis - Sedara will provide equivalent or superior pain relief among term, adult
      parturients in early labor (less than 5cm cervical dilation) compared to intravenous
      butorphanol.

      Primary aim - Compare Sedara versus butorphanol in a single-blinded randomized trial with the
      main outcome measure being reduction in labor pains at various time intervals.

      Our findings may be significant in terms of improving safety and efficacy of pain relief
      among women experienceing labor pains. Given that Sedara has not been previously studied in
      the US, the results may influence current obstetrical and pain management practices.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>September 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain relief</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome measure of pain relief will be measured using a 100mm visual analog scale (VAS) immediately prior to administration of the test medication (either Sedara or butorphanol) and again at 5, 15, 30 and 60 minutes following the medication start time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nausea, Sedation, Satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>60 minutes</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary outcome measures collected include maternal reported level nausea, sedation, and overall satisfaction with analgesia using the Visual Analog Scores Scale at 0, 5, 15, 30 and 60 minutes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Labor Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Butorphanol</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The main study arm will be examining how well a 50% Nitrous Oxide/50% Oxygen gas mixture is in reducing labor pains in term labor patients with less than 5 cm cervical dilation, compared to 2mg of Butorphanol (a common synthetic opiod used for labor pains in this setting).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>50% Nitrous Oxide/50% Oxygen</intervention_name>
    <description>The gas mixture is provided via the Sedara portable gas delivery system. This system is equipped with a non-rebreather mask which the patient holds over their mouth and nose. The delivery of the gas is only triggered by the patient's spontaneous breath. The gas machine will be provided to the patient to use as much as they like during the 60 minutes data collection period. The only dose which the machine allows to be administered is 50% Nitrous Oxide/50% oxygen.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Butorphanol</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sedara (FDA 510K Approval No. K101286)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Female

          -  18 years of age or older

          -  Presents in active labor

          -  Full term pregnancy (at least 37 and up to 42 weeks gestation)

          -  Less than 5 cm cervical dilation on exam

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who have received prior regional or opioid analgesia

          -  Patients who have taken oral analgesics (narcotic or non-steroidal anti inflammatory
             drugs) within 6 hours prior to presentation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Helene Finegold, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Associate Residency Program Director</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher Troianos, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Residency Program Director</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Helene Finegold, MD</last_name>
    <phone>412-578-5323</phone>
    <email>HFinegol@wpahs.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mete Akin, DO, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>786-246-1758</phone>
    <email>makin@wpahs.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>West Penn Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pittsburgh</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>152064231</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mete Akin, DO, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>786-246-1758</phone>
      <email>makin@wpahs.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Helene Finegold, MD</last_name>
      <phone>412-578-5323</phone>
      <email>HFinegol@wpahs.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mete Akin, DO, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Helene Finegold, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Volmanen P, Palomäki O, Ahonen J. Alternatives to neuraxial analgesia for labor. Curr Opin Anaesthesiol. 2011 Jun;24(3):235-41. doi: 10.1097/ACO.0b013e328345ad18. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>21451402</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosen MA. Nitrous oxide for relief of labor pain: a systematic review. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2002 May;186(5 Suppl Nature):S110-26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12011877</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maslekar S, Gardiner A, Hughes M, Culbert B, Duthie GS. Randomized clinical trial of Entonox versus midazolam-fentanyl sedation for colonoscopy. Br J Surg. 2009 Apr;96(4):361-8. doi: 10.1002/bjs.6467.</citation>
    <PMID>19283736</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Young P, Emery NC, Reisin R. Epidural analgesia for labor and delivery. N Engl J Med. 2010 Jul 22;363(4):395.</citation>
    <PMID>20677364</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Viscomi CM. Randomized trial of epidural versus intravenous analgesia during labor. Obstet Gynecol. 1996 Mar;87(3):480-2.</citation>
    <PMID>8598984</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dickinson JE, Paech MJ, McDonald SJ, Evans SF. Maternal satisfaction with childbirth and intrapartum analgesia in nulliparous labour. Aust N Z J Obstet Gynaecol. 2003 Dec;43(6):463-8.</citation>
    <PMID>14712952</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yeo ST, Holdcroft A, Yentis SM, Stewart A, Bassett P. Analgesia with sevoflurane during labour: ii. Sevoflurane compared with Entonox for labour analgesia. Br J Anaesth. 2007 Jan;98(1):110-5.</citation>
    <PMID>17158129</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Volmanen P, Akural E, Raudaskoski T, Ohtonen P, Alahuhta S. Comparison of remifentanil and nitrous oxide in labour analgesia. Acta Anaesthesiol Scand. 2005 Apr;49(4):453-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15777291</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Talebi H, Nourozi A, Jamilian M, Baharfar N, Eghtesadi-Araghi P. Entonox for labor pain: a randomized placebo controlled trial. Pak J Biol Sci. 2009 Sep 1;12(17):1217-21.</citation>
    <PMID>19943458</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kelly AM. Does the clinically significant difference in visual analog scale pain scores vary with gender, age, or cause of pain? Acad Emerg Med. 1998 Nov;5(11):1086-90.</citation>
    <PMID>9835471</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yamamoto LG, Nomura JT, Sato RL, Ahern RM, Snow JL, Kuwaye TT. Minimum clinically significant VAS differences for simultaneous (paired) interval serial pain assessments. Am J Emerg Med. 2003 May;21(3):176-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12811707</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee JS, Hobden E, Stiell IG, Wells GA. Clinically important change in the visual analog scale after adequate pain control. Acad Emerg Med. 2003 Oct;10(10):1128-30.</citation>
    <PMID>14525749</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 6, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 9, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 10, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 9, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 9, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 10, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>West Penn Allegheny Health System</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mete Akin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Anesthesiology Resident</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sedara</keyword>
  <keyword>Nitrous Oxide</keyword>
  <keyword>Butorphanol</keyword>
  <keyword>Visual Analog Scale</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Labor Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obstetric Labor, Premature</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nitrous Oxide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Butorphanol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

