<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01637389</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>UCB_CPHS_2009-1-47</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01637389</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Safe-Water Programs in Baja California Sur, Mexico</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Stepped Wedge, Cluster-randomized Impact Evaluation of a Household UV-treatment and Safe Storage Drinking Water Intervention in Rural Baja California Sur, Mexico</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Berkeley</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundacion Cantaro Azul</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Berkeley</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Fundacion Cantaro Azul (FCA) is a non-profit organization in Baja California Sur, Mexico
      (BCS). Since 2006 FCA has piloted a safe drinking-water program in rural regions of BCS. The
      premise of their safe drinking-water programs has been the installation of household
      drinking-water disinfection systems which utilize an ultra-violet technology (UV) developed
      at the University of California, Berkeley. While the systems have been tested for safety and
      effectiveness at inactivating waterborne pathogens, FCA is interested in rigorously
      evaluating the impact of their safe drinking-water program at the population level. FCA is
      looking to expand their safe-water program during 2009 and 2010 to newly identified
      communities that lack safe-drinking water. In order to evaluate the community level
      effectiveness of their program FCA has agreed to randomize the timing of this expansion which
      will allow the lead investigators and key personal in this protocol to conduct a meaningful,
      scientific evaluation of the impact of their program through a randomized stepped wedge
      design.

      The research described in this protocol has four (4) primary objectives:

        1. To evaluate the impact the implementation of the safe drinking-water programs has on
           rates of gastrointestinal events in rural BCS communities;

        2. To evaluate the impact of the safe drinking-water programs on concentrations of fecal
           contamination in household drinking-water in rural BCS communities;

        3. To evaluate other-health and non-water impacts on communities where the safe-water
           programs are implemented, including school and work absenteeism, and health care costs;

        4. To identify household, program and system design characteristics that affect user
           compliance with the disinfection strategies.

      The investigators hypothesize that households that receive an UV based drinking-water
      disinfection system through the safe-water program will have reduced prevalence of
      gastrointestinal illness, and reductions in fecal contamination of household drinking-water,
      measured as concentrations of Escherichia Coli per 100 ml of water. Similarly, the
      investigators hypothesize that these communities will also have reduced health care costs,
      and school and work absenteeism due to the implementation of the safe drinking-water
      programs. The investigators further hypothesize that household level characteristics and
      specific program characteristics will differentially impact user compliance, measured as the
      sustained use of the systems over the course of the study. In order to evaluate the last
      hypothesis (Objective 4) two program variations will be rolled out to inform future
      programmatic decisions. A priori the investigators do not anticipate that these program
      variations will impact population measures for Objectives 1 and 2, but the investigators will
      explore these assumptions during analysis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Twenty-five to thirty communities (400-600 households) have been identified by Fundacion
      Cantaro Azul (FCA) as communities that are appropriate for their safe water program. These
      communities were identified based on their sources of water (chemical and taste
      characteristics) and resource availability (access to electricity and lack of access to piped
      water). Fundacion Cantaro Azul is planning to expand their safe-drinking water programs to
      all 600 households in these communities. In order to allow for a meaningful evaluation of the
      impact of their program the organization has agreed to randomize the timing of implementation
      of the safe drinking-water program to eligible communities. This will allow independent
      researchers (the lead investigator and key personal in this protocol) to make household
      visits during the implementation of the programs and will further allow for a valid
      evaluation of the programs' impact using a stepped wedge study design. Through the
      stepped-wedge study design all communities, over a 12-15 month, period will be approached by
      Fundacion Cantaro Azul for promotional meetings; since no community will have received the
      intervention they will be acting as their own controls until the time they are approached by
      the organization. Randomizing the time at which a community is approached reduces bias and
      allows for meaningful evaluation of differences in outcomes due to the safe drinking-water
      program. As part of this study design a randomly assigned, predetermined number of rural BCS
      communities will be approached every two-months for enrollment in the safe water program by
      Fundacion Cantaro Azul, and thus 'cross-over' from the comparison group to the safe-water
      group. Within each of these crossover groups half of the clusters will receive a &quot;Basic&quot;
      program variation, and half will receive an &quot;Enhance&quot; program variation. This process will
      continue until all consenting households in the 25-30 communities have received a UV
      disinfection system, and related support through the safe drinking-water program. Field
      teams, trained and supervised by the lead investigator and key personal listed in this
      protocol, will conduct independent (from Fundacion Cantaro Azul) household visits to collect
      data on the outcomes of interest. During household visits structured interviews and
      water-quality sampling will be used to measure these outcomes (prevalence of gastrointestinal
      events, concentrations of E.coli in household drinking-water, school and work absenteeism and
      compliance with the disinfection strategy.) The stepped-wedge design will allow for
      evaluation of the impacts of the safe drinking-water programs while allowing the relatively
      small organization to manage the logistics of installing 600 household disinfection systems,
      in a manner consistent with their mission, commitments to regional governmental
      collaborators, and fiscal restraints.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Household Microbial Drinking Water Quality</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <description>We measure household drinking water quality using Escherichia Coli concentrations measured through standard techniques. Each household is visited a maximum of 7 times over 15 months. Water is collected from household drinking water storage containers by a household respondent as though they were going to take a drink, and a 100 ml sample is taken and processed. We use multiple definitions of water contamination risk based World Health Organization classifications (&gt;1 E.coli (low), &gt;10 E.coli (medium), &gt;100 E.coli (high)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Diarrhea</measure>
    <time_frame>15 months</time_frame>
    <description>We measure the 7-day prevalence of diarrhea symptoms (3 or more loose/watery stools in a 24 hour period, or one with blood or mucus) through household interviews. Each household is visited a maximum of 7 times (every 2 months) over the 15 month study period for a total possible of 49 days of recall.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1731</enrollment>
  <condition>Diarrhea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>All communities (independent units/clusters) start in the control and have no intervention. All control communities cross-over to the intervention in a randomized sequence over the course of 12-15 month study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Basic Safe Water Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Basic program represents a variation in the implementation of the overall intervention: a community level safe-water program that is initiated with promotional meetings and followed by the offer to install Mesita Azul disinfection systems at the household level. Communities (independent units/cluster) cross-over from the control group to the intervention group in a randomized stepped-wedge fashion -- within each crossover group of 4 clusters, 2 are randomized to the Basic program.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Safe Water Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Enhanced program represents a variation in the implementation of the overall intervention: a community level safe-water program that is initiated with promotional meetings and followed by the offer to install Mesita Azul disinfection systems at the household level. Communities (independent units/cluster) cross-over from the control group to the intervention group in a randomized stepped-wedge fashion -- within each crossover group of 4 clusters, 2 are randomized to the Enhanced program.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Basic Safe Water Program</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is community promotional meetings followed by household installations of a UV-based drinking water disinfection system (Mesita Azul). Households can opt-in at the meetings, or when the organization returns for installations in that community (~2 weeks later). Mesita Azul utilizes a 15-watt UV lamp to disinfect water and a closed mouth collection container for safe storage. The system utlizes UV-Tube technology developed as a method to disinfect water in low- and middle-income communities. The Basic Safe Water Program receives: the community meeting; installation of a Mesita Azul; a six month technical guarantee; one safe-storage container; training of one household member in operation and basic maintenance of the technology; training of at least one local resident in repair and system maintenance; and follow up after four to six months of the installation date.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Basic Safe Water Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enhanced Safe Water Program</intervention_name>
    <description>The intervention is community promotional meetings followed by household installations of a UV-based drinking water disinfection system (Mesita Azul). Households can opt-in at the meetings, or when the organization returns for installations in that community (~2 weeks later). Mesita Azul utilizes a 15-watt UV lamp to disinfect water and a closed mouth collection container for safe storage. The system utlizes UV-Tube technology developed as a method to disinfect water in low- and middle-income communities. The Enhanced program complements the Basic version with: a water quality analysis and presentation of results to households at the community meeting; a six-month money back guarantee; the provision of two safe-storage containers to facilitate access to disinfected water at different locations within the household; training of two household members in operation and basic maintenance of the technology; an additional follow up visit about two weeks after the installation date.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Safe Water Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Communities:

          1. are within the La Paz and Los Cabos counties of Baja California Sur, Mexico;

          2. lack access to centrally treated drinking water distribution;

          3. access drinking water sources (i.e. wells and springs) year round for household
             purposes

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Community source water:

          1. contains levels arsenic that are below Mexican limits;

          2. has taste characteristics (e.g. salinity) that are acceptable for drinking among
             community members.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joshua S Gruber, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Berkeley</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fermin Reygadas, MA</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Berkeley</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John M Colford Jr, MD PHD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Berkeley</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fundacion Cantaro Azul</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Paz</city>
        <state>BCS</state>
        <country>Mexico</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Mexico</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brownell SA, Chakrabarti AR, Kaser FM, Connelly LG, Peletz RL, Reygadas F, Lang MJ, Kammen DM, Nelson KL. Assessment of a low-cost, point-of-use, ultraviolet water disinfection technology. J Water Health. 2008 Mar;6(1):53-65.</citation>
    <PMID>17998607</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 6, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 10, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 11, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 10, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 10, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 11, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, Berkeley</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>John M. Colford, Jr.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Epidemiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diarrhea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

