<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01634451</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012/R/AN/01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01634451</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Development and Evaluation of Strategies to Improve Sedation Quality in InTensive Care</brief_title>
  <acronym>DESIST</acronym>
  <official_title>Development and Evaluation of Strategies to Improve Sedation Quality in InTensive Care</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Edinburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Chief Scientist Office of the Scottish Government</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GE Healthcare</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Edinburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Intensive Care Units (ICUs) across Scotland are working with the Scottish Patient Safety
      Programme (SPSP) to reduce healthcare associated infections (HAls). This is being done
      through implementation of &quot;care bundles&quot;. Ensuring that ICU patients get the correct amount
      of sedation (medicine that makes patients sleepy) is part of this bundle, but is proving the
      most difficult to get right. It's important healthcare staff (nurses and doctors) get
      sedation levels correct because too much sedation is linked with increased hospital acquired
      infections (HAIs), longer intensive care (ICU) and hospital stays, and possibly higher death
      rates. This quality improvement project will develop and introduce three interventions that
      may improve sedation practice: first, an ICU sedation education package; second, feedback of
      sedation-related performance data (graphs and charts); and third, introduction of a CE
      (Conformité Européenne - With the CE marking on a product, the manufacturer ensures that the
      product conforms with the essential requirements of European regulations) marked new
      technology designed to improve sedation management. The investigators will study the effect
      these interventions, in different combinations, have on sedation management and quality in
      the participating ICUs. Eight ICUs in Scotland will take part in the project, pairs (2 ICUs)
      will be assigned randomly to different combinations as follows: 1.Enhanced education alone,
      2. Education plus process/outcome measure feedback (graphs and charts), 3. Education plus
      introduction of a new sedation monitoring technology, or 4. Education,process/outcome measure
      feedback, and sedation monitoring technology. The investigators will evaluate which
      combinations of education, feedback, and technology provide the most patient benefit in the
      NHS. In addition both nursing &amp; medical staff will be observed in clinical practice &amp;
      interviewed about their clinical practice to increase understanding about sedation management
      from different view points and inform the education package content. These data will also
      help implement the findings after the research is completed if a benefit is found.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline the effect of individual and combinations of the interventions named on achievement of optimal sedation practice</measure>
    <time_frame>Cluster trial examining group effects over a 20 month period. Data available June 2014.</time_frame>
    <description>The % of ventilated patient days with optimal sedation will be compared across and between the groups. A sedation quality assessment tool has been developed for the purpose of the study:
Group 1 -Education package only (bespoke sedation education) Group 2 -Education package and real time (site specific) process feedback about sedation practices Group 3 - Education and responsiveness (sedation) technology Group 4 - Education package, real time (site specific) process feedback about sedation practices and responsiveness (sedation) technology</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of ventilation days</measure>
    <time_frame>Cluster trial examining group effects over a 20 month period. Data available June 2014.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ICU stay duration</measure>
    <time_frame>Cluster trial examining group effects over a 20 month period. Data available June 2014.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of days on sedation</measure>
    <time_frame>Cluster trial examining group effects over a 20 month period. Data available June 2014.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1637</enrollment>
  <condition>Critical Illness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Education Package</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>2 ICUs; one large and one small. Randomised to receive bespoke education package for the 9 month intervention period</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Education and Feedback</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>2 ICUs; one large and one small. Randomised to receive a bespoke education package and real-time,site specific, outcome process feedback they will disseminate to their staff for the 9 month intervention period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Education and Sedation Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>2 ICUs; one large and one small. Randomised to receive a bespoke education package and a new novel sedation (responsiveness) monitor for the 9 month intervention period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Education, Feedback, Sedation Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>2 ICUs; one large and one small. Randomised to receive a bespoke education package, real-time,site specific, outcome process feedback they will disseminate to their staff and a new novel sedation (responsiveness) monitor for the 9 month intervention period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bespoke on-line sedation education package</intervention_name>
    <description>A bespoke on-line education package has been developed and will be accessible by all ICU nursing staff. They will have unique logins and the system will track their use and completion of the education package. There is a small multiple choice assessment at the end of the package.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Education Package</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Bespoke Education Package</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sedation specific outcome process feedback</intervention_name>
    <description>Using statistical process charts, the data gathered from the Sedation quality Tools (SQATs) completed each shift by the ICU nurses, will be fed back highlighting sedation specific outcomes e.g. number of over sedated days per 1000 ventilator days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Education and Feedback</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Education, Feedback, Sedation Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sedation pecific outcome process feedback</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Responsiveness monitoring; novel sedation monitor</intervention_name>
    <description>Responsiveness monitoring (developed by GE Healthcare) is a novel technology used to monitor patient responsiveness and essentially alert ICU nursing staff when their patients may be over sedated.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Education and Sedation Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Education, Feedback, Sedation Monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Responsiveness Monitoring</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. All patients admitted to ICU mechanically ventilated and intubated.

          2. All patients in whom mechanical ventilation via an endotracheal tube is instituted at
             some time after ICU admission will also be eligible for inclusion from the time
             intubation and mechanical ventilation begins.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients who are not receiving mechanical ventilation via an endotracheal tube

          2. Patients who received mechanical ventilation following ICU admission but this has been
             discontinued at the time of screening for study inclusion

          3. Patients in whom discontinuation of mechanical ventilation is anticipated in the next
             4 hours

          4. Patients in whom a decision to withdraw active therapy has been made

          5. Patients who have already been enrolled in the during the same hospital admission

          6. Patients whom have been mechanically ventilated and intubated for greater than 24 hrs
             by the time relatives are approached for consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timothy S Walsh, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Edinburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Infirmary Edinburgh, Glasgow Royal Infirmary, Monklands Hospital, Victoria Infirmary Glasgow, Forth Valley Royal, Ninewells hospital, Dumfries Infirmary , Victoria Hospital Kirkcaldy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edinburgh, Glasgow, Airdrie, Larbert, Dumfries, Dundee</city>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 20, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 2, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 6, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 10, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 10, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 11, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sedation</keyword>
  <keyword>Quality</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

