<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01632332</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MC1136</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2012-00963</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01632332</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vaccine Therapy in Treating Patients With Previously Treated Stage II-III HER2-Positive Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Trial of the Safety and Immunogenicity of a Multi-epitope HER-2/Neu Peptide Vaccine in Subjects Previously Treated for HER-2 Positive Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Tapimmune Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to look at the safety and immune response to a vaccine used in
      patients previously treated for HER2 (human epidermal growth factor receptor 2) positive
      breast cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the safety profile of a peptide-based vaccine targeting HER-2/neu, in
      patients with stage II/III HER-2 positive breast cancer.

      II. To determine the ability of this vaccination protocol to elicit an immune response as
      measured by activated HER-2/neu-specific T lymphocytes or high-affinity antibodies.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To compile descriptive follow-up data regarding vital status and disease recurrence.

      II. To determine if HER-2/neu peptide 885 generates a T cell response that is specific to
      HER-2/neu or is cross-reactive with epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) protein.

      III. To determine if the human leukocyte antigen (HLA)-DR epitopes contain HLA class I
      embedded epitopes.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive HER-2/neu peptide vaccine intradermally (ID) every 28 days for up to 6
      courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for up to 2 additional years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>July 2012</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients who experience toxicities of attribution during the course of treatment (grades 3-5 of the NCI's Cancer Therapy Evaluation Program [CTEP] Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, version 4.0) for 2 years.</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed up to 2 years following final immunization</time_frame>
    <description>The maximum grade for each type of toxicity will be recorded for each patient, and frequency tables will be reviewed to determine toxicity patterns.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the ability of this vaccination protocol to elicit an immune response as measured by activated HER-2/neu-specific T lymphocytes or high-affinity antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>30 months</time_frame>
    <description>Immune responses to to the vaccine components will be periodically assessed using various assays measuring cytokine release, frequency of T cells, and antibody generation.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>30 months</time_frame>
    <description>Disease-free survival is defined as the time from registration to documentation of disease recurrence, second primary, or death without disease recurrence or second primary. The distribution of disease-free and overall survival times will be estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>HER2-positive Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Male Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage II Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (HER-2/neu peptide vaccine)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive HER-2/neu peptide vaccine ID every 28 days for up to 6 courses in the absence of disease recurrence or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>HER-2/neu peptide vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given ID</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (HER-2/neu peptide vaccine)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>HER-2</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (HER-2/neu peptide vaccine)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histological confirmation of primary breast cancer, stage II or III, completely
             resected; Note: history of a local recurrence allowable if also completely resected

          -  Prior diagnosis of HER-2 positive primary breast cancer using American Society of
             Clinical Oncologists (ASCO)/College of American Pathologists (CAP) guidelines (either
             by evidence of 3+ immunohistochemical staining or with in situ hybridization [FISH]
             amplification)

          -  Completion of surgery +/- radiation at least 30 days prior to registration

          -  Must have received mastectomy or lumpectomy plus radiation

          -  Must have received either neoadjuvant and/or adjuvant chemotherapy for treatment of
             breast cancer

          -  Must have received either neoadjuvant and/or adjuvant trastuzumab for treatment of
             breast cancer

          -  All chemotherapy, trastuzumab, and/or corticosteroids must be completed at least 90
             days prior to registration; Note: hormonal therapy and bisphosphonates may be ongoing

          -  Clinically without any evidence of disease recurrence/progression (per practice
             guidelines for breast cancer)

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1500/mm^3

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 75,000/mm^3

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9.0 g/dL

          -  Creatinine =&lt; 2 x upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT) (aspartate aminotransferase [AST]) =&lt; 2
             x ULN

          -  Albumin &gt;= 3 g/dL

          -  Negative pregnancy test done =&lt; 7 days prior to registration, for women of
             childbearing potential only

          -  Capable of understanding the investigative nature, potential risks, and benefits of
             the study

          -  Capable of providing valid informed consent

          -  Willing to return to enrolling institution (Mayo Clinic Rochester) for all study
             visits (immunizations, blood draws, etc)

          -  Willing to employ adequate contraception from the time of registration through 6
             months after the final vaccine cycle; Note: adequate contraception methods include
             birth control pills, barrier device, intrauterine device

          -  Willing to provide blood samples for correlative research purposes

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status (PS) 0 or 1

          -  Willing to receive a tetanus vaccination if you have not had one within the past year

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Any prior lapatinib or pertuzumab treatment

        Any of the following because this study involves an investigational agent whose genotoxic,
        mutagenic and teratogenic effects on the developing fetus and newborn are unknown:

          -  Pregnant women

          -  Nursing women unwilling to stop breast feeding

          -  Men or women of child bearing potential who are unwilling to employ adequate
             contraception from the time of registration through 6 months after the final vaccine
             cycle Co-morbid systemic illnesses or other severe concurrent disease which, in the
             judgment of the investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for entry into this
             study or interfere significantly with the proper assessment of safety and toxicity of
             the prescribed regimens Immunocompromised patients including patients known to be
             human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) positive or those on chronic steroids; Note: must
             be off systemic steroids at least 90 days prior to registration; topical steroids or
             steroid eye drops are permitted Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not
             limited to, ongoing or active infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure,
             unstable angina pectoris, cardiac arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations
             that would limit compliance with study requirements

        Uncontrolled acute or chronic medical conditions including, but not limited to the
        following:

          -  Active infection requiring antibiotics

          -  Congestive heart failure with New York Heart Association class III or IV; moderate to
             severe objective evidence of cardiovascular disease

          -  Myocardial infarction or stroke within previous 6 months Receiving any other
             investigational agent Other active malignancy at time of registration or within the
             last three years prior to registration; EXCEPTIONS: non-melanoma skin cancer or
             carcinoma-in-situ (eg of cervix, prostate); NOTE: if there is a history of prior
             malignancy, they must not be receiving other specific treatment (cytotoxics,
             monoclonal antibodies, small molecule inhibitors) for their cancer Known history of
             autoimmune disease, including Type I diabetes Any prior hypersensitivity or adverse
             reaction to granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF) History of
             trastuzumab-related cardiac toxicity requiring interruption or discontinuation of
             therapy, even if left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) fully recovered Baseline
             LVEF with a value below 55% Failure to fully recover from acute, reversible effects of
             prior chemotherapy regardless of interval since last treatment History of myocardial
             infarction =&lt; 168 days (6 months) prior to registration, or congestive heart failure
             requiring use of ongoing maintenance therapy for life-threatening ventricular
             arrhythmias Bilateral invasive breast cancer, either synchronous or metachronous;
             Note: ductal carcinoma in situ in the contralateral breast is permissible
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Keith Knutson, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amy Degnim, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kimberly Kalli, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Timothy Hobday, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 28, 2012</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 29, 2012</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 2, 2012</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 8, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 8, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 9, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Keith Knutson, Ph.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms, Male</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

