<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00794573</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EVITA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00794573</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Varenicline (Champix) in Smoking Cessation for Patients Post-Acute Coronary Syndrome (EVITA) Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>EVITA</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Varenicline (Champix) in Smoking Cessation for Patients Post-Acute Coronary Syndrome (EVITA) Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mark Eisenberg</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>St. Michael's Hospital, Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Queen Elizabeth II Health Sciences Centre</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McGill University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The EVITA study is a clinical trial that will test the effect of varenicline (Champix™), a
      new drug used to help people quit smoking, in patients who have suffered a heart attack.
      Varenicline has been recently shown to increase the number of otherwise healthy people who
      quit smoking compared to placebo (sugar pill). Although varenicline has been shown to reduce
      smoking in healthy populations, its effectiveness in patients recovering from a heart attack
      is unknown. The EVITA trial will help answer this question.

      A total of 300 patients who have recently suffered a heart attack and are active smokers will
      be recruited in the study. For twelve weeks, half the patients will receive varenicline and
      the other half will receive placebo pills. Patients will be followed for a period of 12
      months. During this time, patients will receive telephone calls and go to clinic visits in
      order to assess if they are smoking. These follow-ups will also assess any side effects and
      clinical events such as another heart attack or hospitalization that patients may have had.
      Smoking cessation will be checked using exhaled carbon monoxide readings and self-reports.

      The EVITA trial will be the first study to examine the use of varenicline in patients who
      have recently had a heart attack. These patients, if they continue to smoke, are at high risk
      of having another cardiac event. If varenicline is shown to be useful in this population, it
      will have a major impact on prevention of cardiac events in patients who have suffered a
      heart attack.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives: 1. The primary objective of the Evaluation of Varenicline (Champix™) in SmokIng
      Cessation for PaTients Post-Acute Coronary Syndrome (EVITA) Trial is to evaluate the impact
      of varenicline on smoking cessation rates at 24 weeks following an enzyme-positive acute
      coronary syndrome (ACS).

      2. The secondary objectives are to examine the efficacy of varenicline on smoking cessation
      rates and daily cigarette reduction at 52 weeks, and to determine the safety of varenicline
      in patients following an ACS.

      Rationale: Patients who continue smoking after an acute coronary syndrome (ACS) have a 35%
      increased risk of reinfarction or death compared with those who quit. Many patients attempt
      to stop smoking after an ACS, but relapse rates approach 66%. A variety of smoking cessation
      aids have been shown to be effective for the general population. However, physicians are
      reluctant to use a nicotine-based therapy because of its hemodynamic effects. Varenicline has
      been recently shown to improve abstinence rates in healthy young smokers compared to
      bupropion (Zyban™) and placebo. Although varenicline has successfully been shown to reduce
      smoking rates in healthy young populations, its efficacy in the setting of patients
      recovering from an ACS is unknown.

      Methods: The EVITA Trial will directly compare the efficacy of varenicline versus placebo as
      a means of reducing smoking rates in patients following an ACS. The trial will be a
      multi-center effort, coordinated from the Jewish General Hospital/McGill University
      (Montreal, Quebec). A total of 300 patients will be randomized following an ACS but before
      hospital discharge. While in-hospital, patients will quit smoking and they will be instructed
      to not restart smoking following discharged. Half the patients will receive varenicline for
      12 weeks and the other half will receive placebo pills for 12 weeks. Patients receiving
      varenicline will be given 1.0 mg twice a day during the 12-week treatment period. Study
      nurses will perform telephone follow-ups with the patients at weeks 1, 2 and 8, and patients
      will return for clinic visits at weeks 4, 12, 24, and 52. Smoking abstinence will be assessed
      at follow-up clinic visits.

      The primary endpoint will be smoking abstinence at 24 weeks. Smoking abstinence will be
      defined as complete abstinence in the week prior to the clinic visits and levels of exhaled
      carbon monoxide ≤ 10 ppm. The secondary endpoints (smoking abstinence at 52 weeks, side
      effects of varenicline in patients following an ACS, percent of patients attaining a ≥ 50%
      reduction in daily consumption of cigarettes at 52 weeks, and clinical events following
      initiation of treatment) will be measured at 1, 2, 4, 8, 12, 24, and 52 weeks. The occurrence
      of clinical events will be based on the observed frequency of composite events including
      death, myocardial infarction, and hospitalization for unstable angina. Withdrawal symptoms
      and number of cigarettes smoked will also be assessed by the use of questionnaires. The EVITA
      trial will require 36 months for completion: 3 months for preparation, 18 months for patient
      enrollment, 12 months for follow-up, and 3 months for data analysis and manuscript
      preparation.

      Significance: The EVITA trial will be the first to examine the efficacy of varenicline in a
      group of patients who have suffered an ACS. These patients, if they continue to smoke, are at
      exceptionally high risk for recurrent cardiac events. If varenicline is effective in this
      population, it will have a major impact on secondary prevention of recurrent clinical events
      in patients who suffer an ACS.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Smoking cessation rates</measure>
    <time_frame>24 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Smoking abstinence, ≥ 50% reduction in daily consumption of cigarettes, side effects, cumulative side effects, safety</measure>
    <time_frame>Smoking abstinence: 52 weeks. Side effects and safety: 4, 12, 24, and 52 weeks. Cumulative side effects: 12 weeks.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">302</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Coronary Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Varenicline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>0.5 mg tablet once a day for the first three days, a 0.5 mg tablet twice a day for the following four days, and a 1.0 mg tablet twice a day for the remainder of the 12-week treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>placebo for 0.5 mg tablet once a day for the first three days, a 0.5 mg tablet twice a day for the following four days, and a 1.0 mg tablet twice a day for the remainder of the 12-week treatment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>varenicline</intervention_name>
    <description>0.5 mg tablet once a day for the first three days, a 0.5 mg tablet twice a day for the following four days, and a 1.0 mg tablet twice a day for the remainder of the 12-week treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Varenicline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Champix (Canada)</other_name>
    <other_name>Chantix (USA)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>0.5 mg tablet once a day for the first three days, a 0.5 mg tablet twice a day for the following four days, and a 1.0 mg tablet twice a day for the remainder of the 12-week treatment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar pill</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Active smoker, greater than or equal to 10 cigarettes per day, on average, for the
             past year.

          -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years.

          -  Motivated to quit smoking.

          -  Able to understand and to provide informed consent in English or French.

          -  Likely to be available for follow-up.

          -  Suffered an ACS, including myocardial infarction (MI) or unstable angina (UA) with
             significant coronary artery disease, and currently hospitalized or at discharge from
             current hospitalization.

        MI is defined as positive Troponin T, Troponin I, or CK-MB levels and ≥ 1 of the following:

          1. Ischemic symptoms (i.e. typical chest pain) for at least 20 minutes.

          2. Electrocardiogram (ECG) changes indicative of ischemia (ST-segment elevation or
             depression).

          3. Development of pathological Q waves on the ECG.

        UA with significant coronary artery disease is defined as all of the following:

          1. Negative Troponin T, Troponin I, or CK-MB levels;

          2. Ischemic symptoms (i.e. typical chest pain) for at least 20 minutes;

          3. ECG changes indicative of ischemia (ST-segment changes); and

          4. At least one lesion ≥ 50% on angiogram performed during the current hospitalization.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Medical condition with a prognosis of &lt; 1 year.

          -  Pregnant or lactating females.

          -  Reported NYHA Class or Killip III or IV at randomization.

          -  Previous use of varenicline.

          -  Current use of any medical therapy for smoking cessation (e.g. BuSpar,
             doxepin,fluoxetine, nicotine gum, nicotine patch, or bupropion).

          -  History of bulimia or anorexia nervosa.

          -  Diagnosis of major depression (requiring medication) in the previous 5 years or
             diagnosis of two or more lifetime episodes of major depression (requiring medication)

          -  A total of 5 or more responses (one of which includes question 1 or 2) of &quot;more than
             half the days&quot; or &quot;nearly every day&quot; to the questions on the PHQ-9 questionnaire.

          -  History of suicidal events (previous suicide attempt, suicidal ideation) or family
             history of suicide.

          -  History of or current panic disorder, psychosis, bipolar disease, or dementia.

          -  Diagnosed hepatic failure, cirrhosis, hepatitis or history of hepatic impairment (AST
             or ALT levels greater than or equal to 2 times upper limit of normal prior to
             admission for ACS).

          -  Renal impairment with creatinine levels greater than or equal to 2 times the upper
             limit of normal.

          -  Excessive alcohol consumption defined as greater than or equal to 14 alcoholic drinks
             per week.

          -  Use of any illegal drugs in the past year (e.g. cocaine, heroin, opiates).

          -  Use of any marijuana or other tobacco products during the study.

          -  Current use of over-the-counter stimulants (e.g. ephedrine, phenylephrine) or
             anorectics.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark J Eisenberg, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>SMBD - Jewish General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Elizabeth II Health Sciences Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Halifax</city>
        <state>Nova Scotia</state>
        <zip>B3H 1V7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M4N 3M5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St. Michael's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5B 1W8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>SMBD - Jewish General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H3T1E2</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 19, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 19, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 20, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 14, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 14, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 16, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>McGill University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mark Eisenberg</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Medicine, Divisions of Cardiology and Clinical Epidemiology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Smoking Cessation</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiac Population</keyword>
  <keyword>Acute Coronary Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>Varenicline</keyword>
  <keyword>Champix</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acute Coronary Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Varenicline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

