<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00799214</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H07-02330</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00799214</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>BASIC (Boric Acid, Alternate Solution for Intravaginal Colonization) Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Back to BASICS: Boric Acid, Alternate Solution for Intravaginal Colonization, Comparing Intravaginal Metronidazole to Boric Acid in Women Symptomatic for Bacterial Vaginosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of British Columbia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of British Columbia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Bacterial vaginosis (BV), the world's most common vaginal infection, continues to cost
      patients time, energy, comfort and money. BV is associated with increased incidence of
      sexually transmitted infections (including HIV), spontaneous abortion, pre-term labour,
      post-surgical infections, and endometritis. Current treatment for those women symptomatic for
      BV includes both oral and intravaginal antibiotics, such as metronidazole, which have success
      rates of 70-80 % at 1 month after treatment. These treatments also have high recurrence rates
      (49-66 % at one year after treatment) and side effects (10-20 % of women) that include
      secondary vaginal infection with candida. Intravaginal boric acid has been used for &gt;100
      years for the treatment of vaginal infections and is quite commonly prescribed today as a
      treatment for BV. It is cheap, easily accessible, easy to use, and is an effective treatment
      of other vaginal infections, such as candida. To date, there are no clinical trials studying
      the effectiveness of boric acid in the treatment of BV.

      The objective of this study was to determine whether intravaginal BA is comparable to
      standard treatment, metronidazole, for the cure of BV in symptomatic women.

      Our research question is: Among women 16-50 years old symptomatic with BV is intravaginal
      treatment with BA non-inferior to metronidazole to achieve a Nugent score &lt;7 (cure) by day
      17.

      Hypothesis: H0: BA proportion of women cured &lt; metronidazole proportion of women cured - 10%.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A minimum of 240 volunteer women will be recruited through participating family practice
      offices throughout British Columbia. Women with symptoms of BV, who also have a positive
      whiff test/pH test or subsequent positive vaginal swab for BV, will be asked to participate.
      Women will be included if they have both a positive test result for BV (whiff test/vaginal
      swab) and if they have any symptoms of BV present. The following criteria must be met for
      enrolment in the study: 1) ages 16-50 and pre-menopausal; 2) capable of giving written
      informed consent; 3) fluent comprehension of spoken and written English; 4) negative
      pregnancy test on enrolment day; 5) agree to follow study protocol; 6) documented BV
      infection by positive vaginal swab (minimum Nugent score of 7/10) +/- positive whiff test/pH
      &gt;4.5; 7) agree to no intercourse for the 10 days of treatment (or to use non-lubricated
      condoms if unavoidable); 8) agree not to douche or use any intravaginal products during
      treatment (including tampons, medications, devices); 9) abstain from alcohol during the 10
      days of treatment (from 24 hours before through 72 hours after taking study medication); 10)
      agree to no new medications or antibiotics during treatment; 11) no current sexually
      transmitted infection as determined by history, physical exam and negative swabs for
      chlamydia, gonorrhea, candidiasis, trichomonas; 12) patient is reliable for follow up.

      The following women would be excluded from study participation: 1) less than 16 or
      post-menopausal; 2) menstruating at diagnosis; 3) symptoms so severe as to make allocation to
      placebo unacceptable to the patient; 4) currently pregnant or at high risk for pregnancy; 5)
      current sexually transmitted infection (HIV, hepatitis, chlamydia, gonorrhea, trichomonas,
      HPV or HSV); 6) current yeast infection as determined by history, physical and swabs; 7)
      history of PID; 8) allergy to latex or metronidazole; 9) presently breast feeding; 10) any
      open wound, excoriation, vaginal irritation and including bartholin's cyst/abscess as
      determined by physical exam; 11) presence of another vulvar, vaginal or medical condition,
      including cervical neoplasia/treatment, that might confound treatment response; 12) using
      lithium, anti-coagulants or disulfiram drugs; 13) any antifungal or antibiotic use 14 days
      prior to enrolment 14) PAP smear done within one week of enrolment, 15) positive Whiff test,
      but negative vaginal swab result.

      During the initial visit, the physician will take a history and do a speculum and manual
      pelvic exam for the woman. At the time of the pelvic exam the physician will ensure intact
      mucous membranes and anatomy, take swabs for chlamydia and gonorrhea, bacterial vaginosis,
      candidiasis, and trichomonas, and perform a whiff test using a provided, standardized 10% KOH
      potassium hydroxide solution. Vaginal discharge will also have pH testing done. If the whiff
      test is positive and the vaginal discharge pH is &gt;4.5, the woman will then take a urine
      pregnancy test, will be informed about the study, and will be given a handout explaining the
      study and the 3 possible treatment arms.

      If the woman is interested in participating she will be given a &quot;Study Intake Survey&quot; to fill
      out, a consent form to sign, and an assigned number.

      Within a few days, the physician would confirm participation, eligibility and exclusion
      criteria and collect the signed consent form. The patient will then be given a blinded,
      controlled and randomized treatment pack containing 10 capsules compounded and organized by a
      pharmacist. The patient will be given a package containing: 1) capsule applicators; 2) pads;
      3) non-lubricated condoms; 4) a diary to record their daily use of the treatment, any
      problems or side effects, any symptom changes, or any problems with maintaining the study
      agreements; 5) information sheet outlining follow up instructions and emergency contact
      numbers to reach the study members. If the woman does not want to join the study the
      physician will prescribe a standard treatment of their choosing and would follow up as usual.
      If the whiff test is negative but the vaginal swab is found to be positive for bacterial
      vaginosis as per the Nugent score (score minimum of 7/10), the woman will be called back in
      to the office. If her symptoms are found to be persistant at this juncture, then she will be
      offered to enroll in the study or may elect to start a treatment of her physician's choosing.
      If the woman prefers to take some time to decide about the study, she will be given the
      information package, the survey form, and consent form to take home, as well as a
      prescription for the treatment of bacterial vaginosis. She can then return the next day with
      the forms filled out should she decide she would like to enroll in the study and be assigned
      a treatment arm. If she chooses not to enroll, she can fill the above-mentioned prescription
      and start the treatment for BV provided by her physician.

      The women who satisfy the inclusion and exclusion criteria will be blindly and randomly
      assigned to one of 3 treatments (minimum of 80 women per treatment arm): 1) placebo
      (emollient cream); 2) boric acid (600 mg boric acid in emollient cream); 3) metronidazole 10
      % intravaginal cream (Sanofi-Aventis Canada Inc Product DIN 01926861) (for a total of 37.5 mg
      metronidazole) ). The treatments will be taken at night prior to sleep using the provided
      applicators for 10 days. The patient will be instructed to use a provided pads during the day
      and night for any discharge or fluid. The patient will record daily in a diary (provided)
      about compliance, side effects and problems, and changes in symptoms over the 10 days. The
      patient will be welcome to call the provided emergency numbers of the study members for any
      questions or problems related to the treatment. On day 5 of the treatment, the patient will
      receive a call or email from a study member to ask follow up questions about compliance, side
      effects, BV symptoms, and satisfaction of treatment.

      On both follow up visits: days 17-19 (one week after the treatment end) and 40-42 (one month
      after the treatment end), the participant will return to the clinic that enrolled her for
      reassessment, pregnancy test, and follow up examination including pelvic exam and repeat
      swabs. It will be noted whether her BV symptoms are still present, and if she had any side
      effects or problems during treatment. The participant returns her daily treatment diary on
      day 17 visit as well.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-inferiority, per protocol comparison of effectiveness of boric acid to metronidazole at day 17 as measured by Nugent score in 16-50 year olds with a z-based confidence interval for the difference of two proportions</measure>
    <time_frame>day 17</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-inferiority, intent-to-treat comparison of effectiveness of boric acid to metronidazole at day 17 as measured by Nugent score in 16-50 year olds with a z-based confidence interval for the difference of two proportions</measure>
    <time_frame>day 17</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Non-inferiority, comparison of effectiveness of boric acid to metronidazole at day 40 as measured by Nugent score in 16-50 years old analyzed both per protocol and intent-to treat with a z-based confidence interval for the difference of two proportions</measure>
    <time_frame>day 40</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety consideration including intolerable adverse effects requiring patient discontinuation of the 10 day treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>day 1-10</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Bacterial Vaginosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>1 gram emollient cream to be inserted intravaginally qhs (once before bed) for 10 days or less if intolerable side effects occur.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Boric acid = 600 mg boric acid compounded in emollient cream (1 gram total) to be inserted intravaginally qhs (once before bed) for 10 days or less if intolerable side effects occur.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Metronidazole = 10 % intravaginal cream (Sanofi-Aventis Canada Inc Product DIN 01926861) (for a total of 37.5 mg metronidazole) inserted intravaginally qhs (once before bed) for 10 days or less if intolerable side effects occur.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>1 gram emollient cream to be inserted intravaginally qhs (once before bed) for 10 days or less if intolerable side effects occur.</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Boric acid</intervention_name>
    <description>Boric acid = 600 mg boric acid compounded in emollient cream (1 gram total) to be inserted intravaginally qhs (once before bed) for 10 days or less if intolerable side effects occur.</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Metronidazole</intervention_name>
    <description>Metronidazole = 10 % intravaginal cream (Sanofi-Aventis Canada Inc Product DIN 01926861) (for a total of 37.5 mg metronidazole) to be inserted intravaginally qhs (once before bed) for 10 days or less if intolerable side effects occur.</description>
    <arm_group_label>3</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Women will be included whether their complaint is symptoms of BV and have a positive whiff
        test/vaginal swab or if they have a positive whiff test/vaginal swab and are then asked if
        they have any symptoms of BV present. The following criteria must be met for enrolment in
        the study:

          1. ages 16-50 and premenopausal;

          2. capable of giving written informed consent;

          3. English speaking;

          4. negative pregnancy test on enrolment day;

          5. agree to follow study protocol;

          6. documented BV infection by positive vaginal swab +/- positive whiff test/pH &gt; 4.5;

          7. agree to no intercourse for the 10 days of treatment (or to use non-lubricated condoms
             if unavoidable);

          8. agree not to douche or use any intravaginal products during treatment (including
             tampons, medications, devices);

          9. abstain from alcohol during the 10 days of treatment (from 24 hours before through 72
             hours after taking study medication);

         10. agree to no new medications or antibiotics during treatment;

         11. no current sexually transmitted infection as determined by history, physical exam and
             negative swabs for chlamydia, gonorrhea, candidiasis, trichomonas;

         12. patient is reliable for follow up.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        The following women would be excluded from study participation:

          1. less than 16 or post-menopausal;

          2. negative vaginal swab regardless of whiff test/pH &gt; 4.5;

          3. menstruating at diagnosis;

          4. symptoms so severe as to make allocation to placebo unacceptable to the patient;

          5. currently pregnant or at high risk for pregnancy;

          6. current sexually transmitted infection (HIV, hepatitis, chlamydia, gonorrhea,
             trichomonas, HPV or HSV);

          7. current yeast infection as determined by history, physical and swabs;

          8. history of PID;

          9. allergy to latex or metronidazole;

         10. presently lactating;

         11. any open wound, excoriation, vaginal irritation and including bartholin's cyst/abscess
             as determined by physical exam;

         12. presence of another vulvar, vaginal or medical condition, including cervical neoplasia
             treatment, that might confound treatment response;

         13. using lithium, anti-coagulants or disulfiram drugs;

         14. any antifungal or antibiotic use 14 days prior to enrolment

         15. PAP smear done within one week of enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Konia Trouton, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Melinda Zeron Mullins, MD, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of British Columbia</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Multicentered, family practice offices</name>
      <address>
        <city>Province-wide</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 10, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 25, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 27, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 25, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 25, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 27, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>bacterial vaginosis</keyword>
  <keyword>intravaginal</keyword>
  <keyword>boric acid</keyword>
  <keyword>metronidazole</keyword>
  <keyword>placebo controlled</keyword>
  <keyword>double-blind</keyword>
  <keyword>randomized</keyword>
  <keyword>multicenter</keyword>
  <keyword>non-inferiority</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaginal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vaginosis, Bacterial</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metronidazole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Emollients</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tetrahydrozoline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

