<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00799279</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15053</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CTCRI 019826</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CTCRI 19813</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00799279</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Integrating Smoking Cessation Into Routine Primary Care Practice</brief_title>
  <official_title>Comparative Evaluation of the Efficacy and Cost-effectiveness of Two Interventions for Integrating Smoking Cessation Into Routine Primary Care Practice: A Cluster-randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Waterloo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ottawa Heart Institute Research Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Tobacco Control Research Initiative</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Waterloo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to determine if providing smokers identified in family doctors
      offices with follow-up counselling enhances their success with quitting and the number of
      health professionals helping patients with quitting. Six to eight family medicine clinics
      will be involved in the study. We will compare the frequency of addressing smoking with
      patients and the proportion of smokers who are successful with quitting 16-weeks following
      the clinic appointment between practices. It is hypothesized that the addition of follow-up
      counseling to a multi-component smoking cessation intervention will improve smoking outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A family doctor's advice to quit has been shown to increase a smoker's motivation to quit.
      Despite the evidence supporting the importance of smoking cessation, there is a
      well-documented practice gap in the rates at which smoking cessation is being addressed by
      practitioners. The primary objectives of this research study are to determine whether adjunct
      telephone-based smoking cessation follow-up counselling when delivered as part of a
      multi-component intervention:

        1. Increases the rate at which evidence-based smoking cessation interventions are delivered
           to smokers identified in family doctors offices, compared to providing only practice
           supports.

        2. Increases smoking abstinence as measured three months after the estimated target quit
           date (i.e.16 weeks) compared to providing only practice supports.

        3. Is more cost-effective (cost/quit) than providing only practice supports to family
           doctors offices.

      A two-arm before-after matched-pair cluster randomized trial, will test the effectiveness of
      two strategies for integrating smoking cessation treatments into primary care practice
      routines and enhancing cessation. Six to eight family doctors offices will be randomized to
      either a practice support (PS) group, or a follow-up counseling (FC) group. From each of the
      intervention practices a cross-sectional sample of 50 eligible smokers will be recruited pre-
      and post-intervention to assess 5A's delivery and smoking abstinence.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>smoking abstinence</measure>
    <time_frame>16-weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report and biochemically validated point prevelence smoking abstinence</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>cost-effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>16-weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of provider delivery of evidence-based smoking treatments</measure>
    <time_frame>exit survey on day of clinic visits</time_frame>
    <description>Rates of providers, asking, advising, assessing, assisting, and arranging were assessed</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">835</enrollment>
  <condition>Smoking Cessation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Follow-up Counseling Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>smoking cessation training for providers,practice tools for providers, patient quit plan, and follow-up telephone counselling for smokers</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Practice Support Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>smoking cessation training for providers,practice tools for providers, patient quit plan for smokers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Smoking cessation training, support, and telephone follow-up</intervention_name>
    <description>The CF group will receive the same smoking cessation training and practice support tools delivered to the PS group. In addition, patients in the FC group who are smokers and are willing to set a quit date within the next 30 days and who have set a quit date will be enrolled in an interactive voice response (IVR)-mediated telephone follow-up and counselling system. The IVR system will automatically contact patients via telephone 7 days before their TQD, and 5, 14, 30, and 60 days after their TQD to check the patients' smoking status, potential concerns, and their risk of relapse.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Follow-up Counseling Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>smoking cessation intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Intervention practices will be provided with training in smoking cessation, and will be supported with integrating a waiting room screener for smoking and smoking consult form and patient quit plan into their practice routines.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Practice Support Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Practices will be eligible for participation in the present study if they meet the
             following criteria:

               1. Practice is a family health team (FHT), family health group (FHG); or family
                  health network (FHN);

               2. All physicians within the practice are willing to participate in the study;

               3. Practice will see an average of 50 patients per day and 10% of patients are
                  smokers;

               4. Practice is willing to provide consent to contact patients in waiting rooms and
                  survey patients during office hours and by telephone.

          -  Patients will be eligible to participate in the study if they meet the following
             criteria:

               1. Patient is seen in clinic for annual exam or non-urgent visit;

               2. Patient is a current smoker (&gt;1 cigarette per day on most days of the week);

               3. Patient is 18 years of age or older;

               4. Patient is able to read and understand English or French;

               5. Patient has a home or mobile telephone which can be used to receive follow-up
                  telephone counselling calls

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who do not have the mental capacity to provide informed consent and complete
             study protocols will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul McDonald, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Waterloo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>October 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 17, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 26, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 27, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 5, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 5, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 6, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Paul McDonald</name_title>
    <organization>University of Waterloo</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>smoking</keyword>
  <keyword>cessation</keyword>
  <keyword>family medicine</keyword>
  <keyword>evidence-based</keyword>
  <keyword>knowledge translation</keyword>
  <keyword>smoking cessation, primary care</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

