<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00799578</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>07-1699</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00799578</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Preliminary Study to Evaluate Cysteamine Therapy in Human Subjects With Non-Alcoholic Steatohepatitis (NASH)</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Joel Lavine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Raptor Pharmaceuticals Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Diego</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether cysteamine will effectively reduce or
      reverse the biologic markers of steatohepatitis in patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) steatohepatitis represents a spectrum of disease
      occurring in the absence of alcohol abuse. It is characterized by the presence of steatosis
      and may represent a hepatic manifestation of the metabolic syndrome (including obesity,
      diabetes and hypertriglyceridemia). NAFLD is linked to insulin resistance, it causes liver
      disease in adults and children and may ultimately lead to cirrhosis (Skelly et al., 2002).
      The histologic spectrum of NAFLD ranges from the relatively benign isolated predominantly
      macrovesicular steatosis (i.e., nonalcoholic fatty liver or NAFL) to steatohepatitis (NASH)
      (Angulo, &amp; Lindor, 2002). The latter is characterized by the histologic presence of
      steatosis, cytological ballooning, scattered inflammation and pericellular fibrosis(Contos &amp;
      Sanyal, 2002). Estimates of prevalence among children can be inferred from pediatric obesity
      data and the knowledge that 85% of children with NAFLD are obese. Data from the National
      Health and Nutrition Examination Survey has revealed a threefold rise in the prevalence of
      childhood and adolescent obesity over the past 35 years; data from 2000 suggests that 14-16%
      children between 6-19yrs age are obese with a BMI &gt;95% (Fishbein, Miner, Mogren &amp; Chalekson,
      2003), and also the fact that 85% of children with NAFLD are obese.

      Treatment of NASH currently revolves around the reduction of the two main pathogenetic
      factors, namely, fat accumulation within the liver and excessive accumulation of free
      radicals causing oxidative stress. Glutathione (gamma-glutamyl-cysteinyl-glycine; GSH) is a
      major endogenous antioxidant and its depletion is implicated in the development of
      hepatocellular injury (Wu, Fang, Yang, Lupton &amp; Turner, 2004). Glutathione itself is does not
      enter easily into cells, even when given in large amounts. However, glutathione precursors do
      enter into cells and have been shown to be effective in the treatment of conditions such as
      acetaminophen toxicity by preventing significant GSH depletion (Prescott &amp; Critchley, 1983).
      Examples of GSH precursors include cysteine, N-acetylcysteine, methionine and other
      sulphur-containing compounds such as cysteamine (Prescott, Park &amp; Proudfoot, 1976). Studies
      have demonstrated that orally and intravenously administered cysteamine in mice and humans is
      effective in acetaminophen-induced hepatocellular injury (Prescott, 1972; Prescott, Stewart &amp;
      Proudfoot, 1978; Mitchell, Thorgeirsson, Potter, Jollow &amp; Keiser, 1974). Another study where
      N-acetylcysteine was used to treat NASH over a period of 4-12 weeks demonstrated improved
      amniotransferase levels (Pamuk &amp; Sonsuz, 2003), suggesting that increasing GSH levels may
      have a hepato-protective role and may be useful in the treatment of NASH. A possible mode of
      action of cysteamine is that it might react with extracellular cystine to form cysteine which
      then is readily taken up into the cell and transformed into GSH.

      Recent studies have suggested that the essential amino acid cysteine is a major limiting
      factor for GSH synthesis and that factors (e.g., insulin and growth factors) that stimulate
      cysteine uptake by cells generally result in increased intracellular GSH levels (Lyons et
      al., 2000; Lu, 2000).

      Cysteamine, a GSH precursor, is currently available and is used in the treatment of
      cystinosis, an intra-lysosomalcystine storage disorder. In cystinosis, cysteamine acts by
      converting cystine to cysteine and cysteine-cysteamine mixed disulfide which are the both
      able to leave the lysosome through the cysteine and lysine porters respectively (Gahl, Theone
      &amp; Shneider, 2002). Within the cytosol the mixed disulfide can be reduced by its reaction with
      glutathione and the cysteine released can be used for further GSH synthesis. The synthesis of
      GSH from cysteine is catalyzed by two enzymes, gamma-glutamylcysteine synthetase and GSH
      synthetase. This pathway occurs in almost all cell types, with the liver being the major
      producer and exporter or GSH. The reduced cysteine-cysteamine mixed disulfide will also
      release cysteamine, which, in theory is then able to re-enter the lysosome, bind more cystine
      and repeat the process (Dohil et al., 2006). In a recent study in children with cystinosis,
      enteral administration of cysteamine resulted in increased plasma cysteamine levels, which
      subsequently caused prolonged efficacy in the lowering of leukocyte cystine levels (Dohil et
      al., 2006). This may have been due to &quot;re-cycling&quot; of cysteamine when adequate amounts of
      drug reached the lysosome. If cysteamine does act in this fashion, then GSH production may
      also be significantly enhanced.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Normalization or &gt;50% of Serum ALT Levels From Baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Fatty Liver</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cystagon-EC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cysteamine</intervention_name>
    <description>Drug is in enteric-coated capsule form. The dosage will begin at 1g/m-squared body surface area with a maximum dose of 1000mg twice daily. Treatment period is 3-6 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cystagon-EC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Biopsy confirmed diagnosis of non-alcoholic steatohepatitis (within past 12 months)

          -  Ages 10 yrs and older

          -  Must swallow tablets on a regular basis

          -  ALT level &gt;60 iu/L

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with known hypersensitivity to cysteamine

          -  History, currently or within the past 3 months, of the following conditions:

          -  Pancreatitis

          -  Inflammatory bowel disease

          -  Malabsorption

          -  Unstable heart disease, e.g., myocardial infarction, heart failure, arrhythmias.

          -  Unstable diabetes mellitus

          -  Any bleeding disorder.

          -  Zollinger-Ellison syndrome

          -  Malignant disease

          -  Subjects whom maybe pregnant or have health issues that make it unsafe for them
             participate, or whose concomitant medical problems preclude them from committing to
             the study schedule.

          -  No specific NASH medical therapy for 3 months such as vitamin E, s-adenosyl methionine
             or metformin or other NAFLD study drugs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California, San Diego School of Medicine General Clinic Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92103-8203</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www2.niddk.nih.gov/</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://digestive.niddk.nih.gov/ddiseases/pubs/nash/</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www2.niddk.nih.gov/Research/ScientificAreas/DigestiveDiseases/Liver/FLID.htm</url>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://win.niddk.nih.gov/</url>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Skelly AH, Arcury TA, Gesler WM, Cravey AJ, Dougherty MC, Washburn SA, Nash S. Sociospatial knowledge networks: appraising community as place. Res Nurs Health. 2002 Apr;25(2):159-70.</citation>
    <PMID>11933009</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Angulo P, Lindor KD. Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease. J Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2002 Feb;17 Suppl:S186-90. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12000605</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Contos MJ, Sanyal AJ. The clinicopathologic spectrum and management of nonalcoholic fatty liver disease. Adv Anat Pathol. 2002 Jan;9(1):37-51. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11756758</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fishbein MH, Miner M, Mogren C, Chalekson J. The spectrum of fatty liver in obese children and the relationship of serum aminotransferases to severity of steatosis. J Pediatr Gastroenterol Nutr. 2003 Jan;36(1):54-61.</citation>
    <PMID>12499997</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wu G, Fang YZ, Yang S, Lupton JR, Turner ND. Glutathione metabolism and its implications for health. J Nutr. 2004 Mar;134(3):489-92. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14988435</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prescott LF, Critchley JA. The treatment of acetaminophen poisoning. Annu Rev Pharmacol Toxicol. 1983;23:87-101. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>6347057</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prescott LF, Park J, Proudfoot AT. Cysteamine, L-methionine and D-penicillamine in paracetamol poisoning. J Int Med Res. 1976;4(4 Suppl):112-7.</citation>
    <PMID>1026552</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prescott LF. Haemodialysis in paracetomol self-poisoning. Lancet. 1972 Sep 23;2(7778):652.</citation>
    <PMID>4116795</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prescott LF, Stewart MJ, Proudfoot AT. Cysteamine or N-acetylcysteine for paracetamol poisoning? Br Med J. 1978 Apr 1;1(6116):856-7.</citation>
    <PMID>638489</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mitchell JR, Thorgeirsson SS, Potter WZ, Jollow DJ, Keiser H. Acetaminophen-induced hepatic injury: protective role of glutathione in man and rationale for therapy. Clin Pharmacol Ther. 1974 Oct;16(4):676-84.</citation>
    <PMID>4417718</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lyons J, Rauh-Pfeiffer A, Yu YM, Lu XM, Zurakowski D, Tompkins RG, Ajami AM, Young VR, Castillo L. Blood glutathione synthesis rates in healthy adults receiving a sulfur amino acid-free diet. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2000 May 9;97(10):5071-6.</citation>
    <PMID>10792033</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lu SC. Regulation of glutathione synthesis. Curr Top Cell Regul. 2000;36:95-116. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10842748</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gahl WA, Thoene JG, Schneider JA. Cystinosis. N Engl J Med. 2002 Jul 11;347(2):111-21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12110740</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dohil R, Fidler M, Barshop BA, Gangoiti J, Deutsch R, Martin M, Schneider JA. Understanding intestinal cysteamine bitartrate absorption. J Pediatr. 2006 Jun;148(6):764-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16769383</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pamuk GE, Sonsuz A. N-acetylcysteine in the treatment of non-alcoholic steatohepatitis. J Gastroenterol Hepatol. 2003 Oct;18(10):1220-1.</citation>
    <PMID>12974918</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 28, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 28, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 1, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>December 13, 2013</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>December 13, 2013</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">January 31, 2014</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 13, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 13, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 31, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Diego</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Joel Lavine</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>NASH, NAFLD,nonalcoholic steatohepatitis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fatty Liver</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Non-alcoholic Fatty Liver Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cysteamine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Biopsy proven children with nonalcoholic fatty liver disease from fatty liver clinic at University of California, San Diego</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>Not on other therapy for NAFLD</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Cystagon-EC</title>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="13"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="11"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Cystagon-EC</title>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="13"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="13"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="14" spread="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="12"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="13"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Normalization or &gt;50% of Serum ALT Levels From Baseline</title>
        <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Number of Improved Subjects</title>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Normalization or &gt;50% of Serum ALT Levels From Baseline</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="11"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="7"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Number of Improved Subjects</title>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="13"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="13"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. Joel Lavine</name_or_title>
      <organization>Columbia University</organization>
      <phone>212 304 5533</phone>
      <email>jl3553@columbia.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

