<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00790361</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13652</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00790361</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Natural History of Traumatic Spinal Cord Injury Using fMRI, MRS and DTI</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mapping the Natural History of Traumatic Spinal Cord Injury in the Sensorimotor Cortex Using Functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging, Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy and Diffusion Tensor Imaging</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Lawson Health Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Physicians' Services Incorporated Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Lawson Health Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Traumatic spinal cord injury is a common injury to the spine and can lead to a clinical
      syndrome called central cord syndrome (CCS). CCS is an incomplete spinal cord injury where
      one starts to lose more motor function in the upper rather than lower extremities. It affects
      a wide range of the population from the young to the old. However, the natural history of CCS
      is poorly understood.

      Research has shown that the injury resulting in CCS might be due to the pinching or
      compressing of the spinal cord. This creates damage to a part of the spinal cord and creates
      difficulties in the signal getting through. We believe that we can gain a better
      understanding of the natural history of incomplete spinal cord injury as well as the recovery
      process.

      It is possible to track many changes in the brain and motor function through a variety of
      methods. One can track the concentrations of different chemicals (metabolites) by using
      magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS), changes in brain activation by using functional
      magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) and thread-like nerve fibers in the spine by using
      diffusion tensor imaging (DTI). In our study we will be detecting differences in brain
      metabolism and activation of different parts of the brain during specific movement and in the
      nerve fibers in the brain.

      We hypothesize that there will be decreased levels of N-acetylaspartate (NAA, a putative
      marker of neuronal function) and decreased levels of glutamate (the primary excitatory
      neurotransmitter) in the motor cortex in patients with CCS when compared with controls. Over
      time, we hypothesize that the normalization of metabolite levels will correlate with the
      extent of neurologic recovery. We also hypothesize a reorganization of brain activation
      patterns with time such that patients will show increased volumes of activation in the motor
      cortex with recovery and that this will correlate with the extent of neurologic outcome. Over
      time, we predict that there will be normalization of the fibre track anatomy that will
      correlate with neurological recovery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The long-term goal of this project is to develop predictors of neurological recovery based on
      brain metabolism, brain activation patterns, and fibre tracks in patients with traumatic CCS.
      The objective of this preliminary study is to evaluate metabolic changes, brain activation
      pattern reorganization and altered spinal cord fibre tracks in patients suffering from
      traumatic CCS to gain a better understanding of the natural history of this condition.
      Magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS), functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI), and
      diffusion tensor imaging (DTI) will be used to investigate the changes in brain metabolite
      concentrations, cerebral cortical activation, and fibre tract anatomy, respectively, in
      patients and controls.

      Ten patients having traumatic CCS will be recruited from the Clinical Neurological Sciences
      Department at the London Health Sciences Centre, University Campus. All participants will
      undergo an fMRI, MRS and DTI scan of the motor cortex to measure the volume of activation,
      signal intensity and levels of NAA and glutamate. The CCS participants will have three scans,
      one acutely (up to 48 hours after injury), one subacutely (15 days after injury), and one
      late (6 months after injury). Healthy volunteers will have two scans six months apart to
      determine reproducibility.

      Clinical changes will be measured using validated disease specific scoring instruments
      including the Japanese Orthopedic Association scale (JOA), ASIA/ISCOS Impairment Scale, and
      the Neck Disability Index (NDI). General quality of life will be measured using the 36-item
      Short-Form Health Survey (SF-36). A blinded investigator will administer these instruments
      prior to the scan at all time points.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 18, 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 31, 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 31, 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure the volume of activation, signal intensity and levels of NAA and glutamate using fMRI, MRS and DTI.</measure>
    <time_frame>acutely (up to 48 hours after injury), subacutely (15 days after injury), and late (6 months after injury)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical changes will be measured using validated disease specific scoring instruments including the Japanese Orthopedic Association scale (JOA), ASIA/ISCOS Impairment Scale, and the Neck Disability Index (NDI).</measure>
    <time_frame>Acutely (up to 48 hours after injury), subacutely (15 days after injury), and late (6 months after injury)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Central Cord Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <description>Controls (healthy volunteers) will have two scans (fMRI, MRS and DTI) six months apart to determine reproducibility.
A blinded investigator will administer JOA, ASIA/ISCOS, NDI and SF-36 prior to the scan at all time points.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>CCS Participants</arm_group_label>
    <description>CCS participants will have three scans (fMRI, MRS and DTI), one acutely (up to 48 hours after injury), one subacutely (15 days after injury), and one late (6 months after injury).
A blinded investigator will administer JOA, ASIA/ISCOS, NDI and SF-36 prior to the scan at all time points.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Ten patients and ten controls will be recruited from the Clinical Neurological Sciences
        outpatient clinic at the London Health Sciences Centre, University Campus
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  between 30 and 85 years of age

          -  right handed

          -  with normal/corrected hearing and vision

          -  fluent in reading and speaking Canadian or American English

          -  able to follow simple task instructions

          -  able to maintain standardized movements

          -  available to return for the 15 day and 6 month imaging sessions

          -  competent to give consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  must not have any other neurological disorder or systemic disease that may affect
             neurologic function

          -  not have any potential magnetic metal fragments in their body

          -  suffering from claustrophobia

          -  having a pacemaker or other electronic implants

          -  have been or currently is a welder or soldier

          -  have been injured by a metallic object that has not been removed

          -  pregnant or trying to conceive

          -  have cerebral aneurysm clips
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Neil Duggal, M.D., MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>London Health Research Institute, London Health Sciences Centre</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>London Health Sciences Center, University Campus</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>N6A-5A5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aito S, D'Andrea M, Werhagen L, Farsetti L, Cappelli S, Bandini B, Di Donna V. Neurological and functional outcome in traumatic central cord syndrome. Spinal Cord. 2007 Apr;45(4):292-7. Epub 2006 Jun 13.</citation>
    <PMID>16773038</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Clark CA, Werring DJ. Diffusion tensor imaging in spinal cord: methods and applications - a review. NMR Biomed. 2002 Nov-Dec;15(7-8):578-86. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12489104</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Stefano N, Matthews PM, Arnold DL. Reversible decreases in N-acetylaspartate after acute brain injury. Magn Reson Med. 1995 Nov;34(5):721-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8544693</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dvorak MF, Fisher CG, Hoekema J, Boyd M, Noonan V, Wing PC, Kwon BK. Factors predicting motor recovery and functional outcome after traumatic central cord syndrome: a long-term follow-up. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2005 Oct 15;30(20):2303-11. Erratum in: Spine. 2006 May 15;31(11):1289. Kwon, Brian [corrected to Kwon, Brian K].</citation>
    <PMID>16227894</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holly LT, Dong Y, Albistegui-DuBois R, Marehbian J, Dobkin B. Cortical reorganization in patients with cervical spondylotic myelopathy. J Neurosurg Spine. 2007 Jun;6(6):544-51.</citation>
    <PMID>17561743</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kassem MN, Bartha R. Quantitative proton short-echo-time LASER spectroscopy of normal human white matter and hippocampus at 4 Tesla incorporating macromolecule subtraction. Magn Reson Med. 2003 May;49(5):918-27.</citation>
    <PMID>12704775</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pickett GE, Campos-Benitez M, Keller JL, Duggal N. Epidemiology of traumatic spinal cord injury in Canada. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2006 Apr 1;31(7):799-805.</citation>
    <PMID>16582854</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Puri BK, Smith HC, Cox IJ, Sargentoni J, Savic G, Maskill DW, Frankel HL, Ellaway PH, Davey NJ. The human motor cortex after incomplete spinal cord injury: an investigation using proton magnetic resonance spectroscopy. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry. 1998 Nov;65(5):748-54.</citation>
    <PMID>9810950</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yamazaki T, Yanaka K, Fujita K, Kamezaki T, Uemura K, Nose T. Traumatic central cord syndrome: analysis of factors affecting the outcome. Surg Neurol. 2005 Feb;63(2):95-9; discussion 99-100.</citation>
    <PMID>15680638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 12, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 12, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 13, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 25, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 25, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cervical spondylotic myelopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>spinal cord compression</keyword>
  <keyword>magnetic resonance spectroscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>functional magnetic resonance imaging</keyword>
  <keyword>brain plasticity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Central Cord Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

