<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00792324</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SSAT 029</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00792324</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pilot Study Switching Individuals Receiving EFV With Continuing Central Nervous System Toxicity to TMC125</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase III, Double Blind, Mulit-centre, Randomised Placebo Controlled, Pilot Study to Assess the Feasibility of Switching Individuals Receiving Efavirez With Continuing Central Nervous System (CNS) Toxicity to TMC125.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St Stephens Aids Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St Stephens Aids Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to examine the effect of switching from an antiretroviral
      combination that includes efavirenz (Susitiva®), in individuals experiencing
      efavirenz-related side effects, and replacing this with an investigational HIV medication
      called Etravirine (TMC125).

      The study will primarily investigate the effect of change in medication on your viral load
      (the levels of the HIV virus in your blood), on immunological parameters (CD4 count), on
      other safety parameters (such as cholesterol) your side effects and also on your quality of
      life.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The majority of individuals who commence treatment for HIV in the UK start with a regimen
      that includes EFV in combination with other antiretrovirals. These regimens are convenient
      (once daily dosing) and highly efficacious. However EFV has several potential drawbacks
      including continued CNS toxicity, the potential for teratogenesis and a low barrier to the
      development of virological resistance. In the past the only alternative NNRTI available was
      nevirapine which appears to have a lower rate of virological success and is associated with
      potentially life threatening toxicities including hepatotoxicity and cutaneous toxicity
      including the Stevens-Johnson syndrome.

      Clinically controlled trials frequently reported undesirable nervous system side effects in
      patients receiving 600 mg EFV with other antiretroviral agents, including dizziness,insomnia,
      somnolence, impaired concentration and abnormal dreaming. CNS symptoms of moderate to severe
      intensity were experienced by 19.4% of patients compared to 9.0% of patients receiving
      control regimens. These symptoms were severe in 2.0% of patients receiving EFV 600 mg daily
      and in 1.3% of patients receiving control regimens. In clinical studies 2.1% of patients
      treated with 600 mg of EFV discontinued therapy because of nervous system symptoms.

      Nervous system symptoms usually begin during the first one or two days of therapy and often
      resolve after the first 2 -4 weeks. However in a significant proportion of individuals it
      continues with an adverse effect on quality of life. CNS toxicity may also worsen drug
      compliance. In a study of uninfected volunteers, a representative nervous system symptom had
      a median time to onset of 1 hour post dose and a median duration of 3 hours.

      Nervous system symptoms may occur more frequently when EFV is taken concomitantly with meals
      possibly due to increased EFV plasma. Dosing at bedtime seems to improve the tolerability of
      these symptoms and can be recommended during the first weeks of therapy and in patients who
      continue to experience symptoms although this is not always successful and may be associated
      with vivid or disturbing dreams. Dose reduction or splitting the daily dose has not been
      shown to provide benefit.

      Other adverse events associated with efavirenz include rash (5-26%, usually minor),increased
      cholesterol (20-40%) and triglycerides (6-11%), diarrhea (3-14%), nausea and hyperglycemia
      (2-5%). Serious psychiatric adverse events such as precipitation of psychosis, seizure,
      suicidal ideation, paranoia, mania and aggression have also been associated with use. These
      are seen in &lt;1% taking EFV and are thought to be more likely in those with a history of
      mental illness/drug abuse or predisposition to psychological reactions.

      TMC125 is a diarylpyrimidine derivative that has proven efficacy against HIV-1 including
      activity in viral isolates with existing NNRTI signature mutations. Resistance to TMC125 also
      appears to develop less readily than to EFV and NVP. This has been attributed to its
      molecular structure. TMC125 has demonstrated safety and efficacy in short term studies in
      both treatment-naïve and NNRTI-resistant HIV-1 infected patients.

      Recently published results from phase 3 trials give further support to these findings with
      efficacy in reduction of HIV-1-RNA levels seen in patients with substantial NNRTI and PI
      resistance when treated with TMC125 plus an optimized background.

      TMC-125 is generally well tolerated and in particular has lower reported rates of CNS
      toxicity than EFV. Animal studies have shown a low risk of teratogenesis. The major toxicity
      of TMC125 has been skin rash which is usually self-limiting. In the repeated dose trials the
      adverse events (AEs) reported in more than 10% of all subjects were headache, somnolence,
      diarrhea, flatulence, nausea and vomiting, fatigue, fever, rash,and pruritus. Overall, AEs
      were mild to moderate in intensity, with no apparent doseresponse relationship. No consistent
      or clinically relevant changes in electrocardiogram (ECG) or vital signs were observed with
      single and repeated TMC125 dosing.

      TMC125 is a new NNRTI with proven efficacy against HIV-1 with several potential advantages
      over EFV including no CNS toxicity and a high barrier to the development of resistance. This
      study aims to investigate whether substitution of EFV with TMC125 leads to improvement of CNS
      toxicity with continued virological suppression and immunological reconstitution and whether
      this is associated with an improvement in quality of life.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The rate of neuropsychiatric and central nervous system (CNS) toxicity as measured by the proportion of patients experiencing grade 2-4 neuropsychiatric and CNS toxicity after 12 weeks (as defined by the ACTG adverse event scale).</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The rate of neuropsychiatric and central nervous system (CNS) toxicity after 12 and 24 weeks as measured by the change from baseline by the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS).</measure>
    <time_frame>12-24 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with viral load below 50 copies/mL at weeks 12 and 24</measure>
    <time_frame>12-24 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with viral load below 400 copies/mL at weeks 12 and 24</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 24 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in CD4+ count at weeks 12 and 24</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 24 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in laboratory parameters at weeks 12 and 24</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 24 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of patients with non-CNS adverse events at weeks 12 and 24</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 24 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in adherence at weeks 12 and 24 as measured by the adherence questionnaire: Medication Adherence Self- Report Inventory (M-MASRI)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 24 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in patient-perceived distress associated with tolerability problems at weeks 12 and 24 as determined by tolerability index questionnaire (HIV patients symptoms profile)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 and 24 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Four 100mg Etravirine tablets plus one Efavirenz (EFV) placebo tablet once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>One 600mg EFV tablet plus four Etravirine placebo tablet tablets once daily</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Etravirine</intervention_name>
    <description>Four 100mg tablets daily for 12-24 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TMC125</other_name>
    <other_name>Brand Name: Intelence</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Efavirenz</intervention_name>
    <description>One 600mg tablet daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>TMC125</other_name>
    <other_name>Brand Name: Intelence</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Documented HIV-1 infection

          -  Willing to comply with the protocol requirements

          -  Has an HIV-plasma viral load at screening &lt;50 HIV-1 RNA copies/mL

          -  Has a CD4 cell count at screening &gt;50 cells/mm3

          -  Has been on a stable ART, with at least 3 licensed agents, one of which being EFV, for
             at least 12 weeks at screening, and is willing to stay on treatment until baseline

          -  Symptomatic toxicity associated with the EFV after at least 12 weeks of therapy

          -  If subject is female of childbearing potential, she is using effective birth control
             methods and is willing to continue practicing these birth control methods during the
             trial and for at least 30 days after the end of the trial (or after last intake of
             investigational ARV's)

          -  If the subject is a heterosexually active male, he is using effective birth control
             methods and is willing to continue practicing these birth control methods during the
             trial and until 30 days after the end of the trial (or after the last intake of
             investigational ARVs)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has a primary HIV-1 infection

          -  Subject has an HIV-2 infection

          -  Subject is using any concomitant therapy disallowed by the protocol (as per SPC for
             EFV and TMC125)

          -  Subject has any condition (including but not limited to alcohol and drug use) which,
             in the opinion of the investigator, could compromise the subject's safety or adherence
             to the protocol

          -  Subject's life expectancy less than 6 months according to the judgment of the
             investigator

          -  subject has a currently active AIDS defining illness (Category C conditions according
             to the Center for Disease Control [CDC] Classification System for HIV Infection 1993)
             with the following exceptions, which must be discussed with the sponsor prior to
             enrollment:

          -  Stable cutaneous Kaposi's Sarcoma (i.e., no pulmonary or gastrointestinal involvement
             other than oral lesions) that is unlikely to require any form of systemic therapy
             during the trial period

          -  Wasting syndrome due to HIV infection Note: Primary and secondary prophylaxis for an
             AIDS defining illness is allowed if the medication used is not part of the disallowed
             medication

          -  Subject has any active clinically significant disease (e.g., pancreatic, cardiac
             dysfunction) or findings during Screening of medical history or physical examination
             that, in the investigator's opinion, would compromise the outcome of the trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark Nelson</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St Stephen's AIDS Trust</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chelsea and Westminster Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SW10 9TH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 14, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 14, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 17, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 17, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 17, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 18, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Dr Mark Nelson</name_title>
    <organization>St Stephens Aids Trust</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Efavirenz</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Etravirine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

