<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00793429</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GBR-9</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00793429</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Study of Prucalopride in Healthy Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Two-Way Cross-Over in Healthy Volunteers, to Evaluate the Pharmacokinetics, Tolerability and Cardiac Safety of Prucalopride at Steady-State</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Movetis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Movetis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In this study healthy volunteers received increasing doses of prucalopride to study the
      tolerability and cardiac safety of prucalopride. The study hypothesis was that prucalopride
      at doses up to 10 mg has no clinically relevant effect on the cardiovascular safety in
      healthy volunteers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Single-centre, double-blind, placebo-controlled, cross-over study in 33 healthy volunteers
      with 2 sessions. Each session consisted of a run-in day for baseline assessments, 8 treatment
      days and 5 additional days for followup assessments. Subjects were randomised to start with
      either the prucalopride or placebo session. The prucalopride dose was consecutively escalated
      in 2 mg steps per day, starting from 2 mg up to 10 mg once daily If a subject did not
      tolerate the 10- or 8-mg dose, 1 step back in the dosage scheme was allowed, from 10 to 8 mg
      on Day 6, or from 8 to 6 mg on Day 5. Subjects with intolerance for doses of less than 6 mg,
      were withdrawn from the study. Repeated dosing (6, 8 or 10 mg) was continued once daily until
      Day 8, to achieve steady-state. During placebo, the number of placebo tablets was
      consecutively escalated in an identical way as described for prucalopride. Between the 2
      sessions, there was a washout period of 14 to 21 days, to avoid any carry-over effect.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Prucalopride</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged between 18 and 45 years.

          -  Normal weight.

          -  Healthy on the basis of a pre-study physical examination, medical history,
             anamnesis,ECG, 24-hour Holter monitoring, echocardiogram and the results of blood
             biochemistry and haematology tests and a urinalysis carried out in 3 weeks preceding
             randomisation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History or suspicion of alcohol, barbiturate, amphetamine or narcotic abuse.

          -  Smoking more than 10 cigarettes, or 2 cigars, or 2 pipes per day for at least 6 months
             prior to selection.

          -  History of cardiac arrhythmias, bronchospastic or cardiovascular disease (e.g.
             ischaemic heart disease or cerebrovascular accident), diabetes mellitus,
             thyrotoxicosis,Parkinsonism.

          -  Presence of prolonged QTc (Bazett) on ECG at screening (QTc &gt;450 ms in male subjects,
             QTc &gt;470 ms in female subjects).

          -  Use of concomitant medication, except for oral contraceptives and paracetamol.

          -  Participation in an investigational drug study in 30 days prior to the first visit.

          -  Donation of blood in the 60 days preceding the first visit.

          -  Pregnancy or breast-feeding female.

          -  Female subjects of childbearing potential without adequate contraceptive protection
             during the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>November 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 18, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 18, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 19, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 20, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 20, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 21, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>electrocardiographic safety</keyword>
  <keyword>pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

