<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00795522</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P02540</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00795522</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Open-Label Study of the Effects of Desloratadine (Aerius.) Treatment on the Quality of Life of Patients With Chronic Idiopathic Urticaria (Study P02540)</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label Study of the Effects of Desloratadine (Aerius.) Treatment on the Quality of Life of Patients With Chronic Idiopathic Urticaria</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corp.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This open-label study is being conducted to determine the effect of DL treatment for CIU on
      symptom and disease severity, quality of life, daytime functioning, and quality of sleep.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2005</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2005</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in the Short Form 12 (SF-12) Health Survey Questionnaire, mental, physical and total scores on treatment days 7, 14, 21, and 28.</measure>
    <time_frame>treatment days 7, 14, 21, and 28</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in work/school attendance and self-assessed productivity as measured by the WPAI questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>treatment days 7, 14, 21, and 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in pruritus, the number of hives and the maximum size of hives, sleep quality, and activity impairment</measure>
    <time_frame>treatment weeks 1, 2, 3, and 4</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The percent of subjects who rate their response to therapy as either Complete, Marked, or Moderate Relief</measure>
    <time_frame>day 28</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">51</enrollment>
  <condition>Urticaria</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Desloratadine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Desloratadine</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will receive DL 5 mg daily for 28 days. Each active DL tablet contains 5 mg of desloratadine</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SCH 034117</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must demonstrate their willingness to participate in the study and comply
             with its procedures by signing a written informed consent.

          -  Subjects must be &gt;= 18 years of age, of either sex and any race.

          -  Women of childbearing potential (includes women who are less than 1 year
             postmenopausal and women who become sexually active) must be using an acceptable
             method of birth control (e.g., hormonal contraceptive, medically prescribed IUD,
             condom in combination with spermicide) or be surgically sterilized (e.g., hysterectomy
             or tubal ligation). Women of childbearing potential should be counseled in the
             appropriate use of birth control while in this study. Women who are not currently
             sexually active must agree and consent to use one of the above-mentioned methods
             should they become sexually active while participating in the study.

          -  Subjects must be in general good health; i.e., they must be free of any clinically
             significant disease (other than CIU) that would interfere with study evaluations.

          -  Subjects must understand and be able to adhere to the dosing and visit schedules, and
             agree to complete the questionnaires and to record symptom severity scores, medication
             times, concomitant medications, and adverse events accurately and consistently in a
             daily diary.

          -  Subjects must have at least a 6-week history of CIU (pruritus and hives) prior to
             Visit 1 (Screening).

          -  Subjects must have a pruritus score &gt;= 2 and a hive score &gt;= 1 at Visit 1.

          -  Subjects must be experiencing a current CIU flare of at least 3 weeks duration, with
             hives present at least 3 days per week, prior to Visit 1 (Screening).

          -  Subjects must score the overall condition of CIU &gt;= 2 at both Visit 1 (Screening) and
             Visit 2 (Baseline).

          -  Subjects must have a total pruritus score of &gt;= 14 for the sum of morning and evening
             (reflective) diary scores for the 3 days prior to Visit 2 (Baseline) plus the morning
             score on the day of Visit 2.

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative urine pregnancy test at Visit 2
             (Baseline).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women who are pregnant or nursing.

          -  Subjects who have not observed the designated washout periods for any of the
             prohibited medications outlined.

          -  Subjects with asthma requiring chronic use of inhaled or systemic corticosteroids.

          -  Subjects with drug or food allergies that manifest as skin reactions.

          -  Subjects with urticaria that is primarily due to physical urticaria or other known
             etiology.

          -  Subjects with CIU unresponsive to antihistamines.

          -  Subjects who have been hospitalized (including an emergency department visit) because
             of deterioration in their CIU within 3 months prior to Visit 1 (Screening).

          -  Subjects with a history of hypersensitivity to desloratadine or any of its excipients.

          -  Subjects previously randomized into this study.

          -  Subjects who are staff personnel directly involved with the administration of this
             study.

          -  Subjects who have any clinically significant metabolic, cardiovascular, immunologic,
             neurologic, hematologic, gastrointestinal, cerebrovascular, or respiratory disease, or
             any other disorder which, in the judgment of the Investigator, may interfere with the
             study evaluations or affect subject safety.

          -  Subjects with a history of psychosis, antagonistic personality, poor motivation,
             hypochondriasis, or any other emotional or intellectual problems that are likely to
             limit the validity of consent to participate in the study.

          -  Subjects with a history of noncompliance with medications or treatment protocols.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 19, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 20, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 21, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 20, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 20, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 21, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urticaria</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Desloratadine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Loratadine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

