<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01916694</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>13/SC/0176</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01916694</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Remote Evaluation and Treatment of Gestational Diabetes Mellitus</brief_title>
  <acronym>TREAT-GDM</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomised Pilot Trial to Compare Remote Blood Glucose Monitoring With Standard Clinical Care in the Gestational Diabetic Population</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Diabetes in pregnancy (gestational diabetes) is becoming more common. It can lead to problems
      for both mothers-to-be and their babies such as causing a large baby and difficult birth.
      Gestational diabetes in the mother may also lead to effects on the long term health of the
      baby.

      Most people today use mobile phones. Our research is looking at using a mobile phone app to
      help with diabetes care in pregnancy. In particular, the investigators are using phones which
      connect to the standard blood glucose monitoring machines given to all women with gestational
      diabetes to see if sending the hospital team blood test results between clinic appointments
      can result in the need for fewer clinic visits. The investigators are also testing to see how
      acceptable using mobile phones in this way, is to our patients and that the control of the
      blood glucose and outcomes for the mother and baby are at least as good as standard care.

      The investigators are planning to recruit 200 women who receive care for their gestational
      diabetes at the Oxford University Hospitals NHS (National Health Service) Trust. They will be
      randomised so that 100 will receive standard care, and 100 will have a mobile phone &quot;app&quot;
      linked to the blood glucose machines to send blood glucose readings directly to the diabetes
      care team to review.

      Both groups will be asked to test their blood glucose levels at home regularly with a
      glucometer. All participants will also be given lifestyle advice to reduce the chance they
      will need medication. Blood glucose control will be measured also by the percentage of
      glycated hemoglobin (HbA1c) at the time of diagnosis of gestational diabetes and before
      delivery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glycosylated haemogloblin</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks from recruitment at 28 weeks gestation to 36 weeks gestation</time_frame>
    <description>Glycosylated haemoglobin (HbA1C) will be measured at the time of recruitment (around 28 weeks gestation) and at 36 weeks gestation. This will be approximately 8 weeks after recruitment (time 0).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Blood glucose levels for fasting, pre-prandial and post-prandial readings</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks (from 28 weeks gestation to 38 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Mean blood glucose levels for all readings measured fasting, pre-prandial and post prandial will be calculated over the 10 week participation in the trial (from recruitment at 28 weeks gestation to delivery at 38 weeks gestation).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of 'on target' blood glucose readings</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks (from recruitment at 28 weeks gestation to 36 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting readings as defined &gt;=3.5 and &lt;=5.8 mmol/L and post prandial readings &gt;= 3.5 and &lt;= 7.7 mmol/L for the first four weeks after randomisation and the second four weeks after randomisation</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness of monitoring</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks (from 28 weeks gestation to 38 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Time to first trigger point (intensive dietary and lifestyle advice and increase monitoring to 7 days home per week) Time to second trigger point (insulin or metformin therapy) Time to treatment Number of changes to hypoglycaemics Maximum dose of insulin and metformin</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 11 weeks after recruitment</time_frame>
    <description>Perineal trauma (defined as third or fourth degree tear), pregnancy induced hypertension and preeclampsia, admission to higher level of care for mother. This will be measured up to 7 days post delivery (if birth is at 38 weeks, this will be 11 weeks after trial recruitment, unless birth occurs earlier)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal weight gain,</measure>
    <time_frame>10 weeks (from 28 weeks gestation to 38 weeks gestation)</time_frame>
    <description>Weight gain in kilograms from trial recruitment until last antenatal visit prior to delivery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Birthweight</measure>
    <time_frame>At birth (approximately 10 weeks after trial recruitment)</time_frame>
    <description>Z score of weight in kilograms for gestational age at delivery and Birthweight greater than 4.5kg</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Birth injury</measure>
    <time_frame>At birth (approximately 10 weeks after trial recruitment)</time_frame>
    <description>Fracture of clavicle or humerus or other injury attributed to difficult birth, such as Erbs palsy or skull fracture</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neonatal hypoglycaemia</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 10.5 weeks after recruitment</time_frame>
    <description>Documented blood glucose level &lt;2.5mmol/L or requiring parenteral feeding within the first 48 hours of life after birth at around 38 weeks gestation (birth at approximately 10 weeks following trial recruitment and blood glucose monitoring in the neonate up to 48 hours after this)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Economic evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>11 weeks from trial recruitment</time_frame>
    <description>Direct cost of clinical care provision including outpatient appointments, emergency presentations, inpatient admission nights, neonatal intensive and special care admission nights, cost of phone and blue tooth equipment, time spent on computer system by clinical staff, other associated treatment and obstetric management costs, costs associated with co-morbid conditions</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">203</enrollment>
  <condition>Gestational Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <condition>Pregnancy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Smart phone app glucose monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Home blood glucose monitoring results directly transmitted via a bluetooth enabled smart phone app to a central database to be reviewed by clinicians</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard glucose monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Home blood glucose monitoring results recorded by hand in a paper diary by the patient and reviewed by the clinical team in the outpatient clinic.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blue tooth enabled glucose meter with smart phone application</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Smart phone app glucose monitoring</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Self home blood glucose monitoring</intervention_name>
    <description>Fingerprick testing of blood glucose levels before and 2 hours after meals</description>
    <arm_group_label>Smart phone app glucose monitoring</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Standard glucose monitoring</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant women with an abnormal 75 gram 2 hour glucose tolerance test as defined by
             the IADPSG (International Association of Diabetes in Pregnancy Study Group)

          -  Willingness and able to give informed consent

          -  Female aged between 18-40 years

          -  Singleton pregnancy

          -  Able to travel to hospital independently

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Impaired cognitive function such that she is unable to operate m-health equipment

          -  Any evidence of fetal compromise

          -  Known risk factors for obstetric complications, other than obesity and diabetes

          -  Gestational diabetes requiring immediate pharmacologic treatment

          -  Twins or higher order pregnancy

          -  OGTT (Oral Glucose Tolerance Test) suggesting preexisting diabetes (fasting blood
             glucose &gt;= 7.0 or 2 hour &gt;= 11.1 mmol/L

          -  Gestation greater than 34+6 at the time of potential recruitment

          -  Unable to speak English well enough to explain or use equipment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>John Radcliffe Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <state>Oxfordshire</state>
        <zip>OX3 9DU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 4, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 1, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 6, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 19, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 19, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 20, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Gestational diabetes mellitus</keyword>
  <keyword>m Health</keyword>
  <keyword>Smartphone</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood glucose monitoring</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes, Gestational</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

