<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01911910</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ReDa: 007711</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01911910</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Heart Attack Prevention Programme for You (HAPPY) London</brief_title>
  <acronym>HAPPYLondon</acronym>
  <official_title>Heart Attack Prevention Programme for You (HAPPY) London</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Queen Mary University of London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Barts &amp; The London NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Queen Mary University of London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Diseases of the heart and blood vessels, such as heart attacks and strokes, are very common
      and can lead to severe disability or death. Changes in the body leading to heart attacks and
      strokes usually develop over decades as a result of smoking, diet, and lack of exercise,
      obesity, diabetes and high blood pressure. Changes in lifestyle and diet can significantly
      reduce the risk of heart diseases. General Practitioners invite 40 to 74 year-olds who have
      no known heart disease to take part in the NHS Health Check, which measures each person's
      individual risk of developing a heart attack or stroke and encourages them in a face-to-face
      meeting to take part in programmes to help them to give up smoking, lose weight etc. where
      necessary. In this new clinical trial the investigators will test whether computer-tailored
      electronic (e)-coaching via email and the internet can help people make the necessary changes
      in their lifestyle to reduce the risk of heart attacks and strokes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Heart Attack Prevention Programme for You London (HAPPY London) will be conducted as a
      randomised controlled trial comparing the use of tailored e-coaching in addition to the
      standard of care vs. standard care alone. Standard care is defined as the care that would be
      offered by the NHS Health Check programme through the NHS primary care. We will use a range
      of established and novel cardiovascular markers to determine the clinical and cost
      effectiveness of e-coaching and gain pathophysiological insight into how lifestyle
      modifications affect the cardiovascular system. These measures include cardiovascular
      magnetic resonance imaging (CMR), aortic stiffness parameters, vascular ultrasound and other
      biomarkers of CV disease risk.

      Intervention

      The HAPPY London web-based tool will provide the participant with an individualised score for
      their lifestyle and 10 year CV risk score, based on the modified Framingham score and the UK
      specific QRisk Score, and provide tailored advice and education on the suboptimal factors.
      Ideal targets will be set and the information will be updated at 3 and 6 months allowing the
      participant to view their progress. Weekly emails with brief health and lifestyle advice will
      be sent to encourage healthier behaviour based on clinical studies or topical issues in the
      media. Links to social networks, such as Facebook posting and the ability to allow chosen
      'buddies' from family or friends to view their progress will aim to further encourage
      healthier behaviour.

      The study involves the recruitment of 400 adults between the age of 40 and 74 years who have
      a moderate to high 10-year CV risk score (Estimated 10 year CV risk &gt;10%). Half of the study
      group will receive use of the e-coaching in addition to standard care allocated randomly
      stratified according to either moderate (QRisk between 10 and 20%) or high risk (QRisk more
      than or equal to 20%). The initial screening will take place on the www.happylondon.info
      web-based 'mini-check' questionnaire. Potential participants will then be seen at a physical
      screening visit to confirm eligibility. 3 subsequent visits will take place over 6 months;
      baseline, 3 month and 6 month follow up. A subgroup of the study population (65 from each
      intervention arm thus totalling 130 participants ) will also have a baseline and follow up
      cardiovascular magnetic resonance (CMR) imaging. Assessment will be performed using a variety
      of measures through questionnaires, blood pressure (BP) checks, blood tests, ultrasound
      scans, oscillometric method to assess pulse wave velocity and pulse wave analysis and CMR
      multi-parametric scanning.

      The primary aim of this study is to assess the clinical effectiveness of individualised,
      continuous electronic (e-) coaching to support a healthier lifestyle as a primary prevention
      tool to reduce the CV risk and improve the quality of life in asymptomatic individuals with
      intermediate to high 10 year CV risk.

      Other questions that we aim to answer are:

        1. Is computer-tailored e-coaching cost-effective in the short-term (clinical trial period)
           and during the long-term (decision analysis modelling)

        2. What are the associations of personality traits, economic preferences, and sociocultural
           factors with the achieved lifestyle modifications and changes in the cardiovascular
           phenotype?

        3. What is the relationship between changes observed in markers derived from our
           multi-parametric cardiovascular magnetic resonance imaging protocols following lifestyle
           changes?

        4. How frequent are silent myocardial infarctions in a typical NHS Health Check population?

        5. Do treatment effects differ between ethnic groups?
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pulse wave velocity (PWV)</measure>
    <time_frame>Base line visit, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in aortic stiffness using a Vicorder device measured in m/s</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in carotid intima media thickness CIMT</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Lifestyle, quality of life and physical activity questionnaires. Questionnaires SF-36, EQ5D-3L, RPAQ.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulse Wave Velocity by CMR</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Change in aortic stiffness - pulse wave velocity (m/s, CMR)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Aortic distensibility by Cardiovascular magnetic resonance (CMR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>CMR will be performed on 65 participants in the treatment and 65 in the standard care group.
Change in aortic stiffness - aortic distensibility (mmHg-1, CMR)).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Left ventricular mass by CMR</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Change in LV mass index (g/m2, CMR).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Left ventricular ejection fraction by CMR</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>LV end-diastolic and end-systolic volume indices, (ml/m2, CMR), LV EF (%, CMR).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Myocardial fibrosis by CMR</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Extent and change in diffuse myocardial fibrosis (extracellular volume fraction %, CMR)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Diastolic function by CMR</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 6 month</time_frame>
    <description>Diastolic function (strain and strain rate in % and s-1, respectively,CMR).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Framingham Risk Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of cardiovascular risk based on the Framingham algorithm</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QRisk Score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of cardiovascular risk score based on the QRisk risk score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total cholesterol to HDL ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Bloods for lipid profile.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>LDL cholesterol</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Bloods for lipid profile.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glucose levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Fasting glucose bloods</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>hsCRP</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>baseline and change in hsCRP blood test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in physical activity</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Lifestyle, quality of life and physical activity questionnaires. Questionnaires SF-36, EQ5D-3L, RPAQ</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in systolic blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>change in diastolic blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">402</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual care that would be provided by the NHS Health Check or equivalent.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Electronic coaching plus standard care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tailored coaching for participants randomised to use the HAPPY e-coaching tool. Access to lifestyle and heart health scores and personalised advice to improve suboptimal behaviour.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Electronic coaching plus standard care</intervention_name>
    <description>The HAPPY London web-based tool will provide the participant with an individualised score for their lifestyle and 10 year CV risk score, based mainly on the modified Framingham score, and provide tailored advice and education on the suboptimal factors. Ideal targets will be set and the information will be updated at 3 and 6 months allowing the participant to view their progress. Weekly emails with brief health and lifestyle advice will be sent to encourage healthier behaviour based on clinical studies or topical issues in the media. Links to social networks, such as Facebook posting and the ability to allow chosen family and friends to view their progress will aim to further encourage healthier behaviour.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Electronic coaching plus standard care</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Electronic coaching</other_name>
    <other_name>E-Coaching</other_name>
    <other_name>HAPPY E-Coaching</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects will be enrolled following an informed consent. The subject will be able to
             understand and comply with protocol requirements, instructions and protocol-stated
             restrictions

          -  Subjects will be between 40 and 74 years of age

          -  Subjects will have unrestricted access to the Internet

          -  Subjects will be sufficiently fluent in English language.

          -  Subjects will have an estimated intermediate to high risk for CV events based on the
             web-based pre-screening tool (www.happylondon.info), which is based on the
             nonlaboratory Framingham risk score (&gt;10% 10 year cardiovascular risk)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of stroke or transient ischaemic attack (TIA)

          -  Cardiac sounding chest pain requiring further investigations

          -  Current life threatening conditions other than vascular disease (e.g. very severe
             chronic airways disease, HIV positive, life-threatening arrhythmias) that may prevent
             a subject from completing the study

          -  Only for subgroup undergoing cardiac contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance studies: Any
             contraindication to a contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance study, such as known
             allergies to gadolinium-based contrast agents, severe claustrophobia, pacemakers,
             defibrillators, etc
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>74 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steffen E Petersen, MD DPhil</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Queen Mary University of London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre for Advanced Cardiovascular Imaging, William Harvey Research Institute, Queen May University of London</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>E2 9JX</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.happylondon.info</url>
    <description>This is the HAPPY London official website. It has information for potential participants, allows eligible subject to book visits, fill out questionnaires and use the e-coaching if randomised to use it.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 22, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 27, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 30, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 31, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Queen Mary University of London</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr Steffen Erhard Petersen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Reader in Advanced Cardiovascular Imaging, Honorary Consultant Cardiologist, Centre Lead for Advanced Cardiovascular Imaging</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>primary prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular magnetic resonance (CMR)</keyword>
  <keyword>Electronic coaching (e-coaching)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

