<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01913717</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IEO S768/113</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2012-IG133218</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01913717</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Short-term High Precision Radiotherapy for Early Prostate Cancer With Concomitant Boost on the Dominant Lesion</brief_title>
  <official_title>Short-term High Precision Radiotherapy for Early Prostate Cancer With Concomitant Boost on the Dominant Lesion</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>European Institute of Oncology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>European Institute of Oncology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The present research project aims to improve the current treatment for prostate-confined
      tumor, evaluating the safety and feasibility of a very short hypofractionated radiotherapy
      schedule administered with one of the best available dose delivery systems. The study will
      include 2 sub-studies (in-silica and clinical study) and 4 tasks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Approximately 70% of men with newly diagnosed prostate cancer feature organ-confined disease.
      Conventional treatment options for prostate-confined cancer include radical prostatectomy,
      external beam radiation therapy, brachytherapy and active surveillance. All currently
      available treatments have comparable toxicity risk and high social and economic impact, hence
      the best treatment option has not been defined yet. In the radiation oncology field the gold
      standard for prostate cancer management is 7-8 weeks intensity modulated radiotherapy (IMRT),
      which can be delivered with the latest generation of accelerators providing modulated arc
      delivery (eg. RapidArc™, Varian) or with newly developed machines such as the Vero system
      (BrainLab AG - Mitsubishi Heavy Industries Ltd). The present research project aims to improve
      the current treatment for prostate confined tumor, evaluating the best strategy to deliver a
      very-short hypofractionated radiotherapy scheme. In the first part of this AIRC grant an
      in-silica study will be performed on 10 test prostate cancer patients, with comparative
      competitive treatment plans with the state of the art treatment options for prostate cancer:
      the Vero system, the RapidArc system, the Cyberknife (all available at the European Institute
      of Oncology IEO, Milan, Italy), and protontherapy (available at the Centre of Adrotherapy, in
      Pavia, Italy). This dosimetric comparison will be performed in order to define the technique
      that provides the maximum target coverage with the minimum dose to the surrounding organs at
      risk (OARs) to be used to perform the clinical trial that will follow within this AIRC grant.
      After performing the in-silica study, 65 newly diagnosed prostate cancer patients with 2011
      National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) risk category ranging from very low to
      intermediate but not undergoing hormonal treatment, will be consecutively enrolled in a
      prospective phase II trial. The patients will be treated at the Division of Radiation
      Oncology of the IEO, with the dose delivery system that will result most fit at the in-silica
      study. Simultaneous Integrated Boost (SIB) technique will be applied to deliver a total dose
      of 36.25 Gy in 5 fractions (over 10 days) to the whole prostate (7.25 Gy/fraction) and 37.5
      Gy to the dominant intraprostatic lesion DIL (7.5 Gy/fraction), profiting of the high
      sensibility of prostate cancer to high dose/fraction. Several strategies will be applied in
      order to reduce the dose to the surrounding OARs. In order to define the localization of the
      DIL, multiparametic magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the pelvis will be performed (with
      spectroscopy, diffusion weighted and perfusion acquisitions), and fused with computed
      tomography (CT) scan. In-room image-guidance will be applied at each treatment section, in
      order to minimize uncertainties in intra and inter-fraction prostate localization. At the end
      of the radiotherapy course, each patient will be followed-up, in order to assess the
      treatment safety and effectiveness in terms of early and late toxicity, and tumor control. A
      sampling from the prostate tumor tissue for biological study will be taken for microarray
      analysis. The expression of specific markers of radiosensitivity and radioresistance will be
      investigated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>one month after radiotherapy</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is the acute toxicity according to the validated scale Radiotherapy Oncology Group / European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer (RTOG / EORTC). It will measure the proportion of patients who experience at least one event of acute toxicity of grade 3 or 4 according to the scale RTOG / EORTC) as the maximum value of toxicity during radiation treatment or within one month after the completion of radiotherapy.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>late toxicity</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>late toxicity according to Scala CTCAE v4.0 toxicity criteria and scale RTOG / EORTC</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>efficacy of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>assessed in terms of
biochemical progression free survival (biochemical relapse, i.e. rising PSA)
pattern of relapse
clinical progression free survival (including local or distant recurrence)
overall survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">65</enrollment>
  <condition>Adenocarcinoma of Prostate</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>External beam radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>External beam radiotherapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>External beam radiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>The patients will be treated with extreme hypofractionated radiotherapy with the dose delivery system that will result most fit at the in-silica study. Simultaneous Integrated Boost (SIB) technique will be applied to deliver a total dose of 36.25 Gy in 5 fractions (over 10 days) to the whole prostate (7.25 Gy/fraction) and 37.5 Gy to the dominant intraprostatic lesion DIL (7.5 Gy/fraction), profiting of the high sensibility of prostate cancer to high dose/fraction. Several strategies will be applied in order to reduce the dose to the surrounding organs at risk.</description>
    <arm_group_label>External beam radiotherapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>hypofractionated radiotherapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - Histologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of prostate, including the following 2011
        National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) risk categories: very low (T1c PSA &lt;10 ng/ml,
        Gleason score &lt;7, fewer than 3 positive biopsy cores, &lt;50% cancer in each core, PSA density
        &lt;0.15 ng/ml) or low (T1-T2a, PSA &lt;10 ng/ml, Gleason score &lt;7) or intermediate (T2b or T2c,
        PSA between 10 and 20 ng/ml, Gleason score of 7)

          -  cN0 and cM0 stage

          -  Age &gt; 18 years

          -  Good performance status (ECOG&lt; 2),

          -  No previous pelvic radiotherapy

          -  No previous prostatectomy

          -  No hormonal treatment (neoadjuvant or concomitant)

          -  No concomitant bowel inflammatory disease or other serious comorbidities

          -  Good urinary flow (peak flow &gt; 10 ml/s)

          -  No previous invasive cancer (within 5 years before the prostate cancer diagnosis)
             apart from non-melanoma skin malignancies.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Extraprostatic tumor extension (T3) or locally advanced disease (T4)

          -  Pelvic lymph node metastasis (N1)

          -  Distant metastasis (M1)

          -  Urinary obstructive symptoms (IPSS &gt; 20)

          -  Previous pelvic radiotherapy

          -  Severe systemic disorders

          -  Concomitant disorders including: chronic urinary or intestinal inflammatory conditions
             (for example, ulcerous recto-colitis, Crohn disease), anti-coagulant treatment
             (warfarin, heparin)

          -  Previous malignancy except for skin non-melanoma cancer or 3-year disease free
             interval from previous malignancy like in situ cervix cancer or non muscle invasive
             bladder cancer

          -  Non conformity of the radiotherapy dose distribution when compared to the dose
             constraints

          -  Psychiatric disorders or any other condition that can can make unreliable the informed
             consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Roberto Orecchia, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>European Institute of Oncology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>BARBARA A JERECZEK, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>European Institute of Oncology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>European Institute of Oncology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milan</city>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.airc.it</url>
    <description>AIRC: ASSOCIAZIONE ITALIANA PER LA RICERCA SUL CANCRO</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 30, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 31, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 1, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 9, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 9, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 10, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Prostate cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiotherapy</keyword>
  <keyword>hypofractionated radiotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

