<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01912183</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CEH - 126534</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01912183</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Family-centred E-health in Pediatric Weight Management: A Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Family-centred E-health in Pediatric Weight Management: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>McMaster University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research (CIHR)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>McMaster Children's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McMaster University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a pilot study to examine the feasibility of implementing an objective physical
      activity and sleep monitoring tool into a pediatric weight management program in conjunction
      with a personal health record (PHR) for children and their families. This feasibility study
      is intended to provide proof of concept in the incorporation of monitoring devices within the
      PHR for pediatric patients and their families. Additionally, the investigators will examine
      whether the PHR helps to empower pediatric patients, their families and the health care team
      to more effectively monitor the patient's behavior change. Participants will be randomized to
      receive, or not receive, augmented communication with the health care team between clinical
      in person visits.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Lifestyle behaviour changes represent the foundation of pediatric weight management and are
      usually promoted through individual and/or group-based counseling to encourage the adoption
      and maintenance of health lifestyle behaviours including nutritional intake, sleep and
      physical activity. Consensus on the need for comprehensive, behavioural interventions exists,
      but the nature of these interventions vary considerably. The intensity of the intervention
      (i.e. number of contact hours) may be a key determinant of efficacy, but little detail on the
      characteristic of these contact hours for optimal delivery is currently available.

      In this proof of concept study, we will evaluate the enhancement of behavioural change
      strategies utilizing technology that provides direct feedback on behaviour change. These
      devices will be incorporated into a PHR and supplemented with a related e-learning module.

      This study will examine the feasibility and perceived usefulness of incorporation of a
      personal electronic device to encourage behaviour change in children and youth enrolled in a
      weight management program. We intend to incorporate this device within an established PHR and
      supplement with evidence-based e-learning.

      This is a prospective, randomized pilot study of children and youth (ages 5-17 years)
      enrolled in a multidisciplinary pediatric weight management program (at McMaster Children's
      Hospital) for 4 months. This pilot study will include 10 children/youth and parent dyads from
      each of 3 age groups: 5-9 years, 10-13 years and 14-17 years. All families will utilize a
      personal electronic device that they can utilize with the individualized PHR. Participants
      will be randomized to receive, or not receive, regular communication with and access to the
      clinical team outside of their routine clinical visits, this will occur through a secure
      portal in the PHR.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility of the use of personal electronic devices for monitoring behavioural change in response to goal setting through a PHR will be evaluated and compared between the two groups by comparing: 1) percent of consenting families who successfully access the PHR, and 2) percent of children/youth who upload physical activity and sleep data for at least 4/7 days and 75% of weeks of the study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of the personal electronic device and PHR</measure>
    <time_frame>2 and 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Acceptability of the device to the family unit will be evaluated by collating the: 1) number of days per month the family uploads physical activity or sleep information, 2) number of times the family (in the randomized intervention group)interacts with the clinical team through the PHR and 3) number of times over the 4 month period that the family reviews the e-learning module.
Acceptability of the device and PHR to the child and parent will be ascertained separately via standardized questionnaire at 2 and 4 months after randomization.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of goal monitoring</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Acceptability of the method of monitoring goal achievement to the clinic staff will be evaluated by questionnaire at the end of the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of the utilization of the PHR and personal electronic device</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility of the utilization of the PHR and personal electronic device will be measured by examining the percent of eligible, consecutive clinic patients who agree to take part in the study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health education</measure>
    <time_frame>4 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Health Education Impact Questionnaire (heIQ) will be administered to evaluate the impact of the health education intervention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Pediatric Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Monitoring device in PHR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Both groups will receive routine clinical care in the pediatric weight management program at McMaster Children's Hospital. Children/youth in both groups will receive a physical activity and sleep monitor and access to their PHR. The Active Comparator group will not receive any feedback or communication outside of clinic visits from the clinical team regarding their goal progress.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Communication through PHR outside clinic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Both groups will receive routine clinical care in the pediatric weight management program at McMaster Children's Hospital. Children/youth in both groups will receive a physical activity and sleep monitor and access to their PHR. The experimental group will receive regular communication with /access to the clinical team through a secure portal within the PHR(i.e. 2 way communication, weekly feedback to the families on their goal progress).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Communication through PHR outside clinic</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Communication through PHR outside clinic</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Communication with clinic staff through PHR</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Monitoring device in PHR</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Monitoring device in PHR</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical activity and sleep monitor</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Monitoring device in PHR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Communication through PHR outside clinic</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PHR</intervention_name>
    <description>Access to their PHR</description>
    <arm_group_label>Monitoring device in PHR</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Communication through PHR outside clinic</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  children/youth between the ages of 5-17 years

          -  enrolled in pediatric weight management program at McMaster Children's Hospital

          -  provide informed written assent (child/youth)

          -  provision of informed written consent (parent/caregiver)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  no access to internet/home computer
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Katherine Morrison, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>McMaster University/McMaster Children's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pediatric Weight Management Clinic - McMaster Children's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamilton</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>L8N 3Z5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 26, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 30, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 31, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 6, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 6, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">April 7, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>McMaster University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Katherine Morrison</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor, Department of Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pediatric obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>e-learning</keyword>
  <keyword>personal health record</keyword>
  <keyword>personal electronic device</keyword>
  <keyword>pilot</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pediatric Obesity</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

