<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01910740</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NHMRC - 1042680</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01910740</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mobility in Older People</brief_title>
  <acronym>MOVE</acronym>
  <official_title>Optimising Rehabilitation Outcomes in Frail Older Adults: Effects of Increasing the Amount of Physical Activity</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>La Trobe University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Austin Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>La Trobe University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main aim of this study is to investigate whether increasing the amount of physical
      activity in frail older people during hospital based rehabilitation is associated with better
      mobility outcomes compared to usual care. A second aim is to investigate whether this
      physical activity intervention is associated with improvements in health related quality of
      life. Finally we plan to investigate whether increasing the amount of physical activity
      during rehabilitation is cost effective, measured from a health system perspective, compared
      with usual care.

      Older people receiving inpatient rehabilitation will be randomly assigned to an intervention
      group, who will receive extra physical activity on weekdays and weekends or a control group,
      who will receive additional activities based on social interaction. The activity sessions
      will be individualized to the particular participant. Both groups of people will be assessed
      at baseline, discharge from hospital and at 6 months following discharge. The intervention
      group will be provided with one or two extra sessions on weekdays and two extra sessions on
      weekends for the duration of their rehabilitation stay. To account for the extra
      physiotherapy time that the intervention group receives, the people in the control group will
      spend the same amount of time performing other activities, such as cards, board games or
      reading, whilst seated. To ensure the safety of the participants in this study, each physical
      activity session will be supervised by either a physiotherapist or allied health assistant.

      Hypothesis 1: The primary hypothesis is that, compared with usual care, increasing the amount
      of physical activity in frail older people during rehabilitation will lead to more optimal
      mobility at discharge, as measured by gait speed.

      Secondary hypotheses are that, compared with usual care, increasing the amount of physical
      activity during rehabilitation will:

      Hypothesis 2: lead to significantly greater improvements in mobility and function both at
      discharge and six months following discharge.

      Hypothesis 3: lead to better quality of life six months following hospital discharge,
      measured using the EuroQol Health (EQ5D) Questionnaire and the EuroQol-Visual Analogue Scale
      (EQ-VAS).

      Hypothesis 4: be cost effective compared to usual care
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Gait Velocity</measure>
    <time_frame>Discharge (Average Duration of Hospital Stay is 3 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>Gait velocity will be measured using the 6 metre walk test</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gait Velocity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 Months Follow Up (post discharge)</time_frame>
    <description>Gait velocity will be measured using the 6 metre walk test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">198</enrollment>
  <condition>Frail Older People Undergoing Inpatient Rehabilitation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Physical Activity</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in the Enhanced Physical Activity group will receive a program of enhanced physical activity in addition to the usual care.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Usual Care group will receive usual therapy provided by a multidisciplinary team and social interaction.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Enhanced Physical Activity</intervention_name>
    <description>Individually tailored programs focused on increasing the amount of time participants spend performing mobility activities, particularly standing and walking in the late afternoons and evenings and on weekends. These participants will be provided with one or two extra sessions on weekdays and two extra sessions on weekend days for the duration of their rehabilitation stay.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Physical Activity</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care</intervention_name>
    <description>Therapy provided by a multidisciplinary team which includes physiotherapy and occupational therapy on weekdays with other allied health input (eg speech pathology, social work) as indicated. Medical and nursing care is also provided seven days a week.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Enhanced Physical Activity</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Social Interaction</intervention_name>
    <description>To control for the extra hours of physical activity that the experimental group receives, participants in the control group shall have additional activities such as card and board games, conversation or reading as well as upper limb exercises and other physical activities that have minimal impact on ambulant mobility.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  over 60 years of age

          -  a goal of admission is to 'improve weight-bearing mobility or improve walking' as
             determined by either the admission referral or the treating therapist

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  specific medical restrictions that limit mobilisation (e.g. non weight bearing)

          -  if already enrolled in a different Randomised Controlled Trial

          -  previously enrolled in the current trial

          -  the primary reason for admission is awaiting a residential care placement

          -  the primary reason for admission is for carer training
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Meg Morris, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>La Trobe University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Heidelberg Repatriation Hospital, Austin Health</name>
      <address>
        <city>Heidelberg</city>
        <state>Victoria</state>
        <zip>3084</zip>
        <country>Australia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Australia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 22, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 29, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 30, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 31, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 31, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 1, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>La Trobe University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Meg Morris</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor Meg Morris</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Randomized Controlled Trial</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise Movement Techniques</keyword>
  <keyword>Frail Elderly</keyword>
  <keyword>Gait</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

