<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01915706</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00047845</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01915706</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Scheduled Ripcord Removal on the Outcomes of Baerveldt 350 Implants</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Effect of Scheduled Ripcord Removal on the Outcomes of Baerveldt 350 Implants</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the post-operative complication rates and surgical
      outcomes in patients with a Baerveldt 350 implant following scheduled rip-cord removal in
      clinic at post-operative week 3 versus spontaneous tube opening. Patients age 18 or greater
      with uncontrolled glaucoma and scheduled to undergo their first superotemporal Baerveldt 350
      implant will be recruited and randomized at the time of enrollment to either scheduled
      ripcord removal at post-operative week 3 or no ripcord removal. Incidence of complications
      will be documented and compared between the 2 groups. The final intraocular pressure control
      between the 2 groups will also be compared in a secondary outcome analysis. This study will
      help to establish post-operative management guidelines to minimize complications and improve
      intraocular pressure lowering success following Baerveldt 350 implantation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 19, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 19, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of post-operative complications</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of complications (including but not limited to shallowing of the anterior chamber, hypotony, choroidal effusion and choroidal hemorrhage) will be documented and compared between the 2 groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of successful intraocular pressure control</measure>
    <time_frame>Post-operative month 6</time_frame>
    <description>Final intraocular pressure at post-operative month 6 will be assessed and incidence of successful intraocular pressure control will be compared. Successful intraocular pressure control is defined as unqualified when the intraocular pressure is between 6 and 18 mmHg or a 25% reduction from the pre-surgical intraocular pressure without medication and qualified when pressure-lowering therapies are required to maintain intraocular pressure at that level.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">81</enrollment>
  <condition>Glaucoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Observation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to observation will be observed during the post-operative period for spontaneous Baerveldt-350 tube opening. The ripcord will not be removed unless deemed medically necessary by the study physician.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ripcord removal</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized to intervention will have their ripcords removed in clinic at post-operative week 3.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Ripcord removal</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients randomized to intervention will have their ripcords removed in clinic at post-operative week 3. Ripcord removal will be performed by study PI at the slit lamp with standard of care sterile technique and topical/local anesthesia. Patients will be monitored 30 minutes following ripcord removal for intraocular pressure as well as complications.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ripcord removal</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Men or women aged 18 years and older at screening. There is no upper age limit.

          -  Inadequately controlled glaucoma refractory to maximum therapy

          -  Suitable candidate for Baerveldt-350 implant in the superotemporal quadrant in the
             study eye, which the physician deems as medically necessary.

          -  Capable and willing to provide consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable or unwilling to provide consent

          -  Any previous ocular surgery other than cataract extraction or trabeculectomy

          -  Any previous ocular surgeries in the study eye preventing placement of the
             Baerveldt-350 implant in the superotemporal quadrant

          -  Any abnormality other than glaucoma in the study eye that could affect tonometry.

          -  Presence or history of any abnormality or disorder that could interfere with the study
             procedure or prevent the successful completion of the study.

          -  Monocularity (where best corrected visual acuity in the non-operative eye is worse
             than 20/200)

          -  Any significant unstable cardiovascular, hepatic, renal, respiratory,
             gastrointestinal, endocrine, immunologic, dermatologic, hematologic, neurologic, or
             psychiatric disease.

          -  Known pregnant or breastfeeding women
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leon Herndon, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Duke University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Duke Eye Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27710</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 31, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 1, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 5, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 28, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 28, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Glaucoma drainage device</keyword>
  <keyword>Baerveldt 350</keyword>
  <keyword>Ripcord</keyword>
  <keyword>Complications</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

