<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01911117</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>A-ER-102-080</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01911117</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the Correction of Non-invasive Estimated Continuous Cardiac Output in Cardiac Surgical Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluating the Correction of Non-invasive Estimated Continuous Cardiac Output in Cardiac Surgical Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In one previous study, esCCO was compared with continuous thermodilution CO (TDCO),
      measurements in 36 postoperative cardiac surgery patients, showing a bias (mean difference)
      of -0.06 and a precision (1 SD) of 0.82 L/min. In addition, esCCO was compared with
      intermittent bolus TDCO, showing a correlation coefficient of 0.82 (P &lt; 0.001, n = 24), a
      bias of -0.63, and a precision of 1.01 L/min (n = 119). The results of clinical use of esCCO
      suggest that its measurement accuracy is comparable to the thermodilution method in general
      population. However, no any intraoperative comparison for cardiac surgery patients was
      reported before. This study is designed for the accuracy in the patients undergoing cardiac
      surgery.

      Specific aims:

        1. To investigate the correlation of esCCO and the traditional CO measurement in cardiac
           surgical patients.

        2. To investigate the intraoperative t accuracy of time point between ecCCO and traditional
           CO measurement for patients undergoing bypass cardiac surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Determination of cardiac output (CO) is often desirable for assessing a patient's hemodynamic
      condition during the surgery requiring cardiopulmonary bypass. However, the current methods
      of continuous CO measurement are still based on invasive technique, such as thermodilution
      via pulmonary artery catheter (Swan-Ganz), transpulmonary thermodilution via PiCCO kit, or
      pulse contour analysis via arterial line (FloTrac or PiCCO). Noninvasive CO measurement to
      all patients is currently impractical, because most measurement methods available are based
      on invasive techniques. However, two developing trends for this kind of monitor had occurred.
      There are one shifting toward noninvasive technologies and the other trend toward continuous
      measurement rather than intermittent measurement. Therefore, continuous CO (CCO) monitoring
      with less invasive would be desirable.

      The pulse contour method is one of the technologies used for min-invasive monitoring of CO.
      It is based on the relationship between arterial blood pressure and stroke volume and has
      been greatly improved since early 1950s. Arterial waveform-based CO is frequently used in
      current medical practice, but it still requires arterial puncture. Pulse wave transit time
      has been proven to have good correlation with stroke volume. Pulse wave transit time consists
      of a pre-ejection period, pulse wave transit time through the artery, and pulse wave transit
      time through the peripheral arteries, which compensates for the effect of changes in systemic
      vascular resistance (SVR). Based on the relationship between pulse wave transit time and
      stroke volume, the noninvasive device, estimated CCO (esCCO), via measuring electrocardiogram
      (ECG), pulse oximeter wave, and arterial blood pressure had been developed by Sugo et al.. It
      has the great advantage to simplify CO measurement by combining the results of these familiar
      noninvasive monitoring techniques. Thus, it may be a useful technique for optimizing medical
      treatment.

      In one previous study, esCCO was compared with continuous thermodilution CO (TDCO),
      measurements in 36 postoperative cardiac surgery patients, showing a bias (mean difference)
      of -0.06 and a precision (1 SD) of 0.82 L/min. In addition, esCCO was compared with
      intermittent bolus TDCO, showing a correlation coefficient of 0.82 (P &lt; 0.001, n = 24), a
      bias of -0.63, and a precision of 1.01 L/min (n = 119). The results of clinical use of esCCO
      suggest that its measurement accuracy is comparable to the thermodilution method in general
      population. However, no any intraoperative comparison for cardiac surgery patients was
      reported before. This study is designed for the accuracy in the patients undergoing cardiac
      surgery.

      Specific aims

        1. To investigate the correlation of esCCO and the traditional CO measurement in cardiac
           surgical patients.

        2. To investigate the intraoperative t accuracy of time point between ecCCO and traditional
           CO measurement for patients undergoing bypass cardiac surgery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    No man power
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>June 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The correlation of esCCO and the traditional CO measurement in cardiac surgical patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison Between esCCO and Thermodilution Measurements of CO for cardiac surgical patients.
Check the accuracy of esCCO in cardiac surgical patients. It should be well correlated before bypass but will be inaccurate when partial bypass once start. When bypass procedure start to rewarm, it will be accurate initially but gradually well correlated within temperature corrected or heart function become normal again.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiac Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cardiac Surgical Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who undergo cardiac surgery will be included in this study.
Patients undergo cardiac surgery and are over 18 years of age.
Patients need bypass machine for their cardiac surgery and traditional CO measurement.
Patients who are competent to understand the study and provide written informed consent and participate in outcome measurements.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who undergo cardiac surgery will be included in this study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients undergo cardiac surgery and are over 18 years of age.

          2. Patients need bypass machine for their cardiac surgery and traditional CO measurement.

          3. Patients who are competent to understand the study and provide written informed
             consent and participate in outcome measurements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients are over 75 years of age. Patients are unable to read or write the informed
             consent, any condition that could interfere with the interpretation of outcome
             assessments, pregnant or lactating women. Patient with marked arrhythmias, those
             preoperatively receiving treatment with intra-aortic balloon bump (IABP) will also not
             be included.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yen-Chin Liu, Doctor</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Anesthesiology, National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Cheng Kung University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tainan City</city>
        <state>Shengli Rd</state>
        <zip>701</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 26, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 26, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 30, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>National Cheng-Kung University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Yen Chin Liu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Visiting Staff, Department of Anesthesiology Chief</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

