<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01911000</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-06-013-003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01911000</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effectiveness and Safety of the Simultaneous Radiotherapy and Hyperthermia After Transarterial Chemoembolization in Hepatocellular Carcinoma Patients Combined With Portal Vein Tumor Thrombosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effectiveness and Safety of the Simultaneous Radiotherapy and Hyperthermia After Transarterial Chemoembolization in Hepatocellular Carcinoma Patients Combined With Portal Vein Tumor Thrombosis: Prospective Phase II Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Samsung Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Samsung Medical Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The presence of portal vein tumor thrombosis (PVTT)in patients with HCC is one of the most
      significant prognostic factors for poor prognosis, without treatment, their survival is less
      than 3 months. In the HCC patients who combined with PVTT, RT showed 50% of local control and
      about 10 months survival duration. Despite the standard treatment of the HCC combined with
      PVTT is sorafenib, but Korean Liver Cancer Study Group (KLCSG) recommend RT as an option in
      those patients. Investigators previously reported the retrospective study that the scheduled
      interval TACE followed by RT for HCC combined with PVTT and 60% of the patients showed
      objective response without significant elevation of complication. It is reported that
      hyperthermia considered as the most valuable radiosensitizer in cancer treatment,
      theoretically. Based on those studies, we start this prospective study to evaluate the
      objective response and adverse event in the combination treatment of RT and hyperthermia
      after Transarterial chemoembolization (TACE) in the unresectable HCC patients who combined
      with PVTT.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1.1 Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) and standard treatment HCC is the third most common cause
      of cancer death globally. It is also the second cause of cancer mortality in Korea, despite
      the incidence of HCC was fifth. The most important cause of this discrepancy is connected
      with the fact that the significant portion of the HCC is detected as unresectable status. At
      the point of HCC diagnosis, only 30% of the patients could receive standard curative
      treatment, like resection, liver transplantation, and radiofrequency ablation (RFA), TACE has
      been shown in randomized trials to improve survival compared with symptomatic therapy alone,
      in the patients without macrovascular involvement, extrahepatic disease and tumor related
      symptoms. However, in the recent review of TACE, TACE might be contraindicate or not
      recommended in the patients who showed vascular tumor invasion, more than 10 cm size, poor
      portal blood flow and/or repeated poor response.

      1.2 HCC with PVTT The presence of PVTT in patients with HCC is one of the most significant
      prognostic factors for poor prognosis, without treatment, their survival is less than 3
      months. Recently, Sorafenib, which is one of the target agents, showed survival advantage on
      unresectable HCC patients in two randomized study. In those study, sorafenib improved
      approximately three month overall survival increment, however, the median survival duration
      was only 10.7 months in experiment group (received sorafenib), and even 6.5 months in
      Asian-Pacific trial. Additionally, the possibility that sorafenib effect could be reduced in
      the patients had hepatitis B virus (HBV) was suggested in the subgroup analysis.

      1.3 Radiation therapy (RT) for the HCC The use of RT in HCC is increased with the radiation
      technological advances. In the unresectable patients, RT showed 50 to 60% response rate with
      the dose response relationship. Especially, in the HCC patients who combined with PVTT, RT
      showed 50% of local control and about 10 months survival duration. Despite the standard
      treatment of the HCC combined with PVTT is sorafenib, but Korean Liver Cancer Study Group
      (KLCSG) recommend RT as an option in those patients.

      Investigators previously reported the retrospective study that the scheduled interval TACE
      followed by RT for HCC combined with PVTT and 60% of the patients showed objective response
      without significant elevation of complication.

      1.4 Hyperthermia It is reported that hyperthermia is effective in S phase, Low partial oxygen
      pressure (pO2), acidic condition, and low perfusion site which are known as radio-resistant.
      Because of these characteristics, it considered as the most valuable radiosensitizer in
      cancer treatment, theoretically. Furthermore ,mild hyperthermia (41 to 41.5 ºC) can promote
      tumor reoxygenation.

      1.5 Purpose of the study Based on those studies, we start this prospective study to evaluate
      the objective response and adverse event in the combination treatment of RT and hyperthermia
      after TACE in the unresectable HCC patients who combined with PVTT.

      2. Hypothesis and sample size Several prospective trials showed 50% to 60% of objective
      response rate when conventional RT was administered for HCC with PVTT, thus we determined the
      objective response rate of conventional RT as 60%. We expect additional 20% increase of the
      local progression free rate than conventional RT when treated with combined RT and
      hyperthermia for HCC with PVTT.

      To determine sample size, we designed to have 80% power to detect an absolute difference of
      20% points in objective response rate between combined RT and hyperthermia and conventional
      RT, with a two-sided alpha level of 0.05. A total of 87 patients are required for this study
      considering a drop-out rate of 10%.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hyperthermia effect and averse event in RT for HCC with PVTT</measure>
    <time_frame>Radiologic response and adverse event will be evaluated at 3 month after treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>Modified response evaluation criteria in solid tumor(mRECIST) will be used. Objective response was defined as complete and partial response. The common terminology criteria for adverse events (CTCAE version 4.0) will be used to evaluate the adverse events.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hyperthermia effect on local progression free survival rate</measure>
    <time_frame>The liver CT or MRI will be examined at 3 month after treatment and used to determine the response and presence of progression.</time_frame>
    <description>The liver CT or MRI will be examined at 1, 3 month after treatment, after that 3 month follow-up with above images and used to determine the presence of local progression. Progression free survival will be measured from the date of RT start to the date of local progression recognition or last follow up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To measure the time to local tumor progression</measure>
    <time_frame>The liver CT or MRI will be examined at 3 month after treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>The liver CT or MRI will be examined at 1, 3 month after treatment, after that 3 month follow-up with above images and used to determine the presence of local progression. Time to local tumor progression will be measured from the date of RT start to the date of local progression recognition.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To measure the overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>First follow up will be at 1 month after treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>he follow up will be at 1, 3 month after treatment, after that every 3 month. Overall survival will be measured from the date of RT start to the date of death or last follow up visit.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life (QoL) change before and after treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>QoL will be assessed before, 1, 3, 6 months after RT and compared each other.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To validate of the prognostic index of portal vein tumor thrombosis in HCC (PITH) staging system</measure>
    <time_frame>The liver CT or MRI will be examined at 3 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival outcome will be used to validate PITH staging system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate RT response prediction probability by diffusion-weighted (DW) MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>DW MRI will be evaluated at 1 month after treatment.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">69</enrollment>
  <condition>Carcinoma. Hepatocellular</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>RTHT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>RT and hyperthermia after TACE in the unresectable HCC patients who combined with PVTT</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RT and hyperthermia after TACE</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>RTHT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients must have a diagnosis of HCC by at least one criterion listed below (korean
             liver cancer study group (KLCSG) guideline 2009) 1.1 Pathologically (histologically or
             cytologically) proven diagnosis of HCC 1.2 Liver nodule in high risk group 1.2.1 If
             alpha fetoprotein (AFP) ≥200 ng/mL , ≥ 1 typical HCC enhancing pattern on dynamic
             contrast enhanced CT or MRI 1.2.2 If AFP&lt;200 ng/mL, ≥2 typical HCC enhancing pattern
             on dynamic contrast enhanced CT, MRI, and angiography 1.3 ≥ 2 cm nodule in liver
             cirrhosis (LC), ≥ 1 typical HCC enhancing pattern on dynamic contrast enhanced CT or
             MRI

          2. Patients must have a diagnosis of PVTT 2.1 Early arterial enhancement and delayed
             washout on multiphasic CT or MRI

          3. Eastern cooperative oncology group performance status 0 1 2

          4. Age ≥ 20

          5. Unsuitable for resection or transplant or RFA

          6. Unsuitable for or refractory to TACE or drug eluting beads (DEB)

          7. Agreement of study-specific informed consent

          8. Assessment by radiation oncologist and medical oncologist or hepatologist within 28
             days prior to study entry?

          9. Child-Pugh score A-B within 7 days prior to study entry

         10. Normal liver (Liver minus gross tumor volume) ≥ 700 cc

         11. Blood work requirements

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) ≥ 1,500 /mm3, Platelet ≥ 70,000/mm3, Hgb ≥ 8 g/dl

               -  Liver function test (LFT): Total bilirubin&lt;3.0 mg/dL, International normalized
                  ratio(INR) &lt; 1.7, Albumin ≥ 2.8g/dL, Aspartate aminotransferase (AST)/Alanine
                  aminotransferase (ALT)&lt; 6 X normal

               -  Serum creatinine &lt; 1.5 X normal, or creatinine clearance ≥ 60 mL/min

         12. Male, consent contraception at least 6 months

         13. Childbearing potential woman, consent contraception at least 6 months

         14. Life expectancy more than 12 weeks

         15. Stable breathing more than 5 minutes

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Complete obstruction of main portal vein

          2. Pregnant and/or breastfeeding woman

          3. Previous upper abdominal RT history

          4. Uncontrolled active co-morbidity

          5. Another primary cancer history within 2 years

          6. Uncontrolled ascites or hepatic encephalopathy

          7. Connective tissue disease which known as radiation hypersensitivity

          8. Uncontrolled moderate to severe gastroduodenal ulcer or esophagogastric varices
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hee Chul Park, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Samsung Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Samsung Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <zip>135-710</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 22, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 25, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 30, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 19, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 19, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 22, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thrombosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fever</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

