<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01919827</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CMM/FPI</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01919827</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of Autologous Mesenchymal Stem Cells to Treat Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis</brief_title>
  <acronym>CMM/FPI</acronym>
  <official_title>Treatment of Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis With Bone Marrow Derived Mesenchymal Stem Cells</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Clinica Universidad de Navarra, Universidad de Navarra</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Clinica Universidad de Navarra, Universidad de Navarra</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Clinical Trial Phase I, open, multicentric, non randomized, study with escalating doses, to
      evaluate the safety and feasibility of treatment with mesenchymal stem cells in patients with
      diagnosis of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis.

      Primary endpoint: The aim is to evaluate the safety and feasibility of the endobronchial
      administration of mesenchymal autolog stem cells derived from bone marrow (BM-MSC)in patients
      with mild-to-moderate idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis.

      Secondary endpoint:Assess the possible effect of the infusion of BM-MSC in stopping the fall
      of pulmonary function in patients with mild-to-moderate idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 1, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 1, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with adverse side effects.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of participants with adverse side effects, and according to the level of severity:
Low level: Increase in cough, fever or skin reactions
Medium level: Infections not requiring hospital admission, mild alterations of renal or liver function
High level: Death or major side effects requiring hospitalization:
Worsening dyspnea with &gt;=10% reduction in forced vital capacity, reduction in arterial pressure oxygen &gt;= 10 mmHg and radiology progression between 3 months separated visits.
Need for hospitalization due to respiratory failure requiring mechanical ventilation, worsening in gases exchange or lung infection.
Carcinogenesis at 12 months after the endobronchial infusion of mesenchymal stem cells.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of the infusion of mesenchymal stem cells in stopping the fall in pulmonary function in patients with mild to moderate IPF</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Measures of efficacy:
Fall in forced vital capacity as a continuous variable
Progression of the disease defined by: Death, need for transplantation or deterioration in pulmonary function defined by fall in forced vital capacity (FVC) &gt; 10% or in lung diffusion capacity (DLCO) &gt; 15%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">17</enrollment>
  <condition>Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MSC endobronchial infusion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endobronchial infusion of adult mesenchymal stem cells</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>MSC endobronchial infusion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Autologous mesenchymal stem cells derived from bone marrow</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>MSC endobronchial infusion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Capacity for signing informing consent and express the willing to fulfill all the
             requirements of the study protocol during the study.

          2. The patients should be, in the researcher opinion, capable to fulfill all the
             requirements of the trial.

          3. Male or female patients, 30 to 80 years old, inclusive.

          4. Diagnosis of idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis according to the following criteria, based
             on the ATS/ERS Guidelines:

               1. Definite or probable usual interstitial pneumonia confirmed by surgical lung
                  biopsy.

               2. In the absence of surgical lung biopsy, all the following:

             i. High resolution CT (HRCT) showing definite findings for idiopathic pulmonary
             fibrosis (FPI): bibasal reticular opacities with minimal ground glass opacities.

             ii. Absence of other known causes of FPI including toxicity from drugs, environmental
             exposure or connective tissue diseases.

             iii. Pulmonary function tests showing ventilatory restrictive pattern and/or impaired
             gas exchange (FVC and/or DLCO &lt;90% of predicted)

          5. FVC ≥ 50% of predicted value with ratio of FEV1 to FVC ≥ 0.70.

          6. DLco (corrected for hemoglobin) ≥ 35% predicted value.

          7. Capability of performing a 6 minutes walk test at the time of inclusion.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Any of the following:

          1. Current pregnancy or lactation.

          2. Findings that are diagnostic of an interstitial pneumonia or restrictive respiratory
             disease condition other than UIP.

          3. Obstructive pulmonary disease defined by FEV1/FVC &lt; 0,7 or significant emphysema on
             HRCT.

          4. Evidence of sustained improvement in FPI defined by improvement of respiratory
             function tests before inclusion, observed in &gt;=2 test over the year prior to
             inclusion.

          5. Active or recent respiratory infection (less than 60 days before inclusion) or history
             of frequent exacerbations of IPF from an infectious cause (more than 2/year over the
             last 2 years)

          6. Hospitalization in the 60 days prior to inclusion due to acute exacerbation of IPF.

          7. Chronic cardiac failure (functional class NYHA III/IV) or left ventricular ejection
             fraction &lt; 25%.

          8. Chronically receiving corticosteroid more than 10 mg of prednisone or equivalent,
             immunosuppressors or antifibrotic agents, including pirfenidone, D-penicillamine,
             colchicine, ciclosporin A, TNF-alpha antagonists, imatinib, IFN-gamma, azathioprine,
             cyclophosphamide, within the 30 days prior to inclusion.

          9. The patient requires hemodialysis, peritoneal dialysis or hemofiltration.

         10. History of malignancy, with the exception of skin squamous or basocellular carcinoma
             or cervix in situ carcinoma treated successfully.

         11. History of ethanol abuse within the year prior to inclusion

         12. The patient is participating in a clinical trial which includes other drugs or
             research products within the 28 days prior to baseline assessment.

         13. Comorbidities limiting life expectancy to less than 12 months from the baseline
             assessment.

         14. Medical or psychiatric condition serious or active which might interfere with the
             treatment of study, assessment or protocol fulfillment.

         15. Positive test for HBsAg, HCV antibody, syphilis screening essays, or HIV antibody at
             screening.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Servicio de Neumología, Clínica Universidad de Navarra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pamplona</city>
        <state>Navarra</state>
        <zip>31008 Pamplona</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Servicio de Neumología. Hospital Universitario de Salamanaca</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salamanca</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 1, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 6, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 9, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Stem cells</keyword>
  <keyword>Mesenchymal stem cells</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Idiopathic Pulmonary Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Idiopathic Interstitial Pneumonias</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

