<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00914108</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>X03-10-072R</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00914108</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Severe Intrauterine Growth Retardation: Developmental Newborn Intensive Care Unit (NICU) Care</brief_title>
  <official_title>Family-Centered Neuropsychoeducational In-NICU Intervention for Preterm Infants With Severe Intrauterine Growth Retardation and for Their Families</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Boston Children’s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Boston Children’s Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to learn more about the development of small for gestational age
      (SGA) preterm infants and whether focusing on the infant's behavior has a positive effect on
      outcome. The study hypotheses state: 1) High risk severely SGA preterm infants will profit
      from detailed neuropsychological assessment, psychoeducational recommendations and practical
      guidance for caregiving, as well as formal educational and emotional support for the family
      and the professional care team. 2) Neuropsychological education and guidance for
      community-based early intervention providers caring for SGA preterm infants after their
      discharge is effective in promoting improved outcome.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The preterm infant who is not only born early but also did not grow well in the womb is at
      double jeopardy for developmental disabilities. The literature indicates that the fetus who
      has not gained weight properly nor is showing expected head growth in the womb [symmetrical
      intrauterine growth retardation (IUGR) or small for gestational age (SGA) status] will not
      only require significantly longer stays in the newborn intensive care unit (NICU) and grow
      more poorly than the appropriately grown prematurely born infant, but will also show
      significant disabilities later on in terms of fine and gross motor skills, cognitive function
      activity, language abilities, abstract reasoning, concentration, attention, mood and
      temperament. IUGR exerts an independent adverse effect on the developmental outcome of
      preterm infants.

      Given the importance of the last 4 months of gestation and the first 2 years post term for
      brain growth and development, and given the relationship between cerebral development and
      behavior which is a two-way street and a dynamic feedback system, the particular
      vulnerability of SGA children to environmental factors indicates that there are grounds for
      the hypothesis that appropriate support and intervention for severely SGA preterm infants and
      their families might ameliorate dysfunction.

      The general purpose of the proposed project is to develop and test a model of ameliorative
      neuropsychoeducational intervention in the NICU in support of the developmental outcome of
      severely SGA preterm infants and their families. The specific hypotheses to be tested are as
      follows:

        1. High risk severely SGA preterm infants cared for in the NICU with the support of a
           neuropsychoeducational model of intervention will show:

             1. At 2 weeks post term, more well-regulated autonomic, motor, state organizational
                and attentional functioning

             2. At 9 and 24 months post term:

                  -  More well-regulated autonomic and visceral functioning with less colic and
                     improved eating patterns and weight gain

                  -  More well-regulated motor system performance

                  -  More well-regulated state organization, including sleep and awake organization

                  -  More well-regulated cognitive and attentional functioning in various domains,
                     including visual-motor integration, spatial planning, attentional planning,
                     expressive and receptive language function, abstract verbal reasoning, short
                     term memory and continuous performance regulation

                  -  More well-regulated executive function capacities

                  -  More well-regulated affective emotional functioning

        2. Parents whose infants receive the support of a neuropsychoeducational model of care will
           show:

             1. At 2 weeks, 9 and 24 months post term, enhanced appreciation of their infant as an
                individual

             2. At 9 and 24 months post term, more sensitively attuned input in support of their
                child's functioning, more competent parenting strategies, and a greater sense of
                effectiveness in parenting the child.

      The population will consist of severely small for gestational age preterm infants admitted to
      the NICU and randomly assigned to a control and experimental group.

      Effectiveness of the experimental treatment for the experimental group will be tested at
      three systematic outcome points in various domains. The domains assessed include (1) medical
      outcome; (2) neurobehavioral outcome; (3) neuroelectrophysiological outcome; and (4) family
      outcome. The outcome points for infant and family are 2 weeks, 9 and 24 months after expected
      due date.

      The study is expected to demonstrate intervention effectiveness in improving IUGR preterm
      infants' neurodevelopment. It is anticipated that the results will set the stage for a model
      of caregiving and intervention that lives up to the mandate that every child is entitled to
      an environment, care and education appropriate to his or her specific needs. The model can
      then be used in other nurseries to provide improved outcome for preterm populations.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 1996</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2002</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2000</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evidence of improved neurodevelopmental and neurophysiological outcome as assessed with: Assessment of Preterm Infants' Behavior (APIB) and electrophysiological (EEG) assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>At 2 weeks , 9 months and 24 months corrected age</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Intrauterine Growth Retardation</condition>
  <condition>Prematurity</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Newborn Individualized Developmental Care</intervention_name>
    <description>The developmental care model aims to create a relationship-based developmentally supportive care environment for the preterm infant and family. The theory proposes that care implementation that takes into account infants' thresholds of disorganization is most supportive of long term outcome. Specifically, the intervention consisted of weekly neurobehavioral observations and reports of the experimental group infants' behavior with suggestions for parents and staff in ways to support each infant's development. The developmental specialists observed each infant's behavior throughout hospitalization and to 2 weeks corrected age and formulated descriptive neurobehavioral reports with suggestions to structure caregiving procedures adapted to the infant's sleep/wake cycle and in support of the infant's well-regulated behavioral balance. Parents were supported to care for their infant, encouraged to nurse and hold their infant skin-to-skin, and to cradle them during stressful procedures.</description>
    <other_name>NIDCAP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Inborn at the Brigham and Women's Hospital

          -  Gestational age &lt; 36 weeks

          -  Birthweight &lt; 5th percentile

          -  Head circumference at birth &lt; 5th percentile

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Presence of major chromosomal or congenital anomalies (Down's, Turner's, Klinefelter's
             Syndrome, etc.)

          -  Presence of major congenital infections (HIV, TORCH)

          -  Presence of significant prenatal focal brain lesions (intrauterine infarcts; cystic
             changes, etc.)

          -  Presence of major maternal illness (uncontrolled diabetes, active seizure disorder
             requiring medication during pregnancy, renal transplant), mental and/or emotional
             impairment (including heroin addiction and documented alcoholism)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>36 Weeks</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Heidelise Als, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Boston Children’s Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's Hospital Boston</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 3, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 3, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 4, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 3, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 3, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 4, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Heidelise Als, PhD</name_title>
    <organization>Children's Hospital Boston</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Preterm Infants</keyword>
  <keyword>Developmental Care</keyword>
  <keyword>NIDCAP</keyword>
  <keyword>Intrauterine Growth Restriction</keyword>
  <keyword>APIB</keyword>
  <keyword>EEG</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurobehavior</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fetal Growth Retardation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

