<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00916890</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PT-SM-1-Op-Cancer</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00916890</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Study About Clinical and Pharmacogenetic Safety of Opioid Use for Chronic Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>Chronic Administration of Opioids in Cancer Chronic Pain:an Open Prospective Study on Efficacy, Safety and Pharmacogenetic Factors Influence.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>IRCCS Policlinico S. Matteo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Pavia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>IRCCS Policlinico S. Matteo</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aim of this project is to customize the choice of the strong opioid in the treatment of
      cancer chronic pain through the identification of patient clinical history and pain
      characteristics, moreover in the analysis the investigators will also correlate the clinical
      efficacy and safety of opioid treatment with pharmacokinetic and pharmacogenetic patterns in
      order to identify variables able to predict the efficacy of the treatment or the patient
      susceptibility towards a specific treatment.

      Furthermore with this study the investigators want to identify the pharmacogenomic
      characterization responsible for pharmacokinetic variability in the conversion between
      morphine and other opioids, in order to validate the currently available conversion tables
      from a pharmacokinetic viewpoint, estimating the influence of the most common genetic
      polymorphisms, and if this characterization could be useful and cost-effective. This study
      will also focus on the specific clinical-pharmacological response in the elderly and between
      male and female and on the interactions between opioids and those anticonvulsant and
      antidepressant drugs routinely used in the pain therapy (study of pharmacovigilance).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pain continues to be a major problem in patients with cancer, affecting 25% to 30% of
      patients with recently diagnosed cancers. The incidence of pain in advanced stages of cancer
      approaches 70% to 80%. There are a number of reasons that patients with cancer experience
      chronic pain either related to the disease itself or to its treatment.

      Cancer can spread by metastasis or direct invasion, and 90% of patients with metastasis to
      osseous structures report pain. Patients with cancer can have neuropathic pain due to direct
      compression of nerves or plexus or spinal cord involvement.

      Inadequate treatment and undertreatment are associated with increased pain scores, decreased
      functional ability, and increased depression and anxiety.

      Opioid administration though proven to be effective still meets with resistance from both
      healthcare operators, who are seldom willing to prescribe these drugs, and patients, who tend
      to not take them because of many false beliefs still related to opioids.

      It is well demonstrated by the literature that opioids are effective in controlling both
      acute and chronic pain of nociceptive and/or neuropathic origin. Switching type of opioid
      and/or administration routes (e.g., from oral to neuraxial) is also known to be an important
      factor in long-term treatment: appropriate conversion tables elucidating drug equipotence and
      different potency in base of administration route for the different opioids currently
      available have therefore been devised and validated in the clinical setting.

      There have been several attempts to define guidelines for treatment protocols and even recent
      meta-analyses indicate that morphine should remain the gold standard. However, a general
      consensus is still lacking, as opioid management depends not only on the type and cause of
      pain, but also on the patient's history, the pain characteristics and genetic patterns.
      Which, if any, is the best opioid, in relation with previous characters, to start systemic
      treatment remains therefore debated. The different effects that different opioids have on
      spinal cord sensitization as a result of continuous peripheral nociceptive stimulus in long
      term administration have also been partially investigated.

      Current pharmacogenetic publications analyze the pharmacokinetic behavior of opioids in
      short-term administration, but studies are still lacking on how the pharmacokinetics and
      analgesic effect vary after repeated administrations of opioids, especially through direct
      comparison with clinical response. Genetic studies showed differences in the results of
      opioid treatment related to the variability of the genes that have a role in the
      pharmacodynamic and pharmacokinetics of opioids. Regardless these studies, the literature has
      not yet investigated how quantitative and qualitative variability of gene products can
      influence the efficacy or the toxicity of a specific opioid treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    difficulties in patients enrolment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>February 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To identify the drug with the best clinical-pharmacological safety-efficacy profile among the four opioids: oral extended-release morphine, oral extended-release oxycodone, transdermal fentanyl and transdermal buprenorphine.</measure>
    <time_frame>15 days after randomization (Reduction of at least 40% of median daily pain, on a NRS)</time_frame>
    <description>We will define a treatment effective if it will produce a mean reduction of NRS values at least of 40% than basal values. Among all effective treatments, we will identify the best as the one that will have a reduction of NRS to a value of 4 or less in 90% of patients compared to the 70% of the others treatments. To evaluate pharmacological safety the plasma concentrations of the drugs and their metabolites will be measured. We will branch patients population in 3 groups to evaluate the correlation between clinical-pharmacological response and genetics (responder,partially and not responder)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pharmacokinetic of opioids and of their metabolites during long-term administration; correlation between specific genotypes and clinical response or the clinical/pharmacological susceptibility to side-effects on administration of a specific opioid.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months (each patient will be followed for 6 month after enrollment with clinical/pharmacological evaluations once a month and if inefficacy, tolerance or side effects)</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison of plasma levels of opioids and of their metabolites in &quot;responder&quot; patients (clinical effectiveness without side effects), &quot;partially responders&quot; patients (clinical effectiveness without side effects but taking not more than 2 rescue doses per day), and in &quot;non responder&quot; patients (3 groups: clinical un-efficacy, side-effects, tolerance and/or opioid induced hyperalgesia).Evaluation of the correlation between the polymorphisms studied and clinical response; the frequency of allelic variants of interest will be compared in &quot;responder&quot;, &quot;partially responder&quot; and &quot;non responder&quot;.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">320</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral extended-release morphine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oral extended-release oxycodone</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Transdermal fentanyl</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Transdermal buprenorphine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Morphine</intervention_name>
    <description>After a titration phase with fast-release oral morphine, once the optimal dosage (no side effects and less than two rescue doses per day) is reached, an equipotent dose of oral sustained-release morphine will be randomly assigned to a patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oral extended-release morphine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oxycodone</intervention_name>
    <description>After a titration phase with fast-release oral morphine, once the optimal dosage (no side effects and less than two rescue doses per day) is reached, an equipotent dose of oral extended-release oxycodone will be randomly assigned to a patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oral extended-release oxycodone</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fentanyl</intervention_name>
    <description>After a titration phase with fast-release oral morphine, once the optimal dosage (no side effects and less than two rescue doses per day) is reached, an equipotent dosage of transdermal fentanyl will be randomly assigned to a patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Transdermal fentanyl</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Buprenorphine</intervention_name>
    <description>After a titration phase with fast-release oral morphine, once the optimal dosage (no side effects and less than two rescue doses per day) is reached, an equipotent dosage of transdermal buprenorphine will be randomly assigned to a patient.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Transdermal buprenorphine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult oncologic patients (&gt;= 18 years old)

          -  Chronic peripheral neuropathic and/or nociceptive pain

          -  Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pediatric patients

          -  Mental impaired patients

          -  Substance abuse disorder

          -  Opioid allergy

          -  History of opioids use or addiction

          -  Severe immunodeficiency, severe renal impairment, severe liver disease

          -  Cachectic state

          -  HIV positive patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Massimo Allegri, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>IRCCS Foundation Policlinico &quot;San Matteo&quot;, Pavia, Italy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Struttura Complessa di Medicina Interna - Ospedale Civile di Voghera - Azienda Ospedaliera provincia di Pavia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Voghera</city>
        <state>Pavia</state>
        <zip>27058</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Servizio di Anestesia e Rianimazione e Terapia Antalgica - Ospedale Sant'Orsola-Poliambulanza</name>
      <address>
        <city>Brescia</city>
        <zip>25011</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Servizio di Anestesia e Rianimazione e Terapia Antalgica - Ospedale Mellino Mellini</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chiari</city>
        <zip>25032</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Unità operativa di Anestesia e Rianimazione - Azienda Ospedaliera San Gerardo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Monza</city>
        <zip>20052</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fondazione IRCCS Policlinico San Matteo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pavia</city>
        <zip>27100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Unità operativa di Terapia Antalgica e Cure Palliative - Ospedale Infermi</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rimini</city>
        <zip>47900</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 9, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 9, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 10, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 8, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 8, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 9, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>IRCCS Policlinico S. Matteo</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Massimo Allegri</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Opioid pharmacogenetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Opioid pharmacokinetic</keyword>
  <keyword>Long-term opioid treatment</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Morphine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Analgesics, Opioid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fentanyl</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Buprenorphine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oxycodone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

