<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00910026</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>4163/02-09-2008</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00910026</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study of the Influence of Various Tidal Volumes on Exhaled Breath Condensate (EBC) in Mechanically Ventilated Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>TDEBC</acronym>
  <official_title>Exhaled Breath Condensate (EBC) Collection and Analysis in Mechanically Ventilated ICU Patients: Monitoring of the Influence of Various Tidal Volumes on Lung Inflammatory Biomarkers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Larissa University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Thessaly</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Larissa University Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of the present study is to evaluate the effect of low (6 ml/kg) and high (12 ml/kg)
      tidal volume ventilation on inflammatory and oxidative stress biomarkers in the exhaled
      breath condensate (EBC) of ICU patients without lung injury. As the analysis of EBC is
      reflecting the composition of epithelial lining fluid (ELF), the study of EBC pH and
      inflammatory and oxidative stress markers could have the potential for assessing lung
      inflammation caused by mechanical ventilation. This study also aims to look at the
      possibility to identify selective profiles of biomarkers that might have a prognostic and/or
      diagnostic value in the follow up of these patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      INTRODUCTION:

      Airway inflammation plays a key role in many airway diseases. Non invasive methods to study
      these inflammatory processes and to monitor airway diseases are in high demand. Stimulating
      interest is in breath analysis, such as the analysis of exhaled breath condensate (EBC), a
      technique of sampling the epithelial lining fluid of the lung (ELF), as an even easier way to
      assess airway inflammation (1,2). The appeal of EBC lies in its ability to collect
      non-invasively a wide range of nonvolatile molecules from the respiratory tract, the fact
      that it can be repeated frequently within short intervals without adverse events and that
      collection devices can be used in a wide range of settings including intensive care units
      (3,4,5,6).

      Analysis of EBC could not be limited to patient monitoring and understanding mechanisms of
      pulmonary disease. It also could become a useful tool for monitoring and screening for
      healthy individuals for possible early pulmonary tissue damage (6,7). There is a special need
      for more data on intra-subject and day-to-day variation, both essential for the decision as
      to whether a biomarker can serve as a research tool or even has the potential for disease
      monitoring in clinical practice (7).

      It has been recognized for some time that mechanical ventilation may induce lung injury and
      inflammation (8,9,10). Recent experimental and clinical data suggest that in healthy lungs,
      mechanical ventilation with tidal volume ranging between 7 and 12 ml/kg in the absence of
      positive end-expiratory pressure may lead to endothelial, extracellular matrix and peripheral
      airways damage without major inflammatory response, which further worsen with higher tidal
      volumes (15,34). Several mechanisms may explain damage to the lung structure induced by
      mechanical ventilation: regional over distension, 'low lung volume' associated with tidal
      airway closure, and inactivation of surfactant (15).

      High tidal volume ventilation has been shown to result in increased mortality while low tidal
      volume ventilation is regarded as a lung protective strategy in ALI, ARDS (11,12,13,35).

      In contrast, in other randomized studies (31,32) including a heterogeneous group of major
      thoracic and abdominal surgical procedures, protective mechanical ventilation was not
      associated with a decrease in intrapulmonary and systemic inflammation. Furthermore, there
      was no evidence that protective ventilation prevented lung adverse effect or decreased
      systemic cytokine levels in cardiac surgery (33).

      In line with these observations and considering that a practical parameter of increased
      mechanical stress of the lung remains to be demonstrated, studies may address the question
      whether the analysis of EBC biomarkers are related to ventilator-induced lung injury by low
      or high tidal volumes.

      MATERIALS AND METHODS:

      The present study is a prospective, randomized, controlled trial that will take place in the
      ICU of the University Hospital of Larissa, Thessaly. Authorization has been given from the
      Scientific Council and the ethical committee of our hospital.

      Patients:

      ICU patients requiring mechanical ventilation because of stroke, subarachnoid and/or
      intracerebral hemorrhage and with healthy respiratory system (evaluated using criteria as the
      LISS - Murray Lung Injury Severity Score) (14).

      Interventions:

      EBC collection will be performed on mechanically ventilated patients through the endotracheal
      tube according to ATS/ERS task force 2005 (7). Patients must be hemodynamically and
      respiratory stable.

      All patients will be under sedation and will receive ventilation by volume control. The
      respiratory frequency will be adapted at the set tidal volume in order to maintain the pH
      values within normal limits (7.35-7.45). SaO2 will be maintained equal or superior to 95%.

      EBC will be collected by inserting a special conduit (FILT, lung and chest diagnostics Ltd.
      Berlin Germany) for the breath condensate collecting device (Ecoscreen, Jaeger, Germany) into
      the expiratory limb of the ventilator tubing. Collecting time for EBC will be 30 min. No
      humidification will be used during the collection.

      The acidity (pH) of EBC before and after de-aeration with an inert gas Argon, 350 ml/minutes
      for 10 minutes, (gas standardisation) (17) will be readily measured using a pH meter Jenway
      Model 3510.

      All samples will be stored at -80 ο C for subsequent mediator measurements. Variables of
      ventilation (frequency, PEEP, FIO2, Vt), lung mechanics, arterial pressure, heart rate,
      arterial blood saturation, ICP and gas blood samples examination will be registered before
      and during the EBC collection. Also will be registered indices of lung injury (PiO2/FiO2,
      LISS), indices of systemic inflammation (temperature, leucocyte and neutrophil counts in
      blood samples) during the observation period. Disease severity indices (SOFA, SAPS, APACHE
      II) will be registered during the initial assessment.

      EBC analysis:

      EBC collected will be analyzed for pH, 8-isoprostane, H2O2, nitrites/nitrates and cytokines.
      The measurement of biomarkers will be performed using standardized procedures, as previously
      described.

      pH measurements: pH will be measured as previously described (16,17). H2O2 measurements: H2O2
      concentration will be determined by an enzymatic assay using horseradish peroxidase (Sigma
      Chemicals, St. Louis, MO), as previously described (17,18,19,20).

      8-Isoprostane measurements: 8-Isoprostane will be determined by a competitive enzyme
      immunoassay kit (Cayman Chemical, Ann Arbor, MI), as previously described (17,18,21,29). The
      detection limit of the assay is 4 pg/ml.

      Nitrogen oxides, nitrite/nitrate (NO2/NO3), and related products measurements: will be
      performed as previously described (17,22). Briefly, will be determined by using
      spectrophotometric assays (Griess reaction) (23,24,25,26,27,28).

      Cytokines measurement: will be quantified by EIA/ELISA kits as previously described
      (24,25,29,30).

      Protocol Details:

      The patients after the initial assessment will be randomized to receive mechanical
      ventilation with 6 or 12 ml/Kg of ideal body weight calculated through the following
      equation:

      For men [(Height (cm)-154) x 0.9] +50 and For women [(Height (cm)-154) x 0.9] +45.5. The
      observation period will be a minimum of 10 days (if possible) and EBC collection will be
      performed within the first 24 hours of admission (day 0) and through the days 1,2,4,6,8,10.

      EBC collection at day 0 will be performed under both modalities of ventilation with the
      purpose to investigate the quantity and composition of the collected EBC from the same
      patient ventilated with different tidal volumes. For the next measurements, the EBC
      collection for each group will be performed under the preset conditions of ventilation.

      Complications such as VAP, ARDS or sepsis during the period of observation will be recorded.

      Statistical analysis:

      Analysis will be performed using SPSS for Windows v. 16.0. Normality of distribution will be
      checked with Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. Normally distributed data will be presented as mean ±
      standard deviation (SD), whereas skewed data as median (interquartile range). Comparisons
      between two groups will be evaluated with unpaired t tests for normally distributed and
      Mann-Whitney tests for skewed data. Comparisons between more than two groups will be
      performed with analysis of variance (ANOVA) with appropriate post hoc tests
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the effect of low (6 ml/kg) and high (12 ml/kg) tidal volume ventilation on inflammatory and oxidative stress biomarkers in the exhaled breath condensate (EBC) of ICU patients without lung injury.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of the prognostic role of exhaled biomarkers in the subsequent outcome of mechanically ventilated patients (length of ICU hospitalization, subsequent development of ALI or ARDS and morbidity and mortality in the ICU).</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Inflammation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>low tidal volume ventilation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>6 ml/kg tidal volume ventilation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>high tidal volume ventilation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>12 ml/kg tidal volume ventilation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>low tidal volume ventilation</intervention_name>
    <description>6 ml/kg tidal volume ventilation</description>
    <arm_group_label>low tidal volume ventilation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>high tidal volume ventilation</intervention_name>
    <description>12 ml/kg tidal volume ventilation</description>
    <arm_group_label>high tidal volume ventilation</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  ICU patients mechanically ventilated because of stroke, subarachnoid and/or
             intracerebral hemorrhage

          -  Healthy respiratory system

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pulmonary diseases
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Olympia I. Apostolopoulou, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Thessaly</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Intensive Care Unit Department of University Hospital of Larissa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Larissa</city>
        <state>Thessaly</state>
        <zip>41110</zip>
        <country>Greece</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Greece</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Holz O. Catching breath: monitoring airway inflammation using exhaled breath condensate. Eur Respir J. 2005 Sep;26(3):371-2.</citation>
    <PMID>16135713</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hunt J. Exhaled breath condensate: an evolving tool for noninvasive evaluation of lung disease. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2002 Jul;110(1):28-34. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12110814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mutlu GM, Garey KW, Robbins RA, Danziger LH, Rubinstein I. Collection and analysis of exhaled breath condensate in humans. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2001 Sep 1;164(5):731-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11549524</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kharitonov SA, Barnes PJ. Exhaled markers of pulmonary disease. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2001 Jun;163(7):1693-722. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11401895</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muller WG, Morini F, Eaton S, Peters M, Jaffe A. Safety and feasibility of exhaled breath condensate collection in ventilated infants and children. Eur Respir J. 2006 Sep;28(3):479-85. Epub 2006 Apr 26.</citation>
    <PMID>16641124</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moloney ED, Mumby SE, Gajdocsi R, Cranshaw JH, Kharitonov SA, Quinlan GJ, Griffiths MJ. Exhaled breath condensate detects markers of pulmonary inflammation after cardiothoracic surgery. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2004 Jan 1;169(1):64-9. Epub 2003 Oct 9.</citation>
    <PMID>14551168</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horváth I, Hunt J, Barnes PJ, Alving K, Antczak A, Baraldi E, Becher G, van Beurden WJ, Corradi M, Dekhuijzen R, Dweik RA, Dwyer T, Effros R, Erzurum S, Gaston B, Gessner C, Greening A, Ho LP, Hohlfeld J, Jöbsis Q, Laskowski D, Loukides S, Marlin D, Montuschi P, Olin AC, Redington AE, Reinhold P, van Rensen EL, Rubinstein I, Silkoff P, Toren K, Vass G, Vogelberg C, Wirtz H; ATS/ERS Task Force on Exhaled Breath Condensate. Exhaled breath condensate: methodological recommendations and unresolved questions. Eur Respir J. 2005 Sep;26(3):523-48.</citation>
    <PMID>16135737</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Thammanomai A, Majumdar A, Bartolák-Suki E, Suki B. Effects of reduced tidal volume ventilation on pulmonary function in mice before and after acute lung injury. J Appl Physiol (1985). 2007 Nov;103(5):1551-9. Epub 2007 Aug 9.</citation>
    <PMID>17690203</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Halter JM, Steinberg JM, Gatto LA, DiRocco JD, Pavone LA, Schiller HJ, Albert S, Lee HM, Carney D, Nieman GF. Effect of positive end-expiratory pressure and tidal volume on lung injury induced by alveolar instability. Crit Care. 2007;11(1):R20.</citation>
    <PMID>17302983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Del Sorbo L, Slutsky AS. Year in review 2007: Critical Care--respirology. Crit Care. 2008;12(5):231. doi: 10.1186/cc6953. Epub 2008 Oct 14. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18983706</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dreyfuss D, Saumon G. From ventilator-induced lung injury to multiple organ dysfunction? Intensive Care Med. 1998 Feb;24(2):102-4.</citation>
    <PMID>9539065</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parker JC, Hernandez LA, Peevy KJ. Mechanisms of ventilator-induced lung injury. Crit Care Med. 1993 Jan;21(1):131-43. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8420720</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Amato MB, Barbas CS, Medeiros DM, Magaldi RB, Schettino GP, Lorenzi-Filho G, Kairalla RA, Deheinzelin D, Munoz C, Oliveira R, Takagaki TY, Carvalho CR. Effect of a protective-ventilation strategy on mortality in the acute respiratory distress syndrome. N Engl J Med. 1998 Feb 5;338(6):347-54.</citation>
    <PMID>9449727</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murray JF, Matthay MA, Luce JM, Flick MR. An expanded definition of the adult respiratory distress syndrome. Am Rev Respir Dis. 1988 Sep;138(3):720-3. Erratum in: Am Rev Respir Dis 1989 Apr;139(4):1065.</citation>
    <PMID>3202424</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pelosi P, Negrini D. Extracellular matrix and mechanical ventilation in healthy lungs: back to baro/volotrauma? Curr Opin Crit Care. 2008 Feb;14(1):16-21. doi: 10.1097/MCC.0b013e3282f25162. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18195621</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vaughan J, Ngamtrakulpanit L, Pajewski TN, Turner R, Nguyen TA, Smith A, Urban P, Hom S, Gaston B, Hunt J. Exhaled breath condensate pH is a robust and reproducible assay of airway acidity. Eur Respir J. 2003 Dec;22(6):889-94.</citation>
    <PMID>14680074</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kostikas K, Papatheodorou G, Ganas K, Psathakis K, Panagou P, Loukides S. pH in expired breath condensate of patients with inflammatory airway diseases. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2002 May 15;165(10):1364-70.</citation>
    <PMID>12016097</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kostikas K, Papatheodorou G, Psathakis K, Panagou P, Loukides S. Oxidative stress in expired breath condensate of patients with COPD. Chest. 2003 Oct;124(4):1373-80.</citation>
    <PMID>14555568</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Beurden WJ, Harff GA, Dekhuijzen PN, van den Bosch MJ, Creemers JP, Smeenk FW. An efficient and reproducible method for measuring hydrogen peroxide in exhaled breath condensate. Respir Med. 2002 Mar;96(3):197-203.</citation>
    <PMID>11908513</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Razola SS, Ruiz BL, Diez NM, Mark HB Jr, Kauffmann JM. Hydrogen peroxide sensitive amperometric biosensor based on horseradish peroxidase entrapped in a polypyrrole electrode. Biosens Bioelectron. 2002 Dec;17(11-12):921-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12392940</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Montuschi P, Collins JV, Ciabattoni G, Lazzeri N, Corradi M, Kharitonov SA, Barnes PJ. Exhaled 8-isoprostane as an in vivo biomarker of lung oxidative stress in patients with COPD and healthy smokers. Am J Respir Crit Care Med. 2000 Sep;162(3 Pt 1):1175-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10988150</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ganas K, Loukides S, Papatheodorou G, Panagou P, Kalogeropoulos N. Total nitrite/nitrate in expired breath condensate of patients with asthma. Respir Med. 2001 Aug;95(8):649-54.</citation>
    <PMID>11530952</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>23. Hammerschmidt S., Meybaum M., Schauer J. et. al; Effect of tidal volume and end expiratory pressure on pulmonary NO release in an isolated lung model (abstract); Eur.Respir.J. 2001;18(suppl):366s.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berg JT, Deem S, Kerr ME, Swenson ER. Hemoglobin and red blood cells alter the response of expired nitric oxide to mechanical forces. Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol. 2000 Dec;279(6):H2947-53.</citation>
    <PMID>11087251</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Francoeur C, Denis M. Nitric oxide and interleukin-8 as inflammatory components of cystic fibrosis. Inflammation. 1995 Oct;19(5):587-98.</citation>
    <PMID>8543373</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jang AS, Choi IS, Lee S, Seo JP, Yang SW, Park KO, Lee KY, Lee JU, Park CS, Park HS. Nitric oxide metabolites in induced sputum: a marker of airway inflammation in asthmatic subjects. Clin Exp Allergy. 1999 Aug;29(8):1136-42.</citation>
    <PMID>10457119</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Edwards YS, Sutherland LM, Murray AW. NO protects alveolar type II cells from stretch-induced apoptosis. A novel role for macrophages in the lung. Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol. 2000 Dec;279(6):L1236-42.</citation>
    <PMID>11076814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gessner C, Hammerschmidt S, Kuhn H, Lange T, Engelmann L, Schauer J, Wirtz H. Exhaled breath condensate nitrite and its relation to tidal volume in acute lung injury. Chest. 2003 Sep;124(3):1046-52.</citation>
    <PMID>12970036</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carpagnano GE, Kharitonov SA, Resta O, Foschino-Barbaro MP, Gramiccioni E, Barnes PJ. Increased 8-isoprostane and interleukin-6 in breath condensate of obstructive sleep apnea patients. Chest. 2002 Oct;122(4):1162-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12377837</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sack U, Scheibe R, Wötzel M, Hammerschmidt S, Kuhn H, Emmrich F, Hoheisel G, Wirtz H, Gessner C. Multiplex analysis of cytokines in exhaled breath condensate. Cytometry A. 2006 Mar;69(3):169-72.</citation>
    <PMID>16496377</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wrigge H, Uhlig U, Zinserling J, Behrends-Callsen E, Ottersbach G, Fischer M, Uhlig S, Putensen C. The effects of different ventilatory settings on pulmonary and systemic inflammatory responses during major surgery. Anesth Analg. 2004 Mar;98(3):775-81, table of contents.</citation>
    <PMID>14980936</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wrigge H, Zinserling J, Stüber F, von Spiegel T, Hering R, Wetegrove S, Hoeft A, Putensen C. Effects of mechanical ventilation on release of cytokines into systemic circulation in patients with normal pulmonary function. Anesthesiology. 2000 Dec;93(6):1413-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11149435</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koner O, Celebi S, Balci H, Cetin G, Karaoglu K, Cakar N. Effects of protective and conventional mechanical ventilation on pulmonary function and systemic cytokine release after cardiopulmonary bypass. Intensive Care Med. 2004 Apr;30(4):620-6. Epub 2004 Jan 13.</citation>
    <PMID>14722635</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bonetto C, Terragni P, Ranieri VM. Does high tidal volume generate ALI/ARDS in healthy lungs? Intensive Care Med. 2005 Jul;31(7):893-5. Epub 2005 Jun 2.</citation>
    <PMID>15931524</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>35. The ARDS Network; Ventilation with lower tidal volumes compared with traditional tidal volumes for ALI and the ARDS; N. Engl. J Med 342;1334-1349, 2000.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>November 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 28, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 28, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 29, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 24, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 24, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 25, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Larissa University Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Apostolopoulou Olympia</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>EBC and mechanical ventilation</keyword>
  <keyword>low tidal volume ventilation</keyword>
  <keyword>high tidal volume ventilation</keyword>
  <keyword>inflammatory and oxidative stress EBC biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>Ventilator induced lung injury</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Inflammation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

