<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00916461</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SMRI 04T-583</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00916461</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Role of Minocycline in First Episode Psychosis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomised, Double Blind Pilot Study of Minocycline and Placebo Added to Treatment-as-Usual (TAU) in First-Episode Psychosis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Stanley Medical Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rawalpindi Medical College, Pakistan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Pakistan Institute of Living and Learning</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Sao Paulo</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanley Medical Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine whether the addition of minocycline or placebo to
      treatment as usual (TAU):

        1. prevents the accumulation of negative symptoms and intellectual decline following a
           first episode of non-affective psychosis; and

        2. whether minocycline stabilizes the efficacy of antipsychotics.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      There is increasing clinical, neuropsychological and imaging evidence that schizophrenia
      involves a progressive process at the time of the first episode and later in life. However,
      it is not clear which systems are affected nor in which parts of the brain. In two Stanley
      first episode cohorts at Manchester (Stirling et al, 2004,) and in a group of elderly
      patients with schizophrenia (Gabrovska-Johnson et al 2004), evidence of deterioration in
      visuo-spatial functions has been found. This implies a right-hemisphere pathology. Other
      evidence suggests that the initiation of schizophrenia may involve left-sided pathology
      (Lawrie et al 2002) so it could be that right hemisphere pathology may follow left and give
      rise to the deficits of chronic schizophrenia (Gabrovska-Johnson et al 2004). If so, early
      treatment with a neuroprotective agent might prevent the accumulation of deficit symptoms and
      cognitive impairment.

      Minocycline is a tetracycline antibiotic with proven long-term high dose safety in humans, is
      routinely used to treat acne and rheumatoid arthritis demonstrating that it acts as a
      non-steroidal anti-inflammatory, as well as an antimicrobial drug. Minocycline, unlike
      tetracycline, crosses the blood-brain barrier. This and related compounds show
      neuroprotective properties in rat models of ischemic brain damage, in glutamate neurotoxicity
      in cell cultures and in a rat model of Huntington's disease in which it slowed progression
      (Chen et al, 2000; Yrjanheikki et al, 1999). Minocycline delays disease onset and extends
      survival in amyotrophic lateral sclerotic mice (Shan Zhu et al 2002).

      Minocycline has various properties including inhibition of capsases, inhibition of microglial
      activation, reduced cyclooxygenase-2 expression and reduced prostaglandin E (2) formation.
      Furthermore, it inhibits the formation of inducible nitric oxide - a mechanism of glial
      activation. All these mechanisms have been implicated in schizophrenia. All these mechanisms
      have been implicated in schizophrenia.

      Because of its broad spectrum of action, we consider minocycline is an important candidate
      molecule for the prevention of deterioration in schizophrenia. Based on the evidence so far
      we propose a randomised double blind placebo controlled study of minocycline added to
      treatment-as-usual (TAU) in first-episode psychosis.

      Study Hypotheses:

        -  A neurodegenerative process, initially most marked in the left hemisphere, in late
           adolescence is responsible for the onset of schizophrenia in those at risk.

        -  Continuation of this process after onset and its extension to the right hemisphere
           causes accumulation of deficit symptoms and cognitive decline.

        -  Glutamate antagonism may enhance the antipsychotic effects of dopamine receptor blockade
           and prevent attenuation of efficacy with long-term treatment.

      TREATMENT:

      Minocycline is a widely available antibiotic given in doses of 50mg twice daily increasing to
      200mgs per day. It has been used very widely and appears to be tolerated well. The study
      advisor, Dr. Serdar Dursun, has used doses of up to 200mg per day in the treatment of
      Huntington's disease (Denovan-Wright et al 2002).

      It is widely available in Pakistan and Brazil and given in doses of 50mg twice daily
      increasing to 100mg twice daily (in total 200mg per day) (British National Formulary: BNF
      maximum dose 200mg per day). As per counselling recommendations in the British National
      Formulary: &quot;minocycline medication should be swallowed whole with plenty of fluid while
      sitting or standing&quot;, to allow effective absorption. Patients will be counselled that 'the
      study medication should be swallowed whole with plenty of fluid while standing or sitting.'

      Patients will be informed regarding reported side-effects as cited in the BNF these include;
      nausea, vomiting, diarrhoea, dysphagia, oesophageal irritation, anorexia, dizziness,
      tinnitus, vertigo, hypersensitivity reactions (rash, exfoliative dermatitis, urticaria,
      angioedema, anaphylaxis, pericarditis), headache, visual disturbances, hepatotoxicity,
      pancreatitis, antibiotic associated colitis, blood dyscrasias, exacerbation of systemic lupus
      erythematosus and myasthenia gravis, rarely photosensitivity, skin, teeth, conjunctiva, tears
      and sweat discoloration.

      NUMBER OF PATIENTS:

      Using data from the SOCRATES study, we are able to calculate that 40 patients per treatment
      arm will detect a group difference on the primary outcome measure, i.e, PANSS, giving a 85%
      chance of detecting a difference between treatment groups of 4 points. The power estimate is
      likely to be conservative as there are three treatment groups. The automated CSF measures
      will detect a 5% group difference with these sample sizes. A minimum of 52 completed patients
      will be necessary (26 completed patients per treatment group).

      Study Advisors:

      Prof Bill Deakin(design), Prof Serdar Dursun(scientific), Prof Shon Lewis (clinical), Dr John
      Stirling (cognition), Dr Paul Richardson (cognition), Prof Graham Dunn (analysis).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive and negative symptoms on Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical Global Impression (CGI)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global Assessment of Functioning (GAF)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Abnormal Involuntary Movement Scale (AIMS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of side effects</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Doses of antipsychotic drugs</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>neurocognitive test scores</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">52</enrollment>
  <condition>First Episode Psychosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Minocycline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar Pill</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Minocycline</intervention_name>
    <description>Minocycline + treatment as usual. 50 mg twice daily increasing to 200 mgs per day, increments of 50 mgs every 2 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Minocycline</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo + treatment as usual.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sugar Pill</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged 18 to 65 years

          -  Diagnostic and Statistical Manual-IV (DSM-IV) diagnosed first episode psychosis,
             schizophrenia, schizoaffective disorder, psychosis not otherwise specified or
             schizophreniform disorder

          -  First episode (within first 5 years of diagnosis)

          -  Competent and willing to give informed consent

          -  Medication remained stable 4 weeks prior to baseline

          -  Able to take oral medication and likely to complete the required evaluations

          -  Female participants of child bearing capability must be willing to use adequate
             contraceptives for the duration of the study, and, willing to have a pregnancy test
             pre-treatment and at ten weekly intervals while on study medication

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Relevant medical illness [renal, hepatic, cardiac, serious dermatological disorders
             such as exfoliative dermatitis, systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE)] in the opinion of
             the investigators (see section 6.2a)

          -  Prior history of intolerance to any of the tetracyclines

          -  Concomitant penicillin therapy

          -  Concomitant anticoagulant therapy

          -  Presence of a seizure disorder, not including clozapine-induced seizures

          -  Presently taking valproic acid

          -  Any change of psychotropic medications within the previous six weeks

          -  Diagnosis of substance abuse (except nicotine or caffeine) or dependence within the
             last three months according to DSM-IV criteria

          -  Pregnant or breast-feeding
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Imran B Chaudhry, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Manchester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jaime EC Hallak, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of San Paulo, Brazil</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nusrat Husain, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of Manchester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Neurology, Psychiatry and Psychological Medicine, University of San Paulo</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Paulo</city>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Civil Hospital Karachi</name>
      <address>
        <city>Karachi</city>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karwan e Hayat</name>
      <address>
        <city>Karachi</city>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Institute of Psychiatry, Rawalpindi medical College</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rawalpindi</city>
        <country>Pakistan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
    <country>Pakistan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen M, Ona VO, Li M, Ferrante RJ, Fink KB, Zhu S, Bian J, Guo L, Farrell LA, Hersch SM, Hobbs W, Vonsattel JP, Cha JH, Friedlander RM. Minocycline inhibits caspase-1 and caspase-3 expression and delays mortality in a transgenic mouse model of Huntington disease. Nat Med. 2000 Jul;6(7):797-801.</citation>
    <PMID>10888929</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gabrovska-Johnson VS, Scott M, Jeffries S, Thacker N, Baldwin RC, Burns A, Lewis SW, Deakin JF. Right-hemisphere encephalopathy in elderly subjects with schizophrenia: evidence from neuropsychological and brain imaging studies. Psychopharmacology (Berl). 2003 Sep;169(3-4):367-75. Epub 2003 Jul 4.</citation>
    <PMID>12845412</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yrjänheikki J, Tikka T, Keinänen R, Goldsteins G, Chan PH, Koistinaho J. A tetracycline derivative, minocycline, reduces inflammation and protects against focal cerebral ischemia with a wide therapeutic window. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1999 Nov 9;96(23):13496-500.</citation>
    <PMID>10557349</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stirling J, White C, Lewis S, Hopkins R, Tantam D, Huddy A, Montague L. Neurocognitive function and outcome in first-episode schizophrenia: a 10-year follow-up of an epidemiological cohort. Schizophr Res. 2003 Dec 15;65(2-3):75-86.</citation>
    <PMID>14630300</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zhu S, Stavrovskaya IG, Drozda M, Kim BY, Ona V, Li M, Sarang S, Liu AS, Hartley DM, Wu DC, Gullans S, Ferrante RJ, Przedborski S, Kristal BS, Friedlander RM. Minocycline inhibits cytochrome c release and delays progression of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis in mice. Nature. 2002 May 2;417(6884):74-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11986668</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Denovan-Wright EM, Devarajan S, Dursun SM, Robertson HA. Maintained improvement with minocycline of a patient with advanced Huntington's disease. J Psychopharmacol. 2002 Dec;16(4):393-4.</citation>
    <PMID>12503842</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 8, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 8, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 9, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 12, 2009</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 12, 2009</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 15, 2009</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Dr Imran B Chaudhry</name_title>
    <organization>University of Manchester</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>First episode psychosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Minocycline</keyword>
  <keyword>neuroprotection</keyword>
  <keyword>First episode non affective psychosis</keyword>
  <keyword>With in first five years of illness</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mental Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Minocycline</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

