<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00910884</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CDR0000643461</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>BRABANT-00005271</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00910884</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Natural Supplements Special Diet: Eliminating Cancer-impacting Hormones From Sources Outside the Body in Patients With Early-Stage or Remission Breast Cancer.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Gene Expression Control Using Micro-Trace Element Compounds During C.A.M., Adjunct Therapy and Conventional Cancer Protocols</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brabant Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brabant Research</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Natural supplements and a special diet may help rid the body of estrogen and
      testosterone and may slow the growth of tumor cells.

      PURPOSE: The purpose of this randomized Phase I trial is to first IDENTIFY, through
      laboratory analysis and validating cellular biochemical pathways, and HELP CONTROL, using
      natural supplements and a special diet work, extemporaneous and environmental (man-made)
      hormones, hormone impacting compounds and hormone-mimicking compounds that are made outside
      the body, found in manufactured products or in-taken to the body of cancer patients through
      life-style, environmental or consumption products. Patients with early-stage or remission
      stage prostate cancer, breast cancer, or uterine cancer have a much greater sensitivity to
      these extemporaneous hormonal or hormonal influencing compounds.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      To utilize multiple naturally-occurring micro-trace element compounds to sequester exogenous
      estrogens, estrogen-mimicking and estrogen-influencing compounds, from multiple sources,
      including environmental and metabolic sources, and eliminate them from the body prior to
      influencing prostate, breast, and uterine cancer pathways in cancer patients and cancer
      patients in remission.

      To utilize specific naturally-occurring flavonoids to suppress proliferation-stimulating
      activities induced by normal metabolism and environmental estrogen, estrogen-mimicking,
      estrogen-influencing and testosterone-type compounds.

      To utilize DPPH radical-scavenging activity to reduce secondary bonding of TMPRSS2-ERG fusing
      and negative-bonded environmental estrogen.

      To utilize endocrine system related immune response compounds as a means to help control
      and/or chemically influence/impact extemporaneous environmental and accumulated life-style
      estrogen, estrogen-mimicking, estrogen-influencing and testosterone-type compounds for
      preventing or controlling recurrence of breast, uterine or prostate cancers; hormonally
      influenced cancers.

      To utilize a full diet of specifically grown inclusion produce to maintain normal metabolic
      function.

      BACKGROUND DATA:

      Laboratory analytical instrumentation has improved the ability to measure, track and analyze
      extemporaneous environmental and accumulated life-style estrogen, estrogen-mimicking,
      estrogen-influencing and testosterone-type compounds.

      The initial data accumulation of spheres of chemical influence from human hormonal,
      hormonal-mimicking or hormonal-influencing compounds has radically changed since the
      beginning of this Phase 1 clinical trial.

      For example, endocrine disruptor compounds (EDCs) also commonly called hormonally active
      agents (1) have been shown to have strong estrogenic-type effects on the body of both female
      and male cancer patients. Whereas xenoestrogenic compounds, example PCBs, BPA, DDT and
      phthalates, have been found to have direct body influence, other hormonally-influencing
      compounds, like nicotine and atrazine, are not as easily predictable in how they affect
      existing and remission cancers.

      The pharmacological actions of nicotine, for example, have been shown to impact hormonal and
      growth factors and Marinucci et al (2) showed concretely that nicotine differently regulated
      cell growth. With the work of Camargo, et al (3) the effect of nicotine on androgen
      over-production was settled as factual. The tobacco industry has seemingly allowed the
      connection of smoking and cancer to be investigated when the causal agent for the cancers are
      limited to carcinogens found in &quot;smoke.&quot; However, newer analyses show clearly that nicotine
      itself, found in the cigarette smoke and today in e-cigarettes, as having an influence on
      estrogen synthesis in the body as well as blocking monoxygenase control of HMG-CoA Reductase
      and thereby control of oncogenic expression. The pathway is clear that nicotine-induced
      sympathetic activation could account for also the increased thyroid hormone secretion and as
      a result the nicotine-influenced estrogen metabolic pathway, resulting in lower estrogen
      levels but higher androgen levels also affects TSH levels. Combined these two factors,
      influenced by nicotine, show real biochemical pathway to both influencing benign breast
      cancer and remission breast cancer to have a more androgen-influenced aggressive behavior.
      The androgen influenced recurrence breast and prostate are less controllable by any current
      level of pharmaceutical control method.

      Raval (4) showed chemically that nicotine, not other compounds in &quot;smoke,&quot; reduces
      circulating estrogen. Therefore in the metabolic pathway, preventing the final metabolite,
      estrogen, increases the precursor compounds, increasing circulating androgen. While Holloway,
      et al, (5) showed that in utero exposure to nicotine had a demonstrable influence of
      endocrine effect on placental development and corresponding (decrease) of fetomaternal
      circulation.

      Newer research, Bavarva, et al, (6) indicates that environmental impact and/or lifestyle
      addictions, nicotine in this example, alter actual gene expression and, in and of itself, can
      cause the genetic basis for induced cancer development.

      EDCs, (endocrine disruptor/disrupting compounds), are found in multiple industry arenas. Due
      to advances in detection techniques, endocrine disruption, known as far back as the early
      1990s, was generally thought to be &quot;specie-specific.&quot; However, newer research has found that
      not to be the case.

      On a worldwide scientific research basis, the triazine family of nitrogen containing
      six-membered heterocyclic benzene aromatic ring compound herbicides are regarded as an
      endocrine disrupting compound. Hayes (7) found significant sex gland aberrations and
      gender-bending in amphibians exposed to varied levels of atrazine in field/natural conditions
      that were then validated in laboratory conditions.

      In 2007 the EPA found cause to suspect triazine/atrazine as having endocrine/hormonal impact
      on developing children (8) but as atrazine is the number one selling herbicide in the USA,
      pressure from the agricultural and chemical manufacturing industry keeps the product in the
      marketplace.

      Research by Mizota (9) clearly showing &quot;atrazine exerts inflammatory activity through
      activation of putative G(q/11)-coupled neurosteroid receptor and phospholipase C&quot; then allows
      for the atrazine-induced biochemical estrogen impacting pathway with altered receptors of
      male versus female developmental hormonal response. More specifically; progesterone
      receptor-modulation of atrazine-induced mast cell degranulation changes the pathway of
      estrogen/ estriol, 17β-estradiol and progesterone creating an accumulation of precursor
      compound, 17β-estradiol, and therefore the androgen precursor, without the final product of
      the synthesis: estriol.

      17β-estradiol has an extreme level of hormonal activity and as a result, when over-produced
      or found in amounts not of specific ration to other estrogenic hormones, specifically estriol
      (the down-stream product of 17β-estradiol synthesis) the result is a higher affinity in
      receptors for 17β-estradiol instead of the lower DNA influencing compound estriol. This
      bondage impairs G1, S, or G2 phases of DNA repair in the cell cycle and directly accelerates
      the proliferation of DNA damaged cells, cancerous, in breast, uterine and ovarian organs.
      (10) Due to the persistence of the triazine family of herbicides in soils and ground/drinking
      water and its apparent impact on hormonal reactions, the EU banned atrazine/triazine from use
      in any EU country. Further, atrazine residue on products imported into the EU is also
      severely restricted.

      Atrazine is found in virtually every USA woman's body, notably in breast and ovarian tissue.
      It is found in more US state drinking water tests than any other pollutant. It is second in
      usage to glyphosate on USA crop acres but, as it was in use decades before glyphosate, it is
      higher in groundwater sampling as of 2011.

      As a result of these newer levels of cellular research, extemporaneous influences on cancer,
      notably hormonal cancers, are being found as having a crucial role in the continuing rate of
      breast, prostate, uterine and ovarian cancers.

      Negating these near-human and human-like EDCs and/or their influence on the body has, to
      date, been overlooked as a therapy and under-emphasized as the course of action for cancer
      treatments. This study both advances the roles EDCs play in hormonally controlled cancers and
      the effect natural plant compounds, coupled with ultra-trace mineral/elemental molecules,
      have in reducing or eliminating them from negative impact in the human body.

      OUTLINE: Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 arms.

      Arm I: Patients receive oral natural supplements comprising indole-3-carbinol, perillyl
      alcohol, glucuronic acid, and flavonoids daily for 12 months. Patients also consume whole
      foods comprising indole-3-carbinol and a diet that eliminates exogenous growth hormones.

      Arm II: Patients do not receive natural supplements or consume whole foods or a special diet.

      Levels of compounds of interest are measured by inductively-coupled plasma mass spectrometry,
      high performance liquid chromatography, gas chromatography, and matrix-assisted laser
      desorption/ionization time of flight mass spectrometry.

      After completion of study therapy, patients are followed periodically for 6 months and
      monitored for a second 6 months period.

        1. Krimsky S (December 2001). &quot;An epistemological inquiry into the endocrine disruptor
           thesis&quot;. Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci. 948 (1): 130-42. doi:10.1111/j.1749-6632.2001.tb03994.x.
           PMID 11795392.

        2. Marinucci L, Bodo M, Balloni S, Locci P, Baroni T. &quot;Sub-Toxic Nicotine Concentrations
           Affect Extracellular Matrix and Growth Factor Signaling Gene Expressions in Human
           Osteoblasts.&quot; J Cell Physiol. 2014 Apr 29. doi: 10.1002/jcp.24661. PMID: 24777817

        3. Camargo IC, Leite GA, Pinto T, Ribeiro-Paes JT. &quot;Histopathologycal findings in the
           ovaries and uterus of albino female rats promoted by co-administration of synthetic
           steroids and nicotine.&quot; Exp Toxicol Pathol. 2014 Jul;66(4):195-202. doi:
           10.1016/j.etp.2014.01.005. Epub 2014 Feb 18. PMID: 24556002

        4. Raval AP. &quot;Nicotine addiction causes unique detrimental effects on women's brains.&quot; J
           Addict Dis. 2011 Apr;30(2):149-58. doi: 10.1080/10550887.2011.554782. Review. PMID:
           21491296

        5. Holloway AC, Salomon A, Soares MJ, Garnier V, Raha S, Sergent F, Nicholson CJ, Feige JJ,
           Benharouga M, Alfaidy N. &quot;Characterization of the adverse effects of nicotine on
           placental development: in vivo and in vitro studies.&quot; Am J Physiol Endocrinol Metab.
           2014 Feb 15;306(4):E443-56. doi: 10.1152/ajpendo.00478.2013. Epub 2013 Dec 24. PMID:
           24368670

        6. Bavarva JH, Tae H, Settlage RE, Garner HR. &quot;Characterizing the Genetic Basis for
           Nicotine Induced Cancer Development: A Transcriptome Sequencing Study.&quot; PLoS One. 2013
           Jun 18;8(6):e67252. Print 2013. PMID: 23825647

        7. Hayes, Tyrone B.; Anderson, Lloyd L.; Beasley, Val R.; de Solla, Shane R.; Iguchi,
           Taisen; et al. (2011). &quot;Demasculinization and feminization of male gonads by atrazine:
           Consistent effects across vertebrate classes&quot;. The Journal of Steroid Biochemistry and
           Molecular Biology 127 (1-2): 64-73. doi:10.1016/j.jsbmb.2011.03.015. PMID 21419222

        8. Atrazine: Chemical Summary. Toxicity and Exposure Assessment for Children's Health
           (Report). U.S. Environmental Protection Agency. 4/24/2007

        9. Mizota, K.; Ueda, H. (2006). &quot;Endocrine Disrupting Chemical Atrazine Causes
           Degranulation through Gq/11 Protein-Coupled Neurosteroid Receptor in Mast Cells&quot;.
           Toxicological Sciences 90 (2): 362-8. doi:10.1093/toxsci/kfj087. PMID 16381660

       10. Thomas, Christoforos; Strom A.; Lindberg K.; Gustafsson J. (22 June 2010). &quot;Estrogen
           receptor beta decreases survival of p53-defective cancer cells after DNA damage by
           impairing G2/M checkpoint signaling&quot;. Breast Cancer Research and Treatment 127 (2):
           417-427. doi:10.1007/s10549-010-1011-z. PMID 20623183
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sequestration and elimination of exogenous estrogens from the body using multiple naturally-occurring micro-trace element compounds</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>lowering body estrogens as related to hormone driven cancer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Suppression of proliferation-stimulating activities using naturally-occurring flavonoids</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>suppress cancer cell proliferation</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction of secondary bonding of TMPRSS2-ERG fusing and negative-bonded environmental estrogen using DPPH radical-scavenging activity</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Monitor levels</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maintenance of normal metabolic function using a full diet of specifically grown inclusion produce</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>metabolic function testing</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients receive oral natural supplements comprising indole-3-carbinol, perillyl alcohol, glucuronic acid, and flavonoids daily for 12 months. Patients also consume whole foods comprising indole-3-carbinol and a diet that eliminates exogenous growth hormones.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients do not receive natural supplements or consume whole foods or a special diet.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laboratory biomarker analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>No supplements are given</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>therapeutic dietary intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Given orally daily for 12 months</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Breast cancer limited to &quot;in-remission only.&quot; Any Stage of cancer; wholly limited to &quot;in
        remission.&quot;
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Diagnosis of prostate, breast, or uterine cancer

               -  Early-stage disease

          -  Currently waiting to initiate conventional therapy or radiotherapy OR receiving
             concurrent conventional chemotherapy or radiation therapy

          -  Hormone receptor status not specified

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Menopausal status not specified

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  See Disease Characteristics

          -  Prior or concurrent chemotherapy or hormonal therapy for cancer allowed
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Female in breast cancer remission, any Stage.</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Richard E. Lasker, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brabant Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brabant Research, Incorporated</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spokane Valley</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>99216</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Richard E. Lasker, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>509-340-9902</phone>
      <email>rel@brabantresearch.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 29, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 29, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 1, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 21, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brabant Research</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Richard Lasker</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stage I breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage II breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage IIIA breast cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>male breast cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

