<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01982747</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MGN1703-C04</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01982747</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Phase I Study to Assess Cardiac and General Safety and Pharmacokinetics of 60 mg MGN1703</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I, Placebo-Controlled, Double-Blind, 2-Period Crossover Study to Assess Cardiac and General Safety and Pharmacokinetics of a Single Subcutaneous Dose of 60 mg MGN1703 in Healthy Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mologen AG</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mologen AG</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      MGN1703 is being developed for use in treating cancerous tumors effecting the colon, skin,
      kidneys and lungs. The dosage form of MGN1703 under investigation is an injection.

      The goal of this study is to evaluate the effects of MGN1703 on the electrical activity of
      the heart in healthy subjects and to look at general safety.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>cardiac safety of MGN1703 as compared to placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>within the first 5 days after dosing</time_frame>
    <description>assessed by 12 lead ECG</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>general safety of MGN1703 as compared to placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>within 5 days after dosing</time_frame>
    <description>assessed by the following measures: safety laboratory analysis, vital signs and physical examination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>PK parameters of MGN1703</measure>
    <time_frame>within 5 days after dosing</time_frame>
    <description>assessed by the following measures: Cmax, tmax, t1/2, AUCτ</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MGN - Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects of the MGN-Placebo arm will receive 60mg MGN1703 as 2 s.c. injections of 2 ml each during period 1 and physiological saline solution as Placebo as 2 s.c. injections of 2 ml each during period 2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo-MGN</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects of the Placebo-MGN arm will receive physiological saline solution as Placebo as 2 s.c. injections of 2 ml each during period 1 and 60mg MGN1703 as 2 s.c. injections of 2 ml each during period 2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MGN-Placebo</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>MGN - Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo-MGN</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo-MGN</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. The subject signs an IRB/IEC-approved informed consent prior to any study-related
             procedures.

          2. Subject is male or female with no less than 6 subjects per sex in the study.

          3. Subject is 18 to 65 years of age.

          4. Subject's BMI is ≤32 kg/m2.

          5. Female subjects of childbearing potential must not be pregnant or lactating with a
             negative serum HCG pregnancy test result at Screening and a negative urine HCG
             pregnancy test result on Days -1 and 14 prior to receiving study medication.

          6. Female subjects of childbearing potential and male subjects must use an adequate
             method of contraception from Screening until completion of the study. Acceptable
             methods of contraception are barrier methods (male condom, female condom, diaphragm,
             cervical cap, spermicide or IUD), surgical sterility (documented doctor's report of
             vasectomy, hysterectomy and/or bilateral oophorectomy) and/or postmenopausal status
             (defined as at least 1 year without menses as demonstrated by medical history or
             subject report).

          7. Subject is in good health as determined by vital signs, medical history, physical
             exam, and safety laboratory analyses at Screening and during the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject has used an investigational product within 30 days prior to screening or
             during the study.

          2. Subject has used prescription or non-prescription drugs (including vitamins, minerals,
             and herbal/plant-derived preparations) within 2 weeks of Screening (excluding oral
             contraceptives, hormonal IUD, hormone replacement therapy and acetaminophen) unless
             deemed acceptable by the Investigator in consultation with the Sponsor.

          3. Subject has a positive drug and/or alcohol test at Screening, Day -1 or Day 14.

          4. The subject has a history of drug or alcohol abuse within 2 years before Screening.

          5. The subject is unable to abstain from ingesting alcohol, caffeine, grapefruit or
             Grapefruit juice for 72 hour prior to dosing.

          6. The subject has a clinically significant history of cardiovascular, endocrinologic,
             hematologic, hepatic, immunologic, metabolic, urologic, pulmonary, neurologic,
             dermatologic, psychiatric, renal, and/or other major diseases or malignancy.

          7. Subject has a history of cardiac disease or any risk factors for TdP including (but
             not limited to) unexplained syncope, cardiac arrest, unexplained cardiac arrhythmia,
             structural heart disease and family history of Long QT syndrome.

          8. Subject has evidence of any of the following cardiac conduction abnormalities at
             Screening, Day -1 or Day 1 prior to receiving any study medication:

               1. QTcF interval &gt;430 msec for males and &gt;450 msec for females

               2. PR interval &gt;240 msec or &lt;110 msec

               3. Evidence of second- or third-degree AVB

               4. Electrocardiographic evidence of complete LBBB, complete RBBB or incomplete LBBB

               5. Intraventricular conduction delay with QRS duration &gt;120 msec

               6. Heart rate &lt;40 bpm or &gt;90 bpm

               7. Pathological Q waves (defined as &gt;40 msec or depth &gt;0.4-0.5 mV)

               8. Evidence of ventricular pre-excitation

          9. The safety laboratory analyses at Screening are outside the normal limits and
             considered by the Investigator as clinically significant.

         10. Any acute or chronic condition that, in the opinion of the Investigator, would limit
             the subject's ability to complete and/or participate in this clinical study, a history
             of noncompliance to medical regimens, or subjects who are considered to be potentially
             unreliable.

               1. The subject has a positive test result for HIV antibody.

               2. The subject has a positive test result for the hepatitis C antibody or the HBsAg.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carlos R Sanabria, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Spaulding Clinical</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Spaulding Clinical</name>
      <address>
        <city>West Bend</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53095</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 6, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 12, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 13, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 16, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 16, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 19, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cardiac Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>General Safety</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

