<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01980927</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>24116</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01980927</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Changes in Intracranial Compliance in Migraine Subjects Following a National Upper Cervical Chiropractic Association Atlas Correction</brief_title>
  <official_title>Changes in Intracranial Compliance in Migraine Subjects Following a National Upper Cervical Chiropractic Association (NUCCA)Atlas Correction Intervention - a Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Calgary</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Calgary</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A small number of chiropractors, who align only the atlas C-1, or &quot;top&quot; vertebra in the
      spine, practice the National Upper Cervical Chiropractic Association (NUCCA) atlas correction
      procedure. This procedure uses a precise, non-invasive, gentle touch technique to correct
      misalignment of the atlas. Although NUCCA practitioners have long used this procedure in the
      treatment of headache, it has not been formally studied using clinical trials. There is some
      data indicating that NUCCA correction can increase intracranial compliance. This intracranial
      compliance can be measured by a magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) study before and then after
      a NUCCA procedure. In this study, the investigators hope to show that the correction of an
      atlas misalignment will increase intracranial compliance in subjects with migraine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in intracranial compliance; comparing the baseline period to one month post treatment, 4 weeks after initiation of NUCCA care and maintained correction of atlas misalignment, as measured by phase contrast magnetic resonance imaging.</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, at 4 weeks, at 8 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Days with headache per month</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, at 4 weeks, at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Patients use headache diaries to track the number of days with headaches.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average headache intensity on headache days</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, at 4 weeks, at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Patients rate headache pain from 0-10 on 3 segments of the day (morning, afternoon, evening) using headache diaries. These numbers are used to calculate the average intensity of the headache on headache days.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life measurements - comparing quality of life scores by using various questionnaires at baseline and at 8 weeks</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline, at 8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Using MIDAS, Migraine QOL, and HIT-6 questionnaires to score patients' quality of life in measurable terms.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">11</enrollment>
  <condition>Migraine</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>NUCCA atlas correction</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>NUCCA atlas correction for migraine patients</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>NUCCA atlas correction</intervention_name>
    <description>A chiropractic procedure involving correcting a misalignment of the atlas or &quot;top&quot; vertebra in the spine.</description>
    <arm_group_label>NUCCA atlas correction</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must be 18-65 years of age.

          -  Be naive to Upper Cervical Chiropractic care. Other forms of chiropractic care in the
             past are permitted.

          -  Have migraine with or without aura.

          -  Have between 10-26 headache days per month over the last 4 months.

          -  Have at least 4 separate headache episodes per month, with episodes separated by at
             least 4 hours of painfree time.

          -  Have at least 8 days per month with pain of levels greater than or equal to 4/10 for
             part of the day, or have attacks successfully treated with migraine specific
             medication.

          -  Be candidates suitable for NUCCA therapeutic intervention because of atlas
             displacement as assessed by NUCCA investigator.

          -  Subjects on acceptable pharmacological prophylaxis must either remain on a stable dose
             throughout the study, or stop the prophylactic medication one month before entering
             the baseline period.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any medical or psychiatric condition which in the opinion of the investigator would
             make the subject unsuitable for enrolment, because of inability to comply with study
             requirements or possible confounding of the results.

          -  Headache on more than 26 days per month.

          -  Acute medication overuse as defined by the International Classification of Headache
             Disorders.

          -  Pregnancy or lactation

          -  Severe cervical spine degeneration as assessed by cervical spine x-ray.

          -  Claustrophobia or any condition that contraindicates an MRI scan

          -  A history of cardiovascular disease, cerebrovascular disease, brain surgery, or other
             central nervous system disorder.

          -  Other chronic pain disorder which might interfere with headache assessment or study
             procedures.

          -  A history of significant hypo- or hypertension as determined by the investigator.

          -  Subject on a beta-blocker, calcium channel blocker, or other medication which the
             investigator considers might alter cerebral vascular regulation. Triptans are allowed,
             but must not be taken within 24 hours (48 hours for frovatriptan) before an MRI study.

          -  A history of substance abuse or dependence within 1 year.

          -  Current participation in a research study or within the last 30 days.

          -  Any spinal chiropractic care outside of the study protocol is prohibited during the
             baseline and treatment period.

          -  Use of botulinum A within 4 months of study entry.

          -  A history of significant head or neck trauma (as judged by the investigator) within
             the year prior to study entry.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Werner Becker, MD, FRCPC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Calgary</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Foothills Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Calgary</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 4, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 4, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 11, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 10, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 10, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 12, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Calgary</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. Werner Becker</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr. Werner Becker, MD, FRCPC</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Migraine</keyword>
  <keyword>National Upper Cervical Chiropractic Association atlas correction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Migraine Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

