<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01981772</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2012H0437</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01981772</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Efficacy of Buffered Lidocaine in Patients With Facial Swelling</brief_title>
  <official_title>Anesthetic Efficacy of 4% Buffered Lidocaine in Emergency Patients With Facial Swelling.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ohio State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ohio State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the clinical efficacy of a buffered 4% lidocaine
      solution for incision and drainage. Ninety patients will be examined clinically to determine
      a diagnosis of cellulitis or fluctuance. The diagnosis will be confirmed by incision and
      drainage. Patients will receive either 3.6 ml 4% lidocaine with 1:100,000 epinephrine or 3.6
      ml 4% lidocaine with 1:100,000 epinephrine buffered with 8.4% sodium bicarbonate. Patients
      will rate pain prior to and throughout the procedure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Incision and drainage of swellings is painful and anesthetic failure is common. One reason
      may be related to the lowered pH of inflamed tissue reducing the amount of the base form of
      anesthetic. A buffered anesthetic solution may result in more effective anesthesia than a
      non-buffered solution.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>pain measurement as assessed on a visual analog scale</measure>
    <time_frame>during injection and incision and drainage on Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will rate pain on a visual analog scale during needle insertion, placement, and solution deposition phases of the anesthetic injection(s). Patients will also rate pain during the incision and dissection phases of the incision and drainage procedure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>postoperative satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>immediately post-procedure on Day 0</time_frame>
    <description>Patients will rate their level of satisfaction with the incision and drainage procedure using a visual analog scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Facial Swelling</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>buffered lidocaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>administration of 4% buffered lidocaine with 1:100,000 epinephrine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>nonbuffered lidocaine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>administration of 4% lidocaine with 1:100,000 epinephrine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>4% lidocaine with 1:100,000 epinephrine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>nonbuffered lidocaine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>4% buffered lidocaine with 1:100,000 epinephrine</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>buffered lidocaine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 years or older

          -  in good health (ASA classification I or II)

          -  able to give informed consent

          -  necrotic tooth with associated facial swelling

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  allergies to local anesthetics or sulfites

          -  history of significant medical problems (ASA classification III or greater)

          -  pregnancy

          -  inability to give informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Melissa Drum, DDS, MS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The Ohio State University College of Dentistry</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Ohio State University College of Dentistry</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adhikari S, Blaivas M, Lander L. Comparison of bedside ultrasound and panorex radiography in the diagnosis of a dental abscess in the ED. Am J Emerg Med. 2011 Sep;29(7):790-5. doi: 10.1016/j.ajem.2010.03.005. Epub 2010 May 1.</citation>
    <PMID>20825898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Singer AJ, Richman PB, Kowalska A, Thode HC Jr. Comparison of patient and practitioner assessments of pain from commonly performed emergency department procedures. Ann Emerg Med. 1999 Jun;33(6):652-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10339680</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Strichartz GR. Novel ideas of local anaesthetic actions on various ion channels to ameliorate postoperative pain. Br J Anaesth. 2008 Jul;101(1):45-7. doi: 10.1093/bja/aen101. Epub 2008 May 16. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18487246</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cohen JS, Reader A, Fertel R, Beck M, Meyers WJ. A radioimmunoassay determination of the concentrations of prostaglandins E2 and F2alpha in painful and asymptomatic human dental pulps. J Endod. 1985 Aug;11(8):330-5.</citation>
    <PMID>3863874</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Isett J, Reader A, Gallatin E, Beck M, Padgett D. Effect of an intraosseous injection of depo-medrol on pulpal concentrations of PGE2 and IL-8 in untreated irreversible pulpitis. J Endod. 2003 Apr;29(4):268-71.</citation>
    <PMID>12701778</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wells JE, Bingham V, Rowland KC, Hatton J. Expression of Nav1.9 channels in human dental pulp and trigeminal ganglion. J Endod. 2007 Oct;33(10):1172-6. Epub 2007 Aug 27.</citation>
    <PMID>17889684</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luo S, Perry GM, Levinson SR, Henry MA. Nav1.7 expression is increased in painful human dental pulp. Mol Pain. 2008 Apr 21;4:16. doi: 10.1186/1744-8069-4-16.</citation>
    <PMID>18426592</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Warren CA, Mok L, Gordon S, Fouad AF, Gold MS. Quantification of neural protein in extirpated tooth pulp. J Endod. 2008 Jan;34(1):7-10. Epub 2007 Nov 26.</citation>
    <PMID>18155483</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Owatz CB, Khan AA, Schindler WG, Schwartz SA, Keiser K, Hargreaves KM. The incidence of mechanical allodynia in patients with irreversible pulpitis. J Endod. 2007 May;33(5):552-6. Epub 2007 Mar 6.</citation>
    <PMID>17437870</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Modaresi J, Dianat O, Soluti A. Effect of pulp inflammation on nerve impulse quality with or without anesthesia. J Endod. 2008 Apr;34(4):438-41. doi: 10.1016/j.joen.2008.01.014. Epub 2008 Mar 4.</citation>
    <PMID>18358891</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roy ML, Narahashi T. Differential properties of tetrodotoxin-sensitive and tetrodotoxin-resistant sodium channels in rat dorsal root ganglion neurons. J Neurosci. 1992 Jun;12(6):2104-11.</citation>
    <PMID>1318956</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bartfield JM, Homer PJ, Ford DT, Sternklar P. Buffered lidocaine as a local anesthetic: an investigation of shelf life. Ann Emerg Med. 1992 Jan;21(1):16-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1539881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zahl K, Jordan A, McGroarty J, Sorensen B, Gotta AW. Peribulbar anesthesia. Effect of bicarbonate on mixtures of lidocaine, bupivacaine, and hyaluronidase with or without epinephrine. Ophthalmology. 1991 Feb;98(2):239-42.</citation>
    <PMID>2008283</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sinnott CJ, Garfield JM, Thalhammer JG, Strichartz GR. Addition of sodium bicarbonate to lidocaine decreases the duration of peripheral nerve block in the rat. Anesthesiology. 2000 Oct;93(4):1045-52.</citation>
    <PMID>11020760</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richtsmeier AJ, Hatcher JW. Buffered lidocaine for skin infiltration prior to hemodialysis. J Pain Symptom Manage. 1995 Apr;10(3):198-203.</citation>
    <PMID>7629414</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burns CA, Ferris G, Feng C, Cooper JZ, Brown MD. Decreasing the pain of local anesthesia: a prospective, double-blind comparison of buffered, premixed 1% lidocaine with epinephrine versus 1% lidocaine freshly mixed with epinephrine. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2006 Jan;54(1):128-31.</citation>
    <PMID>16384767</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corah NL, Gale EN, Illig SJ. Assessment of a dental anxiety scale. J Am Dent Assoc. 1978 Nov;97(5):816-9.</citation>
    <PMID>31377</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Newton JT, Buck DJ. Anxiety and pain measures in dentistry: a guide to their quality and application. J Am Dent Assoc. 2000 Oct;131(10):1449-57.</citation>
    <PMID>11042984</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heft MW, Parker SR. An experimental basis for revising the graphic rating scale for pain. Pain. 1984 Jun;19(2):153-61.</citation>
    <PMID>6462727</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Whitcomb M, Drum M, Reader A, Nusstein J, Beck M. A prospective, randomized, double-blind study of the anesthetic efficacy of sodium bicarbonate buffered 2% lidocaine with 1:100,000 epinephrine in inferior alveolar nerve blocks. Anesth Prog. 2010 Summer;57(2):59-66. doi: 10.2344/0003-3006-57.2.59.</citation>
    <PMID>20553136</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Corah NL. Development of a dental anxiety scale. J Dent Res. 1969 Jul-Aug;48(4):596.</citation>
    <PMID>5256508</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Catchlove RF. The influence of CO 2 and pH on local anesthetic action. J Pharmacol Exp Ther. 1972 May;181(2):298-309.</citation>
    <PMID>4537424</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ackerman WE 3rd, Ware TR, Juneja M. The air-liquid interface and the pH and PCO2 of alkalinized local anaesthetic solutions. Can J Anaesth. 1992 Apr;39(4):387-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1314142</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benzon HT, Toleikis JR, Dixit P, Goodman I, Hill JA. Onset, intensity of blockade and somatosensory evoked potential changes of the lumbosacral dermatomes after epidural anesthesia with alkalinized lidocaine. Anesth Analg. 1993 Feb;76(2):328-32.</citation>
    <PMID>8424510</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DiFazio CA, Carron H, Grosslight KR, Moscicki JC, Bolding WR, Johns RA. Comparison of pH-adjusted lidocaine solutions for epidural anesthesia. Anesth Analg. 1986 Jul;65(7):760-4.</citation>
    <PMID>3717616</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 31, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 5, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 13, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 7, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 7, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 8, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ohio State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Melissa Drum</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Facies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lidocaine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Racepinephrine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epinephryl borate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>April 24, 2015</submitted>
    <returned>May 11, 2015</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

