<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01985477</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-0624</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2014-01098</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01985477</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Revlimid / All-Trans Retinoic Acid (ATRA) / Dexamethasone in Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I/II Study of Lenalidomide (Revlimid), All-trans Retinoic Acid (ATRA) and Dexamethasone in Patients With Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Celgene Corporation</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of the Phase I portion of this clinical research study is to find the highest
      tolerated dose of the combination of lenalidomide, all-trans retinoic acid (ATRA), and
      dexamethasone that can be given to patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma
      (MM).

      The goal of the Phase II portion of this study is to learn if ATRA when given in combination
      with lenalidomide alone or with lenalidomide and dexamethasone can help to control multiple
      myeloma.

      In September 2015, the study was terminated due to slow accrual while still a Phase I study,
      no additional registration or research performed under the Phase II portion of the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Groups:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will be assigned to a study
      group based on when you joined this study. Up to 2 groups of up to 3-6 patients participants
      will be enrolled in the Phase I portion of the study, and up to 58 participants will be
      enrolled in Phase II.

      If you are enrolled in the Phase I portion, the dose of lenalidomide, dexamethasone, and ATRA
      you receive will depend on when you joined this study. The first group of participants will
      receive the lowest dose level of the combination. Each new group will receive a higher dose
      of the combination than the group before it, if no intolerable side effects were seen. This
      will continue until the highest tolerable dose of the combination of lenalidomide and ATRA is
      found.

      If you are enrolled in the Phase II portion, you will be assigned to 1 of 2 groups based on
      the therapy you were receiving before you began to take part in this study.

        -  If you were receiving lenalidomide alone, you will take lenalidomide and ATRA (Group A).

        -  If you were receiving lenalidomide and dexamethasone when you started this study, you
           will take lenalidomide, dexamethasone, and ATRA (Group B).

      Study Drug Administration:

      Each cycle is 28 days.

      The first part of the study, called induction, will have 3 cycles. After that is the
      maintenance part of the study. You will be able to continue on maintenance for as long as the
      doctor thinks it is in your best interest.

      Induction:

        -  On Day 1-21 of each cycle, you will take lenalidomide by mouth 1 time every day.

        -  On Days 1-21 of each cycle, you will take ATRA by mouth 2 times each day.

        -  On Days 1, 8, 15, and 22 of each cycle (+/- 3 days), you will take dexamethasone by
           mouth.

      Maintenance:

        -  On Day 1-21 of each cycle, you will take lenalidomide by mouth 1 time every day.

        -  On Days 1-14 of each cycle, you will take ATRA by mouth 2 times each day.

        -  If you are in Group A, on Days 1, 8, 15, and 22 of each cycle (+/- 3 days), you will
           take dexamethasone by mouth.

      If a dose of lenalidomide is missed or vomited, you should continue with the regular schedule
      of the drug at the next dose, and a missed dose should NOT be made up.

      Lenalidomide capsules should be swallowed whole, and should not be broken, chewed or opened.
      If you take more than the prescribed dose of lenalidomide, you should seek emergency medical
      care if needed and contact study staff right away

      Study Visits:

      Induction Study Visits:

      On Days 1, 8, and 15 of Cycle 1:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 3 tablespoon) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  Urine will be collected over 24 hours to check the status of the disease (Day 1 only).

      Between Days 19 and 21 of Cycle 1, you will have a bone marrow aspiration and blood (about 1
      teaspoon) will be drawn to measure the levels of certain proteins for research purposes.

      On about Day 1 of Cycles 2-3:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 3 tablespoons) will be drawn for routine tests

        -  Blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn to measure proteins in your blood.

        -  Urine will be collected over 24 hours to check the status of the disease.

      If your doctor thinks it is needed, the visits may take place more often. You may have extra
      visits at any time during the study if your doctor thinks it is needed for your care.

      Maintenance Therapy Study Visits:

      Once a month during Maintenance Therapy:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  Blood (about 1 teaspoon) will be drawn to measure proteins in your blood.

        -  Urine will be collected over 24 hours to check the status of the disease.

        -  If the doctor thinks it is needed, you will have a bone marrow biopsy to check the
           status of the disease.

      Length of Study:

      You will receive up to 3 cycles of the study drugs during induction. You may continue taking
      the study drugs during maintenance for as long as the doctor thinks it is in your best
      interest. You will no longer be able to take the study drug if the disease gets worse if
      intolerable side effects occur, or you are unable to follow study directions.

      Your participation on this study will be over after the end-of-study visit.

      End-of-Study Visit:

      If you go off study for any reason, you will have an end-of-study visit. This is usually done
      about 30 days after the last dose of the study drugs. At this visit, the following tests and
      procedures will be performed:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 2-3 teaspoons) and urine (over 24 hours) will be collected to check the
           status of the disease.

        -  Blood (about 1 tablespoon) will be drawn for routine tests.

        -  If the doctor thinks it is needed, you will have a bone marrow biopsy to check the
           status of the disease.

      This is an investigational study. ATRA is FDA approved and commercially available to treat
      acute promyelocytic leukemia.

      Lenalidomide is FDA approved and commercially available to treat MM.

      Dexamethasone is FDA approved and commercially available to treat inflammation and allergic
      conditions and to manage the symptoms of several types of leukemia and lymphoma.

      The combination of ATRA, lenalidomide, and dexamethasone is investigational.

      Up to 70 participants will be enrolled in this study. All will take part at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Terminated Phase I due to slow accrual without progression to Phase II.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum Tolerated Dose (MTD) of Lenalidomide/Dexamethasone and All-Trans Retinoic Acid (ATRA)</measure>
    <time_frame>28 days</time_frame>
    <description>MTD defined as highest dose level in which 6 patients have been treated with less than 2 instances of dose limiting toxicity (DLT). Dose limiting toxicity refers to a medically significant event which meets one of the following:
Hematologic dose-limiting toxicity defined as either, Grade 4 neutropenia lasting for &gt;/=14 days in duration ( growth factors permitted after DLT established), Grade 4 thrombocytopenia &gt; 14 days despite platelet transfusions.
Non-hematologic DLT defined as any Grade 3, 4 or 5 non-hematologic toxicity, with the specific exception of, Isolated Grade 3 elevation of liver function tests (LFTs) without associated clinical symptoms, lasting for &lt;/=7 days in duration, Isolated Grade 3 elevation of amylase without associated clinical symptoms, Grade 3 hypocalcemia, hyperglycemia, hypokalemia, hypomagnesemia, hyponatremia, or hypophosphatemia which responds to medical intervention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective Response</measure>
    <time_frame>After 4, 28 day cycles</time_frame>
    <description>The objective response (complete response + partial response) at 4 cycles is the primary endpoint. Patients assessed for response each cycle of therapy according to International Myeloma Working Group Criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2</enrollment>
  <condition>Myeloma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone + All-Trans Retinoic Acid (ATRA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Phase I All Patients - Induction: Lenalidomide starting dose 25 mg by mouth 1 time every day on Day 1-21. Dexamethasone starting dose 40 mg by mouth on Days 1,8,15,22. ATRA starting dose 25 mg/m2 by mouth 2 times each day on Days 1-21.
Phase II Group A: Lenalidomide starting dose: Dose tolerated prior to enrollment. Dexamethasone starting dose: Dose previously on when progressing prior to study entry. ATRA starting dose: MTD from Phase I.
Maintenance Therapy Group A: Lenalidomide at dose level tolerated at completion of cycle 3 for 21/28 days, with ATRA at dose determined in Phase I for 14/28 days, and Dexamethasone at last tolerated dose on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22. After 3 months on therapy at MTD in Phase I study, patients must be switched to this dose schedule. Patients unable to tolerate either Dexamethasone during maintenance phase may dose reduce Dexamethasone as needed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide + All-Trans Retinoic Acid (ATRA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Phase II Group B: Lenalidomide will be given as a single oral dose at the level patient was on at the time of progression on single agent Lenalidomide prior to study enrollment. All-Trans Retinoic Acid (ATRA) starting dose: MTD from Phase I.
Maintenance Therapy: Maintenance therapy consists of lenalidomide at the dose level tolerated at the completion of cycle 3 for 21/28 days, with ATRA at the dose determined in the phase I portion of the trial for 14/28 days. Dexamethasone will not be administered. After 3 months on therapy at the MTD in the phase 1 study, patients must be switched to this dose schedule.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lenalidomide</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase I All Patients - Induction: Lenalidomide starting dose 25 mg by mouth 1 time every day on Day 1-21.
Phase II Group A: Lenalidomide starting dose: Dose tolerated prior to enrollment.
Maintenance Therapy: Phase I and Phase II Group A: Maintenance therapy lenalidomide at dose level tolerated at completion of cycle 3 for 21/28 days.
Phase II Group B: Lenalidomide will be given as a single oral dose at the level patient was on at the time of progression on single agent lenalidomide prior to study enrollment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone + All-Trans Retinoic Acid (ATRA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide + All-Trans Retinoic Acid (ATRA)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CC-5013</other_name>
    <other_name>Revlimid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Dexamethasone</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase I All Patients - Induction: Dexamethasone starting dose 40 mg by mouth on Days 1,8,15,22.
Phase II Group A: Dexamethasone starting dose: Dose previously on when progressing prior to study entry.
Maintenance Therapy: Phase I and Phase II Group A: Dexamethasone at last tolerated dose on Days 1, 8, 15 and 22.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone + All-Trans Retinoic Acid (ATRA)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Decadron</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>All-Trans Retinoic Acid (ATRA)</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase I All Patients - Induction: ATRA starting dose 25 mg/m2 by mouth 2 times each day on Days 1-21.
Phase II Group A: ATRA starting dose: MTD from Phase I.
Maintenance Therapy: Phase I and Phase II Group A: ATRA at dose determined in Phase I for 14/28 days.
Phase II Group B: All-Trans Retinoic Acid (ATRA) starting dose: MTD from Phase I.
Maintenance Therapy Group B: ATRA at the dose determined in the Phase I portion of the trial for 14/28 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide + Dexamethasone + All-Trans Retinoic Acid (ATRA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Lenalidomide + All-Trans Retinoic Acid (ATRA)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ATRA</other_name>
    <other_name>Tretinoin (Oral)</other_name>
    <other_name>Vesanoid</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Understand and voluntarily sign an informed consent form

          2. Age &gt;/= 18 years at the time of signing the informed consent form

          3. Serum creatinine &lt;/= 2.5 mg/dl OR Creatine clearance &gt; 30 ml/min

          4. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status score of 0, 1, or 2

          5. Females of childbearing potential (FCBP)* must have a negative serum or urine
             pregnancy test with a sensitivity of at least 50 mlU/mL within 10-14 days prior to and
             again within 24 hours of starting lenalidomide and must either commit to continued
             abstinence from heterosexual intercourse or begin TWO acceptable methods of birth
             control, one highly effective method and one additional affective method AT THE SAME
             TIME, at least 28 days before she starts taking lenalidomide. FCBP must also agree to
             ongoing pregnancy testing. Men must agree to use a latex condom during sexual contact
             with a female of childbearing potential even if they have had a successful vasectomy.
             All patients must be counseled at a minimum of every 28 days about pregnancy
             precautions and risks of fetal exposure.

          6. Continuation from Inclusion #5: *A female of childbearing potential is a sexually
             mature woman who: 1) has not undergone a hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy; or 2)
             has not been naturally postmenopausal for at least 24 consecutive months (i.e., has
             had menses at any time in the preceding 24 consecutive months).

          7. Able to take prophylactic antiplatelet/anticoagulation, warfarin or equivalent agent

          8. Patient is able to understand and comply with the terms and conditions of the
             Lenalidomide Counseling Program.

          9. Phase I Specific Inclusion Criteria: Multiple myeloma that has progressed on
             lenalidomide and dexamethasone combination therapy at a dose of 25 mg daily on
             lenalidomide and 40 mg weekly of dexamethasone with measurable levels of myeloma
             paraprotein in serum ( &gt;/= 0.5 g/dl), urine ( &gt;/= 0.2 g excreted in a 24-hour
             collection sample), or abnormal free light chain (FLC) ratio.

         10. Phase I Specific Inclusion Criteria: Laboratory test results within these ranges:
             Absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1000 cells/mm^3; Platelet count &gt; 100,000 cells/mm^3 for
             patients with &lt; 50% of bone marrow plasma cells and platelet count &gt; 50,000 cells/mm^3
             for patients in whom &gt; 50% of the bone marrow nucleated cells were plasma cells; Total
             bilirubin &lt;/= 2.0 mg/dL; AST (SGOT) and ALT (AGPT) &lt; 3 x upper limits of normal (ULN)

         11. Phase II Specific Inclusion Criteria: Cohort A: Multiple myeloma that has progressed
             on lenalidomide and dexamethasone combination therapy with measurable levels of
             myeloma paraprotein in serum ( &gt;/= 0.5 g/dl), urine ( &gt;/= 0.2 g excreted in a 24-hour
             collection sample), or involved FLC level by more than 10 mg/dL and abnormal free
             light chain (FLC) ratio. Cohort B: Multiple myeloma that has progressed on single
             agent lenalidomide therapy with measurable disease defined as: doubling of the
             M-component in 2 consecutive measurements in less than or equal to 2 months OR
             increase in serum M-protein levels by &gt;/= .5g or urine protein by 200mg/24 hours, or
             involved FLC level by more than 10 mg/dL (with an abnormal FLC ratio).

         12. Phase II Specific Inclusion Criteria: Laboratory test results within these ranges:
             Absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1000 cells/mm^3; Platelet count &gt; 75,000 cells/mm^3 for
             patients with &lt; 50% of bone marrow plasma cells and platelet count &gt; 50,000 cells/mm^3
             for patients in whom &gt; 50% of the bone marrow nucleated cells were plasma cells; Total
             bilirubin &lt;/= 2.0 mg/dL; AST (SGOT) and ALT (AGPT) &lt; 3 x ULN

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any serious medical condition, or psychiatric illness that would prevent the subject
             from signing the informed consent form.

          2. Pregnant or breast feeding females. (Lactating females must agree not to breast feed
             while taking lenalidomide).

          3. Use of any cancer therapy within 14 days prior to beginning cycle 1 day 1 of therapy
             with the exception of lenalidomide and dexamethasone (radiation therapy allowed within
             5 days of completion of radiation therapy)

          4. Known hypersensitivity to lenalidomide or ATRA.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jatin J. Shah, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 8, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 8, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 15, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 12, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 12, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 14, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>Multiple myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>MM</keyword>
  <keyword>Relapsed/Refractory Multiple Myeloma</keyword>
  <keyword>RR MM</keyword>
  <keyword>Lenalidomide</keyword>
  <keyword>CC-5013</keyword>
  <keyword>Revlimid</keyword>
  <keyword>Dexamethasone</keyword>
  <keyword>Decadron</keyword>
  <keyword>All-Trans Retinoic Acid</keyword>
  <keyword>ATRA</keyword>
  <keyword>Tretinoin (Oral)</keyword>
  <keyword>Vesanoid</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Multiple Myeloma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Plasma Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone acetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dexamethasone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lenalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Thalidomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tretinoin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>BB 1101</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

