<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01350193</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MHI-2011</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01350193</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Manuka Honey Irrigation After Sinus Surgery</brief_title>
  <official_title>Manuka Honey Irrigation After Endoscopic Sinus Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>St. Paul's Hospital, Canada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>St. Paul's Hospital, Canada</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      All adult (over 19 years) patients undergoing sinus surgery for chronic rhinosinusitis (CRS)
      or allergic fungal sinusitis (AFS) that do not meet the exclusion criteria will be included
      in the study.

      All participants enrolled in the study will receive antibiotic (Clavulin) therapy 1-week
      pre-and post-operatively and oral steroid therapy 1-week pre-operatively and
      post-operatively.

      Randomization of patients to the Manuka Honey irrigation (treatment arm) and Saline
      irrigation (standard of care) will occur on the day of surgery.

      Participants in both study arms will undergo the standard post-operative endoscopic sinus
      surgery follow-up. This includes follow-up appointments at 6 days, 5 weeks, 3 months, and 6
      months of the post-operative period. During these appointments, the surgeon will assess the
      post-operative appearance (Philpott-Javer Sinus Rating System), number of infections, pain,
      and 1st week post-operative bleeding (only at 6 day visit).

      The Sino-Nasal Outcome Test (SNOT-22) questionnaire is to be completed by the study
      participants at 6 days, 5 weeks, and 3 months of the post-operative period. The SNOT-22 is a
      5-minute questionnaire consisting of 22 questions, which asks participants to rate their
      sinus symptoms and social/emotional consequences of their nasal disorder from &quot;no problem&quot; to
      &quot;problem as bad as it can be.&quot;
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All patients in this study will undergo endoscopic sinus surgery. This is the mainstay of
      treatment for patients with refractory sinus disease.

      All patients that undergo endoscopic sinus surgery must routinely complete nasal irrigations
      to maintain the patency of the sinuses and to encourage healing. The current standard of
      treatment is saline irrigations. Manuka honey has already shown promise in the field of wound
      healing. The Manuka Honey will be used as the treatment arm in this study and will be
      compared to the current standard of care, the saline irrigations.

      Once the subjects have signed the consent form, they will undergo endoscopic sinus surgery as
      planned. Randomization (using sealed envelopes) will occur immediately after surgery where
      patient will receive either the Honey rinse or Saline rinse. There will be 50 envelopes
      containing a sheet of paper stating &quot;Manuka Honey Irrigation&quot; and another 50 envelopes
      containing a sheet of paper stating &quot;Saline Irrigation.&quot; These envelopes will be sealed,
      marked with &quot;Nasal Irrigation Study&quot; on the front of the envelope, and mixed in a random
      fashion. Immediately after surgery, one of these envelopes will be selected to randomize the
      patient to either the Manuka Honey or Saline irrigation arms. As this is a single-blinded
      study, the patients will know to which arm they are assigned to, while the primary
      investigator is blinded.

      The standard treatment, as described involves nasal irrigation using a saline solution. This
      will constitute one arm of the study. The treatment arm will involve the use of the
      pasteurized Manuka honey nasal irrigation, which is not currently the standard of practice,
      but is approved by Health Canada to be used for this indication. The subject will use 30cc of
      the nasal irrigation (to which they are randomized) in each nostril twice daily (once in am,
      once in pm). No other specific manipulations will be used. The SNOT-22 questionnaire will be
      administered before the patient is assessed by the clinic physician at 6 days, 5 weeks, and 3
      months post-operatively. Patients will not be blinded to the irrigation they are assigned to.
      The investigators will not know to which arm the subjects have been assigned to.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative endoscopic appearance</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of post op standard of care, an expected average of 6 months.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-Operative SNOT-22</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of post op standard of care, an expected average of 6 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Sino-Nasal Outcome Test (SNOT-22) is current standard in Rhinology for the assessment of the patient's subjective sinus symptoms and its effect on their daily functioning. It is composed of 22 questions, which ask patients to rate their symptoms on a scale of 0-5 (0=no problem, 5=problem as bad as it can be). Questions include patients perceived nasal congestion/blockage, facial pain, fatigue, sadness, etc. This questionnaire is used as the gold standard for patients to rate their subjective symptoms.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative bleeding</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of post op standard of care, an expected average of 6 months.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-operative pain</measure>
    <time_frame>Participants will be followed for the duration of post op standard of care, an expected average of 6 months.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">78</enrollment>
  <condition>Sinusitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Saline Nasal Irrigation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Saline Nasal Irrigation is actively being used as the standard of care. It does not contain any active ingredients.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Manuka Honey Irrigation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Manuka Honey Irrigation involves the experimental treatment of manuka honey nasal irrigation.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Manuka Honey</intervention_name>
    <description>The use of the nasal irrigation on post-operative day #1. 30mL of the nasal irrigation will be applied to each nostril by a 60mL Toomey syringe (given to patient at pre-operative clinic visit) twice a day (once in am, once in pm). This will continue until the 6 month post-op visit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Manuka Honey Irrigation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Irrigation</other_name>
    <other_name>Endoscopic Sinus Surgery</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline Irrigation</intervention_name>
    <description>The use of the nasal irrigation on post-operative day #1. 30mL of the nasal irrigation will be applied to each nostril by a 60mL Toomey syringe (given to patient at pre-operative clinic visit) twice a day (once in am, once in pm). This will continue until the 6 month post-op visit.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Saline Nasal Irrigation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Control</other_name>
    <other_name>Endoscopic Sinus Surgery</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ability to provide informed consent.

          -  Adult (over 19 years of age) patients undergoing sinus surgery for chronic
             rhinosinusitis (CRS) or allergic fungal sinusitis (AFS).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Co-morbidities, eg. Hypertension, Cardiac Disease, Coagulopathy, CF, Sampter's triad,
             Diabetes, liver failure

          -  Medication, eg. Anticoagulants, statins, anti-hypertensives

          -  Allergies to honey, bee stings
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amin R Javer, MD, FRCSC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>St. Paul's Hospital, Canada</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ENT Clinic, St. Paul's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vancouver</city>
        <state>British Columbia</state>
        <zip>V6Z 1Y6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cooper R. Using honey to inhibit wound pathogens. Nurs Times. 2008 Jan 22-28;104(3):46, 48-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18293880</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>English HK, Pack AR, Molan PC. The effects of manuka honey on plaque and gingivitis: a pilot study. J Int Acad Periodontol. 2004 Apr;6(2):63-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15125017</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Armstrong DG. Manuka honey improved wound healing in patients with sloughy venous leg ulcers. Evid Based Med. 2009 Oct;14(5):148. doi: 10.1136/ebm.14.5.148.</citation>
    <PMID>19794023</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Alandejani T, Marsan J, Ferris W, Slinger R, Chan F. Effectiveness of honey on Staphylococcus aureus and Pseudomonas aeruginosa biofilms. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2009 Jul;141(1):114-8. doi: 10.1016/j.otohns.2009.01.005. Epub 2009 Mar 9.</citation>
    <PMID>19559969</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 3, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 6, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 9, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 2, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 2, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 4, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>St. Paul's Hospital, Canada</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Amin Javer</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD FRCSC FARS, Principal Investigator, Director of St Paul's Sinus Centre</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Manuka Honey</keyword>
  <keyword>Irrigation</keyword>
  <keyword>Endoscopic Sinus Surgery</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sinusitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

