<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01351220</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RSGT CPPB-119384</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01351220</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Community Dissemination of an Evidence-based Colorectal Cancer (CRC) Screening Intervention</brief_title>
  <official_title>Community Dissemination of an Evidence-based CRC Screening Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>American Cancer Society, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jonsson Comprehensive Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Filipino Americans have lower rates of colorectal cancer (CRC) screening, later stage of
      diagnosis and poorer survival relative to other racial/ethnic groups. To address this
      disparity, the investigators developed a multi-component intervention to increase CRC
      screening and have determined its efficacy in a randomized trial (Maxwell,et. al., 2010).
      This study aims to determine how an intervention to increase CRC screening can best be
      integrated within the cultural norms and existing structures of churches and community based
      organizations (CBOs) with predominantly Filipino American membership to ensure broad
      dissemination to those in need of screening.

      The investigators will provide our partner CBOs with resources and technical assistance,
      including training of community volunteers as health advisors, to enable them to promote CRC
      screening to their constituents. Using a scientifically rigorous research design, the
      investigators will compare two dissemination strategies: Basic dissemination which consists
      of a single kick-off event during which community health advisors will receive print
      materials and FOBT kits for distribution and training on how to conduct educational
      small-group sessions; and Organizational dissemination aimed at integrating CRC screening
      dissemination into organizational practices and processes that can be sustained after the end
      of the study. The study will be implemented in 20 CBOs and will train 100 community health
      advisors (CHAs). The impact of the two dissemination strategies will be comprehensively
      assessed by collecting data at the CBO level, from the CHAs and from 1000 Filipino American
      participants. The investigators will compare the proportion of Filipino American participants
      who obtain CRC screening by dissemination strategy, but the investigators will also assess
      how many are reached, if the intervention is implemented as planned, how CBOs support the
      screening efforts at their regular activities, and if CBOs and CHAs maintain their efforts
      over the 4 years of the study.

      The investigators hypothesize that CBOs can implement evidence-based strategies to promote
      CRC screening and CHAs in the organizational dissemination arm will reach more participants
      and more screened participants than CHAs in the basic dissemination arm; and organizations in
      the organizational dissemination arm will adopt more CRC screening activities and maintain
      these better than organizations in the basic dissemination arm.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Screening</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in receipt of CRC screening at 6 months and 24 months</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 6-month and 24-month post intervention</time_frame>
    <description>Subjects will receive any one of the 3 recommended CRC screening tests namely, Fecal Occult Blood Test, Flexible sigmoidoscopy or Colonoscopy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in intention to obtain screening at 6 months and 24 months</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 6-months and 24-months after exposure to the intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in CRC screening knowledge at 6 months and 24 months</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 6 months and 24 months after exposure to the educational program</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in frequency of patient provider communication at 6 months and 24 months</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, 6 and 24 months after exposure to the intervention</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1100</enrollment>
  <condition>Colon Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Rectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Basic dissemination</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Organizational dissemination</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Educational program and FOBT kits</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will participate in a CRC small group educational program and receive FOBT kits from community health advisors who have received a one-time training session.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Basic dissemination</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Educational program and FOBT kits, and technical assistance</intervention_name>
    <description>In addition to subjects' receipt of a CRC small group educational program and FOBT kits, leadership training and technical support will be provided to the community health advisors and selected leaders and members of the organization.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Organizational dissemination</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Filipino American

          -  50 to 75 years of age

          -  Must not have been diagnosed with CRC

          -  Must not be adherent to USPSTF CRC screening guidelines

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Not Filipino American

          -  Younger than 50 or older than 75 years of age

          -  Have been diagnosed with CRC

          -  Adherent to USPSTF CRC screening guidelines
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Annette E Maxwell, Dr.P.H.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Leda L Danao, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCLA Division of Cancer and Prevention Research</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90095-6900</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Maxwell AE, Bastani R, Danao LL, Antonio C, Garcia GM, Crespi CM. Results of a community-based randomized trial to increase colorectal cancer screening among Filipino Americans. Am J Public Health. 2010 Nov;100(11):2228-34. doi: 10.2105/AJPH.2009.176230. Epub 2010 Sep 23.</citation>
    <PMID>20864724</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 6, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 9, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 10, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 28, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 28, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 1, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CRC screening</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention and early detection of CRC</keyword>
  <keyword>Filipino</keyword>
  <keyword>Dissemination</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

