<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01352676</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HS018322</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01352676</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Limit Computed Tomography (CT) Scanning in Suspected Renal Colic</brief_title>
  <acronym>Prospective</acronym>
  <official_title>Validation of a Decision Rule to Limit CT Scanning in Suspected Renal Colic</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yale University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality (AHRQ)</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yale University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Computed tomography (CT) scanning is overused, expensive, and causes cancer. CT scan
      utilization in the U.S. has increased from an estimated 3 million CTs in 1980 to 62 million
      per year in 2007. From 2000 through 2006, Medicare spending on imaging more than doubled to
      $13.8 billion with advanced imaging such as CT scanning largely responsible. CT represents
      only 11% of radiologic examinations but is responsible for two-thirds of the ionizing
      radiation associated with medical imaging in the U.S. Recent estimates suggest that there
      will be 12.5 cancer deaths for every 10,000 CT scans. Renal colic is a common,
      non-life-threatening condition for which CT is overused. As many as 12% of people will have a
      kidney stone in their lifetime, and more than one million per year will present to the
      emergency department (ED). CT is now a first line test for renal colic, and is very accurate.
      However, 98% of kidney stones 5mm or smaller will pass spontaneously, and CT rarely alters
      management. A decision rule is needed to determine which patients with suspected renal colic
      require CT. While the signs and symptoms of renal colic have been shown to be predictable, no
      rule has yet been rigorously derived or validated to guide CT imaging in renal colic. A
      subset of patients with suspected renal colic may have a more serious diagnosis or a kidney
      stone that will require intervention; however the investigators maintain that clinical
      criteria, point of care ultrasound and plain radiography (when appropriate), will provide a
      more comparatively effective and safer approach by appropriately limiting imaging.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Study Aim: The specific aim of this study is to prospectively validate the previously derived
      decision rule for obtaining a Flank Pain Protocol (FPP) CT scan in suspected renal colic.

      The investigators will integrate the derived clinical decision rule from the ongoing
      retrospective analysis with gestalt clinician pre-test probability, point of care ultrasound,
      and plain radiography (when appropriate) to prospectively and observationally test the rule
      at two distinct clinical settings. CT results and 90-day follow-up will be used to determine
      predefined outcomes.

      Study Hypothesis: Prospective observational testing of a clinical decision rule, combined
      with point of care ultrasound and plain radiography when appropriate, will categorize &gt;85% of
      patients who will require intervention, validating a decision rule to avoid unnecessary CT.

      This amendment comes from recent evidence and work at our institution to develop an
      &quot;ultra-low dose&quot; CT scan protocol (ULDCT) with an effective radiation dose close to that of a
      plain film of the abdomen (KUB), or near 1mSv (compared to 8.5mSv in current practice). While
      we expect the ULDCT to be better than a KUB at localizing and characterizing kidney stones,
      what is unknown is how the loss in resolution with an ultra-low dose CT protocol might affect
      this localization and characterization of stones relative to a regular dose CT (current
      protocol), as well as the ability to find alternate diagnoses. Incorporating this additional
      imaging study in a subgroup of patients during the observational phase will allow us to
      determine test characteristics of the ULDCT that will allow incorporation into the
      prospective phase. This will hopefully provide excellent evidence about how to implement an
      ultra-low dose CT scan in practice, ultimately leading to a dramatic reduction in radiation
      exposure for a large number of patients at Yale and other sites.

      We filed an amendment 11-15-2011. This amendment comes from recent evidence and work at our
      institution to develop an &quot;ultra-low dose&quot; CT scan protocol (ULDCT) with an effective
      radiation dose close to that of a plain film of the abdomen (KUB), or near 1mSv (compared to
      8.5mSv in current practice). While we expect the ULDCT to be better than a KUB at localizing
      and characterizing kidney stones, what is unknown is how the loss in resolution with an
      ultra-low dose CT protocol might affect this localization and characterization of stones
      relative to a regular dose CT (current protocol), as well as the ability to find alternate
      diagnoses. Incorporating this additional imaging study in a subgroup of patients during the
      observational phase will allow us to determine test characteristics of the ULDCT that will
      allow incorporation into the prospective phase. This will hopefully provide excellent
      evidence about how to implement an ultra-low dose CT scan in practice, ultimately leading to
      a dramatic reduction in radiation exposure for a large number of patients at Yale and other
      sites.

      This amendment comes from recent evidence and work at our institution to develop an
      &quot;ultra-low dose&quot; CT scan protocol (ULDCT) with an effective radiation dose close to that of a
      plain film of the abdomen (KUB), or near 1mSv (compared to 8.5mSv in current practice). While
      we expect the ULDCT to be better than a KUB at localizing and characterizing kidney stones,
      what is unknown is how the loss in resolution with an ultra-low dose CT protocol might affect
      this localization and characterization of stones relative to a regular dose CT (current
      protocol), as well as the ability to find alternate diagnoses. Incorporating this additional
      imaging study in a subgroup of patients during the observational phase will allow us to
      determine test characteristics of the ULDCT that will allow incorporation into the
      prospective phase. This will hopefully provide excellent evidence about how to implement an
      ultra-low dose CT scan in practice, ultimately leading to a dramatic reduction in radiation
      exposure for a large number of patients at Yale and other sites.

      Future Direction: Ultimately the investigators intend to implement the validated decision
      rule at both study sites to evaluate further the feasibility, physician acceptance and
      comparative effectiveness of our rule. Using standard dissemination techniques and
      integration of the rule into the computerized physician order entry (CPOE) system at our
      institutions the investigators will determine the actual reduction in the number of FPP CT
      scans ordered, clinical outcomes based on 90-day follow up, survey of physician acceptance of
      the rule as well as an comparative effective analysis. The investigators will submit an
      application at a later date nearing the end of our projected enrollment for this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ultra Low Dose vs Regular CT Scans</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline-90 Days</time_frame>
    <description>both the CT results and the follow-up documentation will be reviewed by two separate MD observers who are blinded to both the predictor variables and the outcome of the decision rule. CT results will be categorized as defined above, and intervention as defined above will either be considered present (immediate or delayed) or absent based on follow-up documentation. In the case where there is a discrepancy in the categorization of CT or intervention, a third reviewer will be used as a tie-breaker, with discussion amongst all parties to reach a consensus if this is not clear.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">635</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Colic</condition>
  <condition>Flank Pain</condition>
  <condition>Back Pain</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The target population will be all patients aged 18 or above presenting to the Yale New
        Haven Hospital (YNHH) ED and Shoreline Medical Center (SMC) ED for whom a FPP CT scan is
        ordered by the treating physician for suspected renal colic. A total of 800-1000 patients
        will be enrolled over a 1.5 year period 6-2011 to 1-2013, matching the sex/race/ethnicity
        makeup of that found for the retrospective study.

        The population of the primary catchment area for YNHH is 350,000 and includes a diverse
        ethnic and cultural mix. Women and minorities are strongly represented in the population.
        Women represent approximately 51% of the ED population. The racial mix is approximately 50%
        White, not of Hispanic Origin; 33% Black, not of Hispanic Origin, 15% Hispanic; 1% Asian
        and 1% other. The ethnicity of SMC patients is mostly White and 54% female.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who present to the adult YNHH ED and Shoreline Medical Center SMC ED who are

               -  18 years or older,

               -  renal colic is suspected upon presentation to the ED suggested by flank pain,
                  back pain, abdominal pain, and/or hematuria, and

               -  the physician intends to order a CT FPP study for suspicion of a kidney stone.
                  Members of all ethnic and racial groups are eligible.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients will be excluded for any one of the following reasons: patients that are

               -  pregnant

               -  prisoners

               -  unable or unwilling to consent (including non-English speaking) and

               -  with a history or physical evidence of recent trauma.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher L Moore, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yale University School of Medicine, Emergency Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shoreline Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guilford</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06437</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University, Emergency Department</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06519</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brenner DJ, Hall EJ. Computed tomography--an increasing source of radiation exposure. N Engl J Med. 2007 Nov 29;357(22):2277-84. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18046031</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brenner D, Elliston C, Hall E, Berdon W. Estimated risks of radiation-induced fatal cancer from pediatric CT. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2001 Feb;176(2):289-96.</citation>
    <PMID>11159059</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Medicare Part B Imaging Services. General Accounting Office. Washington D.C., 2008.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mettler FA Jr, Wiest PW, Locken JA, Kelsey CA. CT scanning: patterns of use and dose. J Radiol Prot. 2000 Dec;20(4):353-9.</citation>
    <PMID>11140709</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kalra MK, Maher MM, Toth TL, Hamberg LM, Blake MA, Shepard JA, Saini S. Strategies for CT radiation dose optimization. Radiology. 2004 Mar;230(3):619-28. Epub 2004 Jan 22. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14739312</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jindal G, Ramchandani P. Acute flank pain secondary to urolithiasis: radiologic evaluation and alternate diagnoses. Radiol Clin North Am. 2007 May;45(3):395-410, vii. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17601499</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baumgarten DA, Francis IR, Bluth EI, Bush WH, Imaging EPoU. ACR Appropriateness Criteria® acute onset flank pain, suspicion of stone disease. American College of Radiology; 2007</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Teichman JM. Clinical practice. Acute renal colic from ureteral calculus. N Engl J Med. 2004 Feb 12;350(7):684-93. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14960744</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ripollés T, Errando J, Agramunt M, Martínez MJ. Ureteral colic: US versus CT. Abdom Imaging. 2004 Mar-Apr;29(2):263-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15290956</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Catalano O, Nunziata A, Altei F, Siani A. Suspected ureteral colic: primary helical CT versus selective helical CT after unenhanced radiography and sonography. AJR Am J Roentgenol. 2002 Feb;178(2):379-87.</citation>
    <PMID>11804898</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gottlieb RH, La TC, Erturk EN, Sotack JL, Voci SL, Holloway RG, Syed L, Mikityansky I, Tirkes AT, Elmarzouky R, Zwemer FL, Joseph JV, Davis D, DiGrazio WJ, Messing EM. CT in detecting urinary tract calculi: influence on patient imaging and clinical outcomes. Radiology. 2002 Nov;225(2):441-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12409578</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ripollés T, Agramunt M, Errando J, Martínez MJ, Coronel B, Morales M. Suspected ureteral colic: plain film and sonography vs unenhanced helical CT. A prospective study in 66 patients. Eur Radiol. 2004 Jan;14(1):129-36. Epub 2003 Jun 19.</citation>
    <PMID>12819916</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Broder J, Bowen J, Lohr J, Babcock A, Yoon J. Cumulative CT exposures in emergency department patients evaluated for suspected renal colic. J Emerg Med. 2007 Aug;33(2):161-8. Epub 2007 Jun 5.</citation>
    <PMID>17692768</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elton TJ, Roth CS, Berquist TH, Silverstein MD. A clinical prediction rule for the diagnosis of ureteral calculi in emergency departments. J Gen Intern Med. 1993 Feb;8(2):57-62.</citation>
    <PMID>8441076</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 10, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 11, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 12, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 9, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>renal colic</keyword>
  <keyword>flank pain</keyword>
  <keyword>back pain</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Back Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Colic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Flank Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

