<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01350648</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>110152</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>11-CC-0152</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01350648</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Long-Term Study of Liver Disease in People With Hepatitis B and/or Hepatitis C With or Without HIV Infection</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Natural History of Liver Disease in a Cohort of Participants With Hepatitis B and/or Hepatitis C With or Without HIV Infection</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Washington D.C. Veterans Affairs Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Hepatitis B and hepatitis C can cause liver damage. They can also cause serious illness,
      including liver cancer, and even death. This study will follow people who have hepatitis B or
      hepatitis C. The purpose is to understand more about how these viruses affect the immune
      system over the long term (up to 10 years). The study will also compare how these viruses
      affect people who do and do not have HIV, the virus that causes AIDS.

      Objectives:

        -  To do a long-term study of hepatitis B and hepatitis C infection.

        -  To study the effects of hepatitis B and hepatitis C infection in people do and do not
           have HIV.

      Eligibility:

      - People at least 18 years of age who have hepatitis B or hepatitis C and have a regular
      doctor for their medical care.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. Those who do not
           have a regular doctor to provide medical care during the study will not be able to take
           part.

        -  Participants will have yearly visits with study researchers for up to 10 years. These
           tests will be done at each visit.

        -  Medical history and physical exam.

        -  Questionnaire (optional) on emotions, sexual behaviors, use of alcohol and drugs, and
           quality of life.

        -  Blood and urine tests, including HIV testing.

        -  Tissue sample collections for those who have had a liver or other tissue biopsy.

        -  Participants may leave the study at any time. They will receive the standard of care
           from their regular doctor throughout the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Chronic hepatitis is a major health problem with hepatitis B virus (HBV) affecting upwards of
      350 million people worldwide and over one million in the United States, while hepatitis C
      virus (HCV) infects as many as 70-130 million people worldwide, and approximately 4.1 million
      (1.6% of the US population) in the United States. HBV and HCV are both transmitted sexually,
      perinatally and percutaneously, although each virus has differing infectivity rates depending
      on the mode of transmission. The immunosuppressed population, especially those with HIV
      infection, remains at particular risk given common routes of transmission. The incidence of
      hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is increasing in the US and worldwide, with high rates in
      those who are cirrhotic, and is the 10th most common cause of death in the US.

      The prevalence rates of HIV in Washington DC are likely 3%. HIV-hepatitis coinfection is
      problematic in that HIV patients are currently living longer on highly active antiretroviral
      therapy (HAART) but often die of complications from liver disease, including HCC. Those who
      are coinfected with HBV and/or HCV progress more rapidly to cirrhosis and hepatic failure.
      Treatment for chronic HBV and HCV is limited, even inadequate, especially in those with HIV
      and HCV coinfection. Further research on the epidemiology, optimal screening and new
      therapeutic approaches in HCC is needed.

      The primary objective of the proposed study is to characterize viral liver disease and
      factors affecting the natural history of viral liver disease in persons with and without HIV
      with an emphasis on those living in the Washington DC metropolitan area. There are few
      longitudinal research cohorts of participants with viral hepatitis and HIV coinfection,
      especially at integrated medical care centers. The study, including a participant
      questionnaire for HCV infected participants only and phlebotomy, will be administered on-site
      at clinical facilities in the District of Columbia and at the National Institutes of Health.
      The cohort will be designed to study research questions with respect to liver disease,
      disease pathogenesis using genomics, proteomics, and immunologic disease models. Secondary
      objectives include study of the immunopathogenesis of HBV and HCV disease progression in HIV
      infected subjects. In addition, this is an invaluable opportunity to determine the prevalence
      and risk factors associated with the development of hepatocellular carcinoma, the longterm
      effects of HCV clearance with DAAs, along with biomarker profile(s) for diagnosis and
      outcome. Moreover, this will serve as a catchment protocol to select appropriate participants
      for novel HBV and HCV therapeutic trials.

      The integrated clinics will provide an optimal environment for the adherence and engagement
      of medical care and education in decreasing transmission risks of infection. The study will
      establish a blood and specimen repository for participants and include a research database
      that will be used prospectively to test future hypotheses.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 11, 2011</start_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2000</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis</condition>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <condition>Liver Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        To be eligible for participation on this protocol, a participant must satisfy all of the
        following conditions:

          1. Be greater than or equal to 18 years old

          2. HBV-infected and/or HCV-infected, or was HCV-infected and successfully treated

          3. Willing to undergo genetic testing

          4. Willingness to allow study staff to review your medical records between research
             visits

          5. Willing to have samples stored for future research

          6. Must have an identifiable primary care physician

          7. Willing to undergo HIV testing

        An HBV infected individual is defined as any individual with documentation of the
        following:

        - Positive Hepatitis B surface antigen within the past 12 months or HBV DNA positive, or
        prior documentation if the individual is currently on active therapy

        An HCV infected individual is defined as any individual with documentation of the following
        in the past:

        - Positive HCV antibody and/or positive HCV RNA test (HCV RNA of 2,000 IU/mL or greater)

        An HIV infected individual is defined as any individual with documentation of the
        following:

        - Positive Enzyme Linked Immunosorbent Assay followed by a positive Western Blot or
        detectable HIV viral load or HIV viral less than 50 copies/mL with documentation this
        individuals is curently on an active HIV antiretroviral regimen.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        A participant will be ineligible to participate on this study if any of the following
        criteria are met:

          1. Unable to comply with research study visits

          2. Poor venous access

          3. Have any condition that the investigator considers a contraindication to study
             participation.

        Co-enrollment Guidelines: Participants may be enrolled in other protocols as long as the
        amount of research blood drawn does not exceed the acceptable NIH guidelines.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>99 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Colleen M Hadigan, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Rachel E Silk, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(202) 857-5219</phone>
    <email>silkr@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Colleen M Hadigan, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 594-5754</phone>
    <email>hadiganc@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Unity Health Care, Inc./Walker Jones</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20002</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Family Medical and Counseling Services</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20020</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VA Medical Center, Washington D.C.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20422</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2011-CC-0152.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lok AS, McMahon BJ. Chronic hepatitis B: update 2009. Hepatology. 2009 Sep;50(3):661-2. doi: 10.1002/hep.23190.</citation>
    <PMID>19714720</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lavanchy D. Hepatitis B virus epidemiology, disease burden, treatment, and current and emerging prevention and control measures. J Viral Hepat. 2004 Mar;11(2):97-107. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14996343</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alter MJ. Epidemiology of viral hepatitis and HIV co-infection. J Hepatol. 2006;44(1 Suppl):S6-9. Epub 2005 Nov 21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16352363</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 30, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 7, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 10, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 30, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Viral Hepatitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Prospective Cohort</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV-HCV Co-Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV-HBV Co-Infection</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis B</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis C</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatitis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis B</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

