<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01353326</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2008058-01H</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01353326</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bone Mineral Density (BMD) in Cemented Versus Cementless Hip Resurfacing</brief_title>
  <official_title>Randomized Clinical Trial of a Cemented Versus Cementless Femoral Component for Metal on Metal Hip Resurfacing Assessing Bone Mineral Density</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Corin</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare the bone mineral density of patients who have
      undergone either cemented or cementless hip resurfacing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recent research is inconclusive regarding the degree to which the density or strength of the
      bone around the hip implant is preserved following a hip resurfacing system. Certainly, there
      are many factors which contribute to the preservation of bone mineral density - we are
      studying the role of cement. More specifically, we are trying to compare outcomes between
      patients who receive the cementless Cormet Hip Resurfacing System to those who receive the
      cemented CONSERVE® Plus Total Resurfacing Hip System. Therefore, the primary purpose of the
      current study is to compare the bone mineral density between the cementless and cemented hip
      resurfacing systems. We are also comparing patients who receive these two different hip
      systems in terms of their x-rays and how they are managing with their hip.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 15, 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent change in BMD (g/cm2)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>The primary outcome is percent change in BMD (g/cm2) from baseline to the 1-year post-operative interval, as measured radiographically in zone L1. Analysis of periprosthetic BMD will be achieved using 6 zones of the femoral neck, which have been used in previous studies</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Implant Migration</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Radiographs will be taken preoperatively and until 24 months post-operatively to assess for any cup loosening. Implant migration, both vertical and horizontal, will be measured on serial radiographs using the computer-assisted Ein Bild Röentgen Analyse (EBRA) software for cup migration.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Harris Hip Score (HHS) Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Harris Hip Score (HHS) is intended to evaluate various hip disabilities and methods of treatment. The HHS is comprised of 4 domains: pain, function, absence of deformity, and range of motion. The score has a maximum of 100 points (best possible outcome) covering pain (1 item, 0-44 points), function (7 items, 0-47 points), absence of deformity (1 item, 4 points), and range of motion (2 items, 5 points). The total score is calculated by summing the scores for the 4 domains. The higher the HHS, the less dysfunction.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>WOMAC Questionnaire to assess functionality</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The Western Ontario and McMaster Universities Osteoarthritis Index (WOMAC) consists of 24 items divided into 3 subscales: Pain (5 items), stiffness (2 items), and function (17 items). This questionnaire is self-administered using the 5-point Likert-type scale (none, mild, moderate, severe, extreme). These correspond to an ordinal scale of 0-4. The scores are summed (0-100), where higher scores are indicative of worse pain, stiffness, and functional limitations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>RAND-36 Item Health Survey</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The RAND-36 Item Health Survey assesses patient health-related quality of life and consists of 8 health concepts: physical functioning (10 items), bodily pain (2 items), role limitations due to physical health problems (4 items), role limitations due to personal or emotional problems (3 items), emotional well-being (5 items), social functioning (2 items), energy/fatigue (4 items), and general health perceptions (5 items). It also includes a single item that provides an indication of perceived change in health. Each item is scored on a 0 to 100 range, with a high score defined as a more favourable health state. Scores are averaged together to create the 8 scale scores.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>UCLA Activity Score</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>The UCLA Activity Score will be used to assess the patients highest-rated activity, regardless of the frequency or intensity of participation. Patients are asked to select 1 out of 10 possible answers that best fit their current activity level (0-10). Low values are indicative of a sedentary lifestyle, while higher values are indicative of high impact activities.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoarthritis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cementless Hip Resurfacing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized into the Cementless Hip Resurfacing Group will have their hip resurfaced with the cementless Cormet / Corin Hip Resurfacing System.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cemented Hip Resurfacing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomized into the Cemented Hip Resurfacing Group will have their hip resurfaced with the cemented Conserve Plus Total Resurfacing Hip System.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cormet</intervention_name>
    <description>Cementless hip resurfacing system</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cementless Hip Resurfacing</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cormet Hip Resurfacing System</other_name>
    <other_name>Corin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Conserve</intervention_name>
    <description>Cemented hip resurfacing system</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cemented Hip Resurfacing</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Conserve Plus Total Resurfacing Hip System</other_name>
    <other_name>Wright</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Must be undergoing primary hip surgery for Noninflammatory Degenerative Joint Disease

          -  must be skeletally mature, as determined by Risser sign or reaching 18 years of age

          -  Is reasonable expectation that patient will remain available for all FU's scheduled
             over course of 5 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous fusions, acute femoral neck fractures, and above knee amputations

          -  evidence of active local infection

          -  neurologic or musculoskeletal disease that may adversely affect gait or weight bearing

          -  having previously undergone ipsilateral hemi resurfacing, total resurfacing, total
             bipolar, unipolar or total hip replacement device

          -  BMI &gt;35

          -  neuropathic joints

          -  severe documented psychiatric disease

          -  patients requiring structural bone grafts

          -  documented allergy to cobalt chromium molybdenum

          -  ipsilateral girdlestone

          -  sickle cell disease

          -  significant femoral head or neck deformity, or significant acetabular wall deficiency

          -  patients with renal failure, defined as serum creatinine greater that 180 µmol/L
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dr. Paul Beaule, MD, FRCSC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ottawa General Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ottawa</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>K1H8L6</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tice A, Kim P, Dinh L, Ryu JJ, Beaulé PE. A randomised controlled trial of cemented and cementless femoral components for metal-on-metal hip resurfacing: a bone mineral density study. Bone Joint J. 2015 Dec;97-B(12):1608-14. doi: 10.1302/0301-620X.97B12.36110.</citation>
    <PMID>26637673</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 30, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 12, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 13, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>non-inflammatory degenerative joint disease</keyword>
  <keyword>hip resurfacing</keyword>
  <keyword>bone mineral density</keyword>
  <keyword>cemented</keyword>
  <keyword>cementless</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteoarthritis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

