<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01055054</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HM1587</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01055054</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bariatric Surgery Registry</brief_title>
  <official_title>Analysis Bariatric Surgery Data</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Virginia Commonwealth University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Virginia Commonwealth University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Periodic analyses of our extensive database with regards to different surgical procedures for
      severe obesity and different obesity co-morbidities will be of benefit to our severely obese
      patients as well as to others world-wide.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1980</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>weight loss</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year, 5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>surgical mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>90 day post-surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>surgical morbidity</measure>
    <time_frame>90 day post-surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>resolution of co-morbidities</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year, 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5042</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity, Morbid</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients who have undergone bariatric surgical procedures at the Virginia Commonwealth
        University (VCU) Medical Center.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Clinical diagnosis of morbid obesity

          -  Have undergone a bariatric surgical procedure at the VCU Medical Center
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Guilherme M Campos, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Virginia Commonwealth University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VCU Health Systems</name>
      <address>
        <city>Richmond</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>23298</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sugerman HJ, Fairman RP, Baron PL, Kwentus JA. Gastric surgery for respiratory insufficiency of obesity. Chest. 1986 Jul;90(1):81-6.</citation>
    <PMID>3720390</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sugerman HJ, Starkey JV, Birkenhauer R. A randomized prospective trial of gastric bypass versus vertical banded gastroplasty for morbid obesity and their effects on sweets versus non-sweets eaters. Ann Surg. 1987 Jun;205(6):613-24.</citation>
    <PMID>3296971</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sugerman HJ, Baron PL, Fairman RP, Evans CR, Vetrovec GW. Hemodynamic dysfunction in obesity hypoventilation syndrome and the effects of treatment with surgically induced weight loss. Ann Surg. 1988 May;207(5):604-13.</citation>
    <PMID>3377570</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sugerman HJ, Londrey GL, Kellum JM, Wolf L, Liszka T, Engle KM, Birkenhauer R, Starkey JV. Weight loss with vertical banded gastroplasty and Roux-Y gastric bypass for morbid obesity with selective versus random assignment. Am J Surg. 1989 Jan;157(1):93-102.</citation>
    <PMID>2910132</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sugerman HJ, Fairman RP, Sood RK, Engle K, Wolfe L, Kellum JM. Long-term effects of gastric surgery for treating respiratory insufficiency of obesity. Am J Clin Nutr. 1992 Feb;55(2 Suppl):597S-601S. doi: 10.1093/ajcn/55.2.597s.</citation>
    <PMID>1733136</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sanyal AJ, Sugerman HJ, Kellum JM, Engle KM, Wolfe L. Stomal complications of gastric bypass: incidence and outcome of therapy. Am J Gastroenterol. 1992 Sep;87(9):1165-9.</citation>
    <PMID>1519574</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sugerman HJ, Sugerman EL, Wolfe L, Kellum JM Jr, Schweitzer MA, DeMaria EJ. Risks and benefits of gastric bypass in morbidly obese patients with severe venous stasis disease. Ann Surg. 2001 Jul;234(1):41-6.</citation>
    <PMID>11460821</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>DeMaria EJ, Sugerman HJ, Kellum JM, Meador JG, Wolfe LG. Results of 281 consecutive total laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypasses to treat morbid obesity. Ann Surg. 2002 May;235(5):640-5; discussion 645-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11981209</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>DeMaria EJ, Schweitzer MA, Kellum JM, Meador J, Wolfe L, Sugerman HJ. Hand-assisted laparoscopic gastric bypass does not improve outcome and increases costs when compared to open gastric bypass for the surgical treatment of obesity. Surg Endosc. 2002 Oct;16(10):1452-5. Epub 2002 Jun 14.</citation>
    <PMID>12063573</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kothari SN, DeMaria EJ, Sugerman HJ, Kellum JM, Meador J, Wolfe L. Lap-band failures: conversion to gastric bypass and their preliminary outcomes. Surgery. 2002 Jun;131(6):625-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12075174</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sugerman HJ, Sugerman EL, DeMaria EJ, Kellum JM, Kennedy C, Mowery Y, Wolfe LG. Bariatric surgery for severely obese adolescents. J Gastrointest Surg. 2003 Jan;7(1):102-108. doi: 10.1016/S1091-255X(02)00125-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12559191</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sugerman HJ, Wolfe LG, Sica DA, Clore JN. Diabetes and hypertension in severe obesity and effects of gastric bypass-induced weight loss. Ann Surg. 2003 Jun;237(6):751-6; discussion 757-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12796570</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fernandez AZ Jr, DeMaria EJ, Tichansky DS, Kellum JM, Wolfe LG, Meador J, Sugerman HJ. Experience with over 3,000 open and laparoscopic bariatric procedures: multivariate analysis of factors related to leak and resultant mortality. Surg Endosc. 2004 Feb;18(2):193-7. Epub 2003 Dec 29. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14691697</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Fernandez AZ Jr, Demaria EJ, Tichansky DS, Kellum JM, Wolfe LG, Meador J, Sugerman HJ. Multivariate analysis of risk factors for death following gastric bypass for treatment of morbid obesity. Ann Surg. 2004 May;239(5):698-702; discussion 702-3.</citation>
    <PMID>15082974</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sugerman HJ, DeMaria EJ, Kellum JM, Sugerman EL, Meador JG, Wolfe LG. Effects of bariatric surgery in older patients. Ann Surg. 2004 Aug;240(2):243-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15273547</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bond DS, Evans RK, Wolfe LG, Meador JG, Sugerman HJ, Kellum JM, Demaria EJ. Impact of self-reported physical activity participation on proportion of excess weight loss and BMI among gastric bypass surgery patients. Am Surg. 2004 Sep;70(9):811-4.</citation>
    <PMID>15481300</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Tichansky DS, DeMaria EJ, Fernandez AZ, Kellum JM, Wolfe LG, Meador JG, Sugerman HJ. Postoperative complications are not increased in super-super obese patients who undergo laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass. Surg Endosc. 2005 Jul;19(7):939-41. Epub 2005 May 5.</citation>
    <PMID>15920681</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carmody BJ, Sugerman HJ, Kellum JM, Jamal MK, Johnson JM, Carbonell AM, Maher JW, Wolfe LG, DeMaria EJ. Pulmonary embolism complicating bariatric surgery: detailed analysis of a single institution's 24-year experience. J Am Coll Surg. 2006 Dec;203(6):831-7. Epub 2006 Oct 25.</citation>
    <PMID>17116551</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Carbonell AM, Wolfe LG, Meador JG, Sugerman HJ, Kellum JM, Maher JW. Does diabetes affect weight loss after gastric bypass? Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2008 May-Jun;4(3):441-4. Epub 2007 Dec 11.</citation>
    <PMID>18065289</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ali MR, Tichansky DS, Kothari SN, McBride CL, Fernandez AZ Jr, Sugerman HJ, Kellum JM, Wolfe LG, DeMaria EJ. Validation that a 1-year fellowship in minimally invasive and bariatric surgery can eliminate the learning curve for laparoscopic gastric bypass. Surg Endosc. 2010 Jan;24(1):138-44. doi: 10.1007/s00464-009-0550-z. Epub 2009 Jun 11.</citation>
    <PMID>19517173</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Evans RK, Bond DS, Demaria EJ, Wolfe LG, Meador JG, Kellum JM. Initiation and progression of physical activity after laparoscopic and open gastric bypass surgery. Surg Innov. 2004 Dec;11(4):235-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15756392</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Johnson JM, Maher JW, DeMaria EJ, Downs RW, Wolfe LG, Kellum JM. The long-term effects of gastric bypass on vitamin D metabolism. Ann Surg. 2006 May;243(5):701-4; discussion 704-5.</citation>
    <PMID>16633006</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bond DS, Evans RK, DeMaria E, Wolfe L, Meador J, Kellum J, Maher J, Warren BJ. Physical activity and quality of life improvements before obesity surgery. Am J Health Behav. 2006 Jul-Aug;30(4):422-34.</citation>
    <PMID>16787132</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jamal MK, DeMaria EJ, Johnson JM, Carmody BJ, Wolfe LG, Kellum JM, Meador JG. Impact of major co-morbidities on mortality and complications after gastric bypass. Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2005 Nov-Dec;1(6):511-6. Epub 2005 Oct 27.</citation>
    <PMID>16925280</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jamal MK, DeMaria EJ, Johnson JM, Carmody BJ, Wolfe LG, Kellum JM, Meador JG. Insurance-mandated preoperative dietary counseling does not improve outcome and increases dropout rates in patients considering gastric bypass surgery for morbid obesity. Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2006 Mar-Apr;2(2):122-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16925335</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bond DS, Evans RK, DeMaria EJ, Wolfe LG, Meador JG, Kellum JM, Maher JW. Physical activity stage of readiness predicts moderate-vigorous physical activity participation among morbidly obese gastric bypass surgery candidates. Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2006 Mar-Apr;2(2):128-32. Epub 2006 Mar 3.</citation>
    <PMID>16925336</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>DeMaria EJ, Portenier D, Wolfe L. Obesity surgery mortality risk score: proposal for a clinically useful score to predict mortality risk in patients undergoing gastric bypass. Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2007 Mar-Apr;3(2):134-40.</citation>
    <PMID>17386394</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lee S, Carmody B, Wolfe L, Demaria E, Kellum JM, Sugerman H, Maher JW. Effect of location and speed of diagnosis on anastomotic leak outcomes in 3828 gastric bypass cases. J Gastrointest Surg. 2007 Jun;11(6):708-13.</citation>
    <PMID>17562118</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lee SD, Khouzam MN, Kellum JM, DeMaria EJ, Meador JG, Wolfe LG, Maher JW. Selective, versus routine, upper gastrointestinal series leads to equal morbidity and reduced hospital stay in laparoscopic gastric bypass patients. Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2007 Jul-Aug;3(4):413-6. Epub 2007 Jun 12.</citation>
    <PMID>17567540</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Evans RK, Bond DS, Wolfe LG, Meador JG, Herrick JE, Kellum JM, Maher JW. Participation in 150 min/wk of moderate or higher intensity physical activity yields greater weight loss after gastric bypass surgery. Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2007 Sep-Oct;3(5):526-30.</citation>
    <PMID>17903772</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Maher JW, Martin Hawver L, Pucci A, Wolfe LG, Meador JG, Kellum JM. Four hundred fifty consecutive laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypasses with no mortality and declining leak rates and lengths of stay in a bariatric training program. J Am Coll Surg. 2008 May;206(5):940-4; discussion 944-5. doi: 10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2007.12.043. Epub 2008 Mar 24.</citation>
    <PMID>18471729</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yuan X, Martin Hawver LR, Ojo P, Wolfe LM, Meador JG, Kellum JM, Maher JW. Bariatric surgery in Medicare patients: greater risks but substantial benefits. Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2009 May-Jun;5(3):299-304. doi: 10.1016/j.soard.2008.08.018. Epub 2008 Aug 30.</citation>
    <PMID>18996764</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bond DS, Phelan S, Wolfe LG, Evans RK, Meador JG, Kellum JM, Maher JW, Wing RR. Becoming physically active after bariatric surgery is associated with improved weight loss and health-related quality of life. Obesity (Silver Spring). 2009 Jan;17(1):78-83. doi: 10.1038/oby.2008.501. Epub 2008 Nov 6.</citation>
    <PMID>18997679</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Maher JW, Bakhos W, Nahmias N, Wolfe LG, Meador JG, Baugh N, Kellum JM. Drain amylase levels are an adjunct in detection of gastrojejunostomy leaks after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass. J Am Coll Surg. 2009 May;208(5):881-4; discussion 885-6. doi: 10.1016/j.jamcollsurg.2008.12.022. Epub 2009 Mar 26.</citation>
    <PMID>19476853</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Chikunguwo SM, Wolfe LG, Dodson P, Meador JG, Baugh N, Clore JN, Kellum JM, Maher JW. Analysis of factors associated with durable remission of diabetes after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass. Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2010 May-Jun;6(3):254-9. doi: 10.1016/j.soard.2009.11.003. Epub 2009 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>20303324</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kellum JM, Chikunguwo SM, Maher JW, Wolfe LG, Sugerman HJ. Long-term results of malabsorptive distal Roux-en-Y gastric bypass in superobese patients. Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2011 Mar-Apr;7(2):189-93. doi: 10.1016/j.soard.2010.08.018. Epub 2010 Oct 11.</citation>
    <PMID>21145293</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Browning MG, Baugh NG, Wolfe LG, Kellum JK, Maher JW, Evans RK. Evaluation of pre- and postoperative physical activity participation in laparoscopic gastric banding patients. Obes Surg. 2014 Nov;24(11):1981-6. doi: 10.1007/s11695-014-1283-1.</citation>
    <PMID>24831460</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 20, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 21, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 25, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 25, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 25, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 28, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>bariatrics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity, Morbid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

