<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01051882</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MSC-NTF-001-HMO-CTIL</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01051882</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Autologous Cultured Mesenchymal Bone Marrow Stromal Cells Secreting Neurotrophic Factors (MSC-NTF), in ALS Patients.</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I/II, Open Label Study to Evaluate Safety, Tolerability and Therapeutic Effects of Transplantation of Autologous Cultured Mesenchymal Bone Marrow Stromal Cells Secreting Neurotrophic Factors (MSC-NTF), in ALS Patients.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hadassah Medical Organization</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Brainstorm-Cell Therapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hadassah Medical Organization</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study will evaluate the safety, tolerability and therapeutic effects (preliminary
      efficacy) of injection of autologous cultured mesenchymal bone marrow stromal cells secreting
      neurotrophic factors (MSC-NTF), as a possible treatment for patients with Amyotrophic Lateral
      Sclerosis (ALS) at the early and progressive disease stages.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a single center trial to be conducted at the Department of Neurology &amp;
      Laboratory of Neuroimmunology, at the Hadassah Hebrew University Medical Center, Jerusalem in
      Israel. All patients enrolled will have a documented history of ALS disease prior to study
      enrolment. Patients diagnosed as early stage ALS disease with duration of less than 6 months
      and patients diagnosed with progressive stage ALS disease with duration of 6-12 months.
      Overall, 24 patients will be recruited and allocated based on their ALS disease severity to 2
      treatment groups: Group A - 12 patients of early ALS disease stage and Group B - 12 patients
      of progressive ALS disease.

      Eligible patients will be enrolled into the study and will be observed for every 2 weeks
      during a &quot;run in period&quot; of 3 months for determination of the progression rate of the
      disease. During the &quot;run in period&quot; after about 6 weeks following enrollment, patients of
      both study groups will undergo a Bone Marrow Aspiration procedure and MSC-NTF cells will be
      produced from the bone marrow aspirate based on Brainstorm Cell Therapeutics Ltd proprietary
      method. On the last &quot;run in period&quot; visit, patients of both study groups will undergo the
      treatment and MSC-NTF will be transplanted by IM or IT injection to the early and progressive
      ALS patients respectively.

      After the MSC-NTF transplantation patients will be observed on a monthly basis for a post
      treatment follow up period of 6 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety evaluation and tolerability of a single treatment administration of autologous cultured mesenchymal bone marrow stromal cells secreting neurotrophic factors (MSC-NTF)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Safety evaluation and tolerability of a single treatment administration of autologous cultured mesenchymal bone marrow stromal cells secreting neurotrophic factors (MSC-NTF) by multiple intramuscular injections (IM) at 24 separate sites on the biceps and triceps muscles to patients with ALS at the early disease stage</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety evaluation and tolerability of single intrathecal injection (IT) into the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) of autologous cultured mesenchymal bone marrow stromal cells secreting neurotrophic factors (MSC-NTF)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Safety evaluation and tolerability of single intrathecal injection (IT) into the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) of autologous cultured mesenchymal bone marrow stromal cells secreting neurotrophic factors (MSC-NTF),to patients with ALS at the progressive disease stage.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the progression rate of the disease as evidenced by changes in the ALS functional rating scale (ALS-FRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in muscle strength grading (MVIC) by muscle chart</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in forced vital capacity (FVC %) (In the progressive disease stage group only).</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in muscle bulk estimated by MRI of the upper and lower extremities</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in upper and lower extremities circumference (cm)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in EMG parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Need and time to tracheotomy or permanent assisted ventilation</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival, calculating time to death</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">12</enrollment>
  <condition>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MSC-NTF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MSC-NTF cells transplantation (i.m.)</intervention_name>
    <description>In early ALS subjects: Autologous MSC-NTF cells will be transplanted under mild anesthesia, intramuscularly into patients' clinically unaffected (or only mildly affected) upper arm biceps and triceps muscles according to a pre-designed grid. Intramuscular injections will be by a 26 gauge needle to a 1.5cm depth (ensuring that injection is into muscle and not adipose tissue). The patients will be injected at 24 sites with a total of 24 million cells</description>
    <arm_group_label>MSC-NTF</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MSC-NTF cells transplantation (i.t.)</intervention_name>
    <description>In progressive ALS subjects: Autologous MSC-NTF cells will be transplanted under mild anesthesia intrathecally(via a standard lumbar puncture)with a total of 60 million cells.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MSC-NTF</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. El Escorial criteria for definite or probable ALS

          2. Either men or non pregnant women between 20-75 years of age.

          3. Patient is mentally intact and psychologically stable

          4. For early stage ALS- Patients will be with ALS-FRS-R scale of at least 30 and disease
             duration of less than 2 years.Or, for progressive stage ALS- Patients will be with an
             ALS-FRS-R scale of 15-30 and disease duration of less than 2 years

          5. For early stage ALS- Patient has sufficiently bulky muscles. Or, for progressive stage
             ALS- Patient with at least 60% FVC

          6. Participant understands the nature of the procedure and provides written informed
             consent prior to any study procedure.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Positive test for HBV, HCV, HIV and Mycoplasma.

          2. High protein in the CSF.

          3. Lymphocytosis in the CSF.

          4. Positive for anti-GM1 antibodies.

          5. Patient has significant conduction blocks or slow nerve conduction velocities (a
             reduction of more than 30%) confirmed by nerve conduction velocity - EMG studies.

          6. The patient is a respiratory dependent.

          7. Renal failure, impaired hepatic function

          8. Patients suffering from significant cardiac disease, malignant diseases or any other
             disease that may risk the patient or interfere with the ability to interpret the
             results

          9. Active infections.

         10. Participation in another clinical trial within 1 month prior to start of this study.

         11. Subject unwilling or unable to comply with the requirements of the protocol.

         12. Patient has not been treated previously with any cellular therapy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dimitrios Karussis, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hadassah Medical Organization</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hadassah Medical Organization</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jerusalem</city>
        <zip>91120</zip>
        <country>Israel</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Israel</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 17, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 19, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 20, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 6, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 6, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 7, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mesenchymal Stromal Cells (MSC)</keyword>
  <keyword>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS)</keyword>
  <keyword>Neuroprotection</keyword>
  <keyword>Neurodegeneration</keyword>
  <keyword>Stem cells</keyword>
  <keyword>ALS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Motor Neuron Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>March 7, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

