<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01050387</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>0909005699</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1RC1HD063562</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>M#136410</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01050387</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Vitamin D Dose and Genotype of the Binding Protein in Infants and Children</brief_title>
  <acronym>VitaD</acronym>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Controlled Trial of Vitamin D Supplementation in Infants and Children: Effects of Vitamin D Dose and Genotype of the Binding Protein</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Yale University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Thrasher Research Fund</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Yale University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if the vitamin D binding protein genotype
      influences circulating vitamin D levels and if it may have functional consequences on vitamin
      D activity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Vitamin D has recently been the subject of much attention. Advantages to the prevention of
      vitamin D deficiency (VDD) in young children are obvious: acutely, hypocalcemic seizures may
      occur in VDD, and rickets can result in long-term skeletal deformities. Previous research has
      emphasized the importance of identifying optimal supplementation doses and appropriate target
      thresholds for circulating 25-hydroxyvitamin D (25-OHD), the best described marker of vitamin
      D status. The timely next step is to objectively establish effective doses for the prevention
      of VDD, without creating risk from overzealous supplementation, in a population
      representative of those most at risk for overt disease.

      Although the primary role of vitamin D is considered to be its effect on intestinal calcium
      absorption, enormous variability of fractional calcium absorption in relation to 25-OHD
      levels exists. We provide evidence that a significant component of this variability is
      genetic in nature and in particular, relates to vitamin D binding protein (DBP) genotype.

      The aggregate data suggest that the critical mechanism for the development of nutritional
      rickets is reduction in availability of calcium to the skeleton, which is largely determined
      by vitamin D status and intestinal calcium absorption. Our proposal focuses on the
      establishment of a workable definition of vitamin D deficiency in an underserved and highly
      vulnerable population and to assess the impact of genetic variance in VDR and DBP as factors
      to be considered in the recommendation of vitamin D status assessment, taking into account
      the outcome of 25-OHD level, and in additional studies, potential functional consequences of
      vitamin D related to both its classical and non-classical effects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in serum 25-OH vitamin D</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">193</enrollment>
  <condition>Vitamin D Deficiency</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vitamin D</intervention_name>
    <description>Vitamin D (either 400 IU vs 1000 IU) given orally each day</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  6 months to 6 years of age

          -  healthy or free from any diseases or conditions that may affect nutritional status or
             bone metabolism

          -  willingness of family to participate in a 6-month study of vitamin D supplementation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Chronic disease

          -  Prematurity &lt; 32 weeks gestational age

          -  Liver disease such as hepatitis or renal/urologic disease (e.g., recurrent urinary
             tract infection)

          -  Use of pharmacologic or prescription-level dosages of vitamin D or its metabolites. We
             will exclude users of any systemic glucocorticoid preparation and users of inhaled
             steroids that are considered greater than medium dose for age 4 yrs. Specifically,
             this would exclude users of over 1 mg/day of budesonide, and over 352 mcg/day of
             fluticasone.

          -  Current or recent (within 1 month) use of anticonvulsants or other medications known
             to affect bone and mineral homeostasis or alkaline phosphatase levels.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>6 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Thomas O Carpenter, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Yale University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Yale University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Haven</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06520</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gungor N, Saad R, Janosky J, Arslanian S. Validation of surrogate estimates of insulin sensitivity and insulin secretion in children and adolescents. J Pediatr. 2004 Jan;144(1):47-55.</citation>
    <PMID>14722518</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DeLucia MC, Mitnick ME, Carpenter TO. Nutritional rickets with normal circulating 25-hydroxyvitamin D: a call for reexamining the role of dietary calcium intake in North American infants. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2003 Aug;88(8):3539-45.</citation>
    <PMID>12915633</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heaney RP, Davies KM, Chen TC, Holick MF, Barger-Lux MJ. Human serum 25-hydroxycholecalciferol response to extended oral dosing with cholecalciferol. Am J Clin Nutr. 2003 Jan;77(1):204-10. Erratum in: Am J Clin Nutr. 2003 Nov;78(5):1047.</citation>
    <PMID>12499343</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Safadi FF, Thornton P, Magiera H, Hollis BW, Gentile M, Haddad JG, Liebhaber SA, Cooke NE. Osteopathy and resistance to vitamin D toxicity in mice null for vitamin D binding protein. J Clin Invest. 1999 Jan;103(2):239-51.</citation>
    <PMID>9916136</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zella LA, Shevde NK, Hollis BW, Cooke NE, Pike JW. Vitamin D-binding protein influences total circulating levels of 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D3 but does not directly modulate the bioactive levels of the hormone in vivo. Endocrinology. 2008 Jul;149(7):3656-67. doi: 10.1210/en.2008-0042. Epub 2008 Mar 27.</citation>
    <PMID>18372326</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pettifor JM. Nutritional Rickets. In: Pediatric Bone: Biology and Diseases. Glorieux FH, Pettifor JM, Juppner H (eds.) Academic Press: San Diego, CA, p 541-565, 2003.</citation>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 13, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 14, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 15, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 2, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 2, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 5, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Yale University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Thomas Carpenter</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Vitamin D Deficiency</keyword>
  <keyword>VDD</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamin D Supplementation</keyword>
  <keyword>Vitamin D Binding Protein</keyword>
  <keyword>DBP</keyword>
  <keyword>Nutritional rickets</keyword>
  <keyword>rickets</keyword>
  <keyword>25hydroxyvitamin D</keyword>
  <keyword>25OHD</keyword>
  <keyword>1,25OH2D</keyword>
  <keyword>vitamin D metabolites</keyword>
  <keyword>PTH</keyword>
  <keyword>vitamin D homeostasis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D Deficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vitamins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitamin D</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ergocalciferols</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

