<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01059201</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>100022</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10-CH-0022</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01059201</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exome Sequencing in Autistic Spectrum Disorder</brief_title>
  <official_title>Exome Sequencing in Autistic Spectrum Disorder Patients With Altered Cholesterol Homeostasis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Research into the genetic causes of autism spectrum disorder (ASD) involves studies of
           the DNA of children with autism. New DNA sequencing technology allows researchers to
           study specific genes in search of genetic changes that may cause or contribute to ASD.
           Individuals who donated DNA to the Autism Genetic Resource Exchange may benefit from
           further study of their DNA samples with more advanced DNA sequencing technology.

        -  The role of cholesterol in individuals with ASD is currently under investigation.
           Research has suggested that abnormal cholesterol levels in children with autism may be
           related to genetic mutations or changes in how cholesterol is regulated in the body.

      Objectives:

      - To study existing blood samples of children with autism spectrum disorders to evaluate the
      relationship between genetic traits and cholesterol function.

      Eligibility:

      - Children with ASD who donated blood samples to the Autism Genetic Resource Exchange.

      Design:

      - Parents/guardians of minor children with ASD will provide consent for further research to
      be performed on existing DNA samples in the Autism Genetic Research Exchange databank.
      Information from this research may be provided to the consenting parents/guardians on a case
      by case basis, as directed by the researchers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) is a neurodevelopmental disorder characterized by functional
      deficits in three domains: social interaction, communication, and stereotypic behavior.
      Prevalence has been estimated to be approximately 1/166 children and the public health impact
      is significant. ASD clearly has a genetic component; however, identification of specific
      etiologies has been complicated by the heterogeneous nature of ASD. One approach to minimize
      this problem is to define endophenotypes that can subcategorize ASD patients. Based on our
      work with Smith-Lemli-Opitz syndrome, we have investigated whether alterations in cholesterol
      homeostasis may contribute to ASD. We found in 200 ASD subjects that 23% of subjects had
      serum cholesterol levels less than or equal to 2.28th centile and 9% had levels greater than
      or equal to 97.72nd centile. Analysis of the sterol profile suggested that the
      hypocholesterolemia was due to a synthetic defect rather than decreased oral intake. Thus we
      hypothesize that ASD patients with abnormal cholesterol levels will have polymorphisms or
      mutations of either genes involved in cholesterol homeostasis or genes encoding proteins
      whose function is altered by changes in cholesterol levels. To test this hypothesis we
      propose to 1) use serum cholesterol levels to define ASD endophenotypes and 2) to perform
      genomic resequencing of all known exons in hypo- and normocholesterolemic ASD patients.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 21, 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date>May 15, 2017</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">322</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism Spectrum Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Autism</condition>
  <condition>Autistic Disorder</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. Prior participation in Autism Genetic Research Exchange

               2. Multiple affected children with ASD

               3. Willingness to contact the NIH and reconsent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Forbes D Porter, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kennedy Krieger Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210-1240</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Newschaffer CJ, Croen LA, Daniels J, Giarelli E, Grether JK, Levy SE, Mandell DS, Miller LA, Pinto-Martin J, Reaven J, Reynolds AM, Rice CE, Schendel D, Windham GC. The epidemiology of autism spectrum disorders. Annu Rev Public Health. 2007;28:235-58. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17367287</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jacobson JW, Mulick JA. System and cost research issues in treatments for people with autistic disorders. J Autism Dev Disord. 2000 Dec;30(6):585-93. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11261469</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Seltzer MM, Shattuck P, Abbeduto L, Greenberg JS. Trajectory of development in adolescents and adults with autism. Ment Retard Dev Disabil Res Rev. 2004;10(4):234-47. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15666341</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 15, 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 28, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 28, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 29, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Autism Spectrum Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Cholesterol</keyword>
  <keyword>Exome Sequencing</keyword>
  <keyword>Autistic Spectrum Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>ASD</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autism Spectrum Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Child Development Disorders, Pervasive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

