<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02498561</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2013-62550515-02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02498561</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of Obesity on Glutathione Levels in Patients With Chronic Periodontitis Before and After Periodontal Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 1 Study of Periodontal Disease and Obese Individuals That Investigate of Local and Systemic Antioxidant Levels of Before and After Periodontal Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Figen ÖNGÖZ DEDE</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Bulent Ecevit University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bulent Ecevit University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obesity may affect periodontal health by inducing gingival oxidative damage through increased
      production in circulating reactive oxygen species (ROS). Previous studies have reported
      decreased glutathione levels in patients with periodontitis when compared to healthy subjects
      in gingival crevicular fluid (GCF), plasma and saliva. In the present study we hypothesized
      that high ROS levels in circulation may decrease glutathione levels in the GCF,plasma and
      saliva in obese patients with chronic periodontitis, whereas periodontal therapy could have
      positive effects on glutathione levels.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study was to investigate the effects of obesity on glutathione levels in
      the plasma, GCF and saliva of patients with chronic periodontitis and to evaluate changes
      after nonsurgical periodontal therapy.

      Diagnosed as obese (n=30) and normal-weight (n=30) individuals were categorized; chronic
      periodontitis (CP) and periodontally healthy controls (PH). Gingival crevicular fluid (GCF),
      plasma, saliva samples and clinical measurements were obtained at baseline and a month after
      nonsurgical periodontal therapy.

      Unstimulated salivary samples were collected using standard techniques. About 2 mL whole
      saliva was collected in disposable tubes and centrifuged immediately to remove cell debris
      (10,000 g x 10 minutes). The supernatants (50µL each) were stored at -40C until analyzed. GCF
      samples were collected from a mesio-buccal and disto-palatal site on each tooth. In the CP
      group, the samples were obtained from patients at areas with ≥5 mm CAL, ≥6 mm PD and ≥30%
      bone loss. In gingivitis group, GCF samples were obtained from teeth with BOP and without
      CAL. In the healthy group, GCF samples were collected from teeth exhibiting PD&lt;3 mm without
      CAL and BOP. The area was isolated with cotton rolls, saliva contamination elimination was
      ensured, and it was slightly air dried. GCF was sampled with paper strips. Paper strips were
      placed into the crevice until mild resistance was felt (intracrevicular method) and left in
      the position for 30 seconds. Strips contaminated with blood or saliva were discarded. Each
      sampled strip was placed into a 400µl eppendorf centrifuge tube and stored at -40C until
      analyzed.

      Five milliliters of venous blood was taken from antecubital vein by using a standard
      venipuncture method. Obtained blood sample was collected in vacutainer tubes and
      anti-coagulated with EDTA. The blood samples were then stored at -40C until required for use
      in ELISAs.

      Power analysis indicated that 12 individuals for each group would be sufficient to achieve
      80% power to detect a difference of 0.05 between the alternative and the null hypotheses.

      The Shapiro Wilk test was used to investigate whether or not the data were normally
      distributed. Continuous variables with unequal variances were compared by means of Welch and
      Tamhane's T2 post-hoc test for BMI, PD, CAL and the levels of glutathione. The comparison of
      the age, GI, PI and BOP was analyzed using the Kruskal-Wallis non-parametric test followed by
      post hoc group comparisons with the Bonferroni-adjusted Mann-Whitney U test. Paired Student's
      t-test or Wilcoxon rank-sum test was used to compare the measurements at two points (baseline
      and after SRP). The Spearman's rank correlation test was also used to detect the relationship
      between biochemical and clinical findings.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Biochemical parameters (GSH and GSSG levels, GSH/GSSG ratio )</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in levels of reduced and oxidized glutathione (GSH and GSSG) 1 month after periodontal treatment determined by ELISA. The changes in levels of GSH were analyzed to determine diagnostic and prognostic potential as a biomarker of periodontitis and obesity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Probing pocket depth</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in probing pocket depth after periodontal treatment.Probing pocket depth was measured for determining severity of disease and clinic outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Probing pocket depth and clinical attachment level</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in clinical attachment level after periodontal treatment. The probing depth and the distance from the gingival margin to the cemento-enamel junction are used to measurement of clinical attachment level. Clinical attachment level was measured for determining severity of disease and clinic outcome.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gingival index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>he changes in gingival index after periodontal treatment. Gingival index was recorded for classifying and evaluating (coronally) gingival inflammation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plaque index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in plaque index after periodontal treatment. Plaque index was recorded for determining and classifying oral hygiene status.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Bleeding on probing</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 month after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The changes in bleeding on probing after periodontal treatment. Bleeding on probing was recorded for classifying and evaluating (apically) gingival inflammation.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>obese-chronic periodontitis patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>GCF, plasma and GCF samples were taken before and after nonsurgical periodontal therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>obese-periodontally healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>GCF, plasma and GCF samples were taken at baseline after oral hygiene instructions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>normal weight-CP patients</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>GCF, plasma and GCF samples were taken before and after nonsurgical periodontal therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>normal weight-PH controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>GCF, plasma and GCF samples were taken at baseline after oral hygiene instructions</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>nonsurgical periodontal therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Scaling and root planning under local anaesthesia, in a total of four clinical visits Oral hygiene instructions including the modified Bass technique, regular toothpaste, and an appropriate interdental cleaning device with dental floss and interdental brush.</description>
    <arm_group_label>obese-chronic periodontitis patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>obese-chronic periodontitis patients</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>oral hygiene instructions</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral hygiene instructions including the modified Bass technique, regular toothpaste, and an appropriate interdental cleaning device with dental floss and interdental brush</description>
    <arm_group_label>obese-periodontally healthy controls</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>obese-periodontally healthy controls</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>nonsurgical periodontal therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Scaling and root planning under local anaesthesia, in a total of four clinical visits Oral hygiene instructions including the modified Bass technique, regular toothpaste, and an appropriate interdental cleaning device with dental floss and interdental brush.</description>
    <arm_group_label>normal weight-CP patients</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>normal weight-CP patients</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>oral hygiene instructions</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral hygiene instructions including the modified Bass technique, regular toothpaste, and an appropriate interdental cleaning device with dental floss and interdental brush</description>
    <arm_group_label>normal weight-PH controls</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>normal weight-PH patients</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  never-smokers

          -  no history of systemic disease

          -  no patients had been under periodontal therapy and medicine for at least 6 months
             before the study

          -  no pregnancy or lactation

          -  no alcohol or antioxidant vitamin consumption.

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 9, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 13, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 15, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 14, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 14, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 16, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Bulent Ecevit University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Figen ÖNGÖZ DEDE</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Faculty of Dentistry</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chronic Periodontitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

