<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02498977</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ASF/001-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2014-004557-14</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02498977</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Liver Immunosuppression Free Trial</brief_title>
  <acronym>LIFT</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Randomised Marker-based Trial to Assess the Clinical Utility and Safety of Biomarker-guided Immunosuppression Withdrawal in Liver Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>King's College London</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>King's College Hospital NHS Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute for Health Research, United Kingdom</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>King's College London</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      LIFT is prospective randomised marker-based trial to assess the clinical utility and safety
      of biomarker-guided immunosuppression withdrawal in liver transplantation. 'LIFT' aims to
      validate a biomarker test of operational tolerance to stratify liver transplant recipients
      before withdrawing immunosuppressive medication. Primary objective is clinical utility and
      risk/benefit ratio of employing a transcriptional test of tolerance to stratify liver
      recipients prior to immunosuppression withdrawal. Secondary objectives are: safety of
      biomarker-guided immunosuppression withdrawal; health-economic and quality of life impact of
      biomarker-guided immunosuppression withdrawal; improvement in drug-related co-morbidities;
      prevalence of tolerance over time; role of donor-specific anti-human leukocyte antigen (HLA)
      antibodies; identify mechanisms of liver allograft tolerance. It is a prospective,
      multi-centre, phase IV, biomarker-strategy design trial with a randomized control group in
      which adult liver transplant recipients will undergo immunosuppression withdrawal. The sample
      size is 148 patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, multi-centre, phase IV, biomarker-strategy design trial with a
      randomised control group in which adult liver transplant recipients will undergo
      immunosuppression (IS) withdrawal. Immunosuppression drugs (IS) are: Tacrolimus, cyclosporine
      and/or mycophenolic acid, mycophenolate mofetil or azathioprine.

      Enrolled participants will be randomised 1:1 to either: 1) Non-Biomarker-based IS weaning
      (Weaning-All; Arm A); or 2) Biomarker-based IS weaning (Arm B). In participants allocated to
      Arm A IS will be withdrawn regardless of the result of the biomarker test. Among participants
      allocated to Arm B, only those found to be biomarker-positive (Arm B+, i.e. potentially
      tolerant) will be offered IS withdrawal, while biomarker-negative participants (Arm B-, i.e.
      potentially non-tolerant) will remain on their baseline maintenance IS. This will allow us to
      demonstrate that the biomarker is a useful test to personalise IS by offering drug withdrawal
      only to those participants who are likely to complete the process successfully, avoiding
      unnecessary rejections among those who have not developed tolerance. Comparing the outcome of
      IS withdrawal between arms A and B+ will provide direct evidence of the clinical usefulness
      of the test as a function of its predictive accuracy. We have established that for the
      biomarker to drive safe IS withdrawal its Positive Predictive Value should be no less than
      0.80, and its sensitivity at least 070. To account for centre effects, we will use stratified
      randomization. Furthermore, to avoid biases, participants undergoing drug withdrawal and
      their physicians will be blinded to the biomarker results. Participants randomized to Arm B-
      will know their biomarker status, and will be maintained in the study until its termination
      and contribute to secondary clinical outcomes and to the evaluation of the stability of the
      tolerance signature.

      Cost and quality of life (HrQOL) assessments will be conducted alongside the trial to
      estimate the health-economic implications of the 2 different strategies. Furthermore,
      sequential biological specimens will be collected to conduct ancillary mechanistic studies.
      Recruitment will take place in 11 European liver transplant units (King's College Hospital,
      Royal Free London, Newcastle, Birmingham, Leeds, Edinburgh, Cambridge, Leuven, Hannover,
      Berlin and Barcelona).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Successful discontinuation of IS with maintenance of normal allograft status</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months from IS withdrawal</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients with successful discontinuation of IS with maintenance of normal allograft status as assessed by liver biopsy and liver tests 12 months after IS withdrawal (operational tolerance)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Proportion of tolerant participants remaining free of rejection</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years post IS withdrawal</time_frame>
    <description>Measures of rejection in patients (incidence, severity, timing, steroid resistant rejection, chronic rejection) and to investigate if liver transplant recipients under IS become operationally tolerant over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Renal function at 1, 2 and 3 years after enrollment and change in co-morbidities</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years post IS withdrawal</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the extent to which IS withdrawal improve drug-related co-morbidities associated with IS use (hypertension, cardiovascular risk profile, diabetes mellitus, hyperlipidemia, malignancy) and to explore the association between operational liver transplant tolerance, iron metabolism, immunosenescence, and specific gut microbiome profiles.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Development of anti-HLA antibodies (before and after initiation of IS withdrawal).</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years post IS withdrawal</time_frame>
    <description>To determine if the presence of donor-specific anti-HLA antibodies influence the success of IS withdrawal, and whether IS withdrawal promotes the development of anti-HLA antibodies in liver transplant recipients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Health related quality of life (HrQOL)</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years post IS withdrawal</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the effect of IS withdrawal on the quality of life of liver transplant recipients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Costs of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>3 years post IS withdrawal</time_frame>
    <description>Measuring pharmacoeconomic impact of IS withdrawal.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">148</enrollment>
  <condition>Transplantation, Liver</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (weaning)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants satisfying clinical criteria will be weaned off immunosuppression drugs irrespective of biomarker result.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B+ (weaning- positive biomarker)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants with a positive biomarker will be weaned of immunosuppression drugs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B- (maintenance)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participant with negative biomarker test result will be informed of the result and will remain on baseline maintenance immunosuppression drugs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biomarker</intervention_name>
    <description>Real time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) gene expression measurement</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B+ (weaning- positive biomarker)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm B- (maintenance)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tacrolimus, cyclosporine and/or mycophenolic acid, mycophenolate mofetil or azathioprine</intervention_name>
    <description>Immunosuppression drugs as per protocol</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm A (weaning)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IS</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. At the time of screening: more than 3 years post-transplant if participants are ≥50
             years old, OR more than 6 years post-transplant if participant age is 18-49 years old.

          2. Recipient of either deceased or living donor liver transplant.

          3. Recipient of single organ transplant only

          4. Liver function tests: direct bilirubin ≤17.1 umol/L and Alanine aminotransferase (ALT)
             ≤60 IU/L at the screening visit.

          5. On calcineurin inhibitor (CNI) based maintenance IS and no more than one of the
             following: Low dose mycophenolic acid (≤ 1080 mg daily), mycophenolate mofetil (MMF ≤
             1500 mg daily), or azathioprine (≤ 150 mg daily); or on mycophenolate/mycophenolic
             monotherapy (effective contraception must be used before beginning mycophenolate
             therapy, during therapy, and for six weeks following discontinuation of therapy).

          6. Ability to sign informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Serum positivity for Hepatitis C virus (HCV-RNA)

          2. Serum positivity for HIV-1 infection, Hepatitis B virus (HBV) surface antigen or
             HBV-DNA

          3. Immune-mediated liver disease in which IS discontinuation is inadvisable (autoimmune
             hepatitis, primary sclerosing cholangitis, primary biliary cirrhosis).

          4. Acute or chronic rejection within the 52 weeks prior to screening.

          5. Glomerular filtration rate (GFR) &lt;40 mL/min (to mitigate the risk of worsening renal
             failure should rejection occur and high level of CNI be required).

          6. The need for chronic anti-coagulation that cannot be safely discontinued to safely
             perform for a liver biopsy.

          7. Baseline (screening) liver biopsy showing any of the following: a) acute rejection
             according to Banff criteria; b) early or late chronic rejection according to Banff
             criteria; c) inflammatory activity and/or fibrosis in excess of permissive criteria;
             f) any other findings that might make participation in the trial unsafe. Eligibility
             will be determined by the central pathologist.

          8. Patient age &lt;18 years old at the time of transplant.

          9. Pregnant females and females of childbearing age not using effective contraception.

         10. Current illicit drug or alcohol abuse.

         11. Inability to participate in frequent monitoring of liver function (every 3 weeks) and
             clinical visits during IS withdrawal.

         12. Inability to comply with study directed treatment.

         13. Any medical condition that in the opinion of the principal investigator would
             interfere with safe completion of the trial.

         14. Participation in another clinical trial during the month prior to enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alberto Sanchez-Fueyo</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>King's College London</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jurate Wall</last_name>
    <email>jurate.wall@kcl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alberto Sanchez-Fueyo</last_name>
    <email>sanchez_fueyo@kcl.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>King's College Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE5 9RS</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alberto Sanchez-Fueyo</last_name>
      <email>sanchez_fueyo@kcl.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Jurate Wall</last_name>
      <email>jurate.wall@kcl.ac.uk</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alberto Sanchez-Fueyo</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Newcastle upon Tyne Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newcastle</city>
        <zip>NE7 7DN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Cole</last_name>
      <email>David.Cole@nuth.nhs.uk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven Masson</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 14, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 15, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Liver</keyword>
  <keyword>Transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunosuppression</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tacrolimus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclosporine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Azathioprine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mycophenolic Acid</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

