<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02497872</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ERCP001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02497872</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Early Precut Versus Pancreatic Stent for Post-ERCP Pancreatitis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Early Precut Versus Pancreatic Duct Stent in Preventing Post-ERCP Pancreatitis in High-risk Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centro de Educación Medica e Investigaciones Clínicas Norberto Quirno</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centro de Educación Medica e Investigaciones Clínicas Norberto Quirno</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND: The most common complication of endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography
      (ERCP) is pancreatitis. Precut sphincterotomy has been regarded as a risk factor. However,
      early precut may actually reduce post-ERCP pancreatitis risk. However, early precut as a
      preventive measure has not been compared to other preventive measures, such as pancreatic
      duct stent placement.

      AIM: To compare the efficacy of early precut sphincterotomy versus pancreatic duct stent
      placement in high-risk subjects undergoing ERCP.

      MATERIALS AND METHODS: This is a single-blinded, randomized trial that took place in two
      tertiary referral centers in Buenos Aires. ERCP subjects shall present at least one of the
      following risk factors: female sex, age less than 40 years, clinical suspicion of Sphincter
      of Oddi dysfunction, previous pancreatitis, common bile duct diameter of less than 8 mm. Only
      those who present a difficult biliary cannulation shall be randomized into two groups: those
      who receive early precut sphincterotomy or those in whom persistency of biliary cannulation
      is intended with subsequent pancreatic duct stent placement after cholangiography is
      achieved. The incidence of post-ERCP pancreatitis as well as other complications shall be
      compared.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      It is well known that pancreatitis is the most common and dreadful complication of endoscopic
      retrograde cholangiopancreatography (ERCP). Historically, precut sphincterotomy has been
      regarded as a risk factor for post-ERCP pancreatitis. However, some evidence has suggested
      that if used at an early point during the procedure, it may actually behave as a protective
      factor.

      In high risk patients, such as those patients with sphincter of Oddi dysfunction, pancreatic
      duct stent placement has been considered to be a prophylactic measure against pancreatitis.
      However, pancreatic duct stent placement can sometimes be a cumbersome procedure, and may
      require additional procedures (mainly if spontaneous stent dislodgment is not accomplished).
      There is no evidence comparing early precut versus pancreatic duct stent placement in
      high-risk patients.

      As a consequence, the aim of this study was to compare the efficacy of early precut
      sphincterotomy versus pancreatic duct stent placement in patients presenting at least one
      risk factor for post-ERCP pancreatitis and difficult biliary cannulation.

      A single-blinded, randomized trial was undertaken. Patients fulfilling inclusion criteria who
      presented with difficult biliary cannulation during ERCP were randomized to early precut or
      persistence in biliary cannulation with a sphincterotome with posterior pancreatic duct stent
      placement. The incidence of post-ERCP pancreatitis as well as other complications were
      compared between groups.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Post-ERCP Pancreatitis</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Common Bile Duct Stones</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Early Precut Sphincterectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Biliary stone removal using early precut: Patients enrolled in this arm received biliary drainage through a small incision on the papilla with an endoscopic needle-knife - a technique called precut sphincterotomy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pancreatic Duct Stent</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Biliary stone removal using persistence of cannulation and a later pancreatic duct stent placement: Patients enrolled in this arm received conventional biliary drainage through persistent biliary cannulation. After completion of biliary drainage, a prophylactic pancreatic duct stent was placed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Biliary stone removal</intervention_name>
    <description>Biliary stones are removed from the common bile duct by means of a sphincterotomy performed by standardized endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography</description>
    <arm_group_label>Early Precut Sphincterectomy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Pancreatic Duct Stent</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with in need for ERCP due to benign or malignant biliopancreatic conditions,
             with at least one of the following features:

          -  female sex

          -  age less than 40 years

          -  clinical suspicion of Sphincter of Oddi Dysfunction

          -  previous pancreatitis

          -  common bile duct diameter of less than 8 mm

          -  Subjects with difficult biliary cannulation, as defined by previously published
             criteria

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients with contrast allergy

          -  pregnant women

          -  patients unable to sign informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 29, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 12, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 15, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 12, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 12, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 15, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Centro de Educación Medica e Investigaciones Clínicas Norberto Quirno</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Juan Lasa</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

