<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02494063</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CEEGOG CX-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>16-31643A</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>ENGOT-Cx 2</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CEEGOG CX-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02494063</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy in Patients With Early Stages Cervical Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>SENTIX</acronym>
  <official_title>A Prospective Observational Trial on Sentinel Lymph Node Biopsy in Patients With Early Stage Cervical Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Charles University, Czech Republic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Charles University, Czech Republic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate whether a less radical surgical approach with sentinel lymph node biopsy is
      non-inferior to treatment with systematic pelvic lymphadenectomy.

      The null hypothesis is that the recurrence rate after SLN biopsy is non-inferior to the
      reference recurrence rate of 7 % (at the 24th month of follow-up) in patients after
      systematic pelvic lymphadenectomy, but that the less radical surgery is associated with
      significantly lower postoperative morbidity.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients will be enrolled in the study at the time of surgery planning; at this point, a
      patient´s consent will be requested if inclusion criteria are fulfilled (histological type,
      FIGO stage, age, performance status, lymph node clinical status). The following procedures
      will be provided prior to surgery: clinical staging (MRI or EUS), medical data collection,
      adverse events assessment, lymphedema assessment, quality of life questionnaire, ECOG
      performance status, weight and height, standard pre-operative laboratory workup, pregnancy
      test if clinically indicated.

      Surgery should be done within 6 weeks of the imaging study (MRI or expert US). During the
      surgery, local or distant cancer spread outside of the cervix will be excluded, SLN will be
      detected, and all SLN will be sent for intra-operative pathologic evaluation. In patients
      with SLN detection on both sides of the pelvis no other lymph nodes will be removed and they
      will continue in the study. SLN biopsy will be followed by radical hysterectomy (type B, C1,
      or C2) or fertility-sparing procedure, according to the pre-operative plan.

      Intra-operatively, the following patients will be excluded from the study, systematic pelvic
      lymphadenectomy will be performed on both sides of the pelvis, and further treatment will be
      provided according to institutional guidelines:

        1. Patients with intra-operative detection of more advanced disease stage (&gt; IB1)

        2. Patients without bilateral SLN detection (either no SLN detected or only on one side of
           the pelvis)

        3. Patients with intra-operative pathologic detection of macrometastases or micrometastases
           in SLN Excluded patients will remain in a database and reasons for their exclusion will
           be entered into the SIS (Form 2).

      In patients, who continue in the study, all SLNs will be processed by pathologists according
      to the protocol for SLN ultrastaging (Chapter 7.4.2; Appendix 11). If macrometastases or
      micrometastases are detected in any of the SLNs by pathologic ultrastaging after the surgery,
      adjuvant radiotherapy will be recommended to the patient. No adjuvant treatment will be
      offered to those with negative final lymph node status or ITC (Isolated Tumor Cells)
      detection, confirmed pre-operative disease FIGO stage (IA1 - IB1), and adequately performed
      radical hysterectomy with negative parametrial and vaginal margins.

      Follow-up will consist of visits at regular intervals of 6 months after the surgery
      (additional visits in shorter intervals can be scheduled according to institutional
      guidelines). The following procedures will be provided at each visit during the follow-up
      period: pelvic examination, symptomatic lymphocele assessment, quality of life assessment (6
      and 12 months after the surgery), adverse events assessment, and secondary lower extremity
      lymphedema assessment (2 years after surgery). Other imaging studies will be done only if
      clinically indicated. Any postoperative complication or disease recurrence will be managed
      according to the institutional guidelines.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrence rate at the 24th month of follow-up (cervical recurrences after fertility-sparing procedures will be excluded)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Recurrence rate (RR) will be estimated at the 24th month of follow-up to prove a non-inferiority of SLN biopsy to the reference value (RR 24th month: 7 %), non-inferiority margin = 5 %.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of symptomatic pelvic lymphocele</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in the prevalence of at least 30 % to the reference prevalence at 6%.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prevalence of lower extremity lymphedema</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in the prevalence of at least 30 % to the reference prevalence at 30%</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative morbidity</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Early postoperative morbidity (30 days after surgery) will be evaluated using 5-grade &quot;Dindo&quot; Classification of surgical complications. Late postoperative morbidity (from 30 days up to 2 years after surgery) will be evaluated using Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events v4.0 (CTCAE)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DFS (Disease Free survival)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pelvic DFS (Pelvic Disease Free Survival)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>The quality of life (QoL) will be assessed by European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer (EORTC) QLQ-C30 self-administered multi-dimensional scale cancer specific questionnaire, which is validated in 81 languages. It consists of 5 function scales, three symptom scales, six single-items and a global QoL score.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-operative morbidity</measure>
    <time_frame>1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Intra-operative morbidity will be evaluated using 5-grade &quot;Dindo&quot; Classification of surgical complications.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>FNR (False Negative Rate) of intra-operative pathologic SLN evaluation</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients with lymph nodes negative on intraoperative evaluation but positive on final ultrastaging</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DFS in SLN negative patients</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Disease free survival in patients with SLN negative on final ultrastaging</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Recurrence rate safety margins</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Recurrence rate safety margin (&gt; 0.12) as the study stopping rule will be examined when the first 30, 60 and 150 patients complete the 12-month follow-up.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">350</enrollment>
  <condition>Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SLN</arm_group_label>
    <description>Only sentinel lymph node biopsy, no further pelvic lymph nodes removal, radical hysterectomy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sentinel lymph node biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>Bilateral sentinel lymph node biopsy, pathologic ultrastaging</description>
    <arm_group_label>SLN</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with early stages cervical cancer
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        A) Preoperative:

          1. FIGO stage IA1+LVSI; IA2; IB1

          2. No evidence of bulky or suspicious pelvic lymph nodes or distant metastases in
             preoperative conventional imaging studies

          3. Performance status ECOG: 0 - 1

          4. Age ≥ 18 years, ≤ 75 years

          5. Squamous cell carcinoma OR Adenocarcinoma OR Adenosquamous carcinoma

          6. Suitable candidates for primary surgical treatment such as:

               -  radical hysterectomy in tumors ≤ 4 cm in the largest diameter OR

               -  fertility-sparing treatment in tumors ≤ 2 cm in the largest diameter

          7. History of second primary cancer only if &gt; 5 years with no evidence of disease

          8. Approved and signed Informed consent

        B) Intra-operative

          1. Bilateral SLN detection

          2. Negative intra-operative pathologic SLN evaluation (frozen section)

          3. No intra-operative evidence of more advanced disease (&gt;IB1)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Neoadjuvant chemotherapy

          2. Pregnancy

          3. History of pelvic or abdominal radiotherapy

          4. HIV positivity / AIDS
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Cibula, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Gynecologic Oncology Center, Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, General University Hospital in Prague and 1st Medical Faculty of the Charles University, Prague, Czech Republic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David Cibula, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+420224967451</phone>
    <email>d_cibula@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ivana Nohova, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+420224967451</phone>
    <email>Ivana.Nohova@vfn.cz</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gynecologic Oncology Center in Prague</name>
      <address>
        <city>Prague</city>
        <zip>15000</zip>
        <country>Czechia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>David Cibula, M.D.</last_name>
      <phone>+420603547055</phone>
      <email>d_cibula@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ivana Nohova, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+420224967451</phone>
      <email>Ivana.Nohova@vfn.cz</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Czechia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Czech Republic</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zikan M, Fischerova D, Pinkavova I, Slama J, Weinberger V, Dusek L, Cibula D. A prospective study examining the incidence of asymptomatic and symptomatic lymphoceles following lymphadenectomy in patients with gynecological cancer. Gynecol Oncol. 2015 May;137(2):291-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ygyno.2015.02.016. Epub 2015 Feb 24.</citation>
    <PMID>25720294</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cibula D, Oonk MH, Abu-Rustum NR. Sentinel lymph node biopsy in the management of gynecologic cancer. Curr Opin Obstet Gynecol. 2015 Feb;27(1):66-72. doi: 10.1097/GCO.0000000000000133. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25502426</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giammarile F, Bozkurt MF, Cibula D, Pahisa J, Oyen WJ, Paredes P, Olmos RV, Sicart SV. The EANM clinical and technical guidelines for lymphoscintigraphy and sentinel node localization in gynaecological cancers. Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging. 2014 Jul;41(7):1463-77. doi: 10.1007/s00259-014-2732-8. Epub 2014 Mar 8.</citation>
    <PMID>24609929</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cibula D, Abu-Rustum NR, Dusek L, Slama J, Zikán M, Zaal A, Sevcik L, Kenter G, Querleu D, Jach R, Bats AS, Dyduch G, Graf P, Klat J, Meijer CJ, Mery E, Verheijen R, Zweemer RP. Bilateral ultrastaging of sentinel lymph node in cervical cancer: Lowering the false-negative rate and improving the detection of micrometastasis. Gynecol Oncol. 2012 Dec;127(3):462-6. doi: 10.1016/j.ygyno.2012.08.035. Epub 2012 Aug 31.</citation>
    <PMID>22943880</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cibula D, Abu-Rustum NR, Dusek L, Zikán M, Zaal A, Sevcik L, Kenter GG, Querleu D, Jach R, Bats AS, Dyduch G, Graf P, Klat J, Lacheta J, Meijer CJ, Mery E, Verheijen R, Zweemer RP. Prognostic significance of low volume sentinel lymph node disease in early-stage cervical cancer. Gynecol Oncol. 2012 Mar;124(3):496-501. doi: 10.1016/j.ygyno.2011.11.037. Epub 2011 Nov 25.</citation>
    <PMID>22120175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cibula D, Abu-Rustum NR, Benedetti-Panici P, Köhler C, Raspagliesi F, Querleu D, Morrow CP. New classification system of radical hysterectomy: emphasis on a three-dimensional anatomic template for parametrial resection. Gynecol Oncol. 2011 Aug;122(2):264-8. doi: 10.1016/j.ygyno.2011.04.029. Epub 2011 May 17.</citation>
    <PMID>21592548</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cibula D, Abu-Rustum NR. Pelvic lymphadenectomy in cervical cancer--surgical anatomy and proposal for a new classification system. Gynecol Oncol. 2010 Jan;116(1):33-7. doi: 10.1016/j.ygyno.2009.09.003. Epub 2009 Oct 17.</citation>
    <PMID>19837449</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dindo D, Demartines N, Clavien PA. Classification of surgical complications: a new proposal with evaluation in a cohort of 6336 patients and results of a survey. Ann Surg. 2004 Aug;240(2):205-13.</citation>
    <PMID>15273542</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 6, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 7, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 10, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Charles University, Czech Republic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Cibula</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, PhD, Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>cervical cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>sentinel lymph node</keyword>
  <keyword>lymphadenectomy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

