<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02496884</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DS5565-A-U307</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2014-003972-21</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02496884</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Study of DS-5565 for Treatment of Fibromyalgia Pain in Subjects With Chronic Kidney Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled Safety Study of DS-5565 for Treatment of Pain Due to Fibromyalgia in Subjects With Chronic Kidney Disease</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Daiichi Sankyo, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>INC Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Daiichi Sankyo, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      DS-5565 (mirogabalin) is being studied as treatment for fibromyalgia pain. Because it is
      excreted through the kidneys, people who have reduced kidney function will not process the
      drug as well as with those with normal kidney function, so the dose must be reduced. This
      study will test two reduced dose levels for both moderately reduced and severely reduced
      kidney function. The study will test the hypothesis that the drug will be safe and
      well-tolerated in people who have both fibromyalgia and chronic kidney disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a stratified, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, multi-center safety study
      of DS-5565 in subjects with Fibromyalgia (FM) and renal dysfunction. Eligible subjects will
      be randomized 2:1 to receive either DS-5565 7.5 mg or placebo once daily (QD) for the
      category of subjects with creatinine clearance (CrCl) 15-29 mL/min, or 2:1 to receive
      treatment with DS-5565 7.5 mg or placebo twice daily (BID) for the category of subjects with
      CrCl 30-59 mL/min.

      Subjects will be stratified for renal impairment by CrCl. The treatment period is 13 weeks in
      duration. The total study duration (individual subject) will be approximately 21 weeks. The
      study includes a screening period (approximately 3 weeks but no longer than 35 days,
      including a washout period [if necessary] and a 1-week baseline period), double-blind
      treatment period (13 weeks), and a 4 week follow-up period.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 6, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 6, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants experiencing a Treatment Emergent Adverse Event (TEAE)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline through follow-up period 4 weeks after the last dose of study medication, within 25 months</time_frame>
    <description>A TEAE is defined as an adverse event that emerges during treatment (having been absent prior to treatment) or gets worse than it was before treatment. All withdrawal symptoms and clinical laboratory, vital sign, or electrocardiogram (ECG) values will be appraised by the Investigator as to clinical significance. Clinically significant findings will be reported as AEs if they are symptomatic, lead to study drug discontinuation, require corrective treatment, or are otherwise defined as an adverse event of special interest (AESI)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from Baseline in Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline, Week 13</time_frame>
    <description>The C-SSRS is described as a scale developed at Columbia University that has 2-6 questions each in categories of Suicidal Ideation, Intensity of Ideation, Suicidal Behavior, and Actual Attempts. The higher the score, the higher the suicide risk.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Weekly Average of Individual Daily Pain Scores (ADPS)</measure>
    <time_frame>for 13 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Each day participants will rate their worst pain over the last 24 hours on a scale from 0-10, where 0=no pain and 10=worst pain imaginable. Each week individual pain scores will be averaged, and the mean weekly score for the treatment group will be calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean Patient Global Impression of Change (PGIC) scores</measure>
    <time_frame>at week 13</time_frame>
    <description>At the end of treatment, participants will rate their overall status on a scale of 1-7, where 1=very much improved and 7=very much worse using the standard PGIC questionnaire. The PGIC is a validated outcome measure for treatment of pain in the acute pain setting.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">56</enrollment>
  <condition>Fibromyalgia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MCKD DS-5565</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fibromyalgia patients with moderate chronic kidney disease (MCKD) randomized to receive DS-5565 7.5 mg tablets twice per day, for a total of 15 mg DS-5565</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SCKD DS-5565</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fibromyalgia patients with severe chronic kidney disease (SCKD) randomized to receive a DS-5565 7.5 mg tablet once per day, and a placebo tablet (no drug) once per day, for a total of 7.5 mg DS-5565</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MCKD Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fibromyalgia patients with MCKD randomized to receive placebo tablets twice per day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SCKD Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Fibromyalgia patients with SCKD randomized to receive placebo tablets twice per day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DS-5565</intervention_name>
    <description>DS-5565 7.5 mg tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>MCKD DS-5565</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SCKD DS-5565</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Experimental drug</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo tablet to match DS-5565 7.5 mg tablet</description>
    <arm_group_label>SCKD DS-5565</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>MCKD Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>SCKD Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>No drug</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Abbreviations: alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), creatinine
        clearance [(CrCL) determined by the central laboratory using the Cockcroft-Gault equation],
        upper limit of normal (ULN), Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS)

        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age ≥ 18 years

          -  Able to give written informed consent

          -  Able to complete patient-reported questionnaires per the Investigator's judgment

          -  Estimated CrCl between 15-59 mL/min from serum creatinine by the central laboratory
             using the Cockcroft-Gault equation

          -  Fibromyalgia meeting American College of Rheumatology criteria for FM:

               -  Widespread pain index (WPI) ≥ 7 and symptom severity (SS) scale score ≥ 5 or WPI
                  3 to 6 and SS scale score ≥ 9,

               -  Pain in at least 11 of 18 specific tender point sites,

               -  Symptoms have been present at a similar level for at least 3 months, and

               -  The subject does not have a disorder that would otherwise explain the pain

          -  Average Daily Pain Score of ≥ 4 on the 11-point numeric rating scale (NRS) over the 7
             days prior to randomization (based on completion of at least 4 daily pain assessments
             during the 7-day baseline period prior to randomization)

          -  Women of child bearing potential (WOCBP) must be using adequate methods of
             contraception to avoid pregnancy during the study and for 4 weeks after study
             completion.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Need for ongoing use of concomitant chronic pain medications or any new
             non-pharmacological pain management techniques that may confound assessments of
             efficacy and/or safety, including neurolytic treatments (destruction of nerves by
             chemicals, heat, cold) or surgery, intrathecal pumps, spinal cord stimulators or
             psychological support within the previous year. Also excluded: topical capsaicin
             within 6 months; or systemic corticosteroids within 3 months of baseline period.

          -  Unable to undergo pre-study washout of prohibited concomitant medications

          -  Subjects with recent history (i.e., within 1 year prior to screening) of alcohol abuse
             or illicit drug use (cocaine, heroin, marijuana [including medical, prescribed], etc.)

          -  Use of any selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor (SSRI), unless the subject has been
             on a stable dose for ≥ 90 days prior to screening and is not anticipated to need any
             dose adjustment during the course of the study

          -  Subjects with severe or uncontrolled depression that, in the judgment of the
             Investigator, makes the subject inappropriate for entry into the study

          -  Significant neurological or psychiatric disorder unrelated to neuropathic pain

          -  Other severe pain (eg, sciatica, rheumatoid arthritis) that might impair the
             assessment of neuropathic pain

          -  CrCl ≥ 60 mL/min estimated from serum creatinine by the central laboratory using the
             Cockcroft-Gault equation.

          -  Subjects who are on hemodialysis or who require hemodialysis before the follow-up
             assessment; acute renal failure; history of kidney transplant

          -  Any history of a malignancy other than basal cell carcinoma within the past 5 years

          -  Clinically significant unstable neurologic, ophthalmologic, hepatobiliary,
             respiratory, or hematologic illness or unstable cardiovascular disease (eg, severe
             hypotension, uncontrolled cardiac arrhythmia, or myocardial infarction) within 12
             months prior to screening

          -  Pregnancy or breast feeding or intent to become pregnant during the study period

          -  Known hypersensitivity to α2δ ligands or other components of the study medications.
             Note: Prior exposure to DS-5565 is allowed, as long as hypersensitivity to DS-5565 was
             not observed.

          -  Clinically significant ECG abnormalities at the Screening Visit

          -  Subjects who are at risk of suicide, as defined by their responses to the C-SSRS or in
             the opinion of the Investigator. Note: Subjects answering &quot;yes&quot; to any of the
             questions about active suicidal ideation/intent/behaviors that occurred within the
             past 12 months must be excluded (C-SSRS Suicide Ideation section - Questions 3, 4, or
             5; C-SSRS Suicidal Behavior section - any of the suicide behaviors questions). Such
             subjects should be referred immediately to a mental health professional for
             appropriate evaluation.

          -  Subjects who are unlikely to comply with the protocol (eg, uncooperative attitude,
             inability to return for subsequent visits, and/or otherwise considered by the
             Investigator to be unlikely to complete the study)

          -  Subject is currently enrolled in, or it has been fewer than 30 days since ending,
             another investigational device or drug study or is receiving another investigational
             agent.

          -  Subjects who are employees or immediate family of employees of the study site,
             Sponsor, or contract research organization (CRO)

          -  Screening laboratory values outside the limits listed in the table below:

               -  Hematology

               -  Hemoglobin &lt; 8 g/dL

               -  Platelet count &lt; 100,000/mm3

               -  Absolute neutrophil count &lt; 1,500/mm3

               -  Blood chemistry

               -  AST &gt; 2.0 × ULN

               -  ALT &gt; 2.0 × ULN

               -  Alkaline phosphatase &gt; 1.5 × ULN

               -  Total bilirubin &gt; 1.2 × ULN (If a subject has total bilirubin &gt;ULN: unconjugated
                  and conjugated bilirubin fractions should be analyzed and only subject documented
                  to have Gilbert's syndrome may be enrolled)

               -  Creatine kinase &gt; 3.0 × ULN

               -  Calculated CrCl ≥ 60 mL/min
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Global Clinical Leader</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Daiichi Sankyo, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Phoenix</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85018</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Colton</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92324</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90033</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Santa Ana</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Colorado Springs</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80918</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Brooksville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>34601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>DeBary</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32713</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Hialeah</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33013</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kissimmee</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>34744</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33144</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Grand Blanc</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48439</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>High Point</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27262</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Cincinnati</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>45224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Wyomissing</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19610</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Greer</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29651</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Rapid City</city>
        <state>South Dakota</state>
        <zip>57702</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Knoxville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37919</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77098</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Plano</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75093</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Bellevue</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98007</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>West Virginia</state>
        <zip>25304</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Morgantown</city>
        <state>West Virginia</state>
        <zip>26505</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Plovdiv</city>
        <country>Bulgaria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Sevlievo</city>
        <country>Bulgaria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Sofia</city>
        <country>Bulgaria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Stara Zagora</city>
        <country>Bulgaria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Varna</city>
        <country>Bulgaria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Prague</city>
        <country>Czechia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Ricany</city>
        <country>Czechia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Budapest</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Nyiregyhaza</city>
        <country>Hungary</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Elblag</city>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kraków</city>
        <country>Poland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Cluj-napoca</city>
        <country>Romania</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Johannesburg</city>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Pretoria</city>
        <country>South Africa</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Santiago de Compostela</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Bulgaria</country>
    <country>Czechia</country>
    <country>Hungary</country>
    <country>Poland</country>
    <country>Romania</country>
    <country>South Africa</country>
    <country>Spain</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Czech Republic</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 8, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 13, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 14, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>chronic kidney disease</keyword>
  <keyword>. α2δ ligands</keyword>
  <keyword>mirogabalin</keyword>
  <keyword>pain relief</keyword>
  <keyword>kidney metabolism</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fibromyalgia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofascial Pain Syndromes</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

