<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02495389</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>207102</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02495389</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Mirabegron and Urinary Urgency Incontinence</brief_title>
  <official_title>Mirabegron and Urinary Urgency Incontinence: The Clinical Response and the Female Urinary Microbiome</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Loyola University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Astellas Pharma US, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Loyola University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is for women diagnosed with urgency incontinence or overactive bladder (OAB). Some
      patients continue to have symptoms even while taking medication for OAB. The purpose of this
      study is to see if women who respond to a medication called mirabegron have different bladder
      bacteria than women who do not respond.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Mirabegron is an FDA-approved medication for urgency incontinence. Evaluation of mirabegron's
      influence on clinical symptoms should take into account the effect of the female urinary
      microbiome (FUM) on patient response to treatment. Several bacterial species are more common
      in overactive bladder patients than in asymptomatic controls.

      Currently, physicians have limited ability to personalize urinary urgency incontinence
      treatment, and thus the prescribed medication may provide minimal symptom relief for some
      patients. Since the FUM can be assessed prior to treatment, this study proposes to determine
      if baseline FUM assessment can provide insight into future symptoms relief with mirabegron
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Perception of Bladder Control (PPBC)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure in which patients are asked to rate their perceived bladder condition on a 6-point scale ranging from 1 (no problems at all) to 6 (many severe problems)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overactive Bladder Questionnaire (OAB-q)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure in which patients are asked to rate how much they have been bothered by bladder symptoms on a scale of 1 (not at all) to 6 (a very great deal). Patients are also asked to rate how much symptoms have affected their life on a scale of 1 (none of the time) to 6 (all of the time).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Urinary Distress Inventory (UDI-6)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure in which patients are asked to rate how much they are bothered by symptoms of urinary urgency on a scale from 1(not at all) to 4 (quite a bit)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pelvic Floor Distress Inventory (PFDI)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure in which patients are asked to rate how much they are bothered by pelvic area symptoms on a scale from 1 (not at all) to 4 (quite a bit).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Global Impression of Severity (PGI-S)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure in which patients are asked to rate their urinary tract condition on a scale from 1 (normal) to 4 (severe).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>Overactive Bladder</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mirabegron</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All study participants will receive 25 mg mirabegron (Myrbetriq) to be taken by mouth once a day for 12 weeks. If after 4 weeks symptoms are not adequately improving, participants will have the option of increasing mirabegron dose to 50 mg per day for the remaining 8 weeks.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mirabegron</intervention_name>
    <description>All study participants will be given mirabegron, 25 mg by mouth once a day for 12 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>mirabegron</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Myrbetriq</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Bothersome idiopathic (non-neurologic) urgency urinary incontinence (UUI) who recall ≥
             5 urgency predominant urinary incontinence episodes in the prior week (urgency urinary
             incontinence or mixed urinary incontinence-urgency predominant)

          -  No contraindications to taking mirabegron

          -  Patients on current OAB therapy will undergo a two-week drug washout period prior to
             baseline assessment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Neurologic disease known to affect the lower urinary tract

          -  Systemic immunologic deficiency

          -  Current urinary tract infection (UTI) (based on dipstick assessment) or recurrent
             culture-proven UTIs

          -  History or current pelvic malignancy or radiation

          -  Untreated symptomatic pelvic organ prolapse (POP) &gt; POP-Q Stage II

          -  A contraindication to receiving mirabegron

          -  Women of childbearing potential who are pregnant or nursing or intend to become
             pregnant during the study, or who are not practicing a reliable method of
             contraception

          -  Must not have taken any antibiotics, for any reason, in the 4 weeks prior to
             enrollment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alan Wolfe, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Loyola Univerity Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alan Wolfe, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>708-216-5814</phone>
    <email>awolfe@luc.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Loyola University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Maywood</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60153</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alan Wolfe, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>708-216-5814</phone>
      <email>awolfe@luc.edu</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barber MD, Chen Z, Lukacz E, Markland A, Wai C, Brubaker L, Nygaard I, Weidner A, Janz NK, Spino C. Further validation of the short form versions of the Pelvic Floor Distress Inventory (PFDI) and Pelvic Floor Impact Questionnaire (PFIQ). Neurourol Urodyn. 2011 Apr;30(4):541-6. doi: 10.1002/nau.20934. Epub 2011 Feb 22.</citation>
    <PMID>21344495</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brubaker L, Nager CW, Richter HE, Visco A, Nygaard I, Barber MD, Schaffer J, Meikle S, Wallace D, Shibata N, Wolfe AJ. Urinary bacteria in adult women with urgency urinary incontinence. Int Urogynecol J. 2014 Sep;25(9):1179-84. doi: 10.1007/s00192-013-2325-2. Epub 2014 Feb 11.</citation>
    <PMID>24515544</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chapple CR, Cardozo L, Nitti VW, Siddiqui E, Michel MC. Mirabegron in overactive bladder: a review of efficacy, safety, and tolerability. Neurourol Urodyn. 2014 Jan;33(1):17-30. doi: 10.1002/nau.22505. Epub 2013 Oct 11. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24127366</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chapple CR, Nitti VW, Khullar V, Wyndaele JJ, Herschorn S, van Kerrebroeck P, Blauwet MB, Siddiqui E. Onset of action of the β3-adrenoceptor agonist, mirabegron, in Phase II and III clinical trials in patients with overactive bladder. World J Urol. 2014 Dec;32(6):1565-72. doi: 10.1007/s00345-014-1244-2. Epub 2014 Jan 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24458878</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coyne K, Revicki D, Hunt T, Corey R, Stewart W, Bentkover J, Kurth H, Abrams P. Psychometric validation of an overactive bladder symptom and health-related quality of life questionnaire: the OAB-q. Qual Life Res. 2002 Sep;11(6):563-74.</citation>
    <PMID>12206577</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coyne KS, Matza LS, Kopp Z, Abrams P. The validation of the patient perception of bladder condition (PPBC): a single-item global measure for patients with overactive bladder. Eur Urol. 2006 Jun;49(6):1079-86. Epub 2006 Jan 24.</citation>
    <PMID>16460875</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Boer TA, Salvatore S, Cardozo L, Chapple C, Kelleher C, van Kerrebroeck P, Kirby MG, Koelbl H, Espuna-Pons M, Milsom I, Tubaro A, Wagg A, Vierhout ME. Pelvic organ prolapse and overactive bladder. Neurourol Urodyn. 2010;29(1):30-9. doi: 10.1002/nau.20858. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20025017</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fouts DE, Pieper R, Szpakowski S, Pohl H, Knoblach S, Suh MJ, Huang ST, Ljungberg I, Sprague BM, Lucas SK, Torralba M, Nelson KE, Groah SL. Integrated next-generation sequencing of 16S rDNA and metaproteomics differentiate the healthy urine microbiome from asymptomatic bacteriuria in neuropathic bladder associated with spinal cord injury. J Transl Med. 2012 Aug 28;10:174. doi: 10.1186/1479-5876-10-174.</citation>
    <PMID>22929533</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hartmann, K.E., McPheeters, M.L., Biller, D.H., Ward, R.M., McKoy, J.N., Jerome, R.N., Micucci, S.R., Meints, L., Fisher, J.A., Scott, T.A., et al. (2009). Treatment of overactive bladder in women. Evid Rep Technol Assess (Full Rep), 1-120, v. Haylen, B.T., de Ridder, D., Freeman, R.M., Swift, S.E., Berghmans, B., Lee, J., Monga, A., Petri, E., Rizk, D.E., Sand, P.K., et al. (2010a). An International Urogynecological Association (IUGA)/International Continence Society (ICS) joint report on the terminology for female pelvic floor dysfunction. Int Urogynecol J 21, 5-26.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haylen BT, de Ridder D, Freeman RM, Swift SE, Berghmans B, Lee J, Monga A, Petri E, Rizk DE, Sand PK, Schaer GN; International Urogynecological Association; International Continence Society. An International Urogynecological Association (IUGA)/International Continence Society (ICS) joint report on the terminology for female pelvic floor dysfunction. Neurourol Urodyn. 2010;29(1):4-20. doi: 10.1002/nau.20798. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19941278</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hilt EE, McKinley K, Pearce MM, Rosenfeld AB, Zilliox MJ, Mueller ER, Brubaker L, Gai X, Wolfe AJ, Schreckenberger PC. Urine is not sterile: use of enhanced urine culture techniques to detect resident bacterial flora in the adult female bladder. J Clin Microbiol. 2014 Mar;52(3):871-6. doi: 10.1128/JCM.02876-13. Epub 2013 Dec 26.</citation>
    <PMID>24371246</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irwin DE, Kopp ZS, Agatep B, Milsom I, Abrams P. Worldwide prevalence estimates of lower urinary tract symptoms, overactive bladder, urinary incontinence and bladder outlet obstruction. BJU Int. 2011 Oct;108(7):1132-8. doi: 10.1111/j.1464-410X.2010.09993.x. Epub 2011 Jan 13.</citation>
    <PMID>21231991</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kenton K, Fitzgerald MP, Brubaker L. What is a clinician to do-believe the patient or her urinary diary? J Urol. 2006 Aug;176(2):633-5; discussion 635.</citation>
    <PMID>16813908</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khasriya R, Sathiananthamoorthy S, Ismail S, Kelsey M, Wilson M, Rohn JL, Malone-Lee J. Spectrum of bacterial colonization associated with urothelial cells from patients with chronic lower urinary tract symptoms. J Clin Microbiol. 2013 Jul;51(7):2054-62. doi: 10.1128/JCM.03314-12. Epub 2013 Apr 17.</citation>
    <PMID>23596238</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lowenstein L, Rickey L, Kenton K, Fitzgerald MP, Brubaker L, Tulke M, Fordham J, Mueller ER. Reliability and responsiveness of the Urgency Severity and Life Impact Questionnaire (USIQ). Int Urogynecol J. 2012 Feb;23(2):193-6. doi: 10.1007/s00192-011-1531-z. Epub 2011 Aug 18.</citation>
    <PMID>21850507</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Michel MC, Chapple CR. Basic mechanisms of urgency: roles and benefits of pharmacotherapy. World J Urol. 2009 Dec;27(6):705-9. doi: 10.1007/s00345-009-0446-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19588154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mostwin JL. Pathophysiology: the varieties of bladder overactivity. Urology. 2002 Nov;60(5 Suppl 1):22-6; discussion 27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12493346</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pearce MM, Hilt EE, Rosenfeld AB, Zilliox MJ, Thomas-White K, Fok C, Kliethermes S, Schreckenberger PC, Brubaker L, Gai X, Wolfe AJ. The female urinary microbiome: a comparison of women with and without urgency urinary incontinence. MBio. 2014 Jul 8;5(4):e01283-14. doi: 10.1128/mBio.01283-14.</citation>
    <PMID>25006228</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sajadi KP, Vasavada SP. Overactive bladder after sling surgery. Curr Urol Rep. 2010 Nov;11(6):366-71. doi: 10.1007/s11934-010-0136-2.</citation>
    <PMID>20803179</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Siddiqui H, Nederbragt AJ, Lagesen K, Jeansson SL, Jakobsen KS. Assessing diversity of the female urine microbiota by high throughput sequencing of 16S rDNA amplicons. BMC Microbiol. 2011 Nov 2;11:244. doi: 10.1186/1471-2180-11-244.</citation>
    <PMID>22047020</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith HS, Hughes JP, Hooton TM, Roberts P, Scholes D, Stergachis A, Stapleton A, Stamm WE. Antecedent antimicrobial use increases the risk of uncomplicated cystitis in young women. Clin Infect Dis. 1997 Jul;25(1):63-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9243034</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tincello DG, Owen RK, Slack MC, Abrams KR. Validation of the Patient Global Impression scales for use in detrusor overactivity: secondary analysis of the RELAX study. BJOG. 2013 Jan;120(2):212-216. doi: 10.1111/1471-0528.12069. Epub 2012 Nov 27.</citation>
    <PMID>23189940</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolfe AJ, Toh E, Shibata N, Rong R, Kenton K, Fitzgerald M, Mueller ER, Schreckenberger P, Dong Q, Nelson DE, Brubaker L. Evidence of uncultivated bacteria in the adult female bladder. J Clin Microbiol. 2012 Apr;50(4):1376-83. doi: 10.1128/JCM.05852-11. Epub 2012 Jan 25.</citation>
    <PMID>22278835</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 9, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 10, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 13, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 23, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Loyola University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alan J. Wolfe</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>urinary urgency incontinence</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder, Overactive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Mirabegron</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

