<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02497586</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GN15ON255</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02497586</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Feasibility of Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy in Lung Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>MRS</acronym>
  <official_title>Feasibility of Magnetic Resonance Spectroscopy in Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Lung cancer is commonly characterised either with a surgical procedure or by taking a tissue
      sample with a needle. Unfortunately, these invasive approaches may be unsafe in many patients
      with lung cancer, who often have co-existing illnesses such as emphysema.

      Magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS) is a type of scan which offers the possibility of
      assessing tumour function by measuring concentrations of chemicals (metabolites) within the
      abnormal tissue. It is a well-established technique in imaging brain cancers. It has also
      been more recently studied in assessing prostate, liver and heart. There has been very little
      exploration of the potential role of MRS in lung cancer.

      The proposed feasibility study will recruit 15 patients with proven lung cancer to undergo an
      MRS scan. The reliability of the technique for metabolite measurement will be determined by
      comparing repeated scans from the same region in the same tumour. Further scans from
      different regions in the same tumour, normal lung around the tumour and tumour regions in
      different patients will be used to look for any patterns in the cancer metabolites which may
      indicate avenues for potential future research.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS) is a magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) application that
      we aim to utilise in lung cancer for the first time at a higher magnetic field strength (3
      Tesla). MRS allows nuclear magnetic resonance spectra to be obtained from user-defined
      regions of interest (ROIs) within body tissues. These spectra can be used to quantify
      concentrations of tumour metabolites, providing unique biological information non-invasively
      and without the need for ionising radiation or intravenous contrast material. Proton MRS is a
      well-established technique for characterisation of brain pathology and prostate cancer. MRS
      in the lung is more challenging as it is a moving structure but has been shown to be feasible
      in a previous small study using more basic standard field strength equipment and technique.
      MRS of other moving structures, namely the heart and liver, has been shown to be achievable.

      It is believed that MRS, using a higher field strength (3 Tesla) machine, has not been
      applied before in the evaluation of lung cancer in human subjects. Successful utilisation of
      this technology to quantify metabolite concentrations within lung cancers offers new
      opportunities for non-invasive tumour classification. For example, low tumour oxygen levels,
      a known prognostic indicator, may be identifiable by non-invasive measurement of lactate
      concentration by MRS. Since MRS is an easily repeatable technique without ionising radiation,
      it may also prove useful in response assessment following lung cancer therapies. This is a
      prospective feasibility study, aiming to recruit 15 consecutive patients with lung cancer to
      undergo proton MRS. The feasibility and repeatability of the technique will be assessed by
      analysis of the MR spectra obtained.

      The principal research questions is: Can MRS scans be obtained in lung cancer with a high
      field strength (3 Tesla) MR scanner? The secondary research questions are: Is there any
      indication of reproducibility in the MRS signals obtained? Is there any indication of MRS
      patterns correlating with tumour type and other clinical parameters which might be a useful
      subject for further investigation in lung cancer characterisation?

      Summary of interventions:

        1. During attendance at respiratory clinic, invite patient to participate in study and
           issue Patient Information Sheet (PIS), highlighting contact details for next steps
           (typically 5 min)

        2. Patients with questions may contact a study investigator using the telephone number in
           the PIS to have them answered (typically 5-15 min)

        3. Patients wishing to proceed contact the RIF using the telephone number in the PIS to
           arrange a convenient scan appointment and taxi transfers (typically 5 min) At least 1
           day after clinic attendance

        4. Written informed consent obtained, pre-scan checklist completed and GP letter sent by
           medical member of study team. Research radiographer completes safety checklist with
           patient. Scan undertaken, with maximum 'on table' scan time of 1 hour.

      Implications for research for future service developments:

      If this early study shows MRS of lung cancer to be technically feasible, the investigators
      will apply for external funding for a larger prospective study or studies correlating the MRS
      findings with a panel of clinical, imaging, histopathological and molecular variables. These
      secondary studies would have potential to alter clinical practice in tumour characterisation
      and follow-up. The overall aim of the research would be the development of a non-invasive
      tool to enable diagnosis and characterisation of suspected lung cancers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>August 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of metabolite peaks</measure>
    <time_frame>Data collected on day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Presence of metabolite peaks in MR spectra obtained from lung tumours using a 3T MR system.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reproducability of metabolite peaks</measure>
    <time_frame>Data collected on day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Reproducibility of metabolite peak ratios in MR spectra repeatedly obtained from lung tumours using a 3T MR system.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Metabolite peak-clinical parameter colleration</measure>
    <time_frame>Data collected on day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation between metabolite peak ratios in MR spectra from lung tumours and clinical parameters including lung cancer type and treatment response.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">15</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MRS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS) is a type of scan which offers the possibility of assessing tumour function by measuring concentrations of chemicals (metabolites) within the abnormal tissue. This is a prospective feasibility study, aiming to recruit 15 consecutive patients with lung cancer to undergo proton MRS. The feasibility and repeatability of the technique will be assessed by analysis of the MR spectra obtained.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Magnetic resonance spectroscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>Magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS) is a type of scan which offers the possibility of assessing tumour function by measuring concentrations of chemicals (metabolites) within the abnormal tissue. It is a well-established technique in imaging brain cancers.</description>
    <arm_group_label>MRS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  biopsy-confirmed small cell or non-small cell lung cancer

          -  solid intrapulmonary tumour of at least 3 cm in long and short axis diameters on
             transverse CT images

          -  ECOG performance status ≤ 2

          -  able to provide written informed consent and respond appropriately to verbal
             instructions for scan acquisition

          -  age 18 years or older

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  chemotherapy within the preceding 12 months

          -  previous radiotherapy to the tumour

          -  cardiac pacemaker/defibrillator, internal pacing wires, cerebral aneurysm clip,
             incompatible metallic heart valve replacements, other incompatible
             implants/prostheses, claustrophobia or other MRI contraindication

          -  history of metal entering the body or eye, unless residual metal in the affected area
             likely to cause harm has been adequately excluded by X-ray in the opinion of Dr Cowell
             or Dr Stobo

          -  intractable cough, inability to lie flat or other impediment to acquisition of
             breath-held MR images

          -  pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David B Stobo, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NHS Greater Glasgow and Clyde</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>David B Stobo, Dr</last_name>
    <phone>0141 452 3635</phone>
    <email>david.stobo2@ggc.scot.nhs.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <reference>
    <citation>Castillo M, Kwock L, Mukherji SK. Clinical applications of proton MR spectroscopy. AJNR Am J Neuroradiol. 1996 Jan;17(1):1-15. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8770242</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 15, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 10, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 14, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 10, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 10, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 14, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

