<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02494700</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014-1046</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2015-01203</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02494700</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ultra Low Dose 4 Gy Orbital Radiation for Definitive Therapy of Indolent B Cell Lymphoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Ultra Low Dose 4 Gy Orbital Radiation for Definitive Therapy of Indolent B Cell Lymphoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this clinical research study is to learn about the effectiveness of low dose
      radiation therapy in patients with low grade B cell lymphoma or mantle cell lymphoma
      involving the eye.

      This is an investigational study. It is investigational to treat B cell lymphoma or mantle
      cell lymphoma involving the eye with lower doses of radiation. Radiation therapy given in
      this study is performed using FDA-approved and commercially available methods.

      Up to 50 participants will be enrolled on this study. All will take part at MD Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Baseline Tests:

      If you agree to take part in this study, the following baseline tests and procedures will be
      performed:

        -  You will have a physical exam.

        -  Blood (about 2 teaspoons) will be drawn for routine tests. This routine blood draw will
           include a pregnancy test if you can become pregnant. To take part in this study, you
           cannot be pregnant.

        -  You will have a computed tomography (CT) scan and a positron emission tomography (PET)
           scan of the head and neck to check the status of the disease. If the study doctor thinks
           it is needed, you may also have a magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan.

        -  You will have a biopsy of your eye lesion. You will be given either general or local
           anesthesia with sedation as needed to numb the area.

        -  You will have an eye exam by an eye doctor. This eye exam may include photographs being
           taken of your eyes.

        -  If the study doctor thinks it is needed, you will have a bone marrow aspirate/biopsy to
           check the status of the disease. To collect a bone marrow aspirate, an area of the hip
           or other site is numbed with anesthetic, and a small amount of bone marrow is withdrawn
           through a large needle. To collect a bone marrow biopsy, an area of the hip or other
           site is numbed with anesthetic, and a small amount of bone marrow and bone is withdrawn
           through a large needle.

      Study Visits:

      You will have a CT scan without contrast for the purpose of planning your radiation. This is
      called a &quot;CT simulation.&quot; After you complete CT simulation, you will receive low dose
      radiation with contrast 2 days in a row. Contrast drugs allow researchers to see the
      difference between normal and abnormal tissue.

      Follow Up Visits:

      Every 3 months:

        -  You will have an eye exam by an eye doctor.

        -  You will have an MRI or CT scan to check the status of the disease.

      If the study doctor thinks it is needed, you will receive the standard dose of radiation at
      that time. In that case, you will sign a separate consent that explains the risks.

      Length of Study Participation:

      You may continue taking part in the study as long as the study doctor thinks it is in your
      best interest. You will no longer be able to take part if intolerable side effects occur or
      if you are unable to follow study directions.

      Your active participation on the study will be over after the follow-up visits.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 6, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Local Orbital Control</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Local orbital control monitored using the method of Thall et al. Monitoring rules for time to local orbital control applied continuously with the probability criterion recomputed based on the most recent data available at that time.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Orbital Radiation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants receive radiation to entire involved orbit for a total dose of 4 Gy in 2 fractions over two consecutive days with external beam radiotherapy. If there is stable disease or progressive disease, an additional 20 Gy administered to involved site. If there are two consecutive evaluations with no change in disease burden then an additional 20 Gy administered. At one year if there is persistent disease, an additional 20 Gy administered to involved site.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiation Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants receive radiation to entire involved orbit for a total dose of 4 Gy in 2 fractions over two consecutive days with external beam radiotherapy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Orbital Radiation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>XRT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients 18 years or older with stage I-IV indolent B cell lymphoma, including MALT
             and follicular grade I/II. Patients with mantle cell lymphoma will also be included in
             this study, as mantle cell lymphoma is also radiosensitive, despite it not being an
             indolent B cell lymphoma. Patients with chronic lymphocytic leukemia/small lymphocytic
             lymphoma (CLL/SLL) are ineligible

          2. Patients must have measurable disease within the orbit, either clinically and/or
             radiographically after biopsy confirmation of B cell lymphoma

          3. Bilateral ocular adnexal involvement is permitted, if biopsy confirms unilateral
             disease and there is high clinical suspicion for bilateral disease, biopsy of the
             contralateral ocular adnexa can be waived.

          4. Female patients of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test
             (beta-hCG) within 2 weeks of protocol entry.

          5. Planned systemic therapy after orbital radiation therapy is permitted however the
             timing of systemic therapy will be recorded and patients will be stratified according
             to receipt of adjuvant systemic therapy.

          6. Male patients must agree to use a barrier method of contraception or agree to abstain
             from heterosexual activity for the duration of the study

          7. Female patients must be willing to use two adequate barrier methods of contraception
             to prevent pregnancy or agree to abstain from heterosexual activity throughout the
             study or be post-menopausal (free from menses &gt; two years or surgically sterilized).

          8. Patients must have the ability to give informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients treated with chemotherapy for lymphoma within 4 weeks of protocol enrollment
             (including Rituxan).

          2. Patients with aggressive B cell lymphoma histology, including diffuse large B cell
             lymphoma (DLBCL) and grade 3 follicular lymphoma.

          3. Patients with chronic lymphocytic leukemia/small lymphocytic lymphoma (CLL/SLL)

          4. Patients with a history of prior radiation to the orbit if re-treatment would exceed
             known orbital tolerance

          5. Patients with pre-existing retinopathy

          6. Patients who are pregnant

          7. Patients with active lupus or scleroderma are ineligible
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Chelsea C. Pinnix, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chelsea C. Pinnix, MD, PHD</last_name>
    <phone>713-563-2300</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 8, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 10, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 13, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 15, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Low grade B lymphocyte (B cell) lymphoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Mantle cell lymphoma involving the ocular adnexa</keyword>
  <keyword>Limited and advanced stage</keyword>
  <keyword>Ocular adnexa</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiation therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>XRT</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, B-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

