<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00175214</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AHFMR#2000000389</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00175214</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Controlled Trial to Increase Detection and Treatment of Osteoporosis in Older Patients With a Wrist Fracture</brief_title>
  <official_title>Controlled Trial to Increase Detection and Treatment of Osteoporosis in Older Patients With a Wrist Fracture</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Alberta</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Alberta Heritage Foundation for Medical Research</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Alberta</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this proposed research is to improve the quality of care for
      patients who present to the Emergency Department with osteoporosis and a fracture of the
      wrist, by increasing the use of proven efficacious osteoporosis treatment. This is the
      primary study outcome, and it is defined as starting any one of hormone therapy, a
      bisphosphonate, raloxifene, or calcitonin within 6 months of a fracture of the wrist.

      The study hypothesis is that a quality improvement intervention (with multiple components
      that include a notification system for primary care physicians, patient-specific reminders,
      locally generated treatment guidelines endorsed by opinion leaders, and patient education and
      counseling) will lead to increased use of proven efficacious osteoporosis treatments in
      patients eligible for secondary prevention. This hypothesis will be tested by comparing the
      intervention with usual care controls, in a prospective nonrandomized controlled trial.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      BACKGROUND: Osteoporosis is a progressive condition that causes a loss of bone mass, skeletal
      fragility, and fractures. Fractures result in pain, disability, deformity, and death.
      Osteoporosis is a major population health problem affecting 1.4 million Canadians, 25% of
      women and 12% of men over the age of 50 years. Current guidelines recommend aggressive
      secondary prevention in patients with osteoporosis who have suffered a fracture, because
      these patients have as high as a 20% risk of fracture in the following year, and because
      there are now proven efficacious treatments that can reduce this risk by 40-60%.
      Nevertheless, recent studies have shown that these patients are under-recognized and
      under-treated, demonstrating a care gap between evidence-based best practice and usual care.
      All patients with osteoporotic fractures (i.e., of the hip, vertebrae, or wrist) benefit from
      treatment. However, patients who present with a wrist fracture may be best suited to an
      intervention to improve secondary prevention practices, because wrist fractures are “sentinel
      events” in the natural history of osteoporosis: they are common, easily diagnosed, always
      present to medical attention, and occur years before the more devastating and costly
      fractures of the hip and vertebrae.

      OBJECTIVES: The primary objective of this study is to improve the quality of care for
      patients who present to the ED with osteoporosis and a fracture of the wrist, by increasing
      the use of proven efficacious osteoporosis treatment. This is the primary study outcome, and
      it is defined as starting any one of hormone replacement therapy, a bisphosphonate,
      raloxifene, or calcitonin within 6 months of a fracture of the wrist.

      HYPOTHESIS: A quality improvement intervention directed at patients and their primary care
      physicians will increase the use of proven efficacious osteoporosis treatment. The
      intervention itself has multiple components that include: a notification system and
      patient-specific reminders for primary care physicians, locally developed treatment
      guidelines endorsed by opinion leaders, and patient education and counseling. The study
      hypothesis will be tested by comparing the intervention to usual care controls, in a
      prospective nonrandomized controlled trial.

      SPECIFIC AIMS: To determine whether the proposed intervention can-

        -  1. Increase the use of proven efficacious osteoporosis treatment in patients with a
           fracture of the wrist,

        -  2. Increase appropriate use of bone mineral density testing,

        -  3. Increase patients’ knowledge of osteoporosis and satisfaction.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2001</start_date>
  <completion_date>January 2005</completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Increased use of proven efficacious osteoporosis treatment within six months of study enrollment, defined as: hormone therapy, a bisphosphonate, raloxifene, or calcitonin.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>1. BMD testing</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>2. Osteoporosis diagnosis</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>3. Osteoporosis related knowledge</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>4. Satisfaction</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>5. Generic, Disease Specific, and Function-related QOL</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>6. Falls, falls-related injuries, and fall interventions</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>7. Persistence of effects and generalizability of effects</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>8. 1, 2, 3 year outcomes</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment>160</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteoporosis</condition>
  <condition>Wrist Fractures</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multifaceted intervention (patient education, physician guidelines, reminders)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  age &gt; 50 years

          -  any closed distal forearm fracture

          -  discharged home

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  unwilling or unable to provide consent

          -  admitted to hospital

          -  long term care resident

          -  residence outside Edmonton, Alberta

          -  unable to read and converse in English

          -  currently taking prescription osteoporosis treatment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sumit R Majumdar, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Alberta Hospitals</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edmonton</city>
        <state>Alberta</state>
        <zip>T6G 2B7</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Majumdar SR, Rowe BH, Folk D, Johnson JA, Holroyd BH, Morrish DW, Maksymowych WP, Steiner IP, Harley CH, Wirzba BJ, Hanley DA, Blitz S, Russell AS. A controlled trial to increase detection and treatment of osteoporosis in older patients with a wrist fracture. Ann Intern Med. 2004 Sep 7;141(5):366-73.</citation>
    <PMID>15353428</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>September 2005</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 10, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 10, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 15, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 10, 2005</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 10, 2005</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 15, 2005</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>osteoporosis</keyword>
  <keyword>wrist fractures</keyword>
  <keyword>quality improvement</keyword>
  <keyword>knowledge translation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fractures, Bone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Osteoporosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

