<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00170482</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>05-0028</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00170482</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Elderly Influenza Vaccine Immunogenicity Substudy</brief_title>
  <official_title>In Depth Immunologic Studies in Elderly Subjects Receiving Either Standard-Dose Fluzone (15mcg HA/Virus Strain) or High-Dose (60 Mcg HA/Virus Strain) Trivalent Inactivated Influenza Virus Vaccine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The body's immune system (fights infection) is known to decline during the aging process,
      resulting in an increased risk of catching infections. Vaccinations also are not as effective
      in protecting older people against infection as they are in younger people. The purpose of
      this study is to better understand how and why vaccines are not as effective in older people.
      The researchers believe that the immune response in older people who get a higher dose
      vaccine will be similar to the immune response in young adults who get the standard (lower)
      dose vaccine. This study is a substudy to a main study, evaluating flu vaccines in people 65
      years and older. Volunteers who are in the main study will be asked if they will participate
      in the substudy. The substudy requires them to give 2 additional blood samples for an
      in-depth look at their immune response to the flu vaccine given in the main study. Substudy
      volunteers will have up to 3 clinic visits and participate up to 28 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There is a need to increase protection against influenza conveyed to elderly persons by
      inactivated influenza virus vaccines. Serum antibody titer is the primary surrogate marker
      for immunity to influenza after vaccination; and increasing the antigen dose has been shown
      to increase the serum antibody response in vaccinated persons, including the elderly. However
      it is not known how the remainder of the immune system responds to the higher dose of
      influenza antigen. This study is linked to DMID protocols 04-100 and 05-0055. This study will
      be conducted as a substudy of DMID 04-100 at the University of Maryland, Baltimore. Subjects
      ages 65 years and older, who meet the entry criteria for the primary study, will be
      approached for participation in an immunology substudy of volunteers who receive a single
      intramuscular injection of either the high-dose or standard-dose of licensed 2004-2005
      trivalent inactivated influenza vaccine. A minimum of 30 elderly subjects (with the
      possibility of up to 60 elderly subjects) will be enrolled for the substudy. The substudy
      will require an extra 100 ml (total blood draw of 120 ml) of blood drawn from the same 20 ml
      venipuncture obtained for hemagglutination inhibition assay (HAI) titers (as per the primary
      study) on days 0 and 28. To minimize adverse side effects, the additional 100 ml of blood
      required for the substudy will be obtained from the same venipuncture site from which the 20
      ml blood will be obtained for HAI titers (i.e., if blood collection stops after the 20 ml for
      HAI are drawn, the researchers will not attempt to obtain additional blood from a separate
      venipuncture site). Subjects' blood will be evaluated for key humoral and cell-mediated
      immunity (CMI) responses to better understand the mechanisms underlying the predicted
      suboptimal immune responses to one or more of the three influenza vaccine antigens observed
      in the elderly. With regard to specific study objectives, blood samples will be submitted for
      the following analysis: (1) measurement of serum anti-HA (hemagglutinin) IgG and IgA
      antibodies by ELISA; (2) IgG antibody subclasses; (3) IgG and IgA avidity, (4) virus
      neutralizing functional assay; and (5) HAI antibody titer. Peripheral blood mononuclear cells
      (PBMC) isolated from these subjects will be evaluated for the following: (1) &quot;central&quot; and
      &quot;effector&quot; memory T cell responses, including their proliferative responses and cytokine
      production profiles by flow cytometry; (2) IFN-gamma production by ELISPOT, following
      specific antigenic stimulation; (3) measurement ex vivo of the frequency of circulating
      influenza-specific T cells by using commercially available MHC/tetramers and/or MHC/pentamers
      and flow cytometry; and (4) role of regulatory T cells in the modulation of influenza
      responses in the elderly. Studies for measurement ex vivo of the frequency of circulating
      influenza-specific T cells (by using commercially available MHC/tetramers and/or
      MHC/pentamers and flow cytometry) will concentrate on IFN-gamma, a cytokine shown by many
      investigators to play a central role in the host immune response to influenza antigens. If
      promising results are observed, other cytokines (e.g., IL-12, TNF-alpha) might also be
      evaluated in future investigations if sufficient cells and resources are available. Major
      factors involved in the decision to concentrate these studies on IFN-gamma include the need
      to remain focus in a defined set of scientific questions and the fact that we will only have
      access to a limited number of peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) that might preclude
      the study of additional cytokines.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2005</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2005</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Influenza</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Volunteers who participate in Division of Microbiology and Infectious Diseases (DMID)
             study 04-100, &quot;Comparisons of the Reactogenicity and Immunogenicity in Ambulatory
             Elderly Subjects of a Standard-Dose Fluzone® (15 µg HA/Virus Strain) and a High-Dose
             (60 µg HA/Virus Strain) of a Trivalent Inactivated Influenza Virus Vaccine&quot;

          2. Ambulatory medically stable persons at least 65 years of age on the date of
             vaccination

        2. Provides written informed consent and will be available for all study visits 4. Able to
        understand and comply with planned study procedures

        Subjects will be considered ambulatory if they are not institutionalized, bedridden, or
        homebound. Medically stable subjects may have underlying illnesses such as hypertension,
        diabetes, ischemic heart disease, or hypothyroidism, but their symptoms/signs must be
        controlled with medical therapy. Subjects with acute febrile illnesses [oral temperature
        equal to or exceeding 99.5 degrees F (37.5 degrees C)] will be deferred until 3 days after
        illness resolution.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Known allergy to eggs or other components of the vaccine (eg, thimerosal)

          2. History of a severe reaction following influenza vaccination, systemic
             hypersensitivity to any of the vaccine components, or history of a life-threatening
             reaction to a vaccine containing the same substances

          3. History of Guillain-Barré Syndrome

          4. Immunosuppression as a result of underlying illness or treatment

          5. Use of oral steroids, parenteral steroids, or high-dose inhaled steroids (&gt; 800 µg per
             day of beclomethasone dipropionate or equivalent) within 1 month prior to vaccination

          6. Use of other immunosuppressive or cytotoxic drugs or radiation therapy within the six
             months prior to vaccination

          7. Active neoplastic disease or history of any hematologic malignancy in the past 5 years
             (except localized skin or prostate cancer that is stable in the absence of therapy)

          8. Acute or chronic condition that (in the opinion of the Investigator) would render
             vaccination unsafe or would interfere with the evaluation of responses including, but
             not limited to the following: known chronic liver disease, significant renal disease,
             oxygen-dependent chronic lung disease, New York Heart Association Functional Class III
             or IV, unstable or progressive neurologic disorder, insulin-treated diabetes mellitus

          9. Use of experimental vaccines or medications within the month prior to study entry, or
             expected use of experimental vaccines or medications during the entire study period,
             including the 6-month follow-up phone call, after inoculation with study vaccine

         10. Use of experimental devices or participation in a medical procedure trial within the
             month prior to study entry, or expected use of experimental devices or participation
             in a medical procedure trial during the entire study period, including the 6-month
             follow-up phone call, after inoculation with study vaccine

         11. Receipt of immunoglobulin or other blood product within 3 months prior to enrollment

         12. Receipt of other licensed vaccines within the preceding 4 weeks or expected to receive
             a licensed vaccine within 1 month (prior to visit 2) following trial vaccination

         13. Subject is enrolled in a conflicting clinical trial

         14. Thrombocytopenia or bleeding disorder or therapy contraindicating intramuscular (IM)
             vaccination.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland Baltimore</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 9, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 9, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 15, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 11, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 11, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 12, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Robert Johnson</name_title>
    <organization>HHS/NIAID/DMID</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>influenza vaccine, Fluzone, inactivated, trivalent</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Influenza, Human</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

