<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00178204</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MRSG-04-233-01-CPPB</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00178204</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sleep Architecture and Chemotherapy-Related Fatigue</brief_title>
  <official_title>Sleep Architecture and Chemotherapy-Related Fatigue</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Rochester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>American Cancer Society, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Rochester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to identify specific chemotherapy-related changes in sleep
      stages/architecture that may relate to an increase in fatigue in individuals with cancer.

      The researchers hypothesize that the fatigue experienced by cancer patients receiving
      chemotherapy is in part due to changes in restorative sleeping during the non-rapid eye
      movement cycles of sleep (i.e., delta activity).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Studies have shown a strong positive correlation between self-reported changes in sleep and
      cancer patients' fatigue, and also between an objective measure of sleep continuity, [i.e.,
      actigraphy and polysomnography (PSG)] and self-reported fatigue. Chemotherapy disrupts normal
      sleep patterns, and fatigue, in the later stages of chemotherapy, may occur as a result of
      disturbed nocturnal sleep continuity. However, the causes of chemotherapy-related fatigue
      remain unknown, and whether or not abnormal sleep architecture contributes to this
      debilitating effect has yet to be explored. We believe that fatigue experienced by many
      cancer patients receiving chemotherapy is due, at least in part, to changes in delta activity
      [i.e., restorative sleep during the non-rapid eye movement (NREM) cycles of sleep]. A finding
      that slow wave sleep abnormalities play a significant role in fatigue would prompt further
      confirmatory studies and support controlled intervention studies.

      Comparisons: In a clinical trial of individuals with cancer prior to, during, and after
      completion of chemotherapy, we will identify and compare specific chemotherapy-related
      changes in sleep stages/architecture that may relate to an increase in fatigue. These changes
      will be measured by actigraphy, PSG, and patient self-reporting techniques (e.g., sleep
      diaries, questionnaires).

      The primary objective is to:

        -  examine the role of delta sleep in the development of chemotherapy-induced fatigue in
           cancer patients

      Secondary objectives are to:

        -  characterize the involvement of other elements of sleep architecture [e.g., rapid eye
           movement (REM) sleep] and changes in sleep continuity relating to the development of
           chemotherapy-induced fatigue in cancer patients

        -  examine the role of sleep architecture in the persistence of chemotherapy-induced
           fatigue

        -  examine (in post hoc analyses) the relationship of various physical symptoms and patient
           variables that may be related to fatigue (e.g., pain, hot flashes, anxiety, hemoglobin,
           menopausal status, sleep continuity, and QOL) and to each other, both during and
           following chemotherapy.

      Answers to these questions will provide information that will be helpful in developing
      potential targets for interventions to reduce fatigue.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Polysomnography (PSG)</measure>
    <time_frame>Two consecutive nights prior to first chemotherapy, approximately three weeks following the patient's last chemotherapy, and three months following the last treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>Polysomnography provides direct and quantitative measures of cortical activity during sleep (in the form of brain waves). The sleep continuity data derived from this technique include sleep latency (time taken to fall asleep), wake after sleep onset time, total sleep time, and sleep efficiency (SE). The sleep architecture information derived from this technique consists of the assessment of sleep in terms of its constituent component stages (i.e., percent Stage-1, Stage-2, SWS, and REM sleep).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brief Fatigue Inventory (BFI)</measure>
    <time_frame>On the first night of each of the three polysomnography assessments</time_frame>
    <description>The Brief Fatigue Inventory is a 9-item, patient-report instrument with established reliability and validity that allows for the rapid assessment of fatigue level in cancer patients. Possible scores on this scale range from 0 - 10 with higher numbers indicating greater fatigue.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">26</enrollment>
  <condition>Fatigue</condition>
  <condition>Sleep</condition>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        patients beginning chemotherapy
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Have a diagnosis of cancer and not have had chemotherapy during the prior three years

          -  Be scheduled for chemotherapy that is expected to last at least 9 weeks but not more
             than 33 weeks without concurrent interferon treatment. Radiation therapy is allowed
             provided it is concluded within the 33 week time period

          -  Have a stable sleep/wake schedule (no shift work) with a preferred sleep phase between
             10:00 PM and 9:00 AM

          -  Be 18 years of age or older

          -  Give informed consent

          -  If on beta blockers or being treated for depression or a thyroid disorder, the
             medication has been stable for 3 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  On a short term basis (less than 3 months), taking any prescription medication for the
             control of anxiety, sleep, depression, or fatigue OR taking any over-the-counter
             medications known to affect sleep

          -  Diagnosed with post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) or have a substance abuse
             disorder or psychotic disorder (currently or by history)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joesph A Roscoe, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Rochester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester James P. Wilmot Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 12, 2005</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 12, 2005</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 15, 2005</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 3, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 3, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 5, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Rochester</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Joseph Roscoe</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Research Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>delta sleep</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer-related fatigue</keyword>
  <keyword>Sleep Disturbance</keyword>
  <keyword>chemotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fatigue</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

