<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02787356</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RFA-FD-16-010-SRI-TKL-002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02787356</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Standard TDS Irritation Study: Trained Skin Grader vs. Digital Imaging</brief_title>
  <acronym>TDS_TSG_DI</acronym>
  <official_title>Standard TDS Irritation Study: Trained Skin Grader vs. Digital Imaging</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>SRI International</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>TKL Research, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>SRI International</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to (1) collect trained observer scores and digital images of
      skin irritated by generic and RLD Lidocaine 5% delivered via TDS, and (2) assess performance
      of an automated system for predicting scores directly from the digital images
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Subjects will be screened prior to dosing to ensure subjects meet all inclusion exclusion
      criteria. The test materials will be tested simultaneously. Skin sites on the paraspinal
      region will be utilized for application. The test sites will be randomized among the
      individual subjects according to their assigned identification number. All patches will be
      applied and removed by the laboratory staff.

      Due to safety concerns, it is not recommended to simultaneously apply two whole, active,
      Lidocaine Patch 5% patches on the same subject during the 21-day period. The optimum design
      of this study will depend on the design of the test product patch. Since the RLD has a matrix
      design that can be safely cut, one-fourth of the patch can be used for these studies. If the
      test product patch also has a design that can be cut to a smaller size, it should also be cut
      in one-fourth and one-fourth of the test product patch applied simultaneously with one-fourth
      of a RLD patch (to separate skin sites).

      Each test article will be applied to sites on the skin for a contact period of approximately
      24 hours (+/-1 hr.), with the exception of the weekend (72 hours, +/- 1 hr.). There will be
      no visits during the weekend.

      Evaluations will be made after removal of every patch by a single trained grader along with a
      single digital imaging instrument. Re-applications will be made to the same test sites unless
      reactions become so strong (combination of a number and letter grade of 3) as to make this
      unadvisable, at which point patch application will be discontinued for that test article.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Project was not funded by FDA
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">October 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessing Accuracy of Berger &amp; Bowman Dermal Response Scores Predicted from Images of Skin</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The accuracy of the image analysis system will be assessed on a test set of skin images by analyzing the results of an 8x8 confusion matrix, where the ground truth labels are the scores on the 8-point Berger &amp; Bowman Dermal Response Scale assigned by trained observers, and the classification results are the predicted Berger &amp; Bowman Dermal Response scores from the image analysis system. Accuracy is defined as the number of predicted scores within 1 grade of the ground truth scores, divided by the total number of samples in the test set.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessing Non-Inferiority of Generic Lidocaine 5% TDS from Images of Skin</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>As a baseline, the non-inferiority of generic vs RLD Lidocaine will first be determined using trained observer scores in the image test set using the method described in &quot;Draft Guidance on Lidocaine&quot; (Rev. Jan 2016), namely that the upper bound of the one-sided 95% confidence interval of the mean test product score minus 1.25 times the mean RLD score must be less than or equal to 0. Then, this same method will be used on the predicted scores in the image test set, and the determination will be compared to the baseline.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Skin Manifestations</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TDS Lidocaine 5%; generic</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TDS Lidocaine 5%; generic with trained skin graders and images of skin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TDS Lidocaine 5%; RLD</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>TDS Lidocaine 5%; RLD with trained skin graders and images of skin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TDS Lidocaine 5%; generic</intervention_name>
    <description>TDS Lidocaine 5%; generic</description>
    <arm_group_label>TDS Lidocaine 5%; generic</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TDS Lidocaine 5%; RLD</intervention_name>
    <description>TDS Lidocaine 5%; RLD</description>
    <arm_group_label>TDS Lidocaine 5%; RLD</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males and Females, age [18-65 years old or 18 years or older]

          -  Signed informed consent

          -  Good general health

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject is pregnant or lactating.

          -  Medical history of condition that would significantly influence the immune response
             (e.g., primary or acquired immunodeficiencies, such as HIV positive or AIDS, allergic
             diseases, such as anaphylaxis, asthma or generalized drug reaction, neoplasms, such as
             lymphoma or leukemia, rheumatoid arthritis, or systemic lupus erythematosus).

          -  Medical history of significant dermatologic diseases or conditions, such as atopy,
             psoriasis, vitiligo or conditions known to alter skin appearance or physiologic
             response (e.g. diabetes, porphyria).

          -  History of significant dermatologic cancers (e.g. melanoma, squamous cell carcinoma),
             except basal cell carcinomas that were superficial and did not involve the
             investigative site.

          -  Medical history of hepatic disease

          -  Within three weeks prior to dosing, use of medications or treatments that would
             significantly influence or exaggerate responses to the test product or that would
             alter inflammatory or immune response to the product (e.g. cyclosporine, tacrolimus,
             systemic or topical corticosteroids, cytotoxic drugs, immune globulin,

          -  Bacillus Calmette-Guerin, monoclonal antibodies, radiation therapy).

          -  Within 72 hours prior to dosing, use of antihistamines or use of topical drugs at
             patch site.

          -  Subject has an obvious difference in skin color between arms or the presence of a skin
             condition, excessive hair at the application sites, scar tissue, tattoo, or coloration
             that would interfere with placement of test articles, skin assessment, or reactions to
             drug.

          -  Presence of open sores at the application site.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jonathan Dosik, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>TKL Research, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>http://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/rfa-files/RFA-FD-16-010.html</url>
    <description>Use of Imaging and Digital Image Analysis Software/s to Evaluate Transdermal Irritation and Non - inferiority of Generic Transdermal Products (U01)</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 23, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 1, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 6, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 6, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 9, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Skin Diseases, Erythema</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Skin Manifestations</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lidocaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

