<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02789228</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>7497</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02789228</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Research Study Utilizing Expanded Multi-antigen Specific Lymphocytes for the Treatment of Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <acronym>REST</acronym>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Patients with high-risk solid tumors, those that are refractory to standard up front therapy
      or relapse after completion of therapy, have a very poor prognosis despite attempts to induce
      remission with salvage regimen. Novel therapies are critical for this patient population with
      high-risk cancer.

      The ability of tumors to be recognized and lysed by the immune system offers a unique
      opportunity to aid in tumor eradication by expanding and activating these anti-tumor cells.
      Through this ability to harness sophisticated and specific immunotherapy, residual or
      relapsed disease that is resistant to chemotherapy and/or radiotherapy could be eradicated.
      Prior studies have suggested both safety of expanded specific T cells and efficacy in the
      setting of melanoma, lymphoma or viral eradication. While this therapy has previously been
      limited by the versatility of the tumor to down-regulate antigens and evade a single
      immune-target, the use of multi-antigen specific T cells may permit better and more durable
      anti-tumor immunity. Thus, the investigators propose to infuse these specific multi-antigen
      anti-tumor T lymphocytes into patients with high risk solid tumors. This trial will be
      conducted to demonstrate safety of these cells and generate efficacy and biology data that
      may be important for future studies that may enhance tumor immunotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This phase I dose-escalation trial is designed to evaluate the safety of administering
      rapidly generated TAA CTL to patients who have undergone allogeneic HSCT or conventional
      therapy for a high-risk solid tumor due to the presence of refractory, relapsed and/or
      residual detectable disease.

      Pediatric and adult patients who have high-risk solid tumors with known positivity for one or
      more Tumor Antigen Associated (TAA) (WT1, PRAME and/or survivin) will be eligible. Patients
      will be enrolled in one of two groups: group A includes patients who have undergone an
      allogeneic HSCT as part of their prior therapy and group B includes patients who have
      undergone standard therapy which does not include an allogeneic HSCT. TAA CTL may be
      generated from donor lymphocytes (group A) obtained from either patient peripheral blood
      mononuclear cells (PBMC) or donor PBMC or host lymphocytes (group B).

      Group A patients (post allogeneic HSCT): TAA-CTL will be infused any time after neutrophil
      engraftment post-HSCT or day 30, whichever comes first.

      Group B patients (no prior allogeneic HSCT): TAA-CTL will be infused any time &gt;1 week after
      completing most recent course of conventional (non-investigational) therapy for their
      disease.

      This protocol is designed as a phase I dose-escalation study. Three different TAA CTL dose
      levels will be evaluated in each treatment group (A and B) (see below) with 2 to 4 patients
      enrolled at each dose level.

      Dose Level One: 1 x 107 cells/m2 Dose Level Two: 2 x 107 cells/m2 Dose Level Three: 4 x 107
      cells/m2

      Patients will receive cells due to the presence of refractory disease and/or high risk for
      disease relapse and/or residual detectable disease following conventional therapy at the time
      of the infusion. Ideally, patients should not receive other systemic antineoplastic agents
      for at least 6 weeks after infusion of TAA CTL (for purposes of evaluation), although such
      treatment may be added if deemed critical for patient care by the attending physician.

      Each patient will receive at least one TAA CTL infusion and may receive a maximum of 8 doses.
      The first and second doses will be administered 45 days apart then additional doses will be
      spaced every 4 weeks. The expected volume of each infusion is 1 to 10 cc.

      If patients with measurable or evaluable disease have a response of stable disease or better
      by RECIST criteria at the day 28 evaluation after dose 2 or subsequent evaluations they are
      eligible to receive up to 6 additional doses of CTLs at monthly intervals. Each subsequent
      dose will be at the enrollment dose level (i.e. no subsequent dose escalation). Patients will
      not be able to receive additional doses until the initial safety profile is completed at day
      28 following the second infusion.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Product-Emergent Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 45 days of the last dose of TAA-CT</time_frame>
    <description>Primary endpoint of the study is defined grade ≥3 infusion-related adverse event occurring within 45 days of the last TAA-CTL dose, grade ≥4 non-hematologic adverse event occurring within 45 days of the last TAA-CTL dose and that are not due to the patient's underlying malignancy or pre-existing co-morbidities or grade ≥3 acute GVHD occurring within 45 days of the last TAA-CTL dose, or any unexpected toxicity of any grade attributed to the infusion of TAA-CTL occurring within 45 days of the last TAA-CTL dose. Toxicities will be defined by the NCI Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), Version 4.03</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor associated antigen lymphocytes (TAA-CTL) responses</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>o determine the number of patients who respond to tumor associated antigen lymphocytes (TAA-CTL)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Solid Tumors</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tumor associated antigen lymphocytes (TAA-CTL)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tumor associated antigen lymphocytes (TAA-CTL). Three different dosing schedules will be evaluated.
Dose Level One: 1 x 107 cells/m2 Dose Level Two: 2 x 107 cells/m2 Dose Level Three: 4 x 107 cells/m2
Patients will receive cells due to the presence of refractory disease and/or high risk for disease relapse and/or residual detectable disease following conventional therapy at the time of the infusion. Ideally, patients should not receive other systemic antineoplastic agents for at least 6 weeks after infusion of TAA CTL (for purposes of evaluation), although such treatment may be added if deemed critical for patient care by the attending physician.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tumor associated antigen lymphocytes (TAA-CTL)</intervention_name>
    <description>Pediatric and adult patients who have high-risk solid tumors with known positivity for one or more Tumor Antigen Associated (TAA) (WT1, PRAME and/or survivin) will be eligible to receive Tumor Antigen Associated Cytotoxic T Lymphocytes (TAA CTL). The goal of this cell infusion will be to initiate an immune response against solid tumors that includes multiple antigens and may prevent tumor evasion (through decreased expression of a single antigen).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tumor associated antigen lymphocytes (TAA-CTL)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Recipient procurement inclusion criteria

          -  Diagnosis of high-risk solid tumors: Ewing sarcoma, Wilms tumor, neuroblastoma,
             rhabdomyosarcoma, soft tissue sarcomas, osteosarcoma, and adenocarcinoma

          -  Refractory disease, residual detectable disease following conventional therapy or
             relapsed disease

          -  6 months to 60 years of age at enrollment

          -  Karnofsky/Lansky score of ≥ 50%

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt; 500/ µL (may be supported with G-CSF)

          -  Bilirubin &lt;2x upper limit normal

          -  AST &lt; 5 x upper limit normal

          -  Serum creatinine &lt; 2 x upper limit normal

          -  Hgb &gt;8.0 g/dL(level can be achieved with transfusion)

          -  Pulse oximetry of &gt; 90% on room air

          -  Agree to use contraceptive measures during study protocol participation (when age
             appropriate)

          -  LVEF &gt; 50% or LVSF &gt; 27% if history of TBI (may be performed within the last 6 months)

          -  Patient or parent/guardian capable of providing informed consent

        Recipient inclusion criteria for initial CTL administration and for subsequent infusions

          -  Steroids less than 0.5 mg/kg/day prednisone or equivalent

          -  Karnofsky/Lansky score of ≥ 50%

          -  Bilirubin ≤ 2.5 mg/dL

          -  AST/ALT ≤ 5x the upper limit of normal for age

          -  Serum creatinine &lt; 1.0 mg/dL or 2x the upper limit of normal for age (whichever is
             higher)

          -  Pulse oximetry of &gt; 90% on room air

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Recipient Procurement exclusion criteria

          -  Patients with uncontrolled infections

          -  Patients with HIV infection

          -  Current evidence of GVHD &gt; grade 2 or chronic GVHD manifestations: bronchiolitis
             obliterans syndrome, sclerotic GVHD, or serositis.

          -  Pregnancy or lactating females

          -  Prior immunotherapy with an investigational agent

        Recipient exclusion criteria for initial and subsequent CTL infusions

          -  Patients with uncontrolled infections

          -  Patients who received ATG, Campath or other immunosuppressive T cell monoclonal
             antibodies within 28 days of screening for enrollment.

          -  Acute GVHD &gt; grade 2 or chronic GVHD manifestations: bronchiolitis obliterans
             syndrome, sclerotic GVHD, or serositis.

          -  Pregnancy or lactating females
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Holly Meany, MD</last_name>
    <phone>202-476-2800</phone>
    <email>HMeany@childrensnational.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Fahmida Hoq, MD</last_name>
    <phone>202-476-3634</phone>
    <email>fhoq@cnmc.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children's National Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Holly Meany, MD</last_name>
      <phone>202-476-2800</phone>
      <email>HMeany@childrensnational.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 24, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 1, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 2, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 11, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 11, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 16, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Research Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>HMeany</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor and Hematology-Oncology Fellowship Director</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

