<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02780401</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>9626</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2016-00581</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>UW14090</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01-CN-2012-00033</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>UWI4090</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>UWI2014-03-01</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>N01CN00033</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA014520</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02780401</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT03156309</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Vaccine Therapy in Preventing Cancer Recurrence in Patients With Non-Metastatic, Node Positive, HER2 Negative Breast Cancer That is in Remission</brief_title>
  <acronym>WOKVAC</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase I Trial of the Safety and Immunogenicity of a DNA Plasmid Based Vaccine (WOKVAC) Encoding Epitopes Derived From Three Breast Cancer Antigens (IGFBP-2, HER2, and IGF-1R) in Patients With Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin, Madison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Washington</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase I trial studies the side effects and best dose of a vaccine therapy in preventing
      cancer from coming back in patients with non-metastatic, node positive, human epidermal
      growth factor receptor (HER)2 negative breast cancer in which all signs and symptoms have
      disappeared. Vaccines made from deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) may help the body build an
      effective immune response to kill tumor cells. Giving multiple vaccinations may make a
      stronger immune response and prevent or delay the return of cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the safety of 3 escalating doses of a deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) plasmid based
      vaccine encoding three breast cancer antigens (insulin-like growth factor-binding protein
      [IGFBP]-2, HER2, and insulin-like growth factor [IGF]-1 receptor [1R]) in patients with
      breast cancer.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the immunogenicity of pUMVC3-IGFBP2-HER2-IGF1R (WOKVAC) T helper cells (Th)
      polyepitope plasmid based vaccine in patients with breast cancer at 3 escalating doses.

      II. To determine whether a WOKVAC Th polyepitope plasmid based vaccine elicits a persistent
      memory T cell response.

      III. To evaluate whether WOKVAC vaccination modulates T regulatory cells (Treg) and myeloid
      derived suppressor cells (MDSC).

      IV. To evaluate changes in mammographic density using clinically available images prior to
      baseline and post vaccination as an exploratory analysis.

      V. To determine a recommended phase 2 WOKVAC dose for further breast cancer prevention
      studies.

      OUTLINE: This is a dose escalation study of WOKVAC.

      Patients receive WOKVAC with sargramostim intradermally (ID) on day 1. Courses repeat every
      28 days for up to 3 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

      Patients with axillary lymph node dissection (ALND) will have vaccine administered to the
      contralateral arm. Patients with bilateral ALND will have vaccine administered in the thigh.
      As much as possible each vaccine dose will be given within the same draining lymph node site.
      Patients will be monitored for a minimum of 60 minutes post vaccine administration.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 1 month, 6 months and
      annually for up to 5 years thereafter.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2, 2016</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of toxicity assessed by adverse events per Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Type and grade of toxicities noted during the immunization regimen will be summarized. Duration of toxicities will also be summarized using descriptive statistics such as mean and standard deviation. The frequency and severity of adverse events will be summarized with a proportion and a 95% confidence interval.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of IgG antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Immune response will be measured by indirect enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay and serum antibody avidity to determine an avidity index before and after vaccination. Patients will be considered to have developed an antibody response if antigen specific IgG antibodies are both detectable and have moderate to high avidity.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of T helper Th1:Th2 ratio</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>IFN-g (Th1) and IL-10 (Th2) T-cells will be evaluated using enzyme-linked immunosorbent spot assay. Patients will be considered to have developed a Th1 immune response if the ratio of magnitude of Th1 (IFN-gamma)/Th2 (IL-10) is &gt;1.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of the immunogenicity of WOKVAC by generation of IGFBP-2, HER2, and IGF-1R specific type 1 (Th1) T- cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 months</time_frame>
    <description>Immune responses will be measured by IFN-g enzyme-linked immunosorbent spot assay and summarized with mean and standard deviation. Each patient will be given a value at each immune evaluation that is the sum of the median response to HER2, IGFBP-2 or IGF1R, and a composite median would be calculated for each WOKVAC dose level. Patients will be considered to have generated antigen specific (IGFBP-2, HER2, and IGF-1R) Th1 T-cells if they have a ≥1:20,000 composite mean IFN-gamma (IFN-g) precursor frequency by IFN-g enzyme-linked immunosorbent spot assay or greater than 2 fold increase over basel</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Level of antigen specific central and effector memory phenotypes (Persistent memory T cell response)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months after the last vaccine</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by flow cytometry of peripheral blood mononuclear cells using an established T-cell activation panel and summarized with mean and standard deviation or median and range over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modulation of myeloid derived suppressor cell levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months after the last vaccine</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by flow cytometry of peripheral blood mononuclear cells using an established myeloid derived suppressor cell/ regulatory T-cell panel and summarized with mean and standard deviation or median and range over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modulation of T regulatory cell levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months after the last vaccine</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by flow cytometry of peripheral blood mononuclear cells using an established myeloid derived suppressor cell/ regulatory T-cell panel and summarized with mean and standard deviation or median and range over time.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in mammographic density assessed using clinically available images and the automated Cumulus software program</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 6 months after the last vaccine</time_frame>
    <description>Summarized with mean and standard deviation or median and range at pre- and post-vaccination in tabular and graphical formats, along with the change from pre- to post-vaccination in a similar manner by dose level.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>HER2/Neu Negative</condition>
  <condition>No Evidence of Disease</condition>
  <condition>One or More Positive Axillary Nodes</condition>
  <condition>Stage IB Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage II Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIA Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIB Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIA Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIB Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Stage IIIC Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (WOKVAC with sargramostim)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive WOKVAC with sargramostim ID on day 1. Courses repeat every 28 days for up to 3 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
Patients with ALND will have vaccine administered to the contralateral arm. Patients with bilateral ALND will have vaccine administered in the thigh. As much as possible each vaccine dose will be given within the same draining lymph node site. Patients will be monitored for a minimum of 60 minutes post vaccine administration.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (WOKVAC with sargramostim)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>pUMVC3-IGFBP2-HER2-IGF1R Plasmid DNA Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given ID</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (WOKVAC with sargramostim)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pUMVC3-IGFBP2-HER2-IGF1R</other_name>
    <other_name>pUMVC3-IGFBP2-HER2-IGF1R Vaccine</other_name>
    <other_name>WOKVAC</other_name>
    <other_name>WOKVAC Vaccine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sargramostim</intervention_name>
    <description>Given ID</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (WOKVAC with sargramostim)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>23-L-Leucinecolony-Stimulating Factor 2</other_name>
    <other_name>DRG-0012</other_name>
    <other_name>Leukine</other_name>
    <other_name>Prokine</other_name>
    <other_name>rhu GM-CFS</other_name>
    <other_name>Sagramostim</other_name>
    <other_name>Sargramostatin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with non-metastatic, node positive, HER2 negative breast cancer, confirmed by
             pathology report, who are in remission and defined as having no evidence of disease
             (NED); HER2 negative is defined as

               -  0-1+ HER2 expression by immunohistochemistry (IHC) OR

               -  Fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) negative OR

               -  HER2 2+ and FISH negative

          -  Patients must be at least 28 days post cytotoxic chemotherapy, radiotherapy,
             monoclonal antibody and/or other biologic therapy, prior to enrollment; patients on
             bisphosphonates, denosumab, and/or endocrine therapy and may continue throughout
             duration of study

          -  Patients must be at least 28 days post systemic steroids prior to enrollment

          -  Patients must have Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status score
             of =&lt; 2

          -  White blood cell (WBC) &gt;= 3000/mm^3

          -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) &gt;= 10 g/dl

          -  Lymphocyte count &gt;= 800/mm^3

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 75,000/mm^3

          -  Serum creatinine =&lt; 2.0 mg/dl or creatinine clearance &gt; 60 ml/min

          -  Total bilirubin =&lt; 1.5 mg/dl

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST)/Serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase (SGOT) =&lt; 2
             times upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Glycosylated hemoglobin measurement (HbA1c) &lt; 5.7%

          -  Patients must have recovered from major infections and/or surgical procedures, and in
             the opinion of the investigator, not have any significant active concurrent medical
             illnesses precluding protocol treatment

          -  Patients who are having sex that can lead to pregnancy must agree to use adequate
             contraception (hormonal, barrier method of birth control, or abstinence) for the
             duration of study participation; should a woman become pregnant while participating in
             the study, she should inform her study doctor immediately and will not receive any
             more study treatment

          -  Left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) results must be &gt;= lower limit of normal
             (LLN) for institution performing based on results from the multi-gated acquisition
             (MUGA) or echocardiogram (ECHO) done at baseline

          -  Willing to not undergo any elective surgical procedure with general anesthesia or
             conscious sedation through the 1 month post-vaccination visit

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with any of the following cardiac conditions:

               -  Symptomatic restrictive cardiomyopathy

               -  Dilated cardiomyopathy

               -  Unstable angina within 4 months prior to enrollment

               -  New York Heart Association functional class III-IV heart failure on active
                  treatment

               -  Symptomatic pericardial effusion

          -  Patients may not be receiving any other investigational agents

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to WOKVAC

          -  Patients with any contraindication or known hypersensitivity to receiving
             sargramostatin (recombinant human granulocyte macrophage colony stimulating factor
             [rhuGM-CSF]) or other yeast based products

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study; breastfeeding should be discontinued if
             the mother is treated with this vaccine

          -  History of diabetes

          -  Known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection, hepatitis B, or
             hepatitis C

          -  History of autoimmunity that has not been controlled with treatment in the last 12
             months
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kari Wisinski</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Wisconsin, Madison</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fred Hutch/University of Washington Cancer Consortium</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mary L. Disis</last_name>
      <phone>206-616-1823</phone>
      <email>ndisis@u.washington.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mary L. Disis</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Wisconsin Hospital and Clinics</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madison</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>53792</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kari B. Wisinski</last_name>
      <phone>608-262-2876</phone>
      <email>kbwisinski@medicine.wisc.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kari Wisinksi</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 27, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 20, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 23, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 7, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 7, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Stage I</keyword>
  <keyword>Stage II</keyword>
  <keyword>Stage III</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mecasermin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

