<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02788409</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>18673</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02788409</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Incidence of Second Primary Malignancies in Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer: An Observational Retrospective Cohort Study in the US</brief_title>
  <official_title>Incidence of Second Primary Malignancies in Patients With Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer: An Observational Retrospective Cohort Study in the US</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bayer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>RTI Health Solutions</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bayer</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is conducted to estimate population-based incidence rates of second primary
      malignancies among patients with CRPC similar to those treated with Xofigo. These rates will
      provide context for second primary malignancy incidence rates from the REASSURE study.

      Furthermore this study aims to provide further information about the documentation of bone
      metastases in Medicare data and the extent of use of only oral androgen deprivation drugs
      among patients with Medicare Part D coverage, as well as to estimate overall survival of the
      study population.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Xofigo (radium-223 dichloride) is an alpha-emitting pharmaceutical, which was approved for
      the treatment of patients with castration-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC), symptomatic bone
      metastases, and no known visceral metastatic disease. The long-term safety profile of Xofigo
      is evaluated in the prospective REASSURE study, which estimates the incidence rates of second
      primary malignancies in patients with CRPC receiving Xofigo.

      To provide context on that, this retrospective study is conducted to estimate background
      rates of second primary malignancies among patients with CRPC similar to those who are
      treated with Xofigo.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 15, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 15, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 15, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimation of the collective incidence rate of all second primary malignancies (other than nonmelanoma skin cancer) among men with CRPC (Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 year data period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimation of the individual incidence rates of selected second primary malignancies</measure>
    <time_frame>8 year data period</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimation of the proportion of men with CRPC who have a diagnostic code for bone metastases in their Medicare claims before development of CRPC</measure>
    <time_frame>8 year data period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimation of the proportion of men with CRPC who have received bone-directed therapies before development of CRPC</measure>
    <time_frame>8 year data period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimation of the proportion of men with CRPC and Medicare Part D coverage who received only oral androgen deprivation therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>8 year data period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Estimation of overall survival of men with CRPC</measure>
    <time_frame>8 year data period</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">15750</enrollment>
  <condition>Prostatic Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Medicare CRPC</arm_group_label>
    <description>Men in the US older than 65 years old having CRPC</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Not applicable for study</intervention_name>
    <description>Provide external perspective on background second primary cancer incidence rates for REASSURE study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Medicare CRPC</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The cohort will include men who are enrolled in both Medicare Parts A and B for at least 1
        year before the cohort entry date, have a primary site code of prostate cancer in SEER
        data, have surgical castration or androgen deprivation therapy after prostate cancer
        diagnosis, have evidence that prostate cancer was resistant to the castration as indicated
        by starting a second-line systemic therapy, and have an cohort entry date of 01 January
        2006 or later on which they are aged 65 years or older. All eligible subjects will be
        selected; there will be no sampling. (The probability of selecting each eligible patient is
        equal to 1)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Enrolled in both Medicare Parts A and B for at least 1 year before the cohort entry
             date (minimum lookback period for comorbidities and treatments)

          -  Primary site code of prostate cancer (International Classification of Diseases for
             Oncology, Third Edition [ICD-O-3] topography code C61.9) in SEER data

          -  Surgical castration or androgen deprivation therapy after prostate cancer diagnosis;
             androgen deprivation therapy will be indicated by the use of any of the following
             drugs: abarelix, bicalutamide, buserelin, cyproterone, degarelix, diethylstilbestrol,
             estramustine, flutamide, gonadorelin, goserelin, histrelin, leuprolide,
             medroxyprogesterone, megestrol, nafarelin, nilutamide, polyestradiol, triptorelin

          -  Evidence that prostate cancer was resistant to surgical castration or androgen
             deprivation therapy (&quot;castration-resistant prostate cancer&quot;), as indicated by starting
             one of the following second-line systemic therapies (cohort entry date): abiraterone,
             cabazitaxel, docetaxel, enzalutamide, mitoxantrone, or sipuleucel-T

          -  Cohort entry date 01 January 2006 or later

          -  Age 65 years or older in the US on the cohort entry date

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Enrollment in an HMO (Health Maintenance Organization) in the year before the cohort
             entry date

          -  Diagnosis of any cancer other than prostate cancer or nonmelanoma skin cancer on or
             before the cohort entry date

          -  Any diagnostic code for metastases other than bone metastases or lymph node metastases
             on or before the cohort entry date

          -  Any claim for treatment with Xofigo on or before the cohort entry date.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bayer Study Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Bayer</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Waltham</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.fda.gov/cder/drug/DrugSafety/DrugIndex.htm</url>
    <description>Click here and search for drug information provided by the FDA.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.fda.gov/medwatch/safety.htm</url>
    <description>Click here and search for information on any recalls, market or product safety alerts by the FDA which might have occurred with this product.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 27, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 27, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 2, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 16, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 16, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Prostatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms, Second Primary</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

