<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02785432</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>012016-003</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02785432</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Low Level Laser Therapy With Physical Therapy for Chronic Musculoskeletal Pain</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Use of Low Level Laser Therapy With Physical Therapy for Pain and Improved Function in Individuals With Chronic Musculoskeletal Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      1. Examine the use of low level therapeutic laser (LLLT) combined with physical therapy for
           improvements in pain, range of motion, and function in individuals with chronic pain
           from musculoskeletal conditions.

        2. Compare changes in pain, mobility, and ability to return to home/work/recreational
           activities between treatments with standard physical therapy plus LLLT or the standard
           physical therapy program alone.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Potential subjects will be identified by their physician referral to the pain program and
      after initial evaluation by the medical personnel and physical therapy for appropriate
      inclusion in the pain program. For individuals who meet entry parameters for the pain
      program, this project will be discussed by their physical therapist for consideration of
      voluntary participation. If participants are willing to participate, appropriate consent and
      HIPPA permissions will be obtained.

      After consent, the patient will be randomized to one of the two treatment cohorts which
      consists of utilizing either laser or sham laser before and during pain program
      participation. The principle investigator will be blinded to the treatment allocation group.
      The treating clinician will be aware of their treatment allocation assignment for laser
      application. Each treatment cohort will be completed as assigned. Physical therapy treatment
      in addition to the study intervention will be selected by the treating clinician based on
      participant's specific needs as standard of care would dictate. Outcome measures will be
      collected as described below.

      Testing Schedule:

      The assigned study intervention (LLLT or Sham) will be administered on each of the clinical
      visits for phase 1 and 2 of the study. Outcome measures will be completed on the following
      schedule.

      Phase 1: Conducted during the period between acceptance to pain program and start the of the
      pain program (2-4 weeks). Baseline testing pre (T1) will be completed at the time of initial
      evaluation and enrollment to the study.

      A. Follow-up testing post (T2 a, b, c) will be completed weekly during this phase.

      B. Phase 1 final testing (T3) will be on the first clinic visit of the formal pain program.
      The last testing period of phase 1 will also serve as baseline for Phase 2.

      Phase 2: This phase is the 4-week formal pain program (2 visits/week x 4 weeks, total 8
      visits). Baseline testing (T3) will be on the first clinic visit of the formal pain program.

      C. Follow-up testing post (T4-T7) will be completed weekly during phase 2. D. Following
      completion of the pain program. Follow up measurements will be completed 4 weeks post
      discharge (T8).

      Measurements:

      A. Numerical pain rating scale (NPRS): perceived pain on scale of 0-10 (0=no pain, 10=
      extremely severe pain). Pain during the previous 24-hour period (best, worst, current) will
      be measured at T1-T8. The average of 3 scores will be used.

      B. Pain on palpation: Defined as pain to pressure over top 3 areas of primary complaint.
      Palpation pressure recorded as mild, moderate, heavy. If algometry is used, average number of
      3 trials will be used.

      A. Region specific functional outcome measure: A valid and reliable outcome tool of broad
      based physical function based on the body region of interest will be completed. Measured on
      clinic visit T1, T3, T5, T7, and T8.

      B. Questionnaires of fear avoidance (FABQ, or TKS) and sleep quality (Pittsburg sleep index)
      will be taken as measures of quality of life and impact. Measures will be taken at T1, T3,
      and T7, and T8.

      C. Global Rating of Change scale (GRC): 7-point self-assessed clinical progress scale of
      participant's perception of their change in status. Measured at T3, T7, and T8.

      D. Digital thermography photo: Using a digi-therm camera, a thermogram image of the spine and
      upper or lower extremity will be taken for comparison of areas of circulation and
      inflammation. Measured at T1, T3, T5, T7, and T8.

      All procedures, measurements, and interventions (exercises) are considered to be standard of
      care for rehabilitation and the subject's needs. The experimental aspect of the study is
      derived from the randomized selection of which laser intervention will be utilized before and
      during program participation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Enrolling by invitation</last_known_status>
  <start_date>May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Numeric Pain Rating Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tampa Scale of Kinesiophobia</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pittsburgh Sleep Quality Index</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global Rating of Change Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient Specific Functional Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-program low level laser therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Phase 1: Conducted during the period between acceptance to pain program and start the of the pain program (2-4 weeks). Baseline testing pre (T1) will be completed at the time of initial evaluation and enrollment to the study.
A. Follow-up testing post (T2 a, b, c) will be completed weekly during this phase.
B. Phase 1 final testing (T3) will be on the first clinic visit of the formal pain program. The last testing period of phase 1 will also serve as baseline for Phase 2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Program low level laser therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Phase 2: This phase is the 4-week formal pain program (2 visits/week x 4 weeks, total 8 visits). Baseline testing (T3) will be on the first clinic visit of the formal pain program.
C. Follow-up testing post (T4-T7) will be completed weekly during phase 2. D. Following completion of the pain program. Follow up measurements will be completed 4 weeks post discharge (T8).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pre program low level laser</intervention_name>
    <description>Phase 1 is an intervention only phase (LLLT or Sham) with no additional elements of the pain program (PT, counseling). Intervention will be completed at the Outpatient Physical Therapy Clinic in the School of Health Professions. Intervention will take place in the rooms that are appropriately equipped for laser administration. Application of therapeutic laser will be completed by licensed physical therapists who have completed safety training for therapeutic laser application including appropriate use of safety eyewear, room access, laser signage for laser use, and patient monitoring.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Pre-program low level laser therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Program low level laser</intervention_name>
    <description>Laser intervention (LLLT): Clinician will apply 10 minutes of low level laser therapy at a dosage of 15-25 watts for a total of 9,000-15,000 joules based on body surface area treated. Application will be with light to moderate contact pressure based on patient tolerance (should be no additional discomfort from laser). Area for administration will include 6 minutes of application along spine (C2-S1), and 4 minutes of application either to bilateral upper extremity or bilateral lower extremity based on areas of primary pain complaint.
Sham laser intervention (Sham): same protocol in time, application, and areas of treatment as stated above except laser unit will not discharge any photonic energy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Program low level laser therapy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 18-80 years old

          2. Primary referral and acceptance to the UTSW McDermott Multidisciplinary Pain
             Management Program. All diagnoses will be included.

          3. Physical therapy specific inclusion for acceptance to the pain program (and this
             study) include:

               1. Musculoskeletal pain greater than 3 months

               2. Pain upon palpation or with movement of the extremities

               3. Medically cleared for physical therapy (exercise) in terms of cardiac,
                  orthopedic, neurological impairments.

          4. Cognitive, verbal, and physical abilities to self-detect and report pain and changes
             in exercise effort.

          5. Ability to speak English and follow exercise based instructions.

          6. Able to give informed consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Inability to meet inclusion criteria for pain program

          2. Current use of photosensitive medication (has been instructed to minimize sun
             exposure)

          3. Active metastasis

          4. Active infection

          5. Diagnoses that exclude PT including cauda equine syndrome, myopathy, acute fracture
             (8-weeks).

          6. Impaired sensation
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ross Querry, PT, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UT Southwestern</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>McDermott Pain Management Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 20, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 26, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 27, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 26, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 26, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 27, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ross Querry</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Chronic Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Musculoskeletal Pain</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

