<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02786147</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB00084985</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02786147</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Identification and Referral of Women at Risk for Hereditary Breast/Ovarian Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Strategies to Increase the Identification, Genetic Counseling Referral and Genetic Testing for Women at Risk for Hereditary Breast and/or Ovarian Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Emory University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Emory University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to identify the most effective means of follow-up for women who
      screen positive on B-RST (Breast Cancer Genetics Referral Screening Tool) applied in the
      standard clinical setting of mammography, to maximize the number who are referred to and
      receive cancer genetic counseling services. The clinical utility of B-RST 3.0 will also be
      evaluated by determining the number seen who are appropriate for genetic testing, undergo
      genetic testing and are found to carry a hereditary cancer gene mutations with medical
      management implications for the patient and family. The long-term goal is to reduce the
      morbidity and mortality associated with hereditary causes of breast and ovarian cancer among
      patients seen in the Emory/Winship system.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The three aims for this study are: 1. To develop an electronic version of the revised B-RST
      (Breast Cancer Genetics Referral Screening Tool) with a HIPAA compliant database for
      integration within the Winship Cancer Institute at Emory website. 2. To identify the most
      effective means of follow-up to maximize the number of screen positive individuals who are
      referred to and complete cancer genetics counseling. 3. Evaluate the clinical utility of
      B-RST 3.0 by analyzing the number of individuals who were referred to and received genetic
      counseling and were considered appropriate for genetic testing and underwent genetic testing,
      and were identified with a BRCA1/2 mutation, and/or were identified with a mutation in a
      different hereditary cancer gene, or were not appropriate for genetic testing, but were
      appropriate for referral to high-risk follow-up services.

      The B-RST is a simple yet effective screening tool to identify individuals who may be at risk
      for hereditary breast and ovarian cancer. This study will seek to determine the most
      effective method of follow-up to maximize referral to and completion of cancer genetic
      counseling services following a screen positive result on the B-RST tool, and to understand
      clinical outcomes following participation in genetic counseling (i.e., whether patients who
      receive counseling undergo genetic testing, genetic testing results, and recommendations for
      enhanced screening and preventions).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 28, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 28, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of B-RST screen positive participants who are referred to cancer genetic counseling via Self-Referral, Physician Notification by EeMR, Direct Contact by Cancer Genetics Program</measure>
    <time_frame>18 Months from Baseline</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who complete cancer genetic counseling after Self-Referral, Physician Notification by EeMR, Direct Contact by Cancer Genetics Program</measure>
    <time_frame>18 Months from Baseline</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who underwent genetic testing after genetic counseling</measure>
    <time_frame>18 Months from Baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who were identified with a BRCA1/2 mutation</measure>
    <time_frame>18 Months from Baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who were identified with a mutation in a different hereditary cancer gene</measure>
    <time_frame>18 Months from Baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants who were not appropriate for genetic testing, but were appropriate for referral to high-risk follow-up services</measure>
    <time_frame>18 Months from Baseline</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">665</enrollment>
  <condition>Hereditary Breast and Ovarian Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Initiated</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients randomized into this group will receive a standard handout explaining their result, which includes information on how to obtain cancer genetics services through Winship. However, neither the patient nor their ordering clinician will be directly contacted regarding the B-RST result.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physician Notification</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients randomized into this group will also receive the standard handout explaining their result. In addition, their primary care physician or ordering physician will be notified via Emory Electronic Medical Record (EeMR) that the patient screened positive on the B-RST. The note will provide specific instructions on how to refer the patient for cancer genetic counseling services.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Automatic Follow-Up By Genetic Counseling Staff</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients randomized into this group will also receive the standard handout explaining their result. Within 1-2 weeks after their mammogram appointment, patients will receive a phone call from a genetics counseling staff person to explain their screening result and to offer to set up a genetics counseling appointment. This call may take up to 10 - 15 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Breast Cancer Genetics Referral Screening Tool 3.0</intervention_name>
    <description>The B-RST is a simple yet effective validated screening tool to quickly identify individuals who may be at risk for hereditary breast and ovarian cancer and should be referred for cancer genetic counseling to formally evaluate their family history and discuss the benefits and limitations of genetic testing for hereditary breast and ovarian cancer.
Clinic staff will give each patient arriving for a screening mammogram appointment a packet and briefly inform them about the opportunity to participate in a research study and that these materials can help them decide whether or not to participate.
Patients who indicate that they are interested in completing the B-RST screening while in the clinic will be provided with an electronic tablet that has a secure internet browser tab open to the web-based study version of the screening tool (the B-RST 3.0).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Initiated</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Physician Notification</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Automatic Follow-Up By Genetic Counseling Staff</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>B-RST 3.0</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Standard Handout</intervention_name>
    <description>A document explaining the patient's positive test result indicating that they are at increased risk for HBOC (Hereditary Breast or Ovarian Cancer) which includes information on how to obtain cancer genetics services through Winship.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Initiated</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Physician Notification</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Automatic Follow-Up By Genetic Counseling Staff</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physician Notification</intervention_name>
    <description>Primary care physician or ordering physician will be notified vie EeMR that the patient screened positive on the B-RST. The note provides specific instructions on how to refer the patient for cancer genetic counseling services.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Physician Notification</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Automatic Follow-Up by Genetic Counseling Staff</intervention_name>
    <description>Within 1-2 weeks after the mammogram appointment, patients will receive a phone call from a genetics counseling staff person to explain their screening result and to offer to set up a genetics counseling appointment.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Automatic Follow-Up By Genetic Counseling Staff</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Female adult patients of the Winship Cancer Institute or Emory University Hospital Midtown
        that arrive for screening (non-diagnostic) mammogram appointments will be selected will be
        invited for participation.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient at one of the participating clinics (Winship Cancer Institute and Emory
             University Hospital Midtown) who arrive for a screening mammogram appointment.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients receiving a diagnostic mammogram will not be invited to participate in the
             study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Cecelia Bellcross, PhD, MS, CGC</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Emory University Hospital Midtown</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30308</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Winship Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30322</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://brcagenescreen.org</url>
    <description>Online B-RST tool</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 6, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 27, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 30, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Emory University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Cecelia Bellcross</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Breast Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Ovarian Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>B-RST</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hereditary Breast and Ovarian Cancer Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

