<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02785731</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ANG-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02785731</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Multiple Biomarkers to Estimate Risk of Ovarian Cancer in Patients With a Pelvic Mass.</brief_title>
  <official_title>ANG-001 Pelvic Mass Training Study: Evaluation of Multiple Circulating Tumor Cell-derived RNA Markers to Estimate Risk of Ovarian Cancer in Patients Presenting With a Pelvic Mass.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Angle plc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Medical University of Vienna</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Charite University, Berlin, Germany</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Vivantes Netzwerk für Gesundheit GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Angle plc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      ANGLE has developed the Parsortix™ Cell Separation System (Parsortix), an automated system
      capable of harvesting rare circulating cells for analysis from a sample of peripheral blood
      based on cellular size and deformability. In a small pilot study, scientists at the Medical
      University of Vienna demonstrated that measurement of a combination of mRNA markers extracted
      from CTCs captured using the Parsortix system could be used to identify women with ovarian
      cancer. This study is designed to provide specimens for optimization of an assay using
      clinical and biomarker information (i.e. demographics, imaging results and/or serum tumor
      markers) in combination with mRNA extracted from rare cells in the blood of women presenting
      with a pelvic mass for the detection of malignancy.

      Primary Objective: Optimization of an assay for the differentiation of women with benign
      pelvic masses from those with malignant pelvic masses using mRNA markers extracted from CTCs
      isolated from whole blood. Multiple serum tumor markers and mRNA markers will be measured,
      and the results will be compared to the actual clinical diagnosis made for each patient
      through other recognized methods (e.g. histopathology). The blood samples collected in the
      course of this study will be used to finalize the selection of mRNA and/or serum tumor
      markers to be evaluated in future prospective studies.

      Exploratory Objective: Use statistical modeling to determine the need for and/or preliminary
      design of a mathematical algorithm to combine the multiple serum tumor and/or mRNA markers
      for estimation of the risk of ovarian cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is exploratory in nature and is designed to be hypothesis generating to support
      the design of future studies. A total of 200 women diagnosed with a pelvic mass (defined as a
      simple, complex or a solid ovarian cyst / pelvic mass) who are scheduled for a laparotomy or
      laparoscopy for removal of the pelvic mass will be enrolled for evaluation of the primary and
      exploratory endpoints. An initial evaluation of the data will be conducted after
      identification of 15 evaluable subjects with histopathologically confirmed ovarian cancer. It
      is estimated that 50 - 100 subjects will be required to obtain a minimum of 15 evaluable
      subjects with histopathologically confirmed ovarian cancer. The remainder of the women
      enrolled (expected to be ~100 - 150 subjects) will be used to verify the findings from the
      initial evaluation (i.e. correlation of the markers with the absence or presence of
      malignancy) and to refine the assay/algorithm.

      Within 60 days prior to surgery, each subject must have a pelvic imaging study (e.g.
      ultrasound, CT scan, MRI, etc.) conducted and read to visualize the pelvic mass according to
      the current standard of care. Results of the pelvic imaging study(ies) will be recorded.

      Within 60 days prior to, or on the day of the pelvic mass surgery, collect up to 35mL of
      peripheral blood into one 5mL SST tube, which must be drawn first, followed by three separate
      10mL EDTA tubes. Serum from SST tube will be prepared at the local study center and used for
      protein biomarker testing. The EDTA tubes will be shipped to the Medical University of
      Vienna, where the blood will be pooled and equal volumes processed using two different
      separation methods on the Parsortix™ system to capture and harvest rare cells. The harvested
      material from the EDTA tubes will be lysed, and total RNA will be extracted from the cell
      lysate for evaluation of multiple gene targets using quantitative PCR (qPCR).

      Laparotomy or laparoscopy for removal of the pelvic mass will be performed by a qualified
      individual. Tissue samples will be sent to the local pathology department for histological
      examination in accordance with standard institutional practices. Results of the
      histopathological evaluation will be recorded, including the final diagnosis along with
      histological sub-type, and if available, stage and grade of ovarian cancer where disease is
      identified.

      Subjects will be considered negative for ovarian cancer:

        -  if the subject undergoes surgery and no mass is identified, or;

        -  if the histopathological findings are negative for cancer (i.e. benign conditions).

      Subjects will be considered positive for ovarian cancer:

        -  if the histological examination of the tissue taken at the time of surgery confirms the
           presence of ovarian, primary peritoneal and/or fallopian tube cancers.

      For the purposes of enrollment, subjects diagnosed with a malignancy other than an ovarian
      cancer as well as those diagnosed with low malignant potential (LMP) / borderline tumors will
      not be counted as an ovarian cancer. However, two separate analyses of the final study data
      will be conducted: one where subjects diagnosed with other cancers are excluded from the
      analysis of the primary endpoint and the subjects diagnosed with LMP / borderline tumors are
      classified as being negative for malignancy, and a second where subjects diagnosed with other
      cancers and those diagnosed with LMP / borderline tumors are classified as being positive for
      malignancy.

      Demographical and clinical data may be summarized using descriptive statistics. Continuous
      variables may be summarized using the number of observations, mean, standard deviation,
      coefficient of variation, median, and range as appropriate. Categorical values may be
      summarized using the number of observations and percentages as appropriate.

      The association of the markers (i.e. serum protein markers and mRNA markers) with the
      histopathological diagnosis will be assessed using appropriate statistical methods (e.g.,
      logistic regression, analysis of variance [ANOVA], etc.), depending on the endpoints.
      Analyses may be performed within and between various histopathological diagnosis sub-groups.
      Other clinical covariates (such as imaging results and subject demographics) may also be
      included in the modeling.

      An initial evaluation of the correlation of the markers with the histopathological diagnosis
      will be performed after the identification of 15 subjects with histopathologically verified
      ovarian cancer. The final cohort of patients will be used to verify the findings from the
      initial evaluation (i.e. correlation of the markers with the absence or presence of
      malignancy) and to refine the assay/algorithm. Bootstrap analyses may be utilized on the
      entire set of 200 subjects to finalize an assay/algorithm for further study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 14, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 9, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Histopathological diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 30 days after biopsy or surgical procedure to evaluate pelvic mass</time_frame>
    <description>Tissue samples taken from the pelvic mass will be evaluated in the local institutional pathology department according to institutional guidelines. Results from the histopathological evaluation, including the final diagnosis (i.e. benign, malignant, etc.), histopathology description, and, if malignant, clinical or surgical staging and tumor subtype, will be recorded.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence or absence of circulating tumor cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 days prior to surgical procedure to evaluate pelvic mass</time_frame>
    <description>Blood from EDTA tubes will be pooled and processed on the Parsortix System to capture and harvest rare cells. The captured rare cells will be eluted (harvested) and lysed, and total RNA will be extracted from the cell lysate for evaluation of multiple gene targets using quantitative PCR (qPCR).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum protein markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 60 days prior to surgical procedure to evaluate pelvic mass</time_frame>
    <description>Serum from SST tube will be used for protein biomarker testing.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">204</enrollment>
  <condition>Ovarian Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Women with a pelvic mass</arm_group_label>
    <description>Women diagnosed with a pelvic mass (defined as a simple, complex or a solid ovarian cyst / pelvic mass) who are scheduled for a laparotomy or laparoscopy for removal of the pelvic mass. Must have a pelvic imaging study performed within 60 days prior to surgery and a research blood draw within 60 days prior to surgery.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pelvic imaging</intervention_name>
    <description>Within 60 days prior to the pelvic mass evaluation procedure, each subject must have a pelvic imaging study (e.g. ultrasound, CT scan, MRI, etc.) conducted and read to visualize the pelvic mass according to the current standard of care. Results of the pelvic imaging study(ies) will be recorded.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Women with a pelvic mass</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>pelvic ultrasound</other_name>
    <other_name>CT scan</other_name>
    <other_name>MRI scan</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Blood draw</intervention_name>
    <description>Within 60 days prior to, or on the day of the pelvic mass surgery, collect up to 35mL of whole blood into one 5mL SST tube, which must be drawn first, followed by three separate 10mL EDTA tubes.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Women with a pelvic mass</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>phlebotomy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>laparotomy or laparoscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>A laparotomy or laparoscopic procedure will be performed by a qualified individual for excision of the pelvic mass. Representative tissue samples will be taken from the excised pelvic mass and evaluated in pathology departments within each institution according to institutional guidelines. Results from the histopathological evaluation will be recorded, including the final diagnosis along with histological sub-type, and if available, stage and grade of cancer where disease is identified.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Women with a pelvic mass</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      All excess components (i.e. serum, plasma, RNA, DNA, cells, etc.) generated from the
      peripheral blood samples collected for research testing under this study be stored frozen at
      the Medical University of Vienna for up to 10 years for possible use in future research,
      including but not limited to, serum biomarker analyses, genomic evaluations and genetic
      studies pertaining to cancer and other disease processes.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Women diagnosed with a pelvic mass (defined as a simple, complex or a solid ovarian cyst /
        pelvic mass) who are scheduled for a laparotomy or laparoscopy for removal of the pelvic
        mass.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women &gt;18 years of age;

          -  Documented evidence of a pelvic mass by imaging;

          -  Selected to undergo laparotomy or laparoscopy based on the finding of a pelvic mass
             (defined as a simple, complex or a solid ovarian cyst / pelvic mass);

          -  Willing and able to provide written informed consent prior to the blood collection.

          -  Suitable venous access and healthy enough (as determined by the treating physician) to
             provide required whole blood sample.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Known pregnancy;

          -  Subjects receiving cytotoxic chemotherapies;

          -  Previous malignancy within the past 5 years, excluding skin cancers (squamous cell or
             basal cell);

          -  Unwilling or unable to follow protocol requirements or to provide informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shane Booth, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Angle plc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical University of Vienna</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>A-1090</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vivantes Auguste-Viktoria-Klinikum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>12157</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vivantes-Klinikum Neukölln</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>12351</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Charité - Universitätsmedizin Berlin</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>13353</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vivantes Humboldt-Klinikum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Berlin</city>
        <zip>13509</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.angleplc.com</url>
    <description>Study Sponsor Website</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://cccc.charite.de/en/</url>
    <description>Charite Comprehensive Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.meduniwien.ac.at/homepage/1/homepage/</url>
    <description>Medical University of Vienna Website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Obermayr E, Castillo-Tong DC, Pils D, Speiser P, Braicu I, Van Gorp T, Mahner S, Sehouli J, Vergote I, Zeillinger R. Molecular characterization of circulating tumor cells in patients with ovarian cancer improves their prognostic significance -- a study of the OVCAD consortium. Gynecol Oncol. 2013 Jan;128(1):15-21. doi: 10.1016/j.ygyno.2012.09.021. Epub 2012 Sep 24.</citation>
    <PMID>23017820</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Obermayr E, Sanchez-Cabo F, Tea MK, Singer CF, Krainer M, Fischer MB, Sehouli J, Reinthaller A, Horvat R, Heinze G, Tong D, Zeillinger R. Assessment of a six gene panel for the molecular detection of circulating tumor cells in the blood of female cancer patients. BMC Cancer. 2010 Dec 3;10:666. doi: 10.1186/1471-2407-10-666.</citation>
    <PMID>21129172</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 25, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 25, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 30, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pelvic mass</keyword>
  <keyword>ovarian cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>gynecological cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>risk prediction</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ovarian Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

