<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02783625</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-042</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02783625</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Duvelisib in Combination With Either Romidepsin or Bortezomib in Relapsed/Refractory T-cell Lymphomas</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I Trial of Duvelisib in Combination With Either Romidepsin or Bortezomib in Relapsed/Refractory T-cell Lymphomas</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stanford University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test the safety of a study drug called duvelisib.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The phase I portion of the study is designed to determine the MTD of duvelisib with
      romidepsin and duvelisib with bortezomib. All patients must have a relapsed or refractory
      T-cell lymphoma. The design is a standard 3+3 dose escalation of two parallel phase I
      studies. Patients will be enrolled in Arms A (Romidepsin + duvelisib) and B (Bortezomib +
      duvelisib) of the study starting at dose level 1.

      Three to six patients will be initially treated in each dose level until the MTD is
      determined. If dose level 3 is achieved without exceeding one dose limiting toxicity (DLT)
      after 1 cycle that dose level will be deemed the &quot;optimal dose&quot; and the study will proceed to
      the cohort expansion phase. Should patients be found to develop significant toxicity or not
      tolerate therapy at the MTD with repeated cycles of therapy, the &quot;optimal dose&quot; may be
      determined to be at dose levels less than the MTD. Patients with measurable disease treated
      in the phase I at the optimal dose will be counted towards the accrual of the expansion
      cohorts by disease subtype and all efficacy and toxicity endpoints.

      Cohort Expansion Phase: The expansion cohorts will further assess toxicity and safety and
      allow a preliminary assessment of the efficacy of the combination to provide background for a
      potential future subtype specific phase II study. The assessment of efficacy will be
      descriptive.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>maximum tolerated dose (MTD)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>There will be two parallel phase I studies using the 3+3 dose escalation scheme</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>overall response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Response and progression of disease will be evaluated in this study using a modification of the international criteria proposed by the modified Cheson criteria with incorporation of PET/CT.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">88</enrollment>
  <condition>Lymphoma</condition>
  <condition>Relapsed/Refractory T-cell Lymphomas</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Romidepsin + duvelisib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Romidepsin/duvelisib: Cycle 1 and beyond Days 1, 8, 15* Romidepsin IVPB over 4 hours, days 1, 8, 15 duvelisib by mouth twice daily, days 1-28</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bortezomib + duvelisib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Bortezomib/duvelisib: Cycle 1 and beyond Days 1, 4, 8, and 11* Bortezomib subcutaneous injection, days 1, 4, 8, 11** duvelisib by mouth twice daily, days 1-28</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Romidepsin</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Romidepsin + duvelisib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bortezomib</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Bortezomib + duvelisib</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>duvelisib</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Romidepsin + duvelisib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Bortezomib + duvelisib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IPI-145</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Pathologically confirmed T-cell lymphomas at the enrolling institution, including
             stage ≥ Ib CTCL, which has relapsed or progressed after at least one systemic therapy.

          -  Age ≥ 18

          -  Previous systemic anti-cancer therapy must have been discontinued at least 3 weeks
             prior to treatment. For the dose expansion phase, in progressing subjects, a 2 week
             washout may be allowed after discussion with the MSK Principal Investigator.

          -  Previous radiation and/or surgery must have been discontinued or completed at least 2
             weeks prior to treatment in this study and adverse effects must have resolved to Grade
             1 or baseline. Lymph node or other diagnostic biopsies within 2 weeks are not
             considered exclusionary.

             ° CTCL patients who have received localized RT as part of their immediate prior
             therapy may be allowed to enroll with shorter washout period after discussion with the
             MSK Principal Investigator.

          -  ECOG ≤ 2

          -  Meet the following laboratory criteria without use of growth factor support or
             platelet transfusions for 1 week:

             i) Absolute neutrophil count ≥ 1.0 K/mcl, ii) Platelet count ≥ 80 K/μl (in the
             expansion cohorts, if thrombocytopenia is due to bone marrow involvement platelet
             count must be ≥ 50 K/μL), iii) Patients enrolled in the dose escalation phase who are
             not enrolled on the expansion cohorts must have calculated creatinine clearance ≥
             50ml/min by Cockcroft-Gault formula. Patients enrolled in the Dose Expansion phase
             must have calculated creatinine clearance ≥ 40ml/min by Cockcroft-Gault formula.

        iv) Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) or ≤ 3 x ULN if documented hepatic
        involvement with lymphoma, or ≤ 5 x ULN if history of Gilbert's syndrome; AST (SGOT) and
        ALT (SGPT) ≤ 3 x ULN; ≤ 5 ULN if due to lymphoma involvement

          -  Measurable disease for dose expansion and lead in phase only.

        Measurable disease defined by:

          1. Revised International Working Group (Cheson, 2007) Classification for systemic
             lymphoma or

          2. Atypical and or malignant lymphocytes quantifiable by flow cytometry or morphology in
             blood

          3. or bone marrow mSWAT &gt; 0 or Sezary couny &gt;/= 1000 cells/ul

               -  Short course systemic corticosteroids for disease control, improvement of
                  performance status or non-cancer indication (&lt; 7 days) must have been
                  discontinued at least 6 days prior to study treatment. Stable ongoing
                  corticosteroid use (≥ 30 days) up to an equivalent dose of 20 mg of prednisone is
                  permissible.

                  i) Topical steroids that have been used for &gt; 3 weeks may be continued (CTCL
                  only). All other histologies (not CTCL): Topical steroids use is permissible
                  without restriction

               -  Women of reproductive potential† must have a negative serum or urine β human
                  chorionic gonadotropin (βhCG) pregnancy test. All women of reproductive
                  potential, all sexually active male patients, and all partners of patients must
                  agree to use adequate methods of birth control (e.g. latex condoms) throughout
                  the study and for 30 days after the last dose of study drug.

                    -  A female of reproductive potential is a sexually mature female who: has not
                       undergone a hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy; or has not been
                       naturally postmenopausal for at least 24 consecutive months (i.e. has had
                       menses at any time in the preceding 24 consecutive months).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any serious medical condition, laboratory abnormality, or psychiatric illness that
             would prevent the subject from signing the informed consent form.

          -  Pregnant females. (Lactating females must agree not to breast feed while taking the
             study medications).

          -  Prior use of duvelisib if discontinued due to toxicity.

          -  For the romidepsin arm of the study, prior therapy with romidepsin if discontinued due
             to toxicity.

          -  For the bortezomib arm of the study, prior therapy with a proteasome inhibitor if
             discontinued due to toxicity.

          -  For the bortezomib arm of the study, patients with grade ≥2 peripheral neuropathy.

          -  History of chronic liver disease, veno-occlusive disease, or current alcohol abuse.

          -  Administration of a live vaccine within 6 weeks of first dose of study drug.

          -  Prior surgery or gastrointestinal dysfunction that may affect drug absorption (e.g.,
             gastric bypass surgery, gastrectomy)

          -  Known seropositive and requiring anti-viral therapy for human immunodeficiency virus
             (HIV), hepatitis B virus (HBV) or hepatitis C virus (HCV). Subjects with chronic
             hepatitis B or C as defined as test .

          -  Subjects with positive Hep B serology. Subjects with a negative HBsAg and a positive
             HBcAb require an undetectable/negative hepatitis B DNA test (e.g., polymerase chain
             reaction [PCR] test) to be enrolled, and will require prophylactic antiviral treatment
             (e.g., F) initiated prior to the first dose of study drug, an continued until
             approximately 6 to 12 months after completion of study drug(s).

          -  Patients with positive hepatitis C virus Ab

          -  Subjects with active EBV unrelated to underlying lymphoma (positive serology for
             anti-EBV VCA IgM antibody and negative for anti-EBV EBNA IgG antibody, or clinical
             manifestations and positive EBV PCR consistent with active EBV infection.

          -  Subject with active CMV (positive serology for anti-CMV IgM antibody and negative for
             anti-CMV IgG antibody and positive CMV PCR with clinical manifestations consistent
             with active CMV infection) and requiring therapy will be excluded from participation
             in the study. Carriers will be monitored per institutional guidelines.

          -  Receiving systemic therapy for another primary malignancy (other than T-cell lymphoma)

          -  Patients with more than one type of lymphoma may be enrolled after discussion with the
             MSK Principal Investigator.

          -  Adjuvant or maintenance therapy to reduce the risk of recurrence of other malignancy
             (other than T-call lymphoma) is permissible after discussion with the MSK Principal
             Investigator.

          -  Known central nervous system or meningeal involvement (in the absence of symptoms,
             investigation into central nervous system involvement is not required).

          -  The following known cardiac abnormalities:

               1. Congenital long QT syndrome.

               2. QTc/QTf interval ≥ 480 milliseconds; unless secondary to pacemaker or bundle
                  branch block.

               3. Myocardial infarction within 6 months. (Subjects with a history of myocardial
                  infarction within the last 6 to12 months who are asymptomatic and have had a
                  negative cardiac risk assessment (treadmill stress test, nuclear medicine stress
                  test, or stress echocardiogram) since the event may participate.)

               4. Other significant ECG abnormalities including 2nd degree atrio- ventricular (AV)
                  block (AV) block type II, 3rd degree AV block.

               5. Symptomatic coronary artery disease (CAD), e.g., angina Canadian Class II-IV (see
                  Appendix B). In any patient in whom there is doubt, the patient should have a
                  stress imaging study and, if abnormal, angiography to define whether or not CAD
                  is present.

                  II-IV (see Appendix B). In any patient in whom there is doubt, the patient should
                  have a stress imaging study and, if abnormal, angiography to define whether or
                  not CAD is present.

               6. An ECG recorded at screening showing evidence of cardiac ischemia (ST depression
                  of ≥2 mm, measured from isoelectric line to the ST segment). If in any doubt, the
                  patient should have a stress imaging study and, if abnormal, angiography to
                  define whether or not CAD is present.

               7. Congestive heart failure (CHF) that meets New York Heart Association (NYHA) Class
                  II to IV definitions (see Appendix C) and/or ejection fraction &lt;45% by MUGA,
                  echocardiogram, or cardiac MRI.

               8. A known history of sustained ventricular tachycardia (VT), ventricular
                  fibrillation (VF), Torsade de Pointes, or cardiac arrest unless currently
                  addressed with an automatic implantable cardioverter defibrillator (AICD).

               9. Hypertrophic cardiomegaly or restrictive cardiomyopathy from prior treatment or
                  other causes.

              10. Uncontrolled hypertension, i.e., blood pressure (BP) of ≥170/95; patients who
                  have a history of hypertension controlled by medication must be on a stable dose
                  (for at least one month prior to study registration) and meet all other inclusion
                  criteria.

              11. Any cardiac arrhythmia requiring an anti-arrhythmic medication (excluding stable
                  doses of beta-blockers)

              12. For patients enrolling on the Romidepsin arm; taking drugs associated with
                  significant QTc/QTf prolongation, unless able to be switched to non-QTc/QTf
                  prolonging medication or on a stable dose without significant QT prolongation
                  (&gt;470 msec). Caution should be used when administering study drugs to patients
                  taking medications significantly metabolized by these enzymes refer to
                  (http://medicine.iupui.edu/clinpharm/ddis/clinical-table/) for clinically
                  relevant medications. Particular attention should be paid to patients receiving
                  warfarin. Patient should have coagulation parameters monitored regularly, and
                  warfarin dose adjusted accordingly. If these drugs cannot be discontinued or
                  replaced enrollment may be allowed after discussion with MSK PI.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Steven Horwitz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Steven Horwitz, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-639-3045</phone>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Alison Moskowitz, MD</last_name>
    <phone>212-639-4839</phone>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305-5408</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Youn Kim, MD</last_name>
      <phone>650-498-6000</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dana Farber Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Eric Jacobsen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>617-582-9086</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington School of Medicine in St. Louis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Neha Mehta-Shah, MD</last_name>
      <phone>314-362-5654</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Neha Mehta-Shah, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Neha Mehta-Shah, MD</last_name>
      <phone>314-362-5654</phone>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Neha Mehta-Shah, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memoral Sloan Kettering Cancer Center Basking Ridge</name>
      <address>
        <city>Basking Ridge</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Horwitz, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-3045</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Monmouth</name>
      <address>
        <city>Middletown</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07748</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Horwitz, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-3045</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center @ Commack</name>
      <address>
        <city>Commack</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11725</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Horwitz, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-3045</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memoral Sloan Kettering Westchester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Harrison</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Horwitz, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-3045</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Horwitz, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-3045</phone>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Alison Moskowitz, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-4839</phone>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Steven Horwitz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Memorial Sloan Kettering at Mercy Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rockville Centre</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Steven Horwitz, MD</last_name>
      <phone>212-639-3045</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.mskcc.org/</url>
    <description>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 24, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 24, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 26, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Duvelisib</keyword>
  <keyword>Romidepsin</keyword>
  <keyword>Bortezomib</keyword>
  <keyword>16-042</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Lymphoma, T-Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Romidepsin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bortezomib</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

