<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03152747</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Myopred</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03152747</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Influence of Posterior Vitreous Detachment on Retinal Detachment After Lens Surgery in Myopic Eyes</brief_title>
  <acronym>MYOPRED</acronym>
  <official_title>Influence of Posterior Vitreous Detachment on Retinal Detachment After Lens Surgery in Myopic Eyes</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Prim. Prof. Dr. Oliver Findl, MBA</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ESCRS</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vienna Institute for Research in Ocular Surgery</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Phacoemulsification with implantation of posterior chamber lenses represents the gold
      standard of care for patients needing lens surgery, but there is an increased risk of
      developing pseudophakic retinal detachment after surgery. Especially myopic patients have an
      even higher risk of pseudophakic retinal detachment compared to the general population.

      The aim of this multicenter study is to document the presence and/or post-operative
      development of posterior vitreous detachment (PVD) and to assess its influence on the
      incidence of retinal detachment (RD) in myopes in a time period of three and five years after
      lens surgery.

      618 eyes of patients scheduled for regular lens surgery will be included, defined by an axial
      length of 25.0 mm or more. To examine the vitreous status, all patients will receive a
      comprehensive eye examination pre-operatively, including funduscopy with assessment of a
      Weiss ring and optical coherence tomography (OCT). Patients will be divided into two groups,
      group A with pre-operative complete PVD and group B with no/partial PVD. Group A will be
      invited for one follow-up visit (two months post-operatively) followed up by telephone
      interviews at one, two, three and five years after surgery to determine occurrence of
      pseudophakic retinal detachment. Group B will be invited for follow -up examinations at two
      months, six months and one year after surgery to document occurrence of PVD (if a PVD is
      present at one of the follow-ups, no more visits are necessary). Two, three and five years
      after surgery, all patients from group B will be interviewed by telephone, as in group A, to
      document the occurrence of pseudophakic retinal detachment.

      In the recent literature the association between the occurrence of PVD pre-/post-operative
      and RD after lens surgery is well documented but not described for myopic patients. The
      results of this multicenter study should help to tackle the problem of RD prediction in
      myopic patients depending on their pre-operative vitreous status, especially in the setting
      of refractive lens exchange.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 3, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PVD status</measure>
    <time_frame>Mid 2023</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients with preoperative and/or post-operatively developed posterior vitreous detachment (PVD)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of RD</measure>
    <time_frame>Mid 2023</time_frame>
    <description>Influence of PVD on the incidence of retinal detachment (RD) in myopes after lens surgery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">618</enrollment>
  <condition>Myopia</condition>
  <condition>Cataract</condition>
  <condition>Pseudophakic Retinal Detachment</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group A with pre-operative complete posterior vitreous detachment Group A will be invited for one follow-up visit (two months post-operatively) followed up by telephone interviews at one, two, three and five years after surgery to determine occurrence of pseudophakic retinal detachment.
Examinations: Best corrected Visual Acuity (BCVA) , SD-OCT (spectral domain optical coherence tomography), Ultrasound B-scan (substudy only), Slit lamp examination, telephone interview</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <description>Group B with no/partial PVD
Group B will be invited for follow-up examinations at two months, six months and one year after surgery to document occurrence of PVD (if a PVD is present at one of the follow-ups, no more visits are necessary). Two, three and five years after surgery, all patients from group B will be interviewed by telephone, as in group A, to document the occurrence of pseudophakic retinal detachment.
Examinations: BCVA, SD-OCT, Ultrasound B-scan (substudy only), Slit lamp examination, telephone interview</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ultrasound, b-scan</intervention_name>
    <description>Some selected centres will participate in a substudy. In the substudy population, if the vitreous cortex is not visible on OCT both in the study eye and the fellow eye, or if the OCT is of poor quality and most likely will not allow definite diagnosis, a B-scan ophthalmic ultrasound will be performed by an experienced examiner. The presence or absence of a PVD in the ultrasound measurement will be recorded in the case report form (CRF). If ultrasonography was not performed, allocation to the groups is based on the staging of the reading centre. Otherwise ultrasonography will be used for final diagnosis and group allocation if the reading centre classifies the OCT as not decisive.</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study population: 618. The participants will be selected by the clinical investigators at
        several ophthalmological centres in Austria, Belgium, Spain, Norway and Sweden. As the
        study population is already scheduled for cataract surgery / refractive lens exchange,
        recruitment will be performed directly in these centres at the pre-assessment visits. At
        this visit, optical biometry is performed and patients with suitable axial eye lengths will
        be screened. If all inclusion and no exclusion criteria are met the patients will be asked
        to participate in the trial.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Minimum 21 years of age

          -  Patients scheduled for lens surgery with an axial eye length of 25.0 mm or more

          -  Availability, willingness, sufficient cognitive awareness to comply with examination
             procedures

          -  Ability to sign informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with combined surgery (e.g. combined phacoemulsification and vitrectomy or
             trabeculectomy or DSAEK)

          -  Patients with previous intraocular surgery (except any kind of laser surgery e.g.
             retinopexy, refractive laser surgery)

          -  Patients with recurrent severe anterior or posterior segment inflammation or uveitis
             of unknown aetiology, or any disease producing an inflammatory reaction in the eye

          -  Any ophthalmological pathology with the potential to compromise the measurements (e.g.
             mature/very dense cataract, fixation difficulties)

          -  Penetrating ocular trauma

          -  Previous history of retinal detachment

          -  Patient is pregnant, plans to become pregnant, is lactating or has another condition
             associated with the fluctuation of hormones that could lead to refractive changes

          -  Patients participating in another study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Oliver Findl, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vienna Institute for Research in Ocular Surgery</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Oliver Findl, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <phone>+4319102157564</phone>
    <email>office@viros.at</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vienna Institute for Research in Ocular Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vienna</city>
        <zip>1140</zip>
        <country>Austria</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Oliver Findl, Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+4319102157564</phone>
      <email>office@viros.at</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Austria</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 19, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 11, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 11, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 11, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 15, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Vienna Institute for Research in Ocular Surgery</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prim. Prof. Dr. Oliver Findl, MBA</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principle Investigator, Sponsor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cataract</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dissociative Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinal Detachment</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vitreous Detachment</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

