<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03150706</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>mCRC avelumab</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03150706</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Avelumab for MSI-H or POLE Mutated Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Avelumab in Patients With Mismatch Repair Deficient or POLE Mutated Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Asan Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Merck KGaA</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Asan Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The POLE mutations represent high somatic mutation loads in patients with colorectal cancer,
      especially in those with MMR proficient or MSS, therefore, tumors harbouring POLE mutations
      might be susceptible to immune checkpoint blockade.

      Based on these reasons, Investigator planned a phase II study of avelumab monotherapy in
      patients with previously treated, metastatic, MMR deficient (MSI-H) or POLE mutated
      colorectal cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Later-line therapies after failure of standard treatments for metastatic colorectal cancer
      patients are limited; regorafenib and TAS-102 have shown clinical activity for these
      patients, however, efficacy outcomes seemed not to be sufficient although there have been
      rather higher frequencies of adverse events.

      Mismatch repair (MMR) deficiency or microsatellite instability-high (MSI-H) played a role of
      negative predictive factor for adjuvant fluorouracil-based chemotherapy in patients with
      resected colorectal cancer. In the metastatic setting, deficient MMR or MSI-H represented
      poor prognosis; however, their predictive role has been documented after the pembrolizumab
      trial was reported. The results of the pembrolizumab trial demonstrated that the PD-1
      blockade with pembrolizumab monotherapy showed 40% of confirmed immune-related objective
      response rates in patients with MMR deficient metastatic colorectal cancers; hence there was
      no objective response in those with MMR proficient tumors. The progression-free rates at 20
      weeks were 78% versus 11%, respectively, also favouring those with MMR deficient tumors.
      However, the MMR deficiency of MSI-H is found in only about 5% in patients with metastatic
      colorectal cancer, which is too small to expand potential candidate of immunotherapy.

      One of the proposed mechanism of promising efficacy from pembrolizumab for MMR deficient
      colorectal cancer is that MMR deficient or MSI-H colorectal cancers harbour higher somatic
      mutation loads than MMR proficient colorectal cancer (a mean of 1782 somatic mutations per
      tumor in the MMR deficient tumors versus 73 in the MMR proficient tumors in the results of
      pembrolizumab trial); somatic mutations have the potential to encode non-self immunogenic
      antigens; therefore, immunotherapy enhancing immune surveillance produced promising treatment
      efficacy in the MMR deficient tumors.

      The POLE gene encodes the catalytic subunit of DNA polymerase epsilon, and it involves DNA
      repair and chromosomal replication. The POLE mutations are located in the exonuclease domain,
      and their presence has already been reported in the various cancers including colorectal and
      endometrial cancer.

      The POLE mutations represent high somatic mutation loads in patients with colorectal cancer,
      especially in those with MMR proficient or MSS, therefore, tumors harbouring POLE mutations
      might be susceptible to immune checkpoint blockade.

      Based on these reasons, Investigator planned a phase II study of avelumab monotherapy in
      patients with previously treated, metastatic, MMR deficient (MSI-H) or POLE mutated
      colorectal cancer.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 22, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum CEA, TSH, T3, free T4, EKG,CT (or MRI) scans of evaluable/measurable lesions by RECIST 1.1.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks(maximum 7 weeks)</time_frame>
    <description>During the CRT</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">33</enrollment>
  <condition>Metastatic Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Avelumab</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The mismatch repair deficient or microsatellite instable, or POLE mutated metastatic colorectal cancer patients who were progressed after at least one prior systemic treatment for metastatic setting.
After checking the eligibility for the study entry, patients will be entered into the study treatment with avelumab monotherapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Avelumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive 10 mg/kg of avelumab via intravenous infusion every 2 weeks.
Response evaluation will be performed every 6 weeks (± 1-week window period). Treatment will be continued until disease progression, unacceptable adverse events or the patient's refusal.
Treatment through progression is at the investigator's discretion, and the investigator should ensure that patients do not have any significant, unacceptable, or irreversible toxicity that indicate that continuing treatment will not further benefit the patient. The Investigator should ensure that patients still meet all of the inclusion criteria and none of the exclusion criteria for this study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Avelumab</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>MSB0010718C</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically or cytologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the colon or the rectum.

          2. Mismatch repair deficient or microsatellite instable (defined below), or POLE mutated
             tumors A. Mismatch repair deficient: loss of expression by immunohistochemical stains
             4. ≥ 1 out of 4 markers (MLH1, MSH2, MSH6, PMS2) B. Microsatellite instable: loss of
             stability ≥2 out of 5 gene panels (BAT-25, BAT-26, D2S123, D5S345, D17S250)

          3. Progressed after at least first-line systemic chemotherapy for metastatic setting.

          4. ≥ 1 measurable lesion(s) by RECIST 1.1.

          5. Unresectable advanced or metastatic disease.

          6. Age over 20 years old.

          7. ECOG 0-1, but final decision by clinical.

          8. Adequate organ functions. A. Bone marrow function: Hemoglobin 9.0 g/dL, ANC 1,500/mm3,
             platelet 100,000/mm3 B. Hepatic functions: bilirubin ≤ 1.5 X ULN, AST/ALT ≤ 2.5 X ULN
             (≤ 5 X ULN in cases of liver metastasis) C. Renal functions: serum Cr ≤ 1.5 X ULN or
             calculated CCr (Cockroft) ≥ 30 ml/min

          9. Be willing and able to comply with the protocol for the duration of the study.

         10. Give written informed consent prior to study-specific screening procedures, with the
             understanding that the patient has the right to withdraw the study at any time,
             without prejudice.

         11. Female subjects must either be of non-reproductive potential ( 60 years old and no
             menses for 1 year without an alternative medical cause, or history of hysterectomy, or
             history of bilateral tubal ligation, or history of bilateral oophorectomy) or must
             have a negative serum pregnancy test upon study entry.

         12. Women of childbearing potential and men must agree to use highly efficient
             contraception since signing of the IC form until at least 8 weeks after the last study
             drug administration.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Any prior treatment with PD-1 or PD-L1 inhibitor.

          2. Receipt of the last dose of chemotherapy ≤ 28 days prior to the first dose of study
             drugs.

          3. Current or prior use of immunosuppressive medication within 28 days before the first
             dose of avelumab, with the exceptions for the following: a. intranasal, inhaled,
             topical steroids, or local steroid injection (e.g., intra-articular injection); b.
             Systemic corticosteroids at physiologic doses ≤ 10 mg/day of prednisone or equivalent;
             c. Steroids as premedication for hypersensitivity reactions (e.g., CT scan
             premedication).

          4. Concurrent or previous history of another primary cancer within 3 years prior to
             randomisation except for curatively treated cervical cancer in situ, non-melanomatous
             skin cancer, superficial bladder cancer (pTis and pT1) and curatively treated thyroid
             cancer of any stage. Concurrent, histologically confirmed, unresected thyroid cancer
             without distant metastasis could be allowed with the agreement of the chief principal
             investigator.

          5. Uncontrolled CNS metastases; permitted if asymptomatic or neurologically stable.

          6. Prior radiation therapy would be permitted, but non-radiated evaluable lesions should
             be present at study entry.

          7. Radiation therapy during study treatment is not permitted, but if the local
             investigator decides that radiation therapy should be given during study treatments,
             he should be convinced that there is no evidence of disease progression with agreement
             of the chief principal investigator.

          8. Clinically significant (i.e., active) cardiovascular disease: cerebral vascular
             accident/stroke (&lt; 6 months prior to enrollment), myocardial infarction (&lt; 6 months
             prior to enrollment), unstable angina, congestive heart failure (≥ New York Heart
             Association Classification Class II), or serious cardiac arrhythmia requiring
             medication.

          9. Active or prior documented autoimmune disease within the past 2 years; subjects with
             diabetes type I, vitiligo, psoriasis, or hypo- or hyperthyroid diseases not requiring
             immunosuppressive treatment are eligible.

         10. Active or prior documented inflammatory bowel disease.

         11. History of prior immunodeficiency.

         12. History of allogeneic organ transplantation.

         13. Known prior severe hypersensitivity to investigational product or any component in its
             formulations, including known severe hypersensitivity reactions to monoclonal
             antibodies (NCI CTCAE v4.03 Grade ≥ 3)

         14. History of previous clinical diagnosis of active tuberculosis.

         15. Vaccination within 4 weeks of the first dose of avelumab and while on trials is
             prohibited except for administration of inactivated vaccines

         16. Known history of testing positive for HIV

         17. Hepatitis B virus (HBV) or hepatitis C virus (HCV) infection at screening (positive
             HBV surface antigen or HCV RNA if anti-HCV antibody screening test positive)

         18. Major surgery or significant traumatic injury within 28 days prior to study treatment.

         19. Non-healing wound, ulcer, or bone fracture.

         20. Current evidence of significant gastrointestinal bleeding or (impending) obstruction.

         21. Concomitant participation in another clinical trial.

         22. Pregnant of breast-feeding subjects. Women of child-bearing potential must have
             pregnancy test within 7 days and a negative result must be documented before start of
             study treatment.

         23. Substance abuse, medical, psychological or social conditions that may interfere with
             the subject's participation in the study or evaluation of the study results.

         24. Active infection requiring systemic therapy.

         25. Persisting toxicity related to prior therapy (NCI CTCAE v. 4.03 Grade &gt; 1); however,
             alopecia, sensory neuropathy Grade ≤ 2, or other Grade ≤ 2 not constituting a safety
             risk based on investigator's judgment are acceptable.

         26. Other severe acute or chronic medical conditions including colitis, inflammatory bowel
             disease, pneumonitis, pulmonary fibrosis or psychiatric conditions including recent
             (within the past year) or active suicidal ideation or behavior; or laboratory
             abnormalities that may increase the risk associated with study participation or study
             treatment administration or may interfere with the interpretation of study results
             and, in the judgment of the investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for
             entry into this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tae Won Kim, Professor</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Asan Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tae Won Kim, Professor</last_name>
    <phone>82-2-3010-3910</phone>
    <email>twkimmd@amc.seoul.kr</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Yong Sang Hong, MD,Phd</last_name>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Asan Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seoul</city>
        <state>Songpa</state>
        <zip>138736</zip>
        <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tae Won Kim, Professor</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Korea, Republic of</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 9, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 10, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 12, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Asan Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tae Won Kim</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>POLE mutation</keyword>
  <keyword>mismatch repair deficient</keyword>
  <keyword>Avelumab</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Antibodies, Monoclonal</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

