<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03154203</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SAFAR-CN</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03154203</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Non-Invasive Aortic Ambulatory Blood Pressure Monitoring for The Detection of Target Organ Damage in The Chinese Population</brief_title>
  <acronym>SAFAR-China</acronym>
  <official_title>The Study of Non-Invasive Aortic Ambulatory Blood Pressure Monitoring for The Detection of Target Organ Damage in The Population Of Chinese Patient (SAFAR-China)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Shanghai 10th People's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Shanghai 10th People's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study is a sub-investigation of SAFAR study. Consecutive patients with established
      hypertension (treated or untreated with antihypertensive drugs) or with suspected
      hypertension are recruited and their 24-hour brachial and aortic blood pressures,
      cardiovascular risk factors and target organ damage are assessed. And the participants'
      target organ damage, cardiovascular events, cardiovascular and overall mortality will be
      followed four years later.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      SAFAR study is an ongoing perspective study which is performed in Greek. We have been
      participated this study and now we are going to expand this study in Chinese population.

      In Shanghai Tenth People's Hospital, we recruit consecutive patients who meet the including
      criteria. And their medical and family history are obtained with standardized structured
      questionnaire including information about smoking and drinking and exercise habits, history
      of diabetes mellitus, cardio-cerebrovascular disease, renal disease and peripheral arterial
      disease, use of antihypertensive, lipid-regulating and hypoglycemic drugs. Their biochemical
      examinations of venous blood and urine were measured after an overnight fast.

      For the 24-hour brachial and aortic ambulatory blood pressure monitoring of each patient, we
      use the Mobil-O-Graph NG apparatus (IEM, Stolberg, Germany), which is well validated and now
      commercially available.

      All participants underwent carotid and cardiac ultrasonography by a validated ultrasound
      system (Mylab 30 CV machine, ESAOTE SPA, Genoa, Italy). The parameters of cardiac function
      and structure and the parameters of carotid arteries are assessed according to the ASE
      recommendation. Further, we use these parameters to estimate the damage of heart and carotid
      artery including left ventricular mass index (LVMI), carotid left ventricular diastolic
      function (LVDD), intima-media thickness (CIMT) and cross-sectional area(CCSA).

      Four years later, the above measurements will be performed again and the corresponding data
      of events and mortality will be collected.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular events</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>cardiovascular and all-cause mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">3000</enrollment>
  <condition>Blood Pressure</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Risk Factor</condition>
  <condition>Target Organ Damage</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Events</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Mortality</condition>
  <condition>Overall Mortality</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>No intervention in this study</intervention_name>
    <description>No intervention in this study</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Consecutive patients with established hypertension (treated or untreated with
        antihypertensive drugs) or with suspected hypertension
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients with established hypertension (treated or untreated with antihypertensive
             drugs) or with suspected hypertension

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age&lt;18 years old

          -  the absence of sinus rhythm during BP monitoring

          -  any modification in cardiovascular disease medication in the past month

          -  inability to provide informed consent or unwillingness/inability to adhere to study
             protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shanghai Tenth People's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Shanghai</city>
        <state>Shanghai</state>
        <zip>200072</zip>
        <country>China</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Shikai Yu, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+86 18801790211</phone>
      <email>shikaiyu@yahoo.com</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>China</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Aissopou EK, Argyris AA, Nasothimiou EG, Konstantonis GD, Tampakis K, Tentolouris N, Papathanassiou M, Theodossiadis PG, Papaioannou TG, Stehouwer CD, Sfikakis PP, Protogerou AD. Ambulatory Aortic Stiffness Is Associated With Narrow Retinal Arteriolar Caliber in Hypertensives: The SAFAR Study. Am J Hypertens. 2016 May;29(5):626-33. doi: 10.1093/ajh/hpv145. Epub 2015 Aug 24.</citation>
    <PMID>26304958</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Zhang Y, Kollias G, Argyris AA, Papaioannou TG, Tountas C, Konstantonis GD, Achimastos A, Blacher J, Safar ME, Sfikakis PP, Protogerou AD. Association of left ventricular diastolic dysfunction with 24-h aortic ambulatory blood pressure: the SAFAR study. J Hum Hypertens. 2015 Jul;29(7):442-8. doi: 10.1038/jhh.2014.101. Epub 2014 Nov 13.</citation>
    <PMID>25391758</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Protogerou AD, Argyris AA, Papaioannou TG, Kollias GE, Konstantonis GD, Nasothimiou E, Achimastos A, Blacher J, Safar ME, Sfikakis PP. Left-ventricular hypertrophy is associated better with 24-h aortic pressure than 24-h brachial pressure in hypertensive patients: the SAFAR study. J Hypertens. 2014 Sep;32(9):1805-14. doi: 10.1097/HJH.0000000000000263.</citation>
    <PMID>24999798</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 7, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 12, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 16, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 16, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 16, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 21, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Shanghai 10th People's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ya-Wei Xu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of Department of Cardiology, Professor of Tongji University, FACC</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

