<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03156283</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>5R21NR016046-02</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R21NR016046</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03156283</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>SleepWell24: An Innovative Smartphone Application to Improve PAP Adherence</brief_title>
  <official_title>SleepWell24: An Innovative Smartphone Application to Improve PAP Adherence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Arizona State University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Nursing Research (NINR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Arizona State University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is a major public health concern n the United States. Positive
      airway pressure (PAP) therapy is the treatment-of-choice and &quot;gold standard&quot; for individuals
      with moderate-to-severe OSA. Regular and sustained PAP use can reduce risk for subsequent
      disease and improve quality of life. Nevertheless, PAP adherence rates are low. Most PAP
      adherence programs do not address the self-management skills and strategies that promote
      adherence and are often too costly and complex to integrate into overburdened clinical
      environments. Furthermore, they do not leverage opportunities to change lifestyle behaviors
      that occur across the 24h spectrum (i.e., sleep hygiene, sedentary behavior, physical
      activity), which have promise to improve OSA symptoms and PAP adherence. The investigators
      have previously developed and successfully tested BeWell24, a multicomponent smartphone &quot;app&quot;
      that uses evidence-based behavior change strategies to improve sleep, sedentary, and physical
      activity behaviors. The investigators will enhance this app to create SleepWell24.
      Enhancements will include: (1) specific behavior change strategies from the evidence-based
      Sleep Apnea Self-Management Program to promote PAP adherence; (2) an interface for exchange
      of patient data to facilitate patient-provider communication on treatment progress; and (3)
      real-time feedback via wireless integration with a consumer-based PAP machine and wearable
      sensor. All aspects of this work will be embedded within the Mayo Clinic Arizona Center for
      Sleep Medicine. The investigators will test the effects of SleepWell24 in newly prescribed
      PAP users and gather data on the feasibility and acceptability of using SleepWell24 compared
      to a usual care control group. The investigators will conduct a pilot randomized controlled
      trial with participants randomly assigned to (1) SleepWell24; or (2) usual care for 60 days
      post-PAP prescription. The investigators will track recruitment/retention rates, app usage
      statistics, and measures of treatment satisfaction. The investigators will objectively
      measure PAP adherence to test whether the SleepWell24 group will have more hours/night of PAP
      usage compared to the usual care group. In an exploratory fashion, the investigators will
      also examine the effect of SleepWell24 on selected treatment outcomes (weight, daytime
      sleepiness, cognitive impairment, and health-related quality of life) and evaluate social
      cognitive and lifestyle behavior mediators of SleepWell24 on PAP adherence.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This exploratory study will test the feasibility and initial efficacy of a mobile health
      smartphone intervention to increase adherence to positive airway pressure (PAP) therapy in
      newly diagnosed obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) patients treated at the Mayo Clinic Arizona
      Center for Sleep Medicine and associated outpatient clinics. This app, called SleepWell24,
      will include PAP adherence behavior change strategies (drawn from the evidence-based Sleep
      Apnea Self-Management Program), cloud-based linkages to a consumer-based PAP machine and
      wearable sensor that provides nightly feedback on PAP adherence and sleep and activity
      metrics, and a component to enhance patient-provider communication. The investigators will
      embed SleepWell24 within usual patient care at the Mayo Clinic Arizona Center for Sleep
      Medicine and associated outpatient clinics for app design/development, patient recruitment,
      and treatment feasibility/satisfaction. This design will ensure the best opportunity for
      clinical adoption. The primary aims are:

      Aim 1: Determine the feasibility and acceptability of SleepWell24 from patient and provider
      perspectives.

      Aim 2: Determine the extent to which SleepWell24 improves PAP adherence over the first 60
      days of use relative to usual care.

      As an exploratory aim the investigators will explore the effect of SleepWell24 on treatment
      outcomes (weight, daytime sleepiness, cognitive performance, health-related quality of life)
      and putative social cognitive and behavioral mediators of PAP adherence (e.g., self-efficacy,
      sleep quality, sedentary behavior, physical activity).

      The investigators will test the feasibility, acceptability, initial efficacy and outcomes of
      SleepWell24 compared to usual care during the first 60 days of PAP use among 94 patients
      newly diagnosed with obstructive sleep apnea.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 1, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment and Retention</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of the trial (~60 days)</time_frame>
    <description>numbers recruited and retained over the course of the trial</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>SleepWell24 application usage</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of the trial (~60 days)</time_frame>
    <description>objective metrics of smartphone application usage by intervention group</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment acceptability/satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline vs. Day 60 of trial</time_frame>
    <description>Intervention acceptability questionnaire for both groups</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive airway pressure therapy use</measure>
    <time_frame>Duration of the trial (~60 days)</time_frame>
    <description>How many hours per night therapy was used throughout the trial</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Body Mass Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and follow-up visit between days 31 and 60</time_frame>
    <description>body mass index according to weight and height</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Daytime Sleepiness</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 30, Day 60 of trial</time_frame>
    <description>Epworth Sleepiness Scale</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive functioning</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and follow-up visit between days 31 and 60</time_frame>
    <description>Neurocognitive battery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Day 30, Day 60 of trial</time_frame>
    <description>global and disease-specific quality of life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Obstructive Sleep Apnea of Adult</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SleepWell24 Application</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A mobile health smartphone application based on evidence-based health behavior change theory and interventions to promote adherence to positive airway pressure therapy</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Plus Activity Monitor</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Per usual clinical care standards within the Center for Sleep Medicine at Mayo Clinic Arizona, all patients will receive instructions/education on positive airway pressure (PAP) use, multiple mask fittings, encouragement to use PAP every night, and staff is available in the event of problems. Control patients will also receive a wearable activity monitor to use during the study. The wearable sensor will be used to isolate the effect of SleepWell24 on PAP adherence from potential novelty effects due to receiving a generic health behavior change app.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SleepWell24 Application</intervention_name>
    <description>An evidence-based behavioral change smartphone application designed to promote adherence to positive airway pressure (PAP) therapy</description>
    <arm_group_label>SleepWell24 Application</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Usual Care Plus Activity Monitor</intervention_name>
    <description>Participants will receive usual care at the Mayo Clinic Center for Sleep Medicine when first diagnosed with sleep apnea and prescribed positive airway pressure therapy. In addition, they will receive a commercial activity monitor with an associated smartphone application to isolate the effect of SleepWell24 on PAP adherence from potential novelty effects due to receiving a generic health behavior change app.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Plus Activity Monitor</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Mild to severe obstructive sleep apnea diagnosed through clinical diagnostic testing
             and laboratory or home-based sleep study

          -  current use of appropriate Apple (iOS7 or higher) or Android (2.3 or higher)
             smartphone device

          -  Be able to read, write, and understand English

          -  Prescribed positive airway pressure therapy for obstructive sleep apnea

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Do not agree to be randomized

          -  Currently participating in other lifestyle change programs

          -  Personal, health, cognitive, or psychological conditions that prevent full
             participation

          -  Pregnant, lactating, or trying to become pregnant

          -  Prescribed high-dose benzodiazepines

          -  Daily opioid medication use at night

          -  Unwilling to discontinue use of any current wearable sensor for the duration of the
             trial

          -  Unwilling to consent for out-of-pocket costs

          -  Previous treatment/referral for claustrophobia

          -  Previous Positive airway pressure therapy use

          -  Planning to travel for more than seven consecutive nights during the trial

          -  Currently engaging in shiftwork
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Megan E Petrov, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Arizona State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matthew Buman, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Arizona State University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Megan E Petrov, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>602-496-2297</phone>
    <email>Megan.Petrov@asu.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85054</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lois Krahn, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 27, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 15, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 17, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Arizona State University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Megan Petrov</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>smartphone</keyword>
  <keyword>obstructive sleep apnea</keyword>
  <keyword>adherence</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sleep Apnea, Obstructive</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

