<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03154229</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IRB201601762 - N</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1DP5OD019893</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03154229</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of a mHealth Platform for Diarrheal Disease Decision-support</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Evaluation of a mHealth Platform for Diarrheal Disease Decision-support in Hospitals: a Cluster Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study hypothesis is that clinical decision-support on a smartphone for the management of
      diarrheal disease will improve the assessment of dehydration, reduce IV fluid usage, and
      increase guideline adherence for the use of zinc and antibiotics. To test this hypothesis we
      will conduct a cluster randomized controlled trial in the diarrhea wards of 10 hospitals in
      Bangladesh. A 6-week pre-intervention period will establish a baseline at all sites, and in
      the intervention, hospitals will be randomized to use a paper versus smartphone adaptation of
      the WHO guidelines by the admitting physician. Inclusion criteria are patients 2 months and
      older that have uncomplicated acute diarrheal disease; estimated enrollment is 7893 patients.
      The primary outcome measure is use of IV fluids. This project may have broad impact that will
      include opportunities to provide improved decision-support for the assessment of dehydration,
      decreased use intravenous fluids and more prudent use of antibiotics.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Technology is making possible new approaches to overcome old public health challenges.
      Cellular networks are now ubiquitous in resource-poor settings and offer new opportunities
      for high-yield interventions for both chronic and acute diseases. We are specifically
      interested in developing mHealth solutions for diarrheal disease for two reasons. The first
      reason is that diarrheal disease globally remains the second leading cause of death for
      children less than 5 years of age. Barriers to combat this problem include poor adherence to
      guidelines for rehydrating children and outbreaks often outpace current epidemiological
      tools. The second reason is that diarrheal diseases in a setting like Bangladesh, including
      cholera outbreaks, are a model system to develop and test mHealth solutions that can be
      adapted to more complex chronic and acute diseases in Bangladesh and globally.

      In partnership with the International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh
      (icddr,b; primary collaborator) and the Institute of Epidemiology, Disease Control, Research
      (IEDCR) within the Ministry of Health and Family Welfare in Bangladesh, we propose to compare
      a paper-based versus a smartphone-based decision-support tool in a cluster randomized
      controlled trial (cRCT) to determine the impact of the method of decision-support on the use
      of IV fluids (primary outcome) and indicated medications (secondary outcomes). The smartphone
      tool is an adaptation of the paper-based World Health Organization guidelines, and is called
      the 'Rehydration Calculator.' The cRCT will be conducted collaboratively between the icddr,b
      and government hospitals (N=10) in Bangladesh over 4.5 months per site. A 6-week
      pre-intervention period will establish a baseline at all sites, and in the intervention,
      hospitals will be randomized to use the paper versus smartphone tool by the admitting
      physician. Inclusion criteria are patients 2 months and older that have uncomplicated acute
      diarrheal disease; estimated enrollment is 7893 patients. Standard of care will be practiced
      at all sites, with the exception of the decision-support tool(s) in the interventional
      period. The primary outcome measure is use of IV fluids. This project may have broad impact
      that will include opportunities to provide improved decision-support for the assessment of
      dehydration, decrease intravenous fluid use and improve antibiotic stewardship.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 11, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Cluster randomized controlled trial.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of IV fluid</measure>
    <time_frame>Intervention is 3 months per hospital</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of patients prescribed IV fluid between the paper-based decision-support and the Smartphone decision-support.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of zinc</measure>
    <time_frame>Intervention is 3 months per hospital</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of patients under five years prescribed zinc between the paper-based decision-support and the Smartphone decision-support.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Use of indicated antibiotics</measure>
    <time_frame>Intervention is 3 months per hospital</time_frame>
    <description>The percentage of patients prescribed the indicated antibiotic over 2 years of age that have acute watery diarrhea and severe dehydration between the paper-based decision-support and the Smartphone decision-support.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">8468</enrollment>
  <condition>Diarrhea</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Paper-based decision-support</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Prior to starting the study, 10 hospitals will be made into 5 pairs. The paper versus smartphone intervention will be randomized to one member of each pair. The study arm will consist of a pre-interventional (6 weeks) followed by an interventional period (12 weeks); this arms will use paper-based decision support at the 5 hospitals designated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Smartphone-based decision-support</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Prior to starting the study, 10 hospitals will be made into 5 pairs. The paper versus smartphone intervention will be randomized to one member of each pair. The study arm will consist of a pre-interventional (6 weeks) followed by an interventional period (12 weeks); this arms will use smartphon-based decision support at the 5 hospitals designated.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Smartphone-based decision-support</intervention_name>
    <description>WHO guidelines have been adapted from paper onto a smartphone referred to as a Rehydration Calculator</description>
    <arm_group_label>Smartphone-based decision-support</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Paper-based decision-support</intervention_name>
    <description>WHO guidelines presented on paper</description>
    <arm_group_label>Paper-based decision-support</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pre-Assessment of practices</intervention_name>
    <description>Observation of baseline clinical practice.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Paper-based decision-support</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Smartphone-based decision-support</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Acute uncomplicated diarrhea (less than 7 days with at least 3 loose stools in the
             last 24 hours)

          -  Age greater than or equal to two months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  No diarrhea

          -  Complicated diarrheal disease (e.g. e.g. sepsis, meningitis, convulsions, electrolyte
             imbalance, myocardial infarction, respiratory failure, chronic kidney disease, severe
             malnutrition by clinical measures and mid-upper arm circumference (&lt;11.5cm for &gt;= 6 mo
             to less than 5 years; &lt;11.0 cm for &gt;= 2mo to &lt;6 mo))
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eric J Nelson, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Florida, USA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Eric J Nelson, MD PhD</last_name>
    <phone>13522948536</phone>
    <email>eric.nelson@ufl.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Ashraful I Khan, PhD MS MBBS</last_name>
    <email>ashrafk@icddrb.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh (icddr,b)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dhaka</city>
        <state>Dhaka Division</state>
        <zip>1212</zip>
        <country>Bangladesh</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ashraful I Khan, PhD MSc MBBS</last_name>
      <email>ashrafk@icddrb.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Firdausi Qadri, PhD</last_name>
      <email>fqadri@icddrb.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Bangladesh</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://journals.plos.org/plosntds/article?id=10.1371/journal.pntd.0005290</url>
    <description>Pilot study publication</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Haque F, Ball RL, Khatun S, Ahmed M, Kache S, Chisti MJ, Sarker SA, Maples SD, Pieri D, Vardhan Korrapati T, Sarnquist C, Federspiel N, Rahman MW, Andrews JR, Rahman M, Nelson EJ. Evaluation of a Smartphone Decision-Support Tool for Diarrheal Disease Management in a Resource-Limited Setting. PLoS Negl Trop Dis. 2017 Jan 19;11(1):e0005290. doi: 10.1371/journal.pntd.0005290. eCollection 2017 Jan.</citation>
    <PMID>28103233</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 12, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 12, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 16, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 29, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 2, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diarrhea</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

