<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03154476</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>16-008985</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03154476</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Role of Sildenafil for Fontan Associated Liver Disease (SiFALD) Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>SiFALD</acronym>
  <official_title>Role of Sildenafil for Fontan Associated Liver Disease (SiFALD) Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_us_export>No</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if the medication, sildenafil (also known as
      Revatio), can slow or stop the progression of liver disease in patients who previously had a
      Fontan operation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1. All participants will undergo a baseline liver magnetic resonance elastography. The
           patients with liver stiffness score &gt;2.5 kiloPascal (KPa) [Normal: ≤2.5 KPa] will be
           enrolled in the study.

        2. In addition to a baseline liver MRE, all participants will undergo cardiac MRI,
           transthoracic echocardiogram (TTE), FibroSure® (alpha-2 macroglobulin, haptoglobulin,
           gamma-glutamyltransferase, bilirubin, apolipoprotein A1, and alanine transaminase), and
           chemistry panel.

        3. This will be a double blinded placebo control study design. All participants will be
           randomized 1:1 to sildenafil or placebo for a total of 12 months therapy.

        4. Sildenafil will be initiated at 5 mg 3 times per day for the first week, and titrated to
           10 mg 3 times per day for the second week and 20 mg 3 times per day from the 3rd week to
           the end of the study period. The patients will be required to check their pulse rate and
           blood pressure daily during the first month of drug therapy. Patient who experience
           hypotension (blood pressure &lt; 90/50 plus symptoms such as dizziness) during dose
           titration will be asked to remain on the previous tolerated dose. Patients who cannot
           tolerate 10 mg 3 times daily will be asked to withdraw from the study and will be asked
           to continue checking their blood pressure for three days after stopping the medication.

        5. After 12 months (+/- 2 weeks) of therapy, all imaging studies (liver MRE, cardiac MRI,
           TTE) and blood tests (FibroSure® and chemistry panel) will be repeated. A final liver
           MRE and FibroSure will be performed at 18 months (+/- 2 weeks) for the participants
           whose 18 months follow-up still falls within the study period.

        6. Adverse event and compliance monitoring: During the first month of enrollment
           (initiation and dose titration), adverse events will be collected by subject report and
           by weekly telephone interview with dedicated research personnel. For the rest of the
           study period, adverse events will be collected by subject report and by monthly
           telephone interview with dedicated research personnel. The research personnel will be
           responsible for sending out the monthly supply of medications and obtaining a count of
           the remaining number pills as a measure of compliance. All participants will be provided
           with a pamphlet containing all the side effects of sildenafil, and contact information
           of research team for reporting any adverse event of concerns about the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 5, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Randomized Double-blind Placebo-control study</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>Both the treatment arm (sildenafil) and the placebo arm will receive monthly package of similar pills. Equal number of patients will be randomly assigned to each arm.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in liver stiffness as measured by magnetic resonance elastography (MRE)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline (time zero), at 12 months (52 weeks) from the time of initiation of therapy</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in liver stiffness &gt;500 Pa will be considered significant</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Cirrhosis</condition>
  <condition>Congenital Heart Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sildenafil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects randomized to this arm will receive sildenafil 5 mg 3 times per day for the first week, and titrated to 10 mg 3 times per day for the second week, and 20 mg 3 times per day from the third week to the end of the study period, 12 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects will receive placebo times per day for 12 months.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sildenafil</intervention_name>
    <description>Sildenafil will be initiated at 5 mg 3 times per day for the first week, and titrated to 10 mg 3 times per day for the second week and 20 mg 3 times per day from the third week to the end of the study period, 12 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Sildenafil</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Revatio</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo capsules matching study drug</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  All adult Fontan patients who have no contraindications for magnetic resonance imaging
             (MRI) will be eligible for the study.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Subjects with implantable pacemakers

          -  Residual cardiac lesions (severe ventricular dysfunction, severe atrioventricular
             valve regurgitation, Fontan baffle or conduit obstruction)

          -  Viral hepatitis

          -  Severe renal dysfunction

          -  History of sildenafil use in the six months prior to study enrollment

          -  Ongoing sildenafil therapy

          -  Patients currently taking nitrates

          -  Hypotension at baseline (BP &lt;90/50 mmHg)

          -  Pulmonary veno-occlusive disease

          -  Hearing/vision impairment

          -  Pulmonary hypertension due to sickle cell disease

          -  Women of child-bearing potential with a positive pregnancy test will additionally be
             excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alexander C Egbe</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Alexander Egbe, MD PH</last_name>
    <phone>507-284-2520</phone>
    <email>egbe.alexander@mayo.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Rochester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Alexander Egbe, MD MOH</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Alexander C Egbe</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 12, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 12, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 16, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 6, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 6, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 11, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mayo Clinic</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alexander C. Egbe</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Medicine and Pediatrics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sildenafil Citrate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The safety of the subject will be monitored throughout the duration of the study. During the first month of enrollment (initiation and dose titration), adverse events will be collected by subject report and by weekly telephone interview with dedicated research personnel. For the rest of the study period, adverse events will be collected by subject report and by monthly telephone interview with dedicated research personnel. All participants will be provided with a pamphlet containing all the side effects of sildenafil, and contact information of research team for reporting any adverse event of concerns about the study.
The patients will be required to check their pulse rate and blood pressure daily during the first month of drug therapy. Patient who experience hypotension (blood pressure &lt; 90/60 plus symptoms such as dizziness) during dose titration will be asked to remain on the previous tolerated dose</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

