<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03158519</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IUSCC-0590</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03158519</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>iMETX (Individualized Metabolic RX): a Pilot Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>iMETX (Individualized Metabolic RX): a Pilot Study of an Environmental Intervention to Increase Energy Expenditure Among Breast Cancer Survivors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Indiana University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Susan G. Komen Breast Cancer Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Wisconsin, Madison</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Indiana University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to test the mechanics and feasibility of delivering an
      individualized intervention to increase physical activity in breast cancer survivors.

      In this study, researchers will test an intervention that uses a commonly worn activity
      monitor (i.e., global positioning system [GPS] enabled running watch) to see if they can
      &quot;prescribe&quot; specific ways to increase physical activity that are individually tailored to
      each participant. The goal is to help participants increase their daily physical activity
      without having to join a gym or other traditional fitness program. Researchers want to see if
      they can make specific recommendations (using an application that can be added to a cell
      phone, tablet and/or computer) on ways participants can slowly increase their activity based
      upon where they live and work and in a way that is tailored individually to them. For
      example, participants may be given a route to walk on their lunch break, or new place to park
      to allow for a longer walk to their job. The goal is to meet participants where they are in
      their current level of fitness, and to help them think of new and creative ways of increasing
      activity without the frustration of soreness or risk of injury. As they move more, the
      recommendations will increase with them.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives The investigators hypothesize that developing an individualized and dynamic
      exercise intervention (iMETX) that accounts for factors of the built environment will be
      feasible for breast cancer patients following primary treatment. This pilot study will assess
      the feasibility and provide preliminary estimates of effectiveness of the environmental
      intervention for increasing the energy expenditure and energetic capacity of breast cancer
      patients. The investigators will also explore patient feedback with this intervention and
      changes in levels of fatigue and quality of life. Experience and data from this initial pilot
      study will be used to refine the intervention and design subsequent studies to test its
      effectiveness.

      Primary objective Evaluate the feasibility of an individualized, dynamic, environmental
      physical activity intervention for early stage breast cancer patients following primary
      treatment.

      Secondary objectives

        1. Determine a preliminary estimate of effect size of the environmental intervention on
           energetic capacity (power envelope) as measured by Power Protocol-B

        2. Determine a preliminary estimate of effect size of the environmental intervention on
           average daily EE as measured by a wearable hybrid GPS/accelerometer physical activity
           monitor

        3. Determine the effect of the environment intervention on the physical parameters of BMI
           and lean body mass

        4. Determine the effect of the environmental intervention on patient reported fatigue and
           quality of life

        5. Determine the persistence of changes in average daily EE after the intervention is
           complete (i.e., when individual movement tasks are no longer suggested).

        6. Obtain formal and informal patient feedback throughout and after the intervention to
           assess satisfaction and perceptions of feasibility

        7. Assess safety

      Exploratory objectives Blood samples will be collected prior to and following the
      intervention and banked for future correlative studies, including the following: inflammatory
      cytokines (high sensitivity C reactive protein and interleukin 6), adipokines (adiponectin
      and leptin), sex hormones (estradiol, estrone, testosterone, and sex hormone binding
      globulin), and telomere length. In addition the invstigators will explore correlations of
      built and social environment characteristics and psychosocial characteristics with
      pre-intervention and changes in energy expenditure.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 31, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of intervention</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of enrolled patients who complete study through end of intervention period (week 4-week 15)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>iMETX intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>iMETX intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Pre-intervention the participants will wear the running watch for 3 weeks so that researchers can collect data about their daily routines regarding where and how much energy they expend.
During the intervention participants will wear the running watch for 12 weeks. Every 1-3 days the participants will be given an individualized recommendation for how to increase their activity via the iMETX application. Participants will be able to provide feedback to the researchers throughout intervention period regarding what works and does not in terms of the recommendations for increasing activity.
Post-intervention the participants will wear the running watch for 12 weeks so that researchers can collect data in order to determine whether physical activity changes made during the intervention are sustained.</description>
    <arm_group_label>iMETX intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          1. Age ≥ 18 years

          2. Diagnosis of DCIS or stage I, II, or III breast cancer

          3. Completion of all primary therapy (with the exception of ongoing endocrine or
             trastuzumab therapy), including surgery, radiation, and/or chemotherapy greater than 4
             weeks prior to study enrollment

          4. Body weight less than 350 lbs., as dictated by the weight limit for DXA scanner

          5. Regular access to a smart phone or computer

        Exclusion criteria

          1. Any condition precluding exercise, including: NYHA class II, III, or IV congestive
             heart failure, uncontrolled angina, myocardial infarction in the prior 12 months,
             orthopedic surgery in the previous 6 months or plans for orthopedic surgery during the
             study period, chronic pulmonary conditions such as uncontrolled asthma (symptoms &gt; 2
             days/week) or dyspnea requiring oxygen, symptomatic peripheral vascular disease,
             symptomatic anemia, uncontrolled psychiatric conditions such as schizophrenia, or any
             other comorbidity that would interfere with the ability to complete and comply with
             the study protocol in the opinion of the investigator

          2. Locally recurrent or metastatic breast cancer

          3. Diagnosis of other active malignancy. Prior treated malignancies in addition to breast
             cancer are acceptable.

          4. Pregnancy

          5. Requirement of assistive devices (e.g., cane) for ambulation

          6. Plans for moving to a new home or workplace during, pre-, or post-intervention period

          7. Elective surgery anticipated during, pre-, or post-intervention period (e.g., breast
             reconstruction)

          8. Inability to comply with the study procedures
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kathy Miller, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Indiana University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Jessica Sollars, RN</last_name>
    <phone>317-278-5117</phone>
    <email>jlsherma@iupui.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University Health North Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Carmel</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46032</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jessica Sollars, RN</last_name>
      <phone>317-278-5117</phone>
      <email>jlsherma@iupui.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kathy Miller, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University Health Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jessica Sollars, RN</last_name>
      <phone>317-278-5117</phone>
      <email>jlsherma@iupui.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kathy Miller, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Indiana University Health Melvin and Bren Simon Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jessica Sollars, RN</last_name>
      <phone>317-278-5117</phone>
      <email>jlsherma@iupui.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kathy Miller, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Spring Mill Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Indianapolis</city>
        <state>Indiana</state>
        <zip>46290</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jessica Sollars, RN</last_name>
      <phone>317-278-5117</phone>
      <email>jlsherma@iupui.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kathy Miller, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 16, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 16, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Indiana University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kathy Miller</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Oncology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Physical activity</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

