<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02829047</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>220CLD</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02829047</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tolerability, Safety and Efficacy of a New Frequency of Vibrant Capsule Administration</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Multicenter, Open-label, Single-arm Study to Assess the Tolerability, Safety and Efficacy of a New Frequency of Vibrant Capsule Administration</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Vibrant Ltd.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vibrant Ltd.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is a prospective, multicenter, open-label, single-arm study, to evaluate the
      tolerability, safety and efficacy of the Vibrant Capsule in relieving constipation.

      One arm will be assessed: Vibrant Capsule administered with a sequence of one per day for 2
      days, followed by one day without, one per day for 2 days followed by one day without, etc.
      (14 capsules in 3 weeks).

      The study will have one interim analysis.

      Patients will follow a 2 weeks baseline period and then take the Vibrant Capsule for a
      treatment period of 6 weeks.

      Data reporting will be done on an electronic Case Report Form and an eDiary. During the 2
      weeks of baseline, patients will be asked to refrain from taking any medication or supplement
      to relieve their constipation.

      After 14 days the patients will return and eligibility will be re-assessed. Patients will be
      trained on how to use the base unit.

      Patients will be instructed to complete a simple patient eDiary each day throughout the
      duration of the study. After 3 weeks of treatment, the patient will attend for evaluation and
      to receive new capsules. A final visit will take place at the end of the 6 week treatment
      period.

      Patients will receive phone calls up to twice per week and patient compliance will be
      monitored during the 8 weeks of the study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Study halted at interim analysis to allow the sponsor to focus on a new study with different
    design.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Spontaneous Bowel Movements success rate</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Increase from the run-in period of at least one weekly Spontaneous Bowel Movement during at least 3 of the 6 weeks of treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>All adverse events related and unrelated to the study treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Constipation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Vibrating Capsule</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive vibrating capsule for 6 weeks of treatment (14 capsules in 3 weeks)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Vibrating Capsule</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will receive vibrating capsule for 6 weeks of treatment (14 capsules in 3 weeks)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Vibrating Capsule</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          1. Patients aged 22 years and older

          2. Patients with Chronic Idiopathic Constipation according to Rome III criteria and who
             have not experienced relief of their symptoms from available therapies (osmotic and
             stimulant laxatives used for at least one month at recommended dose)

          3. Patients with an average of less than 3 Spontaneous Bowel Movements per week and at
             least 1 Spontaneous Bowel Movements per week

          4. Normal colonoscopy performed within 10 years prior to study participation, unless the
             patients are less than 50 years old and without alarm signs and/or symptoms

          5. Patient signed the Informed Consent Form

          6. Female subjects must have a negative urine pregnancy test and must not be lactating
             prior to receiving study medication. For females of child-bearing potential, a
             hormonal (i.e., oral, implantable, or injectable) and single-barrier method, or a
             double-barrier method of birth control must be used throughout the study. All other
             female subjects must have the reason for their inability to bear children documented
             in the medical record; in these circumstances, a urine pregnancy test will not be
             necessary.

        Exclusion criteria

          1. History of complicated/obstructive diverticular disease

          2. History of intestinal or colonic obstruction, or suspected intestinal obstruction.

          3. History of significant gastrointestinal disorder, including any form of inflammatory
             bowel disease or gastrointestinal malignancy (celiac disease is accepted if the
             subject has been treated and is in remission)

          4. History of gastroparesis

          5. Use of any of the following medications:

               -  Medications that may affect intestinal motility, prokinetics, anti-depressants,
                  anti-Parkinsonian medications, opiates, opioids, calcium-channel blockers,
                  aluminum/magnesium hydroxide

               -  With the exception of antidepressants, thyroid or hormonal replacement therapy,
                  when the subject has been on a stable dose for at least 3 months prior to
                  enrollment.

          6. Clinical evidence of significant respiratory, cardiovascular, renal, hepatic, biliary,
             endocrine, psychiatric or neurologic disease.

          7. Presence of cardiac pacemaker or gastric electrical stimulator.

          8. History of, or current eating disorders, such as anorexia, bulimia, or compulsory
             overeating.

          9. Diagnosis of mega-rectum or colon, congenital anorectal malformation, clinically
             significant rectocele, history of intestinal resection (with an exception for
             appendectomy, cholecystectomy and inguinal hernia repair), history of bariatric
             surgery or evidence of any structural abnormality of the gastrointestinal tract that
             might affect transit

         10. History of Zenker's diverticulum, dysphagia, Barrett's esophagus, esophageal stricture
             or achalasia

         11. Chronic use of non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs: chronic use is defined as taking
             full dose non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs more than three times a week for at
             least six months. Patients on cardiac doses of aspirin may be enrolled in the study

         12. Patients with pelvic floor dysfunction/defecatory disorder, based on patient history

         13. Participation in another clinical study within one month prior to screening.

         14. Women who are pregnant or lactating

         15. Use of any medication for constipation relief during the study, except as rescue
             medication, as indicated by study rules

         16. Inability to use an electronic daily Diary (on a computer, phone application, tablet
             or other electronic device) to report bowel movements, symptoms and medication usage

         17. Any other condition which in the opinion of the investigator may adversely affect the
             safety of the patient or would limit the patient's ability to complete the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>22 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Eamonn Quigley, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Houston Methodist medical center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Avant Guntersville</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guntersville</city>
        <state>Alabama</state>
        <zip>35976</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Borland-Groover Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jacksonville</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>32256</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Floridian Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33145</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Albuquerque Neuroscience</name>
      <address>
        <city>Albuquerque</city>
        <state>New Mexico</state>
        <zip>87109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 5, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 11, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 12, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 12, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 12, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Constipation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

