<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02822105</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H3N2-V001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02822105</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Immunogenicity Study of H3N2 M2SR Monovalent Influenza Vaccine in Healthy Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 1 Clinical Study To Investigate The Safety And Immunogenicity Of The H3N2 (A/Brisbane/10/2007) M2SR Monovalent Influenza Vaccine</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>FluGen Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>FluGen Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose is of this study is to assess the safety and tolerability of three dose levels of
      H3N2 M2SR influenza vaccine versus placebo delivered intranasally to healthy adult subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Healthy adult subjects will be screened with the objective to randomize 96 subjects with the
      lowest levels of H3 hemagglutination inhibition (HAI) titers that meet all
      inclusion/exclusion criteria and have signed an informed consent. Subjects will be rank
      ordered from low to high based on their HAI titer. Subjects will then be assigned treatment
      based on a randomization to either active vaccine or placebo. The first two subjects dosed in
      each dose cohort will serve as sentinels and will receive active IP (not randomized).

      Subjects will receive a single dose inoculation of the H3N2 M2SR seasonal monovalent
      influenza vaccine administered intranasally as a liquid formulation, or placebo (saline). The
      sentinel subjects will be vaccinated in dose cohort 1 and a safety monitoring committee (SMC)
      will conduct a review of safety data, tolerability, reactogenicity, and clearance of
      infectious virus prior to dosing the remaining subjects of the cohort with active or placebo.

      After the last subject in the cohort has been followed for at least 7 days the SMC will
      conduct another review of safety data prior to proceeding to the next higher dose level:
      Cohort 2. The same processes of sentinel subject dosing and SMC review will be conducted for
      Cohorts 2 and 3.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency and severity of local and systemic adverse events (AEs) through 28 days vaccination and cumulatively through Day 180</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline through study completion (Day 180)</time_frame>
    <description>Record adverse events</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of subjects demonstrating seroconversion to vaccine hemagglutinin antigen and the magnitude of the immune response</measure>
    <time_frame>from baseline through study completion (Day 180)</time_frame>
    <description>Test antibodies pre and post vaccination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Length of time that vaccine virus shedding is detected</measure>
    <time_frame>at 24, 48 and 72 hours post-vaccination and on day 7 post vaccination</time_frame>
    <description>Test nasal swabs for virus</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Flu</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>H3N2 M2SR monovalent influenza vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive a low, medium or high dose of the H3N2 M2SR monovalent influenza vaccine administered intranasally. It will be compared with placebo in a 3:1 ratio.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will receive saline administered intranasally.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>the H3N2 M2SR monovalent influenza vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>The H3N2 Bris10 M2SR influenza vaccine candidate (Bris10 M2SR) is formulated to contain different levels of an M2-deleted non-replicating influenza virus expressing the HA and NA genes of influenza strain A/Brisbane/10/2007.</description>
    <arm_group_label>H3N2 M2SR monovalent influenza vaccine</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>saline</description>
    <arm_group_label>placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Key Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Individuals who are in good health at the time of entry into the study as determined
             by medical history, physical examination, vital signs, and clinical safety laboratory
             values and clinical judgement of the Principal Investigator (PI)

          -  The subject signs and dates a written, informed consent form and any required privacy
             authorization

          -  Willing to use a reliable form of contraception approved by the Investigator (e.g.,
             intrauterine device [IUD], female condom, diaphragm with spermicide, cervical cap, use
             of condom by the sexual partner or a sterile sexual partner) for 1 month prior to
             vaccination and until 28 days following the last visit

          -  Individuals who are willing and able to communicate with the Investigator and
             understand the requirements of the study

          -  Individuals who can comply with trial procedures and are available for the duration of
             follow-up

        Key Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any subject with the following screening lab values (per the Food and Drug Association
             (FDA) Guidance: Toxicity Grading Scale for Healthy Adult and Adolescent Volunteers
             Enrolled in Preventive Vaccine Clinical Trials):

               1. Any ≥ Grade 2 abnormality

               2. Clinically significant Grade 1 abnormality as judged by the Principal
                  Investigator or

               3. Clinically non-significant Grade 1 abnormality as judged by the Principal
                  Investigator which, upon repeat testing becomes more abnormal

          -  History or clinical manifestation of clinically significant health conditions
             including but not limited to: mental illness, active hematological, renal, hepatic,
             pulmonary, central nervous, neurological, cardiovascular, endocrine (including
             diabetes mellitus) or gastrointestinal disorders

          -  Acute febrile illness within 72 hours prior to vaccination, defined as the presence of
             a moderate or severe illness with or without fever (as determined by the Investigator
             through medical history and physical examination), or presence of a fever &gt;38ºC
             orally.

          -  Any confirmed or suspected immunosuppressive or immunodeficient state including:
             asplenia, recurrent severe infections and chronic (more than 14 days)
             immunosuppressant medication

          -  Living in the same household with any person with a non-functional or suppressed
             immune system
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Renee Herber</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>FluGen Inc</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carlos Fierro, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Johnson County Clin Trials</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>JCCT</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lenexa</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <zip>66219</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 27, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 29, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 4, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 31, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 31, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Publications and post to site</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

