<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02824640</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2015-5723</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02824640</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Patient-Centered Models of HCV Care for People Who Inject Drugs</brief_title>
  <acronym>HERO</acronym>
  <official_title>Patient-Centered Models of HCV Care for People Who Inject Drugs</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Alain Litwin</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      People who inject drugs (PWID) have higher rates of hepatitis C virus (HCV) than do other
      groups. Effective, safe new treatments called direct-acting antiviral agents (DAAs) have been
      developed recently. Unfortunately, PWID rarely get these treatments. The drugs are expensive,
      so insurers often do not cover the cost of DAAs. Sometimes providers hesitate to prescribe
      DAAs because they are concerned that PWID won't take their medication or that these patients
      might become reinfected.

      Several good models for treating PWID exist. One of them is to provide directly observed
      treatment (DOT). Another model provides treatment to PWID with the support of patient
      navigators (PN), public health workers who offer support and education to patients. Though
      both the DOT and PN models have been successful, we still don't know which model works best.

      In this study, the investigators will study both DOT and PN models for treating HCV in PWID.
      The investigators' goal is to find out which model produces the best results and is preferred
      by patients. Up to 1,000 HCV-infected PWID will participate in the study in eight sites
      around the country. Patients will be randomized into either the PN or the DOT groups.
      Patients who end up in the PN group will get a biweekly blister pack of medication to take
      home. Their PN will provide education and support. The investigators will find out whether
      patients adhered to medication using an electronic adherence monitoring system. Patients who
      are randomly assigned to the DOT group will take their medication in front of a staff member.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a multi-site national study (8 U.S. cities), where up to 1000 HCV-infected PWIDs
      (injecting illicit substances within the last 3 months) will be randomized to either PN plus
      biweekly blister pack dispensation versus mDOT. Among patients who go on to initiate HCV
      treatment (n=600 targeted) with a once-daily combination regimen, a comparison will be
      conducted of the proportion of patients in each arm who: (a) optimally adhere (&gt;=80%), (b)
      complete treatment, (c) achieve SVR, and (d) develop resistance. The primary outcome will be
      SVR. The 8 sites offer geographic and policy diversity: New York City, Baltimore, Providence,
      Boston, Morgantown, Seattle, San Francisco, and Albuquerque.

      Participants will be recruited from diverse venues: OAT clinics, community health centers,
      syringe exchange programs, community-based organizations, homeless programs, and cohorts
      established by research studies. The clinical sites will determine eligibility based on
      clinical records, or on-site testing including for HCV tests (anti-HCV and HCV viremia) and
      drug toxicology testing as needed. Study participants will be screened, consented and
      enrolled on-site at OAT and non-OAT clinic settings.

      Patients will be randomized to one of two models of care: patient navigation (PN) vs.
      modified directly observed treatment (mDOT). Patients enrolled from OAT clinics who are
      receiving methadone and randomized to mDOT will receive doses of once daily medication at the
      same time as they receive methadone. Patients enrolled from community health settings and
      randomized to mDOT may receive observed doses in a range of settings including: at their
      clinic, at home, a community site (e.g. at a coffee shop or other gathering place), or using
      a mobile health app on a smartphone. Subjects randomized to PN will receive a standardized PN
      intervention and additional support through a peer-led support group.

      Participants will be followed for up to 140 weeks: 12 weeks of pre-treatment evaluation, 12
      weeks of treatment, 12 weeks of follow-up to determine SVR12, and 104 weeks of follow-up to
      determine long-term SVR and reinfection. Data sources will include clinical lab and imaging
      results from medical records, blood tests (HCV viral load during long-term follow-up and
      resistance assays), urine toxicology, questionnaires, electronic monitors for assessing
      adherence, and interview.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sustained Viral Response (SVR)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks after treatment completion</time_frame>
    <description>HCV viral load undetectable 12 weeks after treatment completion.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>HCV Treatment Initiation</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 12 weeks after study enrollment</time_frame>
    <description>(Yes/No). Subject who receive at least one dose of HCV medication (sofosbuvir + velpatasvir) will be considered to have initiated HCV treatment. Those who do not receive one dose within 12 weeks of study enrollment will have been considered not to have initiated HCV treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence (by electronic monitors)</measure>
    <time_frame>During 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Adherence will be measured by electronic blister packs. Adherence will also be measured by pill counts and self-report..</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Treatment Completion measured by the # of weeks of treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>After 12 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>(Yes/No) Patients who received HCV treatment for 12 out of 12 planned treatment weeks will be considered to have completed treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resistance (to NS5A)</measure>
    <time_frame>At weeks 12 or 24</time_frame>
    <description>NS5A resistance by Monogram assays.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Resistance (to NS5B)</measure>
    <time_frame>At weeks 12 or 24</time_frame>
    <description>NS5B resistance by Monogram assays</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis C</condition>
  <condition>Medication Adherence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Navigation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>The study will follow a PN model (Check Hep C) developed by NYCDOH in collaboration with Montefiore and the community. HCV PNs will provide the following interventions to those randomized to the PN arm: coordination of HCV treatment; health promotion; assisting patients to overcome barriers; and psychosocial support.
Health Promotion Sessions: PNs will deliver 4 standardized health promotion sessions to all patients either individually or within a group.
Optional Weekly Support Groups: Subjects randomized to the PN arm will be offered weekly support groups led by Peers.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>modified Directly Observed Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>OAT clinic setting: Observation of HCV medications will be linked to methadone visits among patients receiving methadone. Patients will be receiving methadone as part of routine clinical care for opioid addiction and not as an intervention related to this study. The schedule of five days per week will be considered modified DOT (mDOT). Subjects will initiate HCV treatment on Mondays if feasible. Take home medications will be packed in a weekly electronic blister pack.
Community health clinic setting: This intervention is considered modified DOT (mDOT) since between 3-5 weekly doses will be directly observed. A minimum of one dose will be observed in person by clinic/study staff. For the remaining observed doses, the research staff and provider will present the participant with a menu of options and determine what will work best for that participant.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient Navigation</intervention_name>
    <description>The study will follow a PN model (Check Hep C) developed by NYCDOH in collaboration with Montefiore and the community. HCV PNs will provide the following interventions to those randomized to the PN arm: coordination of HCV treatment; health promotion; assisting patients to overcome barriers; and psychosocial support.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Navigation</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>PN</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>modified Directly Observed Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be observed taking medications, a minimum of 5 times a week for those enrolled in the OAT setting, and a minimum of 3 times a week for those enrolled in the community health clinic setting.</description>
    <arm_group_label>modified Directly Observed Therapy</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>mDOT</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  HCV infection

          -  Actively injecting drugs (any substance within 3 months)

          -  Not previously treated with HCV direct-acting antiviral medications

          -  Age 18 - 70

          -  Willing to receive HCV treatment with sofosbuvir/velpatasvir

          -  Willing to be randomized to either PN vs mDOT

          -  If receiving methadone, be attending OAT clinic a minimum of 5 times per week

          -  Able to provide informed consent

          -  English or Spanish fluency

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or breast feeding

          -  Hepatocellular carcinoma
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Alain Litwin, MD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Montefiore Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Hiral Patel, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>347-491-8687</phone>
    <email>hpatel1@montefiore.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Linda Agyemang, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>347-307-0960</phone>
    <email>lagyeman@montefiore.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Montefiore Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10472</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 23, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 1, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 7, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 1, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 1, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 7, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Albert Einstein College of Medicine, Inc.</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Alain Litwin</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Addiction</keyword>
  <keyword>Adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>Adverse Effects</keyword>
  <keyword>Direct Acting Antiviral Agent</keyword>
  <keyword>Chronic Hepatitis C</keyword>
  <keyword>Resistance Development</keyword>
  <keyword>Methadone Clinic</keyword>
  <keyword>Primary Care</keyword>
  <keyword>Directly Observed Therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>Randomized Controlled Trial</keyword>
  <keyword>Resistance</keyword>
  <keyword>Reinfection</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment Outcome</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient Navigation</keyword>
  <keyword>Multi-Site</keyword>
  <keyword>Liver Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Sustained Viral Response</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methadone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

