<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02821494</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HPV16HH01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02821494</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hespecta Vaccination in HPV+ Tumors or Malignant Lesions</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase I Study: to Determine the Biological Activity of Two HPV16 E6 Specific Peptides Coupled to Amplivant®, a Toll-like Receptor Ligand in Patients Treated for HPV16-positive Tumors or Premalignant Lesions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Leiden University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ISA Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dutch Cancer Society</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Top Institute Pharma</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Leiden University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A phase I study to establish the highest safe dose that induces HPV16 E6-specific T-cell
      responses, using the highly promising novel therapeutic vaccine concept named: Hespecta (HPV
      E Six Peptide Conjugated To Amplivant®) to induce HPV16 E6-specific T-cell responses.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Human papillomavirus (HPV) has been found to be associated with several types of premalignant
      lesions and cancer. HPV16 is the far most common HPV type detected in these tumors and
      premalignant lesions. HPV16 encodes the two tumor-specific oncoproteins E6 and E7. In most
      humans the virus is cleared. However, in some individuals, infection results in an
      uncontrolled persistent HPV16 infection that due to expression of the viral oncoproteins E6
      and E7 may lead to the formation of malignancies. Moreover, these oncoproteins maintain the
      malignant state of the transformed cells. The virus-specific interferon-γ (IFNγ)-producing
      cluster of differentiation 4 (CD4+) helper T cells (Th1 cells) and cluster of differentiation
      8 (CD8+) cytotoxic T-lymphocytes (CTL) are able to recognize peptides processed from the
      highly immunogenic E6 and play a critical role in the elimination and/or control of the
      virus. Studies in patients with HPV associated tumors showed that the spontaneous
      HPV-specific T-cell responses, are weak and fail to sufficiently control tumor outgrowth.
      Preexisting specific T-cell responses against E6 and E7 in patients with HPV related tumors
      such are associated with better outcome after treatment. Since the HPV16-transformed tumor
      cells constitutively express the two HPV16 encoded E6 and E7 oncoproteins, these viral
      antigens are considered to be excellent targets for immunotherapeutic vaccine strategies
      aiming at reinforcing the tumor-specific T-cell response. Previous vaccination studies showed
      that the use of our first generation HPV16 synthetic long peptides vaccine (HPV16-SLP) was
      safe and highly immunogenic in patients with HPV-induced ano-genital lesions. Vaccination of
      patients with cervical cancer (CxCa) also resulted in the induction of HPV16-specific T-cell
      responses but the nature and strength of the induced T cell responses was not sufficient for
      the regression of these tumors. Specifically, it was concluded that the polarization of the T
      cell response to Th1 (IFNγ-response) was not optimal and a much stronger CD8+ T cell response
      was required for clinical efficacy. These results initiated the development of new HPV16
      vaccination strategies that are able to polarize the induced Th1 response and obtain strong
      CD8+ T-cell cytotoxicity. One of these developments consists of conjugating two of the HPV16
      E6 SLP to Amplivant® a synthetic Toll-like receptor (TLR) 2 ligand. These two peptides cover
      the most immunodominant regions of the overlapping HPV16-SLP set and contain both Th and CTL
      epitopes. Peptide conjugated Amplivant® has been selected because it is acknowledged for its
      capacity to strongly enhance antigen presentation by dendritic cells (DCs), enhance T-cell
      priming and cause superior induction of effective anti-tumor CTL responses in mouse tumor
      models, compared to a mixture of free TLR ligand and peptide. In preclinical murine studies,
      Amplivant®-conjugated SLP showed 10 to 100 times higher bioactivity compared to unconjugated
      SLP, in terms of induced immune responses. In addition, the quantity and quality of human
      T-cell responses, and especially the HPV16-specific CD8+ T-cell response, in cancer patients
      could be markedly enhanced by ex vivo stimulation with Amplivant®-conjugated SLPs.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Biological activity of Hespecta</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Blood samples will be drawn and used in an array of complementary immunological assays to assess the biological activity of Hespecta. Vaccine induced immunity in the different assays is defined if the response after vaccination is at least 3-fold higher than the pre-vaccination response.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events (AE) according to Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Safety</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Tumors or Premalignant Lesions</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Hespecta</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Four dose groups of Hespecta</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hespecta</intervention_name>
    <description>A dose escalation of Amplivant® conjugated peptide</description>
    <arm_group_label>Hespecta</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>HPV 16 E6 synthetic peptides (E6 71-95 and E6 127-158)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically documented evidence of HPV16 positive (pre)malignant lesion following
             standard treatment

          2. Patient with a tumor should have no evidence of residual disease based on physical
             examination at the completion of curative intent therapy

          3. At least four weeks and less than twelve weeks after last anti-tumor treatment

          4. Willing and able to comply with the protocol and to provide informed consent in
             accordance with institutional and regulatory guidelines

          5. Patients must be 18 years or older.

          6. Patients of child-bearing potential should test negative using a serum pregnancy test
             and agree to utilize effective contraception during the entire treatment and follow-up
             period of the study (up to 2 months after the last vaccination)

          7. Patients must be in good general health and ambulatory, with an Eastern Cooperative
             Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status of 0 or 1

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Radiotherapy, chemotherapy or other potentially immunosuppressive therapy administered
             within 4 weeks prior to the enrolment visit

          2. History of an autoimmune disease or other systemic intercurrent disease that might
             affect the immunocompetence of the patient, or patients receiving immunosuppressive
             therapy, except for topical application

          3. History of a second malignancy except curatively treated low-stage tumors with a
             histology that can be differentiated from the current tumor or premalignant lesion

          4. Receipt of another investigational product within the previous 4 weeks or at any time
             during the study period.

          5. Receipt of prior HPV directed immunotherapy

          6. Hematology and biochemistry:

               -  Absolute Neutrophil Count (ANC) &lt; 1.5 x 109/L, or platelet count &lt; 100 x 109/L or
                  hemoglobin &lt; 6 mmol/L.

               -  Serum (total) bilirubin &gt; 2 x upper normal limit (ULN);

               -  Aspartate Aminotransferase (ASAT) or Alanine Aminotransferase (ALAT) &gt; 2.5 x ULN;

               -  Alkaline phosphatase levels &gt; 2.5 x ULN;

               -  Serum creatinine &gt; ULN or calculated clearance &lt;/= 40 mL/min/1.73 m2 for patients
                  with serum creatinine levels above the institutional normal value

          7. Human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), chronic hepatitis B or C infection.

          8. Any condition that in the opinion of the investigator could interfere with the conduct
             of the study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>H. Gelderblom, Prof.dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Leiden University Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Frank Speetjens, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+31715263486</phone>
    <email>f.m.speetjens@lumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Leiden University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Leiden</city>
        <zip>2333 ZA</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>H. Gelderblom, Prof.dr.</last_name>
      <phone>+31715263486</phone>
      <email>a.j.gelderblom@lumc.nl</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 2, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 30, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 1, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 9, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 9, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 12, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Leiden University Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>HansGelderblom</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HPV</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaccination</keyword>
  <keyword>Immunotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Precancerous Conditions</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

