<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02828098</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>112/2016-IT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02828098</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exploratory Study of BO-112 in Adult Patients With Aggressive Solid Tumors</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Exploratory First in Human Phase I Clinical and Pharmacokinetic Study of Intra-tumoral Administration of BO-112 in Adult Patients With Aggressive Solid Tumors, With an Extension Cohort in Combination With Anti-PD1 Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bioncotech Therapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bioncotech Therapeutics</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Part 1: 16 to 32 patients with aggressive solid tumors from whom biopsies can be obtained,
      will receive BO-112 through IT administration.

      Injected lesions must be palpable and biopsiable at the time of injection, and biopsied after
      7-14 days. Patients will not receive an alternative therapy during the period comprising from
      first and second biopsy. BO-112 will be administered at a starting dose. Upon confirmation of
      the safety profile of the starting dose and evaluation of the pharmacokinetic (PK) profile,
      three additional dose levels are expected to be tested.

      During the course of the study, subjects will be examined for any side effects that may occur
      (safety and tolerability).

      Additionally this study will also study BO-112 biological activity, the innate and adaptive
      immune system response and signaling pathways, as well as signs of clinical relevance, will
      be studied.

      Part 2: An additional 12 patients with progressive disease while on anti-PD1 treatment for an
      approved indication, will receive BO-112 through IT administration in combination with the
      anti-PD1 treatment to evaluate the safety and tolerability of the combination.

      Injected lesions must be palpable and biopsiable at the time of injection. Patients will
      continue with their anti-PD1 treatment. During the course of the study, patients will be
      examined for any side effects that may occur (safety and tolerability).

      Additionally this part of the trial will also study BO-112 biological activity, the innate
      and adaptive immune system response and signaling pathways, as well as signs of clinical
      response
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of subjects with adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Part 1: Day 30 after administration of the last dose. Part 2: 12 weeks and for patients who continue up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of B0-112 in terms of adverse events at every visit</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Circulating cytokines including type I IFNs, TNFalpha and IL6 (by ELISA)</measure>
    <time_frame>Part 1: At three independent points during the study. Day 7-1 prior to administration, 24 hours after administration and 7-14 days after administration of the agent. Part 2: 12 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma levels of BO-112</measure>
    <time_frame>Part 1: 0-15-30-240 minutes and 24 hours after administration of the drug. Part 2: 1 day</time_frame>
    <description>To characterize the pharmacokinetics (PK) of BO-112 by measuring the amount in plasma at regular timepoints during the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-tumor activity</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks and for patients who continue up to 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Part 2 only: To evaluate the antitumor activity of the combination of BO-112 and anti-PD1 treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: BO-112 IT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>BO-112 dose 1 (starting dose) intratumoral injection. BO-112 dose 2, 3 and 4 are expected to be tested, upon confirmation of the safety profile of the starting dose.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: BO-112 IT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Combination treatment of BO-112 intratumoral injections with standard of care nivolumab intravenous treatment
Or Combination treatment of BO-112 intratumoral injections with standard of care pembrolizumab intravenous treatment</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Part 1: BO-112</intervention_name>
    <description>Cohorts of three patients per dose level will be treated consecutively in the absence of Dose Limiting Toxicity (DLT).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 1: BO-112 IT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Part 2: BO-112</intervention_name>
    <description>BO-112 at a fixed dose will be administered as an intratumoral injection for up to 5 doses over 12 weeks, or up to 7 doses over 24 weeks.
Nivolumab will be administered as an intravenous infusion every 2 weeks at a dose of 3 mg/kg for up to a total period of one year.
OR Pembrolizumab will be administered as an intravenous infusion every 3 weeks at either 200 mg or at 2 mg/kg depending on the indication, for up to a total period of one year.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Part 2: BO-112 IT</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>anti-PD1 monoclonal antibody</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Patients age 18 years or more on the day of signing informed consent form.

          2. Histologically or cytologically confirmed aggressive solid tumors

          3. Patients must have:

               -  Biopsy-accessible tumors

               -  No prior anticancer treatment during the last 14 days

        Additional inclusion criteria for Part 2: disease progression on treatment with anti-PD1
        antibody for an approved indication

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Other relevant and clinically significant concomitant diseases or adverse clinical
        conditions which may jeopardize patient safety:

          -  Increased cardiac risk: congestive heart failure; or unstable angina pectoris; or
             arrhythmia requiring treatment or uncontrolled arterial hypertension; or myocardial
             infarction within 12 months before inclusion in the study.

          -  Patients with active central nervous system (CNS) lesions (including carcinomatous
             meningitis) will be excluded. However, patients will be eligible if:

               -  All known CNS lesions have been treated with stereotactic therapy or surgery, AND

               -  There has been no evidence of clinical and radiographic disease progression in
                  the CNS for ≥ 4 weeks after radiotherapy or surgery, and has not required to
                  increase in the last 4 weeks their steroids use or has not started a new course
                  of steroids

               -  Whole brain radiotherapy is not allowed, with the exception of patients who have
                  had definitive resection or stereotactic therapy of all radiologically detectable
                  parenchymal brain lesions.

          -  Active infection.

          -  Significant non-neoplastic liver disease (e.g., cirrhosis, active chronic hepatitis B
             or C).

          -  Any clinically significant abnormality on history or examination including diagnosis
             of immunodeficiency or receiving systemic steroid therapy or any other form of
             immunosuppressive therapy within 7 days prior to the first dose of study medication
             (physiologic doses of corticosteroids may be approved after consultation with the
             Sponsor).

        Additional exclusion criteria for Part 2: Grade 3-4 toxicity due to anti-PD1 antibody or
        permanent discontinuation of anti-PD1 antibody due to immune related or other adverse
        reaction.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Marisol Quintero</last_name>
    <email>mquintero@bioncotech.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clínica Universitaria Navarra</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pamplona</city>
        <state>Navarra</state>
        <zip>31008</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Clinica Universidad de Navarra</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañón</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28007</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Hospital General Universitario Gregorio Marañón</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 23, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 6, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 11, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 12, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 12, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>aggressive solid tumors</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aggression</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

