<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02820701</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>160616-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02820701</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Ultrasound Evaluation of OMT for Sacral Base Asymmetry</brief_title>
  <official_title>Ultrasound Evaluation of the Effect of Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment on Sacral Base Asymmetry</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>A.T. Still University of Health Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>A.T. Still University of Health Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This prospective, randomized, controlled trial is proposed to investigate the effect of OMT
      on sacral base asymmetry as assessed by ultrasound.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The proposed prospective, randomized, controlled trial will investigate the effect of
      osteopathic manipulative treatment (OMT) on sacral base asymmetry as assessed by ultrasound.
      The study will be conducted between July 2016 - June 2017 with data collection planned for
      August and September 2016. Forty men and women ages 20 to 55 years with at least one or more
      episodes of LBP in the past two weeks will be recruited from the Kirksville area.
      Participants will be randomly assigned into two groups, control or OMT using a random number
      generator. Males and females will be randomized separately to ensure equal distribution into
      the two study groups. Demographics including sex, age, and body mass index (BMI) will be
      collected on all participants. All participants will complete a brief medical history
      questionnaire, receive an initial palpatory assessment of the sacral base asymmetry, and then
      an initial ultrasound evaluation of sacral base asymmetry. After the ultrasound assessment,
      the control group will wait in another room for approximately 30 minutes. Participants in the
      OMT group will receive OMT to address sacral base asymmetry after the initial ultrasound
      assessment. Following the treatment period for the OMT group, all participants will receive a
      second ultrasound assessment of sacral base asymmetry. The ultrasonographer will be blinded
      on whether the subject received an OMT or not. After the second ultrasound measurement, the
      participants in the control group will be offered an OMT treatment consistent with that of
      the OMT group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Sacral Base Asymmetry with OMT</measure>
    <time_frame>Immediately pre and post treatment - approximately 30 minutes between measurements</time_frame>
    <description>Determine the extent to which OMT affects the relative asymmetry between the pelvic and sacral landmarks as measured by ultrasonography when compared to control group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in Sacral Base Asymmetry without OMT</measure>
    <time_frame>30 minutes between measurements</time_frame>
    <description>Determine if ultrasound measurements of sacral landmarks are stable over 30 minutes in untreated (control) participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Agreement between palpatory and ultrasound measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 10 mins between palpatory and ultrasound measurements</time_frame>
    <description>Determine if ultrasound measurements of sacral base asymmetry agree with palpatory assessment.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Manipulation, Osteopathic</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will receive an initial palpatory assessment of the sacral base asymmetry and then an initial ultrasound evaluation of sacral base asymmetry. After the ultrasound assessment, the control group will wait in another room for approximately 30 minutes.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All participants will receive an initial palpatory assessment of the sacral base asymmetry and then an initial ultrasound evaluation of sacral base asymmetry. Participants in the Treatment group will receive OMT to address sacral base asymmetry after the initial ultrasound assessment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OMT</intervention_name>
    <description>Osteopathic Manipulative Treatment to low back region</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Must have experienced at least one or more episodes of LBP in the past two weeks Must be
        able to lie prone for 30 minutes Must be able to tolerate OMT -

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Prior spinal surgery Fractures Known congenital anomalies of the lumbar vertebra and sacrum
        Cannot lie prone for 30 minutes Cannot tolerate OMT
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen T Snider, DO, FAAO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>A.T. Still University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>A.T. Still University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kirksville</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63501</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lockwood MD, Kondrashova T, Johnson JC. Feasibility of Using Ultrasonography to Establish Relationships Among Sacral Base Position, Sacral Sulcus Depth, Body Mass Index, and Sex. J Am Osteopath Assoc. 2015 Nov;115(11):648-53. doi: 10.7556/jaoa.2015.135.</citation>
    <PMID>26501757</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 29, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 29, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 1, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 14, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 14, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 15, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Osteopathic Manipulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Somatic Dysfunction</keyword>
  <keyword>Musculoskeletal Ultrasound</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>May 1, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

