<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02822937</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Akili-027</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02822937</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Sensitivity of Project: EVO Monitor Cognitive Measurements to Pharmacological Agents</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Study to Assess the Sensitivity of Project: EVO Monitor Cognitive Function Measurements to Methylphenidate and Triazolam in Adults 40-55 Years Old</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Akili Interactive Labs, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Akili Interactive Labs, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a study in adults to assess the sensitivity of Project: EVO Monitor cognitive
      measurements to two short-acting cognitively active pharmacological agents. The participants
      will receive a placebo, and two pharmacological agents in a randomized order for three
      in-clinic study days. During each study day in the clinic, the participants will use Project:
      EVO Monitor and another cognitive task through the day.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a study in adults ages 40 to 55 to assess the sensitivity of Project: EVO Monitor
      cognitive measurements to two short-acting cognitively active pharmacological agents,
      methylphenidate (MPH) and triazolam (TRZ). The participants will receive a placebo, MPH, and
      TRZ in a randomized order for three in-clinic study days. All drug administration and
      cognitive testing will take place in the clinic under medical staff supervision. During each
      study day in the clinic, the participants will use Project: EVO Monitor and do a short digit
      symbol substitution task (DSST) 8 times over the day. A minimum of 48 hours will be needed
      between each study day. The investigators plan to evaluate 18 participants in this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-subject sensitivity of Project: EVO cognitive measurements (threshold based) to a cognitive enhancer or a cognitive disruptor at peak drug effects relative to placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements taken 120 min post drug with a comparison between 3 clinic visits (each with different drug) over 2 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-subject sensitivity of Project: EVO cognitive measurements (reaction time based) to a cognitive enhancer or a cognitive disruptor at peak drug effects relative to placebo</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements taken 120 min post drug with a comparison between 3 clinic visits (each with different drug) over 2 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-subject sensitivity of Project: EVO cognitive measurements (threshold based) to the cognitive enhancer and cognitive disruptor relative to the placebo measurements using the area-under-the-curve (AUC) analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements taken predose and 30, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180, and 240 min post drug with a comparison between 3 clinic visits (each with different drug) over 2 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-subject sensitivity of Project: EVO cognitive measurements (reaction time based) to the cognitive enhancer and cognitive disruptor relative to the placebo measurements using the area-under-the-curve (AUC) analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements taken predose and 30, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180, and 240 min post drug with a comparison between 3 clinic visits (each with different drug) over 2 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-subject sensitivity to Project: EVO cognitive measurements (threshold based) with the onset and decline of the predicted drug effects over the study day, using a quadratic regression model</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements taken predose and 30, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180, and 240 min post drug with a comparison between 3 clinic visits (each with different drug) over 2 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intra-subject sensitivity to Project: EVO cognitive measurements (reaction time based) with the onset and decline of the predicted drug effects over the study day, using a quadratic regression model</measure>
    <time_frame>Measurements taken predose and 30, 60, 90, 120, 150, 180, and 240 min post drug with a comparison between 3 clinic visits (each with different drug) over 2 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>6</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">18</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo, Methylphenidate, Triazolam</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The participants will receive placebo on the first day, 40mg Methylphenidate on the second day, and 0.375mg Triazolam on the third day. All drug administration and cognitive measurement will take place in the clinic under medical staff supervision. During each study day in the clinic, the participants will use Project: EVO Monitor and do a short digit symbol substitution task (DSST) 8 times over the day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo, Triazolam, Methylphenidate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The participants will receive placebo on the first day, 0.375mg Triazolam on the second day, and 40mg Methylphenidate on the third day. All drug administration and cognitive measurement will take place in the clinic under medical staff supervision. During each study day in the clinic, the participants will use Project: EVO Monitor and do a short digit symbol substitution task (DSST) 8 times over the day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Methylphenidate, Placebo, Triazolam</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The participants will receive 40mg Methylphenidate on the first day, placebo on the second day, and 0.375mg Triazolam on the third day. All drug administration and cognitive measurement will take place in the clinic under medical staff supervision. During each study day in the clinic, the participants will use Project: EVO Monitor and do a short digit symbol substitution task (DSST) 8 times over the day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Methylphenidate, Triazolam, Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The participants will receive 40mg Methylphenidate on the first day, 0.375mg Triazolam on the second day, and placebo on the third day. All drug administration and cognitive measurement will take place in the clinic under medical staff supervision. During each study day in the clinic, the participants will use Project: EVO Monitor and do a short digit symbol substitution task (DSST) 8 times over the day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Triazolam, Placebo, Methylphenidate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The participants will receive 0.375mg Triazolam on the first day, placebo on the second day, and 40mg Methylphenidate on the third day. All drug administration and cognitive measurement will take place in the clinic under medical staff supervision. During each study day in the clinic, the participants will use Project: EVO Monitor and do a short digit symbol substitution task (DSST) 8 times over the day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Triazolam, Methylphenidate, Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The participants will receive 0.375mg Triazolam on the first day, 40mg Methylphenidate on the second day, and placebo on the third day. All drug administration and cognitive measurement will take place in the clinic under medical staff supervision. During each study day in the clinic, the participants will use Project: EVO Monitor and do a short digit symbol substitution task (DSST) 8 times over the day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methylphenidate</intervention_name>
    <description>Methylphenidate is a central nervous system stimulant. It affects chemicals in the brain and nerves that contribute to hyperactivity and impulse control. Methylphenidate is used to treat attention deficit disorder (ADD), attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD), and narcolepsy.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo, Methylphenidate, Triazolam</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo, Triazolam, Methylphenidate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Methylphenidate, Placebo, Triazolam</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Methylphenidate, Triazolam, Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Triazolam, Placebo, Methylphenidate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Triazolam, Methylphenidate, Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Ritalin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Triazolam</intervention_name>
    <description>Triazolam is a benzodiazepine similar to Valium. Triazolam affects chemicals in the brain that may become unbalanced and cause sleep problems (insomnia). Triazolam is used to treat insomnia (trouble falling or staying asleep).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo, Methylphenidate, Triazolam</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo, Triazolam, Methylphenidate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Methylphenidate, Placebo, Triazolam</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Methylphenidate, Triazolam, Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Triazolam, Placebo, Methylphenidate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Triazolam, Methylphenidate, Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Halcion</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Project: EVO</intervention_name>
    <description>Project: EVO Monitor was designed to incorporate a proprietary multi-tasking assessment into a state-of-the-art mobile video game-like platform, which deploys modern videogame graphics, engaging reward loops, and real-time adaptive mechanics to dynamically personalize difficulty in order to assess the user's ability.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo, Methylphenidate, Triazolam</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo, Triazolam, Methylphenidate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Methylphenidate, Placebo, Triazolam</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Methylphenidate, Triazolam, Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Triazolam, Placebo, Methylphenidate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Triazolam, Methylphenidate, Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Cognitive Monitor</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Sugar pill</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo, Methylphenidate, Triazolam</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo, Triazolam, Methylphenidate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Methylphenidate, Placebo, Triazolam</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Methylphenidate, Triazolam, Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Triazolam, Placebo, Methylphenidate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Triazolam, Methylphenidate, Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Sugar Pill</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age 40-55 at the time of informed consent

          2. Ability to follow written and verbal instructions (English).

          3. Weight between 140 lbs and 240 lbs.

          4. Male and female (Gender-matched).

          5. Ability to comply with all the testing and requirements.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Known adverse reaction to study medications.

          2. Known non-response or paradoxical response to study medications.

          3. Current, controlled (requiring a restricted medication) or uncontrolled, self-reported
             psychiatric diagnosis with significant symptoms such as post-traumatic stress
             disorder, psychosis, bipolar illness, pervasive developmental disorder, severe
             obsessive compulsive disorder, severe depressive or anxiety disorder, conduct
             disorder, attention deficit disorder, autism spectrum disorder, or other symptomatic
             manifestations that in the opinion of the Investigator that may confound study
             data/assessments.

          4. Current self-reported community diagnosis of cognitive ailments such as dementia,
             Alzheimer's disease, stroke, traumatic brain injury, or other diseases that in the
             opinion of the Investigator that may confound study data/assessments.

          5. Current diagnosis of severe learning disorder, dyslexia, or dyscalculia.

          6. Current subjective complaints of inattention or memory loss.

          7. Currently undergoing psychotherapy, behavioral therapy, or occupational therapy.

          8. Current use of psychotropic medication, prescription or otherwise.

          9. Motor condition that prevents game playing, as reported by parent or observed by
             investigator.

         10. Impaired visual acuity, as defined by difficulty reading the informed consent even
             with corrective lenses.

         11. Lifetime history of suspected substance abuse or dependence.

         12. Current use (defined as within the last 30 days) of products with nicotine, e.g.
             cigarettes, chewing tobacco, e-cigarettes, nicotine patch, and nicotine gum.

         13. History of seizures (exclusive of febrile seizures), a tic disorder, significant tics,
             a current diagnosis of Tourette's Disorder.

         14. Taken part in a clinical trial within 30 days prior to screening.

         15. Diagnosis of or patient-reported color blindness.

         16. Regular use of psychoactive drugs that in the opinion of the Investigator may confound
             study data/assessments.

         17. Pregnancy.

         18. Currently nursing or breastfeeding.

         19. Resting heart rate &gt; 100 beats/min.

         20. Systolic blood pressure &gt; 150 mm/Hg.

         21. History of cardiac abnormalities.

         22. History of glaucoma.

         23. Current use of monoamine oxidase inhibitors, HIV protease inhibitors, ranitidine,
             isoniazid, ketoconazole, itraconazole, nefazodone and other azole-type antifungal
             agents or any other drugs that are contra-indicated for use with study medications.

         24. Any other medical condition that in the opinion of the investigator may confound study
             data/assessments.

         25. Any other medical condition that in the opinion of the investigator prohibits the
             administration of any study medication.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ted Riley</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>ProMedica International</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinical Trials of Texas</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 2, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 5, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 6, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 3, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 3, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 7, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methylphenidate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Triazolam</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

