<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02827812</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1_neuro_veruno</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02827812</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Telemedicine Program in Parkinson's Disease (TELEPARK)</brief_title>
  <acronym>TELEPARK</acronym>
  <official_title>Home-Based Telesurveillance and Rehabilitation Program in Parkinson's Disease: Pilot Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fondazione Salvatore Maugeri</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fondazione Salvatore Maugeri</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Parkinson's disease (PD) is a chronic neurodegenerative disease due to the loss of
      dopaminergic neurons in the substantia nigra, leading to motor symptoms of tremor, rigidity,
      and bradykinesia, as well as an array of non-motor symptoms that affect cognition, sleep,
      behaviour, and the autonomic nervous system.

      Lifelong rehabilitation measures, along with medication treatment, are the major components
      of patient management. Physical exercises positively affect patients' quality of life (QOL)
      and their functional capacities. Poor adherence to rehabilitation, limited patient education,
      and access to specialized care can be barriers to treatment. A number of papers in fact
      report that telemedicine is an acceptable means of care delivery reduces travel burdens and
      may improve patient outcomes. However, most of these studies were not randomized or
      controlled and did not include nursing home patients, who may benefit the most from specialty
      care.

      Moreover, there is no evidence supporting the use of telerehabilitation for physical
      assessments of people with PD. For this reason investigators hypothesize that a home
      telerehabilitation system guiding patients in following their exercise program combined with
      a computerized decision-support tool monitoring patient performance, would be feasible for
      and acceptable to patients with PD and would improve functional status.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Aim of the study:

        1. Demonstrate the feasibility of at home telesurveillance and rehabilitation program

        2. Demonstrate the effectiveness of the program in improving quality of life and functional
           aspects in patients affected by Parkinson's disease

      30 patients affected by Parkinson's disease (PD), will be consecutively screened. The method
      of sequence generation relied on a computerized random number generator. The person who
      allocated patients to the two groups was not involved either in treatment or in evaluation of
      the patients.

      The study was submitted for approval of the Central Ethics Review Board. Participants will be
      randomly assigned to two different groups of training using a random number table to receive
      either telemedicine care (PTE) or their usual care (PUC).

      All the patients will receive in our Institute a comprehensive baseline evaluation conducted
      by both the neurologist and the physical therapist specialized in the treatment of PD.

      During the baseline evaluation (T0), both PTE and PUC will perform two supervised
      familiarization sessions using the same training protocol to be used once at home.

      Caregivers are an essential part in the PD patients' home management and rehabilitation and
      they therefore will be involved in all educational stages.

      Each patient of both groups will receive two types of physical intervention:

        1. A traditional custom-tailored rehabilitative exercise program; he will be trained by the
           therapist on how to perform the exercises. These exercises will include functional
           strengthening, stretching, postural changes and balance activities

        2. An aerobic training All patients will be asked to perform these exercises for 60 minutes
           3 days/week for three months.

      The training phase will last 20 minutes during the first month and 30 minutes over the second
      and third month; Training intensity could be progressively increased over the three months of
      intervention, Aerobic training familiarization sessions will be performed on the same
      ergometer they will receive for home-based training.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of participants in the PTE group who will concluded the home-based program.</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>The program is feasible if at least 80% of participants in the PTE group complete the home program lasting 3 months. The participant completes the home program if carries out at least 50% of the prescribed physical activity.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of quality of life (QoL) measured by the &quot;Parkinson's disease questionnaire&quot; (PDQ-39)</measure>
    <time_frame>Difference between two groups of PDQ-39 measured at baseline (T0) and after 3 months (T1)</time_frame>
    <description>The PDQ consider eight discrete scales on mobility (10 items), activities of daily living (6 items), emotional well-being (6 items), stigma (4 items), social support (3 items), cognitions (4 items), communication (3 items) and bodily discomfort (3 items). Participants are asked to indicate the frequency of each event by selecting one of 5 options (from never to always). Each dimension total score range from 0 (never have difficulty) to 100 (always have difficulty). Lower scores reflect better QoL</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of exercise tolerance capacity measured in the meters walked, by the 6-min walk test (6MWT)</measure>
    <time_frame>Difference between two groups of 6MWT measured at baseline (T0) and after 3 months (T1)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvement of balance measured by Balance Evaluation Systems Test (Mini BesTest)</measure>
    <time_frame>Difference between two groups of Mini BesTest measured at baseline (T0) and after 3 months (T1)</time_frame>
    <description>The Mini-BESTest includes 14 items representing four domains of dynamic balance:anticipatory postural adjustments (items 1-3), postural responses (items 4-6), sensory orientation (items 7-9) and balance during gait (items 10-14). The Mini-BESTest items are rated on a 3-point scale from 0 to 2 and the total score ranges from 0 to 28 with a higher score indicating better balance performance.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Parkinson's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Participants Telemedicine Care (PTE)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A. Comprehensive evaluation at baseline (T0) and at the end of the study (T1).
B. Physical Intervention at home for 60 minutes 3 days/week for three months
C. Home-Based telemedicine program:</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Participants Usual Care (PUC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>A. Comprehensive evaluation at baseline (T0) and at the end of the study (T1).
B. Physical Intervention at home for 60 minutes 3 days/week for three months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Comprehensive evaluation</intervention_name>
    <description>At baseline (T0) and after 3-months (T1) all patients will be evaluated with Scales and questionnaire.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participants Telemedicine Care (PTE)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Participants Usual Care (PUC)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical Intervention at home</intervention_name>
    <description>A traditional custom-tailored rehabilitative exercise program. The exercises will include functional strengthening, stretching, postural changes and balance activities; - An aerobic training on a cycle ergometer 3 days /week for three months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participants Telemedicine Care (PTE)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Participants Usual Care (PUC)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Home-Based telemedicine program</intervention_name>
    <description>A nurse-tutor will follow patients through structured telephone appointments, collecting information about disease status and symptoms, offering advice regarding diet, lifestyle and medications and suggesting changes in therapy, according with the neurologist. The patient's clinical data and any suggestions made will be filled in a personal health electronic record.
A physiotherapist-tutor will supervise the patient's home-based individualized rehabilitation program, through scheduled videoconferences.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Participants Telemedicine Care (PTE)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  30 patients affected by Parkinson's disease (PD), according to the United Kingdom
             Parkinson's Disease Society Brain Bank Criteria (Hughes et al.,1992), will be
             consecutively screened. Participants should have a Hoehn &amp; Yahr stage between 1,5 and
             3. All subjects will be on stabilized treatment with L-dopa or dopamine agonists.

        All participants will provide written informed consent to the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  inability to participate in the exercise programs, other neurological conditions in
             addition to PD, psychiatric complications or personality disorders, musculoskeletal or
             cardiopulmonary conditions affecting mobility, and non-consent to participate in the
             study A cognitive impairment scores measured with Mini Mental State Examination (MMSE)
             ≤ 26/30.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Schwab S, Vatankhah B, Kukla C, Hauchwitz M, Bogdahn U, Fürst A, Audebert HJ, Horn M; TEMPiS Group. Long-term outcome after thrombolysis in telemedical stroke care. Neurology. 2007 Aug 28;69(9):898-903.</citation>
    <PMID>17724293</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Scalvini S, Zanelli E, Comini L, Dalla Tomba M, Troise G, Febo O, Giordano A. Home-based versus in-hospital cardiac rehabilitation after cardiac surgery: a nonrandomized controlled study. Phys Ther. 2013 Aug;93(8):1073-83. doi: 10.2522/ptj.20120212. Epub 2013 Apr 18.</citation>
    <PMID>23599353</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hubble JP, Pahwa R, Michalek DK, Thomas C, Koller WC. Interactive video conferencing: a means of providing interim care to Parkinson's disease patients. Mov Disord. 1993 Jul;8(3):380-2.</citation>
    <PMID>8341308</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Samii A, Ryan-Dykes P, Tsukuda RA, Zink C, Franks R, Nichol WP. Telemedicine for delivery of health care in Parkinson's disease. J Telemed Telecare. 2006;12(1):16-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16438773</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Biglan KM, Voss TS, Deuel LM, Miller D, Eason S, Fagnano M, George BP, Appler A, Polanowicz J, Viti L, Smith S, Joseph A, Dorsey ER. Telemedicine for the care of nursing home residents with Parkinson's disease. Mov Disord. 2009 May 15;24(7):1073-6. doi: 10.1002/mds.22498.</citation>
    <PMID>19353687</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Arcolin I, Pisano F, Delconte C, Godi M, Schieppati M, Mezzani A, Picco D, Grasso M, Nardone A. Intensive cycle ergometer training improves gait speed and endurance in patients with Parkinson's disease: A comparison with treadmill training. Restor Neurol Neurosci. 2015;34(1):125-38. doi: 10.3233/RNN-150506.</citation>
    <PMID>26684265</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 1, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 11, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 8, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 8, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 11, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Fondazione Salvatore Maugeri</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Fabrizio Pisano</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of Neurological Rehabilitation Division</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Parkinson Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

