<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02821676</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20160235-01H</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02821676</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PECI/SPB vs Intercostal Nerve Block for the Management of Postoperative Pain in Latissimus Dorsi Flap Reconstruction</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized Controlled Comparison of PECI/SPB Versus Intercostal Nerve Block for the Management of Postoperative Pain in Latissimus Dorsi Flap Reconstruction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Regional Anesthesia is a procedure in which numbing medication is injected around nerves that
      transmit pain from areas involved in a surgery. The objective is to block the nerves so a
      patient does not feel pain after surgery. Regional nerve blocks offer many advantages over
      traditional anesthetic techniques, including faster recovery time, fewer side effects and a
      dramatic reduction in post-surgical pain.

      The use of regional anesthesia in breast reconstructive surgery, such as the latissimus dorsi
      flap, has led to major improvements in patient care. Today, the most common regional
      anesthetic used in latissimus dorsi flap reconstruction is the intercostal nerve block, where
      numbing medication is injected around the nerves supplying the chest wall.

      While intercostal nerve blocks have been used successfully in breast surgery, they do not
      provide a complete nerve block to the chest wall, as there are some nerves that are
      unaccounted for in the block which can contribute to a patients pain after surgery.

      The mixed pectoral one / serratus plane block (PECI/SPB) block is another regional nerve
      block that has been successfully used by anesthesiologists at The Ottawa Hospital and offers
      a more complete pain blockade than the intercostal nerve block, as it includes more nerves
      that supply the breast. In addition to this, the intercostal nerve block is a so-called
      &quot;blind-technique&quot; compared to the PECI/SPB block, which is more accurately guided by
      ultrasound. Blind techniques are associated with higher failure rates.

      Both the intercostal nerve block and the PECI/SPB nerve block have been used successfully at
      the Ottawa Hospital. In this study, the investigators propose a prospective, double blinded,
      randomized controlled, head to head comparison of the PECI/SPB and intercostal nerve block to
      determine which block is associated with the best pain blockade and patient satisfaction in
      lattissimus dorsi flap surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Recent literature has unequivocally demonstrated that postoperative pain remains
      under-treated in hospitals. While breast surgery remains one of the most common surgeries
      performed in hospitals today, it has been shown that 40% of women still experience meaningful
      pain postoperatively. It is well known that poor pain control is not only associated with
      slower recovery, longer admission in hospital and poor patient satisfaction but it also can
      lead to the development of chronic post surgical pain.

      In recent years, regional nerve blocks have emerged as a promising adjunct to standard
      postoperative analgesic ladder protocols. The main advantage of regional anesthesia is the
      reduction of postoperative pain while limiting the amount of oral and intravenous narcotic
      use. The reduction of postoperative narcotic use is advantageous for the patient and
      caregiver alike as it reduces common side effects associated with such medications, such as
      drowsiness, nausea, vomiting, upset stomach and dizziness.

      Regional anesthesia in breast reconstruction surgery commonly include thoracic epidurals,
      intercostal nerve blocks and paravertebal nerve blocks. To date, there remains no standard of
      care for perioperative pain management and it is usually left to the discretion of the
      surgeon and anesthesiologist involved to decide which pain blockade is preferable on a case
      by case basis. While paravertebral and intercostal nerve blocks have shown promising results,
      they do not provide a complete sensory block to the anterior chest wall, as innervation is
      supplied not only from the thoracic spinal nerves but also via medial and lateral pectoral
      nerves off the brachial plexus.

      The pectoral nerve block is a novel interfascial block placed into the plane between
      pectoralis major and minor muscles and is particularly useful in reconstructive breast
      surgery involving subpectoral prosthesis. It has been associated with minimal analgesia
      postoperatively and is thought to be particularly useful in the daycare setting.

      To the best of the knowledge of the investigators, the utility of the pectoral nerve block in
      pedicled Latissimus Dorsi breast reconstruction has not been investigated. A mixed PEC I/
      Serratus Plane Block provides analgesia to the lateral and medial pectoral nerves, lateral
      and anterior branches of the T2-T4 spinal nerves, long thoracic nerve and thoracodorsal
      nerve, theoretically offering a more comprehensive block than the midaxillary intercostal
      block and with no additional morbidity to the patient. Furthermore, the intercostal nerve
      block is a blind technique that may be associated with higher failure rates compared to the
      more precise, ultrasound guided, PECI/SPB block.

      In this study, the investigators plan to systematically investigate these two blocks in
      latissimus dorsi flap reconstruction in order to document optimal postoperative pain
      management.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total 24 Hour Narcotic Usage</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>This is the most common primary outcome used in the regional anesthesia literature when comparing nerve blocks.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to first analgesic request (TFA)</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Postoperative Pain score at 0h, 1h, 3h, 5h, 24 hours</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient self reported pain score at 24 hours post-surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak expiratory flow rate</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Breast Q Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Physical and Psychological well-being questionnaire after breast reconstruction</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QoR-40 Patient Satisfaction Questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Perioperative Care Satisfaction Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">42</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>PEC1/SPB Block</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intercostal Block</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PECI/SPB Block with Active Anesthetic + Placebo Multilevel Intercostal Nerve Block followed by Latissimus Dorsi Flap Breast Reconstruction</intervention_name>
    <description>30mL of 0.5% Ropivacaine with 1:200,000 epinephrine preoperatively via an ultrasound guided PECI/SPB regional block and 5mL of Normal Saline intraoperatively as an intercostal nerve block to each of the T2-T7 nerve segments</description>
    <arm_group_label>PEC1/SPB Block</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo PEC/SPB Block + Multilevel Intercostal Nerve Block with Active Anesthetic followed by Latissimus Dorsi Flap Breast Reconstruction</intervention_name>
    <description>30mL of Normal Saline via an ultrasound guided PECI/SPB block and 5mL of 0.5% Ropivacaine with 1:200,000 epinephrine as an Intercostal nerve block to each of the T2-T7 nerve segments</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intercostal Block</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Breast Reconstruction using the Latissimus Dorsi Flap

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  All patients undergoing breast reconstruction using techniques other than the pedicled
             latissimus dorsi myocutaneous flap

          -  Preexisting diagnosis of a chronic pain disorder

          -  BMI &gt; or = to 35/kg/m2

          -  History of allergy or sensitivity to local anesthetic

          -  History of coagulopathy or bleeding disorder

          -  Weight &lt;50Kg

          -  Allergies to local anesthetic, celecoxib, acetaminophen, hydromorphone
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael J Stein, MD</last_name>
    <phone>6132864646</phone>
    <email>micstein@toh.on.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 31, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 29, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 1, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 29, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 29, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 1, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Ottawa Hospital Research Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jing Zhang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Staff Plastic Surgeon</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pain, Postoperative</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Individual participant data will not be made available. Anonymity will be maintained throughout the study.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

