<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03180242</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EGC001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03180242</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pharmacokinetic Study Comparing EG12014 and Herceptin (Trastuzumab) in Healthy Male Volunteers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 1, Double-Blind, Randomized, Parallel-Group, Single-Dose, 3-Arm, Two-Stage, Comparative Pharmacokinetic Study of EirGenix' Trastuzumab and Herceptin® (Trastuzumab) Sourced From US and EU Administered to Healthy Male Volunteers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>EirGenix, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>EirGenix, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this trial is to assess the pharmacokinetic similarity of EG12014
      (Test IMP) compared to reference products sourced from the European Union (Reference IMP 1:
      Herceptin® 150 mg powder for concentrate for solution for infusion) and the United States
      (Reference IMP 2: Herceptin® 440 mg powder for concentrate for solution for infusion) after
      intravenous infusion over 90 minutes of a single dose of 6 mg/kg trastuzumab in 3 parallel
      groups of healthy male subjects.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 22, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 22, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 22, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the concentration/time curve, from time 0 h extrapolated to infinity (AUC(0-∞))</measure>
    <time_frame>70 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Peak Plasma Concentration (Cmax)</measure>
    <time_frame>70 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the concentration/time curve, calculated by the trapezoidal rule from time 0 h to last observed concentration at time t (AUC(0-t))</measure>
    <time_frame>70 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Residual area in percent (AUCres)</measure>
    <time_frame>70 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum concentration half-life (t½)</measure>
    <time_frame>70 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>70 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical laboratory values</measure>
    <time_frame>70 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local tolerability at infusion site</measure>
    <time_frame>70 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Vital signs and physical examination results</measure>
    <time_frame>70 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Electrocardiogram (ECG) measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>70 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of anti-drug antibodies (ADA)</measure>
    <time_frame>70 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">84</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EG12014</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>EG12014</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>EU-sourced Herceptin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>EU-sourced Herceptin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>US-sourced Herceptin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>US-sourced Herceptin</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EG12014</intervention_name>
    <description>EG12014, single-dose IV infusion over 90 min at 6 mg/kg</description>
    <arm_group_label>EG12014</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>EU-sourced Herceptin</intervention_name>
    <description>EU-sourced Herceptin, single-dose IV infusion over 90 min at 6 mg/kg</description>
    <arm_group_label>EU-sourced Herceptin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>US-sourced Herceptin</intervention_name>
    <description>US-sourced Herceptin, single-dose IV infusion over 90 min at 6 mg/kg</description>
    <arm_group_label>US-sourced Herceptin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  male Caucasian subject

          -  age between 18 and 55 years (inclusive)

          -  physically and mentally healthy as judged by means of medical and standard laboratory
             examinations

          -  non-smokers or ex-smokers (stopped at least 6 months ago) with a smoking history of ≤5
             pack-year equivalents (1 pack-year equivalent is equal to smoking 1 pack per day for 1
             year ) and non-users of other nicotine containing products, confirmed by urine
             cotinine test

          -  BMI within the range (including the borders) of 18.5 to 30.0 kg/m2 and body weight not
             more than 105.0 kg

          -  Informed consent given in written form according to Section 5.4 of the protocol.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  participation in another clinical trial at same time or within the preceding 3 months
             from the screening examination (calculated from the date of the final examination of
             the previous study)

          -  randomization into the present trial more than once

          -  blood donation or blood loss including plasmapheresis of &gt;500 ml in the last 3 months
             before day 0 of the study

          -  history of drug abuse or use of illegal drugs: use of soft drugs, e.g. marihuana
             within 6 months of screening or hard drugs, e.g. cocaine, amphetamines, opioids,
             phencyclidine within 1 year of screening

          -  alcohol abuse, i.e. regular use of more than 2 units of alcohol per day or 10 units
             per week or a history of alcoholism (one unit of alcohol equals 250 ml beer, 125 ml
             wine or 25 ml spirits) or recovered alcoholics

          -  regular consumption of beverages or food containing methylxanthines (e.g. coffee, tea,
             cola, caffeine containing sodas, chocolate) equivalent to more than 500 mg
             methylxanthines per day

          -  positive drug screening and/or positive alcohol test at entry screening or on
             hospitalization day 0

          -  history of allergic diathesis or any clinically significant allergic disease (e.g.
             asthma or bronchial hyperreactivity, or allergic reactions to insect bites)

          -  any history of drug hypersensitivity (especially to the active and inactive
             ingredients of the trastuzumab preparation, or other monoclonal antibody or protein
             drugs) or intolerance to any sugar (e.g. fructose, glucose, or lactose)

          -  presence or a history of clinically significant cardiovascular, renal, hepatic,
             pulmonary, metabolic, endocrine, hematological, gastrointestinal, neurological,
             psychiatric or other diseases

          -  clinically significant illness within 4 weeks before day 0 of the study and during the
             study

          -  major surgery of the gastrointestinal tract except for appendectomy

          -  any chronic disease which might interfere with resorption, distribution, metabolism or
             excretion of the drug

          -  positive serologic findings for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibodies,
             hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), and/or hepatitis C virus (HCV) antibodies

          -  administration of depot injectable solutions or medications with a half-life &gt; 1 week
             (including study medications) within 6 months from day 0 of the study

          -  intake of enzyme-inducing, organotoxic or long half-life drugs, including prescription
             or OTC medications or herbal remedies (such as St. John's wort), within 4 weeks from
             day 0 of the study

          -  intake or administration of any systemic or topical medication within 2 weeks of day 0
             of the study and during the study, except of up to a total dose of 1000 mg paracetamol
             or metamizole per day given in case of an adverse event (e.g. IRR's: pyrexia,
             headache) during the study

          -  intake of drugs known to alter the major organs or systems such as barbiturates,
             phenothiazines, cimetidine, omeprazole etc. within the last 2 months

          -  previous exposure to a monoclonal antibody drug or current or expected use of other
             biological products.

          -  systolic blood pressure outside the range of 100 to 140 mmHg and/or diastolic blood
             pressure outside the range of 60 to 90 mmHg at screening and on day 0

          -  heart rate outside the range of 50 to 90 beats/min at screening and on day 0

          -  axillary body temperature outside the interval of 35.5 to 37.1°C at screening and on
             day 0

          -  any clinically significant abnormality of the resting ECG (12-lead) (i.e. AV block, 2°
             to 3°, sinus bradycardia, sick sinus syndrome, SA block)

          -  laboratory values outside normal range with clinical relevance at screening
             examination and on day 0 of the study

          -  special diet due to any reason, e.g. vegetarians

          -  not fulfilling study specific restrictions given in Sections 9.4 Restrictions and 9.6
             Diet of the protocol

          -  any planned surgery within 78 days after dosing on day 1

          -  subjects who are known or suspected: not to comply with the study directives or meet
             the required visit schedules; not to be reliable or trustworthy; not to be capable of
             understanding and evaluating the information given to them as part of the formal
             information policy (informed consent), in particular regarding the risks and
             discomfort to which they would agree to be exposed; to be in such a precarious
             financial situation that they no longer weigh up the possible risks of their
             participation and the unpleasantness they may be involved in.

          -  left ventricular ejection fraction (LVEF) &lt;55%, assessed by means of transthoracic
             echocardiography .
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 17, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 6, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 8, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 6, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 6, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 8, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Trastuzumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

