<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03188822</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RSRB 00058385</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03188822</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Steroid Delivery to the Frontal Sinus Opening With a Bioabsorbable Implant vs. a Bioabsorbable Nasal Dressing</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Randomized, Controlled Trial of Steroid Delivery to the Frontal Sinus Opening With a Bioabsorbable Steroid Releasing Implant vs. a Bioabsorbable Nasal Dressing With Added Steroid</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Rochester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Rochester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to compare how two different post-surgical treatments that both
      deliver steroids to the frontal sinus opening affect your healing after frontal sinus
      surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single center, randomized &amp; controlled trial comparing the efficacy of the Propel
      mini stent or Propel contour stent vs. Nasopore impregnated with Triamcinolone Acetonide at
      reducing frontal sinus opening stenosis and polypoid edema after endoscopic sinus surgery in
      patients with chronic rhinosinusitis with polyposis. Eligible subjects who undergo standard
      of care bilateral frontal sinusotomy will have each frontal sinus randomly assigned to either
      a Propel mini or contour steroid eluding stent or a Nasopore nasal dressing impregnated with
      2.5 ml of Triamcinolone Acetonide 40 mg/ml. Specific Propel stent will be chosen based on the
      shape of frontal sinus opening and best fit as decided by the operating Surgeon. Patients
      will be reassessed on approximately post-operative day 7, 14, 30, 90 days, 6 months, and 12
      months at their standard of care follow-up visits. On the day 14 visit, the frontal sinus
      Propel stent and Nasopore will be completely removed per Standard of care. Video will be
      taken of the frontal sinus opening, and assessed for scarring/adhesions, presence of polypoid
      edema, frontal sinus patency, need for oral steroids or other interventions. Additionally,
      endoscopic scoring of frontal sinus by the above measures will be evaluated by 2 independent
      sinus surgeon reviewers. The reviewers will also be asked to rank the two frontal sinus
      openings as better, same or worse, compared to the opposite side
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">August 25, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Frontal sinus appearance</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Odds ratio for Frontal sinus appearance with designation &quot;better&quot; for bioabsorbable steroid releasing implant vs. bioabsorbable nasal dressing with added steroid</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adhesion/Scarring Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Average adhesion/scarring Likert scale score (range from 0 to 4 with higher numbers indicating worse health) for appearance of the Frontal sinus opening after bioabsorbable steroid releasing implant placement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adhesion/Scarring Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Average adhesion/scarring Likert scale score (range from 0 to 4 with higher numbers indicating worse health) for appearance of the Frontal sinus opening after bioabsorbable nasal dressing with added steroid placement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Polypoid edema scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Average polypoid edema Likert scale score (range from 0 to 4 with higher numbers indicating worse health) for appearance of the Frontal sinus opening after bioabsorbable steroid releasing implant placement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Polypoid edema scale</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Average polypoid edema Likert scale score (range from 0 to 4 with higher numbers indicating worse health) for appearance of the Frontal sinus opening after bioabsorbable nasal dressing with added steroid placement</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frontal sinus opening size</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Odds ratio of frontal sinus opening greater than or equal to 4 mm for bioabsorbable steroid releasing implant vs. bioabsorbable nasal dressing with added steroid</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visualization of Frontal Sinus Roof</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Odds ratio of frontal sinus roof visualized for bioabsorbable steroid releasing implant vs. bioabsorbable nasal dressing with added steroid</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Rhinosinusitis (Diagnosis)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bioabsorbable steroid releasing sinus implant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will undergo bilateral endoscopic sinus surgery which will include bilateral frontal sinusotomy of Draf 2a or 2b type as previously described in the literature. At the conclusion of the procedure, if the patient still meets all inclusion criteria, one frontal sinus will be randomly assigned using the envelop method to receive a bioabsorbable steroid releasing implant and the other frontal sinus will receive a bioabsorbable nasal dressing impregnated with steroid</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>bioabsorbable nasal dressing impregnated with steroid</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will undergo bilateral endoscopic sinus surgery which will include bilateral frontal sinusotomy of Draf 2a or 2b type as previously described in the literature. At the conclusion of the procedure, if the patient still meets all inclusion criteria, one frontal sinus will be randomly assigned using the envelop method to receive a bioabsorbable steroid releasing implant and the other frontal sinus will receive a bioabsorbable nasal dressing impregnated with steroid</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bioabsorbable steroid releasing sinus implant</intervention_name>
    <description>After completion of indicated frontal sinus surgery, patients will have a bioabsorbable steroid releasing implant placed in the frontal sinus opening, which will remain in place for 14 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Bioabsorbable steroid releasing sinus implant</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bioabsorbable nasal dressing impregnated with steroid</intervention_name>
    <description>After completion of indicated frontal sinus surgery, patients will have a bioabsorbable nasal dressing impregnated with steroid placed in the frontal sinus opening, which will remain in place for 14 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>bioabsorbable nasal dressing impregnated with steroid</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults aged 18 and older

          -  Diagnosis of chronic rhinosinusitis with nasal polyps based on the American Academy of
             Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery guidelines

          -  Patient scheduled for bilateral endoscopic sinus surgery with evidence of bilateral
             frontal sinus disease based on Computed Tomography (Lund-Mackay score greater than or
             equal to 1)

          -  At the time of surgery bilateral frontal sinusotomy of type Draf 2a or 2b was
             performed using the same technique on both sides

          -  Bilateral endoscopic sinus surgery performed successfully without complication

          -  Frontal sinus opening diameter greater than 4.0 mm achieved (4 mm olive tipped suction
             easily passed into frontal sinus)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any patient who had frontal sinus surgery for tumor

          -  Allergy to mometesone and/or triamcinolone

          -  Frontal sinusotomy type Draf 1 or Draf 3 performed

          -  One or both frontal sinus openings not amenable to implant placement

          -  Patients with chronic oral steroid dependent conditions

          -  Invasive fungal sinusitis

          -  Immune deficiency
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Li-Xing Man, MSc, MD, MPA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Rochester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paul Allen, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>(585) 276-5181</phone>
    <email>Paul_Allen@URMC.Rochester.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester Department of Otolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paul Allen, PhD</last_name>
      <email>Paul_Allen@URMC.Rochester.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Li-Xing Man, MSc, MD, MPA</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosenfeld RM, Piccirillo JF, Chandrasekhar SS, Brook I, Ashok Kumar K, Kramper M, Orlandi RR, Palmer JN, Patel ZM, Peters A, Walsh SA, Corrigan MD. Clinical practice guideline (update): adult sinusitis. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2015 Apr;152(2 Suppl):S1-S39. doi: 10.1177/0194599815572097.</citation>
    <PMID>25832968</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fokkens WJ, Lund VJ, Mullol J, Bachert C, Alobid I, Baroody F, Cohen N, Cervin A, Douglas R, Gevaert P, Georgalas C, Goossens H, Harvey R, Hellings P, Hopkins C, Jones N, Joos G, Kalogjera L, Kern B, Kowalski M, Price D, Riechelmann H, Schlosser R, Senior B, Thomas M, Toskala E, Voegels R, Wang de Y, Wormald PJ. EPOS 2012: European position paper on rhinosinusitis and nasal polyps 2012. A summary for otorhinolaryngologists. Rhinology. 2012 Mar;50(1):1-12. doi: 10.4193/Rhino50E2.</citation>
    <PMID>22469599</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ragab SM, Lund VJ, Scadding G, Saleh HA, Khalifa MA. Impact of chronic rhinosinusitis therapy on quality of life: a prospective randomized controlled trial. Rhinology. 2010 Sep 1;48(3):305-11. doi: 10.4193/Rhin08.137.</citation>
    <PMID>21038021</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chandra RK, Palmer JN, Tangsujarittham T, Kennedy DW. Factors associated with failure of frontal sinusotomy in the early follow-up period. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2004 Oct;131(4):514-8.</citation>
    <PMID>15467628</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Valdes CJ, Bogado M, Samaha M. Causes of failure in endoscopic frontal sinus surgery in chronic rhinosinusitis patients. Int Forum Allergy Rhinol. 2014 Jun;4(6):502-6. doi: 10.1002/alr.21307. Epub 2014 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>24616299</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DeConde AS, Smith TL. Outcomes After Frontal Sinus Surgery: An Evidence-Based Review. Otolaryngol Clin North Am. 2016 Aug;49(4):1019-33. doi: 10.1016/j.otc.2016.03.024. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>27450618</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rowe-Jones JM, Medcalf M, Durham SR, Richards DH, Mackay IS. Functional endoscopic sinus surgery: 5 year follow up and results of a prospective, randomised, stratified, double-blind, placebo controlled study of postoperative fluticasone propionate aqueous nasal spray. Rhinology. 2005 Mar;43(1):2-10.</citation>
    <PMID>15844495</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wright ED, Agrawal S. Impact of perioperative systemic steroids on surgical outcomes in patients with chronic rhinosinusitis with polyposis: evaluation with the novel Perioperative Sinus Endoscopy (POSE) scoring system. Laryngoscope. 2007 Nov;117(11 Pt 2 Suppl 115):1-28.</citation>
    <PMID>18075447</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huang Z, Hwang P, Sun Y, Zhou B. Steroid-eluting sinus stents for improving symptoms in chronic rhinosinusitis patients undergoing functional endoscopic sinus surgery. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2015 Jun 10;(6):CD010436. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD010436.pub2. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>26068957</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Côté DW, Wright ED. Triamcinolone-impregnated nasal dressing following endoscopic sinus surgery: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. Laryngoscope. 2010 Jun;120(6):1269-73. doi: 10.1002/lary.20905.</citation>
    <PMID>20513050</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smith TL, Singh A, Luong A, Ow RA, Shotts SD, Sautter NB, Han JK, Stambaugh J, Raman A. Randomized controlled trial of a bioabsorbable steroid-releasing implant in the frontal sinus opening. Laryngoscope. 2016 Dec;126(12):2659-2664. doi: 10.1002/lary.26140. Epub 2016 Jul 1.</citation>
    <PMID>27363723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 13, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 15, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 8, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 8, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Rochester</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Li-Xing Man</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sinusitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Chronic Disease</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

