<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03188484</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IDIAP Jordi Gol</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>275/C/2015</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03188484</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Atrial Fibrillation Research In CATalonia</brief_title>
  <acronym>AFRICAT</acronym>
  <official_title>Stepwise High Risk Individuals Screening for Atrial Fibrillation Using Sequential Clinical-electro-biological Register: the AFRICAT Study (Atrial Fibrillation Research In CATalonia)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Jordi Gol i Gurina Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundación Pública Andaluza para la gestión de la Investigación en Sevilla</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Fundació La Marató de TV3</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Laboratorio de Investigación Neurovascular Institut de Recerca, Hospital Vall d'Hebron, Barcelona</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Jordi Gol i Gurina Foundation</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      It is a randomized, observational and controlled non-blinded interventional cohort study,
      divided into two different phases of generation and validation of the screening program. From
      5,500 patients, 100 will be randomly selected for the first phase of the project to create
      and apply a sequential screening program in a high-risk population by integrating clinical,
      electrocardiographic and biological information, testing of different pulse devices
      (MyDiagnostick, AliveCor and WatchBP) for AF screening, discovery of blood biomarkers for AF
      by aptamer technology, and validation of biological candidates from the literature and
      previous results. AF diagnosis will be based on detection in four-week Holter-EKG monitoring.
      In the second phase, the investigators will apply the best candidates in a sequential
      screening program in a high-risk population (aged 65-75 with hypertension and diabetes) by
      clinical variables and performing pulse device detection. Biomarkers will be measured in the
      negative cases to perform Holter-ECG monitoring in the highest-risk patients. In the final
      step of the study, cost-efficacy analyses will be carried out.

      The main objective is to develop a clinical model for AF prediction with the combination of
      clinical information plus pulse device and blood markers in high-risk populations.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study has been approved by the Ethics Committee of Research Institute IDIAP Jordi Gol
      (P15/047/2015) and by Hospital Universitari Vall d'Hebron Clinical Research Ethics Committee
      (PR(AG)133-2015). The study will be conducted in compliance with the Declaration of Helsinki.
      Registry information was collected from the government-run healthcare provider responsible
      for all inpatient care in Catalonia. All participants will receive written information and
      thereafter sign informed consent before inclusion, will be selected among the electronic
      registers from two different health areas in Catalonia, and will be identified by their
      10-digit personal identification number assigned to all citizens in Catalonia.

      These patients will be given an appointment in their primary care centre and will receive a
      comprehensive assessment consisting of:

        -  Clinical characteristics: demographic factors (age, gender, habits); vascular risk
           factors (hypertension, diabetes, dyslipidemia), medications, comorbidities (especially
           those related to AF such as coronary disease, heart failure), vital signs (blood
           pressure, glycaemia, weight and height).

        -  Electrocardiographic assessment: three different devices will be tested on each
           participant (MyDiasnostik, AliveCor and WatchBP). A conventional ECG will be performed
           to be compared with the results from these devices.

        -  Blood sample collection: a blood sample of 32 cc divided into two serum tubes (8.5 cc),
           two plasma EDTA tubes (6 cc) and one TempusTM RNA tube (3 cc). Samples will be processed
           and stored at -20 ºC at the recruiting centre until shipment to Neurovascular Research
           Laboratory, where the sample bank will be set up.

        -  Holter ECG monitoring: a Nuubo Holter will be given to each patient to be carried for
           four weeks. Electrocardiographic devices will be read blindly. The device records,
           anonymized and encrypted, will be sent for blinded reading to the Rhythm Disorders Unit
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Ecologic or Community</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>2 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Atrial fibrillation (AF) diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>Study visit/1 month monitoring</time_frame>
    <description>Absence of discrete P waves together with an irregular, arrhythmic pattern of ventricular activation, more than 60 seconds.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">5000</enrollment>
  <condition>Arrhythmia Atrial</condition>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <condition>Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      A blood sample of 32 cc divided into two serum tubes (8.5 cc), two plasma EDTA tubes (6 cc)
      and one TempusTM RNA tube (3 cc). Samples will be processed and stored at -20 ºC at the
      recruiting centre until shipment to Neurovascular Research Laboratory, where the sample bank
      will be set up.

      Biomarker discovery study will be performed by exploration with a multiple screening platform
      with 1,310 different proteins, based on DNA aptamer technology (SOMAscan, Somalogic). These
      aptamers have been modified in their lateral chains, increasing their chemical diversity and,
      therefore, the number of targets. The whole library will be explored and, after the
      statistical analyses, the best candidates will be chosen for replication by simple ELISA.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All people included were managed by the Public Health System. Therefore 5,000 participants
        aged 65-75 with active diagnoses of hypertension (I10) and diabetes (E10.9 E11.9) will be
        selected from the electronic health record of Primary Care. Given that the registered
        prevalence of Atrial Fibrillation was 7.3%, the investigators estimated that around 2.8%
        will be newly diagnosed with AF at the first study visit. Therefore, the investigators
        estimate that the number of patients in this population who have undiagnosed AF might be
        from 140 to 210 patients, taking into account that AF detection should be improved in the
        study given the long-term monitoring.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  patients aged 65-75 with active diagnoses of hypertension (I10) and diabetes (E10.9
             E11.9)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  absence or not accessibility to singular person or its clinical record or/and
             difficulty to follow the instructions about how managing the devices or/and no
             acceptation of conditions.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Joan Montaner Villalonga, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Neurovascular Research Group</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 13, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 14, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 15, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 23, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 23, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 26, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Jordi Gol i Gurina Foundation</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Josep Lluís Clua Espuny</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD Medicine and Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Atrial Fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>Electrocardiography</keyword>
  <keyword>Biological Markers</keyword>
  <keyword>Risk Assessment</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

