<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03184428</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>STN 05/15</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03184428</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Posterior Capsule Opacification Following Cataract Surgery With Implantation of the MICS IOL L313</brief_title>
  <official_title>Retro- and Prospective Monocentric Study to Evaluate the Rate of Posterior Capsule Opacification Following Cataract Surgery With Implantation of the MICS (Micro Incision Cataract Surgery) -IOL (Intraocular Lens) L313</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dietrich-Bonhoeffer-Klinikum</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dietrich-Bonhoeffer-Klinikum</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study collects intra- and postoperative data from the patients´charts retrospectively
      and evaluates retro- and prospectively the rate of posterior capsule opacification (PCO)
      following implantation of the intraocular lens L 313.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study is a postmarket study without interventions. Within the Standard Care Cataract
      surgery the participants have been implanted with the intraocular lens L313 in the period
      between September 2009 and December 2013. As criterium for the PCO was considered the Nd:YAG
      capsulotomy.

      In the first step of the study, data was collected from the patients´charts.

      In the second phase, a questionaire was sent to the patients with no recent examination,
      asking them to answer whether or not participants received a laser procedure due to PCO. In
      doubt the participants could answer: &quot;I am not certain&quot;. For this step the investigator
      ensured the positive Votum of the Ethic Committee of the University of Greifswald, Germany.

      On the third step of the study, the patients that were not certain of having such a laser
      procedure or did not answer per post, will be contacted on telephone. By uncertainty or no
      answer on the telephone the family eye doctor will be contacted to receive the necessary
      information. If the eye doctor has lost contact to the patient, then this patient will be
      documented as lost-to-follow-up.

      Excluded were the patients that live &gt;50km from the Department of Ophthalmology in
      Neubrandenburg, as well as patients with intraoperative capsule tear.

      For the statistical analysis was used the program STATISTICA (StatSoft, Hamburg, Germany) and
      the survival analysis using the Kaplan-Meier formula, the statistical significance using the
      Chi-squared test and Spearman-Rank corelation and the Bonferroni adjustment if the test was
      repeated.

      The investigators compared these results with the results of other publication. In order to
      do that the investigators calculated the capsulotomy quote from this study according to the
      time of the PCO recorded on the other studies. Included were only comparing studies that also
      used YAG-capsulotomy as criterium for the PCO.

      Furthermore secondary data was collected: age, gender, cutting length, core hardness,
      duration of whole operation, time of phaco-emulsification, phaco-energy, phaco-machine,
      combination with other operation, surgeon, power of IOL. This data will be taken in concern
      for the validity of this study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 1, 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 1, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Longterm rate of posterior capsule opacification following implantation of IOL 313</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 years</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of the Longterm rate of posterior capsule opacification following implantation of the IOL L313</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison to capsulotomy rates of other IOLs</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 years</time_frame>
    <description>Comparison in the literature regarding to the Rate of posterior capsule opacification of other IOLs</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlations of capsulotomy rate to parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 8 years</time_frame>
    <description>Correlations of capsulotomy rate to the patient parameters:
age
gender,
and to the surgical parameters:
cutting length,
core hardness,
duration of whole operation,
time of phaco-emulsification,
phaco-energy,
phaco-machine,
combination with other operation,
surgeon,
power of IOL.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">2775</enrollment>
  <condition>Posterior Capsule Opacification</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Implantation of IOL L313</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients who have undergone a cataract surgery with implantation of the monofocal MICS IOL L313 more than 3 Years ago will be asked about the Treatment for Postoperative observation and survey.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Postoperative observation and survey</intervention_name>
    <description>For postoperative Observation with a survey we ask the patients (or in case of no information the ophthalmologist) whether they had undergone a YAG-Laser-Capsulotomy after Cataract-Surgery or not.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Implantation of IOL L313</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        2775 (5564 eyes)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  retrospective: Patients who have undergone a Cataract surgery with Implantation of IOL
             L313

          -  prospective: signed informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  capsule rupture

          -  patients with to much travel distance between study center and home
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Helmut Hoeh, Prof. Dr.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, Neubrandenburg, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christoforos Stylianides</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Ophthalmology, Neubrandenburg, Germany</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ulrike Holland</last_name>
    <phone>+49 395 77 53427</phone>
    <email>aug-st2@dbknb.de</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Mandy Denkert</last_name>
    <phone>+49 395 77 53425</phone>
    <email>aug-st1@dbknb.de</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dietrich-Bonhoeffer-Klinikum</name>
      <address>
        <city>Neubrandenburg</city>
        <state>Mecklenburg/Vorpommern</state>
        <zip>17036</zip>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ulrike Holland</last_name>
      <phone>+49 395 775 3427</phone>
      <email>aug-st2@dbknb.de</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Mandy Denkert</last_name>
      <phone>+49 395 775 3425</phone>
      <email>aug-st1@dbknb.de</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Helmut Hoeh, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christoforos Stylianides</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Apple DJ, Peng Q, Visessook N, Werner L, Pandey SK, Escobar-Gomez M, Ram J, Auffarth GU. Eradication of posterior capsule opacification: documentation of a marked decrease in Nd:YAG laser posterior capsulotomy rates noted in an analysis of 5416 pseudophakic human eyes obtained postmortem. Ophthalmology. 2001 Mar;108(3):505-18.</citation>
    <PMID>11237905</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Apple DJ, Peng Q, Visessook N, Werner L, Pandey SK, Escobar-Gomez M, Ram J, Whiteside SB, Schoderbeck R, Ready EL, Guindi A. Surgical prevention of posterior capsule opacification. Part 1: Progress in eliminating this complication of cataract surgery. J Cataract Refract Surg. 2000 Feb;26(2):180-7.</citation>
    <PMID>10683785</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Auffarth GU, Brezin A, Caporossi A, Lafuma A, Mendicute J, Berdeaux G, Smith AF; European PCO Study Group. Comparison of Nd : YAG capsulotomy rates following phacoemulsification with implantation of PMMA, silicone, or acrylic intra-ocular lenses in four European countries. Ophthalmic Epidemiol. 2004 Oct;11(4):319-29.</citation>
    <PMID>15512993</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chitkara DK, Smerdon DL. Risk factors, complications, and results in extracapsular cataract extraction. J Cataract Refract Surg. 1997 May;23(4):570-4.</citation>
    <PMID>9209994</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meacock WR, Spalton DJ, Boyce JF, Jose RM. Effect of optic size on posterior capsule opacification: 5.5 mm versus 6.0 mm AcrySof intraocular lenses. J Cataract Refract Surg. 2001 Aug;27(8):1194-8.</citation>
    <PMID>11524189</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Menapace R. [After-cataract following intraocular lens implantation. Part II: prevention with alternative implants and techniques]. Ophthalmologe. 2007 Apr;104(4):345-53; quiz 354-5. Review. German.</citation>
    <PMID>17372739</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Menapace R. [After-cataract following intraocular lens implantation. Part I. Genesis and prevention by optimizing conventional lens implants and surgical techniques]. Ophthalmologe. 2007 Mar;104(3):253-62; quiz 263-4. Review. German.</citation>
    <PMID>17323043</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mester U, Fabian E, Gerl R, Hunold W, Hütz W, Strobel J, Hoyer H, Kohnen T. Posterior capsule opacification after implantation of CeeOn Edge 911A, PhacoFlex SI-40NB, and AcrySof MA60BM lenses: one-year results of an intraindividual comparison multicenter study. J Cataract Refract Surg. 2004 May;30(5):978-85.</citation>
    <PMID>15130632</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pandey SK, Apple DJ, Werner L, Maloof AJ, Milverton EJ. Posterior capsule opacification: a review of the aetiopathogenesis, experimental and clinical studies and factors for prevention. Indian J Ophthalmol. 2004 Jun;52(2):99-112. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15283214</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Prosdocimo G, Tassinari G, Sala M, Di Biase A, Toschi PG, Gismondi M, Corbanese U. Posterior capsule opacification after phacoemulsification: silicone CeeOn Edge versus acrylate AcrySof intraocular lens. J Cataract Refract Surg. 2003 Aug;29(8):1551-5.</citation>
    <PMID>12954304</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schaumberg DA, Dana MR, Christen WG, Glynn RJ. A systematic overview of the incidence of posterior capsule opacification. Ophthalmology. 1998 Jul;105(7):1213-21.</citation>
    <PMID>9663224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schmidbauer JM, Vargas LG, Apple DJ, Auffarth GU, Peng Q, Arthur SN, Escobar-Gomez M. [Millenniums update on posterior capsule opacification (PCO) scores, centration, biocompatibility and fixation of foldable intraocular lenses (IOL) - an analysis of 1,221 pseudophakic post mortem globes]. Klin Monbl Augenheilkd. 2001 Oct;218(10):649-57. German.</citation>
    <PMID>11706380</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tetz MR, Nimsgern C. Posterior capsule opacification. Part 2: Clinical findings. J Cataract Refract Surg. 1999 Dec;25(12):1662-74. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10609214</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wehner W. [Microincision intraocular lens with plate haptic design. Evaluation of rotational stability and centering of a microincision intraocular lens with plate haptic design in 12-19 months of follow-up]. Ophthalmologe. 2007 May;104(5):393-4, 396-8. German.</citation>
    <PMID>17384950</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Nishi Y, Ikeda T, Nishi K, Mimura O. Epidemiological evaluation of YAG capsulotomy incidence for posterior capsule opacification in various intraocular lenses in Japanese eyes. Clin Ophthalmol. 2015 Sep 1;9:1613-7. doi: 10.2147/OPTH.S89966. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26366054</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Schriefl SM, Leydolt C, Stifter E, Menapace R. Posterior capsular opacification and Nd:YAG capsulotomy rates with the iMics Y-60H and Micro AY intra-ocular lenses: 3-year results of a randomized clinical trial. Acta Ophthalmol. 2015 Jun;93(4):342-7. doi: 10.1111/aos.12543. Epub 2014 Nov 13.</citation>
    <PMID>25393894</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Spyridaki M, Höh H. [Comparison of four MICS intraocular lenses regarding their rates of neodymium:YAG laser capsulotomy]. Klin Monbl Augenheilkd. 2010 Mar;227(3):208-14. doi: 10.1055/s-0028-1109853. Epub 2010 Mar 16. German.</citation>
    <PMID>20234985</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 9, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 9, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 12, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>YAG-Laser Capsulotomy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cataract</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Capsule Opacification</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>results will be published in ophthalmological journals</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

