<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03187418</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CE16.351</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03187418</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Treatment Outcomes of MicroPulse Trans-scleral Cyclophotocoagulation in Uncontrolled Glaucoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Treatment Outcomes of MicroPulse Trans-scleral Cyclophotocoagulation (mTSCPC) in Uncontrolled Glaucoma at the University of Montreal Hospital Center (CHUM)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Centre hospitalier de l'Université de Montréal (CHUM)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Centre hospitalier de l'Université de Montréal (CHUM)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>Yes</is_fda_regulated_device>
    <is_unapproved_device>No</is_unapproved_device>
    <is_ppsd>No</is_ppsd>
    <is_us_export>Yes</is_us_export>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of this study is to evaluate the efficacy and safety of the novel form of
      trans-scleral cyclophotocoagulation using micropulse diode laser and trans-pars plana
      treatment (Micropulse TSCPC, mTSCPC MP3, IRIDEX CYCLO G6™ Glaucoma Laser System, CA, USA) in
      adults for the treatment of uncontrolled glaucoma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cyclophotocoagulation (CPC) is a type of cycloablation using laser to treat glaucoma. It
      involves ciliary body destruction by targeting the ciliary epithelium and stroma, resulting
      in a reduction in aqueous secretion and hence intraocular pressure. This strategy is
      effective for all forms of glaucoma.

      Traditional trans-scleral cyclophotocoagulation (TSCPC) achieve its cyclodestructive action
      by using continuous diode laser to target the melanin in the pigmented ciliary body
      epithelium. However, the continuous mode has been shown to cause significant collateral
      tissue damage to adjacent non-pigmented structures including the ciliary stroma and ciliary
      muscle. Traditional TSCPC may therefore be associated with serious complications including
      uveitis, visual deterioration, chronic hypotony, and others.

      More recently, a micropulse delivery mode of diode laser (Micropulse TSCPC, mTSCPC) has been
      used to treat glaucoma by ablating the ciliary processes and reduce aqueous humor production
      with more selective targeting and less collateral damage. In contrast to conventional laser
      delivery where a continuous flow of high intensity energy is delivered, micropulse laser
      application delivers a series of repetitive short pulses of energy with rest periods in
      between pulses. Only a few studies have described the outcomes of this novel glaucoma
      therapy, showing mTSCPC to have comparable efficacy with fewer side effects when compared
      with traditional continuous wave mode diode laser delivery.This improved side effect profile
      has the potential to make mTSCPC an earlier therapeutic option instead of reserving it
      exclusively for end-stage refractory eyes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">June 19, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Prospective, interventional and monocentric study based in a university hospital setting</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraocular pressure (IOP)</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>In millimeters of mercury (mmHg), measured with the Goldmann applanation tonometer</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Intraocular pressure (IOP)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>In millimeters of mercury (mmHg), measured with the Goldmann applanation tonometer</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of repeat treatments</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of necessary laser treatment repeats during the study</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of intraocular pressure lowering medications</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months, 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of drops and oral medications used by the patient compared to baseline</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Corrected distance visual acuity (CDVA)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months, 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Number of lines reduction or improvement from baseline on Snellen acuity chart at 6 meters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cup-to-disc ratio (CDR)</measure>
    <time_frame>1 week, 1 month, 3 months, 6 months, 12 months, 18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Progression of CDR compared to baseline, assessed by an ophthalmologist on dilated fundus examination</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visual field index (VFI)</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Determined by Humphrey automated perimetry Sita 24-2 visual field testing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean deviation (MD)</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Determined by Humphrey automated perimetry Sita 24-2 visual field testing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pattern standard deviation (PSD)</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Determined by Humphrey automated perimetry Sita 24-2 visual field testing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Glaucoma hemifield test (GHT)</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Determined by Humphrey automated perimetry Sita 24-2 visual field testing</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average retinal nerve fiber layer (RNFL) thickness</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>In micrometer, determined by optical coherence tomography (OCT)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Average ganglion cell layer (GCL) thickness</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>In micrometer, determined by optical coherence tomography (OCT)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cup-to-disc ratio (CDR)</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Progression of vertical CDR compared to baseline, assessed by optical coherence tomography (OCT) parameters</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain level during laser treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>1 day</time_frame>
    <description>Using a verbal analog scale for pain level (none = no subjective feeling of pain, mild = pain easily tolerable, moderate = pain tolerable with difficulty, severe = pain intolerable)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Glaucoma</condition>
  <condition>Glaucoma, Open-Angle</condition>
  <condition>Glaucoma, Neovascular</condition>
  <condition>Glaucoma and Ocular Hypertension</condition>
  <condition>Glaucoma Eye</condition>
  <condition>Glaucoma, Uncompensated</condition>
  <condition>Glaucoma Secondary</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Micropulse trans-scleral CPC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>A treatment session of micropulse trans-scleral cyclophotocoagulation in the affected eye, using the MicroPulse® P3 Glaucoma Device (MP3) powered by the CYCLO G6™ Glaucoma Laser System (Iridex, Mountain View, CA, USA).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>MicroPulse® P3 Glaucoma Device (MP3)</intervention_name>
    <description>Laser settings will be programmed as follows: power—2000mW-2500mW (average 2000mW) of 810nm infrared diode laser set on micropulse delivery mode; micropulse &quot;on&quot; time—0.5ms; micropulse &quot;off&quot; time—1.1ms; and duty cycle (proportion of each cycle during which the laser is on)—31.33 %.
The laser probe will be applied in a continuous sliding or painting motion from 9:30 to 2:30 and from 3:30 to 8:30. The probe will be applied perpendicular to the limbus with the edge directly on the limbus at all times (fiberoptic tip at 3 mm posterior to the limbus).
The laser will be delivered over 360° for 160-320s. Treatment duration will be adjusted based on iris color and glaucoma severity (mild glaucoma: 160s, moderate glaucoma: 240s, advanced glaucoma: 240-320s).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Micropulse trans-scleral CPC</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CYCLO G6 Glaucoma Laser System (Iridex, Mountain View, CA)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients of either sex and any race aged 18 years old and above.

          -  Followed by a glaucoma subspecialist at University of Montreal Hospital Center.

          -  Intraocular pressure (IOP) above target and unresponsive to maximal tolerated medical
             therapy with or without previous surgical intervention.

               1. mild glaucoma: IOP &gt; 18 mmHg

               2. moderate glaucoma: IOP &gt; 15 mmHg

               3. advanced glaucoma: IOP &gt; 12 mmHg

          -  Considered poor candidates for additional filtering surgery or implantation of
             glaucoma drainage devices.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients unable to give informed consent.

          -  Patients with significant scleral thinning, defined as thinning of more than one clock
             hour noticed on scleral transillumination.

          -  Ocular infection or inflammation in the study eye in the 2 months prior to enrolment.

          -  Intraocular surgery in the study eye in the 2 months prior to enrolment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Harmanjit Singh, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centre hospitalier de l'Université de Montréal (CHUM)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Marchand, MD</last_name>
    <phone>514-805-1247</phone>
    <email>mic9@sympatico.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Harmanjit Singh, MD</last_name>
    <phone>289-981-2464</phone>
    <email>harman25@hotmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centre Hospitalier de l'Université de Montréal (CHUM)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montréal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H2X 3E4</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Marchand, MD</last_name>
      <phone>514-805-1247</phone>
      <email>mic9@sympatico.ca</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Marie-Catherine Tessier</last_name>
      <phone>1-514-890-8000</phone>
      <phone_ext>11550</phone_ext>
      <email>marie-catherine.tessier.chum@ssss.gouv.qc.ca</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Harmanjit Singh, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Marchand, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Quigley HA, Broman AT. The number of people with glaucoma worldwide in 2010 and 2020. Br J Ophthalmol. 2006 Mar;90(3):262-7.</citation>
    <PMID>16488940</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tham YC, Li X, Wong TY, Quigley HA, Aung T, Cheng CY. Global prevalence of glaucoma and projections of glaucoma burden through 2040: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Ophthalmology. 2014 Nov;121(11):2081-90. doi: 10.1016/j.ophtha.2014.05.013. Epub 2014 Jun 26. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24974815</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nguyen QH. Primary surgical management refractory glaucoma: tubes as initial surgery. Curr Opin Ophthalmol. 2009 Mar;20(2):122-5. doi: 10.1097/ICU.0b013e32831da828. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19240544</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schlote T, Derse M, Rassmann K, Nicaeus T, Dietz K, Thiel HJ. Efficacy and safety of contact transscleral diode laser cyclophotocoagulation for advanced glaucoma. J Glaucoma. 2001 Aug;10(4):294-301.</citation>
    <PMID>11558814</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Agarwal HC, Gupta V, Sihota R. Evaluation of contact versus non-contact diode laser cyclophotocoagulation for refractory glaucomas using similar energy settings. Clin Exp Ophthalmol. 2004 Feb;32(1):33-8.</citation>
    <PMID>14746588</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Schlote T, Derse M, Zierhut M. Transscleral diode laser cyclophotocoagulation for the treatment of refractory glaucoma secondary to inflammatory eye diseases. Br J Ophthalmol. 2000 Sep;84(9):999-1003.</citation>
    <PMID>10966953</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Egbert PR, Fiadoyor S, Budenz DL, Dadzie P, Byrd S. Diode laser transscleral cyclophotocoagulation as a primary surgical treatment for primary open-angle glaucoma. Arch Ophthalmol. 2001 Mar;119(3):345-50.</citation>
    <PMID>11231767</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leszczyński R, Gierek-Lapińska A, Formińska - Kapuścik M. Transscleral cyclophotocoagulation in the treatment of secondary glaucoma. Med Sci Monit. 2004 Sep;10(9):CR542-8. Epub 2004 Aug 20.</citation>
    <PMID>15328489</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rotchford AP, Jayasawal R, Madhusudhan S, Ho S, King AJ, Vernon SA. Transscleral diode laser cycloablation in patients with good vision. Br J Ophthalmol. 2010 Sep;94(9):1180-3. doi: 10.1136/bjo.2008.145565. Epub 2010 Jun 24.</citation>
    <PMID>20576775</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pantcheva MB, Kahook MY, Schuman JS, Rubin MW, Noecker RJ. Comparison of acute structural and histopathological changes of the porcine ciliary processes after endoscopic cyclophotocoagulation and transscleral cyclophotocoagulation. Clin Exp Ophthalmol. 2007 Apr;35(3):270-4.</citation>
    <PMID>17430515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tan AM, Chockalingam M, Aquino MC, Lim ZI, See JL, Chew PT. Micropulse transscleral diode laser cyclophotocoagulation in the treatment of refractory glaucoma. Clin Exp Ophthalmol. 2010 Apr;38(3):266-72. doi: 10.1111/j.1442-9071.2010.02238.x.</citation>
    <PMID>20447122</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aquino MC, Barton K, Tan AM, Sng C, Li X, Loon SC, Chew PT. Micropulse versus continuous wave transscleral diode cyclophotocoagulation in refractory glaucoma: a randomized exploratory study. Clin Exp Ophthalmol. 2015 Jan-Feb;43(1):40-6. doi: 10.1111/ceo.12360. Epub 2014 Jun 21.</citation>
    <PMID>24811050</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bloom PA, Tsai JC, Sharma K, Miller MH, Rice NS, Hitchings RA, Khaw PT. &quot;Cyclodiode&quot;. Trans-scleral diode laser cyclophotocoagulation in the treatment of advanced refractory glaucoma. Ophthalmology. 1997 Sep;104(9):1508-19; discussion 1519-20.</citation>
    <PMID>9307649</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kosoko O, Gaasterland DE, Pollack IP, Enger CL. Long-term outcome of initial ciliary ablation with contact diode laser transscleral cyclophotocoagulation for severe glaucoma. The Diode Laser Ciliary Ablation Study Group. Ophthalmology. 1996 Aug;103(8):1294-302.</citation>
    <PMID>8764801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mistlberger A, Liebmann JM, Tschiderer H, Ritch R, Ruckhofer J, Grabner G. Diode laser transscleral cyclophotocoagulation for refractory glaucoma. J Glaucoma. 2001 Aug;10(4):288-93.</citation>
    <PMID>11558813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oguri A, Takahashi E, Tomita G, Yamamoto T, Jikihara S, Kitazawa Y. Transscleral cyclophotocoagulation with the diode laser for neovascular glaucoma. Ophthalmic Surg Lasers. 1998 Sep;29(9):722-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9760607</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sivaprasad S, Sandhu R, Tandon A, Sayed-Ahmed K, McHugh DA. Subthreshold micropulse diode laser photocoagulation for clinically significant diabetic macular oedema: a three-year follow up. Clin Exp Ophthalmol. 2007 Sep-Oct;35(7):640-4.</citation>
    <PMID>17894684</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parodi MB, Spasse S, Iacono P, Di Stefano G, Canziani T, Ravalico G. Subthreshold grid laser treatment of macular edema secondary to branch retinal vein occlusion with micropulse infrared (810 nanometer) diode laser. Ophthalmology. 2006 Dec;113(12):2237-42. Epub 2006 Sep 25.</citation>
    <PMID>16996596</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Desmettre TJ, Mordon SR, Buzawa DM, Mainster MA. Micropulse and continuous wave diode retinal photocoagulation: visible and subvisible lesion parameters. Br J Ophthalmol. 2006 Jun;90(6):709-12. Epub 2006 Mar 10.</citation>
    <PMID>16531424</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Laursen ML, Moeller F, Sander B, Sjoelie AK. Subthreshold micropulse diode laser treatment in diabetic macular oedema. Br J Ophthalmol. 2004 Sep;88(9):1173-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15317711</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Moorman CM, Hamilton AM. Clinical applications of the MicroPulse diode laser. Eye (Lond). 1999 Apr;13 ( Pt 2):145-50.</citation>
    <PMID>10450372</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pollack JS, Kim JE, Pulido JS, Burke JM. Tissue effects of subclinical diode laser treatment of the retina. Arch Ophthalmol. 1998 Dec;116(12):1633-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9869794</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berger JW. Thermal modelling of micropulsed diode laser retinal photocoagulation. Lasers Surg Med. 1997;20(4):409-15.</citation>
    <PMID>9142680</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kuchar S, Moster MR, Reamer CB, Waisbourd M. Treatment outcomes of micropulse transscleral cyclophotocoagulation in advanced glaucoma. Lasers Med Sci. 2016 Feb;31(2):393-6. doi: 10.1007/s10103-015-1856-9. Epub 2015 Dec 29.</citation>
    <PMID>26714976</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hauber FA, Scherer WJ. Influence of total energy delivery on success rate after contact diode laser transscleral cyclophotocoagulation: a retrospective case review and meta-analysis. J Glaucoma. 2002 Aug;11(4):329-33.</citation>
    <PMID>12169970</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vernon SA, Koppens JM, Menon GJ, Negi AK. Diode laser cycloablation in adult glaucoma: long-term results of a standard protocol and review of current literature. Clin Exp Ophthalmol. 2006 Jul;34(5):411-20. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16872335</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murphy CC, Burnett CA, Spry PG, Broadway DC, Diamond JP. A two centre study of the dose-response relation for transscleral diode laser cyclophotocoagulation in refractory glaucoma. Br J Ophthalmol. 2003 Oct;87(10):1252-7.</citation>
    <PMID>14507761</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meyer JJ, Lawrence SD. What's new in laser treatment for glaucoma? Curr Opin Ophthalmol. 2012 Mar;23(2):111-7. doi: 10.1097/ICU.0b013e32834f1887. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22186007</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 12, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 12, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 15, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 12, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cyclophotocoagulation</keyword>
  <keyword>Micropulse TSCPC</keyword>
  <keyword>Laser ablation</keyword>
  <keyword>Laser therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ocular Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma, Open-Angle</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma, Neovascular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma, Angle-Closure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

