<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03180957</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11069</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HICF-R8-433</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2015-001780-40</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>ISRCTN27786905</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>15/SC/0259</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>CTU0028</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03180957</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Repurposing Anti-TNF for Treating Dupuytren's Disease</brief_title>
  <acronym>RIDD</acronym>
  <official_title>A Multi-centre, Double Blind, Randomised, Placebo-controlled, Parallel Group, Phase II Trial to Determine the Efficacy of Intra-nodular Injection of Anti-TNF to Control Disease Progression in Early Dupuytren's Disease, With a Dose Response.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Department of Health, United Kingdom</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Wellcome Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>180 Therapeutics LP</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Dupuytren's disease is a very common condition, affecting 4% of the general UK and US
      population. It causes the fingers to curl irreversibly into the palm and can be extremely
      disabling. The disease usually starts as a small firm lump (nodule) in the palm, and in about
      40% of patients advances to form cords that pull the fingers into the palm. There is no
      approved treatment for the early stage of disease. Once patients have established
      deformities, the diseased tissue can removed by surgery or cut using less invasive techniques
      such as a needle or an enzyme. However, recovery following surgery usually takes several
      months and recurrence rates with the less invasive techniques are high.

      The investigators have unravelled the cellular process that initiates and maintains the
      disease progress and identified tumour necrosis factor (TNF) as a new target for treatment.
      Based on these findings the investigators plan to test the effects of adalimumab, an anti-TNF
      drug which currently approved for use in patients with rheumatoid arthritis and other
      inflammatory conditions. The aim of the study is to find out whether treatment by injection
      with adalimumab directly into the diseased tissue will control the advance of early
      Dupuytren's disease better than a placebo injection with normal saline.

      The investigators will first carry out a small trial in up to 40 patients with established
      disease to determine the best dose that reduces the activity of the cells responsible for the
      disorder (Dose Response study). In this part patients who will be having surgery to remove
      their diseased tissue will receive a single injection of adalimumab into the nodule in their
      hand about 2 weeks before surgery. The tissue that is then removed during surgery will be
      analysed in the investigator's laboratories to determine the effect of the drug on the
      tissue. Patients will be followed for 12 weeks after surgery.

      In the second part of the study the investigators will assess whether the optimal dose of the
      drug prevents early disease advancing in 138 patients (Early Disease study). Patients who
      take part in the second part of the study will receive a total of 4 injections of adalimumab
      into the nodule in their hand at three monthly intervals. They will then be checked at 3 &amp; 9
      months after the last injection. In additional to assessing the effect of the injections on
      the nodule and hand function, information will also be collected to assess the cost
      effectiveness of the treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 2, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>During Dose Response part of the trial the Investigator will be blinded. During the Early Disease part of the trial the Investigator will not be blinded but will not carry out any outcome assessments.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Response: expression of mRNA for α-SMA</measure>
    <time_frame>Analysis of tissue removed at 12-18 days post-treatment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Early Disease: change in nodule hardness between baseline at 12 months</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Tonometry</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Response: expression of mRNA for COL-1A1, COL-3A1, cadherin 11</measure>
    <time_frame>Analysis of tissue removed at 12-18 days post-treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Response: Levels of α-SMA and collegen protein</measure>
    <time_frame>Analysis of tissue removed at 12-18 days post-treatment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Response: Nodule hardness</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks post treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Tonometry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Response: Visual comparison of surgical wounds using hand photographs</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks post surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Response &amp; Early Disease: Change in nodule size and vascularity from baseline</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks post treatment (dose response) / 18 months (early disease)</time_frame>
    <description>Pixel analysis of ultrasound imaging</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Response and Early Disease: participant injection experience</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline (Dose response) / 12 months (early disease)</time_frame>
    <description>Numeric rating scale of pain</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Response &amp; Early Disease: Adverse event assessment</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks (dose response) / 12 months (early disease)</time_frame>
    <description>Assessment of the injection site for pre-specified Adverse Events; surgery site assessment (Dose response only): wound assessment criteria, Centres for Disease Control and Prevention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Early Disease: Nodule hardness</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months post treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Tonometry</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Early Disease: range of motion of the affected digit</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Goniometer reading</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Early Disease: Grip strength</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Jamar meter</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Early Disease: patient reported outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Michigan Hand Outcomes Questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Early Disease: patient reported outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Participant identified activity most restricted by DD scored on a scale of 1-10</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Early Disease: progression to surgery of the digit being assessed</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Response &amp; Early Disease: Circulating levels of adalimumab in the blood</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks (dose response) / 12 months (early disease)</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Response &amp; Early Disease: Circulating levels of antibodies to adalimumab in the blood</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks (dose response) / 12 months (early disease)</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Response: Acceptability of the injection and return to paid work</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks post-surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Patient-completed questionnaire: numeric rating scale</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Early Disease: Cost effectiveness</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>EQ-5D-5L data</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Early disease: Analysis of resource use data</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Patient completed questionnaire about health &amp; social care and financial costs of Dupuytren's disease</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Dose Response &amp; Early Disease: Exploratory Objective: Investigation of newly identified relevant molecular markers</measure>
    <time_frame>Dose Response: 12-18 days post treatment (tissue)/ 2 weeks post treatment (blood). Early Disease: 3 &amp; 12 months post 1st treatment (blood)</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">178</enrollment>
  <condition>Dupuytren's Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Anti-TNF</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>adalimumab</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>saline</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Adalimumab</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Anti-TNF</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Humira</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Saline</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participant is willing and able to give informed consent for participation in the
             study.

          -  Male or Female, aged 18 years or above.

          -  For Part 1: Diagnosed with DD affecting the fingers resulting in flexion deformities
             of ≥30° at the metacarpophalangeal joint and or the proximal interphalangeal joint
             with impaired hand function and awaiting surgery. Or for Part 2: Participants with
             early disease nodules who have shown or reported progression of the disease in the
             previous 6 months with flexion deformities of their fingers of ≤30° at the
             metacarpophalangeal and/or at the proximal interphalangeal joint, i.e. total flexion
             deformity of up to 60°.

          -  The DD nodule to be treated must be distinct and identifiable.

          -  Female participants of child bearing potential, and male participants whose partner is
             of child bearing potential, must be willing to ensure that they or their partner use
             effective contraception throughout the treatment period and for 5 months following the
             last research injection. Acceptable methods of contraception include: a combination of
             male condom with either cap, diaphragm or sponge with spermicide (double barrier
             methods), injectables, the combined oral contraceptive pill (at a stable dose for at
             least 3 months before entering the study), an intrauterine device, vasectomised
             partner, or true sexual abstinence (when this is in line with the preferred and usual
             lifestyle of the participant).

          -  Participant results from safety screening tests within normal ranges within 12 weeks
             of enrolment, with the exception that an earlier clear chest x-ray result may be used
             where this is in accordance with the time frames of local standard procedures for
             anti-TNF screening.

          -  Able (in the Investigators opinion) and willing to comply with all study requirements.

          -  Willing to allow his or her general practitioner to be notified of participation in
             the study.

          -  Sufficient language fluency to ensure informed consent is obtained and to complete the
             questionnaires pertaining to hand function.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  For Part 1: Participant has previously had fasciectomy, dermofasciectomy, needle
             fasciotomy, collagenase injection, steroid injection or radiotherapy to treat
             Dupuytren's disease in the digit concerned. Or for Part 2: Participant has previously
             had fasciectomy, dermofasciectomy, needle fasciotomy, collagenase injection, steroid
             injection to the digit to be treated or radiotherapy to treat Dupuytren's disease in
             the hand concerned.

          -  Female participant who is pregnant, lactating or planning pregnancy during the course
             of the study and for 5 months following last injection.

          -  Male participant who is planning a pregnancy during the course of the study and for 5
             months following last injection.

          -  Significant renal or hepatic impairment.

          -  For Part 1: Scheduled elective surgery or other procedures requiring general
             anaesthesia during the study other than the scheduled Dupuytren's surgery. Or for Part
             2: Scheduled elective surgery or other procedures requiring general anaesthesia during
             the study

          -  Participant who has ever been diagnosed with cancer, is terminally ill or is
             inappropriate for placebo medication

          -  Systemic inflammatory disorder such as rheumatoid arthritis (RA) or inflammatory bowel
             disease.

          -  Any other significant disease or disorder which, in the opinion of the Investigator,
             may either put the participants at risk because of participation in the study, or may
             influence the result of the study, or the participant's ability to participate in the
             study.

          -  Participated in another research study involving an investigational medicinal product
             in the past 12 weeks.

          -  Known allergy to any anti-TNF agent.

          -  Have HIV or hepatitis B or C.

          -  Known to have an infection or history of repeated infections.

          -  History of Tuberculosis (TB).

          -  Have Multiple Sclerosis (MS) or other demyelinating disease.

          -  History of local injection site reactions.

          -  Needle phobia.

          -  Have moderate or severe heart failure.

          -  Part 1: Being treated with coumarin anticoagulants, such as warfarin.

          -  Have known lung fibrosis (thickening of lung tissue).

          -  Being treated with concomitant biologic DMARDS.

          -  Have received a live vaccine within the previous 4 weeks. Participants may receive
             concurrent vaccinations but must avoid the use of live vaccines for 12 weeks after
             their last injection.

          -  Have received parenteral steroid within the previous 6 weeks.

          -  Part 2: Participants at risk of Hepatitis B infection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jagdeep Nanchahal, PhD FRCS</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Oxford</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>RIDD Trial Manager</last_name>
    <phone>+44 (0)0165 612610</phone>
    <email>ridd@kennedy.ox.ac.uk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Queen Victoria Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>East Grinstead</city>
        <zip>RH19 3DZ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Completed</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NHS Lothian</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edinburgh</city>
        <zip>EH1 3EG</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>RIDD Trial Manager</last_name>
      <phone>01865 612610</phone>
      <email>ridd@kennedy.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Oxford University Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oxford</city>
        <zip>OX3 9DU</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>RIDD Trial Manager</last_name>
      <phone>01865 612610</phone>
      <email>ridd@kennedy.ox.ac.uk</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://ridd.octru.ox.ac.uk/</url>
    <description>Trial website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 23, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 7, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 8, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Dupuytren</keyword>
  <keyword>adalimumab</keyword>
  <keyword>anti TNF</keyword>
  <keyword>phase II clinical trial</keyword>
  <keyword>randomized controlled trial</keyword>
  <keyword>double-blind method</keyword>
  <keyword>Dupuytren's</keyword>
  <keyword>Dupuytren's contracture</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Dupuytren Contracture</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Adalimumab</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

