<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03180216</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00008637</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03180216</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>T-Lymphocytes for Prevention or Treatment of Viral Infections Following Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</brief_title>
  <acronym>NATS</acronym>
  <official_title>Novel Antigens Targeted by ex Vivo Expanded T-Lymphocytes for Prevention or Treatment of Viral Infections Following Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Research Institute</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Phase I dose-escalation trial is designed to evaluate the safety of rapidly generated
      multivirus-specific T-cell products with antiviral activity against CMV, EBV, adenovirus,
      HHV6, BK virus, JC virus, and human parainfluenza-3 (HPIV3), derived from eligible HSCT
      donors.

      In this trial, the investigators will utilize a rapid generation protocol for broad spectrum
      multivirus-specific T cells for infusion to recipients of allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell
      transplant (HSCT), who are at risk of developing EBV, CMV, adenovirus, HHV6, BKV and/or
      HPIV3, or with PCR/culture confirmed infection(s). These cells will be derived from HSCT
      donors, and the study agent will be assessed at each dose for evidence of dose-limiting
      toxicities (DLT).

      This study will have two arms: Arm A will include patients who receive prophylactic
      treatment, and Arm B will include patients who receive VSTs for one or more active infections
      with targeted viruses. Determination of the study arm will be determined by the patient's
      clinical status. Study arms will each be analyzed for safety endpoints and secondary
      endpoints.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Viral infections are normally controlled by T-cell immunity and are a cause of significant
      morbidity and mortality during the period of immune recovery after hematopoietic stem cell
      transplantation (HSCT). Risk for infection is impacted by the degree of tissue mismatch
      between donor and recipient and the immune status of the donor, including the degree and
      length of immunosuppression following transplantation. Reactivation of latent viruses such as
      cytomegalovirus (CMV), Epstein-Barr virus (EBV), and Human Herpesvirus 6B (HHV6) are common
      and often cause symptomatic disease. Reactivations of the polyomaviruses BK virus and JC
      virus are also common and frequently cause renal disease including hemorrhagic cystitis and
      less commonly neurologic disease (pervasive multifocal leukoencephalopathy). Respiratory
      viruses such as adenovirus and human parainfluenza also frequently cause infection. Antiviral
      pharmacologic agents are only effective against some of these viruses; their use is costly,
      and associated with significant toxicities and the outgrowth of drug-resistant mutants. As
      delay in recovery of virus-specific cellular immune response is clearly associated with viral
      reactivation and disease in these patients, cellular immunotherapy to restore viral-specific
      immunity is an attractive option that has already been successfully used to target several of
      these viruses.

      To broaden the specificity of single T cells lines to include the three most common viral
      pathogens of stem cell recipients, the investigators reactivated CMV and adenovirus-specific
      T cells by using mononuclear cells transduced with a recombinant adenoviral vector encoding
      the CMV antigen pp65 (Ad5f35CMVpp65). Subsequent stimulations with EBV-LCL transduced with
      the same vector both reactivated EBV-specific T cells and maintained the expansion of the
      activated adenovirus and CMV-specific T cells. This method reliably produced T cells with
      cytotoxic function specific for all three viruses, which the investigators infused into 14
      stem cell recipients in a Phase I prophylaxis study. The investigators observed recovery of
      immunity to CMV and EBV in all patients but an increase in adenovirus-specific T cells was
      only seen in patients who had evidence of adenovirus infection pre-infusion. A follow-up
      study in which the frequency of adenovirus-specific T cells was increased in the infused T
      cells produced similar results, thus highlighting the importance of endogenous antigen to
      promote the expansion of infused T cells in vivo. Nevertheless, all patients in both clinical
      trials with pre-infusion CMV, adenovirus or EBV infection or reactivation were able to clear
      the infection, including one patient with severe adenoviral pneumonia requiring ventilatory
      support. T cells recognizing multiple antigens can therefore produce clinically relevant
      effects against all three viruses.

      Recent studies have extended the number of targeted viruses, and included HHV6B, BK virus,
      and Varicella-zoster virus (VZV). In a recent study, 11 patients were treated with VST
      targeting 5-viruses (CMV, EBV, Adv, HHV6B, BKV) which were generated using a rapid protocol
      with overlapping peptides encompassing 12 viral protein. VST infusion resulted in a 94%
      antiviral response rate in these patients (complete or partial responses against CMV=3/3,
      EBV=5/5, Adv=1/1, HHV6B=2/2, BKV=6/7). Two of the patients who received 5-virus VST developed
      transplant-associated microangiopathy, which was deemed secondary to HSCT and unrelated to
      VST infusion. One of these patients developed grade II skin GVHD, which improved with topical
      therapy. In another recent study, ten adult patients were prophylactically treated with VST
      specific for CMV, EBV, Adv, and Varicella (VZV). These VSTs were generated using
      donor-derived dendritic cells which were infected with either Ad5f35-pp65 or with varivax
      vaccine, and were then pooled and used to stimulate donor PBMCs. All ten patients were
      protected against EBV, Adv, and VZV. Six patients developed CMV reactivation, but only one
      required antiviral therapy. Of these 10 patients, 7 developed acute or chronic GVHD, though
      compared to a non-treated group at the same institution, the rate of GVHD did not differ
      significantly. Thus, it has been possible to target an extended panel of viruses with a
      single VST product.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 15, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of acute GvHD (grade III-IV)</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 45 days of the last VSTs dose</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients with acute GvHD grades III-IV within 45 days of the last dose of VSTs</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events as per CTCAE common criteria guidelines.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 45 days of the last VSTs dose</time_frame>
    <description>2) Grades 3-5 infusion-related adverse events within 45 days of the last dose of VSTs, or 3) Grades 4-5 non-hematological adverse events within 45 days of the last VSTs dose based on a standardized clinical assessment form.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antiviral response</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Peripheral blood and, where relevant, stool and urine will be monitored for viral load by PCR assay. The response in viral load will be defined as follows:
Complete response: Clearance of targeted virus by PCR assay. Partial response: Decrease in viral load of &gt;= 1 log from baseline Mixed response: Decrease in viral load of &gt;= 1 logarithm from baseline for one targeted infection and an increase or no change in viral load for a second infection.
Stable disease: Changes insufficient to qualify as partial response or progression Progression: Increase in viral load in body fluids of &gt;= 1 log from baseline or dissemination to other sites of disease.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antiviral Immunity</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Reconstitution of Antiviral Immunity:
Patient peripheral blood mononuclear cells will be assessed for the presence of virus-reactive T cells using ELIspot and flow cytometry using the MACS Gamma capture kit to assess the percentage of peripheral blood T-cells specific for the targeted virus(es).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Viral Infections</condition>
  <condition>Bone Marrow Transplant Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Prophylactic and treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Virus Specific T cells (VSTs) for prophylactic and treatment of active viral infection(s) after HSCT.
3 different dose levels starting with 1 x 10E7 /m2 (a T cell number more than an order of magnitude lower than that administered at the time of an unmanipulated marrow infusion), followed by 2 x 10E7/m2 and a final dose 5 x 10E7 VSTs/m2</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Virus Specific T cells (VSTs)</intervention_name>
    <description>Pediatric and adult patients following any type of allogeneic transplant (HSCT) will receive VSTs as prophylaxis or treatment of reactivation or infection with CMV, adenovirus, EBV, HHV6, BK virus, JC virus, and/or HPIV3). The goal of this cell infusion will be to initiate an immune response against viral infections after HSCT.
VSTs will be generated using clinical grade overlapping peptides (Pepmixes) to directly stimulate PBMCs, growth promoting cytokines and the G-Rex culture device optimized for T cell expansion. Donor T-cells will be stimulated with overlapping peptide libraries encompassing pp65 and IE-1 (CMV), Hexon and Penton (Adenovirus), LMP2 and EBNA-1 (EBV), LgT and VP1 (BK virus), U54 and U90 (HHV6B), and Mat and NP (HPIV3).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Prophylactic and treatment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Recipient Inclusion Criteria at the time of VST infusion

          1. Prior myeoloablative or non-myeloablative allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell
             transplant using either bone marrow or peripheral blood stem cells no earlier than 5
             days prior to the date of VST infusion, AND

          2. Prophylaxis for patients at risk of CMV, adenovirus, EBV, HHV6, BK virus, JC virus,
             and/or HPIV3 infection, OR

          3. Treatment of reactivation or active infection which is defined for each virus as below

          4. Treatment may be given to eligible patients with a single or multiple infections.
             Patients with multiple infections with one or more reactivation and one or more
             controlled infection are eligible to enroll.

          5. Clinical status at enrollment to allow tapering of steroids to less than 0.5 mg/kg/day
             prednisone or equivalent.

          6. Karnofsky/Lansky score of ≥ 50

          7. Bilirubin &lt;2x upper limit normal

          8. AST &lt; 5 x upper limit normal

          9. Serum creatinine &lt; 2 x upper limit normal

        12. Hgb &gt;8.0 g/dL(level can be achieved with transfusion)

        13. Pulse oximetry of &gt; 90% on room air

        14. Available multivirus-specific T cells (VSTs)

        15. Negative pregnancy test in female patients if applicable (childbearing potential who
        have received a reduced intensity conditioning regimen).

        16. Written informed consent and/or signed assent line from patient, parent or guardian.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Recipient Exclusion criteria at the time of VST infusion:

          1. Patients receiving ATG, Campath, Basiliximab, or other immunosuppressive T cell
             monoclonal antibodies within 28 days of screening for enrollment. In patients who have
             received these therapies as part of their conditioning regimens, 28 days must have
             elapsed since the final dose before VST may be given.

          2. Patients with other uncontrolled infections. For bacterial infections, patients must
             be receiving definitive therapy and have no signs of progressing infection for 72
             hours prior to enrollment. For fungal infections patients must be receiving definitive
             systemic anti-fungal therapy and have no signs of progressing infection for 1 week
             prior to enrollment.

             Progressing infection is defined as worsening clinical symptoms, physical findings,
             vital sign abnormalities (including hemodynamic instability), and/or microbiologic or
             radiographic findings attributable to infection. Persisting fever without other signs
             /symptoms or laboratory evidence will not be interpreted as progressing infection.

          3. Patients who have received donor lymphocyte infusion (DLI) or other cellular therapies
             (with the exception of the allogeneic cells relating to the transplantation) within 28
             days.

          4. Patients with active acute GVHD grades II-IV.

          5. Active and uncontrolled relapse of malignancy

          6. Patients with Grade &gt;3 hyperbilirubinemia

          7. Patients who have received investigational (IND) product within 28 days of screening
             for enrollment under this study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael D Keller, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Michael Keller, MD</last_name>
    <phone>202-476-5843</phone>
    <email>MKeller@childrensnational.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Fahmida Hoq, MBBS, MS</last_name>
    <phone>202-476-2634</phone>
    <email>fhoq@cnmc.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Childrens National Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Washington</city>
        <state>District of Columbia</state>
        <zip>20010</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Fahmida Hoq, MBBS, MS</last_name>
      <phone>202-476-3634</phone>
      <email>fhoq@cnmc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Catherine Bollard, MD</last_name>
      <phone>202-476-4776</phone>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 1, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 6, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 8, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 4, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 4, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Children's Research Institute</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Michael Keller</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor, Division of Allergy / Immunology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infection</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Communicable Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Virus Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

