<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03189485</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>825944</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>R01AG055005</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03189485</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tau PET Imaging in the NACC Study Cohort</brief_title>
  <acronym>TPI</acronym>
  <official_title>Tau PET Imaging in the NACC Study Cohort: Modulators of MTL Subregion Structure and Function in Normal and Pathological Aging</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute on Aging (NIA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to measure the amount of a protein in the brain known as tau
      using an imaging procedure called Positron Emission Tomography (PET/CT). 18F-AV-1451 is a
      specialized radioactive PET imaging agent that is able to detect the presence of tau in the
      brain. In this study, the investigator will use the 18F-AV-1451 to capture images of tau in
      the brain. Findings from this study will likely provide insight into the mechanisms and
      distinctions of age-related cognitive decline and that of very early Alzheimer's disease.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The investigator will conduct a tau PET scan in cognitively normal older adults enrolled in
      the National Alzheimer's Coordinating Center (NACC) study at the University of Pennsylvania's
      Penn Memory Center/Alzheimer's Disease Core Center (PMC/ADC).

      Study Duration: 5 years. Study Center(s): Penn Memory Center/Alzheimer's Disease Core Center
      at Perelman Center for Advanced Medicine, UPHS.

      Objectives: To collect Tau PET imaging in cognitively normal older adults in the NACC study
      to determine relationship to clinical, cognitive, and other biomarker data. In particular,
      the investigator will examine relationship of tau PET to structural and functional measures
      of medial temporal lobe (MTL) subregions. Findings from this study will likely provide
      insight into the mechanisms and distinctions of age-related cognitive decline and that of
      preclinical Alzheimer's Disease.

      Number of Subjects: 100 Diagnosis and Main Inclusion Criteria Eligible subjects will be NACC
      cohort participants who have received a consensus conference designation of &quot;Cognitively
      Normal.&quot; All participants must have had their annual NACC clinical and cognitive examination
      within 6 months of the tau PET imaging and an MRI scan (including high resolution imaging of
      medial temporal lobe regions) and amyloid PET within 6 months.

      Study Design: This is a cross-sectional study using the radiotracer 18F-AV-1451 to determine
      the relationship of tau pathology to both cross-sectional and longitudinal clinical and
      biomarker data of NACC cohort participants who are Cognitively Normal. All subjects will
      already be part of the longitudinal cohort study, known as the &quot;NACC&quot; cohort, of the PMC/ADC.
      For the current protocol, participants will provide informed consent before beginning any
      study procedures. After screening assessments, participants will undergo PET scan imaging
      with 18F-AV-1451.

      Study Drug Administration: Subjects will receive a single IV bolus injection target dose of
      approximately 370 MBq (10 mCi ± 20%) of 18F-AV-1451 At approximately 75 minutes post dose,
      scanning will begin. An approximately 30-minute acquisition (six 5 minute intervals) will be
      performed.

      Adverse events will be monitored continuously during the imaging session. Subjects who
      experience any adverse event during an imaging session will not be discharged until the event
      has resolved or stabilized.

      Statistical Methodology This is a data gathering protocol to obtain molecular imaging data in
      a cohort of older adults without cognitive symptoms. However, specific analyses will include
      quantitative measures of 18F-AV-1451 within the medial temporal lobe (MTL) and its
      relationship to volume and thickness of MTL subregions measured with high-resolution MRI.
      Additional correlation and regression analyses will be performed to determine relationships
      between 18F-AV-1451 and cross-sectional and longitudinal measures acquired as part of each
      individuals participation in the NACC longitudinal cohort study, including, but not limited
      to, MRI imaging, neurocognitive testing, demographic information, genetic data, and clinical
      outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 22, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2022</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 31, 2022</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Early Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine uptake of 18F-AV-1451 in the medial temporal lobe (MTL) and its relationship with high-resolution structural and functional MRI measures of MTL subregions.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Specific analyses will include quantitative measures of 18F-AV-1451 within the medial temporal lobe (MTL) and its relationship to volume and thickness of MTL subregions measured with high-resolution MRI.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine relationship to clinical, cognitive, and other biomarker data</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation and regression analyses will be performed to determine relationships between 18F-AV-1451 and cross-sectional and longitudinal measures acquired as part of each individuals participation in the NACC longitudinal cohort study, including, but not limited to, MRI imaging, neurocognitive testing, demographic information, genetic data, and clinical outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Normal Controls</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>All subjects will receive 18F-AV-1451 PET scan.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>the radiotracer 18F-AV-1451</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will receive a single IV bolus injection target dose of approximately 370 MBq (10 mCi ± 20%) of 18F-AV-1451 At approximately 75 minutes post dose, scanning will begin. An approximately 30-minute acquisition (six 5 minute intervals) will be performed</description>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Controls</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Males and females ≥ 60 years of age.

          -  Part of the NACC longitudinal cohort (Protocol #: 068200) of the PMC/ADCC with
             consensus conference designation of cognitively normal.

          -  NACC longitudinal visit must be completed or scheduled to be completed within 6 months
             of the 18F-AV-1451 TAU PET scan.

          -  A brain MRI must be performed ≤ 6 months prior to enrollment in this study and be
             deemed of adequate quality that the scan may be used for study analysis, including 7
             Tesla high-resolution imaging of medial temporal lobe structures.

          -  An amyloid PET scan ≤ 6 months prior to enrollment in this study

          -  Women must be post-menopausal or surgically sterile

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any medical or psychiatric conditions that, in the opinion of the investigator, would
             compromise the subject's safety or successful participation in the study.

          -  Have evidence of structural abnormalities such as major stroke or mass on MRI that is
             likely to interfere with analysis of the PET scan

          -  Inability to tolerate or contraindication to imaging procedures in the opinion of an
             investigator or treating physician

          -  Have current clinically significant cardiovascular disease or clinically significant
             abnormalities on screening ECG (including but not limited to Fridericia's corrected QT
             (QTcF) &gt;450 msec)

          -  Have a history of significant or ongoing alcohol abuse or substance abuse or
             dependence based on medical record review or self-reported
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Wolk, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UPenn</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 8, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 13, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">June 16, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 18, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 18, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Wolk</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Co Director of the Penn Memory Center</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

