<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00648674</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>07-MOA-001-AG</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00648674</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Post-Marketing Clinical Study of Apligraf for Venous Leg Ulcers</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Prospective, Single-Site Study to Identify and Characterize the Molecular Mechanisms of Apligraf in Non-healing Wounds of Subjects With Venous Leg Ulcers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Organogenesis</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Organogenesis</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Single site clinical study utilizing the novel technology of microarrays to identify and
      characterize the molecular mechanisms through which Apligraf promotes healing of venous leg
      ulcers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To use the novel technology of microarrays to identify and characterize the molecular mechanisms through which Apligraf promotes healing of venous leg ulcers.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine how venous leg ulcer (VLU) wounds transition from chronic to acute wound healing</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine how Apligraf rescues deficiencies of chronic wounds (VLU) and promotes transition from chronic to acute wound</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine growth factors induced by Apligraf in the wound</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine growth factors suppressed by Apligraf in the wound</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety endpoints assessed by monitoring adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>5 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Varicose Ulcer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Apligraf</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Apligraf</intervention_name>
    <description>Applied at Day 0, possible re-application at Week 6</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject has non-infected partial or full-thickness venous leg ulcer for a duration of
             four weeks or greater which has not adequately responded to conventional therapy

          -  Stage II or III ulcer as defined by the IAET/WOCN ulcer classification guide listed in
             Appendix IV.

          -  Subject is female and 18 years of age or older.

          -  Subject with venous leg ulcer (target ulcer) between 5 - 40 cm2 in size.

          -  Sexually active females must be practicing a medically proven form of contraception
             during the course of the study period.

          -  Subject or legal guardian must have read, understood and signed an institutional
             review board (IRB) approved Informed Consent Form.

          -  Subject and/or legal guardian must be able and willing to follow study procedures and
             instructions.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject whose target ulcer has healed 60% or greater in area from post debridement (if
             applicable) Baseline Screen (Visit 1) to post debridement Day 0 (Visit 2) as
             determined by wound tracings.

          -  Subjects who are being treated with VAC® (Vacuum Assisted Closure™) Therapy.

          -  Subject has arterial disease as determined by an Ankle Brachial Index (ABI ) of &lt;0.65.

          -  Subject with any systemic condition like uncontrolled diabetes mellitus (glycosylated
             HbA1C &gt; 12%), cancer (biopsy confirmed active malignancy), positive HIV test, or any
             disorder(s) that may compromise wound healing.

          -  Subjects who are currently receiving, or have received at any time within one month
             prior to entry into the study, corticosteroids (&gt;15 mg/day), immunosuppressive agents,
             radiation therapy, hemodialysis or chemotherapy. Anticipated use of the above agents
             will exclude subjects from entry into the study.

          -  Clinical vasculitis, severe rheumatoid arthritis, and other collagen vascular
             diseases.

          -  Signs and symptoms of cellulitis or osteomyelitis.

          -  Necrotic or avascular ulcer beds.

          -  Venous leg ulcer with exposed bone, tendon or fascia.

          -  Subject with the presence of recent infections in the area intended for treatment.

          -  Known hypersensitivity to bovine collagen or to the components of the Apligraf agarose
             shipping medium.

          -  Subject who is lactating or pregnant (hCG positive as determined by lab testing).

          -  Subject with liver (ALT/SGPT, ALP, AST/SGOT, bilirubin, Albumin, total protein, LDH)
             and/or renal function (BUN and creatinine) tests greater than 2 x upper limit of
             normal (ULN) or Albumin &lt; 2.5 mg/dL.

          -  Subject enrolled in any wound or investigational device study for any disease within
             the past four weeks.

          -  Subject previously treated at target site with Apligraf, Dermagraft or any other cell
             therapy at the target site.

          -  Subject with a history of alcohol or substance abuse within the previous year, which
             could interfere with study compliance such as inability to attend scheduled study
             visits or compliance with home dressing changes.

          -  Subject who, in the opinion of the investigator, for any reason other than those
             listed above, will not be able to complete the study per protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Damien Bates, MD, PhD, FRACS (Plast.)</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Organogenesis Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>August 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 28, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 28, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 1, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 18, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 18, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 19, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Damien Bates, MD, PhD, Chief Medical Officer</name_title>
    <organization>Organogenesis Inc.</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leg Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Varicose Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

