<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00541164</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>05-19</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00541164</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Effects of Coenzyme Q10 on Charcot-Marie-Tooth Disease</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effects of Coenzyme Q10 (CoQ10) on Subjects With Charcot-Marie-Tooth Disease (CMT):A Double Blind, Randomized, Controlled Trial With an Open Label Follow-up Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Memorial Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>United States Department of Defense</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Memorial Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The object of this research is to test the effectiveness of Coenzyme Q10 (CoQ10) on symptoms
      of weakness, fatigue, and pain in persons with Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease (CMT).In this
      study we also intend to examine the impact of daily supplementation on overall quality of
      life.We are also interested in identifying any differences in serum ratios of CoQ10 in the
      oxidized and reduced forms.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      CoQ10 is an integral part of the electron transport chain in the mitochondria, or the energy
      production centers of cells. Within recent years, there has been expanding interest in the
      potential benefits of CoQ10 supplementation on a variety of neuromuscular diseases, some of
      which involve mitochondrial dysfunction, such as CMT. Daily supplementation may have
      cytoprotective and neuroprotective properties, which may improve symptoms of weakness,
      fatigue, and pain, as well as increase quality of life (QOL) among persons with CMT.

      With regards to within group comparisons we hypothesize that daily supplementation of CoQ10
      taken as a 300 milligram wafer twice a day for 3 months will produce a statistically
      significant reduction in weakness, fatigue, and pain, along with a significant improvement in
      QOL as indicated from scores in both standardized physiological and scale measures.

      The addition of serum level analysis will help to contextualize clinical results. We
      hypothesize the ratios of the oxidized and reduced forms of CoQ10 will be modified upon
      supplementation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in weakness, fatigue and pain in persons with Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease after supplementation with 600 mgs a day of Coenzyme Q10.</measure>
    <time_frame>60 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Improvements in quality of life in subjects with CMT before and after CoQ10 supplementation.</measure>
    <time_frame>60 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure blood serum levels of the oxidized and reduced forms of CoQ10.</measure>
    <time_frame>60 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measure liver function tests</measure>
    <time_frame>visits 1, 6, 12</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">23</enrollment>
  <condition>Charcot Marie Tooth Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>300 mg CoQ10 chewable wafer twice a day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Chewable placebo wafer twice a day for 24 weeks with crossover to 300mg CoQ10 twice a day for weeks 24-48.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Coenzyme Q10</intervention_name>
    <description>300 mg CoQ10 twice a day for 48 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>1</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CoQ10</other_name>
    <other_name>Ubiquinone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Coenzyme Q10</intervention_name>
    <description>300mg CoQ10 twice a day for 24 weeks beginning at week 24 of the study</description>
    <arm_group_label>2</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CoQ10</other_name>
    <other_name>Ubiquinone</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must have a diagnosis of CMT, confirmed by review of medical records by the
             study physician

          -  Subjects can be of either gender

          -  Subjects must be between the ages of 18 and 75

          -  Subjects must be able to complete all assessments at the designated time intervals

          -  Subjects must review and sign the informed consent statement according to Conemaugh
             Memorial Medical Center's (CMMC) Institutional Review Board (IRB) guidelines

          -  Subjects must receive approval from their primary care physician (PCP) to enroll in
             the study

          -  Regarding weakness, fatigue, and pain, subjects must experience at least two of the
             three symptoms on most days over the past month

          -  Regarding weakness, fatigue, and pain, subjects must report experiencing maximum
             levels of &gt;/= 3.0 centimeters (cm) on the 10 cm visual analog scale (VAS) for any two
             of the three symptoms over the past month

          -  Female subjects must be willing to practice stable birth control during involvement in
             the study

          -  Subjects must agree to be randomized

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects having another general medical condition, which might confound the assessment
             of weakness, fatigue, and pain due to CMT

          -  Subjects taking warfarin or Coumadin

          -  Subjects who are pregnant, verified by a urine pregnancy test*

          -  Subjects having a cognitive impairment scoring &lt; 20 on the Mini-Mental State Exam

          -  Subjects who are currently using CoQ10 supplementation or have used it in the past 6
             months

          -  Subjects with a history of chronic liver disease or other condition causing
             malabsorption

          -  Drug intake that could modify lipid absorption (such as statins)

          -  Subjects who consume &gt;3 alcoholic drinks per day on more than one occasion per month

          -  Subjects with abnormal liver function tests as defined through a Hepatic -Function
             Panel or a Liver Function Panel

               -  Women of childbearing age who have had at least one menstrual cycle within the
                  past 12 months and who have not undergone a sterilization procedure will undergo
                  a urine pregnancy test at visits 1-10 regardless of group assignment in order to
                  maintain the single blind. The urine samples will be processed at CMMC's lab
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sharon Plank, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>John P. Murtha Neuroscience and Pain Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>John P Murtha Neuroscience and Pain Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Johnstown</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>15904</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hendler SS, Rorvik D, eds. PDR for Nutritional Supplements. Montvale, NJ: Thomson PDR; 2001:105-106.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chaudhuri A, Behan PO. Fatigue in neurological disorders. Lancet. 2004 Mar 20;363(9413):978-88. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15043967</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Beal MF. Coenzyme Q10 as a possible treatment for neurodegenerative diseases. Free Radic Res. 2002 Apr;36(4):455-60. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12069110</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shults CW. Coenzyme Q10 in neurodegenerative diseases. Curr Med Chem. 2003 Oct;10(19):1917-21. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12871093</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bhagavan HN, Chopra RK. Coenzyme Q10: absorption, tissue uptake, metabolism and pharmacokinetics. Free Radic Res. 2006 May;40(5):445-53. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16551570</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Shults CW, Oakes D, Kieburtz K, Beal MF, Haas R, Plumb S, Juncos JL, Nutt J, Shoulson I, Carter J, Kompoliti K, Perlmutter JS, Reich S, Stern M, Watts RL, Kurlan R, Molho E, Harrison M, Lew M; Parkinson Study Group. Effects of coenzyme Q10 in early Parkinson disease: evidence of slowing of the functional decline. Arch Neurol. 2002 Oct;59(10):1541-50.</citation>
    <PMID>12374491</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Huntington Study Group. A randomized, placebo-controlled trial of coenzyme Q10 and remacemide in Huntington's disease. Neurology. 2001 Aug 14;57(3):397-404.</citation>
    <PMID>11502903</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones K, Hughes K, Mischley L, McKenna DJ. Coenzyme Q-10: efficacy, safety, and use. Altern Ther Health Med. 2002 May-Jun;8(3):42-55; quiz 56, 138. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12017500</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lagendijk J, Ubbink JB, Vermaak WJ. Measurement of the ratio between the reduced and oxidized forms of coenzyme Q10 in human plasma as a possible marker of oxidative stress. J Lipid Res. 1996 Jan;37(1):67-75.</citation>
    <PMID>8820103</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 9, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 9, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 10, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 11, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 11, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 15, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>CMT</keyword>
  <keyword>Charcot-Marie Tooth</keyword>
  <keyword>CoQ10</keyword>
  <keyword>Coenzyme Q10</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tooth Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Charcot-Marie-Tooth Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Nerve Compression Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hereditary Sensory and Motor Neuropathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Coenzyme Q10</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ubiquinone</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>April 17, 2014</submitted>
    <returned>May 15, 2014</returned>
    <submitted>October 3, 2014</submitted>
    <returned>October 9, 2014</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

