<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00542438</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2007-0278</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2011-02917</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00542438</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Home-Based Measures of Physical Activity and Body Composition</brief_title>
  <official_title>Feasibility and Validity of Home-Based Measures of Physical Activity and Body Composition</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The specific aim of this study is to collect preliminary data on the feasibility and validity
      of home-based data collection methods to measure four constructs:

        -  Physical Activity: Real-time assessment using Ecological Momentary Assessment (EMA) and
           pedometers

        -  Cardiorespiratory Fitness: Step test

        -  Anthropometry: Waist and hip circumference measurements

        -  Environmental Variables: Examples include density of neighborhood physical activity
           facilities (including gyms, parks, walking trails), crime, land use mix, and
           transportation variables, collected by participants using EMA.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      SCREENING PHONE CALL:

      If you are interested in taking part in this study, the study staff will contact you by phone
      and you will answer questions about your physical ability to exercise. Based on the answers
      you give, the study doctor will decide if you are eligible to participate. The phone call
      will last about 10-15 minutes.

      STUDY PROCEDURES:

      If you are found to be eligible to take part in this study, you will be randomly assigned (as
      in the toss of a coin) to complete physical activity recall and environmental assessments on
      a palm pilot either 3 times a day or once a day. For the physical activity recall assessment,
      you will describe what types of physical activity you did that day. The environmental
      assessments will be to describe your current location or environment. It should take less
      than 5 minutes to complete each assessment.

      Visit 1:

      You will come to the M. D. Anderson Behavioral Research and Treatment Center for 2 visits. At
      the first visit, the following tests and procedures will be performed:

        -  Your height and weight will be measured.

        -  You will complete a questionnaire about your health, your neighborhood, and your
           physical activity. The questionnaire will take about 30 minutes to complete.

        -  You will walk on a treadmill while your heart rate, blood pressure, and respiration
           (breathing) are monitored. You will walk until you feel fatigued.

      The research staff will then give you instructions for the tests you will do at home. This
      visit will last about 120 minutes.

      At Home Activities:

      During the next week, you will wear a pedometer and an actigraph. These are small devices
      that you wear on your waist during the day from the time you get up in the morning to when
      you go to bed at night. You will not wear the devices in water. These devices will record how
      active you are.

      You will answer questions on a handheld computer 5-7 times each day. These questions will ask
      about your physical activity and about how your environment may encourage or discourage
      physical activity. It will take between 30 seconds and 3 minutes to answer the questions each
      time.

      You will measure the distance around your waist and hips (circumference). You will do a
      fitness test that involves stepping up and down on a small stool for 3 minutes. You will take
      your heart rate after the stool-stepping exercise. The study staff will give you all the
      equipment and supplies needed for these tests at the first visit, and you will be asked to
      return the equipment at the second visit.

      Visit 2:

      Seven (7) days after the first visit, you will return to M. D. Anderson for the second visit.
      The following tests and procedures will be performed:

        -  You will perform the stool-stepping test.

        -  You will have your waist and hip circumference measured.

        -  You will be asked about your physical activity over the past week.

      This visit will take about 60 minutes.

      LENGTH OF STUDY:

      You will be off-study once you complete Visit 2.

      This is an investigational study. Up to 75 individuals will take part in the study. All will
      be enrolled at M. D. Anderson.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Feasibility of home-based data collection methods: Percentage of Participants Completing Step Test</measure>
    <time_frame>3 Years</time_frame>
    <description>Feasibility measured by the percentage of participants who have adequate cardiorespiratory fitness (i.e., V02 max greater than or equal to 31) to perform the step test. Researchers will consider the test feasible if greater than or equal to 75% of the participants have adequate fitness to perform the test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">75</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physical Activity Recall</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Hand-held computers will be used to record information for 7 days about physical activity. Assessments will be completed either 3 times a day or once a day.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Environmental Assessment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Environmental assessments on a palm pilot either 3 times a day or once a day. Hand-held computer programs will be used to collect information about the community. Some factors will be assessed only once (e.g., availability of facilities) while other information will be collected over the course of 7 days (e.g., perceptions of neighborhood safety).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Physical Activity Recall</intervention_name>
    <description>Hand-held computers will be used to record information for 7 days about physical activity. Assessments will be completed either 3 times a day or once a day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Physical Activity Recall</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Environmental Assessments</intervention_name>
    <description>Hand-held computer programs will be used to collect information about the community. Some factors will be assessed only once (e.g., availability of facilities) while other information will be collected over the course of 7 days (e.g., perceptions of neighborhood safety).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Environmental Assessment</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. low-risk for cardiovascular disease, as defined by the American College of Sports
             Medicine (under 45 years of age for men and under 55 years of age for women, and less
             than two cardiovascular risk factors)

          2. speaks English

          3. able to give informed consent

          4. no previous cancer diagnosis

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. pregnant women

          2. children under 18
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karen Basen-Engquist, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.mdanderson.org</url>
    <description>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center Website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 10, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 10, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 11, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 16, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cardiovascular Disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Cancer Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Physical Activity</keyword>
  <keyword>Body Composition</keyword>
  <keyword>Environment</keyword>
  <keyword>Exercise</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

