<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00548626</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15497A</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00548626</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Multiple Needle Use in EUS-FNA for Pancreatic Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>EMUNE-07</acronym>
  <official_title>EMUNE-07 Evaluation of Multiple Needle Use in EUS-FNA for Pancreatic Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Chicago</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cook Group Incorporated</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Chicago</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to evaluate if the early change of needle during EUS-FNA for
      suspected pancreatic cancer allows an earlier preliminary cytological diagnosis of neoplasia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective randomized controlled trial which will recruit patients referred for
      suspicion of pancreatic mass and indication of EUS-FNA as part of standard of care in the
      Interventional Endoscopy Unit at the University Of Chicago Medical Center. Basic demographic
      data will be recorded for each patient. If a pancreatic mass is confirmed in EUS evaluation
      the patient will be randomized in a 1:1 ratio to either Control group (Single needle) or
      Investigational group (Multiple Needle). There will be an expert cytopathologist in the
      exploration room (blinded to the group assignment). Samples obtained through FNA will be
      prepared onsite either for cytological evaluation by the cytopathologist: each fine needle
      sample will be expressed by using a 10mL air-filled syringe onto a separate glass slide, and
      a direct smear will be made by an on-site cytopathologist. Each slide will be air-dried
      and/or alcohol fixed (95% ethanol), and direct smears will be prepared for immediate
      interpretation by staining with Diff-quick staining system.

      Patients assigned to simple needle group (SN) will be sampled for a total of 6 consecutive
      FNA passes with a single EUS-FNA needle (only replaced if the needle has a reduced
      performance). After completing the 6th pass the endoscopist will be informed by the onsite
      cytopathologist about the preliminary cytological diagnosis.

      Patients assigned to multiple needle group (MN) will be sampled for a total of 6 consecutive
      FNA passes, replacing the needle after every 2 passes. After completing the 6th pass the
      endoscopist will be informed by the onsite cytopathologist about the preliminary cytological
      diagnosis.

      A cytopathologist (#1) will be present during each EUS-FNA procedure to prepare the slides
      and determine whether each specimen was adequately cellular. After the procedure, all the
      cytological samples will be sent to the Pathology department in order to complete the study.
      A cytopathologist (#2) not present during the procedure will study all the sampling specimens
      obtained during the EUS-FNA procedure and produce the final and definitive cytopathological
      diagnosis.

      Criteria for pancreatic cancer and benign pancreatic lesions will be defined. Follow-up of
      all patients to assess early and late complications will be carried out for 30 days after the
      procedure.

      Endpoints:

        1. Primary endpoint: Evaluate if the early change of needle during EUS-FNA for suspected
           pancreatic cancer can reduce the number of passes needed to obtain a preliminary
           cytological diagnosis of neoplasia. We hypothesized that the number of passes needed
           using the multiple needles will be significantly less than that using the single needle.

        2. Secondary endpoints:

             -  Rate of complications related with EUS-FNA

             -  Influence of different factors in obtaining a positive cytological result
                (histological differentiation)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate if the early change of needle during EUS-FNA for suspected pancreatic cancer can reduce the number of passes needed to obtain a preliminary cytological diagnosis of neoplasia.</measure>
    <time_frame>October 2007- September 2008</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of complications related with EUS-FNA</measure>
    <time_frame>October 2007- September 2008</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Influence of different factors in obtaining a positive cytological result</measure>
    <time_frame>October 2007- September 2008</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">47</enrollment>
  <condition>Pancreatic Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients assigned to simple needle group (SN) will be sampled for a total of 6 consecutive FNA passes with a single EUS-FNA needle (only replaced if the needle has a reduced performance). After completing the 6th pass the endoscopist will be informed by the onsite cytopathologist about the preliminary cytological diagnosis.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients assigned to multiple needle group (MN) will be sampled for a total of 6 consecutive FNA passes, replacing the needle after every 2 passes. After completing the 6th pass the endoscopist will be informed by the onsite cytopathologist about the preliminary cytological diagnosis.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Single needle</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be sampled for a total of 6 consecutive FNA passes with a single EUS-FNA needle (only replaced if the needle has a reduced performance). After completing the 6th pass the endoscopist will be informed by the onsite cytopathologist about the preliminary cytological diagnosis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>A</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multiple needle</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be sampled for a total of 6 consecutive FNA passes, replacing the needle after every 2 passes. After completing the 6th pass the endoscopist will be informed by the onsite cytopathologist about the preliminary cytological diagnosis.</description>
    <arm_group_label>B</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Suspicion of pancreatic mass due to previous exam/s (CT, MR, ERCP, US, …) that
             requires EUS-FNA in order to complete diagnosis

          -  Age ≥ 18 y/o

          -  Formal informed consent

          -  No previous chemotherapy or radiotherapy

          -  No previous pancreatic surgery

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any patient unable to understand the procedure, nature of the current study, or sign a
             consent form.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Irving Waxman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Medicine, University of Chicago Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Chicago Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60637</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>LeBlanc JK, Ciaccia D, Al-Assi MT, McGrath K, Imperiale T, Tao LC, Vallery S, DeWitt J, Sherman S, Collins E. Optimal number of EUS-guided fine needle passes needed to obtain a correct diagnosis. Gastrointest Endosc. 2004 Apr;59(4):475-81.</citation>
    <PMID>15044881</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wallace MB, Kennedy T, Durkalski V, Eloubeidi MA, Etamad R, Matsuda K, Lewin D, Van Velse A, Hennesey W, Hawes RH, Hoffman BJ. Randomized controlled trial of EUS-guided fine needle aspiration techniques for the detection of malignant lymphadenopathy. Gastrointest Endosc. 2001 Oct;54(4):441-7.</citation>
    <PMID>11577304</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eloubeidi MA, Tamhane A, Varadarajulu S, Wilcox CM. Frequency of major complications after EUS-guided FNA of solid pancreatic masses: a prospective evaluation. Gastrointest Endosc. 2006 Apr;63(4):622-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16564863</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eloubeidi MA, Gress FG, Savides TJ, Wiersema MJ, Kochman ML, Ahmad NA, Ginsberg GG, Erickson RA, Dewitt J, Van Dam J, Nickl NJ, Levy MJ, Clain JE, Chak A, Sivak MV Jr, Wong R, Isenberg G, Scheiman JM, Bounds B, Kimmey MB, Saunders MD, Chang KJ, Sharma A, Nguyen P, Lee JG, Edmundowicz SA, Early D, Azar R, Etemad B, Chen YK, Waxman I, Shami V, Catalano MF, Wilcox CM. Acute pancreatitis after EUS-guided FNA of solid pancreatic masses: a pooled analysis from EUS centers in the United States. Gastrointest Endosc. 2004 Sep;60(3):385-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15332028</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harewood GC, Wiersema MJ. Endosonography-guided fine needle aspiration biopsy in the evaluation of pancreatic masses. Am J Gastroenterol. 2002 Jun;97(6):1386-91.</citation>
    <PMID>12094855</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eloubeidi MA, Jhala D, Chhieng DC, Chen VK, Eltoum I, Vickers S, Mel Wilcox C, Jhala N. Yield of endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine-needle aspiration biopsy in patients with suspected pancreatic carcinoma. Cancer. 2003 Oct 25;99(5):285-92.</citation>
    <PMID>14579295</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>O'Toole D, Palazzo L, Arotçarena R, Dancour A, Aubert A, Hammel P, Amaris J, Ruszniewski P. Assessment of complications of EUS-guided fine-needle aspiration. Gastrointest Endosc. 2001 Apr;53(4):470-4.</citation>
    <PMID>11275888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wiersema MJ, Vilmann P, Giovannini M, Chang KJ, Wiersema LM. Endosonography-guided fine-needle aspiration biopsy: diagnostic accuracy and complication assessment. Gastroenterology. 1997 Apr;112(4):1087-95.</citation>
    <PMID>9097990</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Niederhuber JE, Brennan MF, Menck HR. The National Cancer Data Base report on pancreatic cancer. Cancer. 1995 Nov 1;76(9):1671-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8635074</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Binmoeller KF, Thul R, Rathod V, Henke P, Brand B, Jabusch HC, Soehendra N. Endoscopic ultrasound-guided, 18-gauge, fine needle aspiration biopsy of the pancreas using a 2.8 mm channel convex array echoendoscope. Gastrointest Endosc. 1998 Feb;47(2):121-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9512275</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cotton PB, Lehman G, Vennes J, Geenen JE, Russell RC, Meyers WC, Liguory C, Nickl N. Endoscopic sphincterotomy complications and their management: an attempt at consensus. Gastrointest Endosc. 1991 May-Jun;37(3):383-93. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2070995</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mortensen MB, Pless T, Durup J, Ainsworth AP, Plagborg GJ, Hovendal C. Clinical impact of endoscopic ultrasound-guided fine needle aspiration biopsy in patients with upper gastrointestinal tract malignancies. A prospective study. Endoscopy. 2001 Jun;33(6):478-83.</citation>
    <PMID>11437039</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 22, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 23, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 24, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 18, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 18, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 21, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pancreatic Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Endoscopic Ultrasonography</keyword>
  <keyword>Fine-Needle Aspiration</keyword>
  <keyword>Cytopathology</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pancreatic Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

