<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00542191</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LJCC 07-03</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00542191</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Trial of Neoadjuvant Metronomic Chemotherapy in Triple-Negative Breast Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Trial of Neoadjuvant Metronomic Chemotherapy in Triple-Negative Breast Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Leo W. Jenkins Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Leo W. Jenkins Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This neoadjuvant chemotherapy protocol focusing on &quot;triple-negative&quot; breast cancers alone
      will gather a foundation of primary tumor and axillary lymph nodal response to primary
      chemotherapy and ongoing correlated disease-free (DFS) and overall survival (OS) outcome
      data. This comparative data can then be used in building subsequent trials.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Women with a diagnosed &quot;triple-negative&quot; proxy of basal-like breast cancer confirmed on a
      core biopsy and larger than 2 cm will be treated neoadjuvantly with the Livingston metronomic
      regimen of 12 weeks of weekly doxorubicin 24 mg/m2 and daily oral cyclophosphamide 60 mg/m2
      followed by 12 successive weeks of taxol 80 mg/m2 and carboplatin AUC 2. Although clinical
      response will be evaluated prior to surgery, the primary end-point is the pathologic
      response. Secondary end-points will be DFS and OS based upon standard of care surveillance. A
      pathologic complete response (pCR) will require no histologic evidence of residual malignant
      cells seen in the primary tumor area specimen or the lymph nodes. Standard of care surgery
      and radiation therapy will be undertaken.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Enrollment Completed
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>July 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>1) Pathologic response</measure>
    <time_frame>within 3 weeks of completing neoadjuvant chemotherapy</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>1) Clinical response 2) Disease free survival (DFS) 3) Overall Survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing clinical surveillance follow-up assessing Disease Free and Overall Survival</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm study; taxol, XRT, gemzar and carbo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Doxorubicin / Cyclophosphamide / Paclitaxel / Carboplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>DOXORUBICIN 24mg/m2 IV plus CYCLOPHOSPHAMIDE 60mg/m2 PO weekly x 12 successive weeks followed by PACLITAXEL 80mg/m2 IV over 1 hour plus CARBOPLATIN AUC 2 IV weekly x 12 successive weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm study; taxol, XRT, gemzar and carbo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Definitive Surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard of care definitive surgery as determined by medical provider</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm study; taxol, XRT, gemzar and carbo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Radiotherapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Standard of care RADIATION THERAPY as indicated</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm study; taxol, XRT, gemzar and carbo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with Estrogen Receptor (ER), Progesterone Receptor (PR),and HER2 negative
             invasive breast cancer confirmed on core biopsy.(Note: HER2 negative by FISH
             preferred; HER2 0 or 1+ by IHC acceptable)

          -  Primary tumor size 2cm or greater by physical exam or radiographic measurements.(Note:
             Locally advanced T4 or inflammatory breast cancer is eligible.)

          -  Assessment of pre-treatment axillary lymph nodal status (Note: FNA biopsy if palpable
             or sentinel lymph node biopsy (SLNB) if not palpable preferred; clinical exam
             acceptable.)

          -  Absolute neutrophil count &gt; 1500 mm3 and platelet count &gt; 100,000 mm3

          -  Normal myocardial left ventricular function

          -  Serum creatinine &lt; 2.0 mg/dl

          -  Total bilirubin and AST &lt; 3X upper limits normal

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Recurrent or metastatic breast cancer findings (Note: If oncologically felt to be a
             second breast primary, patient eligible for this protocol)

          -  Another active cancer present

          -  Medical contraindications to chemotherapy or surgery

          -  First trimester pregnancy

          -  Breast feeding
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul Walker, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brody School of Medicine at East Carolina University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brody School of Medicine at East Carolina University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Greenville</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27834</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sørlie T, Perou CM, Tibshirani R, Aas T, Geisler S, Johnsen H, Hastie T, Eisen MB, van de Rijn M, Jeffrey SS, Thorsen T, Quist H, Matese JC, Brown PO, Botstein D, Lønning PE, Børresen-Dale AL. Gene expression patterns of breast carcinomas distinguish tumor subclasses with clinical implications. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2001 Sep 11;98(19):10869-74.</citation>
    <PMID>11553815</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perou CM, Sørlie T, Eisen MB, van de Rijn M, Jeffrey SS, Rees CA, Pollack JR, Ross DT, Johnsen H, Akslen LA, Fluge O, Pergamenschikov A, Williams C, Zhu SX, Lønning PE, Børresen-Dale AL, Brown PO, Botstein D. Molecular portraits of human breast tumours. Nature. 2000 Aug 17;406(6797):747-52.</citation>
    <PMID>10963602</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sotiriou C, Neo SY, McShane LM, Korn EL, Long PM, Jazaeri A, Martiat P, Fox SB, Harris AL, Liu ET. Breast cancer classification and prognosis based on gene expression profiles from a population-based study. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2003 Sep 2;100(18):10393-8. Epub 2003 Aug 13.</citation>
    <PMID>12917485</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brenton JD, Carey LA, Ahmed AA, Caldas C. Molecular classification and molecular forecasting of breast cancer: ready for clinical application? J Clin Oncol. 2005 Oct 10;23(29):7350-60. Epub 2005 Sep 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16145060</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Nielsen TO, Hsu FD, Jensen K, Cheang M, Karaca G, Hu Z, Hernandez-Boussard T, Livasy C, Cowan D, Dressler L, Akslen LA, Ragaz J, Gown AM, Gilks CB, van de Rijn M, Perou CM. Immunohistochemical and clinical characterization of the basal-like subtype of invasive breast carcinoma. Clin Cancer Res. 2004 Aug 15;10(16):5367-74.</citation>
    <PMID>15328174</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chang HY, Nuyten DS, Sneddon JB, Hastie T, Tibshirani R, Sørlie T, Dai H, He YD, van't Veer LJ, Bartelink H, van de Rijn M, Brown PO, van de Vijver MJ. Robustness, scalability, and integration of a wound-response gene expression signature in predicting breast cancer survival. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2005 Mar 8;102(10):3738-43. Epub 2005 Feb 8.</citation>
    <PMID>15701700</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Turner N, Tutt A, Ashworth A. Hallmarks of 'BRCAness' in sporadic cancers. Nat Rev Cancer. 2004 Oct;4(10):814-9. doi: 10.1038/nrc1457. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15510162</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carey LA, Perou CM, Livasy CA, Dressler LG, Cowan D, Conway K, Karaca G, Troester MA, Tse CK, Edmiston S, Deming SL, Geradts J, Cheang MC, Nielsen TO, Moorman PG, Earp HS, Millikan RC. Race, breast cancer subtypes, and survival in the Carolina Breast Cancer Study. JAMA. 2006 Jun 7;295(21):2492-502.</citation>
    <PMID>16757721</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berry DA, Cirrincione C, Henderson IC, Citron ML, Budman DR, Goldstein LJ, Martino S, Perez EA, Muss HB, Norton L, Hudis C, Winer EP. Estrogen-receptor status and outcomes of modern chemotherapy for patients with node-positive breast cancer. JAMA. 2006 Apr 12;295(14):1658-67. Erratum in: JAMA. 2006 May 24;295(20):2356.</citation>
    <PMID>16609087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kennedy RD, Quinn JE, Mullan PB, Johnston PG, Harkin DP. The role of BRCA1 in the cellular response to chemotherapy. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2004 Nov 17;96(22):1659-68. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15547178</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kerbel RS, Klement G, Pritchard KI, Kamen B. Continuous low-dose anti-angiogenic/ metronomic chemotherapy: from the research laboratory into the oncology clinic. Ann Oncol. 2002 Jan;13(1):12-5.</citation>
    <PMID>11863092</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robert N, Leyland-Jones B, Asmar L, Belt R, Ilegbodu D, Loesch D, Raju R, Valentine E, Sayre R, Cobleigh M, Albain K, McCullough C, Fuchs L, Slamon D. Randomized phase III study of trastuzumab, paclitaxel, and carboplatin compared with trastuzumab and paclitaxel in women with HER-2-overexpressing metastatic breast cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2006 Jun 20;24(18):2786-92.</citation>
    <PMID>16782917</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perez EA, Suman VJ, Rowland KM, Ingle JN, Salim M, Loprinzi CL, Flynn PJ, Mailliard JA, Kardinal CG, Krook JE, Thrower AR, Visscher DW, Jenkins RB. Two concurrent phase II trials of paclitaxel/carboplatin/trastuzumab (weekly or every-3-week schedule) as first-line therapy in women with HER2-overexpressing metastatic breast cancer: NCCTG study 983252. Clin Breast Cancer. 2005 Dec;6(5):425-32.</citation>
    <PMID>16381626</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaufmann M, Hortobagyi GN, Goldhirsch A, Scholl S, Makris A, Valagussa P, Blohmer JU, Eiermann W, Jackesz R, Jonat W, Lebeau A, Loibl S, Miller W, Seeber S, Semiglazov V, Smith R, Souchon R, Stearns V, Untch M, von Minckwitz G. Recommendations from an international expert panel on the use of neoadjuvant (primary) systemic treatment of operable breast cancer: an update. J Clin Oncol. 2006 Apr 20;24(12):1940-9. Erratum in: J Clin Oncol. 2006 Jul 1;24(19):3221.</citation>
    <PMID>16622270</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hennessy BT, Hortobagyi GN, Rouzier R, Kuerer H, Sneige N, Buzdar AU, Kau SW, Fornage B, Sahin A, Broglio K, Singletary SE, Valero V. Outcome after pathologic complete eradication of cytologically proven breast cancer axillary node metastases following primary chemotherapy. J Clin Oncol. 2005 Dec 20;23(36):9304-11.</citation>
    <PMID>16361629</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Buzdar AU, Ibrahim NK, Francis D, Booser DJ, Thomas ES, Theriault RL, Pusztai L, Green MC, Arun BK, Giordano SH, Cristofanilli M, Frye DK, Smith TL, Hunt KK, Singletary SE, Sahin AA, Ewer MS, Buchholz TA, Berry D, Hortobagyi GN. Significantly higher pathologic complete remission rate after neoadjuvant therapy with trastuzumab, paclitaxel, and epirubicin chemotherapy: results of a randomized trial in human epidermal growth factor receptor 2-positive operable breast cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2005 Jun 1;23(16):3676-85. Epub 2005 Feb 28.</citation>
    <PMID>15738535</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rouzier R, Anderson K, Hess KR, et al: Basal and luminal types of breast cancer defined by gene expression patterns respond differently to neoadjuvant chemotherapy. San Antonio Breast Cancer Symposium. San Antonio, TX, 2004 (abstr 1023)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carey LA, Dees EC, Sawyer L, et al: The triple negative paradox: Primary tumor chemosensitivity of the basal-like breast cancer (BBC) phenotype. San Antonio Breast Cancer Symposium. San Antonio, TX, 2004 (abstr 1023)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jacquemier J, Penault-Llorca F, Mnif H, et al: Identification of a basal-like subtype and comparative effect of epirubicin-based chemotherapy and sequential epirubicin followed by docetaxel chemotherapy in the PACS 01 breast cancer trial: 33 markers studied on tissue microarrays (TMA). J Clin Oncol 2006 (suppl; abstr 509)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hudis C, Citron M, Berry D, et al: Five-year follow-up of INT C9741: dose-dense chemotherapy is safe and effective. San Antonio Breast Cancer Symposium. San Antonio, TX, 2005 (abstr 41)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ellis GK, Livingston RB, Rinn K, et al: Pilot adjuvant study: 12 weeks of dose dense doxorubicin with scheduled G-CSF support followed by 4 cycles of docetaxel. J Clin Oncol 2003 (suppl; abstr 148)</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ellis GK, Barlow WE, Gralow JR, Hortobagyi GN, Russell CA, Royce ME, Perez EA, Lew D, Livingston RB. Phase III comparison of standard doxorubicin and cyclophosphamide versus weekly doxorubicin and daily oral cyclophosphamide plus granulocyte colony-stimulating factor as neoadjuvant therapy for inflammatory and locally advanced breast cancer: SWOG 0012. J Clin Oncol. 2011 Mar 10;29(8):1014-21. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2009.27.6543. Epub 2011 Jan 10.</citation>
    <PMID>21220618</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>August 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 9, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 9, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 10, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">August 24, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Triple negative (ER/PR negative; HER2 negative)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Triple Negative Breast Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Paclitaxel</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liposomal doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cyclophosphamide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carboplatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Doxorubicin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>March 13, 2018</submitted>
    <returned>April 9, 2018</returned>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

