<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00547768</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>M016455A_4144</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00547768</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparative Study Evaluating the Effects of Fexofenadine HCI 180 mg With Orange Juice Versus Placebo With Orange Juice in a Skin Wheal and Flare Challenge Model.</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sanofi</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Sanofi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Compare the effect of a single dose of fexofenadine HCl 180 mg plus orange juice versus
      placebo plus orange juice on the change from baseline (pre-dose) in histamine skin flares.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2002</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2002</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Size of change in skin flares from baseline measured at pre-specified times post-dose.</measure>
    <time_frame>20 min, 40 min, 60 min, and hourly through 12 hours, with an additional 2 time points obtained at Hours 23 and 24.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Size and change in skin wheals from baseline measured at pre-specified time points.</measure>
    <time_frame>20 min, 40 min, 60 min, and hourly through 12 hours, with an additional 2 time points.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Allergy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Fexofenadine HCI</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy male or non-pregnant, non-lactating female subjects; 12-55 years of age;
             within 15% of normal body weight for their height or had a body mass index (BMI) less
             than 29.9 kg/m2; positive histamine skin prick tests (or a duplicate histamine skin
             prick test) of summation flare &gt; 20 mm larger than diluent control, and summation
             wheal &gt; 6 mm larger than diluent control at the screening Visit 1.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Asthma that required treatment with medication other than an inhaled, short-acting
             beta agonist

          -  Signs and symptoms of currently active allergic disease (SAR, perennial allergic
             rhinitis, episodic allergic rhinitis)

          -  Upper respiratory tract infection, sinusitis, asthma or flu-like symptoms within 2
             weeks prior to Visit 1

          -  Dermatographism or other skin conditions that might interfere with the interpretation
             of the skin test results

          -  Treatment with escalating doses of immunotherapy, oral immunotherapy, or short course
             (rush) immunotherapy

          -  Any excessive amounts of alcohol (no more than two drinks/day on average)

          -  Any excessive use of caffeine (more than six cups of coffee per day or equivalent)

          -  Any history of chronic alcohol or mood-altering drug abuse

          -  Any use of tobacco/nicotine products within 90 days of visit 1

          -  Any disease state or surgery known to affect the gastrointestinal absorption of drugs

          -  Treatment with an H1-receptor antagonist regularly within the past year before study
             entry

          -  Known hypersensitivity to the investigational product or to drugs with similar
             chemical properties, or to orange juice

          -  Need to visit a tanning salon during the study

          -  Need to use artificial tanning products during the study

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Breast-feeding

          -  Likelihood of requiring treatment during the study period with drugs not permitted by
             the clinical study protocol (see Section 6.2)

          -  Treatment with any investigational product in the last 30 days before study entry

          -  Clinically relevant cardiovascular, hepatic, neurologic, endocrine, or other major
             systemic disease making implementation of the protocol or interpretation of the study
             results difficult

          -  Mental condition rendering the subject unable to understand the nature, scope, and
             possible consequences of the study

          -  Unlikelihood of complying with protocol, e.g., uncooperative attitude, inability to
             return for follow-up visits, and unlikelihood of completing the study.

          -  Use of any of the following drugs within the time indicated prior to the first dosing
             visit (Time prior to Visit 2):

          -  Systemic or injected corticosteroids (including oral, parenteral, intravenous,
             rectal)(30 days).

          -  Nasal or inhaled or ocular corticosteroids (30 days).

          -  Nasal or inhaled ipratropium bromide (or atropine), inhaled nedocromil, or nasal,
             inhaled, or ophthalmic sodium cromolyn (14 days)

          -  Agents with antihistaminic/anticholinergic activity (e.g.antidepressants,
             antipsychotics)(14 days).

          -  Leukotriene pathway modifiers (Accolate®, Singulair®, Zyflo®) 10 days Ocular
             anti-allergy medications including lodoxamide (Alomide®), olopatadine (Patanol®),
             emedastine difumarate (Emadine®), levocabastine (Livostin®) (10 days).

          -  Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory ophthalmics including ketorolac (Acular®),
             flurbiprofen (Ocufen®), suprofen (Profenal®), diclofenac (Voltaren®) (10 days).

          -  Antihistamines including desloratadine (Clarinex®), loratadine (Claritin®)(10 days).

          -  Fexofenadine HCl (Allegra®), cetirizine (Zyrtec®), hydroxyzine, azelastine nasal spray
             (Astelin®), clemastine (7 days)

          -  Other short-acting antihistamines such as chlorpheniramine or drugs with
             antihistaminic activity (3 days).

          -  OTC oral antihistamines, decongestants (includes pseudoephedrine and other
             decongestants), or antihistamines/decongestant combinations including all cold, cough,
             and sleep aids (3 days).

          -  OTC ophthalmic decongestant, antihistamine, or decongestant/ antihistamine
             combinations (3 days).

          -  Other anticholinergic agents (3 days).

          -  Immunotherapy injection (1 day).

          -  Other drugs were to be permitted if they were not expected to interfere with the
             ability of the subject to participate in the study.

          -  Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents were not allowed for 2 days prior to each
             treatment visit day through 24 hours post-dose.

          -  Medications or agents not specified above that might confound the interpretation of
             the results were prohibited as follows:

          -  Caffeine within 6 hours prior to each visit (coffee, tea, cola, including Mountain Dew
             and Surge).

          -  Decaffeinated coffee, tea and colas within 6 hours of each visit

          -  Alcohol within 24 hours prior to each study visit.

          -  Chocolate within 6 hours prior to each visit.

          -  Antacids within + 2 hours of investigational product dosing.

          -  Any waiver of these inclusion and exclusion criteria required approval by the
             investigator and the sponsor on a case-by-case basis prior to enrolling the subject.
             Approval had to be documented by both the sponsor and the investigator.

          -  No subject was to be allowed to enroll in this study more than once.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>12 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Phyllis Diener</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Sanofi</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sanofi-Aventis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bridgewater</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>08807</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 22, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 22, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 23, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 10, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 10, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 11, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fexofenadine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Terfenadine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

