<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00973648</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>09-0481</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00973648</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Exploring Voluntary Control of Tinnitus</brief_title>
  <official_title>Exploring Voluntary Control of Tinnitus: A Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Washington University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This pilot study aims to increase the understanding of tinnitus through the identification of
      potentially altered brain networks in patients who are able to voluntarily control or alter
      their tinnitus. Upon completion of this study, new knowledge will be gained about the changes
      in brain activity in people who are able to modify their tinnitus.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Certain patients report that they are able to modulate the loudness or pitch of their
      tinnitus temporarily through various means, including attention re-direction or somatosensory
      mechanisms such as oral facial movements or head turn. This subset of patients may represent
      a unique opportunity for the researcher to gain insight into the mechanisms responsible for
      tinnitus.

      Neural activity in the brain has been linked to increases in blood flow and blood
      oxygenation. These changes in the concentration of oxyhemoglobin versus deoxyhemoglobin alter
      the magnetic resonance signal of blood which may then be detected using an appropriate MR
      pulse sequence as blood-oxygen-level-dependent (BOLD) contrast. In addition to increases in
      blood flow due to evoked neural activity, the brain exhibits continuous low frequency
      spontaneous activity. These fluctuations tend to be synchronous in functionally related, but
      spatially distinct, regions of the brain even when not performing a prescribed task. The
      phrase functional connectivity has been used to implicate the neural activity that
      facilitates the coordinated activity of functionally related brain regions.

      This study will use functional connectivity magnetic resonance imaging (fcMRI) to measure the
      network of synchronous brain activity in patients with tinnitus. Several targeted networks
      are those linked to the auditory system, attention, and control systems and the emotion
      systems linked to prefrontal cortex. Previously, functional MRI (fMRI) used changes in blood
      flow and blood oxygenation within the brain to detect which isolated regions of the brain
      were active during a task. The goal of functional connectivity research is to describe a
      pattern of interactions or a picture of the connectivity that occurs within distinct regions
      of the brain when the individual is not involved in a task.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in brain neural activity between before and after tinnitus modulation as detected on functional connectivity MRI.</measure>
    <time_frame>After completion of functional connectivity MRI</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">17</enrollment>
  <condition>Tinnitus</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Speciality clinic Community health centers Solicitation of participants from American
        Tinnitus Association and Acoustic Neuroma Society Research database
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adults, between the ages of 18 and 80 years.

          -  Idiopathic, subjective, troublesome, unilateral or bilateral, non-pulsatile tinnitus
             of 6 month's duration or greater.

          -  Patient has some voluntary control over their tinnitus, whether through attention
             redirection or somatosensory control, such as orofacial movements or head turn.

          -  Able to give informed consent.

          -  English-speaking.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with tinnitus related to cochlear implantation, retrocochlear lesion, or
             other known anatomic/structural lesions of the ear and temporal bone.

          -  Patients with hyperacusis or misophonia (hyper-sensitivity to loud noises).

          -  Patients with cardiac pacemakers, intracardiac lines, implanted medication pumps,
             implanted electrodes in the brain, or other intracranial metal objects with the
             exception of dental fillings or any other contraindication for MRI scan.

          -  Patients with an acute or unstable medical condition including all individuals with
             any significant heart disease, history of seizures, pneumonia, recent hip fracture
             (within 3 months), acute GI bleed, uncontrolled hypertension, or other disorders which
             would require stabilization prior to initiation of imaging.

          -  Patients with a history of a brain-related injury or brain-related illness such as
             increased intracranial pressure, brain mass, Huntington's chorea).

          -  Patients currently taking psychoactive drugs that cannot be suspended for several days
             prior to imaging.

          -  Weight over 350 pounds.

          -  Patients with a history of claustrophobia.

          -  Patients who have an inability to lay flat for 1 hour.

          -  Patients with tinnitus related to Workman's Compensation claim or litigation-related
             event.

          -  Patients whose ability to give informed consent is in question.

          -  Any exclusions from radiology screening.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jay F Piccirillo, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Washington University School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>St. Louis</city>
        <state>Missouri</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lee MH, Solowski N, Wineland A, Okuyemi O, Nicklaus J, Kallogjeri D, Piccirillo JF, Burton H. Functional connectivity during modulation of tinnitus with orofacial maneuvers. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg. 2012 Oct;147(4):757-62. Epub 2012 Jun 6.</citation>
    <PMID>22675003</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 8, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 8, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 9, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 10, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 10, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 11, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Washington University School of Medicine</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jay F. Piccirillo, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Otolaryngology, Director of Clinical Outcomes Research Office</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Tinnitus</keyword>
  <keyword>Ringing in ears</keyword>
  <keyword>Functional connectivity MRI</keyword>
  <keyword>Voluntary control of tinnitus</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tinnitus</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

