<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00979797</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2007-059</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00979797</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Community-Integrated Management of Childhood Illness (IMCI) Programme Evaluation</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Assessment of Public Health Effectiveness of Approaches to Promote Key Family &amp; Community Behaviors for Child Survival</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Directorate General for Health Services, Ministry of Health, Bangladesh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>World Health Organization</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>UNICEF</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, Bangladesh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The proposed four-year randomized study will attempt to test the hypothesis that
      community-based child health interventions in conjunction with facility-based IMCI will
      improve child care practices, nutritional status and child survival. The objectives of this
      research are:

        1. To measure the effectiveness of the community-based interventions in improving selected
           child care practices in the community.

        2. To measure the effectiveness of the community-based interventions in improving child
           nutritional status and in reducing child morbidity and mortality.

        3. To document the process of implementation of community-based interventions at scale to
           promote selected key family and community practices related to child health.

        4. To undertake cost-effectiveness analysis of the interventions.

      Integrated Management of Childhood Illness (IMCI) is a strategy developed by the World Health
      Organization (WHO) and UNICEF to reduce childhood mortality and morbidity and to contribute
      to improved growth and development of children under-5 years of age Experience suggests that
      a purely facility based strategy will not reach the significant portion of the population
      that does not have access to or choose not to use a health facility. Links between the
      service providers and families at household levels is essential in order to ensure that
      families have the knowledge, skills and ability to provide appropriate preventative and
      curative care to their children. However, globally, actual evidence of effectiveness of
      community-based IMCI interventions implemented at scale is meager.

      C-IMCI in Bangladesh will be implemented by GoB in partnership with NGOs and also through
      active participation of different community groups, civil societies, and the private sector.

      Both GoB and UNICEF/Bangladesh have agreed that an evaluation of the C-IMCI implementation by
      GoB, as proposed here, would be very opportune and useful in providing the evidence and
      analysis of lessons that will guide further scale-up in the country.

      A cluster-randomized design will be used for this evaluation. Fourteen Upazilas where
      facility-based IMCI is already in place will be selected, and 7 upazillas will be randomly
      allocated to C-IMCI intervention and 7 to comparison. Community-based IMCI in the
      intervention upazillas will be implemented by GoB through the district health system while in
      the comparison upazillas existing services will continue, including facility-based IMCI.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Overall study design

      For the proposed cluster randomized community-based intervention trial, upazilas
      (Sub-districts) will be randomized to either intervention or comparison. The upazila is the
      lowest local government structure with a health management unit. The usual upazila has a
      population of about 200,000 to 250,000. Fourteen upazilas where facility-based IMCI is
      already in place will be selected for the study, and 7 upazilas will be randomized to
      intervention and 7 to comparison. The objective of the randomization is to achieve a balance
      on the basis of facility IMCI interventions, functionality of health system, demographic and
      socioeconomic indicators, and population size. Community-based IMCI in the intervention
      upazilas will be implemented through the district health system while in the comparison
      upazilas existing services will continue, including facility-based IMCI.

      Selection of Upazilas and randomization

      The upazilas for the study will be selected based on the following steps:

      Step 1: Eligibility

      Facility based IMCI has been implemented in 300 upazilas as of December 2008. Most of these
      upazilas were selected from parts of Bangladesh with high rates of under-five mortality. In
      addition, the IMCI expansion plan of the Government of Bangladesh emphasizes achieving
      complete coverage of a district and selecting upazilas where other implementing partners are
      present so as to facilitate eventual expansion of community IMCI interventions. Out of 300
      upazilas, 100 were excluded where facility IMCI is in very early stage. Within remaining 200
      upazilas, Government has decided to implement community IMCI in all upazials of 14 districts
      and began the implementation in 5 districts in 2008 and early 2009. Seven pairs of upazilas
      will be selected form the upzilas of these 6 districts for evaluation. We are using district
      mortality rate as upazila under-five mortality rates are not available. We assume that that
      the variation of the true upazila under-five mortality rates is similar to that of district
      rates. We also exclude upazilas with or adjoining municipal areas as these are atypical.

      Step 2: Pairing and re-randomization

      The fourteen upazilas will be paired based on demographic and socio-economic indicators:
      population density, literacy rate (total &amp; female), male and female school attendance, and
      work status, source of drinking water, sanitary toilet, electricity, and flow of remittance.
      . A composite score using Principal Component Analysis will be constructed from these
      demographic and socio-economic indicators. This score will be used to sort upazilas within a
      district. In addition geographical location (proximity, within same district), population
      size, and health system functionality) assessed using immunization coverage) will also be
      considered in pairing of upazilas within a district. The National Nutrition Program (NNP) is
      the largest nutrition programme being implemented by GoB. Whether or not NNP is covering a
      particular upazila or is planning to is an important piece of information for this study as
      NNP was designed to reduce the prevalence of moderate and severe underweight in young
      children, address micronutrient deficiencies, increase pregnancy weight gain, reduce the
      incidence of low birth weight, and the prevalence of iron-deficiency anaemia among adolescent
      girls and pregnant women. Ongoing or planned implementation of NNP or the presence of any
      other substantive and similar community-based programmes will also be considered before
      selecting a upazila. Seven (07) pairs of upazilas will be formed and one upazila from each of
      the 7 pairs would be randomly assigned to C-IMCI intervention arm and the other to
      comparison. We have increased the number of pairs for the evaluation study from six to seven
      based on discussions with GoB, UNICEF, and WHO. The additional pair was from Bandarban
      district which was selected at the request of the MNCS programme (GoB/UNICEF). Bandarban
      district is in the hilly South-Eastern region of Bangladesh and is home to ethnically
      distinct populations and GoB/UNICEF is keen on including the district in the evaluation as
      programme experiences in these populations are limited.

      Documentation and monitoring of implementation

      Documentation and monitoring is essential to achieve the proposal's third aim - to document
      the process of implementation of community-based interventions at scale to promote selected
      key family and community practices related to child health. This documentation and monitoring
      of the implementation will be conducted both qualitatively and quantitatively to assess the
      feasibility and acceptability of the intervention and to document how and why the
      intervention may or may not work. A combination of qualitative and quantitative documentation
      is important to triangulate the findings of the study.

      Implementation of the C-IMCI component of IMCI will involve a series of processes, undertaken
      by the government. To identify the lessons learnt from the processes so that they may be
      useful in other settings and for the intervention itself, documentation and monitoring of key
      processes are very important. Five key processes have been identified for documentation -
      situation analysis, partnerships with NGOs, training, implementation and community
      perceptions and as mentioned earlier, these processes will be documented both qualitatively
      and quantitatively. While routine MIS data and other questionnaires will be analysed for
      quantitative documentation, for qualitative documentation, periodic in-depth studies will be
      carried out with community members, different health care providers and other populations
      involved with the intervention. These processes along with the system for process
      documentation are described below.

        1. Documenting situation analyses

           The process by which the Upazilla health manager conducts the situation analysis of the
           human resources and communication mediums available in the upazilla will be documented.
           This will include documentation of what method and sources are used to establish the
           number of government health workers (health assistants and family welfare assistants),
           village doctors, NGO health workers. Additionally the methods and sources of determining
           who in the community are considered opinion leaders, the number of mosques and imams
           will be documented. Especially important to this process is to document the confounding
           factors that may effect the inclusion or exclusion of human resources or communication
           mediums (e.g. village doctors may not be included because they do not wish to
           participate, NGOs may be excluded because of lack of necessary skills or infrastructure
           etc.). This will be documented prior to the intervention.

        2. Documenting the development of Partnerships with NGOs

           Creation of cross-institutional partnerships is a major and innovative part of the
           proposal. For this reason the documentation of this process is vitally important for its
           application in other areas of Bangladesh and outside of Bangladesh. Documentation of how
           partnerships with NGOs are established, the roles of the government and the NGO in the
           partnership, modes of communication and other factors affecting the functioning of the
           partnership should be identified. Further to this the relationships of the partner
           organization with mothers, workers and community leaders need to be documented. This
           will be documented through out the study.

        3. Documenting training

           The government will facilitate a training module for each component of the intervention
           (R1-R5). The major goal of documentation will be to record the process of the training
           and the quality of the training. In doing so, special focus will be given to the
           recruitment methods of trainers and participants, their attendance, completion of the
           training modules, factors affecting their participation, their knowledge retention,
           attitudes to training and intentions to practice what they have learnt. This will be
           documented at the beginning of the study.

        4. Documenting implementation

           GoB has authority over the planning and implementation of the C-IMCI interventions.
           Development of the interventions has already taken place however continued revisions,
           planning and monitoring is expected to continue through the implementation process. The
           implementation process as conducted by the District and Upazilla as well as National
           Core Committee will be documented and monitored. The operations, planning activities and
           decision making processes will be observed and documented through meeting records, and
           interviews with the District and Upazilla as well as National Core Committee staff. Of
           key importance will be the documentation of decision making processes to observe how and
           for what reason actionable decisions are made.

        5. Documenting community perceptions Prior to implementation of the intervention,
           documentation of attitudes of the community at baseline will be conducted. This will
           address the community's current attitudes towards the health system and health workers
           currently available, care-seeking patterns, and areas of demand (for example what
           services would they like to get from health workers). In addition to this, documentation
           of different community leaders and health care providers (including teachers, opinion
           leaders, religious leaders, village doctors, government health workers etc) will be held
           to determine their current attitudes to the health system, their perceived barriers to
           accessing health needs and areas of demand. The same activities will be conducted at the
           end of the intervention. This will particularly focus on documenting changes in the
           community's health care-seeking behaviour, changes in knowledge and attitudes of the
           community leaders and heath care providers, social participation of the community
           leaders and religious leaders in health care, mother's interactions with outreach
           workers and community leaders and the perceived benefits and disadvantages of the
           component approaches to improving child health. These documentations will take place
           periodically throughout the study.

      Documentation for each process will be in the form of reports providing a brief overview,
      rationale, objectives and description of the process. Each report will record the process and
      lessons learned by identifying the key phases of each process, the factors which affect these
      phases, how these factors relate to each phase and to each other and confounding or external
      factors.

      Methods for documentation

      Qualitative:

      The study will have an anthropologist to carry out the qualitative documentation. The
      following methods will be used to document the intervention implementation

        1. Documenting situation analysis

           1. In-depth semi-structured interviews will be carried out with Upazilla health managers
           to ascertain which method and sources were used to establish what type and how many
           health providers are available in the upazilla, who in the community were opinion
           leaders and the number and mosques and imams as well as the confounding factors that may
           have effected the inclusion or exclusion of these human resources/communication mediums:
           7 (one from each intervention upazilla)

        2. Documenting the development of partnerships with NGOs

             1. Focus group discussion will be conducted to understand community's knowledge,
                attitudes and expectations towards the partner NGOs: 14 (2 in each of the 6 7
                intervention upazillas, one with women and one with men)

             2. In-depth semi-structured interviews will be carried out with focal persons of both
                GoB and partner NGOs who will be in charge of enrolling the partnership to
                understand the modes of communication and other associating factors while working
                together: the number of respondents for this component will be determined in the
                field since the number of NGOs involved in the intervention areas is unknown. 2 GoB
                focal persons from each intervention upazilla will be selected for interview (14
                persons total).

        3. Documenting training

             1. Focus group discussions will be carried out with the participants of the training
                to understand their perceptions and attitudes regarding the training and the
                intervention: the number of focus group discussions for this component will be
                based on the number of training sessions conducted. We will be doing one group
                discussion for each training session.

             2. In-depth semi-structured interviews will be carried out with trainers to understand
                their perceptions regarding the training module, time allocated for the training
                and participant's attitudes: the number of in-depth interviews for this component
                will be based on the number of training sessions conducted. We will be doing one
                trainer interview from each training session.

        4. Documenting implementation

             1. In-depth semi-structured interviews will be conducted with the District and
                Upazilla as well as National Core Committee of DGHS members to ascertain their
                attitudes and understanding of decision making processes surrounding the
                implementation of the C-IMCI intervention.

             2. Regular attendance at the District and Upazilla as well as National Core Committee
                meetings to observe decision making processes, structure of meetings, and the main
                issues discussed will be conducted. The observer will in particular be documenting
                the processes for planning and decision making by taking into account how issues
                are raised and managed. The number of observation attendances at the meetings will
                be based on the number of meetings held.

        5. Documenting community perceptions

      At baseline:

        1. In-depth semi-structured interviews will be carried out with community members (both
           married women and men) to understand their current attitudes towards the health system
           and health workers, care-seeking patterns for child health and their demand: 42
           respondents (6 from each intervention upazilla and among them three interviews will be
           with married women and three will be with married men having children/grandchildren age
           under five years of age.)

        2. In-depth semi-structured interviews with community leaders (teachers, opinion leaders,
           religious leaders) will be carried out to understand their current attitudes towards the
           health system and health workers, care-seeking patterns for child health and their
           demand: 21 respondents (one from each category in each intervention upazilla).

        3. In-depth semi-structured interviews with health workers (village doctors, traditional
           healers, HA, FWA, and other Govt. and NGO health workers who are currently available in
           the community) will be carried out to understand their current role, their attitudes
           towards the health system and their perceptions: 42 respondents (one from each category
           in each upazilla).

      At end-line The same number and type of interviews will be conducted at the end of the
      intervention. However, this piece of work will particularly focus on changes in the
      community's health care-seeking behaviour, changes in knowledge and attitudes of the
      community leaders and health care providers.

      In addition to baseline and end-line, data collection may also take place with these types of
      respondents throughout the study to understand the ongoing changes or if there is any changes
      in the community over time.

      Quantitative:

      MIS data and other questionnaires will be used to document the intervention quantitatively.

      Evaluation and monitoring of the performance of the community based health workers

      To assess the adequacy of the implementation of the proposed intervention it is necessary to
      regularly document and monitor the performance of the community based health workers. Both
      utilization of the community based health workers and quality of care will be measured.

      Utilization of Community Based Health Workers Quantitative data will be collected from
      routine MIS, e.g., patient registers, referral slips, reports, drug utilization registers as
      well as reports from referral centres.

      Quality of Care of provided by Health Workers Existing generic MCE -IMCI health facility
      survey tools will be modified, translated and used to assess the quality of care at first
      level facility and at community. Information will be collected through observation of case
      management using a standard checklist, exit interviews with care givers, re-examination of
      each child with &quot;gold standard&quot; surveyor, interviews with health care providers and an audit
      of the supplies and equipment available at the facilities and with the community health
      workers. Quality of care and facility preparedness for antenatal checkups at GoB first level
      health facilities will be assessed using a standard checklist. Quality will be assessed at
      baseline and end line of the study.

      Evaluation of Effectiveness

      Measuring effectiveness of C-IMCI intervention implementation is the primary objective of
      this project. The principle outcome indicators are under-five child mortality, appropriate
      care seeking for childhood illness, exclusive breast feeding and nutritional status (weight
      for age). The secondary outcome indicators include number of antenatal care received by women
      during pregnancy; deliveries conducted by trained birth attendants; mothers and newborns who
      received postnatal care from a trained provider; newborn received drying and wrapping and
      bath delayed by at least three days ; newborn breastfed within 1 hour of birth, and infants
      0-5 months exclusively breastfeed . These indicators will be measured on a population of
      children aged 0-5 years and women who have given birth in last one year and compared between
      C-IMCI intervention areas and comparison areas. Primary comparisons will be made on the basis
      of key indicators measured over the last two years of the project. However, baseline rates
      will be estimated to identify any differences between the two arms at project commencement
      and to make before and after comparisons within intervention arm. Special evaluations will be
      designed during the course of the intervention implementation to understand and assess C-IMCI
      intervention sub-components based on both MIS and independently collected data.

      Household surveys of selected households in each upazila will provide information on
      indicators such as under-five child mortality, exclusive breast feeding, newborn breastfed
      within 1 hour of birth, infants 0-5 months exclusively breastfed, antenatal care received by
      women during pregnancy; deliveries conducted by trained birth attendants, newborn dried and
      wrapped immediately after bath and delayed bathing, child nutritional status (weight,
      height/length), under-5 morbidity, care-seeking practices associated with the episodes of
      morbidity, practices relating to home care and case management, and compliance with health
      care advice.

      For cost-effectiveness analyses of the facility and community IMCI interventions activities
      the study will also track costs and make estimates of the cost-effectiveness of different
      IMCI intervention models.

      Methods of Data Collection

      Household Surveys Three large household surveys will be carried out in the selected study
      population, first at commencement, at midterm and then at the end of the project.

      For each household coverage survey a fresh sample of household will be selected from each
      upazila. The sample HHs will be drawn through a multi-stage sampling process. In each
      upazila, first villages will be randomly selected by probability proportional to size (PPS)
      sampling and in the second stage a fixed number of households will be selected randomly from
      the household lists of the selected villages to reach the desired number of households. Each
      village will be mapped and all households of the selected villages will be listed. The
      household lists will contain bari name and household head name of every existing household.
      Data collectors will identify the sampled households in each village (cluster) and will
      complete interviews of caretakers of all available under-5 children in the households,
      including mothers of newborns born in the previous 12 months.

      The baseline survey will be completed within first 6 months of the project and using a
      Demographic Health Survey-type instrument. The instrument used by the IMCI-MCE study in
      Matlab, Bangladesh and Bangladesh Demographic and Health Survey 2007 (BDHS) will be adapted,
      and used for this purpose. Information on socio-economic and demographic variables, practices
      and care during pregnancy, delivery and after delivery, immediate newborn care, care seeking
      practices for under-five children with the episodes of morbidity, practices relating to home
      care and case management, contact with service providers, compliance with health care advice,
      and user costs will be collected. Morbidity data will be based on 2-weeks recall of diarrhea,
      ARI and other serious illnesses. Causes of under-5 deaths, water and sanitation conditions
      and other possible confounders or correlates of mortality will be collected through this
      baseline survey so that any differences between the intervention and comparison arms at
      baseline can be adjusted for in the analysis.

      The midterm survey will provide insight on the direction and achievements of the project
      objectives and will be used for any modification of intervention. The end-of-project (EoP)
      survey (in year 4) will be completed with similar tools that used at baseline. The EoP survey
      will be completed in last 6 months period. A mortality survey module will be included in the
      End of Project survey. The data will be used to estimate baseline mortality levels.

      Cost-effectiveness analyses of the facility and community IMCI interventions activities:

      For the purpose of cost-effectiveness analyses of the facility and community IMCI
      intervention the study will also track costs and make estimates of the cost-effectiveness of
      different IMCI interventions (Facility and Community IMCI). The analyses of both costs and
      effects will generate 2 cost-effectiveness ratios in terms of costs per YLS (Years of Life
      Saved).

        1. Total costs of IMCI/YLS from treating all under-five based on facility and community
           IMCI.

        2. Incremental costs of introducing community IMCI (aggregate approach)/difference in YLS
           between intervention and comparison districts. This will show if the additional costs
           adding community IMCI into the current system justified the additional health benefits.

      Cost data will be collected in three facility IMCI upazilas and three facility and community
      IMCI upazilas from societal perspective. Programme intervention costs (in case of facility
      and community IMCI), which can be directly compared to changes in outcome measures in
      cost-effectiveness analysis, will be collected by the research team and will include payments
      to health workers; training courses for health workers; drugs, supplies, and all other
      activities in the course of the intervention; and amortized capital costs (equipment,
      vehicles, buildings). We will track and include capital costs, using depreciation techniques
      to calculate the portion of the investment cost that is appropriate to include in the
      cost-effectiveness calculation. Users' costs (individuals and families) will be measured
      through the household surveys. These costs include any direct financial payments for
      services, as well as transportation costs and the amount of time that individuals spend to
      use the services of the intervention. Time costs will be translated into financial costs
      based on the economic level of the household, as measured by the household survey.

      In addition to efforts to capture programme and users' costs we will capture Provider costs
      associated with project activities. Data collection will focus on the amassing of all costs
      associated with the provision of IMCI services at the health facility and community levels.
      Major direct cost categories will include costs associated with staff time treating under 5
      children drugs and all other community activities. While major indirect cost categories will
      include building costs (e.g. percent of capital and recurrent costs, including electricity
      and maintenance costs); a proportion of non-medical staff salary costs (e.g. cleaning staff,
      security guards) etc.

      Survey management and Quality control

      The study team will recruit data collectors and their local supervisors at upazilla level.
      Training of the Trainors (ToT) will be arranged at Dhaka and training of the data collectors
      will be arranged at upazilla level. All training, data collection process, progress and
      quality will be closely monitored by the central team at ICDDR,B.

      Data quality and Data management

      All questionnaires and data forms will be reviewed for accuracy, consistency and
      completeness. Repeat interviews will be conducted in a 5% sample of the households. The
      Project Coordinator and investigators will make periodic field visits to observe data
      collection by the interviewers. All data will be entered in databases using on-line
      custom-designed data entry programmes with necessary range and consistency checks built in.
      Data will be periodically checked by running and reviewing frequency distributions and cross
      tabulations.

      Ethical Considerations

      No children in the study area will be deprived of existing health care services or other
      services scheduled to be implemented in the area during the study period. Children of the
      intervention area are expected to be benefited from the interventions to promote family and
      community practices, e.g., through the intensive education of the families and communities on
      improved child caring and care seeking. If the study hypothesis is proven to be correct,
      community IMCI could be scaled up and all the children in the study area will be benefited.

      Sample Size Calculation and Outcome Variable(s)

      Sample Size Calculation Since the upazila is the unit of randomization, sample size
      calculations have been carried out to determine the number of households needed for detecting
      expected declines in under-5 mortality/1,000 live births, assuming 7 upazilas in each group,
      and allowing for cluster level randomization. The formula estimates the number of clusters
      need for given cluster size (n). Since we know the number of clusters in each group is fixed
      at 6 7, we can also use the formula to estimate cluster size (n) for a given indicator. Here
      k is the coefficient of variation of the true (population) proportions between clusters
      within each group. The estimation was done iteratively based on the t-distribution,
      confidence levels of 95%, and 80% power, and assuming refusal rate of 20% and an expected 20%
      reduction in under-5 mortality. Thus we get 6 clusters required for each of the arms
      (intervention and comparison).

      9,375households are needed for each upazila to measure 20% under-5 mortality reduction. The
      sample HHs will be drawn through a multi-stage sampling process. In the first stage 60
      villages will be selected with probability proportional to size from each upazila and in the
      second stage fixed number of households will be randomly selected from those 60 villages to
      reach the 9,375 households. If a selected village does not include enough households then we
      will add households from the nearest village.

      A sub-sample of 930 households including 110 households with women who have given birth in
      last one year from each upazila will be required for the baseline, midterm and final
      household coverage surveys. At first stage 30 villages will be selected from each upazila by
      PPS sampling and in the second stage 31 households will be randomly selected from the
      household list. If a selected village does not include enough households then we will add
      households from the nearest village. The same procedure will be repeated for each survey to
      draw the fresh sample of 930 households. Data collectors will identify the sampled households
      and will interview caretakers of all available under-5 children in the household, including
      mothers of newborns who given birth in the previous 12 months
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Under 5 mortality Proportion of sick &lt;5 years old children seeking appropriate care Proportion of 0-5 months old children exclusively breastfed Proportion of &lt;5 years old children &lt;-2 z weight for age</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Care-seeking for childhood illness Antenatal and Postnatal care Deliveries by trained birth attendants Essential newborn care (drying and wrapping, delayed bathing, Breastfeeding) Complementary feeding</measure>
    <time_frame>24 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">140000</enrollment>
  <condition>Childhood Illness</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Maternal &amp; Child Health</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Community-based interventions to promoto Maternal and Child Survival in collaboration with GoB, Donors and NGOs.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Community-based interventions to promote maternal and child health</intervention_name>
    <description>Promotion of antenatal and postnatal care and safe delivery Essential Newborn care Community case management, and feeding for children.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Maternal &amp; Child Health</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Areas with facility-based IMCI in place

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children &gt; 5 years

          -  Women &lt; 15 and &gt; 49 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>49 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ICDDR,B</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dhaka</city>
        <zip>1212</zip>
        <country>Bangladesh</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Bangladesh</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2009</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 17, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 17, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 18, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 28, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 28, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 30, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Community IMCI</keyword>
  <keyword>C-IMCI</keyword>
  <keyword>CHW</keyword>
  <keyword>Children</keyword>
  <keyword>Evaluation</keyword>
  <keyword>Behaviour</keyword>
  <keyword>Counselling</keyword>
  <keyword>Under 5 mortality</keyword>
  <keyword>Under 5 Nutrition</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

