<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00972179</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20080390</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00972179</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety Study of AMG 157 in Healthy Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Ascending Multiple Dose Study to Evaluate the Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of AMG 157 in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Amgen</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Amgen</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study will follow a randomized, multiple-dose, double-blind, placebo-controlled,
      sequential dose-escalation study design. This healthy volunteer study will consist of five
      subcutaneous (SC) cohorts and one intravenous (IV) cohort. Each dose cohort will enroll 8
      subjects, randomized such that 6 subjects will receive AMG 157 and 2 will receive placebo
      (3:1 ratio). The doses of AMG 157 planned to be evaluated include 35 mg (SC every 28 days,
      Cohort 1), 105 mg (SC every 28 days, Cohort 2), 210 mg (SC every 28 days, Cohort 3), 210 mg
      (SC every 14 days, Cohort 4), 210 mg (SC every 7 days, Cohort 5) and 700 mg (IV every 28
      days, Cohort 6).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety evaluations: Subject incidence of treatment-emergent adverse events, clinically significant changes in vital signs, physical examinations, laboratory safety tests, ECGs, and the development of anti-AMG 157 antibodies</measure>
    <time_frame>169 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum PK parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>169 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">49</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AMG 157</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Six subjects in each cohort (cohorts 1 to 6) will receive AMG 157 for a total of 36 subjects.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>AMG 157 Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Two subjects in each cohort (cohorts 1 to 6) will receive placebo, for a total of 12 subjects.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AMG 157 Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>A total of 12 subjects will be receiving multiple doses of AMG 157 placebo. Each subject enrolled in cohorts 1-3 will receive three SC doses; each subject enrolled in cohort 4 will receive six SC doses; each subject enrolled in cohort 5 will receive 12 SC doses; and each subject enrolled in cohort 6 will receive three IV doses throughout the study period of 169 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AMG 157 Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AMG 157</intervention_name>
    <description>A total of 36 subjects will be receiving multiple doses of AMG 157 (dose escalating by cohort). Each subject enrolled in cohorts 1-3 will receive three SC doses; each subject enrolled in cohort 4 will receive six SC doses; each subject enrolled in cohort 5 will receive 12 SC doses; and each subject enrolled in cohort 6 will receive three IV doses throughout the study period of 169 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>AMG 157</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must sign an Institutional Review Board (IRB) approved informed consent form
             before any study-specific procedures;

          -  Healthy subject, aged between 18 and 45 years, inclusive;

          -  Female subject must be of non-reproductive potential (ie, postmenopausal by history -
             no menses for ≥ 1 year and by FSH [using local reference ranges]; OR history of
             hysterectomy; OR history of bilateral tubal ligation; OR history of bilateral
             oophorectomy);

          -  Male subjects with female partner of childbearing potential who agrees to inform their
             female partner of their participation in this clinical study and use highly effective
             methods of birth control during the study. (Highly effective methods of birth control
             may include abstinence, vasectomy, or a condom with spermicide in combination with
             either hormonal birth control, IUD or barrier methods used by the woman.);

          -  Male subject who agrees to use birth control for five months after last dose of study
             medication, male subject who agrees not to donate sperm during the study and for five
             months after last dose of study medication;

          -  Healthy subject with a body mass index (BMI) between 18 and 32 kg/m2, inclusive at
             screening;

          -  Subject must have normal or clinically acceptable physical examination and
             electrocardiogram (ECG) results (12-lead reporting RR, PR, QRS, QT and QTcF) prior to
             Day 1 based on the opinion of the investigator;

          -  Subject must have normal or clinically acceptable clinical laboratory tests at
             screening as determined by Amgen and the investigator;

          -  Subject must have adequate renal function (defined as CrCl &gt; 80 mL/min using the
             Cockcroft Gault equation).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subject who has history or evidence of a clinically significant disorder, condition or
             disease (including but not limited to cardiopulmonary, oncologic, immunologic,
             autoimmune, collagen vascular, renal, metabolic, hematologic or psychiatric), that, in
             the opinion of the Investigator in consultation with the Amgen physician, would pose a
             risk to subject safety or interfere with the study evaluation, procedures or
             completion;

          -  Subject who has evidence of any active or suspected bacterial, viral, fungal or
             parasitic infections within the past 30 days prior to randomization (eg, common cold,
             viral syndrome, flu-like symptoms). Subject who, in the opinion of the investigator,
             has a high risk of parasitic disease is also excluded;

          -  Subject who has known positive tuberculin skin test (if not treated with appropriate
             chemoprophylaxis) or recent (within six months from randomization) exposure to an
             individual with active tuberculosis;

          -  Subject who has history of malignancy of any type, other than in situ cervical cancer
             or surgically excised non-melanomatous skin cancers within five years before
             randomization of the study;

          -  Subject who has known type I/II diabetes;

          -  Subject who uses nonprescription drugs within 14 days prior to randomization and for
             the entire duration of the study. All herbal supplements, vitamins, and nutritional
             supplements taken within the last 30 days prior to dosing on Day 1 (and continued use,
             if appropriate), must be reviewed and approved by the PI and Amgen Medical Monitor;

          -  Subject who has used any systemic cytotoxic or systemic immunosuppressive medications
             (other than corticosteroids) within 6 months prior to randomization and for the entire
             duration of the study; subject who has used any corticosteroid, topical cytotoxic or
             topical immunosuppressive medications within 30 days or five half-lives (whichever is
             longer) prior to randomization and for the entire duration of the study;

          -  Subject who has previously received any other therapeutic monoclonal antibody;

          -  Subject who has previously received any investigational drug (or is currently using an
             investigational device) within 30 days or five half-lives (whichever is longer) prior
             to randomization;

          -  Subject who has tested positive for drugs and/or alcohol use at screening or before
             randomization, subject who has consumed alcohol within 48 hours prior to any study
             visit including screening, and subject with alcohol intake of &gt; 2 drinks/day on
             average during the study (one drink being equivalent to 12 ounces of regular beer, 8
             to 9 ounces of malt liquor, 5 ounces of wine or 1.5 ounces of 80 proof distilled
             spirits);

          -  Female subject who is pregnant or lactating; female subject who is of child-bearing
             potential;

          -  Subject who has donated blood (including blood products) or experienced loss of blood
             ≥ 500 mL within two months of study screening;

          -  Subject who is positive for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) antibodies, hepatitis B
             surface antigen, or hepatitis C antibodies;

          -  Subject who has regularly used nicotine or tobacco containing products (including but
             not limited to: snuff, chewing tobacco, cigars, cigarettes, pipes, or nicotine
             patches) during six months before randomization and during the study;

          -  Subject who has any other condition that might reduce the chance of obtaining data
             (eg, known poor compliance) required by the protocol or that might compromise the
             ability to give truly informed consent.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Amgen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.amgentrials.com</url>
    <description>AmgenTrials clinical trials website</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>August 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 3, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 3, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 4, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 25, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 25, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 26, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Global Development Leader</name_title>
    <organization>Amgen Inc.</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>healthy volunteers</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

