<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00977041</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>36292-D Phase 2</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>124155</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00977041</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neurofeedback Treatment of Pain in Persons With Spinal Cord Injury (SCI)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Neurofeedback Treatment of Pain in Persons With SCI: Phase 2</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Washington</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Craig H. Neilsen Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Washington</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A number of studies suggest that training to increase different types of brain waves is
      related to pain relief. The purpose of the second phase of this study is to see if
      neurofeedback training might help people with chronic pain control their pain better. The
      information from the study may help the investigators treat chronic pain better in the
      future.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      During this phase of the study, research personnel will provide up to 15 of the subjects with
      SCI-related pain with a full course (up to 40 sessions) of NF training to determine the
      effects of this treatment on (a) chronic daily pain, (b) EEG-assessed frequency band
      amplitudes, and (c) other measures of quality of life (specifically, sleep quality, fatigue,
      and pain interference).

      Standard NF training procedures will be used that involve simply asking participants to relax
      while looking at the feedback screen and to &quot;Do whatever is necessary to make and keep the
      color bar wide.&quot; EEG bandwidth activity that is associated with being pain-free or with
      experiencing less pain will be reinforced. This protocol will be repeated for up to 40
      30-minute sessions, scheduled at least weekly (but more often if the participant and study PI
      can arrange this with their schedules. Brain wave activity will be measured three times
      during the study: once before treatment begins, once immediately after treatment ends, and
      three months following treatment. Research staff will collect data regarding pain intensity
      and quality of life from subjects via the telephone three times: before treatment,
      immediately after treatment, and three months after treatment ends.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Average daily (past 24 hours) pain will be the primary outcome measure for the clinical phase of this study. This will be assessed using a 0-10 NRS via four phone interviews performed on different days by a research assistant.</measure>
    <time_frame>Just before treatment begins, just after treatment ends (approximately 1 to 6 months following the beginning of treatment), and 3 months following the end of treatment.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Brain wave activity will be assessed in all of second phase participants with the use of an electroencephalogram(EEG).</measure>
    <time_frame>EEG activity will be collected just before the first treatment session (baseline), just after the last treatment session, and three months following the end of treatment.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep quality will be assessed using the six-item Medical Outcomes Study Sleep measure(Hays &amp; Stewart, 1992).</measure>
    <time_frame>Just before treatment begins, just after treatment ends (approximately 1 to 6 months following the beginning of treatment), and 3 months following the end of treatment.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pain interference will be assessed using the PROMIS Pain Impact Scale.</measure>
    <time_frame>Just before treatment begins, just after treatment ends (approximately 1 to 6 months following the beginning of treatment), and 3 months following the end of treatment.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fatigue severity will be assessed using the Fatigue Severity Scale (FSS; Krupp et al., 1998). The FSS is a 9-item measure assessing both fatigue severity and impact.</measure>
    <time_frame>Just before treatment begins, just after treatment ends (approximately 1 to 6 months following the beginning of treatment), and 3 months following the end of treatment.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication use in the week prior to each assessment including medication use as well as pain treatments such as massage.</measure>
    <time_frame>Just before treatment begins, just after treatment ends (approximately 1 to 6 months following the beginning of treatment), and 3 months following the end of treatment.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Benefits received from treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>Following the end of treatment (approximately 1 to 6 months after treatment begins) and 3 months following the end of treatment.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">13</enrollment>
  <condition>Spinal Cord Injuries</condition>
  <condition>Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Neurofeedback</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>See Intervention description below.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Neurofeedback</intervention_name>
    <description>Electrodes will be placed over the temporal lobes bilaterally and a ground electrode placed on the left earlobe. EEG activity will be amplified using a Procomp 2 or Nexus amplifier, and EEGer software will be used to provide subjects with feedback. Contingencies will be set such that alpha brain activity will be reinforced, and high beta and theta brain activity will be inhibited. Standard NF training procedures will be used, which involve simply asking subjects to relax while looking at the feedback screen and &quot;Do whatever is necessary to make and keep the bar wide.&quot; This protocol will be repeated for up to 40 60-minute sessions (that will include 30 minutes of NF training), scheduled at least weekly.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Neurofeedback</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. 18 years old or older.

          2. At least 12 months post-SCI.

          3. Otherwise healthy (i.e., no other secondary medical complications, such as pressure
             ulcers, that could impact pain scores).

          4. Read, write and understand English.

          5. Experience SCI-related pain on a daily basis.

          6. Report an average pain intensity of at least 4 on a 0-10 Numerical Scale.

          7. An individual must have one significant pain problem that is the worst or most painful
             if he/she has more than one pain problem.

          8. Pain problem has lasted at least six months, and began after injury.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. History of seizure activity or has non-normative brain activity.

          2. Suicidal or paranoid thoughts.

          3. Presence of traumatic brain injury or significant skull defects.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mark P Jensen, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Washington</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Washington</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seattle</city>
        <state>Washington</state>
        <zip>98104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Jensen MP, Gertz KJ, Kupper AE, Braden AL, Howe JD, Hakimian S, Sherlin LH. Steps toward developing an EEG biofeedback treatment for chronic pain. Appl Psychophysiol Biofeedback. 2013 Jun;38(2):101-8. doi: 10.1007/s10484-013-9214-9.</citation>
    <PMID>23532434</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>October 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 27, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 11, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 15, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 4, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 4, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 6, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Washington</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Mark Jensen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neurofeedback</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spinal Cord Injuries</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

