<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00977847</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2009P0011908</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1RC1HG005331-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00977847</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Integrating Patient Generated Family Health History From Varied Electronic Health Record (EHR) Entry Portals</brief_title>
  <official_title>Integrating Patient Generated Family Health History From Varied Electronic Health Record Entry Portals</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Brigham and Women's Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Brigham and Women's Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      In the 21st century, the importance of family health history will increase as it will be
      essential to put detailed personal genetic information into the context of an individual's
      health, namely the context of how the shared code has played out in an individual and his/her
      closest relatives. These scientific developments in the investigators' understanding of
      genetics will demand a more comprehensive family history dataset for all patients, and the
      time limitations on healthcare providers demand a technology-driven solution that integrates
      an individual's knowledge of their family history with the medical records maintained by
      their health care providers. A solution does not currently exist by which most Americans can
      organize their family health history and then place it into their electronic health record
      (EHR). The investigators propose to develop and compare three different ways of proactively
      collecting family history information from patients using computer technology independent of
      a health care visit, including telephone (interactive voice response technology), tablet
      computers in a physician's waiting room, and a secure internet portal at home. These tools
      will be based on the US Surgeon General's My Family Health Portrait, an electronic family
      history collection tool. Family history data will be transferred and integrated with a
      patient's EHR in a large primary care network. This project will seek to demonstrate that
      family history data can be accurately reported by diverse patients using these technologies,
      and that these data can be integrated to tailor an individual's health care based on their
      familial risk.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: The long established wisdom of including family health history as a key part of
      an individual's medical record has been invigorated by the new emphasis on personalized
      medicine. While in the past, family health history was used to understand an individual's
      disease risk and to focus disease prevention efforts, in 21st century medicine, family health
      history's importance will increase as it will be essential to put detailed personal genetic
      information into a clinical context, namely the context of how the shared code has played out
      in a person's closest relatives. This new need for family health history will demand a more
      comprehensive family history dataset for all patients, and the time limitations faced by
      healthcare providers demand a technology-driven solution whereby the patient performs primary
      data entry and the provider then refines these data. Solutions do not currently exist by
      which most Americans can organize their family health history and then place it into their
      electronic health record (EHR). My Family Health Portrait (MFHP) is an open source,
      electronic family history collection tool developed by the Surgeon General that offers
      interoperability with EHRs, yet to our knowledge has not been widely integrated because of
      limitations in the capacity of many EHRs to accept these data, and barriers to the systematic
      collection of these data in clinical practice. Additionally, obstacles exist for those
      individuals who are not computer literate or do not have access to a home computer. In order
      to capture patient-generated family history data across diverse patient populations, EHR's
      may need to offer patients a variety of data entry options which allow for differences in
      preference, convenience, computer literacy, and computer availability. This proposal seeks to
      develop new resources for family history data entry into the EHR. These resources will be
      developed, tested and validated in a primary care setting within of a large complex
      healthcare system.

      Research Plan: The proposed project will examine the reach, effectiveness, adoption and
      implementation of three innovative portals to transfer and integrate patient generated family
      history data with an EHR.

      Specific Aim 1 (technical development) is to develop the three portals for entry of patient
      generated family history data integrated with an EHR. The pathways will include: : (1)
      computer tablets in waiting rooms to complete the MFHP, (2) a secure internet portal to
      transfer data collected by patients at home using MFHP, and (3) an interactive voice response
      (IVR) system to collect the necessary data elements by phone. Each of these modalities will
      interface with the EHR of a large health delivery system using current data standards. Each
      of these modalities will be designed to interface with the EHR of a large health delivery
      system using current data standards using current data standards.

      Specific Aim 2 (content development and validation) is to evaluate facilitators and barriers
      to the adoption, and implementation of these three electronic portals by assessing
      differences in patient preferences, privacy concerns, convenience, and understanding. The
      validity of the family history data collected by each of these three portals will also be
      assessed by a genetic counselor.

      Specific Aim 3 (pilot randomized controlled trial) is to conduct a 4-armed pilot randomized
      controlled trial (RCT) to measure the reach and effectiveness of integrating this family
      history data with a patient's EHR. The trial will examine and compare changes in family
      history documentation, patient-doctor discussion of family history, and patient and provider
      satisfaction with each data entry portal described in Aim 1, as well as a control arm. The
      trial will be conducted as a pilot cluster RCT in selected practices within the Brigham and
      Women's Primary Care Practice-Based Research Network.

      Potential Impact: The impact of obtaining accurate family history data and integrating this
      with an individual's health record are substantial, and will be of growing importance as our
      understanding of the genome advances. This project will ultimately contribute to a better
      understanding of how available technologies can be integrated with EHR's to obtain accurate
      family history in ways that allow for widespread acquisition and integration of accurate
      family history data in a variety of settings and diverse patient populations. The technology
      and lessons learned from this project will be exportable to healthcare settings throughout
      the United States.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Project will seek to demonstrate that family history data can be accurately reported by 5000 diverse patients using three portals, and that these data can be used to tailor an individual's health care based on their familial risk.</measure>
    <time_frame>2.5 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Develop three portals for collection of patient generated family history data integrated with an EHR: computer tablets in waiting rooms; a secure internet portal for use at home; and an interactive voice response system to get data by phone.</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate facilitators and barriers to adoption and implementation of these portals by assessing differences in patient preferences, privacy, convenience, and understanding. Validate data collected by each portal by a genetic counselor.</measure>
    <time_frame>1.5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To conduct a 4-armed pilot RCT to measure the reach and effectiveness of integrating family history data with a patient's EHR.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>For patients in the RCT who report a family history that is associated with an increased risk of coronary artery disease, we will examine how often their physician initiates screening and/ or primary prevention based on the family history information.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5000</enrollment>
  <condition>Family Characteristics</condition>
  <condition>Health Status</condition>
  <condition>Family Research</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Interactive Voice Response Practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The introductory letter to patients will allow them an opportunity to &quot;opt-out&quot; of the study using a toll-free number. If they do not opt-out within 2 weeks of receiving the letter, the IVR system will make up to 15 call attempts over a 2 week period to reach the patient. The system will make outbound calls during preset hours. The system continuously checks the call list for the next scheduled call. Once contact is made, the spoken script greets the patient by name, authenticates identify, and will ask the patient the programmed questions. The IVR server will send completed family history assessments to the patients EHR as an HL7 compliant summary note as well as transmitting the separate coded responses for each condition/ family member to coded family history fields in the EHR.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Wireless Tablet PC Practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients will receive an info letter in advance of their visit explaining the project with description of what information they will be asked to provide. Study staff will train the practice staff to hand out and collect the tablets for the patient. Staff will be trained to verify a patient's identity to ensure that the family history is sent to the correct EHR record. The initial screen of the tablet PC portal will include a paragraph of informed consent, and patients in this practice will be given the opportunity to decline participation. For patients who participate, the completed family history data will be transmitted to the patient's EHR as an HL7 compliant note and transmitting separate coded responses for each condition/ family member to coded family history fields.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Internet Portal Practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients in this practice will receive the informational letter either by email or mail one month before their scheduled visit. It will have directions to access the MFHP website and how to transfer data through the hospitals secure internet portal (Patient Gateway). About 1/3 of patients are signed up to use this service. Those who do not have a Patient Gateway account will be provided with directions on how to establish this service. Patients will be required to have a Gateway account to ensure that the MFHP data file is sent securely to the correct EHR record. Patients in this arm will receive an initial email or letter with a single follow-up reminder sent 2 weeks later. For patients who participate, the completed family history data will be transmitted to the patient's EHR.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Physician Assesment Practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Usual standard family history assessments will be conducted by physicians during the patient visit. This arm will allow us to account for any temporal trends in family history assessment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Electronic Health Portals for collecting Family History data</intervention_name>
    <description>Comparison of multiple portals for integrating patient generated family history data into the electronic health record.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Interactive Voice Response Practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Wireless Tablet PC Practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Internet Portal Practice</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Usual Care Physician Assesment Practice</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Male and Female Patients who:

          -  receive primary care at one of the study selected Primary Care Practices,

          -  are between 18-75 years old,

          -  are English or Spanish speakers, and

          -  have appointments scheduled in the upcoming 1 - 3 months for an annual or
             comprehensive visit.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  We will not include individuals over the age of 75 because the role of family risk
             assessment and prevention is less established.

          -  Also will not include non-English or non-Spanish speakers.

          -  Patients will also be excluded if they are hearing impaired.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jennifer S Haas, MD, MSPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02120</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yoon PW, Scheuner MT, Peterson-Oehlke KL, Gwinn M, Faucett A, Khoury MJ. Can family history be used as a tool for public health and preventive medicine? Genet Med. 2002 Jul-Aug;4(4):304-10.</citation>
    <PMID>12172397</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sabatino SA, McCarthy EP, Phillips RS, Burns RB. Breast cancer risk assessment and management in primary care: provider attitudes, practices, and barriers. Cancer Detect Prev. 2007;31(5):375-83. Epub 2007 Nov 26.</citation>
    <PMID>18037249</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Acheson LS, Wiesner GL, Zyzanski SJ, Goodwin MA, Stange KC. Family history-taking in community family practice: implications for genetic screening. Genet Med. 2000 May-Jun;2(3):180-5.</citation>
    <PMID>11256663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Awareness of family health history as a risk factor for disease--United States, 2004. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2004 Nov 12;53(44):1044-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15538320</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Qureshi N, Wilson B, Santaguida P, Carroll J, Allanson J, Culebro CR, Brouwers M, Raina P. Collection and use of cancer family history in primary care. Evid Rep Technol Assess (Full Rep). 2007 Oct;(159):1-84. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18457477</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wagner EH, Austin BT, Von Korff M. Organizing care for patients with chronic illness. Milbank Q. 1996;74(4):511-44. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8941260</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glasgow RE, McKay HG, Piette JD, Reynolds KD. The RE-AIM framework for evaluating interventions: what can it tell us about approaches to chronic illness management? Patient Educ Couns. 2001 Aug;44(2):119-27. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11479052</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Glasgow RE, Vogt TM, Boles SM. Evaluating the public health impact of health promotion interventions: the RE-AIM framework. Am J Public Health. 1999 Sep;89(9):1322-7. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10474547</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Acheson LS, Zyzanski SJ, Stange KC, Deptowicz A, Wiesner GL. Validation of a self-administered, computerized tool for collecting and displaying the family history of cancer. J Clin Oncol. 2006 Dec 1;24(34):5395-402. Epub 2006 Nov 6.</citation>
    <PMID>17088568</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scheuner MT, Wang SJ, Raffel LJ, Larabell SK, Rotter JI. Family history: a comprehensive genetic risk assessment method for the chronic conditions of adulthood. Am J Med Genet. 1997 Aug 22;71(3):315-24.</citation>
    <PMID>9268102</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karliner LS, Napoles-Springer A, Kerlikowske K, Haas JS, Gregorich SE, Kaplan CP. Missed opportunities: family history and behavioral risk factors in breast cancer risk assessment among a multiethnic group of women. J Gen Intern Med. 2007 Mar;22(3):308-14.</citation>
    <PMID>17356960</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaplan CP, Haas JS, Pérez-Stable EJ, Gregorich SE, Somkin C, Des Jarlais G, Kerlikowske K. Breast cancer risk reduction options: awareness, discussion, and use among women from four ethnic groups. Cancer Epidemiol Biomarkers Prev. 2006 Jan;15(1):162-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16434605</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Murff HJ, Byrne D, Haas JS, Puopolo AL, Brennan TA. Race and family history assessment for breast cancer. J Gen Intern Med. 2005 Jan;20(1):75-80.</citation>
    <PMID>15693932</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Weingart SN, Hamrick HE, Tutkus S, Carbo A, Sands DZ, Tess A, Davis RB, Bates DW, Phillips RS. Medication safety messages for patients via the web portal: the MedCheck intervention. Int J Med Inform. 2008 Mar;77(3):161-8. Epub 2007 Jun 19.</citation>
    <PMID>17581772</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adler-Milstein J, Bates DW, Jha AK. U.S. Regional health information organizations: progress and challenges. Health Aff (Millwood). 2009 Mar-Apr;28(2):483-92. doi: 10.1377/hlthaff.28.2.483.</citation>
    <PMID>19276008</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wright A, Poon EG, Wald J, Schnipper JL, Grant R, Gandhi TK, Volk LA, Bloom A, Williams DH, Gardner K, Epstein M, Nelson L, Businger A, Li Q, Bates DW, Middleton B. Effectiveness of health maintenance reminders provided directly to patients. AMIA Annu Symp Proc. 2008 Nov 6:1183.</citation>
    <PMID>18999087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Linder JA, Ma J, Bates DW, Middleton B, Stafford RS. Electronic health record use and the quality of ambulatory care in the United States. Arch Intern Med. 2007 Jul 9;167(13):1400-5.</citation>
    <PMID>17620534</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ozanne EM, Loberg A, Hughes S, Lawrence C, Drohan B, Semine A, Jellinek M, Cronin C, Milham F, Dowd D, Block C, Lockhart D, Sharko J, Grinstein G, Hughes KS. Identification and management of women at high risk for hereditary breast/ovarian cancer syndrome. Breast J. 2009 Mar-Apr;15(2):155-62. doi: 10.1111/j.1524-4741.2009.00690.x.</citation>
    <PMID>19292801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dominguez FJ, Lawrence C, Halpern EF, Drohan B, Grinstein G, Black DM, Smith BL, Gadd MA, Specht M, Kopans DB, Moore RH, Hughes SS, Roche CA, Hughes KS. Accuracy of self-reported personal history of cancer in an outpatient breast center. J Genet Couns. 2007 Jun;16(3):341-5. Epub 2007 May 17.</citation>
    <PMID>17508275</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guttmacher AE, Collins FS, Carmona RH. The family history--more important than ever. N Engl J Med. 2004 Nov 25;351(22):2333-6.</citation>
    <PMID>15564550</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 14, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 15, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 16, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 17, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 17, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">March 20, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Brigham and Women's Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jennifer S. Haas, MD, MSPH</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Family History</keyword>
  <keyword>Electronic Health Record</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

