<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00976807</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RJ1 09/N153</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00976807</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Rehabilitation Following Critical Illness</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomised Controlled Trial of Rehabilitation Following Critical Illness: A Short Term Feasibility and Follow-Up Pilot Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Guy's and St Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Guy's and St Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The principal research question to be answered by this study is whether an exercise based
      rehabilitative intervention following critical illness can generate improvements in exercise
      capacity and quality of life beyond current (usual) care. The investigators will also aim to
      demonstrate that such an intervention is both practical and cost-effective.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Advances in medicine mean that an increasing number of critically ill people, including those
      with severe pneumonia (lung infection), chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (also known as
      emphysema or chronic bronchitis) or the &quot;acute respiratory distress syndrome&quot;, survive
      admission to the hospital intensive care unit. Survivors report health problems such as
      breathlessness and weakness long after discharge. In a study monitoring over 800 patients
      discharged from an intensive care ward, over half required some form of caregiver assistance
      after 1-year.

      Whilst on intensive care, patients usually require help to breathe from a ventilator machine
      and become immobilised. This leads to weak breathing muscles in three quarters of patients,
      as well as weak and wasted arm and leg muscles. Survivors struggle to regain their previous
      level of daily activity and function, limited by shortness of breath, muscle weakness and
      tiredness. It is recognised that people with chronic lung problems, such as chronic
      obstructive pulmonary disease, face similar problems. In this condition, exercise based
      therapy has been shown to improve muscle strength, walking ability, shortness of breath, and
      importantly quality of life.

      Given these experiences, a new trial will evaluate a novel programme of exercise-based
      rehabilitation training in patients discharged from intensive care. The programme will last
      for 8-weeks and will use exercises designed to correct the breathing and limb muscle
      weakness, as well as education to help patients cope more effectively. The programme will
      begin as soon as possible following discharge from hospital and will be conducted on a mostly
      outpatient basis until the course is completed. By speeding the recovery of strength and
      activity, it is anticipated that quality of life will be improved, which this trial will
      attempt to measure.

      The rehabilitation programme will include aerobic cardiovascular, and upper and lower limb
      strengthening exercises, in addition to relevant education sessions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incremental Shuttle Walk Test</measure>
    <time_frame>Eight weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health Related Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>Eight weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Critical Illness Myopathy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pulmonary Rehabilitation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pulmonary Rehabilitation</intervention_name>
    <description>Eight week programme of twice-weekly (sixteen sessions) supervised exercise and education sessions. Exercise will include aerobic cardiovascular and upper and lower limb strengthening exercises. Each session will comprise a warm-up period, followed by individualised exercises, and completed with a cool-down, and last approximately 40minutes.
Aerobic exercise will be prescribed based on the results of walking tests and include walking, step-ups, cycling, and strength prescription according to the repetition maximum principle. Patients will complete three sets using this weight.
Furthermore Borg scores will be used within each session to guide and direct exercise intensity. A home exercise programme will also be designed and accompanied by a manual detailing the individual warm-up, exercises and cool-down, and diary sections to record independent activity.
Each session will also include an education session where relevant.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &gt;18 years AND admitted to critical care unit

          -  Ventilated &gt;48-hours (via endotracheal tube) OR received continuous non- invasive
             ventilation (NIV)/non-invasive continuous positive airways pressure (CPAP)

          -  Admitted to ICU &gt; 48-hours and evidence of SIRS

          -  Glasgow Coma Score (GCS) 15 (of 15) AND Abbreviated Mini-Mental Test Score (AMMTS) &gt;/=
             8 (of 10) on enrolment into rehabilitation programme

          -  Mobilising on ward to a degree sufficient as to begin a majority of proposed
             exercises. Clinical stability for observed exercise as judged by trial team is a
             prerequisite.

          -  Participant willingness to complete a programme of exercise based therapy aimed at
             reducing weakness and shortness of breath: subjective weakness or dyspnoea relative to
             their pre-admission state is implicit

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients referred for terminal care or prognosis likely to be less than 12-months

          -  Unstable coronary artery syndrome

          -  Limb amputation (given special requirement for orthotics/rehabilitation)

          -  Critical peripheral vascular disease awaiting re-vascularisation procedure (or
             claudication distance &lt;100 metres)

          -  Stroke with hemiparesis (likely need for specialised rehabilitation/stay on stroke
             unit)

          -  Severe, disabling locomotor problem or severe burns, which prevent effective
             participation in the exercises contained in the rehabilitation programme.

          -  Psychiatric disease necessitating anti-psychotic medication, deliberate drug overdose
             as the admitting ICU indication, ongoing treatment for drug or alcohol addiction,
             persons of no fixed abode post-discharge

          -  Patients undergoing renal haemodialysis (given the associated commitment to outpatient
             attendance)

          -  Extra contractual ICU referral (only if distance greater than suitable for twice
             weekly travel)

        Additional exclusion criteria for muscle biopsy samples:

          -  Coagulopathy e.g. warfarin use
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nicholas Hart, BSc (Hons), MBBS, MRCP, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>St.Thomas' Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>St.Thomas' Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE1 7EH</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>King's College Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>London</city>
        <zip>SE5 9RS</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 11, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 11, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 14, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 5, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 5, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 6, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Guy's and St Thomas' NHS Foundation Trust</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Bronwen Connolly</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Research Fellow</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>critical care</keyword>
  <keyword>intensive care</keyword>
  <keyword>weakness</keyword>
  <keyword>myopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>paresis</keyword>
  <keyword>rehabilitation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Critical Illness</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Muscular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

