<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00975013</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2-07-02-009</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00975013</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bone Loss After Laparoscopic Roux-en-Y Gastric Bypass</brief_title>
  <official_title>Losing More Than Just Weight: Bone Loss After Laparoscopic Roux-en-Y Gastric Bypass</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Gundersen Lutheran Medical Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Gundersen Lutheran Health System</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Gundersen Lutheran Medical Foundation</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to assess changes bone mineral density and bone metabolism
      after laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass surgery. The investigators hypothesize that
      weight loss after laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass surgery will be associated with
      increased bone turnover, changes in bone metabolism, and loss of bone mass.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Obesity is an increasing problem within the United States. Fifteen million people in the
      United States are considered morbidly obese, with a body mass index (BMI) greater than 40
      kg/m2. A wealth of literature has shown laparoscopic Roux-en Y gastric bypass surgery to be
      an effective procedure to reduce excess body weight. But a paucity of research examines the
      effects of laparoscopic Roux-en Y surgery on the skeleton.

      Bone remodeling is a complex process involving bone resorption and formation-a process
      dependent upon local and systemic influences. Obesity is one of these influences that is
      poorly understood. Obesity is associated with a reduced risk of osteoporosis. Obesity may be
      protective due to increased weight bearing, increased production of estrogen by adipose
      tissue, or increased bone formation due to higher levels of insulin.

      It is known that weight loss in healthy individuals is associated with bone loss. Several
      small studies have reported bone loss in patients undergoing vertical band gastroplasty or
      jejunoileal bypass weight loss surgeries. Other reported metabolic disease disarrangements
      following weight loss surgery are decreased serum calcium, decreased serum 25-hydroxy vitamin
      D, and hyperparathyroidism.

      In the bariatric literature, weight loss has been associated with an increased risk of bone
      mineral loss and fracture. Osteoporosis has been described in patients who lost weight after
      jejunoileal bypass surgery. Premenopausal women appeared to be spared from bone mineral loss,
      thus indicating a protective effect from the premenopausal state. Bone mineral loss is seen
      both in premenopausal women and in men after weight loss surgery.

      Roux-en Y gastric bypass has been shown to be more effective at weight loss than has the
      adjustable silicone gastric band. It has also been linked with increased loss of bone mineral
      density. Another study found an increase in bone turnover as well as a decrease in total bone
      mass and trochanteric bone density in laparoscopic Roux-en Y gastric bypass patients.

      Previous research at our institution has shown a statistically significant increase in the
      prevalence of hyperparathyroidism in post-gastric bypass patients. However, our previous
      research did not examine the impact that these hormonal changes impart upon bone density. We
      have found a statistically significant incidence of vitamin D deficiency in our patients
      following this surgery. We intend to expand upon our own research as well as that of others
      by exploring the associations between the development of hyperparathyroidism, bone metabolic
      derangements, weight loss, and bone density.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate bone densitometry and lab tests to assess changes in bone mass and bone turnover after laparoscopic gastric bypass surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>preoperatively and at 6 and 12 months after laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate weight loss, menopausal and nutritional status to assess correlations with results from bone densitometry and lab values after laparoscopic gastric bypass surgery</measure>
    <time_frame>preoperatively, and at 6 and 12 months after laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric bypass</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Bone Loss</condition>
  <condition>Bone Density</condition>
  <condition>Gastric Bypass</condition>
  <condition>Bariatric Surgery</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Bone Density Study Group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Morbidly obese, (BMI &gt;40 kg/m2, or 35 kg/m2 with comorbidities) female patients who have given consent to undergo additional testing including bone densitometry, and lab testing preoperatively and at 6 and 12 months after undergoing elective laparoscopic roux-en-Y gastric bypass.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      whole blood
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Study population will consist of patients undergoing laparoscopic gastric bypass at a
        community-based teaching institution
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Morbidly obese female patients undergoing elective laparoscopic Roux-en-Y gastric
             bypass at a single institution

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Male patients

          -  Patients unable to fulfill the study protocol requirements
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shanu N Kothari, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Gundersen Lutheran Health System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kevin P Riess, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Gundersen Lutheran Medical Foundation; Current Practice: SMDC Health System-Duluth Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Gundersen Lutheran Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Crosse</city>
        <state>Wisconsin</state>
        <zip>54601</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Must A, Spadano J, Coakley EH, Field AE, Colditz G, Dietz WH. The disease burden associated with overweight and obesity. JAMA. 1999 Oct 27;282(16):1523-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10546691</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morberg CM, Tetens I, Black E, Toubro S, Soerensen TI, Pedersen O, Astrup A. Leptin and bone mineral density: a cross-sectional study in obese and nonobese men. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2003 Dec;88(12):5795-800.</citation>
    <PMID>14671171</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cundy T, Evans MC, Kay RG, Dowman M, Wattie D, Reid IR. Effects of vertical-banded gastroplasty on bone and mineral metabolism in obese patients. Br J Surg. 1996 Oct;83(10):1468-72.</citation>
    <PMID>8944476</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>von Mach MA, Stoeckli R, Bilz S, Kraenzlin M, Langer I, Keller U. Changes in bone mineral content after surgical treatment of morbid obesity. Metabolism. 2004 Jul;53(7):918-21.</citation>
    <PMID>15254887</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Meyer HE, Tverdal A, Selmer R. Weight variability, weight change and the incidence of hip fracture: a prospective study of 39,000 middle-aged Norwegians. Osteoporos Int. 1998;8(4):373-8.</citation>
    <PMID>10024908</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bano G, Rodin DA, Pazianas M, Nussey SS. Reduced bone mineral density after surgical treatment for obesity. Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord. 1999 Apr;23(4):361-5.</citation>
    <PMID>10340813</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coates PS, Fernstrom JD, Fernstrom MH, Schauer PR, Greenspan SL. Gastric bypass surgery for morbid obesity leads to an increase in bone turnover and a decrease in bone mass. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2004 Mar;89(3):1061-5.</citation>
    <PMID>15001587</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goode LR, Brolin RE, Chowdhury HA, Shapses SA. Bone and gastric bypass surgery: effects of dietary calcium and vitamin D. Obes Res. 2004 Jan;12(1):40-7.</citation>
    <PMID>14742841</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carlin AM, Rao DS, Yager KM, Parikh NJ, Kapke A. Treatment of vitamin D depletion after Roux-en-Y gastric bypass: a randomized prospective clinical trial. Surg Obes Relat Dis. 2009 Jul-Aug;5(4):444-9. doi: 10.1016/j.soard.2008.08.004. Epub 2008 Aug 14.</citation>
    <PMID>18996761</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>September 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 10, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 10, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 11, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 4, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 4, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 7, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Gundersen Lutheran Medical Foundation</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kara Kallies</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Academic Researcher</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Laparoscopic Gastric Bypass</keyword>
  <keyword>Morbid Obesity</keyword>
  <keyword>Bone Mineral Density</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

