<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00965068</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>090203</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>09-CH-0203</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00965068</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cholesterol in ASD: Characterization and Treatment</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cholesterol in Autism Spectrum Disorder (ASD): Characterization and Treatment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - Autism spectrum disorders (ASD) are developmental disabilities characterized by impaired
      social interaction and repetitive and/or stereotypical behaviors. Research studies suggest
      that some individuals with ASD have very low blood cholesterol levels. This low cholesterol
      level and other abnormal sterol levels may be important markers for

      subtypes of ASD. Providing additional cholesterol to the diets of children with ASD may help
      improve behavior.

      - These findings will guide the medical community in identifying individuals who should be
      tested for sterol disorders. This study will also help researchers learn whether adding extra
      cholesterol to the diet will improve behavioral and other autism spectrum characteristics
      seen in individuals with ASD and low cholesterol.

      Objectives:

        -  To determine cholesterol levels in children with autism spectrum disorders.

        -  To compare behavioral and other characteristics among children who have autism spectrum
           disorders and high, low, or normal cholesterol levels.

        -  To determine whether adding cholesterol to the diet will improve behavioral and other
           characteristics in individuals with ASD and low cholesterol.

      Eligibility:

      - Children between the ages of 4 and 12 who have been diagnosed with an autism spectrum
      disorder.

      Design:

        -  Initial screening study will involve a collection of blood samples (for study purposes
           and cholesterol testing).

        -  Children who have low cholesterol levels will take part in a study in which they will
           receive either cholesterol supplementation or a placebo, and will have detailed physical
           and psychological examinations to measure possible improvement in behavioral or other
           characteristics.

        -  Children who have high or normal cholesterol levels will have further blood samples
           taken, and will undergo an additional set of examinations for comparison purposes.

        -  Researchers may request blood or DNA samples from other family members (parents or
           siblings), which will be collected through blood draws and cheek swabs.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pilot work suggests that some individuals with autism spectrum disorders (ASD) have very low
      blood cholesterol levels. This low cholesterol level and other abnormal sterol levels may be
      important markers for subtypes of ASD. The proposed trial aims to characterize any clinical
      differences between low-cholesterol ASD and normal-or-high-cholesterol ASD and to test the
      response of individuals with ASD and low cholesterol to increased cholesterol in the diet.

      Evidence for the role of low cholesterol in causing ASD in a subgroup of individuals comes
      from five sources. First, half of individuals with Smith-Lemli-Opitz syndrome (SLOS) meet the
      behavioral criteria for autistic disorder (Tierney et al, 2001), and three quarters have some
      type of ASD (Sikora et al, 2006). Second, in individuals with SLOS, the lower the cholesterol
      was in the blood and cerebrospinal fluid, the more severe were the autism and IQ and adaptive
      function deficits. Third, in SLOS, improvement was found in social and communication
      abilities with added dietary cholesterol. Fourth, cholesterol was low in a pilot study of 100
      children with autism of unknown cause (Tierney et al, 2006). Fifth, it is becoming
      increasingly clear that cholesterol plays a pivotal role in several aspects of brain
      development.

      This proposal is designed to 1) determine the prevalence of hypocholesterolemia in ASD
      individuals (ASD+Hypo); 2) determine the prevalence of hypercholesterolemia (in ASD
      individuals (ASD+Hyper); 3) determine the rate of SLOS in the ASD subjects; 4) determine the
      phenotype (physical, behavioral, and developmental) at less than the 5th centile (ASD+Hypo)
      and greater than the 95th centile (ASD+Hyper) individuals and normal cholesterol (ASD+Normal)
      in the ASD subjects; 5) test the efficacy of dietary cholesterol supplementation in ASD
      individuals with hypocholesterolemia; 6) determine whether a raised dose of cholesterol
      supplementation is more effective than a lower dose; and 7) create a repository of
      biomaterial samples from individuals with ASD and their biological family members.

      Three sites (Kennedy Krieger Institute [KKI], Ohio State University [OSU], and the National
      Institutes of Health [NIH]) will collaborate to accomplish the objectives of this study. In
      addition to defining the frequency of altered cholesterol homeostasis in ASD, 60 youths (20
      at each site) with ASD plus hypocholesterolemia will enter a 12-week, double-blind,
      placebo-controlled trial immediately followed by a 12-week open-label cholesterol trial to
      test the efficacy of dietary cholesterol supplementation. Outcome measures will include
      standard tests of behavior, communication, and other autism features.

      These findings will guide the medical community in identifying individuals who should be
      tested for sterol disorders. This study will also help researchers learn whether adding extra
      cholesterol to the diet will improve behavioral and other autism spectrum characteristics
      seen in individuals with ASD and low cholesterol. The results of this study may help
      individuals with hypocholesterolemic ASD by the knowledge of the therapeutic value and safety
      of the use of cholesterol supplementation both biochemically and behaviorally. If improvement
      is demonstrated, it opens a new window to understanding the neurologic mechanisms of ASD.
      This knowledge may also be helpful for hypocholesterolemic individuals with ASD in that this
      newly identified population will benefit from such supplementation. Even if cholesterol
      supplementation is found to not be effective, important behavioral phenotype and
      developmental information will be obtained that might be useful in identifying subjects with
      ASD plus cholesterol abnormalities.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 28, 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 14, 2013</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Behavioral Changes</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">44</enrollment>
  <condition>Autism</condition>
  <condition>Asperger Disorder</condition>
  <condition>PDD-NOS</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cholesterol</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION/EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Screening Visit:

        Inclusion:

          -  Parents agree to use a multivitamin with minerals if their child is selected to
             continue to the cholesterol supplementation clinical trial.

          -  Parents agree to not change the doses of other dietary supplement throughout the
             clinical trial, including megavitamins.

          -  Supplements or medications that are not meant to lower cholesterol levels but are
             likely to have cholesterol-lowering effects (such as Omega 3 or fish oil) will be
             permitted if the dose has been stable for at least 3 months prior to the initial
             screening visit.

          -  Male or female between the ages of 4.0-12.0 years at the time of consent/assent.

          -  Clinically diagnosed with an ASD for which no cause has been detected.

          -  Anticonvulsants used for the treatment of a seizure disorder will be permitted if the
             dosage has been stable for 3 months, and the subject is seizure free for at least 3
             months.

        Exclusion:

          -  Known pregnancy.

          -  Subject has SLOS or known cholesterol synthesis/regulation disorder.

          -  The subject has had an anticonvulsant dose change in the preceding 3 months or a
             seizure in the preceding 3 months.

          -  DSM-IV diagnosis of Rett Disorder, childhood disintegrative disorder, schizophrenia,
             another psychotic disorder, or substance abuse.

          -  A significant medical condition such as heart disease, hypertension, liver or renal
             failure, pulmonary disease, diabetes, or unstable seizure disorder identified by
             history, physical examination, or laboratory tests.

          -  Dietary supplementation doses, including megavitamins, have changed within the
             preceding 3 months.

          -  Currently on or has taken a statin or other medication meant to lower cholesterol
             within the preceding 3 months.

          -  Currently on or has taken dietary cholesterol supplementation within the preceding 3
             months.

          -  Subjects will be excluded if they are on other medications or supplements that affect
             cholesterol or other lipid levels.

          -  Subjects with gastronomy feeding tubes (G-tubes) will be excluded.

          -  Subjects for whom English is not the primary language will be excluded.

        (No subjects will be excluded based on race, ethnicity or gender).

        Characterization Visit:

        Inclusion:

          -  Same inclusion criteria as the Screening Visit.

          -  Participants must have a mental age of 18 months as measured at the Characterization
             Visit by the age-appropriate form of the Stanford Binet-V, the Differential Abilities
             Scale, or the Mullen Scales of Early Learning (N.B. potential subjects who test below
             18 months of age, but are otherwise eligible, may be admitted to the study following a
             case review convened by the Multisite Steering Committee).

          -  Child must have an ASD diagnosis using DSM-IV and clinical judgment in order to
             proceed to the other components of the Characterization Visit.

          -  Neuroleptics will be permitted for the ASD+Hypo group only if the dosage remains
             stable for the duration of the study.

          -  Neuroleptic medication free for at least three months (ASD+Hyper and ASD+Normal only).

        Exclusion:

          -  Same exclusion criteria as the Screening Visit.

          -  Allergy to lanolin or soy (Hypo+ASD only).

          -  Non-verbal mental age below 18 months as measured by the developmentally-appropriate
             form of the Stanford-Binet-V, Differential Abilities Scale, or the Mullen Scales of
             Early Learning (N.B. potential subjects who test below 18 months of age, but are
             otherwise eligible, may be admitted to the study following a case review convened by
             the Multisite Steering Committee).

          -  Did not meet the criteria for an ASD during the Characterization Visit.

        Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled trial phase for ASD+Hypo Only:

        Inclusion:

          -  Met Characterization Visit inclusion criteria and completed Characterization Visit
             procedures.

          -  Met criteria for hypocholesterolemia in ASD.

        Exclusion:

        -Same exclusion criteria as the Characterization Visit.

        Open-Label Trial for ASD+Hypo only:

        Inclusion:

        - Subject continues to meet double-blind, placebo-controlled trial phase inclusion
        criteria.

        Exclusion:

        - Subject started a neuroleptic medication or medication that affects cholesterol synthesis
        or metabolism.

        Family Members of ASD+Hypo only:

        Inclusion:

        - Biological parent(s) and full or half-sibling(s) of any age.

        Exclusion:

        - Those individuals not willing to provide a blood sample or a saliva sample for DNA.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>4 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>12 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Forbes D Porter, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Irons M, Elias ER, Abuelo D, Bull MJ, Greene CL, Johnson VP, Keppen L, Schanen C, Tint GS, Salen G. Treatment of Smith-Lemli-Opitz syndrome: results of a multicenter trial. Am J Med Genet. 1997 Jan 31;68(3):311-4.</citation>
    <PMID>9024565</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elias ER, Irons MB, Hurley AD, Tint GS, Salen G. Clinical effects of cholesterol supplementation in six patients with the Smith-Lemli-Opitz syndrome (SLOS). Am J Med Genet. 1997 Jan 31;68(3):305-10.</citation>
    <PMID>9024564</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kaufmann WE, Cortell R, Kau AS, Bukelis I, Tierney E, Gray RM, Cox C, Capone GT, Stanard P. Autism spectrum disorder in fragile X syndrome: communication, social interaction, and specific behaviors. Am J Med Genet A. 2004 Sep 1;129A(3):225-34.</citation>
    <PMID>15326621</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 8, 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 24, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 24, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 25, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Autism</keyword>
  <keyword>Autism Spectrum Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Cholesterol</keyword>
  <keyword>Smith-Lemli-Opitz Syndrome</keyword>
  <keyword>ASD</keyword>
  <keyword>Pervasive Developmental Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>PPD-NOS</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Autistic Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Autism Spectrum Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Asperger Syndrome</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

