<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00968721</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>090527</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00968721</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Decisional Influences and Inflammatory Bowel Disease (IBD) Patients' Medication Use</brief_title>
  <official_title>Decisional Influences and IBD Patients' Medication Use</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Vanderbilt University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Procter and Gamble</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Vanderbilt University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this study is to pilot test an instrument that the investigators will
      develop to assess decision influences on inflammatory bowel disease patients' medication
      adherence decision-making.

      This pilot study will use an exploratory, descriptive cross-sectional survey approach to
      pilot test the instrument and answer the research questions.

      The main hypothesis is that patients at risk for intentionally modifying their prescribed
      medication regimen will differ on influences on decision-making, health status, and
      utilization of the IBD clinic services compared to those who are intentionally adherent and
      who continue adherence over time.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Clinical research has produced significant advances in the pharmacologic management of
      inflammatory bowel disease (IBD). Preliminary research, however, suggest that patient
      non-adherence may be blunting medication effectiveness. The etiology of medication
      non-adherence likely depends on several coexisting factors. We believe that naturalistic
      decision making links patient level/ &quot;micro&quot; variables to services-level/ &quot;macro&quot; variables
      and behavioral outcomes. Every day, natural decisions about medication use are likely made in
      the context of patients' experience of their illness, knowledge about the illness and
      treatments, the physician-patient relationship, personal priorities and values, and other
      influences related to deciding to use medicine. By their very nature, illness related
      decisions are uncertain and risky because outcomes are unknown and patients often have
      limited knowledge and experience of the progression of their chronic illness. During the
      progression of an illness, patients may experiment with and analyze risks and benefits of
      therapies and relying on interpersonal interaction with health-care professionals to
      determine the self-management strategies best suited to patients and their life goals.
      Patient decision-making is thus and iterative process that evolves over time. An
      understanding of medication use decisions requires the description and understanding of those
      decision influences that may affect medication use decision-making over the course of the
      illness. Therefore, the primary purpose of this study is to develop and test a psychometric
      instrument that assesses influences on patients' decisions to use/not use their IBD
      medication.

      The main hypothesis underlying the instrument development project is that patients at risk
      for intentionally modifying their prescribed medication regimen will differ on influences on
      decision-making, health status, and utilization of the IBD clinic services compared to those
      who are intentionally adherent and who continue adherence over time.

      The following questions will be studied:

        -  What influences do therapeutic values, task difficulty, physician-patient relationship,
           information sources, personal beliefs and values have on patients' IBd medication
           adherence?

        -  What are the relationships between decision influences and illness activity?

        -  What associations exist among decision influences, illness activity, medication
           adherence and utilization of IBD Clinic services?
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    lack of support
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>June 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>What influences do therapeutic values, task difficulty, physician-patient relationship, information sources, personal beliefs and values have on patients' IBd medication adherence?</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>What are the relationships between decision influences and illness activity?</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>What associations exist among decision influences, illness activity, medication adherence and utilization of IBD Clinic services?</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">55</enrollment>
  <condition>Crohn's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Ulcerative Colitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>IBD patients</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The Vanderbilt University Medical Center Research Recruitment Registry will be used to
        identify the medical record and phone numbers of all VUMC patients recieving treatment for
        IBD.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All Vanderbilt University Medical Center IBD patients that are 18 years or older

          -  Those who volunteered to participate in this online web-based survey study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Vanderbilt University Medical Center patients unable to take the survey because they
             do not have an e-mail address or access to one.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lawrence S Gaines, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Inflammatory Bowel Disease Clinic c/o Divison of Gastroenterology, Hepatology and Nutrition, Department of Medicine, School of Medicine, Vanderbilt University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cervený P, Bortlík M, Kubena A, Vlcek J, Lakatos PL, Lukás M. Nonadherence in inflammatory bowel disease: results of factor analysis. Inflamm Bowel Dis. 2007 Oct;13(10):1244-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17538983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ediger JP, Walker JR, Graff L, Lix L, Clara I, Rawsthorne P, Rogala L, Miller N, McPhail C, Deering K, Bernstein CN. Predictors of medication adherence in inflammatory bowel disease. Am J Gastroenterol. 2007 Jul;102(7):1417-26. Epub 2007 Apr 16.</citation>
    <PMID>17437505</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harvey RF, Bradshaw JM. A simple index of Crohn's-disease activity. Lancet. 1980 Mar 8;1(8167):514.</citation>
    <PMID>6102236</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hicks FD, Holm K. Self-management decision influences in heart failure: a preliminary investigation. Clin Nurs Res. 2003 Feb;12(1):69-84.</citation>
    <PMID>12583500</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Horne, R. The medication adherence report scale. University of Brighton, Brighton, UK, 2004.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson MJ. The Medication Adherence Model: a guide for assessing medication taking. Res Theory Nurs Pract. 2002 Fall;16(3):179-92. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12472293</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kane SV, Brixner D, Rubin DT, Sewitch MJ. The challenge of compliance and persistence: focus on ulcerative colitis. J Manag Care Pharm. 2008 Jan;14(1 Suppl A):s2-12; quiz s13-5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18240888</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kane SV, Loftus EV Jr, Dubinsky MC, Sederman R. Disease perceptions among people with Crohn's disease. Inflamm Bowel Dis. 2008 Aug;14(8):1097-101. doi: 10.1002/ibd.20418.</citation>
    <PMID>18338774</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Riegel B, Carlson B, Moser DK, Sebern M, Hicks FD, Roland V. Psychometric testing of the self-care of heart failure index. J Card Fail. 2004 Aug;10(4):350-60.</citation>
    <PMID>15309704</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sewitch MJ, Abrahamowicz M, Dobkin PL, Tamblyn R. Measuring differences between patients' and physicians' health perceptions: the patient-physician discordance scale. J Behav Med. 2003 Jun;26(3):245-64.</citation>
    <PMID>12845937</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sewitch MJ, Abrahamowicz M, Barkun A, Bitton A, Wild GE, Cohen A, Dobkin PL. Patient nonadherence to medication in inflammatory bowel disease. Am J Gastroenterol. 2003 Jul;98(7):1535-44.</citation>
    <PMID>12873575</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Powell-Tuck J, Bown RL, Lennard-Jones JE. A comparison of oral prednisolone given as single or multiple daily doses for active proctocolitis. Scand J Gastroenterol. 1978;13(7):833-7.</citation>
    <PMID>364626</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wroe AL. Intentional and unintentional nonadherence: a study of decision making. J Behav Med. 2002 Aug;25(4):355-72.</citation>
    <PMID>12136497</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 28, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 28, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 31, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 28, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 28, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 2, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Inflammatory bowel disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Crohn's disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Ulcerative colitis</keyword>
  <keyword>medication adherence</keyword>
  <keyword>Decisional influences</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Crohn Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colitis, Ulcerative</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Inflammatory Bowel Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

