<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00969943</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>10598</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00969943</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Gender Differences in Response to Cues in Cocaine Dependence</brief_title>
  <official_title>Gender Differences in Response to Cues in Cocaine Dependence</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Medical University of South Carolina</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Medical University of South Carolina</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate whether men and women respond differently to seeing
      items related to cocaine use or to remembering stressful events. Four groups of individuals
      will be recruited to participate in this study: men with cocaine dependence, women with
      cocaine dependence, men without cocaine dependence, and women without cocaine dependence.

      Hypothesis #1: Cocaine-dependent women will demonstrate smaller increases in neuroendocrine,
      but greater increases in heart rate and more cocaine craving and subjective distress when
      exposed to stress as compared to cocaine-dependent men and non cocaine-dependent men and
      women.

      Hypothesis #2: Cocaine-dependent men will demonstrate greater increases in neuroendocrine,
      but greater increases in heart rate and more cocaine craving and subjective distress when
      exposed to cocaine-related cues as compared to cocaine-dependent women and non
      cocaine-dependent men and women.

      Hypothesis #3: Cocaine-dependent women will demonstrate greater increases in heart rate and
      more cocaine craving and subjective distress when exposed to stress inducing stimuli as
      compared to their own responses to a cocaine-related cue.

      Hypothesis #4: The neuroendocrine response to a stress hormone (corticotropin releasing
      hormone; CRH) will be greater in cocaine-dependent women as compared to cocaine-dependent
      men.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2007</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <condition>Cocaine Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cocaine-dependent Men</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cocaine-dependent Women</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Men</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control Women</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        There will be four primary sources of recruitment for cocaine dependent subjects: (1)
        patients referred from the Center for Drug and Alcohol Programs (CDAP) intake coordinator,
        (2) individuals presenting to CDAP for either inpatient or outpatient treatment, (3)
        individuals presenting to the Charleston Center for inpatient or outpatient treatment, (4)
        and individuals presenting to the Dorchester Alcohol and Drug Commission (DADC) for
        treatment. Control subjects will be recruited from the Charleston community
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects must be able to provide informed consent and function at an intellectual
             level sufficient to allow accurate completion of all assessment instruments.

          -  Subjects must consent to remain abstinent from all drugs of abuse (except nicotine)
             for a two-day period immediately prior to the GCRC admission. In cases where lab
             results, subject self-report, or staff observation suggests that a patient has used
             alcohol or drugs within two days of hospital admission, the patient will be admitted
             at the discretion of on-call study staff. Nicotine dependence can affect HPA function
             (Baron et al., 1995) therefore it would be ideal to exclude subjects with nicotine use
             from all four groups. Because of the high comorbidity of alcohol use and cocaine
             dependence, individuals with alcohol abuse or dependence will be included.
             Approximately equal numbers of nicotine-dependent individuals will be recruited into
             each of the study groups. Alcohol use for two days prior to testing will be
             discouraged, and nicotine use immediately prior to the testing session will be
             controlled.

          -  Subjects must consent to random assignment.

          -  Subjects must consent to outpatient admission at the GCRC and two overnight admissions
             at the Medical University Hospital.

          -  Subjects must consent to a one-week and one-month follow-up visit after the GCRC
             admission.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Women who are pregnant, nursing or of childbearing potential and not practicing an
             effective means of birth control. Because oral contraceptives may affect HPA axis
             function, the number of women on various types of oral contraceptives (triphasic vs
             static) and women on depot progesterone will be balanced between groups

          -  Women with premenstrual dysphoric disorder as this may impact on the response to the
             stress test procedure (Woods et al., 1994).

          -  Subjects with evidence of or a history of significant hematological, endocrine,
             cardiovascular, pulmonary, renal, gastrointestinal, or neurological disease including
             diabetes, as these conditions may affect HPA axis function.

          -  Subjects with any liver function test (LFTs) of greater than two times normal, as
             compromised liver function can interfere with HPA axis activity (Williams &amp; Dluhy,
             1987).

          -  Subjects with Addison's disease, Cushing's disease or other diseases of the adrenal
             cortex likely to affect HPA axis function.

          -  Subjects with a history of or current psychotic disorder or bipolar affective disorder
             as these may interfere with HPA function.

          -  Subjects with current major depressive disorder or post-traumatic stress disorder as
             these disorders are associated with characteristic changes in HPA axis function.

          -  Subjects receiving synthetic glucocorticoid therapy, any exogenous steroid therapy, or
             treatment with other agents that interfere with HPA axis function within one month of
             the time of testing.

          -  Subjects taking opiates, opiate antagonists, or benzodiazepines. (Subjects who have
             been maintained on SSRI's, anticonvulsants, or antipsychotics (for sleep only) for
             more than 8 weeks or longer are NOT excluded).

          -  Subjects with any acute illness or fever as this may affect HPA axis activity.
             Individuals who otherwise meet study criteria will be rescheduled for evaluation for
             participation.

          -  Subjects who are 30% over ideal weight or have a BMI greater than 30 will be
             considered for study participation based on the clinical judgment of study staff.

          -  Subjects who are unwilling to maintain abstinence from alcohol and other drugs of
             abuse (except nicotine) for two days prior to the stress task procedure.

          -  Women who gave birth to a child within the past 6 months of initial screening.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MUSC-Clinical Neurosciences Division</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charleston</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29425</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Brady KT, McRae AL, Moran-Santa Maria MM, DeSantis SM, Simpson AN, Waldrop AE, Back SE, Kreek MJ. Response to corticotropin-releasing hormone infusion in cocaine-dependent individuals. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2009 Apr;66(4):422-30. doi: 10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2009.9.</citation>
    <PMID>19349312</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 1, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 1, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 2, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Medical University of South Carolina</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Kathleen Brady, MD, PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Distinguished University Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HPA axis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cocaine-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cocaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

