<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03239782</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MONW</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03239782</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The &quot;Metabolically-obese Normal-weight&quot; Phenotype and Its Reversal by Calorie Restriction</brief_title>
  <official_title>The &quot;Metabolically-obese Normal-weight&quot; Phenotype in Two Asian Ethnic Groups and Its Reversal by Calorie Restriction</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Clinical Nutrition Research Centre, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Clinical Nutrition Research Centre, Singapore</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The prevalence of overweight and obesity in Singapore is approximately half of that in the
      United States, yet the incidence of type 2 diabetes is similar, and is expected to double in
      the near future. This indicates that metabolic dysfunction, particularly insulin resistance,
      is widely prevalent even among individuals who are considered normal-weight or lean by
      conventional measures, i.e. body mass index (BMI) and percent body fat. These individuals are
      often referred to as &quot;metabolically-obese normal-weight&quot; (MONW), and have increased risk for
      cardiometabolic disease despite their normal BMI and total body fat values. The prevalence of
      the MONW phenotype varies across populations and differs markedly among different
      ethnicities. However, our understanding of the complex interactions between ethnicity, body
      composition, and metabolic dysfunction and its reversal remains rudimentary. Previous
      attempts to characterize the MONW phenotype are confounded by the small but significant
      differences in BMI or percent body fat between groups (even if all subjects were lean, within
      the &quot;normal&quot; range), with MONW subjects being always &quot;fatter&quot; than the corresponding control
      subjects. There are no published studies that prospectively recruited groups of metabolically
      healthy and unhealthy lean individuals matched on BMI and percent body fat. Furthermore,
      although weight loss improves body composition and many of the cardiometabolic abnormalities
      in most obese patients, little is known about the possible therapeutic effects of calorie
      restriction in MONW subjects.

      Accordingly, a better understanding of the MONW phenotype and the evaluation of therapeutic
      approaches for its reversal will have important implications for public health. By
      facilitating earlier identification of these subjects, who are more likely to go undiagnosed
      and thus less likely to be treated before clinically overt cardiometabolic disease develops,
      results from this study will allow for earlier and effective intervention.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      By the year 2050, it is estimated that more than half of the Singapore population will be
      overweight or obese, defined as having a body mass index (BMI, calculated as the weight in
      kilograms divided by the square of height in meters) equal to or greater than 25 kg/m2 (Phan
      et al. 2014). This is likely responsible, at least in part, for the concomitant increase in
      obesity-related co-morbid conditions, particularly type 2 diabetes (Phan et al. 2014; Ni
      Mhurchu et al. 2006). The relationship between BMI and the risk for type 2 diabetes in
      populations from the Asia-Pacific region is linear within a wide range of BMI values (from
      ~21 kg/m2 to ~34 kg/m2), so that for every 2 kg/m2 increase in BMI (which corresponds to ~6
      kg for a normal-weight person of average stature), the risk for developing type 2 diabetes
      rises by ~27 % (Ni Mhurchu et al. 2006). In Singapore, the prevalence of type 2 diabetes is
      expected to double from 7.3 % in 1990 to ~15 % in 2050, predominantly as a result of the
      fattening of the population, with the burden being greater for those of Indian descent than
      those of Chinese descent (Phan et al. 2014). This is expected to reduce productivity, inflate
      healthcare costs, and increase mortality among Singaporeans (Phan et al. 2014; Ma et al.
      2003).

      The prevalence of type 2 diabetes in Singapore is similar to that in the United States, even
      though the prevalence of overweight and obesity (BMI ≥25 kg/m2) in Singapore is approximately
      half that in the US (Yoon et al. 2006). This observation corroborates findings from many
      studies showing that markers of metabolic dysfunction (e.g. hyperglycemia, hyperinsulinemia,
      insulin resistance, dyslipidemia, and hypertension) are highly prevalent among Singaporean
      adults even at normal BMI values, i.e. even among people who are considered &quot;normal-weight&quot;
      or &quot;lean&quot; by conventional measures (Deurenberg-Yap et al. 1999; Deurenberg-Yap, Chew, et al.
      2001). The existence of people who have normal body weight but also have metabolic
      dysfunction, and therefore greater risk for developing cardiometabolic disease, was
      recognized several decades ago (Ruderman et al. 1998; Ruderman, Schneider, and Berchtold
      1981). At the extreme of this paradigm, even among members of the Calorie Restriction Society
      who undergo self-imposed calorie restriction for years based on the belief that this will
      help them ensure a long and healthy life, there are many individuals (~40 %) with impaired
      glucose tolerance, despite very low BMI and total body fat (Fontana, Klein, and Holloszy
      2010). These individuals are often referred to as &quot;metabolically-obese normal-weight&quot; (MONW)
      or &quot;metabolically-abnormal lean&quot; or &quot;metabolically-unhealthy lean&quot; subjects. The prevalence
      of this phenotype ranges from 5 % to 45 % depending on the BMI and the metabolic criteria
      used for its definition, as well as the characteristics of the population (i.e. age, sex, and
      ethnicity) (Conus, Rabasa-Lhoret, and Peronnet 2007; Teixeira et al. 2015). Similar
      variability has been observed across Asia (Lee et al. 2011; Luo et al. 2015; Yoo et al. 2014;
      Jung et al. 2015; Indulekha et al. 2015). For example, among the Chinese, ~8 % of the
      population as a whole, or ~13 % of those who are considered lean by virtue of body fat
      percent (i.e. ≤25 % for men and ≤35 % for women), are metabolically unhealthy, defined as
      having three or more metabolic abnormalities characteristic of the metabolic syndrome (Luo et
      al. 2015). Among Indians, on the other hand, 15-25 % of the population (or 20-40 % of those
      who are considered lean by virtue of BMI, i.e. &lt;25 kg/m2) satisfies the criteria for
      metabolic syndrome (Indulekha et al. 2015; Geetha et al. 2011). The MONW phenotype in Asians
      is associated with 3-fold greater risk for carotid atherosclerosis (i.e. cardiovascular
      disease) (Yoo et al. 2014) and 4.5-8.5-fold greater risk for developing type 2 diabetes (Luo
      et al. 2015). In fact, MONW subjects have increased risk for cardiometabolic disease (Luo et
      al. 2015; Yoo et al. 2014) and greater all-cause mortality (Choi et al. 2013) not only
      compared to metabolically-healthy lean subjects, but also compared to metabolically-healthy
      obese subjects. This underscores the importance of metabolic dysfunction independent of
      excess body weight and total adiposity.

      The mechanisms responsible for the development of metabolic abnormalities in lean people are
      not entirely clear. The MONW phenotype can manifest early in life, e.g. during childhood
      (Guerrero-Romero et al. 2013), which corroborates the existence of genetic predisposition for
      metabolic dysfunction in the face of low BMI values (Yaghootkar et al. 2014). Previous
      studies have identified a number of factors associated with the MONW phenotype, including
      increased intra-abdominal (visceral) adipose tissue, increased liver and muscle fat content,
      increased fat cell size, adipose tissue inflammation, altered inflammatory and adipokine
      profiles, reduced skeletal muscle mass, lack of physical activity, and low cardio-respiratory
      fitness (Badoud et al. 2015; Dvorak et al. 1999; Ruderman et al. 1998; Conus, Rabasa-Lhoret,
      and Peronnet 2007; De Lorenzo et al. 2007; Karelis et al. 2004; Kim et al. 2013; Lee 2009;
      Oliveros et al. 2014; Teixeira et al. 2015; Di Renzo et al. 2006; Conus et al. 2004;
      Indulekha et al. 2015; Luo et al. 2015; Fontana, Klein, and Holloszy 2010). All of these
      factors have been directly or indirectly associated with insulin resistance (defined by a
      variety of methods), which is by far the commonest metabolic correlate of the MONW phenotype
      across all ethnicities, age groups, and sexes (Conus, Rabasa-Lhoret, and Peronnet 2007;
      Oliveros et al. 2014; Karelis et al. 2004; Ruderman et al. 1998). In fact, the greater
      prevalence of the MONW phenotype in Indians (Indulekha et al. 2015; Geetha et al. 2011) than
      in the Chinese (Luo et al. 2015) mirrors results obtained recently by our team, showing that
      among lean Singaporean men (BMI &lt;25 kg/m2 or body fat ≤20 %), those of Indian descent have
      significantly lower insulin sensitivity, evaluated as the insulin-mediated glucose disposal
      rate during a hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp procedure, compared to those of Chinese
      descent (Khoo et al. 2014). Similar results have been reported by other investigators in
      smaller groups of subjects (Liew et al. 2003) or when using simpler indices of insulin
      sensitivity (Khoo et al. 2011; Tai et al. 2000). Therefore, an insulin resistant glucose
      metabolism, broadly defined by subnormal responses to physiological insulin concentrations
      (Kahn 1978), is the hallmark of the MONW phenotype.

      Owing to the lack of a consistent definition, there is some variability among studies in the
      phenotypic characterization of MONW subjects (Teixeira et al. 2015). This is further
      complicated by the small but significant differences in BMI and, more commonly, percent body
      fat between groups of metabolically healthy and unhealthy lean subjects, with MONW subjects
      being always somewhat &quot;fatter&quot; (even though within the &quot;lean&quot; range) (Ruderman et al. 1998;
      Di Renzo et al. 2006; Badoud et al. 2015; Luo et al. 2015; Indulekha et al. 2015; Dvorak et
      al. 1999; Conus et al. 2004; De Lorenzo et al. 2007). Likewise, BMI and body fat are
      typically greater in relatively insulin-resistant (e.g. Indian) than in relatively
      insulin-sensitive (e.g. Chinese) individuals in studies reporting on ethnic differences in
      insulin action among lean people (Khoo et al. 2014; Khoo et al. 2011). This in itself could
      be responsible for the differences observed in metabolic function. There is considerable
      (~2-fold range) variability between individuals in the percent body fat (Gallagher et al.
      2000; Gallagher et al. 1996) and the insulin-mediated glucose disposal rate (a direct measure
      of whole-body insulin sensitivity) (Bradley, Magkos, and Klein 2012) for the same BMI value
      within the normal-weight range (i.e. BMI &lt;25 kg/m2), so that people with the same BMI can
      have very different body fat and insulin sensitivity without this necessarily being
      associated with the presence or absence of generalized metabolic dysfunction. Even among lean
      and metabolically-healthy Asians, total body fat is a major correlate of insulin-mediated
      glucose disposal (Rattarasarn et al. 2003). It is thus possible that some of the reported
      differences between metabolically healthy and unhealthy lean subjects arise from normal
      variability and the differences in body fat between groups, rather than being an inherent
      characteristic of the MONW phenotype. In support of this possibility, when metabolically
      healthy and unhealthy lean subjects (defined as those having normal and impaired glucose
      tolerance, respectively) were retrospectively matched on total body fat, there were no
      differences between phenotypes in circulating concentrations of metabolic and inflammatory
      markers (i.e. high-density lipoprotein (HDL)-cholesterol, triglycerides, free fatty acids,
      C-reactive protein, adiponectin, and leptin) (Fontana, Klein, and Holloszy 2010). There are
      no studies that prospectively recruited groups of metabolically healthy and unhealthy lean
      individuals matched on BMI and percent body fat. A deeper understanding of the MONW
      phenotype, as proposed here, is important to dissect the metabolic abnormalities that are
      inherent to the phenotype from those merely associated with differences in total body fat.
      This will allow for proper identification and more efficient therapeutic targeting of MONW
      individuals, who are at greater risk for cardiometabolic disease.

      Little is known about possible interventions for improving metabolic function in MONW
      subjects. It is well established that diet-induced weight loss can improve body composition
      and many of the cardiometabolic abnormalities in most obese patients (e.g. decreases total
      body fat, intra-abdominal adipose tissue, and ectopic fat deposition in liver and muscle;
      increases insulin sensitivity; improves blood lipid profile; and reduces blood pressure)
      (Dattilo and Kris-Etherton 1992; de Leiva 1998; Goldstein 1992; Kirk et al. 2009; Muscelli et
      al. 1997; Pi-Sunyer 1993; Pasanisi et al. 2001; Escalante-Pulido et al. 2003; Mazzali et al.
      2006; Klein, Wadden, and Sugerman 2002), so that a moderate 10 % weight loss has become the
      cornerstone of obesity treatment (Jensen et al. 2014). However, MONW individuals are by
      definition lean, so recommending even moderate amounts of weight loss may not be a feasible
      therapeutic target (Miller and Parsonage 1975). It is therefore important to better
      understand the metabolic effects of smaller amounts of weight loss. Recently, the principal
      investigator conducted a randomized controlled trial to evaluate the effects of mild weight
      loss (5 % of initial body weight) on cardiometabolic function in non-Asian subjects with
      obesity and insulin resistance and found that even this small amount of weight loss decreases
      fat deposition in the liver and the intra-abdominal area, and increases insulin action in
      skeletal muscle, liver, and adipose tissue (Magkos et al. 2016). These results demonstrate
      that mild weight loss can improve many cardiometabolic abnormalities in
      metabolically-unhealthy obese subjects, but whether the same holds true for
      metabolically-unhealthy lean subjects is not known. A small, non-randomized, single-arm study
      in 7 lean, insulin-resistant offspring of parents with type 2 diabetes reported that modest
      ~6 % diet-induced weight loss reduced intra-myocellular lipid (i.e. fat within skeletal
      muscle fibers) content and increased insulin-mediated glucose disposal rate (both by ~30 %
      compared with baseline values), but did not significantly affect intra-abdominal adipose
      tissue volume or liver fat content (Petersen et al. 2012). It is thus not known whether mild
      diet-induced weight loss produces similar changes in body composition, fat distribution, and
      metabolic function in lean versus obese metabolically unhealthy subjects.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">March 29, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 7, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 7, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Whole-body insulin sensitivity</measure>
    <time_frame>3 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Our primary endpoint is whole-body insulin sensitivity (i.e. the major metabolic correlate of the MONW phenotype), determined by using the hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">77</enrollment>
  <condition>Glucose Metabolism Disorders</condition>
  <condition>Obesity, Visceral</condition>
  <condition>Obesity; Endocrine</condition>
  <condition>Insulin Sensitivity/Resistance</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Metabolically unhealthy</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Subjects classified as metabolically unhealthy (MONW) go on to participate in a calorie restriction intervention.
MONW subjects will participate in a supervised weight loss program to help ensure they are under a similar weekly energy deficit and achieve a 5 % weight loss at approximately the same time. Participants will be prescribed a reduced-calorie diet (~500 kcal/d below their needs for weight maintenance), and will be instructed not to change their physical activity habits, in order to achieve a weekly weight loss of ~0.5 kg.
The macronutrient composition of the diet will be the same for all groups (55-60 % of energy from carbohydrate, 15-20 % from protein, and 20-30 % from fat); no vitamins or other nutritional supplements will be given.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Calorie restriction</intervention_name>
    <description>Calorie restriction with behavioral modification and provision of one catered, reduced calorie meal a day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Metabolically unhealthy</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy male or female

          -  Chinese or Indian descent

          -  Between 21-65 years old (inclusive)

          -  BMI from &gt;=19 to &lt;25 kg/m2

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  BMI ≥25 kg/m2

          -  BMI &lt;19 kg/m2 (to avoid the risk of subjects becoming seriously underweight (i.e. BMI
             ≤18 kg/m2) after 5 % weight loss)

          -  Age &lt;21 and &gt;65 yrs

          -  Use of medications that can affect metabolic function (including oral contraceptives
             and hormone replacement therapy)

          -  Regular use of tobacco products

          -  Regular consumption of alcohol

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women

          -  Evidence of significant organ system dysfunction or disease

          -  Recent weight loss (≥5 % over the past 6 months)

          -  Severe asthma and respiratory problems that prevent subjects from exercising
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Faidon Magkos, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Singapore Institute for Clinical Sciences, Agency for Science, Technology and Research</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Phan TP, Alkema L, Tai ES, Tan KH, Yang Q, Lim WY, Teo YY, Cheng CY, Wang X, Wong TY, Chia KS, Cook AR. Forecasting the burden of type 2 diabetes in Singapore using a demographic epidemiological model of Singapore. BMJ Open Diabetes Res Care. 2014 Jun 11;2(1):e000012. doi: 10.1136/bmjdrc-2013-000012. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25452860</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Asia Pacific Cohort Studies Collaboration, Ni Mhurchu C, Parag V, Nakamura M, Patel A, Rodgers A, Lam TH. Body mass index and risk of diabetes mellitus in the Asia-Pacific region. Asia Pac J Clin Nutr. 2006;15(2):127-33. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>16672195</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ma S, Cutter J, Tan CE, Chew SK, Tai ES. Associations of diabetes mellitus and ethnicity with mortality in a multiethnic Asian population: data from the 1992 Singapore National Health Survey. Am J Epidemiol. 2003 Sep 15;158(6):543-52.</citation>
    <PMID>12965880</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yoon KH, Lee JH, Kim JW, Cho JH, Choi YH, Ko SH, Zimmet P, Son HY. Epidemic obesity and type 2 diabetes in Asia. Lancet. 2006 Nov 11;368(9548):1681-8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17098087</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deurenberg-Yap M, Yian TB, Kai CS, Deurenberg P, VAN Staveren WA. Manifestation of cardiovascular risk factors at low levels of body mass index and waist-to-hip ratio in Singaporean Chinese. Asia Pac J Clin Nutr. 1999 Sep;8(3):177-83.</citation>
    <PMID>24394159</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deurenberg-Yap M, Chew SK, Lin VF, Tan BY, van Staveren WA, Deurenberg P. Relationships between indices of obesity and its co-morbidities in multi-ethnic Singapore. Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord. 2001 Oct;25(10):1554-62.</citation>
    <PMID>11673781</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruderman N, Chisholm D, Pi-Sunyer X, Schneider S. The metabolically obese, normal-weight individual revisited. Diabetes. 1998 May;47(5):699-713. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9588440</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ruderman NB, Schneider SH, Berchtold P. The &quot;metabolically-obese,&quot; normal-weight individual. Am J Clin Nutr. 1981 Aug;34(8):1617-21.</citation>
    <PMID>7270486</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Conus F, Rabasa-Lhoret R, Péronnet F. Characteristics of metabolically obese normal-weight (MONW) subjects. Appl Physiol Nutr Metab. 2007 Feb;32(1):4-12. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>17332780</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Teixeira TF, Alves RD, Moreira AP, Peluzio Mdo C. Main characteristics of metabolically obese normal weight and metabolically healthy obese phenotypes. Nutr Rev. 2015 Mar;73(3):175-90. doi: 10.1093/nutrit/nuu007. Epub 2015 Feb 13.</citation>
    <PMID>26024540</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee SH, Ha HS, Park YJ, Lee JH, Yim HW, Yoon KH, Kang MI, Lee WC, Son HY, Park YM, Kwon HS. Identifying metabolically obese but normal-weight (MONW) individuals in a nondiabetic Korean population: the Chungju Metabolic disease Cohort (CMC) study. Clin Endocrinol (Oxf). 2011 Oct;75(4):475-81. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2265.2011.04085.x.</citation>
    <PMID>21521351</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Luo D, Liu F, Li X, Yin D, Lin Z, Liu H, Hou X, Wang C, Jia W. Comparison of the effect of 'metabolically healthy but obese' and 'metabolically abnormal but not obese' phenotypes on development of diabetes and cardiovascular disease in Chinese. Endocrine. 2015 May;49(1):130-8. doi: 10.1007/s12020-014-0444-2. Epub 2014 Oct 14.</citation>
    <PMID>25312689</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yoo HJ, Hwang SY, Hong HC, Choi HY, Seo JA, Kim SG, Kim NH, Choi DS, Baik SH, Choi KM. Association of metabolically abnormal but normal weight (MANW) and metabolically healthy but obese (MHO) individuals with arterial stiffness and carotid atherosclerosis. Atherosclerosis. 2014 May;234(1):218-23. doi: 10.1016/j.atherosclerosis.2014.02.033. Epub 2014 Mar 16.</citation>
    <PMID>24681911</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jung CH, Lee MJ, Kang YM, Jang JE, Leem J, Hwang JY, Kim EH, Park JY, Kim HK, Lee WJ. The risk of incident type 2 diabetes in a Korean metabolically healthy obese population: the role of systemic inflammation. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2015 Mar;100(3):934-41. doi: 10.1210/jc.2014-3885. Epub 2014 Dec 9. Erratum in: J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2015 Apr;100(4):1709.</citation>
    <PMID>25490279</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Badoud F, Perreault M, Zulyniak MA, Mutch DM. Molecular insights into the role of white adipose tissue in metabolically unhealthy normal weight and metabolically healthy obese individuals. FASEB J. 2015 Mar;29(3):748-58. doi: 10.1096/fj.14-263913. Epub 2014 Nov 19. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>25411437</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bradley D, Magkos F, Klein S. Effects of bariatric surgery on glucose homeostasis and type 2 diabetes. Gastroenterology. 2012 Oct;143(4):897-912. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2012.07.114. Epub 2012 Aug 8. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22885332</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Choi KM, Cho HJ, Choi HY, Yang SJ, Yoo HJ, Seo JA, Kim SG, Baik SH, Choi DS, Kim NH. Higher mortality in metabolically obese normal-weight people than in metabolically healthy obese subjects in elderly Koreans. Clin Endocrinol (Oxf). 2013 Sep;79(3):364-70. doi: 10.1111/cen.12154. Epub 2013 May 11.</citation>
    <PMID>23330616</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Conus F, Allison DB, Rabasa-Lhoret R, St-Onge M, St-Pierre DH, Tremblay-Lebeau A, Poehlman ET. Metabolic and behavioral characteristics of metabolically obese but normal-weight women. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2004 Oct;89(10):5013-20.</citation>
    <PMID>15472199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dattilo AM, Kris-Etherton PM. Effects of weight reduction on blood lipids and lipoproteins: a meta-analysis. Am J Clin Nutr. 1992 Aug;56(2):320-8.</citation>
    <PMID>1386186</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Leiva A. What are the benefits of moderate weight loss? Exp Clin Endocrinol Diabetes. 1998;106 Suppl 2:10-3. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9792475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De Lorenzo A, Del Gobbo V, Premrov MG, Bigioni M, Galvano F, Di Renzo L. Normal-weight obese syndrome: early inflammation? Am J Clin Nutr. 2007 Jan;85(1):40-5.</citation>
    <PMID>17209175</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Di Renzo L, Del Gobbo V, Bigioni M, Premrov MG, Cianci R, De Lorenzo A. Body composition analyses in normal weight obese women. Eur Rev Med Pharmacol Sci. 2006 Jul-Aug;10(4):191-6.</citation>
    <PMID>16910350</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dvorak RV, DeNino WF, Ades PA, Poehlman ET. Phenotypic characteristics associated with insulin resistance in metabolically obese but normal-weight young women. Diabetes. 1999 Nov;48(11):2210-4.</citation>
    <PMID>10535456</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Escalante-Pulido M, Escalante-Herrera A, Milke-Najar ME, Alpizar-Salazar M. Effects of weight loss on insulin secretion and in vivo insulin sensitivity in obese diabetic and non-diabetic subjects. Diabetes Nutr Metab. 2003 Oct-Dec;16(5-6):277-83.</citation>
    <PMID>15000438</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fontana L, Klein S, Holloszy JO. Effects of long-term calorie restriction and endurance exercise on glucose tolerance, insulin action, and adipokine production. Age (Dordr). 2010 Mar;32(1):97-108. doi: 10.1007/s11357-009-9118-z. Epub 2009 Nov 11.</citation>
    <PMID>19904628</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gallagher D, Heymsfield SB, Heo M, Jebb SA, Murgatroyd PR, Sakamoto Y. Healthy percentage body fat ranges: an approach for developing guidelines based on body mass index. Am J Clin Nutr. 2000 Sep;72(3):694-701.</citation>
    <PMID>10966886</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gallagher D, Visser M, Sepúlveda D, Pierson RN, Harris T, Heymsfield SB. How useful is body mass index for comparison of body fatness across age, sex, and ethnic groups? Am J Epidemiol. 1996 Feb 1;143(3):228-39.</citation>
    <PMID>8561156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Geetha L, Deepa M, Anjana RM, Mohan V. Prevalence and clinical profile of metabolic obesity and phenotypic obesity in Asian Indians. J Diabetes Sci Technol. 2011 Mar 1;5(2):439-46.</citation>
    <PMID>21527117</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goldstein DJ. Beneficial health effects of modest weight loss. Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord. 1992 Jun;16(6):397-415. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>1322866</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Guerrero-Romero F, Aradillas-García C, Simental-Mendía LE, Torres-Rodríguez ML, Mendoza Ede L, Rosales-Cervantes J, Rodríguez-Ramírez G, Rodríguez-Moran M. Biochemical characteristics and risk factors for insulin resistance at different levels of obesity. Pediatrics. 2013 Apr;131(4):e1211-7. doi: 10.1542/peds.2012-1421. Epub 2013 Mar 11.</citation>
    <PMID>23478864</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Indulekha K, Surendar J, Anjana RM, Geetha L, Gokulakrishnan K, Pradeepa R, Mohan V. Metabolic obesity, adipocytokines, and inflammatory markers in Asian Indians--CURES-124. Diabetes Technol Ther. 2015 Feb;17(2):134-41. doi: 10.1089/dia.2014.0202. Epub 2014 Dec 5.</citation>
    <PMID>25478993</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jensen MD, Ryan DH, Apovian CM, Ard JD, Comuzzie AG, Donato KA, Hu FB, Hubbard VS, Jakicic JM, Kushner RF, Loria CM, Millen BE, Nonas CA, Pi-Sunyer FX, Stevens J, Stevens VJ, Wadden TA, Wolfe BM, Yanovski SZ; American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines; Obesity Society. 2013 AHA/ACC/TOS guideline for the management of overweight and obesity in adults: a report of the American College of Cardiology/American Heart Association Task Force on Practice Guidelines and The Obesity Society. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2014 Jul 1;63(25 Pt B):2985-3023. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2013.11.004. Epub 2013 Nov 12. Erratum in: J Am Coll Cardiol. 2014 Jul 1;63(25 Pt B):3029-3030.</citation>
    <PMID>24239920</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kahn CR. Insulin resistance, insulin insensitivity, and insulin unresponsiveness: a necessary distinction. Metabolism. 1978 Dec;27(12 Suppl 2):1893-902.</citation>
    <PMID>723640</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karelis AD, St-Pierre DH, Conus F, Rabasa-Lhoret R, Poehlman ET. Metabolic and body composition factors in subgroups of obesity: what do we know? J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2004 Jun;89(6):2569-75. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>15181025</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khoo CM, Leow MK, Sadananthan SA, Lim R, Venkataraman K, Khoo EY, Velan SS, Ong YT, Kambadur R, McFarlane C, Gluckman PD, Lee YS, Chong YS, Tai ES. Body fat partitioning does not explain the interethnic variation in insulin sensitivity among Asian ethnicity: the Singapore adults metabolism study. Diabetes. 2014 Mar;63(3):1093-102. doi: 10.2337/db13-1483. Epub 2013 Dec 18. Erratum in: Diabetes. 2014 Jun;63(6):2183. Lee, Yun Seng [corrected to Lee, Yung Seng].</citation>
    <PMID>24353181</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Khoo CM, Sairazi S, Taslim S, Gardner D, Wu Y, Lee J, van Dam RM, Shyong Tai E. Ethnicity modifies the relationships of insulin resistance, inflammation, and adiponectin with obesity in a multiethnic Asian population. Diabetes Care. 2011 May;34(5):1120-6. doi: 10.2337/dc10-2097. Epub 2011 Apr 4.</citation>
    <PMID>21464462</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim TN, Park MS, Yang SJ, Yoo HJ, Kang HJ, Song W, Seo JA, Kim SG, Kim NH, Baik SH, Choi DS, Choi KM. Body size phenotypes and low muscle mass: the Korean sarcopenic obesity study (KSOS). J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 2013 Feb;98(2):811-7. doi: 10.1210/jc.2012-3292. Epub 2013 Jan 4.</citation>
    <PMID>23293328</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kirk E, Reeds DN, Finck BN, Mayurranjan SM, Patterson BW, Klein S. Dietary fat and carbohydrates differentially alter insulin sensitivity during caloric restriction. Gastroenterology. 2009 May;136(5):1552-60. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2009.01.048. Epub 2009 Jan 25. Erratum in: Gastroenterology. 2009 Jul;137(1):393. Mayurranjan, Mitra S [corrected to Mayurranjan S Mitra].</citation>
    <PMID>19208352</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klein S, Wadden T, Sugerman HJ. AGA technical review on obesity. Gastroenterology. 2002 Sep;123(3):882-932. Review. Erratum in: Gastroenterology 2002 Nov;123(5):1752.</citation>
    <PMID>12198715</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee K. Metabolically obese but normal weight (MONW) and metabolically healthy but obese (MHO) phenotypes in Koreans: characteristics and health behaviors. Asia Pac J Clin Nutr. 2009;18(2):280-4.</citation>
    <PMID>19713189</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Liew CF, Seah ES, Yeo KP, Lee KO, Wise SD. Lean, nondiabetic Asian Indians have decreased insulin sensitivity and insulin clearance, and raised leptin compared to Caucasians and Chinese subjects. Int J Obes Relat Metab Disord. 2003 Jul;27(7):784-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12821962</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Magkos F, Fraterrigo G, Yoshino J, Luecking C, Kirbach K, Kelly SC, de Las Fuentes L, He S, Okunade AL, Patterson BW, Klein S. Effects of Moderate and Subsequent Progressive Weight Loss on Metabolic Function and Adipose Tissue Biology in Humans with Obesity. Cell Metab. 2016 Apr 12;23(4):591-601. doi: 10.1016/j.cmet.2016.02.005. Epub 2016 Feb 22.</citation>
    <PMID>26916363</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mazzali G, Di Francesco V, Zoico E, Fantin F, Zamboni G, Benati C, Bambara V, Negri M, Bosello O, Zamboni M. Interrelations between fat distribution, muscle lipid content, adipocytokines, and insulin resistance: effect of moderate weight loss in older women. Am J Clin Nutr. 2006 Nov;84(5):1193-9.</citation>
    <PMID>17093174</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Miller DS, Parsonage S. Resistance to slimming: adaptation or illusion? Lancet. 1975 Apr 5;1(7910):773-5.</citation>
    <PMID>48002</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Muscelli E, Camastra S, Catalano C, Galvan AQ, Ciociaro D, Baldi S, Ferrannini E. Metabolic and cardiovascular assessment in moderate obesity: effect of weight loss. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1997 Sep;82(9):2937-43.</citation>
    <PMID>9284723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Oliveros E, Somers VK, Sochor O, Goel K, Lopez-Jimenez F. The concept of normal weight obesity. Prog Cardiovasc Dis. 2014 Jan-Feb;56(4):426-33. doi: 10.1016/j.pcad.2013.10.003. Epub 2013 Oct 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24438734</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pasanisi F, Contaldo F, de Simone G, Mancini M. Benefits of sustained moderate weight loss in obesity. Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis. 2001 Dec;11(6):401-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12055705</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Petersen KF, Dufour S, Morino K, Yoo PS, Cline GW, Shulman GI. Reversal of muscle insulin resistance by weight reduction in young, lean, insulin-resistant offspring of parents with type 2 diabetes. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2012 May 22;109(21):8236-40. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1205675109. Epub 2012 Apr 30.</citation>
    <PMID>22547801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pi-Sunyer FX. Short-term medical benefits and adverse effects of weight loss. Ann Intern Med. 1993 Oct 1;119(7 Pt 2):722-6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>8363205</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rattarasarn C, Leelawattana R, Soonthornpun S, Setasuban W, Thamprasit A, Lim A, Chayanunnukul W, Thamkumpee N. Relationships of body fat distribution, insulin sensitivity and cardiovascular risk factors in lean, healthy non-diabetic Thai men and women. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2003 May;60(2):87-94.</citation>
    <PMID>12706316</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tai ES, Lim SC, Chew SK, Tan BY, Tan CE. Homeostasis model assessment in a population with mixed ethnicity: the 1992 Singapore National Health Survey. Diabetes Res Clin Pract. 2000 Aug;49(2-3):159-68.</citation>
    <PMID>10963828</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yaghootkar H, Scott RA, White CC, Zhang W, Speliotes E, Munroe PB, Ehret GB, Bis JC, Fox CS, Walker M, Borecki IB, Knowles JW, Yerges-Armstrong L, Ohlsson C, Perry JR, Chambers JC, Kooner JS, Franceschini N, Langenberg C, Hivert MF, Dastani Z, Richards JB, Semple RK, Frayling TM. Genetic evidence for a normal-weight &quot;metabolically obese&quot; phenotype linking insulin resistance, hypertension, coronary artery disease, and type 2 diabetes. Diabetes. 2014 Dec;63(12):4369-77. doi: 10.2337/db14-0318. Epub 2014 Jul 21.</citation>
    <PMID>25048195</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 3, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 3, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 4, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 13, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Clinical Nutrition Research Centre, Singapore</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Faidon Magkos</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Obesity</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin Resistance</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucose Metabolism Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Obesity, Abdominal</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

