<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03233516</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2017/958-31</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03233516</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Trial of Respiratory Infections in Children for Enhanced Diagnostics</brief_title>
  <acronym>TREND</acronym>
  <official_title>Trial of Respiratory Infections in Children for Enhanced Diagnostics</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Karolinska Institutet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Stockholm South General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Science for Life Laboratory</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Uppsala University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Astrid Lindgren Children´s Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sahlgrenska University Hospital, Sweden</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Turku University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Karolinska Institutet</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall aim of the TREND study is to improve the differential diagnosis of bacterial and
      viral etiology in children below 5 years of age with clinical community acquired pneumonia.

      Specific objectives:

        -  To assess the diagnostic accuracy of MxA for viral CAP (sub-study I)

        -  To study etiologies in children with CAP (sub-study II)

        -  To evaluate sensitivity and specificity for MariPOC® Respi test versus PCR for detection
           of respiratory viruses (sub-study III)

        -  To assess sensitivity and specificity for a novel RPA-based point-of-care test versus
           PCR for detection of respiratory viruses (sub-study IV)

        -  To assess long-term complications in children with CAP (sub-study V

      The study takes place at Sachs' Children and Youth hospital in Stockholm.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Respiratory viral and bacterial infections are hard to distinguish clinically,
      and many children with viral infections receive unnecessary treatment with antibiotics, which
      contributes to development and spread of antibiotic resistance. Therefore, there is a need
      for new point-of-care diagnostic tests that better distinguish viral from
      antibiotic-requiring bacterial infections, particularly in children presenting with suspected
      clinical community-acquired pneumonia (CAP), and thus assist health-care workers decision
      making and improve rational use of antibiotics.

      Myxovirus resistance protein A (MxA) is a promising biomarker for viral infection, but no
      studies have investigated MxA in children with CAP. Procalcitonin (PCT) is used as a
      biomarker for severe bacterial infection as the protein rapidly increases in plasma levels in
      response to stress and systemic infection. PCT has been reported to be more specific for
      bacterial infection as compared to CRP, but there are conflicting data on the clinical
      utility of PCT in children with CAP.

      The role of viruses and atypical bacteria in childhood CAP Is increasingly recognized. Recent
      studies have reported an increasing incidence of B. pertussis and there have been several
      deaths in previously healthy infants associated with whooping cough in Sweden over the last
      ten years. Consequently, there is a need for new etiologic studies in childhood CAP.

      Real-time PCR is currently considered gold-standard for detection of respiratory viruses in
      children with respiratory tract infection. Nevertheless, the turn-around time is usually long
      and the test results can rarely be used for decision making regarding treatment. There are
      currently several new antigen-based point-of-care tests of respiratory infections on the
      market, one is Multianalyte Point-of-care Antigen Detection Test System (MariPOC®) Respi. The
      sensitivity for respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) and influenza virus is as high as 90% as
      compared to PCR, the current gold-standard PCR, but, the sensitivity for less common
      respiratory viruses such as metapneumovirus (hMPV), parainfluenza virus (PIV), coronavirus
      and bocavirus have been insufficiently investigated.

      Recombinase polymerase amplification (RPA) is a nucleic acid amplification method that
      doesn't require thermal cycling. As the test reaction can be carried out at room temperature
      it is a particularly interesting method for resource-limited settings where the need for new
      diagnostic tests is high.

      Studies on long-term outcomes of radiologically confirmed bacterial CAP have indicated that
      the disease is associated with later development of asthma and decreased lung-function. Given
      the ongoing change in etiology of pediatric CAP, there is a need for new studies of long-term
      complications in pediatric CAP.

      Overall Aim:

      The overall aim of the TREND study is to improve the differential diagnosis of bacterial and
      viral etiology in children below 5 years of age with clinical CAP.

      Specific objectives:

        -  To assess the diagnostic accuracy of MxA for viral CAP (sub-study I)

        -  To study etiologies in children with CAP (sub-study II)

        -  To evaluate sensitivity and specificity for MariPOC® Respi test versus PCR for detection
           of respiratory viruses (sub-study III)

        -  To assess sensitivity and specificity for a novel RPA-based point-of-care test versus
           PCR for detection of respiratory viruses (sub-study IV)

        -  To assess long-term complications in children with CAP (sub-study V)

      Study Design:

      The TREND study is a hospital-based prospective observational study of children with clinical
      CAP with asymptomatic controls at the emergency department at Sachs' Children and Youth
      hospital, Stockholm.

      Case definition Children 1-59 months with clinical CAP according to WHO-criteria.

      Bronchodilator challenge:

      Inhalation with a rapid acting bronchodilator will be administered to children with wheezing
      and in-drawings to improve the specificity of the WHO clinical CAP criteria as suggested by
      the PERCH study team. Resolved in-drawings after bronchodilator challenge will be recorded
      but not considered an exclusion criteria to be able to exclude these patients in a
      sub-analysis.

      Control definition:

      Children 1-59 months at Sachs' Children and Youth Hospital treated for a minor orthopedic or
      minor surgical disease. The parents to the controls will be contacted via email/telephone 1-2
      weeks after enrollment and be asked whether the child has developed respiratory symptoms or
      not. No matching will be performed but adjustments for age and season will be performed in
      the analyses.

      Sampling:

      A capillary blood sample and nasopharyngeal swabs/aspirates will be collected from all study
      subjects.

      Microbiological and Biochemistry Analyses:

      MariPOC® Respi as well as real-time PCR analysis (detecting: 16 respiratory viruses as well
      as Streptococcus pneumoniae, Bordetella pertussis, B. parapertussis and Mycoplasma
      pneumoniae) will be performed.

      Biochemistry Analyses:

      Serum MxA, procalcitonin and CRP levels will be analysed.

      Study Variables:

      Information regarding the study subject, number of siblings, days of illness, current
      symptoms, vaccinations, antibiotic treatment, medication, underlying diseases, heredity for
      asthma, previous hospitalization, recent stay abroad, allergies, smoking, recent travel
      abroad, recent contact with unwell individual, breastfeeding, preschool, origin of parents
      and socio-economic status will be collected through a standardized questionnaire based on
      previous studies.

      Clinical parameters will be registered by the study doctor responsible for patient
      screening/enrolment in line with the study protocol of PERCH. Some of the clinical parameters
      included in the PERCH protocol are very rare in a Swedish context and to avoid overloading of
      the case report form, these will not be systematically registered at inclusion. However,
      information about these symptoms will be retrospectively collected from the medical records.
      Some clinical parameters are routinely recorded multiple times at the emergency unit. In
      these cases, the most extreme value (highest pulse/respiratory rate/body temperature/etc and
      lowest peripheral oxygen saturation) during the visit at the emergency unit until enrolment
      will be recorded. Information regarding admission, length of stay, radiological, routine
      clinical examination, microbiological and chemistry analyses, treatment, discharge diagnosis
      and complications will be retrospectively collected from the medical records.

      All study subjects will be linked to the National Vaccination register to collect information
      regarding previous immunizations. To allow assessment of long-term complication, study
      subjects will also be linked to the National Patient Register, the National Death Register
      and the National Prescribed Drug Register for collection of discharge diagnoses according to
      ICD-10 as well as prescribed drugs.

      Classification of Disease:

      Etiology will be classified as probable or definitive based on clinical significance of the
      different microbiological test in the studies above. In TREND, the combination of probable
      and definitive etiology will be used in the main analysis, whereas children with definitive
      etiology will be assessed separately in a sub-analysis.

      Definitive Viral Infection:

      • PCR positive for influenza, RS virus, metapneumovirus or parainfluenza virus

      Probable Viral Infection:

        -  PCR positive for adenovirus

        -  PCR positive for coronavirus, rhinovirus, bocavirus or enterovirus AND CRP &lt;20 AND
           reported fever &gt;24h.

      Definitive Bacterial Infection:

        -  positive bacterial blood culture in blood or pleura fluid

        -  positive pneumococcal antigen test in pleura fluid

      Probable Bacterial Infection:

        -  CRP &gt;80 (children ≤2 years) / &gt;120 (children 2-5 years) AND/OR

        -  Radiographic evidence of empyema on X-ray or ultrasound AND/OR

        -  Large dense infiltrate or lobar consolidation on chest x-ray

      Definitive Atypical Bacterial Infection:

      • Positive PCR B. pertussis or B. parapertussis

      Probable Atypical Bacterial Infection:

      • Positive PCR M. pneumoniae

      Undetermined:

      • Cases not fulfilling any criteria above

      Mixed Viral-bacterial Infection:

      • Children fulfilling criteria for both viral and bacterial infection

      Classification of Long-term Complications:

      Long-term complications (asthma and number of hospital-requiring respiratory infections) will
      be assessed after 3, 7 and 10 years following study completion by linking to the National
      Patient Register. Asthma will be classified as ICD-10 diagnosis of J45 or ≥3 prescriptions of
      inhalation steroids, beta-2-agonists or leukotriene antagonists according to the Prescribed
      Drug Register.

      Power Calculation:

      For the sample size calculation, the investigators focused on the assessment of MxA-levels in
      cases with viral CAP as compared to cases with bacterial CAP/controls (study I). Two power
      calculations were made, one for viral CAP versus bacterial CAP and one for viral CAP versus
      controls. The following assumptions were made:

      A difference in MxA-level of 500µg/l between the groups was considered clinically relevant. A
      standard deviation of 1000 and 300 was assumed in cases with viral CAP and bacterial
      CAP/controls respectively based on previous studies on MxA.

      Using an alpha-level of 0.05 (two-sided) at an 80% power, with an additional 20% addition to
      account for non-parametric testing and multivariate analyses, 42 children in each group
      (viral CAP, bacterial CAP and controls) would be needed.

      To ensure that enough of the included cases would fulfill the TREND definition of viral and
      bacterial CAP, the proportion of viral respectively bacterial CAP (TREND definition) was
      calculated in our previous study that assessed Swedish children with x-ray verified CAP. By
      doing this, the prevalence of viral and bacterial CAP was estimated to 45% and 14%
      respectively. Hence 300 cases and 42 controls would be needed to ensure sufficient collection
      of cases with viral and bacterial CAP respectively. The investigators also would like to
      compare cases with viral CAP with controls testing positive for one or more virus by PCR. In
      our previous study, 35.4% of asymptomatic children tested positive for one or more virus. To
      include a sufficient number of virus-positive controls, the investigators hence aim at
      including 300 cases and 119 controls (42/0.354=119) in the TREND-study.

      Ethical Considerations:

      The study will be conducted in accordance with the latest version of The Declaration of
      Helsinki and the fundamental principles of respect for the individual (Article 8), their
      right to self-determination and the right to make informed decisions (Articles 20, 21 and 22)
      regarding participation in research, both initially and during the course of the research.

      Significance:

      The findings from the TREND project can be an important step to improve the care of children
      with clinical CAP. Improved near-patient differential diagnosis is a prerequisite for
      rational antibiotic use and decreasing unnecessary antibiotic treatment. Further better
      diagnosis of the pathogens causing acute respiratory infections makes it easier to give
      advice to parents on how their children should be cared for and better surveillance in the
      society.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 20, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>10 Years</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>MxA - cases with viral and bacterial clinical CAP</measure>
    <time_frame>2021</time_frame>
    <description>Clinically relevant difference in MxA-levels between cases with viral and bacterial clinical CAP</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mxa viral clinical CAP and controls</measure>
    <time_frame>2021</time_frame>
    <description>Clinically relevant difference in MxA-levels between cases with viral clinical CAP and controls</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>PCR - respiratory pathogens in cases and controls</measure>
    <time_frame>2020</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of respiratory pathogens in cases and controls, using real time PCR</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity and specificity - MariPOC</measure>
    <time_frame>2021</time_frame>
    <description>Sensitivity and specificity for different respiratory viruses with MariPOC® Respi as compared to real-time PCR</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity and specificity a novel PCR-based point-of-care test</measure>
    <time_frame>2021</time_frame>
    <description>Sensitivity and specificity for different respiratory viruses with a novel PCR-based point-of-care test as compared to PCR</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference asthma prevalence and number of hospital-requiring respiratory infections - cases and controls,</measure>
    <time_frame>2027</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in asthma prevalence between cases and controls and difference in number of hospital-requiring respiratory infections between cases and controls after 3, 7 and 10 years</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific assessment of MxA as a clinical biomarker</measure>
    <time_frame>2021</time_frame>
    <description>Clinically relevant difference in MxA-levels comparing cases with viral clinical CAP with cases with atypical and mixed viral-bacterial clinical CAP as well as with controls with and without presence of respiratory viruses by PCR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific assessment of MxA as a clinical biomarker</measure>
    <time_frame>2021</time_frame>
    <description>Clinically relevant differences in MxA-levels in cases with regard to specific respiratory agents</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific assessment of MxA as a clinical biomarker</measure>
    <time_frame>2021</time_frame>
    <description>Sensitivity and specificity for MxA in identifying viral clinical CAP</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specific assessment of MxA as a clinical biomarker</measure>
    <time_frame>2021</time_frame>
    <description>Sensitivity and specificity for identifying viral and bacterial infection respectively for CRP, PCT and combination test of CRP, PCT and MxA</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of PCT and CRP as clinical biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>2021</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in CRP and PCT between children with viral, bacterial, atypical bacterial and mixed viral-bacterial infection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Descriptive statistics of study cohort with regard to etiologic agent</measure>
    <time_frame>2020</time_frame>
    <description>Differences in symptom, antibiotic treatment, acute complications, radiologic exams admission rate and length of stay between cases with viral, bacterial, atypical bacterial and mixed viral-bacterial infection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of MariPOC® Respi in a clinical setting</measure>
    <time_frame>2022</time_frame>
    <description>Differences in symptom, antibiotic treatment, acute complications, radiologic exams admission rate and length of stay between cases who tested positive for respiratory virus by MariPOC® Respi as compared to those with a negative test</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of long-term outcomes of children with CAP</measure>
    <time_frame>2027</time_frame>
    <description>Number of hospital-requiring respiratory infections in cases and controls</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of long-term outcomes of children with CAP</measure>
    <time_frame>2027</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in asthma prevalence between cases with viral and bacterial clinical CAP as compared to an estimate of the prevalence in the general population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Assessment of long-term outcomes of children with CAP</measure>
    <time_frame>2027</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in proportion of hospital-requiring respiratory infections between cases with viral, bacterial, atypical and mixed viral-bacterial infection</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of MariPOC® Respi</measure>
    <time_frame>2022</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in MxA-levels between PCR+/MariPOC® Respi+ and PCR+/MariPOC® Respi- study subjects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Etiology of cases in TREND study</measure>
    <time_frame>2020</time_frame>
    <description>Estimation of etiology of cases using two levels of certainty (definitive as well as probable definition).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">419</enrollment>
  <condition>Community-acquired Pneumonia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cases with clinical CAP</arm_group_label>
    <description>Children 1-59 months at Sachs' Children and Youth Hospital with clinical CAP (both severe and non-severe) according to WHO-criteria.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control subjects</arm_group_label>
    <description>Children 1-59 months at Sachs' Children and Youth Hospital treated for a minor orthopedic (elective (e.g. hand surgery) or acute) or minor surgical disease, e.g. minor trauma (excluding e.g. appendicitis, major burns, major trauma).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      -  capillary lithium-heparin tube (will be separated into two aliquots and diluted in a
           commercial buffer)

        -  capillary point-of-care test CRP

        -  nasopharyngeal swab for Mari-POC (diluted in 1.3ml MariPOC RTI buffer)

        -  nasopharyngeal aspirate (diluted into 1.3ml saline) divided into three aliquots:

             1. Real-time PCR-analysis of respiratory agents (400μl)

             2. Frozen down at -80°C for study IV (400μl)

             3. Available for routine microbiological testing as ordered by the attending
                physician. If not used, frozen down at -80°C for potential reanalyses. (500μl)

      All samples will be taken within 24h from arrival at the emergency unit and time for both
      blood and nasopharynx samples will be registered. It will also be noted if antibiotics have
      been given before samples taken.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Case definition:

        Children 1-59 months at Sachs' Children and Youth Hospital with clinical CAP (both severe
        and non-severe) according to WHO-criteria

        Control definition:

        Children 1-59 months at Sachs' Children and Youth Hospital treated for a minor orthopedic
        (elective (e.g. hand surgery) or acute) or minor surgical disease, e.g. minor trauma
        (excluding e.g. appendicitis, major burns, major trauma). No matching will be performed but
        adjustments for age and season will be performed in the analyses.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Cases:

        (all inclusion criteria to be met to be eligible for participation in the study).

          -  Age 28 days to 59 months

          -  Reported and/or observed breathing troubles OR cough

          -  Observed age-adjusted tachypnea (≥50 breaths/min in children 1-12 months, ≥40/min in
             children &gt;1year) OR chest in-drawings

          -  Written informed consent

        Controls:

        (all inclusion criteria to be met to be eligible for participation in the study).

          -  Age 28 days to 59 months

          -  Minor surgical or orthopedic disease (elective (e.g. hand surgery) or acute) or minor
             surgical disease, e.g. minor trauma (excluding e.g. appendicitis, major burns, major
             trauma)

          -  Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Cases:

          -  Previously included as case in the study

          -  Hospitalized during last 14 days

        Controls:

        Symptoms of respiratory disease 7 days before enrollment

          -  Previously included as control in the study

          -  Hospitalized during last 14 days
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>59 Months</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sachs' Children and Youth Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tobias Alfvén, Ass. Prof.</last_name>
      <phone>+46 8 6164118</phone>
      <email>tobias.alfven@ki.se</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Samuel Rhedin, MD-PhD</last_name>
      <phone>+46 70 518 66 51</phone>
      <email>samuel.rhedin@ki.se</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adams PF, Hendershot GE, Marano MA; Centers for Disease Control and Prevention/National Center for Health Statistics. Current estimates from the National Health Interview Survey, 1996. Vital Health Stat 10. 1999 Oct;(200):1-203.</citation>
    <PMID>15782448</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mäkelä MJ, Puhakka T, Ruuskanen O, Leinonen M, Saikku P, Kimpimäki M, Blomqvist S, Hyypiä T, Arstila P. Viruses and bacteria in the etiology of the common cold. J Clin Microbiol. 1998 Feb;36(2):539-42.</citation>
    <PMID>9466772</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Elfving K, Shakely D, Andersson M, Baltzell K, Ali AS, Bachelard M, Falk KI, Ljung A, Msellem MI, Omar RS, Parola P, Xu W, Petzold M, Trollfors B, Björkman A, Lindh M, Mårtensson A. Acute Uncomplicated Febrile Illness in Children Aged 2-59 months in Zanzibar - Aetiologies, Antibiotic Treatment and Outcome. PLoS One. 2016 Jan 28;11(1):e0146054. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0146054. eCollection 2016.</citation>
    <PMID>26821179</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Malhotra-Kumar S, Lammens C, Coenen S, Van Herck K, Goossens H. Effect of azithromycin and clarithromycin therapy on pharyngeal carriage of macrolide-resistant streptococci in healthy volunteers: a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. Lancet. 2007 Feb 10;369(9560):482-90.</citation>
    <PMID>17292768</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rhedin S. Establishment of childhood pneumonia cause in the era of pneumococcal conjugate vaccines. Lancet Respir Med. 2016 Jun;4(6):423-4. doi: 10.1016/S2213-2600(16)30067-4. Epub 2016 Apr 21.</citation>
    <PMID>27117546</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Reinhart K, Karzai W, Meisner M. Procalcitonin as a marker of the systemic inflammatory response to infection. Intensive Care Med. 2000 Sep;26(9):1193-200. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11089742</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Korppi M, Remes S, Heiskanen-Kosma T. Serum procalcitonin concentrations in bacterial pneumonia in children: a negative result in primary healthcare settings. Pediatr Pulmonol. 2003 Jan;35(1):56-61.</citation>
    <PMID>12461740</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Esposito S, Tagliabue C, Picciolli I, Semino M, Sabatini C, Consolo S, Bosis S, Pinzani R, Principi N. Procalcitonin measurements for guiding antibiotic treatment in pediatric pneumonia. Respir Med. 2011 Dec;105(12):1939-45. doi: 10.1016/j.rmed.2011.09.003. Epub 2011 Sep 29.</citation>
    <PMID>21959024</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Engelmann I, Dubos F, Lobert PE, Houssin C, Degas V, Sardet A, Decoster A, Dewilde A, Martinot A, Hober D. Diagnosis of viral infections using myxovirus resistance protein A (MxA). Pediatrics. 2015 Apr;135(4):e985-93. doi: 10.1542/peds.2014-1946.</citation>
    <PMID>25802344</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sambursky R, Shapiro N. Evaluation of a combined MxA and CRP point-of-care immunoassay to identify viral and/or bacterial immune response in patients with acute febrile respiratory infection. Eur Clin Respir J. 2015 Dec 10;2:28245. doi: 10.3402/ecrj.v2.28245. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26672961</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Toivonen L, Schuez-Havupalo L, Rulli M, Ilonen J, Pelkonen J, Melen K, Julkunen I, Peltola V, Waris M. Blood MxA protein as a marker for respiratory virus infections in young children. J Clin Virol. 2015 Jan;62:8-13. doi: 10.1016/j.jcv.2014.11.018. Epub 2014 Nov 18.</citation>
    <PMID>25542463</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rhedin S, Lindstrand A, Rotzén-Östlund M, Tolfvenstam T, Ohrmalm L, Rinder MR, Zweygberg-Wirgart B, Ortqvist A, Henriques-Normark B, Broliden K, Naucler P. Clinical utility of PCR for common viruses in acute respiratory illness. Pediatrics. 2014 Mar;133(3):e538-45. doi: 10.1542/peds.2013-3042. Epub 2014 Feb 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24567027</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lindstrand A, Bennet R, Galanis I, Blennow M, Ask LS, Dennison SH, Rinder MR, Eriksson M, Henriques-Normark B, Ortqvist A, Alfvén T. Sinusitis and pneumonia hospitalization after introduction of pneumococcal conjugate vaccine. Pediatrics. 2014 Dec;134(6):e1528-36. doi: 10.1542/peds.2013-4177. Epub 2014 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>25384486</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rhedin S, Lindstrand A, Hjelmgren A, Ryd-Rinder M, Öhrmalm L, Tolfvenstam T, Örtqvist Å, Rotzén-Östlund M, Zweygberg-Wirgart B, Henriques-Normark B, Broliden K, Naucler P. Respiratory viruses associated with community-acquired pneumonia in children: matched case-control study. Thorax. 2015 Sep;70(9):847-53. doi: 10.1136/thoraxjnl-2015-206933. Epub 2015 Jun 15.</citation>
    <PMID>26077969</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Barger-Kamate B, Deloria Knoll M, Kagucia EW, Prosperi C, Baggett HC, Brooks WA, Feikin DR, Hammitt LL, Howie SR, Levine OS, Madhi SA, Scott JA, Thea DM, Amornintapichet T, Anderson TP, Awori JO, Baillie VL, Chipeta J, DeLuca AN, Driscoll AJ, Goswami D, Higdon MM, Hossain L, Karron RA, Maloney S, Moore DP, Morpeth SC, Mwananyanda L, Ofordile O, Olutunde E, Park DE, Sow SO, Tapia MD, Murdoch DR, O'Brien KL, Kotloff KL; Pneumonia Etiology Research for Child Health (PERCH) Study Group. Pertussis-Associated Pneumonia in Infants and Children From Low- and Middle-Income Countries Participating in the PERCH Study. Clin Infect Dis. 2016 Dec 1;63(suppl 4):S187-S196.</citation>
    <PMID>27838672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>He Q, Viljanen MK, Arvilommi H, Aittanen B, Mertsola J. Whooping cough caused by Bordetella pertussis and Bordetella parapertussis in an immunized population. JAMA. 1998 Aug 19;280(7):635-7.</citation>
    <PMID>9718056</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carlsson RM, von Segebaden K, Bergstrom J, Kling AM, Nilsson L. Surveillance of infant pertussis in Sweden 1998-2012; severity of disease in relation to the national vaccination programme. Euro Surveill. 2015 Feb 12;20(6). pii: 21032.</citation>
    <PMID>25695476</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van den Brink G, Wishaupt JO, Douma JC, Hartwig NG, Versteegh FG. Bordetella pertussis: an underreported pathogen in pediatric respiratory infections, a prospective cohort study. BMC Infect Dis. 2014 Sep 30;14:526. doi: 10.1186/1471-2334-14-526.</citation>
    <PMID>25267437</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jartti T, Söderlund-Venermo M, Hedman K, Ruuskanen O, Mäkelä MJ. New molecular virus detection methods and their clinical value in lower respiratory tract infections in children. Paediatr Respir Rev. 2013 Mar;14(1):38-45. doi: 10.1016/j.prrv.2012.04.002. Epub 2012 May 5. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23347659</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Koskinen JO, Vainionpää R, Meltola NJ, Soukka J, Hänninen PE, Soini AE. Rapid method for detection of influenza a and B virus antigens by use of a two-photon excitation assay technique and dry-chemistry reagents. J Clin Microbiol. 2007 Nov;45(11):3581-8. Epub 2007 Sep 12.</citation>
    <PMID>17855571</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tuuminen T, Suomala P, Koskinen JO. Evaluation of the automated multianalyte point-of-care mariPOC® test for the detection of influenza A virus and respiratory syncytial virus. J Med Virol. 2013 Sep;85(9):1598-601. doi: 10.1002/jmv.23660.</citation>
    <PMID>23852685</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sanbonmatsu-Gámez S, Pérez-Ruiz M, Lara-Oya A, Pedrosa-Corral I, Riazzo-Damas C, Navarro-Marí JM. Analytical performance of the automated multianalyte point-of-care mariPOC® for the detection of respiratory viruses. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis. 2015 Nov;83(3):252-6. doi: 10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2015.07.010. Epub 2015 Jul 18.</citation>
    <PMID>26283523</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leblanc N, Gantelius J, Schwenk JM, Ståhl K, Blomberg J, Andersson-Svahn H, Belák S. Development of a magnetic bead microarray for simultaneous and simple detection of four pestiviruses. J Virol Methods. 2009 Jan;155(1):1-9. doi: 10.1016/j.jviromet.2008.04.010. Epub 2008 Jun 2.</citation>
    <PMID>18514335</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chinnasamy T, Segerink LI, Nystrand M, Gantelius J, Svahn HA. A lateral flow paper microarray for rapid allergy point of care diagnostics. Analyst. 2014 May 21;139(10):2348-54. doi: 10.1039/c3an01806g.</citation>
    <PMID>24690935</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Caliendo AM, Gilbert DN, Ginocchio CC, Hanson KE, May L, Quinn TC, Tenover FC, Alland D, Blaschke AJ, Bonomo RA, Carroll KC, Ferraro MJ, Hirschhorn LR, Joseph WP, Karchmer T, MacIntyre AT, Reller LB, Jackson AF; Infectious Diseases Society of America (IDSA). Better tests, better care: improved diagnostics for infectious diseases. Clin Infect Dis. 2013 Dec;57 Suppl 3:S139-70. doi: 10.1093/cid/cit578. Review. Erratum in: Clin Infect Dis. 2014 May;58(9):1346.</citation>
    <PMID>24200831</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Burgess JA, Abramson MJ, Gurrin LC, Byrnes GB, Matheson MC, May CL, Giles GG, Johns DP, Hopper JL, Walters EH, Dharmage SC. Childhood infections and the risk of asthma: a longitudinal study over 37 years. Chest. 2012 Sep;142(3):647-654. doi: 10.1378/chest.11-1432.</citation>
    <PMID>22459783</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chan JY, Stern DA, Guerra S, Wright AL, Morgan WJ, Martinez FD. Pneumonia in childhood and impaired lung function in adults: a longitudinal study. Pediatrics. 2015 Apr;135(4):607-16. doi: 10.1542/peds.2014-3060. Epub 2015 Mar 2.</citation>
    <PMID>25733757</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scott JA, Wonodi C, Moïsi JC, Deloria-Knoll M, DeLuca AN, Karron RA, Bhat N, Murdoch DR, Crawley J, Levine OS, O'Brien KL, Feikin DR; Pneumonia Methods Working Group. The definition of pneumonia, the assessment of severity, and clinical standardization in the Pneumonia Etiology Research for Child Health study. Clin Infect Dis. 2012 Apr;54 Suppl 2:S109-16. doi: 10.1093/cid/cir1065. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22403224</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Brittain-Long R, Westin J, Olofsson S, Lindh M, Andersson LM. Access to a polymerase chain reaction assay method targeting 13 respiratory viruses can reduce antibiotics: a randomised, controlled trial. BMC Med. 2011 Apr 26;9:44. doi: 10.1186/1741-7015-9-44.</citation>
    <PMID>21521505</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Almqvist C, Adami HO, Franks PW, Groop L, Ingelsson E, Kere J, Lissner L, Litton JE, Maeurer M, Michaëlsson K, Palmgren J, Pershagen G, Ploner A, Sullivan PF, Tybring G, Pedersen NL. LifeGene--a large prospective population-based study of global relevance. Eur J Epidemiol. 2011 Jan;26(1):67-77. doi: 10.1007/s10654-010-9521-x. Epub 2010 Nov 21.</citation>
    <PMID>21104112</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Virkki R, Juven T, Rikalainen H, Svedström E, Mertsola J, Ruuskanen O. Differentiation of bacterial and viral pneumonia in children. Thorax. 2002 May;57(5):438-41.</citation>
    <PMID>11978922</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jain S, Williams DJ, Arnold SR, Ampofo K, Bramley AM, Reed C, Stockmann C, Anderson EJ, Grijalva CG, Self WH, Zhu Y, Patel A, Hymas W, Chappell JD, Kaufman RA, Kan JH, Dansie D, Lenny N, Hillyard DR, Haynes LM, Levine M, Lindstrom S, Winchell JM, Katz JM, Erdman D, Schneider E, Hicks LA, Wunderink RG, Edwards KM, Pavia AT, McCullers JA, Finelli L; CDC EPIC Study Team. Community-acquired pneumonia requiring hospitalization among U.S. children. N Engl J Med. 2015 Feb 26;372(9):835-45. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1405870.</citation>
    <PMID>25714161</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zar HJ, Barnett W, Stadler A, Gardner-Lubbe S, Myer L, Nicol MP. Aetiology of childhood pneumonia in a well vaccinated South African birth cohort: a nested case-control study of the Drakenstein Child Health Study. Lancet Respir Med. 2016 Jun;4(6):463-72. doi: 10.1016/S2213-2600(16)00096-5. Epub 2016 Apr 21. Erratum in: Lancet Respir Med. 2016 Oct;4(10 ):e50.</citation>
    <PMID>27117547</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Berkley JA, Munywoki P, Ngama M, Kazungu S, Abwao J, Bett A, Lassauniére R, Kresfelder T, Cane PA, Venter M, Scott JA, Nokes DJ. Viral etiology of severe pneumonia among Kenyan infants and children. JAMA. 2010 May 26;303(20):2051-7. doi: 10.1001/jama.2010.675. Erratum in: JAMA. 2010 Jun 23;303(24):2477.</citation>
    <PMID>20501927</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spichak TV, Yatsyshina SB, Кatosova LК, Кim SS, Korppi MO. Is the role of rhinoviruses as causative agents of pediatric community-acquired pneumonia over-estimated? Eur J Pediatr. 2016 Dec;175(12):1951-1958. Epub 2016 Oct 6.</citation>
    <PMID>27714467</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Gageldonk-Lafeber AB, Heijnen ML, Bartelds AI, Peters MF, van der Plas SM, Wilbrink B. A case-control study of acute respiratory tract infection in general practice patients in The Netherlands. Clin Infect Dis. 2005 Aug 15;41(4):490-7. Epub 2005 Jul 15.</citation>
    <PMID>16028157</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Loeffelholz MJ, Trujillo R, Pyles RB, Miller AL, Alvarez-Fernandez P, Pong DL, Chonmaitree T. Duration of rhinovirus shedding in the upper respiratory tract in the first year of life. Pediatrics. 2014 Dec;134(6):1144-50. doi: 10.1542/peds.2014-2132. Epub 2014 Nov 17.</citation>
    <PMID>25404719</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chonmaitree T, Alvarez-Fernandez P, Jennings K, Trujillo R, Marom T, Loeffelholz MJ, Miller AL, McCormick DP, Patel JA, Pyles RB. Symptomatic and asymptomatic respiratory viral infections in the first year of life: association with acute otitis media development. Clin Infect Dis. 2015 Jan 1;60(1):1-9. doi: 10.1093/cid/ciu714. Epub 2014 Sep 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25205769</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Spuesens EB, Fraaij PL, Visser EG, Hoogenboezem T, Hop WC, van Adrichem LN, Weber F, Moll HA, Broekman B, Berger MY, van Rijsoort-Vos T, van Belkum A, Schutten M, Pas SD, Osterhaus AD, Hartwig NG, Vink C, van Rossum AM. Carriage of Mycoplasma pneumoniae in the upper respiratory tract of symptomatic and asymptomatic children: an observational study. PLoS Med. 2013;10(5):e1001444. doi: 10.1371/journal.pmed.1001444. Epub 2013 May 14.</citation>
    <PMID>23690754</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chen SP, Huang YC, Chiu CH, Wong KS, Huang YL, Huang CG, Tsao KC, Lin TY. Clinical features of radiologically confirmed pneumonia due to adenovirus in children. J Clin Virol. 2013 Jan;56(1):7-12. doi: 10.1016/j.jcv.2012.08.021. Epub 2012 Sep 26.</citation>
    <PMID>23021965</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Örtqvist AK, Lundholm C, Wettermark B, Ludvigsson JF, Ye W, Almqvist C. Validation of asthma and eczema in population-based Swedish drug and patient registers. Pharmacoepidemiol Drug Saf. 2013 Aug;22(8):850-60. doi: 10.1002/pds.3465. Epub 2013 Jun 11.</citation>
    <PMID>23754713</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 26, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 26, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 28, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 7, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 7, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 8, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Karolinska Institutet</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tobias Alfvén</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Community-acquired pneumonia</keyword>
  <keyword>Pediatrics</keyword>
  <keyword>Etiology</keyword>
  <keyword>Point-of-care test</keyword>
  <keyword>MxA</keyword>
  <keyword>CRP</keyword>
  <keyword>Procalcitonin</keyword>
  <keyword>Infectious diseases</keyword>
  <keyword>Respiratory viruses</keyword>
  <keyword>Pediatric asthma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Respiratory Tract Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

