<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03231228</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HC-G-H-1601</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03231228</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety of 1 g and 2 g of Cefazolin in Pediatric Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase 4, Open-Label, Single-Dose, Parallel-Group Study to Evaluate the Safety of 1 g of Cefazolin in Pediatric Subjects Weighing 25 to Less Than 60 kg and 2 g of Cefazolin in Pediatric Subjects Weighing at Least 60 kg Scheduled for Surgery</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>B. Braun Medical Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>B. Braun Medical Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a Phase 4, open-label, single-dose, parallel-group, multicenter, safety study of
      cefazolin (1 g or 2 g) in pediatric subjects between 10 and 17 years of age (inclusive)
      scheduled for surgery.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Approximately 110 subjects will be enrolled and assigned to 1 of the 2 dose groups in a 1:1
      ratio (55 subjects in each group). Subjects with a weight of at least 25 kg but less than 60
      kg will receive a single IV dose of 1 g cefazolin. Subjects with a weight of at least 60 kg
      will receive a single IV dose of 2 g cefazolin. Dose groups will not be balanced by age or
      gender. Additional subjects may be enrolled if necessary to ensure at least 50 evaluable
      subjects with complete safety data per dose group complete the study.

      In a subset of approximately 40 subjects, 4 PK samples will be obtained to determine the
      cefazolin plasma concentrations in this population.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">November 20, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Approximately 110 subjects will be enrolled and assigned to 1 of the 2 dose groups in a 1:1 ratio (55 subjects in each group). Subjects with a weight of at least 25 kg but less than 60 kg will receive a single IV dose of 1 g cefazolin. Subjects with a weight of at least 60 kg will receive a single IV dose of 2 g cefazolin. Dose groups will not be balanced by age or gender.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
    <masking_description>n/a, this is an open label study</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events [Safety]</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>Safety will be assessed by monitoring adverse events (AEs), physical examinations, vital signs, ECGs, and clinical laboratory results.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cefazolin plasma concentration following infusion</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 4 hours after start of study drug infusion</time_frame>
    <description>Concentrations will be determined through analysis of 4 blood samples drawn at up to 4 hours after the start of study drug infusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">110</enrollment>
  <condition>Postoperative Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cefazolin 1 g Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pediatric surgical subjects weighing at least 25 kg to less than 60 kg will receive a single 30-minute infusion of 1 g cefazolin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cefazolin 2 g Infusion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Pediatric surgical subjects weighing at least 60 kg will receive a single 30-minute infusion of 2 g cefazolin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cefazolin 1 g Infusion</intervention_name>
    <description>1 g cefazolin infusion for pediatric surgical subjects weighing ≥25 to &lt;60 kg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cefazolin 1 g Infusion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Cefazolin 2 g Infusion</intervention_name>
    <description>2 g cefazolin infusion for pediatric surgical subjects weighing at least 60 kg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cefazolin 2 g Infusion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. The subject is between the ages of 10 and 17 years (inclusive) at the time of giving
             informed consent.

          2. The subject is scheduled for surgery that will last less than 3 hours.

          3. The subject and the subject's legally authorized representative voluntarily agree that
             the subject will participate in this study. In accordance with applicable laws,
             regulations, and institutional review board requirements, the subject signs or orally
             agrees to an age-appropriate assent and the subject's legally authorized
             representative signs both an institutional review board approved informed consent form
             and Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act authorization prior to the
             performance of any screening procedures.

          4. For subjects who agree to participate in the PK subgroup additional consent will be
             obtained.

          5. The subject weighs (on Day 1) ≥25 kg but &lt;60 kg for inclusion in 1 g dose group.

          6. The subject weighs (on Day 1) ≥60 kg for inclusion in 2 g dose group.

          7. The subject has been scheduled for any type of surgery requiring single dose
             perioperative cefazolin prophylaxis.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Female subjects who are pregnant or lactating/breastfeeding.

          2. Female subjects of childbearing potential who are sexually active and who are not
             willing to use an effective method of birth control during the study period, eg, oral
             contraceptives, double barrier methods, hormonal injectable or implanted
             contraceptives, tubal ligation, or have a partner with a vasectomy.

          3. The subject has impaired renal function based on the revised Schwartz formula.

          4. The subject has a known allergy or hypersensitivity to β lactam/cephalosporin
             antibiotics, penicillins, corn products, or dextrose containing products or solutions,
             or any of the other ingredients of Cefazolin for Injection United States Pharmacopeia
             (USP) and Dextrose Injection USP in DUPLEX.

          5. The subject has abnormal vital signs or an abnormal electrocardiograph (ECG)
             considered by the investigator to be clinically significant.

          6. The subject has a result of any laboratory test (or repeat test, if done), obtained as
             standard of care, that is outside the normal limit of the site's laboratory reference
             range AND is considered by the investigator to be clinically significant.

          7. The subject has a known history of human immunodeficiency virus, hepatitis B, or
             hepatitis C infection.

          8. The subject has a history of alcohol or drug abuse.

          9. The subject has received any other investigational drug/device within 30 days prior to
             the study drug administration.

         10. The subject has a history of or is currently smoking or using nicotine-containing
             substances or electronic cigarettes as determined by medical history or subject's
             verbal report.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>10 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>17 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Diana Valencia, MD</last_name>
    <phone>6105962845</phone>
    <email>diana.valencia@bbraunusa.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Arkansas Children's Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72202</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Michael Schmitz, MD</last_name>
      <phone>501-364-2933</phone>
      <email>schmitzmichaell@uams.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Michael Schmitz, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2004/50461slr139_ancef_lbl.pdf</url>
    <description>Ancef (cefazolin for injection) [package insert]. GlaxoSmithKline. Research Triangle Park (NC); 2004 [cited 2016 Jun 08]</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/label/2015/050779s025lbl.pdf</url>
    <description>Cefazolin and Dextrose for Injection [package insert]. B. Braun Medical Inc. Bethlehem [PA]; revised 10/2015</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 25, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 25, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">July 27, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 10, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 10, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 11, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cefazolin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

