<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03235154</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>15-05</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03235154</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pilot Study of Treating HCV at a Psychiatrist-staffed Outpatient Addiction Clinic</brief_title>
  <official_title>Bridging Care to HCV Treatment Among Opiate Dependent Patients on Buprenorphine/Naloxone Maintenance Therapy: A Pilot Study of Treating HCV With Epclusa at a Psychiatrist-staffed Outpatient Addiction Clinic</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Community Research Initiative of New England</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Gilead Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Community Research Initiative of New England</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The main purpose of this pilot study is to investigate the safety, effectiveness and
      tolerability of the study medication in the treatment of people with chronic hepatitis C
      virus infection who regularly attend a psychiatrist-staffed clinic for opiate addiction
      treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      An estimated 3.2 million people in the United States are currently infected with hepatitis C
      virus (HCV). Since 1990, when the US introduced screening of the blood supply for HCV,
      injection drug use has been the primary mode of HCV transmission in the United States. It is
      widely recognized that addressing the HCV epidemic among people who inject drugs (PWID)
      depends on increasing access to: 1) clean injection equipment; 2) opiate substitution therapy
      (OST); 3) curative HCV treatment; and 4) assistance with comorbid psychiatric conditions and
      social issues (Robaeys, C et al, 2013).

      Nevertheless, access to HCV treatment among current and former injection drug users is
      thought to be limited by several factors including: 1) insufficient number of infectious
      disease and gastroenterology providers and 2) provider and third-party payor concerns about
      adherence to medication and the risk of reinfection (Aspinall, EJ et al, 2013). Strategies to
      increase access among current and former injection drug users to direct acting antiviral
      drugs are urgently needed. The purpose of the current study is to assess the impact of
      co-treating chronic hepatitis C infection and opiate dependence within the context of an
      outpatient addiction clinic staffed by psychiatrists. The beneficial impact of co-treating
      opiate dependence and an infectious illness has been demonstrated in the case of HIV
      infection. Altice and colleagues conducted an observational study of HIV-infected
      opiate-dependent patients who were offered OST with buprenorphine/naloxone at 10 different
      HIV clinics. Subjects initiating buprenorphine/naloxone were more likely to initiate or
      remain on ART (Altice, 2011).

      The Extension for Community Healthcare Outcomes (ECHO) program has demonstrated that with
      proper training and mentorship, primary care providers with no prior experience in managing
      HCV are able to treat the disease effectively (Arora et al, 2011). Since the publication of
      the ECHO study, the treatment of HCV has become considerably less complicated due to the
      widespread availability of safe, highly effective single tablet regimens, such as Epclusa.
      The investigators believe that treatment of HCV is now well within the grasp of physicians
      and other healthcare providers without training in internal or family medicine.

      This single arm pilot study will assess HCV treatment with Epclusa at an outpatient addiction
      clinic staffed by psychiatrists. The investigators hypothesize that with proper training and
      mentorship, psychiatrists who are also a licensed buprenorphine/naloxone providers will be
      able to effectively assess liver health and treat chronic hepatitis C infection with Epclusa.
      Further, the investigators hypothesize that patients with chronic hepatitis C infection on
      buprenorphine/naloxone maintenance therapy who are treated for HCV by a psychiatrist during
      regularly scheduled visits to an addiction clinic will have high rates of adherence to HCV
      treatment and achieve SVR 12.

      Given that subjects will receive standard of care evaluation and treatment for their chronic
      hepatitis C infection, the investigators believe that study participation poses minimal risk.
      Indeed, The investigators believe that subjects will benefit from improved access to this
      important treatment which will be provided at a convenient location by a known physician
      under the guidance of an infectious disease physician with extensive experience treating HCV
      infection.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">October 11, 2017</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of Sustained Virologic Response at 12 Weeks Post Treatment (SVR-12) Achieved by Participants</measure>
    <time_frame>This outcome measure will be assessed for each participant 12 weeks after completion of a 12 week course of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>To assess the effectiveness of HCV treatment with velpatasvir/sofosbuvir administered by psychiatrist/licensed buprenorphine/naloxone providers during regularly scheduled visits to an outpatient addiction clinic for buprenorphine/naloxone replacement therapy and mental healthcare, as measured by percentage of patients achieving SVR-12 (defined as HCV RNA &lt; lower limit of quantification (LLOQ) 12 weeks after discontinuation of study treatment),</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Health-Related Quality of Life</measure>
    <time_frame>This outcome measure will be assessed for each participant during a 12 week course of study treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>Mean quality of life scores from baseline to the end of treatment will be reported for all participants on buprenorphine/naloxone therapy receiving study treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to Study Treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>This outcome measure will be assessed for each participant during a 12 week course of study treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>To assess adherence to velpatasvir/sofosbuvir therapy among participants administered treatment in the context of visits to an outpatient addiction clinic for buprenorphine/naloxone replacement therapy and mental health care.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Psychiatrists Comfort Providing HCV Care</measure>
    <time_frame>Approximately 1 year.</time_frame>
    <description>Exploratory analysis describing the psychiatrists' comfort providing HCV care among six areas of counseling, over the course of the study.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatitis C, Chronic</condition>
  <condition>Hepatitis C</condition>
  <condition>Opiate Dependence</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>In this open label, single arm study, all subjects will receive the intervention as prescribed by psychiatrists in the office based opiate addition treatment program.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>sofosbuvir/velpatasvir</intervention_name>
    <description>12 week treatment with once daily sofosbuvir/velpatasivir fixed dose combination therapy. Tablets are formulated with 400mg sofosbuvir and 100mg velpatasvir in pink, diamond-shaped, film coated tablets.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment Arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Willing and able to provide written informed consent

          2. Age ≥ 18 years

          3. Confirmation of chronic HCV infection as documented by a positive HCV antibody test at
             least 6 months prior to the Baseline/Day 1 visit and positive HCV RNA test at
             screening

          4. HCV genotype 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 or 6

          5. In stable remission from opiate use on buprenorphine/naloxone for at least 12 weeks

          6. Within the following laboratory parameters as assessed at the screening visit:

               1. HCV RNA quantifiable

               2. Screening rhythm strip without bradycardia (heart rate &gt; 60 or, if on beta
                  blocker, &gt; 55 BPM)

               3. Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 10 x ULN (upper limit of normal)

               4. Aspartate Aminotransferase (AST) ≤ 10 x ULN

               5. Direct bilirubin ≤ 1.5 x ULN

               6. Platelets &gt; 60,000

               7. Hemoglobin A1C (HbA1c) ≤ 10%

               8. Creatinine clearance ≥ 30 mL/min, as calculated by the Cockcroft-Gault equation

               9. Albumin ≥ 3g/dL

              10. International Normalized Ratio (INR) ≤ 1.5 x ULN or on an anticoagulant regimen
                  affecting INR

          7. Female subject is eligible to enter if it is confirmed that she is:

               1. Not pregnant or nursing

               2. Not of childbearing potential (i.e. s/p hysterectomy, oophorectomy or has
                  medically documented ovarian failure, or are postmenopausal women &gt; 50 years of
                  age with cessation of menses for 12 months or greater) OR Of childbearing
                  potential with a negative serum pregnancy test within 2 weeks of screening, a
                  negative urine pregnancy test on Day 1, and a commitment to either abstain from
                  intercourse or consistently use an acceptable method of birth control (Appendix
                  4) in addition to condom use by her male partner(s) from the date of screening
                  until 30 days after the last dose of study drug

          8. All male study participants must agree to consistently and correctly use condoms with
             their female partner(s) and their female partner(s) must agree to use an acceptable
             method of birth control (listed) from the date of screening until 90 days after the
             last dose of study drug

          9. Male subjects must refrain from sperm donation from the date of screening until 90
             days after the last dose of study drug

         10. Subject must be in generally good health, with the exception of HCV, in the opinion of
             the Sponsor-Investigator or Sub-Investigator(s)

         11. Subject must be able to comply with dosing instructions for study drug administration
             and able to complete the study visits, including all required post-treatment visits

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Presence of decompensated cirrhosis as defined by encephalopathy, ascites, or a
             history of a variceal bleed

          2. Prior treatment with direct acting antiviral hepatitis C medications

          3. Positive urine drug toxicity test at screening (except for cannabinoids and prescribed
             medications)

          4. Absence of buprenorphine in urine sample at screening

          5. Currently pregnant or breastfeeding female

          6. Detectable HIV RNA &gt; 50 copies/ml (co-infected subjects with suppressed viral load ARE
             eligible for participation)

          7. Use of any prohibited concomitant medication within 28 days prior to day 1

          8. Chronic use of systemically administered immunosuppressive agents

          9. Difficulty with blood collection or poor venous access

         10. History of solid organ transplantation

         11. Known significant allergy to sofosbuvir or velpatasvir

         12. Current chronic liver disease of a non-HCV etiology (including hemochromatosis,
             Wilson's disease, alfa-1 antitrypsin deficiency)

         13. Active Hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection defined as either a positive HBV surface
             antigen test or a positive test for HBV DNA. (Subjects who are positive for HBV core
             antibody but negative for Hepatitis B surface antibody, surface antigen, and DNA ARE
             eligible)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Amy E Colson, MD MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Community Research Initiative of New England</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Project Manager</last_name>
    <phone>617-502-1707</phone>
    <email>info@crine.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cambridge Health Alliance Outpatient Addiction Services</name>
      <address>
        <city>Somerville</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Zev Schuman-Olivier, MD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Altice FL, Bruce RD, Lucas GM, Lum PJ, Korthuis PT, Flanigan TP, Cunningham CO, Sullivan LE, Vergara-Rodriguez P, Fiellin DA, Cajina A, Botsko M, Nandi V, Gourevitch MN, Finkelstein R; BHIVES Collaborative. HIV treatment outcomes among HIV-infected, opioid-dependent patients receiving buprenorphine/naloxone treatment within HIV clinical care settings: results from a multisite study. J Acquir Immune Defic Syndr. 2011 Mar 1;56 Suppl 1:S22-32. doi: 10.1097/QAI.0b013e318209751e.</citation>
    <PMID>21317590</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Arora S, Thornton K, Murata G, Deming P, Kalishman S, Dion D, Parish B, Burke T, Pak W, Dunkelberg J, Kistin M, Brown J, Jenkusky S, Komaromy M, Qualls C. Outcomes of treatment for hepatitis C virus infection by primary care providers. N Engl J Med. 2011 Jun 9;364(23):2199-207. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa1009370. Epub 2011 Jun 1.</citation>
    <PMID>21631316</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Robaeys G, Grebely J, Mauss S, Bruggmann P, Moussalli J, De Gottardi A, Swan T, Arain A, Kautz A, Stöver H, Wedemeyer H, Schaefer M, Taylor L, Backmund M, Dalgard O, Prins M, Dore GJ; International Network on Hepatitis in Substance Users. Recommendations for the management of hepatitis C virus infection among people who inject drugs. Clin Infect Dis. 2013 Aug;57 Suppl 2:S129-37. doi: 10.1093/cid/cit302.</citation>
    <PMID>23884061</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aspinall EJ, Corson S, Doyle JS, Grebely J, Hutchinson SJ, Dore GJ, Goldberg DJ, Hellard ME. Treatment of hepatitis C virus infection among people who are actively injecting drugs: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Clin Infect Dis. 2013 Aug;57 Suppl 2:S80-9. doi: 10.1093/cid/cit306. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23884071</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 27, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 27, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">August 1, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 24, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HCV</keyword>
  <keyword>suboxone</keyword>
  <keyword>epclusa</keyword>
  <keyword>psychiatrist</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis A</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hepatitis C, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Opioid-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sofosbuvir</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

