<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01393470</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>115006 (HPV-027)</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01393470</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Long-term HPV Vaccine Efficacy</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Long-term Follow-up Registry-based Cohort Study of HPV Vaccine Efficacy Against Cervical Pre-cancerous Lesions and Cervical Cancers in a Cohort of Females Previously Enrolled From Finland in Study HPV-008, as Compared to a Non-intervention Population -Based Reference Cohort of Females From Finland</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Tampere</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>FinnMedi Oy</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Tampere</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Summary

      For ethical and practical reasons pre-licensure clinical efficacy phase III trials for GSK
      Biologicals' HPV-16/18 LI VLP AS04 vaccine used cervical intraepithelial grade 2 and above
      (CIN2+) lesions as surrogate efficacy endpoint for cervical cancer. The long-term impact of
      HPV vaccination on cervical cancer as well as other HPV-related non- cervical cancers is,
      however, an area warranting further exploration in the post-licensure setting. Results of the
      multinational phase III trial demonstrated high vaccine efficacy against CIN2+ associated
      with HPV-16 and/or HPV-18, significant vaccine efficacy against CIN2+ and CIN3+ irrespective
      of HPV type in the lesion as well as evidence of protection against CIN2+ associated with HPV
      types 31 and 45 [Paavonen, et al. 2009]. Over time, vaccinated cohorts should benefit from a
      substantial reduction in the incidence of cervical cancer considering impact on oncogenic
      non-vaccine HPV types. This long-term study is conducted to evaluate the long-term impact of
      GSK Biologicals' HPV-16/18 vaccine on the occurrence of cervical pre-cancerous lesions and
      cervical cancer with the following objectives:

        -  To assess the long-term efficacy of the HPV-16/18 L1 VLP AS04 vaccine on the occurrence
           of cervical cancer including its immediate precursors (CIN3+): cervical intraepithelial
           neoplasia grade 3 (CIN3) and adenocarcinoma in situ (AIS) by comparing cohorts A and C
           (see below).

        -  To assess the efficacy of HPV-16/18 L1 VLP AS04 vaccine on the occurrence of the
           following potentially HPV related non-cervical cancers such as vulvar intraepithelial
           neoplasia, vaginal intraepithelial neoplasia, anogenital neoplasia and oropharyngeal
           neoplasia by comparing cohorts A and C (see below)

        -  To assess as an explanatory objective the occurrence of CIN3+ breakthrough cases
           associated with HPV-16 or HPV-18 infection in subjects vaccinated with HPV-16/18 L1 VLP
           AS04 vaccine by close surveillance of cohorts and cross vaccinated cohort B (see below)

      This prospective, observational cohort study is undertaken in originally 16-17 year-old
      Finnish females who have participated in the GSK Biologicals' HPV-008 trial (NCT00122681)
      with regular clinical follow-up, and can be divided in Cohort A: Female subjects from Finland
      who received HPV-16/18 L1 VLP AS04 vaccine in the HPV-008 study between May 2004 and May 2005
      (N=2409), and Cohort B: Female subjects from Finland who received the Hepatitis A control
      vaccine in the HPV-008 study (N=2399). All subjects were offered the HPV-16/18 L1 VLP AS04
      vaccine or screening for cervical cancer at the end of the study (age 21-22): 50% of the
      subjects, chose not to take cross-over HPV vaccination at HPV-008 study end. Referent Cohort
      C: A population-based reference cohort of female subjects from Finland who have not been
      exposed to any HPV vaccine (either during a HPV vaccine trial, or commercially available
      vaccine; i.e. Cervarix or Gardasil), enrolled in this study in May - September 2003 or May -
      September 2005, altogether 15536 subjects).

      Prospective data collection will start at the HPV screening invitation for each subject in
      2013. Several analyses are planned including an analysis at 8 years post-completion of the
      HPV-008 study (by 2020) and will provide a total evaluation time of approximately 15 years
      since first vaccination in the Cohort A.

      The study is self-contained for the primary and secondary endpoints. Data from the HPV-008
      trial will be used to address exploratory objectives mentioned above. Data collection will be
      performed using the databases from the University of Tampere.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2024</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of intraepithelial neoplasia grade 3 or worse (CIN3+). including CIN3, cervical cancer (squamous cell carcinoma or adenocarcinoma).</measure>
    <time_frame>The time frame is up to 15 years (for the interim analyses: 4, 7 and 10 years). (Start and end of passive follow-up, Cohorts A and B: 01.01.2010 - 31.12. 2024; Cohorts C1 and C2: 01.10.2007/01.10.2008 - 30.09.2021/30.09.2023.)</time_frame>
    <description>To estimate the long-term vaccine efficacy by comparing the incidence rate of cervical cancers and pre-cancerous lesions (CIN3+) in Cohort A vs. Cohort C.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurrence of potentially HPV related non-cervical cancers or pre cancerous lesions, including but not limited to the occurrence of vulvar intraepithelial neoplasia and vaginal intraepithelial neoplasia.</measure>
    <time_frame>The time frame for the objectives of the study is up to 15 years. (Start and end of passive follow-up, Cohorts A and B: 01.01.2010 - 31.12. 2024; Cohorts C1 and C2: 01.10.2007/01.10.2008 - 30.09.2021/30.09.2023.)</time_frame>
    <description>To estimate the efficacy of HPV-16/18 vaccine against non-cervical cancers by comparing the incidence of non-cervical cancers in Cohort A vs. Cohort C.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">10000</enrollment>
  <condition>Uterine Cervical Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A (Trial Cohort, Vaccinated during HPV-008)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Cohort A subjects were previously enrolled in the HPV-008 study, and have received at least 1 dose of the HPV vaccine.
Cohort A subjects have provided written informed consent prior to enrolment to allow retrieval of biospecimens for HPV DNA testing and confirmation of diagnosis.
Subjects who provided written informed consent prior to enrolment for the use of their personal identifier for linkage purposes to Finnish Registries.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort B1 + B2</arm_group_label>
    <description>Cohort B1 subjects were previously enrolled in the HPV-008 study and received at least 1 dose of HPV vaccine as cross-over vaccination at the end of the HPV-008 study.
Cohort B1 subjects have provided written informed consent prior to enrolment to allow retrieval of biospecimens for HPV DNA testing and confirmation of diagnosis.
Subjects who provided written informed consent prior to enrolment for the use of their personal identifier for linkage purposes to Finnish Registries.
Cohort B2 (Trial Cohort, Non-Vaccinated)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort C (Referent Cohort, Non-Vaccinated)</arm_group_label>
    <description>Cohort C subjects have not participated in the HPV-008 study but have been enrolled in the Referent Cohort.
Cohort C subjects have not received any HPV vaccination (neither Cervarix, nor Gardasil, nor any experimental HPV vaccine).
Cohort C subjects are partially matched to HPV-008 in terms of the geographical recruitment area.
Subjects who provided written informed consent prior to enrolment for the use of their personal identifier for linkage purposes to Finnish Registries.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Screening for cervical cancer</intervention_name>
    <description>Organized screening for cervical cancer start for all cohorts at the age of 25 years with 5 year interval.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort A (Trial Cohort, Vaccinated during HPV-008)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort B1 + B2</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Cohort C (Referent Cohort, Non-Vaccinated)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Cytological cervical (liquid based and/or conventional) samples. Colposcopy directed cervical
      biopsy samples fixed in formalin.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Trial Cohort (16-17 years at baseline) - the cohort of Finnish subjects who participated in
        the GSK Biologicals' HPV-008 trial (NCT00122681):

        Cohort A: subjects who received HPV-16/18 L1 VLP AS04 vaccine between May 2004 and May
        2005.

        Cohort B: subjects who received the Hepatitis A control vaccine. All subjects were offered
        the HPV-16/18 L1 VLP AS04 vaccine at the end of the study (age 21-22):

        Cohort B1: subjects who received the Hepatitis A control vaccine and then received
        cross-over HPV vaccination at HPV-008 study end.

        Cohort B2: subjects who received the Hepatitis A control vaccine and who did not receive
        cross-over HPV vaccination at HPV-008 study end.

        Referent cohort (18-19 years at baseline):

        Cohort C: A population-based reference cohort of female subjects from Finland who have not
        been exposed to any HPV vaccine enrolled in this study in May 2005, immediately after
        recruitment of the HPV-008 clinical trial subjects had been stopped (approximately 9,000
        subjects).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Trial Cohort (16-17 years at baseline) - the cohort of Finnish subjects who
             participated in the GSK Biologicals' HPV-008 trial (NCT00122681):

          -  Cohort A: subjects who received HPV-16/18 L1 VLP AS04 vaccine between May 2004 and May
             2005.

          -  Cohort B: subjects who received the Hepatitis A control vaccine. All subjects were
             offered the HPV-16/18 L1 VLP AS04 vaccine at the end of the study (age 21-22).

          -  Cohort B1: subjects who received the Hepatitis A control vaccine and then received
             cross-over HPV vaccination at HPV-008 study end.

          -  Cohort B2: subjects who received the Hepatitis A control vaccine and who did not
             receive cross-over HPV vaccination at HPV-008 study end.

          -  Referent cohort (18-19 years at baseline):

          -  Cohort C: A population-based reference cohort of female subjects from Finland who have
             not been exposed to any HPV vaccine enrolled in this study in May 2005, immediately
             after recruitment of the HPV-008 clinical trial subjects had been stopped
             (approximately 9,000 subjects).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Trial Cohort (Cohort A and B): Previous or planned administration of an HPV vaccine
             not foreseen by the HPV-008 study protocol or any HPV-008 extension study protocol
             (Gardasil or any experimental HPV vaccine).

          -  Referent cohort (Cohort C): Previous or planned administration of an HPV vaccine
             (Cervarix, Gardasil or any experimental HPV vaccine).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>19 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Matti Lehtinen, M.D., Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Tampere</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Väestöliitto Seksuaaliterveysklinikka</name>
      <address>
        <city>Helsinki</city>
        <zip>00101</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nuorten rokotetutkimukset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jyväskylä</city>
        <zip>40100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nuorten rokotetutkimukset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kotka</city>
        <zip>48100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nuorten rokotetutkimukset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kouvola</city>
        <zip>45100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nuorten rokotetutkimukset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Kuopio</city>
        <zip>70100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nuorten rokotetutkimukset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lahti</city>
        <zip>15110</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nuorten rokotetutkimukset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lappeenranta</city>
        <zip>53100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nuorten rokotetutkimukset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mikkeli</city>
        <zip>50100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VL-Medi Oy/Pikkuklinikka</name>
      <address>
        <city>Oulu</city>
        <zip>90220</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nuorten rokotetutkimukset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Pori</city>
        <zip>28100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nuorten rokotetutkimukset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rauma</city>
        <zip>26100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nuorten rokotetutkimukset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Seinäjoki</city>
        <zip>60100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nuorten rokotetutkimukset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampere</city>
        <zip>33100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nuorten rokotetutkimukset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Turku</city>
        <zip>20100 Turku</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nuorten rokotetutkimukset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vaasa</city>
        <zip>65100</zip>
        <country>Finland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Finland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paavonen J, Naud P, Salmerón J, Wheeler CM, Chow SN, Apter D, Kitchener H, Castellsague X, Teixeira JC, Skinner SR, Hedrick J, Jaisamrarn U, Limson G, Garland S, Szarewski A, Romanowski B, Aoki FY, Schwarz TF, Poppe WA, Bosch FX, Jenkins D, Hardt K, Zahaf T, Descamps D, Struyf F, Lehtinen M, Dubin G; HPV PATRICIA Study Group. Efficacy of human papillomavirus (HPV)-16/18 AS04-adjuvanted vaccine against cervical infection and precancer caused by oncogenic HPV types (PATRICIA): final analysis of a double-blind, randomised study in young women. Lancet. 2009 Jul 25;374(9686):301-14. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(09)61248-4. Epub 2009 Jul 6. Erratum in: Lancet. 2010 Sep 25;376(9746):1054.</citation>
    <PMID>19586656</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paavonen J, Jenkins D, Bosch FX, Naud P, Salmerón J, Wheeler CM, Chow SN, Apter DL, Kitchener HC, Castellsague X, de Carvalho NS, Skinner SR, Harper DM, Hedrick JA, Jaisamrarn U, Limson GA, Dionne M, Quint W, Spiessens B, Peeters P, Struyf F, Wieting SL, Lehtinen MO, Dubin G; HPV PATRICIA study group. Efficacy of a prophylactic adjuvanted bivalent L1 virus-like-particle vaccine against infection with human papillomavirus types 16 and 18 in young women: an interim analysis of a phase III double-blind, randomised controlled trial. Lancet. 2007 Jun 30;369(9580):2161-2170. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(07)60946-5. Erratum in: Lancet. 2007 Oct 20;370(9596):1414.</citation>
    <PMID>17602732</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lehtinen M, Idänpään-Heikkilä I, Lunnas T, Palmroth J, Barr E, Cacciatore R, Isaksson R, Kekki M, Koskela P, Kosunen E, Kuortti M, Lahti L, Liljamo T, Luostarinen T, Apter D, Pukkala E, Paavonen J. Population-based enrolment of adolescents in a long-term follow-up trial of human papillomavirus vaccine efficacy. Int J STD AIDS. 2006 Apr;17(4):237-46.</citation>
    <PMID>16595046</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lehtinen M, Paavonen J. Effectiveness of preventive human papillomavirus vaccination. Int J STD AIDS. 2003 Dec;14(12):787-92. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>14678583</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lehtinen M, Apter D, Dubin G, Kosunen E, Isaksson R, Korpivaara EL, Kyhä-Osterlund L, Lunnas T, Luostarinen T, Niemi L, Palmroth J, Petäjä T, Rekonen S, Salmivesi S, Siitari-Mattila M, Svartsjö S, Tuomivaara L, Vilkki M, Pukkala E, Paavonen J. Enrolment of 22,000 adolescent women to cancer registry follow-up for long-term human papillomavirus vaccine efficacy: guarding against guessing. Int J STD AIDS. 2006 Aug;17(8):517-21.</citation>
    <PMID>16925896</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 5, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 12, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 13, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 14, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 14, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 15, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Tampere</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Matti Lehtinen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof.</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>HPV</keyword>
  <keyword>Vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>long-term efficacy</keyword>
  <keyword>registry-based study</keyword>
  <keyword>Evaluation of long-term HPV vaccine efficacy: a population-based, registry-based cohort study in Finland.</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Uterine Cervical Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

