<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01398696</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>n° IRB 5891</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01398696</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of Four Patient Information Leaflets (PIL) on Patient Behaviour</brief_title>
  <acronym>PIL</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of Four Patient Information Leaflets (PIL) on Patient Behaviour : a Randomised Controlled Trial in Primary Care.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Hospital, Grenoble</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Hospital, Grenoble</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess the impact of four Patient Information Leaflets (PIL) on patient behaviour in
      primary care.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A patient who visited, for a gastroenteritis or a pharyngitis, one GP of the intervention
      group, received a Patient Information Leaflets (PIL) related to his disease and his age:
      either the gastroenteritis leaflet for adult or the one for child, either the pharyngitis
      leaflet for adult or the one for child.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome measure was the mean behaviour score</measure>
    <time_frame>In ten to fifteen days after patient after the visit</time_frame>
    <description>All patients were called, ten to fifteen days after the visit, to answer a questionnaire on their behaviour related to the disease since they visited the GP. It permitted to calculate a behaviour score. Better was the score, better was the patient's behaviour related to his disease.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>the mean comprehension score</measure>
    <time_frame>in ten to fifteen days after the visit</time_frame>
    <description>All patients (or their parent) were called, ten to fifteen days after the visit, to answer a questionnaire on their comprehension related to the disease since they visited the GP. It permitted to calculate a comprehension score. Better was this score, better was the patient's comprehension.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>number of visit of patient's family for the same pathology</measure>
    <time_frame>in ten to fifteen days after the visit</time_frame>
    <description>we get the information by a phone call to the patient, in ten to fifteen days after the visit</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">400</enrollment>
  <condition>Gastroenteritis</condition>
  <condition>Pharyngitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Information Leaflets</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patient Information Leaflets (PIL) is given to the patient during consultation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>usual consultation without PIL</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>no particular intervention during consultation for the patient.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Patient Information Leaflets</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient Information Leaflets (PIL) about adult gastroenteritis, children gastroenteritis, adult pharyngitis or either children pharyngitis in consultation room</description>
    <arm_group_label>Patient Information Leaflets</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>usual consultation</intervention_name>
    <description>No particular intervention during consultation for the Patient. No Information Leaflets (PIL) is given</description>
    <arm_group_label>usual consultation without PIL</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Adult patient.

          -  Minor child accompanied by a responsible adult.

          -  The patient or the caregiver must be reachable by telephone within ten to fifteen days
             following the consultation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Illiterate patient

          -  Patient refusing follow-up call.

          -  Patient with visual or hearing impairment.

          -  Patient non-Francophone.

          -  Private patient of liberty by judicial or administrative.

          -  Person being a measure of legal protection.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Melanie Sustersic, GP</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Grenoble</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jean-Luc Bosson, PHD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Grenoble</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>LUCILE REIN, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Grenoble</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>EVA JEANNET, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Hospital, Grenoble</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Antibes Juan Les Pins</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Beaulieu Sur Mer</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chambery</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Charolles</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chirens</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Coublevie</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Echirolles</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <zip>38000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital Grenoble</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Buisse</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Murette</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lyon</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Massy</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Megeve</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Plessis Robinson</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Etienne de Crossey</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Marcellin</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Martin D'heres</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Priest</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Sorlin</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ugine</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valence</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>General practitioner office</name>
      <address>
        <city>Voiron</city>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stewart M, Brown JB, Donner A, McWhinney IR, Oates J, Weston WW, Jordan J. The impact of patient-centered care on outcomes. J Fam Pract. 2000 Sep;49(9):796-804.</citation>
    <PMID>11032203</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kitching JB. Patient information leaflets--the state of the art. J R Soc Med. 1990 May;83(5):298-300.</citation>
    <PMID>2380944</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kenny T, Wilson RG, Purves IN, Clark J Sr, Newton LD, Newton DP, Moseley DV. A PIL for every ill? Patient information leaflets (PILs): a review of past, present and future use. Fam Pract. 1998 Oct;15(5):471-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>9848435</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Little P, Griffin S, Kelly J, Dickson N, Sadler C. Effect of educational leaflets and questions on knowledge of contraception in women taking the combined contraceptive pill: randomised controlled trial. BMJ. 1998 Jun 27;316(7149):1948-52.</citation>
    <PMID>9641933</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Little P, Dorward M, Warner G, Moore M, Stephens K, Senior J, Kendrick T. Randomised controlled trial of effect of leaflets to empower patients in consultations in primary care. BMJ. 2004 Feb 21;328(7437):441. Epub 2004 Feb 13.</citation>
    <PMID>14966078</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coudeyre E, Givron P, Vanbiervliet W, Benaïm C, Hérisson C, Pelissier J, Poiraudeau S. [The role of an information booklet or oral information about back pain in reducing disability and fear-avoidance beliefs among patients with subacute and chronic low back pain. A randomized controlled trial in a rehabilitation unit]. Ann Readapt Med Phys. 2006 Nov;49(8):600-8. Epub 2006 May 26. French.</citation>
    <PMID>16793163</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Coudeyre E, Poiraudeau S, Revel M, Kahan A, Drapé JL, Ravaud P. Beneficial effects of information leaflets before spinal steroid injection. Joint Bone Spine. 2002 Dec;69(6):597-603.</citation>
    <PMID>12537268</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>McIntosh A, Shaw CF. Barriers to patient information provision in primary care: patients' and general practitioners' experiences and expectations of information for low back pain. Health Expect. 2003 Mar;6(1):19-29.</citation>
    <PMID>12603625</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Watkins CJ, Papacosta AO, Chinn S, Martin J. A randomized controlled trial of an information booklet for hypertensive patients in general practice. J R Coll Gen Pract. 1987 Dec;37(305):548-50.</citation>
    <PMID>3503941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roberts L, Little P, Chapman J, Cantrell T, Pickering R, Langridge J. The back home trial: general practitioner-supported leaflets may change back pain behavior. Spine (Phila Pa 1976). 2002 Sep 1;27(17):1821-8.</citation>
    <PMID>12221342</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Johnson LK, Edelman A, Jensen J. Patient satisfaction and the impact of written material about postpartum contraceptive decisions. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2003 May;188(5):1202-4.</citation>
    <PMID>12748478</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mancini J, Noguès C, Adenis C, Berthet P, Bonadona V, Chompret A, Coupier I, Eisinger F, Fricker JP, Gauthier-Villars M, Lasset C, Lortholary A, N'Guyen TD, Vennin P, Sobol H, Stoppa-Lyonnet D, Julian-Reynier C. Impact of an information booklet on satisfaction and decision-making about BRCA genetic testing. Eur J Cancer. 2006 May;42(7):871-81. Epub 2006 Mar 23.</citation>
    <PMID>16563745</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Al-Asfour A, Andersson L. The effect of a leaflet given to parents for first aid measures after tooth avulsion. Dent Traumatol. 2008 Oct;24(5):515-21. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-9657.2008.00651.x.</citation>
    <PMID>18821954</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carré PC, Roche N, Neukirch F, Radeau T, Perez T, Terrioux P, Ostinelli J, Pouchain D, Huchon G. The effect of an information leaflet upon knowledge and awareness of COPD in potential sufferers. A randomized controlled study. Respiration. 2008;76(1):53-60. doi: 10.1159/000115947. Epub 2008 Feb 5.</citation>
    <PMID>18253024</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Scala D, Cozzolino S, D'Amato G, Cocco G, Sena A, Martucci P, Ferraro E, Mancini AA. Sharing knowledge is the key to success in a patient-physician relationship: how to produce a patient information leaflet on COPD. Monaldi Arch Chest Dis. 2008 Jun;69(2):50-4.</citation>
    <PMID>18837416</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vetto JT, Dubois PM, Vetto IP. The impact of distribution of a patient-education pamphlet in a multidisciplinary breast clinic. J Cancer Educ. 1996 Fall;11(3):148-52.</citation>
    <PMID>8877574</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leichtnam-Dugarin L, Carretier J, Delavigne V, Brusco S, Hoarau H, Philip T, Fervers B; Comité d'Organisation des Standards, Options et Recommentations SAVOIR; Fédération Nationale des Centres de lutte contre le cancer; Ligue contre le Cancer; Fédération Hospitalière de France; Fédération Nationale de Cancérologie des CHRU; Fédération Française de Cancérologie. [The SOR SAVOIR Patient, a project of patient information and education]. Cancer Radiother. 2003 Jun;7(3):210-2. French.</citation>
    <PMID>12834779</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Roland M, Dixon M. Randomized controlled trial of an educational booklet for patients presenting with back pain in general practice. J R Coll Gen Pract. 1989 Jun;39(323):244-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2556518</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Macfarlane JT, Holmes WF, Macfarlane RM. Reducing reconsultations for acute lower respiratory tract illness with an information leaflet: a randomized controlled study of patients in primary care. Br J Gen Pract. 1997 Nov;47(424):719-22.</citation>
    <PMID>9519518</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Macfarlane J, Holmes W, Gard P, Thornhill D, Macfarlane R, Hubbard R. Reducing antibiotic use for acute bronchitis in primary care: blinded, randomised controlled trial of patient information leaflet. BMJ. 2002 Jan 12;324(7329):91-4.</citation>
    <PMID>11786454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vuorma S, Rissanen P, Aalto AM, Hurskainen R, Kujansuu E, Teperi J. Impact of patient information booklet on treatment decision--a randomized trial among women with heavy menstruation. Health Expect. 2003 Dec;6(4):290-7.</citation>
    <PMID>15040791</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dedianne MC, Hauzanneau P, Labarere J, Moreau A. Relation médecin-malade en soins primaires: qu'attendent les patients? Investigation par la méthode qualitative des focus groups. La revue du praticien Médecine générale. 2003;17 (612):653-6.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Paul F, Jones MC, Hendry C, Adair PM. The quality of written information for parents regarding the management of a febrile convulsion: a randomized controlled trial. J Clin Nurs. 2007 Dec;16(12):2308-22.</citation>
    <PMID>18036121</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sustersic M, Voorhoeve M, Menuret H, Baudrant M, Meneau A, Bosson JL. Fiches d'information pour les patients: quel intérêt? L'étude EDIMAP. La Revue de la médecine générale. 2010;276:332-9.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Francis NA, Butler CC, Hood K, Simpson S, Wood F, Nuttall J. Effect of using an interactive booklet about childhood respiratory tract infections in primary care consultations on reconsulting and antibiotic prescribing: a cluster randomised controlled trial. BMJ. 2009 Jul 29;339:b2885. doi: 10.1136/bmj.b2885.</citation>
    <PMID>19640941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lerman C, Ross E, Boyce A, Gorchov PM, McLaughlin R, Rimer B, Engstrom P. The impact of mailing psychoeducational materials to women with abnormal mammograms. Am J Public Health. 1992 May;82(5):729-30.</citation>
    <PMID>1566953</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sustersic M, Meneau A, Drémont R, Paris A, Laborde L, Bosson JL. [Developing patient information sheets in general practice. Proposal for a methodology]. Rev Prat. 2008 Dec 15;58(19 Suppl):17-24. French.</citation>
    <PMID>19253787</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sustersic M, Meneau A, Drémont R, Paris A, Laborde L, Bosson JL. Elaboration d'un outil d'aide à l'éducation du patient pas la réalisation de 125 fiches d'information et de conseil concernant des motifs de consultation les plus fréquents en médecin générale. Université Joseph Fourier, faculté de médecine de Grenoble. juillet 2007.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>October 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 19, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 19, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 20, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 11, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 11, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 12, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Patient Information Leaflets</keyword>
  <keyword>primary care</keyword>
  <keyword>patient behaviour</keyword>
  <keyword>pharyngitis</keyword>
  <keyword>gastroenteritis</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Gastroenteritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pharyngitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

