<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01396954</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CREED-ENDO</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01396954</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cirrhosis-Diabetes</brief_title>
  <acronym>CH-DM</acronym>
  <official_title>Prevalence and Clinical Characteristics of the Patients With Liver Cirrhosis and Different Glucose Metabolism Disorders - A Prospective Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospital Universitario Dr. Jose E. Gonzalez</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Glucose metabolism disorders (GMD) can be present in an overt and a subclinical way. They
      have negative impact in survival of patients with liver cirrhosis (LC). Their prevalence has
      not been determined in compensated cirrhotic patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Overt Diabetes Mellitus (DM) is observed in 21 to 40% of patients with liver cirrhosis (LC).
      There are two ways in which DM is related to LC: firstly, type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM),
      which has a genetic component and is often associated with metabolic syndrome (obesity,
      hypertriglyceridemia, and hypertension), causes chronic liver disease (steatosis,
      steatohepatitis, and LC Secondly, LC may cause impaired glucose tolerance (IGT) and DM.
      During the initial stages of LC these metabolic disorders are subclinical as can only be
      detected by an oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT). As liver disease progresses, DM becomes
      clinically evident.

      Diabetes mellitus secondary to LC is known as &quot;hepatogenous diabetes&quot; (HD). Although it has
      been accepted that the LC is a diabetogenic condition, HD is not recognized by the American
      Diabetes Association and the WHO. Cirrhosis caused by alcohol, HCV, and hemochromatosis are
      more frequently associated to HD than other etiologies . It has been observed that HCV core
      protein induces insulin resistance (IR), steatosis, and DM regardless of body mass index
      (BMI). Patients with chronic alcoholism often have chronic pancreatic damage resulting in DM
      . In short, T2DM and HD have different etiology, but they seem to have similar
      pathophysiologic mechanisms for liver function deterioration. They increase the risk of
      complications and death.

      In recent years, the incidence of obesity has increased alarmingly in the world, particularly
      in the Western countries . In Mexico, overweight and obesity, which are suffered by about 70%
      of the adult population are a serious public health problem,. This figure puts this country
      in second place in the world, behind only the United States of America. The incidence of T2DM
      and metabolic syndrome has increased rapidly in our country . They have became the most
      common causes of cryptogenic cirrhosis in Mexico. Many published studies, which have reviewed
      the prevalence of DM in cirrhotic patients, do not make a distinction between T2DM and HD;
      additionally, subclinical glucose metabolism disorders (GMD) are not routinely identified, so
      the magnitude of the problem has been underestimated. On the other hand, the clinical and
      biochemical features of cirrhotic patients with different GMD are not known at present. The
      clinical distinction of GMD may be useful for prognosis and therapeutic purposes. Based on
      the aforementioned, the objectives of the present study were: a) To establish the prevalence
      of clinical and subclinical forms of GMD (T2DM, HD, IGT) in a cohort of patients with
      compensated LC of diverse etiology; and b) To determine the clinical and biochemical
      characteristics of patient with these different GMD and to find whether there are significant
      differences among them..
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>November 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">130</enrollment>
  <condition>Glucose Metabolism Disorders</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        We prospectively included patients with compensated liver cirrhosis who were admitted in
        the Regional Center for the Study of Digestive Diseases and the Liver Unit of the
        University Hospital and Faculty of Medicine
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  the presence of biopsy- or clinically diagnosed liver cirrhosis; clinically
             compensated cirrhosis; age above 18 years; and any sexExclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with complications due to liver disease (such as hepatocellular carcinoma,
             alcoholic hepatitis, active gastrointestinal bleeding, hepatic encephalopathy,
             hepatorenal syndrome, and severe infection)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>November 2007</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 18, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 18, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 19, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 18, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 18, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 19, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Diego Garcia-Compean</name_title>
    <organization>Gastroenterology Service and Department of Internal Medicine, University Hospital</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Liver cirrhosis</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetes mellitus</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatogenous diabetes</keyword>
  <keyword>Oral glucose tolerance test</keyword>
  <keyword>Insulin resistance.</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fibrosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Cirrhosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metabolic Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Glucose Metabolism Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

