<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01394614</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Narco-H1N1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01394614</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Risk of Narcolepsy Associated With Administration of H1N1 Vaccine</brief_title>
  <official_title>Risk of Narcolepsy Associated With Administration of Inactivated Adjuvanted (AS03) A/H1N1 Pandemic Influenza Vaccine in Quebec</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hopital du Sacre-Coeur de Montreal</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hopital du Sacre-Coeur de Montreal</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The goal of the study is to assess the risk of occurrence of narcolepsy following the
      administration of inactivated (AS03) adjuvanted A/H1N1 pandemic influenza vaccine in the
      province of Quebec, Canada, using different case definitions and time intervals to disease
      onset, while controlling for potential confounding variables such as age, gender, season and,
      when possible, A/H1N1 pandemic influenza infection. Another aim is to describe the
      epidemiology and clinical features of narcolepsy cases with onset during the period January
      1st, 2009 to December 31, 2010 in the population of Quebec.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to describe the epidemiological and clinical characteristics of cases of
      narcolepsy which occurred in Quebec during the period 1 January 2009 to December 31, 2010 and
      to assess the risk of developing narcolepsy associated with the vaccine against influenza
      A/H1N1. The study will last about six months. Based on the prevalence of narcolepsy, an
      estimated 100 people who developed symptoms of narcolepsy between January 1st, 2009 and
      December 31, 2010 will participate in this study at the sleep clinic of the Sacré-Coeur
      Hospital in Montreal.

      Narcolepsy is primarily characterized by the presence of excessive daytime sleepiness (EDS)
      and cataplexy. EDS occurs daily and is usually the most disabling symptom of narcolepsy.
      Cataplexy consists of a sudden drop of muscle tone triggered by strong and sudden emotions
      such as laughter, anger and surprise. Cataplexy is the most specific symptom of narcolepsy
      but it is not present in every patient especially at disease onset. Two other auxiliary
      symptoms are sleep paralysis and hypnagogic hallucinations either at sleep onset or upon
      awakening during the night or in the morning. They are present in approximately two thirds of
      narcoleptic patients especially in the younger individuals during the early stage of
      narcolepsy. Narcolepsy is associated with an absence or low level of hypocretin1 peptide in
      the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF).

      Narcolepsy with cataplexy can be diagnosed purely on clinical grounds but this diagnosis
      should whenever possible be confirmed by night-time polysomnography (PSG) followed by the
      daytime multiple sleep latency test (MSLT). Sleep latency on the MSLT should be inferior or
      equal to 8 minutes with the presence of two or more sleep onset REM periods (SOREMPs). Human
      leukocyte antigen (HLA) typing of patients with narcolepsy-cataplexy almost always shows the
      presence of HLA DQB1*0602. Finally, measuring CSF level of hypocretin-1 is specific and
      sensitive for the diagnosis of narcolepsy with cataplexy.

      Cases of narcolepsy following administration of A/H1N1 pandemic vaccines have been reported
      in Sweden, Finland, France and Canada. The majority of reports have shown a temporal
      association with inactivated (AS03) adjuvanted A/H1N1 vaccines. These cases had some common
      features: severe sleepiness and presence of cataplexy, abrupt onset and rapid evolution,
      presence of HLA DBQ1*0602 marker, very low CSF hypocretin-1, and positive MSLT test. At the
      request of the European Medicines Agency (EMA), a series of investigations have been
      considered by GlaxoSmithKline Biologicals, including one in Quebec. In this province,
      following the report of four cases of narcolepsy with cataplexy potentially associated with
      administration of Arepanrix, our research team was contacted both by federal and provincial
      public health authorities to evaluate the possibility of an independent investigation.

      A retrospective cohort study is proposed. The existence of a comprehensive influenza
      immunization registry in Quebec allows a precise identification of the cohort of exposed
      subjects, by age and gender. Exposed subjects will be followed from the time of vaccine
      administration (first dose of inactivated AS03 A/H1N1 pandemic vaccine) as recorded in the
      immunization registry. The size of non-exposed subjects by gender- and age-specific
      categories will be estimated from the number in census data (a more accurate source than
      provincial health insurance data) minus the number in the influenza immunization registry.
      Pseudo-dates of vaccine administration will be generated for non-exposed subjects based on
      the distribution of dates of vaccinated subjects. Non-exposed subjects will be followed from
      the pseudo-date of vaccine administration.

      All neurologists, pulmonologists, neuro-pediatricians and child psychiatrists practicing in
      the province of Quebec will be contacted and asked to report confirmed or suspected cases of
      narcolepsy with onset during the period from January1st, 2009 to December 31, 2010. Patients
      will be contacted by their physicians and invited to call the sleep center to participate in
      a study of newly diagnosed cases of narcolepsy. They will then undergo a brief screening
      telephone questionnaire. At this point, if they meet the minimum criteria of narcolepsy, they
      will be asked if they agree to participate in the study. The study includes, at first,
      signing a consent form and completing a questionnaire.

      The questionnaire includes questions on demographics, medical history, medications, and
      detailed questions about symptoms of narcolepsy. In children, the information will be based
      on parental responses. A physician specializing in sleep medicine will call the participant
      to review the questionnaire with him and will propose a series of tests at the sleep
      laboratory of the 'Hôpital du Sacré-Coeur de Montréal', including nocturnal polysomnography,
      MSLT test, blood sampling (for HLA typing) and, lumbar puncture (for hypocretin
      measurements). Patients will sign a second consent form on site at 'Hôpital du Sacré-Coeur de
      Montréal' if they agree to participate in that second portion of the study. Monitoring of
      subjects during the study will be done under the supervision of Dr. Jacques Montplaisir, MD,
      PhD.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Narcolepsy Among Narcoleptic Subjects Exposed or Unexposed to Vaccine</measure>
    <time_frame>Narcolepsy onset during the 16-week post-vaccination period.</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence rates will be computed by comparing narcolepsy incidence rates in exposed and non-exposed subjects. Comparison of narcolepsy incidence rates in the period prior to vaccine administration and pseudo-vaccine administration will be used to test the comparability of exposed and non-exposed group.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Narcolepsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Narcoleptics exposed to A/H1N1 vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <description>Adjuvanted (ASO3) A/H1N1 pandemic vaccine</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Narcoleptics unexposed to A/H1N1 vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <description>Narcoleptic subjects who were unexposed (non-vaccinated or vaccinated after onset) to adjuvanted (ASO3) A/H1N1 pandemic vaccine.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>A/H1N1 vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Verify if exposure to Arepanrix vaccine increase risk of developing narcolepsy in 16 weeks post-vaccination.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Narcoleptics exposed to A/H1N1 vaccine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Arepanrix vaccine</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      HLA typing
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The study population includes persons more than 6 months of age residing in the province of
        Quebec.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with symptoms of narcolepsy with onset during the period between January 1st,
             2009 and December 31, 2010.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects younger than 6 months of age
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Months</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jacques Montplaisir, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Sacre-Coeur Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Sacre-Coeur Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H4J 1C5</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Montplaisir J, Petit D, Quinn MJ, Ouakki M, Deceuninck G, Desautels A, Mignot E, De Wals P. Risk of narcolepsy associated with inactivated adjuvanted (AS03) A/H1N1 (2009) pandemic influenza vaccine in Quebec. PLoS One. 2014 Sep 29;9(9):e108489. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0108489. eCollection 2014.</citation>
    <PMID>25264897</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 12, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 13, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 14, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>November 28, 2014</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>March 19, 2015</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">April 2, 2015</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 12, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 12, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 14, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Hopital du Sacre-Coeur de Montreal</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jacques Montplaisir</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director of the Sleep Clinic, Sacre-Coeur Hospital</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Cataplexy</keyword>
  <keyword>MSLT</keyword>
  <keyword>Hypocretin</keyword>
  <keyword>HLA typing</keyword>
  <keyword>Polysomnography</keyword>
  <keyword>A/H1N1 vaccine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Narcolepsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Narcoleptic Subjects Exposed to Vaccine</title>
          <description>Exposed narcoleptic subjects (vaccinated and onset of narcolepsy is after vaccine administration)</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Unexposed Narcoleptic Subjects</title>
          <description>Unexposed narcoleptic subjects (not vaccinated or vaccinated after the onset of symptoms)</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="8"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="16"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="8"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="16"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Exposed Narcoleptic Subjects</title>
          <description>Exposed (vaccinated and onset of narcolepsy is after vaccine administration) narcoleptic subjects to adjuvanted A/H1N1 vaccine</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Unexposed Narcoleptic Subjects</title>
          <description>Unexposed (non-vaccinated or vaccinated after onset of symptoms) narcoleptic subjects to adjuvanted A/H1N1 vaccine</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="8"/>
            <count group_id="B2" value="16"/>
            <count group_id="B3" value="24"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="7"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="13"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="9"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="11"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="19.9" lower_limit="6" upper_limit="50"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="26.1" lower_limit="8" upper_limit="55"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="24.0" lower_limit="6" upper_limit="55"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="6"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="12"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="10"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="12"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Canada</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="8"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B2" value="16"/>
                    <measurement group_id="B3" value="24"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Incidence of Narcolepsy Among Narcoleptic Subjects Exposed or Unexposed to Vaccine</title>
        <description>Incidence rates will be computed by comparing narcolepsy incidence rates in exposed and non-exposed subjects. Comparison of narcolepsy incidence rates in the period prior to vaccine administration and pseudo-vaccine administration will be used to test the comparability of exposed and non-exposed group.</description>
        <time_frame>Narcolepsy onset during the 16-week post-vaccination period.</time_frame>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Exposed Narcoleptic Subjects</title>
            <description>Exposed (vaccinated and onset of narcolepsy is post-vaccination) narcoleptic subjects
Intervention: Adjuvanted (ASO3) A/H1N1 pandemic vaccine Arepanrix.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Unexposed Narcoleptic Subjects</title>
            <description>Unexposed narcoleptic subjects (non-vaccinated or vaccinated after onset of symptoms)</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Incidence of Narcolepsy Among Narcoleptic Subjects Exposed or Unexposed to Vaccine</title>
          <description>Incidence rates will be computed by comparing narcolepsy incidence rates in exposed and non-exposed subjects. Comparison of narcolepsy incidence rates in the period prior to vaccine administration and pseudo-vaccine administration will be used to test the comparability of exposed and non-exposed group.</description>
          <units>events per 100,000 person-years</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="8"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="16"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="0.52"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="0.11"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <param_type>Incidence-rate difference</param_type>
            <param_value>0.41</param_value>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <estimate_desc>Difference between the incidence rate of exposed-to-vaccine cases (0.52) and that of unexposed cases (0.11) is 0.41 per 100,000 persons-years</estimate_desc>
          </analysis>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
              <group_id>O2</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <param_type>Risk Ratio (RR)</param_type>
            <param_value>4.32</param_value>
            <ci_percent>95</ci_percent>
            <ci_n_sides>2-Sided</ci_n_sides>
            <ci_lower_limit>1.5</ci_lower_limit>
            <ci_upper_limit>11.12</ci_upper_limit>
            <estimate_desc>Risk of developing narcolepsy if exposed to H1N1 vaccination (using the 16-week post-vaccination period as reference).</estimate_desc>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>Adverse Events were not reported since this was a retrospective study (only onset of narcolepsy, which is the main outcome, was reported)</time_frame>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Exposed Narcoleptic Subjects</title>
          <description>Exposed narcoleptic subjects (vaccinated and onset of narcolepsy is post-vaccination)
Intervention: Adjuvanted (ASO3) A/H1N1 pandemic vaccine (Arepanrix)</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Unexposed Narcoleptic Subjects</title>
          <description>Unexposed narcoleptic subjects (non-vaccinated or vaccinated after onset of symptoms)</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="0"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="0"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="0"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="0"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>Small number of subjects; Impossibility to completely exclude a confounding effect of the A/H1N1 virus infection itself.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. Jacques Montplaisir</name_or_title>
      <organization>Center for Advanced Research in Sleep Medicine</organization>
      <phone>514-388-2693</phone>
      <email>jy.montplaisir@umontreal.ca</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

