<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01394835</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AAT-02</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01394835</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of Inhaled Alpha-1 Antitrypsin in Preventing Bronchiolitis Obliterable Syndrome in Lung Transplant Recipients</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rabin Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rabin Medical Center</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Bronchiolitis obliterable syndrome (BOS) is the most common cause of death in long-term
      survivors after lung transplantation and refractory to most interventions. Many risk factor
      for BOS were identified in previous studies such as acute cellular rejection, lymphocytic
      bronchiolitis, cytomegalovirus (CMV) and non-CMV respiratory infections, injury to the
      allograft or airways, Primary graft dysfunction, HLA mismatching, and organizing pneumonia.
      (Belperio JA. et al.). Neutrophils and their released products may be involved in the
      development of BOS. Neutrophilia was repeatedly observed in the bronchoalveolar lavage fluid
      of patients after lung transplantation. In addition, infiltration of neutrophils into the
      bronchial epithelium has been detected in patients with higher degrees of active airway
      damage. Neutrophils are capable of causing severe damage to the lung tissue by releasing
      toxic proteases and reactive oxygen species if not counterbalanced by the antiprotease/
      antioxidant screen of the lung. Based on this background, a causal relationship between
      neutrophilia and the development of BOS has been proposed. (Hirsch J. et al.) Detection of
      unopposed Neutrophile elastase (NE) activity in BAL appears to correlate with poor outcome
      due to refractory BOS. Unopposed NE in these subjects may not only serve as a marker of
      evolving graft dysfunction but also participate in damaging the airways of the allograft and
      inhibit adequate bacterial clearance. Prevention of neutrophil sequestration or inhibition of
      NE may prevent or attenuate airway damage and improve bacterial clearance mechanisms. (Nutley
      D et al.) These data demonstrate the importance of neutrophils and unopposed NE in the
      pathogenesis of BOS and call for new approach to prevent or modulate BOS targeting this
      mechanism.

      AAT is the main inhibitor of neutrophil elastase in the lower airways and patients with AAT
      deficiency have low concentrations of the protein in this region of the lung. This explains
      the proteinase/antiproteinase theory of the development of emphysema in deficient patients in
      which the amount of elastase released in the lung exceeds the amount of AAT. The net result
      is persistence of elastase activity leading to lung destruction and the pathological changes
      of emphysema. (Abusriwil H. et al.) The administration of the AAT is to address
      proteinase/antiproteinase imbalance.

      Administration of AAT will help to prevent further destruction of the lung architecture and
      reduce the inflammatory dysregulation that causes pulmonary dysfunction. It is expected that
      by attacking a specific and previously untreated key component part of the pathophysiological
      cycle of BOS, AAT therapy would decrease the prevalence of BOS in lung transplant recipients
      and prolong life expectancy of these patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>September 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical diagnosis of BOS according to Estenne M. et al Treatment of lung transplant recipients to prevent BOS Clinical diagnosis of BOS according to Estenne M. et al. Adverse events and conc</measure>
    <time_frame>12 Month</time_frame>
    <description>Adverse events and concomitant medication recording and follow up. Safety/tolerability parameters at baseline (Day #1) will be compared with values generated at the following visits every 6 weeks (+/- 10 days).
At all visits, AEs and concomitant medications will be recorded. Additionally, the study coordinator will check occurrence of AE and concomitant medications by a telephone visit</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in lung function test</measure>
    <time_frame>12 month</time_frame>
    <description>Change in lung function FEV%, FEV1, FVC Baseline (Day #1) values of FEV1 and FVC (and FEV%) will be compared to the following visits every 6 weeks (+/- 10 days).
Incidence of Acute cellular rejection. Incidence of respiratory infection leading to antibiotics administration according to the decision of the investigator.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Lung Transplantation</condition>
  <condition>Bronchiolitis Obliterable Syndrome</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alpha -1 Antitrypsin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alpha -1 Antitrypsin</intervention_name>
    <description>Inhalation twice daily of 160mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Alpha -1 Antitrypsin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alpha-1 Antitrypsin</intervention_name>
    <description>Inhalation twice daily .Dosage 160mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Alpha -1 Antitrypsin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>AAT</intervention_name>
    <description>Inhalation twice daily' 160mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Alpha -1 Antitrypsin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:• Patients aged ≥18 years

          -  Signature of informed consent

          -  Lung transplant recipient in the past 6 months.

          -  Stable concomitant therapy &gt;2 weeks prior to visit 1

          -  Non-tobacco user of any kind

          -  No significant abnormalities in serum hematology, serum chemistry to the Principal
             Investigator's judgment((Hg&gt;8g/dL ,Creatinine&lt;2mg/dl,Liver enzymes&lt;3*ULN)

          -  Non-pregnant, non-lactating female subjects, whose screening pregnancy test is
             negative and who are using contraceptive methods deemed reliable by the investigator,
             or who are more than 5 years post-menopausal or surgically sterilized or whose
             way-of-life excludes sexual activity.

          -  Sexually active female subjects of child-bearing potential, as well as male subjects,
             must use a medically acceptable effective contraceptive method (for male - method such
             us condoms; for female - methods such as oral contraceptive medication used for at
             least two weeks before study start, or a combination of any two of the following:
             diaphragm, cervical cap, condom or spermicide), before study start and throughout the
             entire duration of the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:• Diagnosis of BOS with according to Estenne M. et al.

          -  Hospitalization within 1 month before study entry, not due to an airway disease

          -  Severe liver cirrhosis with ascites

          -  Hypersplenism

          -  Grade III/IV esophageal varices;

          -  Active pulmonary exacerbation within the 4 weeks prior to screening

          -  History of massive hemoptysis: greater than 200 cc in a 24 hour period

          -  Pregnancy or breastfeeding

          -  Any serious or active medical or psychiatric illness which, in the opinion of the
             investigator, would interfere with patient treatment, assessment, or compliance with
             the protocol.

          -  Fever at the time of the start of first (day #1) inhalation (oral temperature &gt;38ºC)

          -  Evidence of uncontrolled hypertension

          -  Pulse &gt;120/min (prior to study drug administration)

          -  Any serious malignancy except for basal and squamous (scaly or plate-like) cell skin
             cancer within the previous 3 years prior to study start

          -  Receipt of exogenous AAT within the last 6 months

          -  Previous enrolment in this study (subject can not be enrolled twice into the study)

          -  Evidence of congestive heart failure or other clinically significant cardiovascular
             conditions: myocardial infarction during the last year, arrhythmia requiring drug
             treatment during the last year, uncontrolled hypertension

          -  Current smoker (someone who has smoked within 4 weeks prior to screening)

          -  Subjects with an additional clinically significant inter-current illness (beside lung
             disease) (e.g., cardiac, hepatic, renal, endocrine, respiratory, neurological,
             hematological, neoplastic, immunological and skeletal) that the investigator
             determines that it could interfere with the safety or other assessments of this study

          -  Any evidence of alcohol abuse or history of abuse of illegal and/or legally prescribed
             drugs such as barbiturates, benzodiazepines, amphetamines, cocaine, opioids, and
             cannabinoids

          -  Being a sexually active female of child-bearing age without adequate contraception

          -  Any other factor that, in the opinion of the investigator, would prevent the subject
             form complying with the requirements of the protocol
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mordechai R Kramer, M.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Rabin Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Mordechai Kramer, MD</last_name>
    <phone>972-39377221</phone>
    <email>kremerm@clalit.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Liora Yehoshua, Bsc</last_name>
    <phone>972-39377214</phone>
    <email>lioray@clalit.org.il</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>July 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 5, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 13, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 14, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 13, 2011</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 13, 2011</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 14, 2011</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Mordechai Kramer MD</name_title>
    <organization>Rabin Medical Center</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Patient after lung transplantation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Syndrome</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bronchiolitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alpha 1-Antitrypsin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Protein C Inhibitor</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

