<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01398579</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E\10\703</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01398579</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Comparison Between Probe-based Confocal Laser Endomicroscopy, White-light Endoscopy and Virtual Chromoendoscopy</brief_title>
  <acronym>pCLE-GCEP</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Comparison Between Probe-based Confocal Laser Endomicroscopy, White-light Endoscopy and Virtual Chromoendoscopy for the Diagnosis of Gastric Pre-neoplastic and Neoplastic Lesions (pCLE-GCEP)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National University Hospital, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Medical Research Council (NMRC), Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National University Hospital, Singapore</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators hypothesis that

        1. clinical applicability and overall diagnostic sensitivity and specificity of pCLE for
           diagnosing gastric preneoplastic and neoplastic lesions is acceptable

        2. pCLE, as compared to white-light endoscopy (WLE), AFI and magnifying NBI has higher
           sensitivity and specificity for the diagnosing gastric pre-neoplastic and neoplastic
           lesions
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Patients will be recruited from an ongoing study - Gastric Cancer Epidemiology, Clinical and
      Genetic Programme Cohort Study (GCEP). GCEP is a prospective cohort study aiming to enroll
      3,000 Singapore- Chinese subjects aged &gt;50 years, and offers screening by endoscopy and
      systematic follow-up for a minimum of 5 years. 20 patients will be randomized into two
      groups. All of them will be examined using four different endoscopy imaging technologies by
      one trained specialist. 10 patients will be in group A and another 10 patients will be in
      group B. Group A: WLE followed by AFI followed by NBI followed by pCLE. Group B: WLE followed
      by NBI followed by AFI followed by pCLE. The difference between two groups is the sequence of
      two endoscopy imaging modes - AFI and NBI. Diagnosis made during NBI and AFI must be made
      based on pre-defined criteria, and should not be influenced by the preceding imaging
      modality. To control for the possible bias on the third imaging modality caused by influence
      from the preceding imaging modality, patients are randomized to receive NBI before AFI or AFI
      before NBI.

      Endoscopic diagnosis will be made for each suspected lesion with every imaging modality. The
      biopsy of lesions will be taken after pCLE examination is completed and sent for histology.
      In the absence of suspicious lesions, the area of examination will be as follows (as stated
      in main GCEP protocol):

        -  A1- lesser curvature of the antrum, within 2-3cm of the pylorus.

        -  A2- greater curvature of the antrum, within 2-3cm of the pylorus.

        -  IA- incisura angularis.

        -  B1- lesser curvature of the corpus, 4cm proximal to the angulus.

        -  B2- middle portion of the greater curvature of the corpus, 8cm from the cardia.

        -  Cardia (C) - within 1 cm below the OGJ (defined as the point where gastric folds
           disappear).

      The results will be compared with the gold standard diagnosis - histopathology diagnosis. The
      sensitivity and specificity for each imaging tool will be calculated accordingly.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>September 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Participant)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of accurate endoscopic diagnosis made with pCLE compared with histopathology diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>An average of 1 week for which histology report will be out for comparison</time_frame>
    <description>For each patient, the minimum sites of pCLE examination must consist of 2 sites at antrum, 1 site at the incisura, 2 sites at the corpus, and 1 site at the cardia. When suspicious lesions are present, more sites of pCLE examination will be allowed. Each site of pCLE examination will be biopsied and sent for histology.The pCLE examination will be video recorded and interpretation will be done independently on a separate day from the endoscopy day.The analysis will be by per biopsy site matched with corresponding video sequence</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Intestinal Metaplasia</condition>
  <condition>Intestinal Dysplasia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group A: WLE followed by AFI followed by NBI followed by pCLE.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Group B: WLE followed by NBI followed by AFI followed by pCLE.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Gastroscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>20 patients will be randomized into two groups. All of them will be examined using four different endoscopy imaging technologies by one trained specialist. 10 patients will be in group A and another 10 patients will be in group B.
Group A: WLE followed by AFI followed by NBI followed by pCLE. Group B: WLE followed by NBI followed by AFI followed by pCLE.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group A</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group B</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>OGD</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  The subject is Chinese

          -  The subject is greater than 50 years of age

          -  The subject satisfies one or more of the following criteria:

               -  has (had) a history of dyspepsia of at least 4 weeks or more. Dyspeptic symptoms
                  include bloating, epigastric discomfort and early satiety

               -  has a family history of gastric cancer

               -  has a medical condition for which an OGD is indicated.

          -  Has past history of intestinal metaplasia or dysplasia

          -  The subject must have personally signed and dated the patient informed consent form
             indicating that he/she has been informed of all pertinent aspects of the study.

          -  The subject must be willing and able to comply with scheduled visits and other study
             procedures

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients who cannot undergo gastroscopies

          -  have a personal history of stomach cancer or surgery

          -  any disabling illnesses

          -  are pregnant or breast-feeding

          -  have bronchial asthma or a known allergy to fluorescein

          -  have renal impairment with serum creatinine above the upper limit of normal

          -  have uncorrected coagulopathy or severe thrombocytopenia precluding biopsy

          -  unable to provide informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>90 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Khek Yu Ho, Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NUHS</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Lee Guan Lim</last_name>
    <phone>67795555</phone>
    <email>lee_guan_lim@nuhs.edu.sg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Singapore</city>
        <zip>119974</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Lee Guan Lim, Doctor</last_name>
      <phone>67795555</phone>
      <email>lee_guan_lim@nuhs.edu.sg</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Uedo N, Ishihara R, Iishi H, Yamamoto S, Yamamoto S, Yamada T, Imanaka K, Takeuchi Y, Higashino K, Ishiguro S, Tatsuta M. A new method of diagnosing gastric intestinal metaplasia: narrow-band imaging with magnifying endoscopy. Endoscopy. 2006 Aug;38(8):819-24.</citation>
    <PMID>17001572</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eisen GM, Baron TH, Dominitz JA, Faigel DO, Goldstein JL, Johanson JF, Mallery JS, Raddawi HM, Vargo JJ 2nd, Waring JP, Fanelli RD, Wheeler-Harbough J; American Society for Gastrointestinal Endoscopy. Complications of upper GI endoscopy. Gastrointest Endosc. 2002 Jun;55(7):784-93.</citation>
    <PMID>12024128</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Pohl H, Rösch T, Vieth M, Koch M, Becker V, Anders M, Khalifa AC, Meining A. Miniprobe confocal laser microscopy for the detection of invisible neoplasia in patients with Barrett's oesophagus. Gut. 2008 Dec;57(12):1648-53. doi: 10.1136/gut.2008.157461. Epub 2008 Aug 28.</citation>
    <PMID>18755886</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Buchner AM, Shahid MW, Heckman MG, Krishna M, Ghabril M, Hasan M, Crook JE, Gomez V, Raimondo M, Woodward T, Wolfsen HC, Wallace MB. Comparison of probe-based confocal laser endomicroscopy with virtual chromoendoscopy for classification of colon polyps. Gastroenterology. 2010 Mar;138(3):834-42. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2009.10.053. Epub 2009 Nov 10.</citation>
    <PMID>19909747</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Inoue T, Uedo N, Ishihara R, Kawaguchi T, Kawada N, Chatani R, Kizu T, Tamai C, Takeuchi Y, Higashino K, Iishi H, Tatsuta M, Tomita Y, Tóth E. Autofluorescence imaging videoendoscopy in the diagnosis of chronic atrophic fundal gastritis. J Gastroenterol. 2010;45(1):45-51. doi: 10.1007/s00535-009-0150-7. Epub 2009 Oct 30.</citation>
    <PMID>19876586</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kato M, Kaise M, Yonezawa J, Yoshida Y, Tajiri H. Autofluorescence endoscopy versus conventional white light endoscopy for the detection of superficial gastric neoplasia: a prospective comparative study. Endoscopy. 2007 Nov;39(11):937-41.</citation>
    <PMID>18008201</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Ezoe Y, Muto M, Horimatsu T, Minashi K, Yano T, Sano Y, Chiba T, Ohtsu A. Magnifying narrow-band imaging versus magnifying white-light imaging for the differential diagnosis of gastric small depressive lesions: a prospective study. Gastrointest Endosc. 2010 Mar;71(3):477-84. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2009.10.036.</citation>
    <PMID>20189506</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yao K, Iwashita A, Tanabe H, Nishimata N, Nagahama T, Maki S, Takaki Y, Hirai F, Hisabe T, Nishimura T, Matsui T. White opaque substance within superficial elevated gastric neoplasia as visualized by magnification endoscopy with narrow-band imaging: a new optical sign for differentiating between adenoma and carcinoma. Gastrointest Endosc. 2008 Sep;68(3):574-80. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2008.04.011. Epub 2008 Jul 26.</citation>
    <PMID>18656862</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kato M, Kaise M, Yonezawa J, Goda K, Toyoizumi H, Yoshimura N, Yoshida Y, Kawamura M, Tajiri H. Trimodal imaging endoscopy may improve diagnostic accuracy of early gastric neoplasia: a feasibility study. Gastrointest Endosc. 2009 Nov;70(5):899-906. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2009.03.1171.</citation>
    <PMID>19595318</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wallace MB, Meining A, Canto MI, Fockens P, Miehlke S, Roesch T, Lightdale CJ, Pohl H, Carr-Locke D, Löhr M, Coron E, Filoche B, Giovannini M, Moreau J, Schmidt C, Kiesslich R. The safety of intravenous fluorescein for confocal laser endomicroscopy in the gastrointestinal tract. Aliment Pharmacol Ther. 2010 Mar;31(5):548-52. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2036.2009.04207.x. Epub 2009 Nov 30.</citation>
    <PMID>20002025</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>August 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 26, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 19, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 20, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 10, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 10, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 12, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>intestinal metaplasia</keyword>
  <keyword>dysplasia</keyword>
  <keyword>probe-based confocal endomicroscopy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Metaplasia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

