<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00428207</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>06-18</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00428207</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Glycemic Stability of Insulin Aspart Versus Insulin Lispro in Insulin Pump Therapy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Glycemic Stability of Insulin Aspart Versus Insulin Lispro in Insulin Pump Therapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Joslin Diabetes Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Novo Nordisk A/S</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Joslin Diabetes Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine:

        1. whether there is a difference between insulin aspart and insulin lispro in continuous
           insulin pump therapy

        2. whether duration of the insulin infusion set placement effect blood sugar control if the
           infusion set is in place for longer then 72-96 hours
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Insulin instability in pump infusion systems can result in unexplained hyperglycemia in
      patients on continuous subcutaneous insulin infusion (CSII) therapy. We have noted that some
      pump patients develop glycemic instability with use of insulin lispro, and that this resolves
      with change to insulin aspart. Several patients using lispro have reported noting a whitish
      precipitate in the infusion set, and in two cases we have examined the catheters and
      confirmed biochemically that this precipitate was insulin. Furthermore, in vitro studies
      indicate that insulin aspart is more resistant to isoelectric precipitation than insulin
      lispro. Although it has been rare for patients to notice a visible precipitate in the pump
      catheter, there is a subset of patients using lispro who have noted that their blood glucose
      levels will tend to rise 2 or more days after the insertion of a new pump infusion system.
      These findings mirror bench studies showing that the relative stability differences between
      aspart and lispro in pump infusion systems becomes more apparent over time.

      The endpoints examined in previous randomized clinical trials comparing aspart and lispro
      were not directed specifically at assessing the effect of insulin type on glycemic stability.
      In these previous studies, pump infusion systems were changed every 48 hours whereas most
      pump patients routinely replace their infusion catheters only every 72-96 hours; this
      discrepancy may account for the failure of these trials to demonstrate the difference in the
      stability of insulin aspart and lispro that has been noted in clinical practice.

      This investigator-initiated clinical trial is intended to assess the safety and efficacy of
      CSII with insulin aspart compared to insulin lispro with use of pump infusion catheters for
      up to 96 hours.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Treatment differences not detected with 7 point fingerstick monitoring
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>February 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glycemic Stability</measure>
    <time_frame>48 to 96 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Glycemic stability will be assessed by MAGE (Mean Amplitude of Glycemic Excursion)(5), M value of Schlichtkrull, standard deviation &amp; coefficient of variation using 7 point finger stick blood glucose measurements performed 48-96 hours after insertion of the pump infusion catheter. Data collected 48 to 72 hours post-catheter insertion will be analyzed separately from the data collected 72 to 96 hours post-catheter insertion. The mean of the measurements taken throughout the study will be used for calculation of the primary endpoint.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of Catheter Change</measure>
    <time_frame>48 to 96 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Recorded by the subjects who will use a checklist to document the reason for the catheter change (routine, insufficient insulin in infusion system, unexplained hyperglycemia, catheter site irritation, suspected occlusion/kinking of catheter, loosening of catheter.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">4</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Insulin Aspart Versus Insulin Lispro</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Insulin aspart will be used for diabetes management, and will be delivered continuously, subcutaneously using a pump for a four week period. Insulin aspart doses will be adjusted by the principal investigator as needed to maintain glycemic control. Insulin dose adjustments will vary from patient to patient based on the carbohydrate consumption, level of physical activity, and fingerstick monitoring results SMBG (7 times per day). SMBG results collected during this four week period will be compared to the SMBG results collected while participant uses alternative treatment (insulin Lispro).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Insulin Lispro Versus Insulin Aspart</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Insulin lispro will be used for diabetes management, and will be delivered continuously, subcutaneously using a pump for a four week period. Dose will be adjusted as needed to maintain glycemic control. Insulin dose adjustments will vary from patient to patient based on the carbohydrate consumption, level of physical activity, and fingerstick monitoring results SMBG (7 times per day). SMBG results collected during this four week period will be compared to the SMBG results collected while participant uses alternative treatment (insulin Aspart).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Insulin Aspart versus Insulin Lispro</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be randomly assigned to insulin aspart versus insulin lispro via random number generation. Half of the patients will begin with insulin aspart, and then will be crossed over to insulin lispro. The insulin sequence will be reversed for the other half of the patients.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Insulin Aspart Versus Insulin Lispro</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>NovoLog</other_name>
    <other_name>NovoRapid</other_name>
    <other_name>Humalog</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Insulin Lispro versus Insulin Aspart</intervention_name>
    <description>Subjects will be randomly assigned to insulin lispro versus insulin aspart via random number generation. Half of the patients will begin with insulin lispro, and then will be crossed over to insulin aspart. The insulin sequence will be reversed for the other half of the patients.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Insulin Lispro Versus Insulin Aspart</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Humalog</other_name>
    <other_name>NovoRapid</other_name>
    <other_name>Novolog</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Type 1 diabetes treated with CSII at least 3 months.

          -  Males and females, &gt; 18 years but &lt; 75 years old.

          -  Hemoglobin A1c ≤ 8.0 % at measurement taken at week 0 (screening visit).

          -  Duration of diabetes ≥ 12 months.

          -  Willingness to perform self-blood glucose monitoring several times/day.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous insulin precipitation in pump infusion catheters.

          -  Daily insulin requirements &gt; 25% of pump reservoir capacity. (This would preclude the
             subject from using the pump infusion system for more than 3 days).

          -  Use of an insulin pump that does not have a downloadable record of basal and bolus
             doses.

          -  Known or suspected allergy to trial products.

          -  Pregnancy, breast-feeding, intention to become pregnant or inadequate contraception
             measures.

          -  Known or suspected alcohol or drug abuse.

          -  Impaired renal function with creatinine ≥ 1.7 mg/dl.

          -  Pronounced catheter site scarring.

          -  Chronic use of drugs that may influence glycemic control (e.g. steroids).

          -  Any other significant concomitant disease that would interfere with participation in
             and completion of the trial.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Howard A Wolpert, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Joslin Diabetes Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Joslin Diabetes Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02215</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 25, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 25, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 29, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>April 17, 2013</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>April 25, 2017</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Actual">May 30, 2017</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 25, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 25, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 30, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>type 1 diabetes, insulin pump therapy, glycemic stability</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Insulin, Globin Zinc</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin degludec, insulin aspart drug combination</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin Aspart</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin, Long-Acting</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Insulin Lispro</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Around November 2006, patients were recruited through physician recommendations and also patient lists from clinic. Patients were sent letters asking them to be in the study. Study visits took place in the clinic.</recruitment_details>
      <pre_assignment_details>This was a crossover study, so patients all began in one arm and were then switched to the other arm.</pre_assignment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Insulin Lispro</title>
          <description>Subjects will be randomly assigned to one of the two insulins (insulin Lispro) by the statistician working in the study via random number generation.
First Intervention- four weeks using insulin Aspart in the pump. Subjects will use their current basal rates, insulin to carb ratios and correction factors to dose insulin.
After the four weeks of the first intervention have been completed subjects will be switched to insulin lispro, for the second intervention period.
The sequence of interventions may be reversed due to random assignment of treatment.</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Insulin Aspart</title>
          <description>Subjects will be randomly assigned to one of the two insulins (insulin Aspart) by the statistician working in the study via random number generation.
First Intervention- four weeks using insulin Aspart in the pump. Subjects will use their current basal rates, insulin to carb ratios and correction factors to dose insulin.
After the four weeks of the first intervention have been completed subjects will be switched to insulin lispro, for the second intervention period.
The sequence of interventions may be reversed due to random assignment of treatment.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="2"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="0"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="0"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <population>All study participants received both interventions.</population>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Insulin Aspart Versus Insulin Lispro</title>
          <description>insulin Aspart versus insulin Lispro : Subjects will be randomly assigned to one of the two insulins by the statistician working in the study via random number generation. Half of the patients will begin with insulin aspart, and then will be crossed over to insulin lispro. The insulin sequence will be reversed for the other half of the patients.
Period 1: four weeks using insulin aspart in the pump, followed by Period 2: four weeks using insulin lispro in the pump, or vice versa depending on randomization.
insulin pump :</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="4"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>&lt;=18 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Between 18 and 65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>&gt;=65 years</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="63.25" spread="10.8"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Sex: Female, Male</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Count of Participants</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <title>Female</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
                <category>
                  <title>Male</title>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="1"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>United States</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="4"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Glycemic Stability</title>
        <description>Glycemic stability will be assessed by MAGE (Mean Amplitude of Glycemic Excursion)(5), M value of Schlichtkrull, standard deviation &amp; coefficient of variation using 7 point finger stick blood glucose measurements performed 48-96 hours after insertion of the pump infusion catheter. Data collected 48 to 72 hours post-catheter insertion will be analyzed separately from the data collected 72 to 96 hours post-catheter insertion. The mean of the measurements taken throughout the study will be used for calculation of the primary endpoint.</description>
        <time_frame>48 to 96 hours</time_frame>
        <population>Data collection was &quot;incomplete/insufficient&quot; and therefore endpoint could not could not be evaluated</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Insulin Aspart Versus Insulin Lispro</title>
            <description>Insulin aspart will be used for diabetes management, and will be delivered continuously, subcutaneously using a pump for a four week period. Insulin aspart doses will be adjusted by the principal investigator as needed to maintain glycemic control. Insulin dose adjustments will vary from patient to patient based on the carbohydrate consumption, level of physical activity, and fingerstick monitoring results SMBG (7 times per day). SMBG results collected during this four week period will be compared to the SMBG results collected while participant uses alternative treatment (insulin Lispro).
Insulin Aspart versus Insulin Lispro: Subjects will be randomly assigned to insulin aspart versus insulin lispro via random number generation. Half of the patients will begin with insulin aspart, and then will be crossed over to insulin lispro. The insulin sequence will be reversed for the other half of the patients.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Insulin Lispro Versus Insulin Aspart</title>
            <description>Insulin lispro will be used for diabetes management, and will be delivered continuously, subcutaneously using a pump for a four week period. Dose will be adjusted as needed to maintain glycemic control. Insulin dose adjustments will vary from patient to patient based on the carbohydrate consumption, level of physical activity, and fingerstick monitoring results SMBG (7 times per day). SMBG results collected during this four week period will be compared to the SMBG results collected while participant uses alternative treatment (insulin Aspart).
Insulin Lispro versus Insulin Aspart: Subjects will be randomly assigned to insulin lispro versus insulin aspart via random number generation. Half of the patients will begin with insulin lispro, and then will be crossed over to insulin aspart. The insulin sequence will be reversed for the other half of the patients.</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Glycemic Stability</title>
          <description>Glycemic stability will be assessed by MAGE (Mean Amplitude of Glycemic Excursion)(5), M value of Schlichtkrull, standard deviation &amp; coefficient of variation using 7 point finger stick blood glucose measurements performed 48-96 hours after insertion of the pump infusion catheter. Data collected 48 to 72 hours post-catheter insertion will be analyzed separately from the data collected 72 to 96 hours post-catheter insertion. The mean of the measurements taken throughout the study will be used for calculation of the primary endpoint.</description>
          <population>Data collection was &quot;incomplete/insufficient&quot; and therefore endpoint could not could not be evaluated</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Frequency of Catheter Change</title>
        <description>Recorded by the subjects who will use a checklist to document the reason for the catheter change (routine, insufficient insulin in infusion system, unexplained hyperglycemia, catheter site irritation, suspected occlusion/kinking of catheter, loosening of catheter.</description>
        <time_frame>48 to 96 hours</time_frame>
        <population>Data collection was incomplete/insufficient and therefore end points could not be evaluated for this assessment.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Insulin Aspart Versus Insulin Lispro</title>
            <description>insulin Aspart versus insulin Lispro : Subjects will be randomly assigned to one of the two insulins by the statistician working in the study via random number generation. Half of the patients will begin with insulin aspart, and then will be crossed over to insulin lispro. The insulin sequence will be reversed for the other half of the patients.
Period 1: four weeks using insulin aspart in the pump, followed by Period 2: four weeks using insulin lispro in the pump, or vice versa depending on randomization.
insulin pump :</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Frequency of Catheter Change</title>
          <description>Recorded by the subjects who will use a checklist to document the reason for the catheter change (routine, insufficient insulin in infusion system, unexplained hyperglycemia, catheter site irritation, suspected occlusion/kinking of catheter, loosening of catheter.</description>
          <population>Data collection was incomplete/insufficient and therefore end points could not be evaluated for this assessment.</population>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="0"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>4 Week study treatment period</time_frame>
      <desc>Adverse Events will be 'self-reported' by study participants at each study visit in addition to potential AEs observed by the investigator on the study participant's study diary (logbook).</desc>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Insulin Aspart Versus Insulin Lispro</title>
          <description>insulin Aspart versus insulin Lispro : Subjects will be randomly assigned to one of the two insulins by the statistician working in the study via random number generation. Half of the patients will begin with insulin aspart, and then will be crossed over to insulin lispro. The insulin sequence will be reversed for the other half of the patients.
Period 1: four weeks using insulin aspart in the pump, followed by Period 2: four weeks using insulin lispro in the pump, or vice versa depending on randomization.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, all-cause mortality</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="4"/>
              </event>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="4"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="4"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <limitations_and_caveats>The 7 point fingerstick blood glucose profile was not sensitive enough to detect differences in the treatments.</limitations_and_caveats>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Howard Wolpert, MD</name_or_title>
      <organization>Joslin Diabetes Center</organization>
      <phone>6173092665</phone>
      <email>howard.wolpert@joslin.harvard.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

