<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00425152</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>NSABP C-04</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U10CA012027</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>NCOG-NSABP-C-04</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00425152</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Fluorouracil and Leucovorin and/or Levamisole After Surgery In Treating Patients With Dukes' B Or Dukes' C Colon Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Clinical Trial to Assess the Relative Efficacy of 5-FU + Leucovorin, 5-FU + Levamisole, and 5-FU + Leucovorin + Levamisole in Patients With Dukes' B and C Carcinoma of the Colon</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>NSABP Foundation Inc</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Northern California Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>NSABP Foundation Inc</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as fluorouracil, work in different ways to stop
      the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing.
      Leucovorin may help fluorouracil kill more tumor cells. Biological therapies, such as
      levamisole, may interfere with the growth of tumor cells and slow the growth of solid tumors.
      It is not yet known whether fluorouracil is more effective when given together with
      leucovorin and/or levamisole after surgery in treating colon cancer.

      PURPOSE: This randomized phase III trial is studying giving fluorouracil together with
      leucovorin to see how well it works compared with giving fluorouracil together with
      levamisole, or giving fluorouracil together with leucovorin and levamisole after surgery in
      treating patients with Dukes' B or Dukes' C colon cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES: I. Compare, in a Phase III setting, disease-free survival and overall survival of
      patients who have undergone potentially curative resection of Dukes' B or C carcinoma of the
      colon randomly assigned to adjuvant therapy with 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin vs.
      5-fluorouracil/levamisole vs. 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin/levamisole.

      OUTLINE: Randomized study. Arm I: Single-agent Chemotherapy with Drug Modulation.
      5-Fluorouracil, 5-FU, NSC-19893; with Leucovorin calcium, Citrovorum Factor, CF, NSC-3590.
      Arm II: Single-agent Chemotherapy with Drug Modulation plus Biological Response Modifier
      Therapy. 5-FU; with CF; plus Levamisole, LEV, NSC-177023. Arm III: Single-agent Chemotherapy
      plus Biological Response Modifier Therapy. 5-FU; plus LEV.

      PROJECTED ACCRUAL: 1,800 evaluable patients will be accrued over about 3 years; an additional
      2 years will be required before final analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 1989</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2004</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 1998</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">2151</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>fluorouracil</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>leucovorin calcium</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>levamisole hydrochloride</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS: See General Eligibility Criteria

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS: See General Eligibility Criteria
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Norman Wolmark, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Allegheny Cancer Center at Allegheny General Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert W. Carlson, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wilkinson NW, Yothers G, Lopa S, Costantino JP, Petrelli NJ, Wolmark N. Long-term survival results of surgery alone versus surgery plus 5-fluorouracil and leucovorin for stage II and stage III colon cancer: pooled analysis of NSABP C-01 through C-05. A baseline from which to compare modern adjuvant trials. Ann Surg Oncol. 2010 Apr;17(4):959-66. doi: 10.1245/s10434-009-0881-y.</citation>
    <PMID>20082144</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim GP, Colangelo LH, Wieand HS, Paik S, Kirsch IR, Wolmark N, Allegra CJ; National Cancer Institute. Prognostic and predictive roles of high-degree microsatellite instability in colon cancer: a National Cancer Institute-National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project Collaborative Study. J Clin Oncol. 2007 Mar 1;25(7):767-72. Epub 2007 Jan 16.</citation>
    <PMID>17228023</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dignam JJ, Polite BN, Yothers G, Raich P, Colangelo L, O'Connell MJ, Wolmark N. Body mass index and outcomes in patients who receive adjuvant chemotherapy for colon cancer. J Natl Cancer Inst. 2006 Nov 15;98(22):1647-54.</citation>
    <PMID>17105987</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang SJ, Zamboni BA, Wieand HS, et al.: Conditional survival for patients with colon cancer: an analysis of National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project (NSABP) trials C-03 through C-06. [Abstract] J Clin Oncol 24 (Suppl 18): A-6005, 302s, 2006.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kim GP, Colangelo L, Wieand H, et al.: Prognostic and predictive roles of high-degree microsatellite instability (MSI-H) in colon cancer: National Cancer Institute (NCI)-National Surgical Adjuvant Bowel Project (NSABP) collaborative study. [Abstract] American Society of Clinical Oncology 2005 Gastrointestinal Cancers Symposium, 27-29 January 2005, Miami, Florida. A-227, 2005.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allegra CJ, Paik S, Colangelo LH, Parr AL, Kirsch I, Kim G, Klein P, Johnston PG, Wolmark N, Wieand HS. Prognostic value of thymidylate synthase, Ki-67, and p53 in patients with Dukes' B and C colon cancer: a National Cancer Institute-National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project collaborative study. J Clin Oncol. 2003 Jan 15;21(2):241-50.</citation>
    <PMID>12525515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolmark N, Colangelo L, Wieand S. National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project trials in colon cancer. Semin Oncol. 2001 Feb;28(1 Suppl 1):9-13.</citation>
    <PMID>11273592</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dignam JJ, Colangelo L, Tian W, Jones J, Smith R, Wickerham DL, Wolmark N. Outcomes among African-Americans and Caucasians in colon cancer adjuvant therapy trials: findings from the National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project. J Natl Cancer Inst. 1999 Nov 17;91(22):1933-40.</citation>
    <PMID>10564677</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mamounas E, Wieand S, Wolmark N, Bear HD, Atkins JN, Song K, Jones J, Rockette H. Comparative efficacy of adjuvant chemotherapy in patients with Dukes' B versus Dukes' C colon cancer: results from four National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project adjuvant studies (C-01, C-02, C-03, and C-04). J Clin Oncol. 1999 May;17(5):1349-55.</citation>
    <PMID>10334518</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wolmark N, Rockette H, Mamounas E, Jones J, Wieand S, Wickerham DL, Bear HD, Atkins JN, Dimitrov NV, Glass AG, Fisher ER, Fisher B. Clinical trial to assess the relative efficacy of fluorouracil and leucovorin, fluorouracil and levamisole, and fluorouracil, leucovorin, and levamisole in patients with Dukes' B and C carcinoma of the colon: results from National Surgical Adjuvant Breast and Bowel Project C-04. J Clin Oncol. 1999 Nov;17(11):3553-9.</citation>
    <PMID>10550154</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wolmark N, Rockette H, Mamounas EP, et al.: The relative efficacy of 5-FU + leucovorin (FU-LV), 5-FU + levamisole (FU-LEV), and 5-FU + leucovorin + levamisole (FU-LV-LEV) in patients with Dukes' B and C carcinoma of the colon: first report of NSABP C-04. [Abstract] Proceedings of the American Society of Clinical Oncology 15: A460, 205a, 1996.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 18, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 18, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 22, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 5, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 5, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 8, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Norman Wolmark, MD</name_title>
    <organization>NSABP Foundation, Inc.</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stage II colon cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III colon cancer</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fluorouracil</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levamisole</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Levoleucovorin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

