<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00429039</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>01.0082</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2000-66</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00429039</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Accelerate Immune System Recovery Following Stem Cell Transplantation</brief_title>
  <official_title>LLME Treated Cellular Immunotherapy Following T-cell Depleted Allogeneic Heamtopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation for Acceleration of Immune Reconstitution</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sidney Kimmel Cancer Center at Thomas Jefferson University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Thomas Jefferson University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine if pre-treating donor lymphocytes with an
      investigational drug known as L-leucyl-L-leucine methyl ester (LLME, prior to donor
      lymphocyte infusion (DLI) will improve the recovery of the immune system following stem cell
      transplant.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      If you agree to participate in this research study you will be evaluated during the 4th-6th
      week after your transplant to determine the number of CD4 cells in your circulation and to
      determine that your body has eliminated all of the immune suppressing medicines used around
      the time of your transplant. This will be performed by studying the cells from two tubes of
      blood. Thereafter, blood cells will be obtained from your donor (the same donor as used for
      the transplant). These cells from the donor will be treated with LLME in the laboratory. The
      cells will then be washed to eliminate the LLME, counted, and the desired number will be
      administered to you by transfusion.

      Four to six weeks later, you will have additional blood drawn (2-3 teaspoons) to determine
      the number of CD4 cells in your blood. If the number is below 100, you will be given another
      transfusion of LLME treated cells, but you will receive a larger number of cells. Above 100
      CD4 cells, the risk of infections appears to decrease. This will be repeated every 8 weeks
      provided that you and your donor remain willing to continue until one of three things
      happens. The three things that would cause us to stop further DLI would be: (1) you develop a
      CD4 count of over 100, (2) you develop evidence of GVHD, or (3) we reach the maximum
      practical number of cells which your donor could provide.

      Your donor will also be reevaluated by medical history, physical examination, and blood tests
      to ensure that he/she remains healthy and can undergo the cell donation procedure safely. He
      or she will donate the first doses of white cells by drawing a small amount of blood. Later
      donations, if necessary, will be collected in a manner that is very similar to how platelets
      are normally collected from volunteer donors by the blood bank. The manner in which the
      transfusions are given will be similar to that in which you have received red blood cell and
      platelet transfusions in the past.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Low accrual.
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>September 2000</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2007</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">21</enrollment>
  <condition>ALLOGENEIC HEMATOPOIETIC STEM CELL TRANSPLANTATION</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>L-leucyl-L-leucine methyl ester (LLME)</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  To be treated on this study, patients must have recently undergone a T-cell depleted
             allogeneic bone marrow or peripheral blood stem cell transplant from an HLA-matched
             sibling donor, an HLA matched unrelated donor, or an HLA partially matched (single
             antigen mismatched, two antigen mismatched, or haplodisparate) donor. Patients will be
             counseled and will sign informed consent for this study prior to their transplant. Our
             intention is to analyze the effectiveness of LLME treated DLI (Donor Lymphocyte
             Infusion) on an intent to treat basis. To proceed with this therapy after HSCT,
             patients must meet the other selection criteria below at the time of first DLI.
             Additionally, discussion prior to transplant helps present the patient (and donor) a
             picture of the proposed therapy in its entirety, rather than in piecemeal fashion. A
             patient or donor's unwillingness to participate in this study will in no way affect
             their eligibility for transplant therapy at our center.

          -  At the time of initial DLI therapy, patients must be between 28 and 42 days post
             allogeneic HSCT or between 28 and 42 days after the last dose of ATG if that agent was
             used after the transplant as part of their graft rejection prophylaxis. They must also
             meet the following criteria during the week prior to first infusion:

          -  Patients must have achieved primary engraftment with an absolute neutrophil count of
             at least 1000 per l for 3 consecutive days.

          -  Patients must have a CD4+ lymphocyte count of less than 200 per l. An absolute
             lymphocyte count of less than 200 per l will be taken as prime facie evidence that the
             CD4+ lymphocyte count meets this criteria.

          -  Patients may not exhibit overt hematologic manifestations of relapse or persistent
             disease. Evidence of recurrent/persistent disease based primarily on flow cytometry,
             cytogenetics, chimerism analysis, or other molecular studies does not by itself
             represent grounds for exclusion.

          -  Patients must be 16 years of age or older. There is no upper age limit for this study.

          -  Patients must not be pregnant.

          -  Patients must not have any documented graft-versus-host disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Neal Flomenberg, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Thomas Jefferson University, Department of Medical Oncology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.KimmelCancerCenter.org</url>
    <description>Kimmel Cancer Center at Thomas Jefferson University</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 29, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 29, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 31, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 19, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 19, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 21, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

