<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02796378</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>LIFESTAT - Exercise study</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02796378</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Living With Statins - Interventional Exercise Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>LIFESTAT</acronym>
  <official_title>Living With Statins - The Impact of Cholesterol Lowering Drugs on Health, Lifestyle and Well-being</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Copenhagen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Copenhagen</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background. Statins are cholesterol lowering drugs that are prescribed to lower the risk of
      cardio-vascular diseases. The use of statins has increased markedly and it is now one of the
      most prescribed drugs in the world. More than 600,000 people in Denmark are taking statins on
      a daily basis, approximately 40 % of these are taking the medication without having any other
      risk factors for cardio-vascular diseases than elevated blood-cholesterol i.e. they are in
      primary prevention.

      Statins are not without side effects and studies have shown that there is an elevated risk of
      developing diabetes when taking statins. This has led to an increased debate about the use of
      statins in primary prevention. Furthermore a large meta-analysis has shown that to prevent
      one event of cardio-vascular disease, it is necessary to treat 200 people for 3-5 years.
      These data suggest that more conservative use of statins to prevent CVD in otherwise healthy
      individuals at low risk for future CVD may be warranted.

      Other side effects of statins are muscle myalgia, muscle cramps and fatigue which potentially
      can prevent a physically active lifestyle. The biomedical background of these side effects is
      not fully elucidated but it has been shown that there is a link to decreasing levels of an
      important enzyme, Q10, which plays a role in muscle energy metabolism.

      Hypothesis

      The overarching research question is: why does statin treatment cause muscle pain? Does
      statin treatment impair (or even prohibit) physical exercise training? Furthermore the
      following questions will be investigated:

      A. Does statin treatment cause:

        1. Decreased muscle strength?

        2. Skeletal muscle inflammation?

        3. Decreased mitochondrial respiratory function? B. Abnormal glucose homeostasis?

      Re question A &amp; B: If so, can physical training counteract this effect of statin treatment?
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      Hypercholesterolemia and statin use in Denmark

      Simvastatin is the most commonly prescribed statin, a class of drugs that inhibit
      hydroxyl-methyl-glutaryl (HMG) coenzyme A reductase, and thereby blocking biosynthesis of
      cholesterol in the liver. Simvastatin is prescribed for individuals with elevated low-density
      lipoprotein cholesterol (LDL-C) and/or total cholesterol, because these clinical parameters
      are viewed as a risk factor for cardiovascular-disease (CVD), even in the absence of other
      health problems or risk factors, such as previous myocardial infarction, diabetes or
      hypertension.

      Approximately 40% of the prescriptions for statins are issued for primary prevention of
      elevated cholesterol by general practitioners to patients without bodily symptoms or signs.
      Only the &quot;cholesterol number&quot; makes the risk of heart attack and stroke visible. The lack of
      symptoms is likely to be of importance for patients' adherence to treatment as is adverse
      effects. A number of factors, such as information in mass media and changes in daily life,
      may affect the decision to take the treatment

      Treatment guidelines for hypercholesterolemia:

      The guidelines indicate preventive treatment with statins is appropriate in individuals with
      &gt;10% predicted risk of a major vascular event within 5 years, while, some, but not all
      opinion-leaders advocate a 5% threshold. Nevertheless, statin therapy failed to reduce
      all-cause mortality in a meta-study of 65,229 patients without CVD, some of whom had
      diabetes. Similarly, a Cochrane review analysis, which included some studies in which more
      than 10% of the patients had history of CVD, showed only 0.5% reduction in all-cause
      mortality, indicating that for every 200 patients taking statins daily for 5 years, 1 death
      would be prevented. These data suggest that more conservative use of statins to prevent CVD
      in otherwise healthy individuals at low risk for future CVD may be warranted.

      The downside:

      Rhabdomyolysis (skeletal muscle cell death) is an infrequent but serious side-effect of
      statin use, that can on rare occasion lead to acute renal failure and death (i.e., 1.5 deaths
      per 106 prescriptions). Statin use is much more frequently associated with muscle
      dysfunction, including myalgia (muscle pain), cramps, and weakness. The reported incidence of
      myalgia varies from 1% (pharmaceutical company reports) to as high as 75% in statin-treated
      athletes. Mild to severe myalgia is a strong disincentive to regular exercise, and because
      regular exercise is one of the critical life-style approaches to preventing CVD and reducing
      blood cholesterol, this is a significant down-side of statin use. Regular exercise is also
      effective in preventing and treating obesity and type 2 diabetes, which themselves are risk
      factors for CVD.

      The mechanism behind the myalgia is not known. However, the investigators behind this study
      has recently demonstrated that muscle mitochondrial function is impaired with statin
      treatment and the Q10 protein may play a key role in this. In addition, the statins also
      negatively affect the glucose tolerance, increasing the risk of type 2 diabetes.

      Research questions:

      The overarching research question is: why does statin treatment cause muscle pain? Does
      statin treatment impair (or even prohibit) physical exercise training? Furthermore the
      following questions will be investigated:

      A. Does statin treatment cause:

        1. Decreased muscle strength?

        2. Skeletal muscle inflammation?

        3. Decreased mitochondrial respiratory function? B. Abnormal glucose homeostasis?

      Re question A &amp; B: If so, can physical training counteract this effect of statin treatment?

      Methodology:

      Cohort

      Patients that fulfil defined inclusion and exclusion criteria will be recruited from General
      Practice clinics in Copenhagen and news paper advertisements. The vast majority of these
      patients are being assessed on basis of the HeartScore risk estimation system that offers
      direct estimation of the ten-year risk of fatal cardiovascular disease in a format suited to
      the constraints of clinical practice. A staggered recruitment will be implemented.

      30 men (age: 40-70 years; BMI: 25-35 kg/m2) before initiation of a statin treatment as
      primary prevention are recruited. No other risk factors for CVD except elevated total
      cholesterol (&gt;6 mmol/l) and/or elevated LDL cholesterol (&gt;3,5 mmol/l) and mild hypertension
      (&lt;160/100 mm Hg) must be present.

      The patients will be allocated (randomization by drawing a lot) to one of three groups:

        -  Physical exercise training and Simvastatin 40 mg/day and Q10 placebo

        -  Physical exercise training and Simvastatin 40 mg/day and Q10 400 mg/day supplementation

        -  Physical exercise training, Simvastatin placebo and Q10 placebo

      The intervention period is 8 weeks with a series of experimental days before and after.

      Experimental days (identical before and after the interventions):

      Information day: health examination, ECG and Maximal oxygen uptake take (VO2 max).

      Day 1 (overnight fasting, approximately 5 hours):

        -  Dual energy x-ray absorptiometry (DXA) scan (body composition and body fat).

        -  Oral glucose tolerance test + score questionnaire for muscle pain/discomfort (incl.
           Visual Analog Scale)

        -  Isokinetic strength and Rate of Force Development (PowerRig and KinCom dynamometer).

        -  Repeated VO2-max-test

      Day 2 (overnight fasting approximately 7 hours):

        -  Muscle biopsy, vastus lateralis

        -  2 step Euglycemic, hyperinsulinaemic clamp.

      Training programme All training is supervised and takes place at the department. The training
      is aerobic, bicycle ergometer training (45 min/session at 60-70% of VO2max) three times a
      week for 8 weeks.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical performance measured by VO2-max</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in physical performance measured by VO2-max (mlO2/min/kgBW) in the three different intervention groups.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Myalgia measured by VAS</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in potential myalgia, measured by visual analog scale (VAS) between the three different intervention groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in muscle strength measured by KinCom dynamometer and PowerRig</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in muscle strength between the three different intervention groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in glucose metabolism measured by hyperinsulinemic euglycemic clamp</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in glucose metabolism between the three different intervention groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Difference in mitochondrial function measured by respirometry</measure>
    <time_frame>8 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Difference in mitochondrial function between the three different intervention groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Disease</condition>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Training+Simvastatin+Q10-placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Training+Simvastatin+Q10-placebo. 8 Weeks of exercise training on a bicycle ergometer three times a week and 40 mg of Simvastatin pr day and Q10-placebo.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Training+Simvastatin-placebo+Q10-placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Training+Simvastatin-placebo+Q10-placebo. 8 Weeks of exercise training on a bicycle ergometer three times a week, Simvastatin-placebo and Q10-placebo.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Training+Simvastatin+Q10</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Training+Simvastatin+Q10. 8 Weeks of exercise training on a bicycle ergometer three times a week and 40 mg of Simvastatin pr day in combination with 400 mg of oral supplementation with Q10.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Training+Simvastatin+Q10-placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>8 weeks of exercise training on a bycycle ergometer 3 times/week combined with Simvastatin 40 mg/day and Q10-placebo.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Training+Simvastatin+Q10-placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Simvastatin KRKA</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Training+Simvastatin-placebo+Q10-placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>8 weeks of exercise training on a bycycle ergometer 3 times/week combined with Simvastatin-placebo and Q10-placebo.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Training+Simvastatin-placebo+Q10-placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Training+Simvastatin+Q10</intervention_name>
    <description>8 weeks of exercise training on a bycycle ergometer 3 times/week combined with Simvastatin 40 mg/day and Q10 400 mg/day.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Training+Simvastatin+Q10</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Simvastatin KRKA</other_name>
    <other_name>Bioquinone Q10</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Elevated blood-cholesterol

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Cholesterol-lowering drugs

          -  Diabetes Mellitus

          -  Cardiovascular disease such as arrythmia, ischaemic heart disease.

          -  Musculoskeletal disorders preventing the subject to perform physical training

          -  Mental disorders preventing the subject to understand the project description.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Flemming Dela, MD, MDSci</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Copenhagen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Flemming Dela, MD, MDSci</last_name>
    <email>fdela@sund.ku.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Copenhagen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <zip>2200</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Anja B Kuhlman, MD</last_name>
      <email>anjabk@sund.ku.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Flemming Dela, MD, DMSci</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Boushel R, Gnaiger E, Schjerling P, Skovbro M, Kraunsøe R, Dela F. Patients with type 2 diabetes have normal mitochondrial function in skeletal muscle. Diabetologia. 2007 Apr;50(4):790-6. Epub 2007 Feb 15.</citation>
    <PMID>17334651</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ebrahim S, Casas JP. Statins for all by the age of 50 years? Lancet. 2012 Aug 11;380(9841):545-7. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60694-1. Epub 2012 May 17.</citation>
    <PMID>22607823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larsen S, Hey-Mogensen M, Rabøl R, Stride N, Helge JW, Dela F. The influence of age and aerobic fitness: effects on mitochondrial respiration in skeletal muscle. Acta Physiol (Oxf). 2012 Jul;205(3):423-32. doi: 10.1111/j.1748-1716.2012.02408.x. Epub 2012 Feb 11.</citation>
    <PMID>22212519</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larsen S, Nielsen J, Hansen CN, Nielsen LB, Wibrand F, Stride N, Schroder HD, Boushel R, Helge JW, Dela F, Hey-Mogensen M. Biomarkers of mitochondrial content in skeletal muscle of healthy young human subjects. J Physiol. 2012 Jul 15;590(14):3349-60. doi: 10.1113/jphysiol.2012.230185. Epub 2012 May 14.</citation>
    <PMID>22586215</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larsen S, Stride N, Hey-Mogensen M, Hansen CN, Andersen JL, Madsbad S, Worm D, Helge JW, Dela F. Increased mitochondrial substrate sensitivity in skeletal muscle of patients with type 2 diabetes. Diabetologia. 2011 Jun;54(6):1427-36. doi: 10.1007/s00125-011-2098-4. Epub 2011 Mar 18.</citation>
    <PMID>21424396</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Larsen S, Stride N, Hey-Mogensen M, Hansen CN, Bang LE, Bundgaard H, Nielsen LB, Helge JW, Dela F. Simvastatin effects on skeletal muscle: relation to decreased mitochondrial function and glucose intolerance. J Am Coll Cardiol. 2013 Jan 8;61(1):44-53. doi: 10.1016/j.jacc.2012.09.036.</citation>
    <PMID>23287371</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Singh P, Kohr D, Kaps M, Blaes F. Skeletal muscle cell MHC I expression: implications for statin-induced myopathy. Muscle Nerve. 2010 Feb;41(2):179-84. doi: 10.1002/mus.21479.</citation>
    <PMID>19813190</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cholesterol Treatment Trialists' (CTT) Collaborators, Mihaylova B, Emberson J, Blackwell L, Keech A, Simes J, Barnes EH, Voysey M, Gray A, Collins R, Baigent C. The effects of lowering LDL cholesterol with statin therapy in people at low risk of vascular disease: meta-analysis of individual data from 27 randomised trials. Lancet. 2012 Aug 11;380(9841):581-90. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60367-5. Epub 2012 May 17.</citation>
    <PMID>22607822</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Parker BA, Thompson PD. Effect of statins on skeletal muscle: exercise, myopathy, and muscle outcomes. Exerc Sport Sci Rev. 2012 Oct;40(4):188-94. Review. Erratum in: Exerc Sport Sci Rev. 2013 Jan;41(1):71.</citation>
    <PMID>23000957</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Perk J, De Backer G, Gohlke H, Graham I, Reiner Z, Verschuren WM, Albus C, Benlian P, Boysen G, Cifkova R, Deaton C, Ebrahim S, Fisher M, Germanò G, Hobbs R, Hoes A, Karadeniz S, Mezzani A, Prescott E, Ryden L, Scherer M, Syvanne M, Scholte Op Reimer WJ, Vrints C, Wood D, Zamorano JL, Zannad F; Comitato per Linee Guida Pratiche (CPG) dell'ESC. [European Guidelines on Cardiovascular Disease Prevention in Clinical Practice (version 2012). The Fifth Joint Task Force of the European Society of Cardiology and other societies on cardiovascular disease prevention in clinical practice (constituted by representatives of nine societies and by invited experts)]. G Ital Cardiol (Rome). 2013 May;14(5):328-92. doi: 10.1714/1264.13964. Italian.</citation>
    <PMID>23612326</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ray KK, Seshasai SR, Erqou S, Sever P, Jukema JW, Ford I, Sattar N. Statins and all-cause mortality in high-risk primary prevention: a meta-analysis of 11 randomized controlled trials involving 65,229 participants. Arch Intern Med. 2010 Jun 28;170(12):1024-31. doi: 10.1001/archinternmed.2010.182. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20585067</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ridker PM, Pradhan A, MacFadyen JG, Libby P, Glynn RJ. Cardiovascular benefits and diabetes risks of statin therapy in primary prevention: an analysis from the JUPITER trial. Lancet. 2012 Aug 11;380(9841):565-71. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(12)61190-8.</citation>
    <PMID>22883507</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Taylor F, Ward K, Moore TH, Burke M, Davey Smith G, Casas JP, Ebrahim S. Statins for the primary prevention of cardiovascular disease. Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2011 Jan 19;(1):CD004816. doi: 10.1002/14651858.CD004816.pub4. Review. Update in: Cochrane Database Syst Rev. 2013;1:CD004816.</citation>
    <PMID>21249663</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 27, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 6, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 10, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 3, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 3, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 4, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Copenhagen</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Flemming Dela</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>physical activity</keyword>
  <keyword>statin therapy</keyword>
  <keyword>diabetes mellitus</keyword>
  <keyword>cardiovascular disease</keyword>
  <keyword>Q10-supplementation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Simvastatin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA Reductase Inhibitors</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coenzyme Q10</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

