<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02791711</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-HPNCL-09</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02791711</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Using Nasal Broadband Glasses in the Initial Management of Severe Bronchiolitis in Infants Admitted in ICU</brief_title>
  <acronym>HFNC</acronym>
  <official_title>Using Nasal Broadband Glasses HFNC (High Flow Nasal Cannula) in the Initial Management of Severe Bronchiolitis in Infants Admitted in ICU: Bicentric Observational Study on the 2013-2014 Epidemic</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fondation Lenval</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fondation Lenval</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim of this study is to evaluate the use of nasal broadband glasses HFNC (High Flow Nasal
      Cannula) in the initial management of severe bronchiolitis in infants admitted in ICU.

      Nasal HFNC can deliver warmed humidified gas through a nasal interface, greatly improving the
      safety and efficacy of administering O2. This device generates a continuous positive pressure
      in the airways, to reduce the work of breathing. The sealing absence of the HFNC at the nasal
      interface improves patient comfort and avoiding nasal trauma.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Bronchiolitis in infants is a common and potentially serious disease. It corresponds to an
      acute pulmonary disease and dyspnea usually viral (70 to 80% of Respiratory syncytial virus
      RSV in infants less than 1 year). It particularly affects infants under 2 years.

      The 2001 consensus conference and bronchiolitis 2006 on the management clarified the criteria
      for hospitalization and simplified therapeutic attitudes. These conferences have highlighted
      the importance of humidification, the nasopharyngeal desobstruction for less severe forms of
      oxygen therapy and for others. Recent literature has also shown that the use of noninvasive
      ventilation type CPAP (Continuous Positive Airway Pressure) nasal or broadband nasal glasses
      (HFNC: High Flow Nasal canula) in severe forms possible to reduce the work of breathing of
      children with severe bronchiolitis and their use in studies &quot;before / after&quot; was accompanied
      by a significant decrease in the use of invasive ventilation.

      The HFNC and nasal CPAP can deliver warmed humidified gas through a nasal interface, greatly
      improving the safety and efficacy of administering O2. These devices generate a continuous
      positive pressure in the airways, for decreasing the work of breathing. The sealing absence
      of the HFNC at the nasal interface improves patient comfort and avoiding nasal trauma,
      sometimes encountered with nasal CPAP interfaces.

      The HFNC is a simple, effective and safe, commonly used in severe bronchiolitis admitted in
      ICU (Intensive Care Unit). However instead of this technique is not yet well defined.

      The investigators assume that the use of HFNC in severe bronchiolitis in first line allows
      sufficient respiratory improvement to avoid recourse to other technical assistance
      ventilatory more binding.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of early success for the number of bronchiolitis who once admitted in the ICU and placed HFNC will not need another support ventilation mode after one hour of treatment (H1)</measure>
    <time_frame>after one hour of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>the number of children who once set HFNC at baseline Hour 0 will not need another breathing assistance technique After 1 hour H1 of treatment</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall success rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Comparaison between baseline Hour 0 and after 1 hour of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Number of children who will not need another technique while respiratory assistance throughout the ICU stay</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Predictive factors of failure of HFNC</measure>
    <time_frame>At baseline hour 0</time_frame>
    <description>Correlation of clinical and demographic data H0 to failure of HFNC</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The child's comfort HFNC</measure>
    <time_frame>comparison to H0, H1, H12</time_frame>
    <description>EDEN (pain scale and discomfort newborn) comfort Scores comparison to H0, H1, H12</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events in HFNC</measure>
    <time_frame>From baseline hour 0 to the end of hospitalization</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency and types of adverse events throughout the ICU hospitalization period</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Effectiveness of HFNC on reducing the work of breathing after 1 hour</measure>
    <time_frame>Comparaison between baseline Hour 0 and after 1 hour of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>H0 and H1 evaluation criteria for assessing the change in clinical status including respiratory work HFNC</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">33</enrollment>
  <condition>Bronchiolitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High Flow Nasal Cannula</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Use of High Flow Nasal Cannula</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High Flow Nasal Cannula</intervention_name>
    <description>Evaluation of the use of High Flow Nasal Cannula by biological marqers, questionnary of quality of use of HFNC by the physician, questionnary of evaluation of adverse events with HFNC</description>
    <arm_group_label>High Flow Nasal Cannula</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  In which the diagnosis of bronchiolitis is strongly suspected (1st or nth episode).
             Acute bronchiolitis is defined by the presence of respiratory distress (wheezing,
             crackles ausculatory, wrestling signs) or apnea can not be explained by another
             existing pathology in children with a clinical history of upper respiratory infection.

          -  Satisfactory at least 1 of the following severity criteria:

        EN&gt; 50 quiet, Trouble consciousness / hypotonia, Significant Apnea (with desaturation and /
        or bradycardia) Hypercapnic acidosis (pH &lt;7.3 and PCO2&gt; 55mmHg) SpO2 &lt;92% on room air

          -  Including the holders of parental authority / legal representative are informed of the
             study and expressed no opposition to the participation of their child.

          -  Affiliated with a social security scheme by one of the holders of parental authority /
             legal guardian

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Children with neuromuscular disease known heart or lung (even without decompensation)
             at the time of admission.

          -  Any vital distress, including respiratory or neurological justifying intubation or
             other emergency resuscitation gesture.

          -  Opposition to a parent / guardian to the participation of their children in the study.

          -  Desire to study withdrawal expressed by one of the holders of parental authority /
             legal guardian

          -  Voluntary or involuntary break current care protocol or research by the healthcare
             team.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>1 Year</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mickael AFANETTI, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fondation LENVAL - Hôpitaux Pédiatriques de Nice CHU-LENVAL</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Arnaud de Villeneuve - CHU de Montpellier</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montpellier</city>
        <zip>34295</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fondation LENVAL - Hôpitaux Pédiatriques de Nice CHU-LENVAL</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nice</city>
        <zip>06200</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 1, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 6, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 7, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 6, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 6, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 7, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Bronchiolitis</keyword>
  <keyword>Continuous Positive Airway Pressure</keyword>
  <keyword>HFNC</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bronchiolitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

