<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02791724</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EP28b_01</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02791724</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating a Novel Internet Intervention for Persons With Epilepsy and Depression</brief_title>
  <acronym>ENCODE</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluating a Novel Cognitive-Behavioral Online Depression Intervention for Persons With Epilepsy (Desiconnect): Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Gaia AG</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Universitätsklinikum Hamburg-Eppendorf</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Gaia AG</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The trial aims to evaluate the effectiveness of a novel internet intervention (Desiconnect),
      which was designed to introduce relevant cognitive-behavioral therapy (CBT) techniques to
      Persons with Epilepsy (PwE) and comorbid depression. Therefore, 200 PwE and a current
      depressive disorder (major depressive disorder or dysthymic disorder) will be recruited and
      randomized to two groups: (1) a control group, in which they may engage with any epilepsy
      treatment (Care-as-Usual, CAU) and receive access to Desiconnect after a delay of three
      months (i.e., CAU/wait list control group), or (2) to a treatment group that immediately
      receives six-month access to Desiconnect and may also use CAU. The primary outcome measure is
      the depression scale of the Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9), collected at three months
      post-baseline.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Depression is common among persons with epilepsy (PwE), affecting roughly one in three
      individuals, and its presence is associated with personal suffering, impaired quality of
      life, and worse prognosis. Despite the availability of effective treatments, depression is
      often overlooked and treated inadequately in PwE, in part because of concerns over drug
      interactions. Previous studies strongly suggest that cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) can
      help alleviate depression in PwE, but CBT is not always available to patients.
      Internet-administered psychological interventions are easily accessible and might complement
      antidepressant medication or psychotherapy, and preliminary evidence suggests that such
      interventions can be effective. However, no trial has yet examined whether a CBT-based
      internet intervention designed to meet the needs of PwE can achieve sustained reductions in
      depression and related symptoms, such as anxiety, when offered as adjunct to treatment as
      usual.

      The Internet-based intervention evaluated in this trial was designed with the aim of
      conveying evidence-based psychotherapeutic techniques, gleaned primarily from CBT, to PwE
      over a period of 180 days. The intervention focuses on identifying and challenging cognitions
      that trigger or sustain depression and anxiety, increasing activities that are likely to
      reduce depression and anxiety, practicing relaxation and stress management exercises and
      increasing mindfulness skills. The program is based on general CBT and other evidence-based
      psychotherapeutic techniques that have been shown to be helpful for patients suffering from
      depression (and ideally, that have been shown to be helpful among PwE). Furthermore, program
      content addresses other issues in disease self-management, including lifestyle habits (e.g.,
      nutrition, exercise) and medication adherence. The delivery and training of content is
      continuously individualized to match users' preferences and needs, based on responses within
      the program. The intervention is delivered via the Internet and protected by individually
      assigned passwords.

      This randomized controlled trial will include 200 participants with epilepsy and a current
      depressive disorder, along with currently at least moderately elevated depression.
      Participants will be recruited from various settings, including epilepsy treatment clinics,
      outpatient treatment centers, and Internet forums/groups. Methods such as newspaper articles,
      flyers, posters, and media articles or web-advertisements will be used to inform potential
      participants about the study (all material will be in German). Participants will be randomly
      assigned to either (1) a control group, in which they receive care as usual (CAU) and are
      given access to the internet intervention (Desiconnect) after a delay of 3 months (i.e.,
      CAU/Wait list control group), or (2) a treatment group that may also use CAU and in addition
      immediately receives six-month access to the novel, internet-administered intervention
      (Desiconnect). Measurements are collected online at pre-treatment (baseline, T0), three
      months (T1), six months (T2), and nine months (T3).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Severity of depressive symptoms, measured by Patient Health Questionnaire - 9 items (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 3 months (also assessed at 6 and 9 months post-baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report depression symptom severity measure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NDDIE (Neurological Disorders Depression Inventory for Epilepsy)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 3 months (also assessed at 6 and 9 months post-baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>Epilepsy-specific self-report measure of depression symptom severity</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>GAD-7 (Generalized Anxiety Disorder Questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 3 months (also assessed at 6 and 9 months post-baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report anxiety symptom severity measure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>DASS-21 (Depression and Anxiety Scales)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 3 months (also assessed at 6 and 9 months post-baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure of anxiety, depression, and stress symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>WSAS (Work and Social Adjustment Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>Change from baseline to 3 months (also assessed at 6 and 9 months post-baseline)</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure of depression-related psychosocial impairment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Subjective usefulness of the program</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Individually designed self-report items</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>INEP (Inventory for the Assessment of Negative Effects of Psychotherapy)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at 3 and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adapted self-report measure assessing potential negative effects of the Internet intervention</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>PESOS</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, 3, 6, and 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure of epilepsy symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>LSSS (Liverpool Seizure Severity Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, 3, 6, and 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure of epilepsy symptoms</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QOLIE-10 (Health-related Quality of Life)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, 3, 6, and 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure of health-related quality of life</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>ESMS (Epilepsy Self-Management Scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>Assessed at baseline, 3, 6, and 9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Self-report measure of epilepsy self-management practices</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <condition>Epilepsy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Desiconnect</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Desiconnect is an Internet-administered intervention developed for persons with epilepsy and elevated depression symptoms.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Care-as-Usual (CAU) / wait list</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In the CAU/wait list control group, participants are free to continue to engage with any treatment they require (i.e., CAU). However, they will receive access to Desiconnect three months post-baseline (i.e., wait list with respect to Desiconnect access).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Desiconnect</intervention_name>
    <description>Desiconnect is an Internet intervention for persons with epilepsy and elevated depression. Content is continuously adapted to patients' concerns and needs. Techniques to overcome depression (e.g., cognitive restructuring, behavioral activation) and to cope with anxiety symptoms (e.g., exposure, role of avoidance, mindfulness exercises) are conveyed in interactive sequences that are accompanied by audio recordings, illustrations, and worksheets. Topics covered also include coping with epilepsy symptoms, identifying and coping with seizure auras and triggers, and the role of nutrition and exercise. Patients are also prompted to regularly complete brief symptom severity self-monitoring questionnaires. Optional daily text messages with motivational content accompany the program. The program can be accessed for 180 days after registration.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Desiconnect</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>CAU</intervention_name>
    <description>Care as Usual</description>
    <arm_group_label>Desiconnect</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Care-as-Usual (CAU) / wait list</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age at least 18 years

          -  diagnosis of active epilepsy (that is, at least one epileptic seizure within the past
             10 years or taking antiseizure medicines within the past five years)

          -  current depressive disorder (either major depressive disorder or dysthymic disorder,
             as determined by telephone interview with the MINI Neuropsychiatric Interview)

          -  no current antidepressant medication, or current antidepressant medication but no
             changes in dosage for at least one month prior to study inclusion (medication changes
             after study inclusion are permitted, given the pragmatic design of the trial)

          -  currently at least moderate self-reported depressive symptom severity, as
             operationalized by a score of at least 10 on the PHQ-9, a cut-off score that has been
             well validated

          -  ability to speak and read German

          -  access to the internet and personal possession of an appropriate device on which the
             internet-based intervention can be used regularly (e.g., smartphone, computer, laptop)

          -  expressed motivation to participate in the trial and use an internet-based
             intervention to acquire skills and knowledge that may aid in the amelioration of
             depression symptoms

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  current psychotherapy

          -  other known major psychiatric disorder, such as bipolar disorder, schizophrenia or
             another psychotic disorder, or borderline personality disorder (based on the MINI
             interview)

          -  acute suicidality (that is, intention or plan to commit suicide, as assessed with the
             respective module of the MINI interview)

          -  newly prescribed antidepressant medication or change in antidepressant medication
             dosage in month prior to study inclusion
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Yvonne Nestoriuc, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf (UKE), Department of Psychosomatic Medicine and Psychotherapy</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Björn Meyer, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+494035105231</phone>
    <email>bjoern.meyer@gaia-group.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Tina Schwarzkopp, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <phone>+494035105231</phone>
    <email>tina.schwarzkopp@gaia-group.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Center Hamburg-Eppendorf (UKE), Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hamburg</city>
        <country>Germany</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Johanna Schröder, Ph.D.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Johanna Schröder, Ph.D.</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 1, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 3, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 7, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 3, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 3, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 7, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Epilepsy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Anonymized individual participant data shall be made available upon request for projects such as meta-analyses after completion of the study</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

