<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02793063</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BBD7702</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>U01TR001263</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02793063</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Osteogenesis Imperfecta (OI) Quality of Life Survey Pilot Project 2</brief_title>
  <official_title>Rare Diseases Clinical Research Network Brittle Bone Disorders Consortium Osteogenesis Imperfecta (OI) Quality of Life Survey Pilot Project 2</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of South Florida</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Rare Diseases Clinical Research Network</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of South Florida</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to explore the patient perspective of disease burden in
      Osteogenesis Imperfecta (OI). Participants will complete a web-based survey of questions
      which are usually administered within the Patient-Reported Outcome Measurement Information
      System (PROMIS) and provide feedback regarding the appropriateness of the questions for
      someone with OI.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Participants will be recruited through the RDCRN BBD Contact Registry. An email invitation
      will be sent to all RDCRN BBD Contact Registry participants that meet the inclusion criteria
      to complete the online PROMIS CAT instruments. The email invitation will contain a link to
      the informed consent form. Once participants have consented to the study, they will have
      access to the online instruments. Follow-up emails will be sent to participants that have not
      completed any of the instruments. Reminder emails will be sent to participants with partially
      completed instruments.

      Data will be collected and stored by the RDCRN DMCC at USF.

      Data from patients co-enrolled in the &quot;Longitudinal Study of Osteogenesis Imperfecta&quot; and the
      BBD RDCRN Contact Registry will be linked and compared. Additional disease specific
      information will be collected by the survey (e.g., information on OI type and diagnosis,
      height, number of fractures, concurrent medication use, utilization of any mobility aid,
      hearing aid, or other device that they may use.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 10, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 10, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Validated Computer Adaptive Testing (CAT) PROMIS instruments</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
    <description>An online assessment will be used to obtain responses for each instrument. Scores for each are norm-based with a mean of 50 and standard deviation of 10 based upon the general population. Calibration of the standard error (SE) surrounding the reported score is possible. Default setting of 0.30 will be used for standard error with the minimum number of questions per item of 4 and maximum number of questions 8, using the computer adapted testing structure of the PROMIS instruments. Lower maximum number than the default settings will be used to avoid too many questions being given to a respondent when they do not report a diminished quality of life on any dimension. With these settings, survey respondents will be administered an average of 4-5 items per instrument and the testing among patients with OI indicate that the whole assessment will typically take 15-30 minutes in most instances.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Osteogenesis Imperfecta</condition>
  <condition>Brittle Bone Disorders</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>BBD Consortium Contact Registrants</arm_group_label>
    <description>Osteogenesis Imperfecta patients who have self-registered at the Brittle Bone Disorders Consortium (BBD) Consortium Contact Registry, a web-based contact registry developed and supported by the Data Management and Coordinating Center (DMCC) for the Rare Diseases Clinical Research Consortium (RDCRN), located at the University of South Florida.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Web-based Survey</intervention_name>
    <description>This study will occur online. Participants will be asked to complete multiple surveys one time. Participants may receive study reminder emails to complete surveys. Participants will be able to complete the surveys all at once or in multiple sessions. Participants will have approximately 3 months to complete the surveys after consenting.</description>
    <arm_group_label>BBD Consortium Contact Registrants</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with Osteogenesis Imperfecta who are enrolled in the RDCRN BBD Contact Registry
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Enrollment in the RDCRN BBD Contact Registry English speaking Age 2 to adult

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability to provide informed consent Inability to complete instruments
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>2 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Krischer, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of South Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Laura Tosi, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Jeffrey Krischer, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of South Florida</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Laura Tois, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Research Institute</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of South Florida, Health Informatics Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tampa</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Richesson RL, Young K, Lloyd J, Adams T, Guillette H, Malloy J, Krischer JP. An automated communication system in a Contact Registry for persons with rare diseases: tools for retaining potential clinical research participants. AMIA Annu Symp Proc. 2007 Oct 11:1094.</citation>
    <PMID>18694191</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Richesson RL, Lee HS, Cuthbertson D, Lloyd J, Young K, Krischer JP. An automated communication system in a contact registry for persons with rare diseases: scalable tools for identifying and recruiting clinical research participants. Contemp Clin Trials. 2009 Jan;30(1):55-62. doi: 10.1016/j.cct.2008.09.002. Epub 2008 Sep 7.</citation>
    <PMID>18804556</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>March 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 26, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 2, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 8, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 6, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Brittle Bone</keyword>
  <keyword>Osteogenesis Imperfecta</keyword>
  <keyword>BBD</keyword>
  <keyword>OI</keyword>
  <keyword>Congenital Abnormalities</keyword>
  <keyword>Congenital Bone Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Lobstein Syndrome</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Osteogenesis Imperfecta</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bone Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Bone Diseases, Developmental</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

