<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02798172</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>20140508</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02798172</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effect of Alogliptin on Pulmonary Function in Obese Patients With Type 2 Diabetes Inadequately Controlled by Metformin Monotherapy</brief_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fourth People's Hospital of Shenyang</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fourth People's Hospital of Shenyang</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective: To observe the effect of alogliptin combined with metformin on pulmonary function
      in obese patients with type 2 diabetes inadequately controlled by metformin monotherapy (500
      mg, bid po, for at least 3 months), and evaluate its efficacy and safety.

      Method: After a 2-week screening period, adult patients (aged 36-72 years) entered a 4-week
      run-in/stabilization period. Then, patients were randomly assigned to either the intervention
      group (n=55) or control group (n=50) for 26 weeks. The patients in the control group were
      given metformin (1,000 mg, bid po) and the patients in the intervention group were given
      metformin (500 mg, bid po) combined with alogliptin (25 mg, qd po). All the patients received
      counseling about diet and exercise from a nutritionist during run-in and treatment periods.

      The primary endpoints were the between-group differences in the changes pulmonary function
      parameters [VC%, FVC%, FEV1%, PEF%, MVV%, TLC%, FEV1/FVC%, DLCO%, and DLCO/VA%] between
      pretherapy and posttreatment. The secondary endpoints were changes from baseline to week 26
      in HbA1c, FPG, 2hPG, HOMA-IR, WC, and BMI. The tertiary endpoints were the changes from
      baseline to week 26 in blood-fat (TC, HDL-C, LDL-C, and TG). The quartus endpoints were the
      changes from baseline to week 26 in SBP and DBP. The fifth endpoints were the changes from
      baseline to week 26 in oxidative/antioxidative parameters (ROS, MDA, SOD, and GSH-PX). In
      addition, safety endpoints were assessed (AEs, clinical laboratory tests, vital signs, and
      electrocardiographic readings).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Alogliptin was provided by Takeda Chemical industries Ltd in Japan, trade name: Nesina, 25
      mg/tablet. Metformin was provided by Bristol Myers Squibb in America, trade name: Glucophage,
      500 mg/tablet. Research kits for ROS, MDA, and SOD, GSH-PX were provided by Nanjing Jiancheng
      Bioengineering Institute in China. Research kits for TC, HDL-C, HDL-C, and TG were provided
      by were provided by Nanjing Jiancheng Bioengineering Institute in China. The spirometer used
      for pulmonary function tests was provided by Jaska Corporation in Japan, model number: HI-101
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary endpoints were changes from baseline to week 26 in pulmonary function parameters [VC%, FVC%, FEV1%, PEF%, MVV%, TLC%, FEV1/FVC%, DLCO%, and DLCO/VA%] between pretherapy and posttreatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The secondary endpoints were changes from baseline to week 26 in HbA1c in intervention group (n=44) and control group (n=37).</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The tertiary endpoints were the changes from baseline to week 26 in blood-fat (TC, HDL-C, LDL-C, and TG) in the intervention group (n=44) and control group (n=37).</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The fourth endpoints were the changes from baseline to week 26 in FPG, 2hPG in the intervention group (n=44) and control group (n=37).</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The fourth endpoints were the changes from baseline to week 26 in oxidative/antioxidative parameters (ROS, MDA, SOD, and GSH-PX) in the intervention group (n=44) and control group (n=37).</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>In addition, safety endpoints were assessed (AEs, clinical laboratory tests, vital signs, and electrocardiographic readings)</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>The changes of BMI from baseline to week 26 in intervention group (n=44) and control group (n=37).</measure>
    <time_frame>26 weeks</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">81</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Alogliptin+metformin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Alogliptin (alogliptin benzoate) is the most recent DPP-4 inhibitor; it entered the market in 2006. It is a potent and highly selective DPP-4 inhibitor with oral antidiabetic activity; Metformin is the most commonly prescribed first-line drug worldwide for the treatment of T2DM, it acts by decreasing both hepatic glucose production and intestinal glucose absorption, while improving insulin sensitivity, metformin as a safe and valid oral antidiabetic drug was recommended to the obese patients with a body mass index (BMI) &gt;30 kg/m2, it has some value in reducing or preventing weight gain and changes in metabolic parameters during treatment, and it can be combinated with other antidiabetic drug</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>metformin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Metformin is the most commonly prescribed first-line drug worldwide for the treatment of T2DM, it acts by decreasing both hepatic glucose production and intestinal glucose absorption, while improving insulin sensitivity, metformin as a safe and valid oral antidiabetic drug was recommended to the obese patients with a body mass index (BMI) &gt;30 kg/m2, it has some value in reducing or preventing weight gain and changes in metabolic parameters during treatment, and it can be combinated with other antidiabetic drug</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Alogliptin and Metformin</intervention_name>
    <description>The patients in the control group were given metformin (1,000 mg, bid po) and the patients in the intervention group were given metformin (500 mg, bid po) combined with alogliptin (25 mg, qd po)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Alogliptin+metformin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>metformin</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  1) Aged from 36 to 72 years of either gender; 2) BMI &gt;28.0 kg/m2, and WC &gt;90 cm
             (male), or WC &gt;85 cm (female); 3) The patients were diagnosed with T2DM and the
             serological outcome (7.0%&lt;HbA1c&lt;10.0%) did not reach the therapeutic targets and oral
             metformin monotherapy (500 mg, bid po, ≥3 months prior to screening); 4) No smoking
             history, pulmonary disease nor pulmonary infection within a fortnight; 5) Did not have
             hepatopathy, nephropathy and gastrointestinal disease; and 6) Likely to have good
             compliance and able to visit our hospital for periodic assessments.

        Exclusion Criteria:1) T1DM, gestation and lactation; 2) Renal inadequacy; 3) hypohepatia;
        4) Intensive care with insulin treatment; 5) Intolerance to alogliptin and metformin; 6)
        Heart failure; 7) Had received antidiabetic agents; 8) Antihypertensive drugs can not
        control the BP adequately or severe uncontrolled hypertension; 9) Cholesterol-lowering
        drugs can not control the blood-fat adequately; and 10) Use of weight loss drugs.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>36 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>72 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 30, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 8, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 14, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 8, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 8, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 14, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Fourth People's Hospital of Shenyang</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Jin-song Kuang</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Chief physician</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alogliptin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Metformin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

