<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02790905</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SMRU1503</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02790905</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Validating the Patient Health Questionnaire in Pregnant and Post-partum Migrant Women</brief_title>
  <official_title>Validating the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) and Refugee Health Screener-15(RHS-15) Questionnaires to Screen for Depression in Pregnant and Post-partum Migrant Women on the Thai-Myanmar Border</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Oxford</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Oxford</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The objective of this study is to validate the Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9) and the
      Refugee Health Screener-15 (RHS-15) screening tools for depression in pregnant and
      post-partum migrant women on the Thai-Myanmar border.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Mental illness affects a significant proportion of women during and after
      pregnancy. The most common form of mental illness is depression, which can manifest with
      symptoms such as sadness, loss of pleasure in activities, poor sleep, changes in appetite
      and, in severe cases, suicide. Depression during or after pregnancy can have profound effects
      on the mother, her family and wider society. Left untreated, depression can become chronic
      and recurrent and lead to reduced ability to work and provide care. Children of depressed
      mothers are at increased risk of poor growth, increased infections and delayed cognitive,
      behavioural and emotional development. Recognising maternal depression at an early stage and
      offering effective treatment such as counselling or anti-depressant medication is vital to
      helping women and minimising impacts on their families. To effectively diagnose depression, a
      variety of screening tools is available. However, psychometric properties vary across
      populations and contexts, and tools must be validated locally prior to use. This validation
      study will be based at the Shoklo Malaria Research Unit (SMRU), which has provided health
      services and conducted research in rural and disadvantaged populations living on the
      Thai-Myanmar border for nearly three decades.

      Research design: The study will be an observational, cross-sectional validation study. Women
      will be asked to complete two questionnaires and an interview.

      Study population: The study population will be women who are pregnant and post-partum (up to
      12 months) attending SMRU antenatal and postnatal clinics at Wang Pha, Mawker Tai and Maela.

      Method and technique (survey, interview, observation): The questionnaires will be translated
      into Burmese and Karen, and back-translated into English to ensure that semantics have been
      maintained. Pregnant and post-partum women attending antenatal clinics (ANC) and postnatal
      clinics (PNC) who volunteer to participate will be asked to provide consent. Participants
      will first be asked to complete two questionnaires: the PHQ-9 and RHS-15. These will be
      administered by a member of SMRU staff in Karen or Burmese. Participants will then be asked
      to attend a diagnostic interview conducted by the principal investigator with an interpreter.
      The principal investigator will be blinded to the results of the PHQ-9 and RHS-15 until
      completion of the interview.

      Anticipated outcomes: The outcomes of this validation study will be measures of validity,
      reliability, sensitivity, specificity, positive predictive value and negative predictive
      value for each of the screening tools (PHQ-9 and RHS-15).

      Potential value and significance: If the questionnaires are found to be valid in the local
      population they can be used as a routine screen for depression for all women attending
      antenatal and postnatal clinics at SMRU. Helping to identify women with depression will
      enable earlier treatment and minimise the impact of depression on her and her family.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 30, 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 30, 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Validity of Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>at enrollment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Validity of Refugee Health Screener-15 (RHS-15) questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>at enrollment</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reliability of Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>at enrollment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Reliability of Refugee Health Screener-15 (RHS-15) questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>at enrollment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity of Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>at enrollment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sensitivity of Refugee Health Screener-15 (RHS-15) questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>at enrollment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specificity of Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>at enrollment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Specificity of Refugee Health Screener-15 (RHS-15) questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>at enrollment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive predictive value for each of Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>at enrollment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Positive predictive value for each of Refugee Health Screener-15 (RHS-15) questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>at enrollment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Negative predictive value for each of Patient Health Questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)</measure>
    <time_frame>at enrollment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Negative predictive value for each of Refugee Health Screener-15 (RHS-15) questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>at enrollment</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">370</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Women who are pregnant (at any stage of pregnancy) and post-partum up to 12 months
        post-partum, aged 18 years or over, who are willing and able to participate.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women who are pregnant (at any stage of pregnancy) and post-partum (up to 12 months
             post-partum)

          -  Willing and able to give informed consent for participation in the study

          -  Aged 18 years or over

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Deemed by study staff to be acutely unwell and unable to participate

          -  Known mental illness and undergoing treatment/therapy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Shoklo Malaria Research Unit</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mae Sot</city>
        <state>Tak</state>
        <zip>63110</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 19, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 2, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 6, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 5, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 6, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pregnant and post-partum women</keyword>
  <keyword>Validation questionnaires</keyword>
  <keyword>Thai-Myanmar border</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

