<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02799576</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TFTammam</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>Ghada A. K</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02799576</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Curved Block Needle for the Infraclavicular Brachial Plexus Block</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Curved Block Needle for the Infraclavicular Brachial Plexus Block in Patients Undergoing Surgery Distal to the Elbow</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Suez Canal University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Suez Canal University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The investigators hypothesized that using the curved needle could facilitate the block
      placement and provide short procedure time. Aim of the work: The investigators will compare
      namely straight and curved block needle with in-plane needle insertion techniques for the
      infraclavicular brachial plexus nerve block (ICNB) regarding the block performance time.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Sometimes, there is a limited block needle access at the inferior edge of the clavicle while
      performing in- plane infraclavicular parasagittal blockade. This might present a challenge in
      manipulating and visualizing the block needle in easy way along its entire trajectory during
      the blockade. The curved block needle might have its positive impact on the capacity to
      control the block needle advancement relative to the target nerve.

      70 patients between the ages of 18 and 60 years with American Society of Anesthesiologists
      (ASA) physical status I- II, scheduled for elective surgery distal to the elbow will be
      enrolled in a prospective, comparative, randomized clinical study.

      Patients will be randomly assigned into two groups: C (n = 35), in whom US-guided single
      injection ICNB will be performed using a curved line needle; and S (n = 35), in whom
      US-guided ICNB will be performed using a straight line needle. All patients will be
      pre-medicated with oral diazepam (7.5 mg) 30 min before the procedure, and IV fentanyl (50
      ug) will be administered 5 minutes before placement of the block. Before the procedure, an IV
      access and standard monitoring of electrocardiogram (ECG), noninvasive blood pressure (NIBP),
      and peripheral oxygen saturation (SPO2) will be established.

      The ultrasound guided Infraclavicular brachial plexus block will be performed in the block
      room using a linear-array US probe (8-13 MHz). The ultrasound probe will be placed just below
      the lower edge of the clavicle and medial to the coracoid process (parasagittal orientation),
      with adjustment of depth, frequency and gain to spot the best view of the transverse axillary
      artery and its surrounding cords (short-axis view).

      After sterile skin preparation with chlorhexidine solution, local infiltration with 2 ml of
      lidocaine (10 mg/ml) will be made at the cephalad aspect of the ultrasound probe. A 10-cm,
      short-bevel block (straight or curved) needle will be attached to the nerve stimulator
      delivering a current of 1.2 mA ( milliampere) at a frequency of 2 Hz (Hertz), will be
      inserted in-plane just inferior to the clavicle.

      After eliciting the posterior cord motor response (finger or wrist extension) with a current
      intensity of ≤ 0.5 mA, correct needle-tip position will be confirmed by test injections with
      1 ml of 5 % dextrose solution. Then, thirty milliliters of local anesthetic mixture
      (lidocaine 10 mg/ml and bupivacaine 2.5 mg/ml) will be incrementally injected after careful
      aspiration. The goal is to ensuring a U-shaped distribution of anaesthetic solution with
      anterior displacement of the axillary artery.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Performance time</measure>
    <time_frame>12 min</time_frame>
    <description>The time to perform the Infraclavicular brachial nerve block. Performance time is defined as the sum of recognition time and local anesthetics injection time. Recognition time is defined as the time interval in seconds (s) from needle insertion to achievement of proper motor response. Local anesthetics injection time is defined as the time interval in seconds (s) between the achievement of motor response and the end of local anesthetics injection through the block needle</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of needle attempts to elicit proper motor response</measure>
    <time_frame>12 min</time_frame>
    <description>New attempt will be defined as needle reinsertions through separate skin puncture.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of needle redirections to elicit proper motor response</measure>
    <time_frame>12 min</time_frame>
    <description>Needle redirection will be defined as draw back and redirects the needle if no proper nerve response could be elicited.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Infraclavicular brachial nerve block success rate</measure>
    <time_frame>30 min after local anesthetics administration</time_frame>
    <description>The Infraclavicular brachial nerve block success will be assessed according to the adequacy of surgical anesthesia and is defined as complete loss of pinprick sensation within 30 min of anesthetic administration and if no supplementation (sedative or analgesic) is required during surgery. Partial block is defined as inadequate sensory blockade after 30 min of anesthetic administration. The supplementation (IV analgesic, rescue blocks or local infiltration) is required to complete the proposed surgery. Failed block is considered if general anesthesia is required to complete the proposed surgery.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>during surgical procedures</time_frame>
    <description>All patients will be asked to rate their discomfort during the block placement and tourniquet pain using the Verbal Rating Scale (VRS: 0 = no discomfort, 10 = the worst discomfort).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anesthesiologist satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>12 min</time_frame>
    <description>Level of anesthesiologist satisfaction for using different block needles will be evaluated using VRS (0, no satisfaction; 10, maximum satisfaction).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Intraoperative and in the first 48 post-operative hours</time_frame>
    <description>Incidence of adverse events and complications during and after the procedure will be also recorded. Complications, including hematoma, infection and neuropathies, will be recorded intraoperatively and in the first 48 post-operative hours.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">70</enrollment>
  <condition>Needle Track</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Curved needle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This will utilize the curved block needle of performance of regional block</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Traditional needle</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This will utilize the traditional block needle of performance of regional block</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Curved needle</intervention_name>
    <description>In this arm, the curved block needle will be used for regional blockade</description>
    <arm_group_label>Curved needle</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18 - 60 year old both sex, able to provide informed consent to participate, enrolled
             in elective surgery distal to the elbow, single procedure.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to consent to participate, known to have lidocaine or bupivacaine allergy, more
             than one procedure will be performed at the same setting, patients with local
             infections,neuropathies, coagulopathies,and history of chronic analgesic therapy,
             Obesity (body mass index ≥ 30 kg/m2),
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>60 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tarek F. Tammam, Prof.</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Suez Canal university,Faculty of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Suez canal University hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ismailia</city>
        <zip>41522</zip>
        <country>Egypt</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Egypt</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 6, 2016</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 9, 2016</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 15, 2016</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 17, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 17, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">October 19, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Suez Canal University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tarek F.Tammam</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof. of anesthesia and intensive care,faculty of medicine,Suez Canal University</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>Regional blockade</keyword>
  <keyword>Infraclavicular brachial plexus</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

