<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02623101</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>RCM-onco ZonMw-1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02623101</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Reflectance Confocal Microscopy in Basal Cell Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>In Vivo Reflectance Confocal Microscopy, a Novel Non-invasive Tool for Diagnosing Skin Cancer - A Randomized Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Radboud University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>ZonMw: The Netherlands Organisation for Health Research and Development</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Mavig GmbH</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Radboud University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Skin cancer is the most common cancer and its incidence is increasing rapidly. The rising
      number of skin cancer may result in long waiting lists for consultation at departments for
      dermatological care and in increasing health care costs. In case of suspicion on skin cancer
      it is of utmost importance to diagnose and treat in an early phase, preferable in a patient
      friendly manner. Skin cancer comprises melanoma and non-melanoma skin cancer (NMSC: basal
      cell carcinoma (BCC), squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) and its precursors actinic keratosis (AK)
      and Bowen disease). As BCC is the most common skin cancer type with an estimated incidence of
      51,000 new tumors in 2015 (The Netherlands), this study will focus on this skin cancer type.
      In case of suspicion on BCC, at present, the pathological examination of a biopsy is the gold
      standard for diagnosing a BCC. With the implementation of non invasive diagnosis by
      reflectance confocal microscopy (RCM) in routine patient care settings the diagnosis can be
      assessed at the first consultation in a non-invasive way and the patient can be treated
      instantly.

      Overall, the aim of this study is to investigate whether reflectance confocal microscopy can
      correctly identify the subtype of basal cell carcinoma.

      Study design: Randomized controlled trail. Comparison with usual care: punch biopsy and
      excision.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      INTRODUCTION AND RATIONALE:

      Skin cancer is the most common cancer and its incidence is increasing rapidly in Western
      countries. In the Netherlands the registry of skin cancer is poor, however based on recent
      literature and guidelines the investigators estimate the number of new malignant skin tumors
      and the precursor actinic keratosis (AK) in 2015 at around 235,278, having a major impact on
      the health care system. Moreover, it is predicted that numbers of skin cancer will rise with
      4.5-8% per year, depending on the type of skin cancer. Skin cancer comprises melanoma and
      non-melanoma skin cancer (NMSC: basal cell carcinoma (BCC), squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) and
      its precursors actinic keratosis (AK) and Bowen disease). In case of suspicion on NMSC, at
      present, the pathological examination of a biopsy is the gold standard. In case of clinical
      suspicion on AK, the diagnosis is made à vue, without pathological confirmation. In the
      United States, already in 2003, skin cancer was found to be among the most costly of all
      cancers to treat, thus, it is evident that skin cancer places an enormous burden on western
      healthcare systems with increasing costs. As BCC is the most common skin cancer (about 75% of
      all skin cancers) with an estimated incidence of 51,000 new tumors in 2015, this study will
      focus on this skin cancer type.

      HEALTH CARE EFFICIENCY PROBLEM:

      As described above, the incidences of the various malignant skin tumours are increasing
      dramatically. The rising number of skin cancer may result in long waiting lists for
      consultation at departments for dermatological care and in increasing health care costs. In
      case of suspicion on skin cancer it is of utmost importance to diagnose and treat in an early
      phase, preferable in a patient friendly manner. With the implementation of reflectance
      confocal microscopy (RCM) in routine patient care settings the diagnosis is assessed at the
      first consultation and the patient can be treated instantly. A second consultation for
      explaining the diagnosis is than not necessary, which time can then be used for other new
      patients. Also, with the conventional diagnostic procedure (pathological investigation of a
      skin biopsy) the investigators experience in 29% of the cases a sample error, so the BCC
      subtype is not correctly identified, and as treatment depends on BCC subtype many patients
      need a subsequent treatment because of treatment failure or recurrence. Also for
      pathologists, to examine skin tumor after skin tumor is not that efficient and challenging.
      More pathologists are needed if there will not be other diagnostic techniques in the future.
      RCM will also, not unimportantly, lower the costs for diagnosing skin cancer.

      USUAL CARE:

      Currently, in case of suspicion on NMSC, including BCC, an invasive diagnostic biopsy for
      pathological examination is performed.Treatment choices depend on BCC subtype.

      THE INTERVENTION TO BE INVESTIGATED:

      RCM is a non-invasive imaging technique. It provides real time images of cell- and tissue
      structures and dynamics in situ, without the need for ex vivo tissue samples. RCM visualizes
      human skin up to a depth of around 250 μm. Most, but not all tumors can be visualized. For
      thicker tumors RCM may help to find the optimal localization to perform a biopsy, as
      superficial features in these tumors may help to spot these. Moreover, the whole tumor can be
      imaged by RCM and a diagnosis can be made instantly.

      RCM features for skin cancer are reported, which showed a high correlation with conventional
      pathological features. These features allow to diagnose AK and SCC, and subtypes in BCC
      (superficial, nodular, micronodular, infiltrative and mixed type BCCs).

      RCM in the RELEVANCE FOR PRACTICE

      Skin cancer is responsible for 50% of the costs in dermatological patient care, 75-80% of
      these costs are caused by BCC. These costs will increase even more, as incidence rates will
      rise further. As described above, the gold standard is pathological investigation of a biopsy
      or of an excision. However, pathological diagnosis of a biopsy often results in sampling
      errors, as only a small part of the tumor is investigated resulting in potentially
      inappropriate chosen therapies. The subtypes of BCC are treated differently. As a sample
      error may lead to treatment failures or recurrences, other subsequent treatments are needed,
      increasing costs. In addition, the conventional method is unfriendly for patients, as it is
      invasive, painful, scarring, and the diagnosis is not instantly available. In order to
      implement patient friendly RCM in daily BCC care, a large prospective study is needed. The
      ability of RCM in determining the correct diagnosis and subtyping BCC needs to be
      investigated as well as preparing protocols for use in patient care. It is believed that this
      diagnostic imaging technique will be more cost-effective and more patient friendly as
      compared to the biopsy procedure, the gold standard at present. Therefore, the purpose of
      this study is to investigate whether reflectance confocal microscopy can correctly identify
      the subtype of basal cell carcinoma.

      Study design: Randomized controlled trail. Comparison with usual care; punch biopsy and
      excision.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2016</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of correctly identified basal cell carcinoma and the subtype by Reflectance confocal microscopy validated by histopathological examination of the excision specimen</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 3 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life (Qol)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>VAS (Visual analogue scale)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost effectiveness of Reflectance confocal microscopy as diagnostic tool to diagnose basal cell carcinoma</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>Productivity Cost Questionnaire (IMCQ, generic instrument for measuring medical costs)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality Adjusted Live Years (QALY's)</measure>
    <time_frame>Through study completion, an average of 3 years</time_frame>
    <description>EQ-5D-5L health questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">329</enrollment>
  <condition>Carcinoma, Basal Cell</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care procedure</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Clinical suspected basal cell carcinomas, of all subtypes, will be diagnosed by conventional 3mm punch biopsy of the most clinical suspicious part of the lesion. Punch biopsies will be performed under local anesthetics using 1% xylocaine/adrenaline. Hematoxylin/eosin stained sections of the punch biopsies will be evaluated by an experienced pathologist. Subjects will receive surgical excision according to subtype.
When there is any doubt by reflectance confocal microscopic diagnosis, a punch biopsy will also be obtained and the lesion will be excized when the biopsy reveals a basal cell carcinoma.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Reflectance confocal microscopy (RCM)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Vivascope 1500 and Vivascope 3000 (handheld divice) will be used (CE certified, Lucid Technologies, Henrietta, NY, USA). Reflectance confocal microscopy (RCM) imaging will be performed on clinical suspected basal cell carcinomas, of all subtypes. When there are signs of a basal cell carcinoma imaged by RCM, subjects will receive surgical excision according to subtype. When there is any doubt by RCM diagnosis, a punch biopsy will also be obtained and the lesion will be excized when the biopsy reveals a basal cell carcinoma.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Reflectance confocal microscopy</intervention_name>
    <description>Non-invasive imaging of the lesion</description>
    <arm_group_label>Reflectance confocal microscopy (RCM)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Confocal microscopy</other_name>
    <other_name>Vivascope 1500</other_name>
    <other_name>Vivascope 3000</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Punch biopsy</intervention_name>
    <description>Obtaining a skin sample of the suspicious lesion under local anesthetics</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care procedure</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Biopsy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Surgical excision</intervention_name>
    <description>Excision of the basal cell carcinoma lesion under local anesthetics</description>
    <arm_group_label>Standard of care procedure</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Reflectance confocal microscopy (RCM)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Surgical removal</other_name>
    <other_name>Surgery</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients must be able to adhere to all requirements of the study

          -  Patients must be willing to give written informed consent

          -  Clinically diagnosed/ clinical suspicion of basal cell carcinoma

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participating in other investigational research currently or in the previous 28 days
             before the study

          -  Patient is having a medical condition which excludes participating the research,
             according to the investigator

          -  Incapacitated subjects will not be included

          -  Lesion(s) on parts of the body which do not allow to adequately image the tumour with
             RCM.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>M JP Gerritsen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Radboud University Medical Center, Department of Dermatology</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>M JP Gerritsen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+31243613724</phone>
    <email>rianne.gerritsen@radboudumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Malou Peppelman, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>+31243613724</phone>
    <email>malou.peppelman@radboudumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Canisius Wilhelmina Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>J AC Alkemade, MD. PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Radboud University Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>M JP Gerritsen, MD. PhD.</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>M JP Gerritsen, MD. PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>M Peppelman, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rijnstate Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Velp</city>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>M B Maessen-Visch, MD. PhD</last_name>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flohil SC, de Vries E, Neumann HA, Coebergh JW, Nijsten T. Incidence, prevalence and future trends of primary basal cell carcinoma in the Netherlands. Acta Derm Venereol. 2011 Jan;91(1):24-30. doi: 10.2340/00015555-1009.</citation>
    <PMID>21264452</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Flohil SC, van der Leest RJ, Dowlatshahi EA, Hofman A, de Vries E, Nijsten T. Prevalence of actinic keratosis and its risk factors in the general population: the Rotterdam Study. J Invest Dermatol. 2013 Aug;133(8):1971-8. doi: 10.1038/jid.2013.134. Epub 2013 Mar 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23510990</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Housman TS, Feldman SR, Williford PM, Fleischer AB Jr, Goldman ND, Acostamadiedo JM, Chen GJ. Skin cancer is among the most costly of all cancers to treat for the Medicare population. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2003 Mar;48(3):425-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12637924</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wolberink EA, Pasch MC, Zeiler M, van Erp PE, Gerritsen MJ. High discordance between punch biopsy and excision in establishing basal cell carcinoma subtype: analysis of 500 cases. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol. 2013 Aug;27(8):985-9. doi: 10.1111/j.1468-3083.2012.04628.x. Epub 2012 Jul 3.</citation>
    <PMID>22759209</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peppelman M, Wolberink EA, Blokx WA, van de Kerkhof PC, van Erp PE, Gerritsen MJ. In vivo diagnosis of basal cell carcinoma subtype by reflectance confocal microscopy. Dermatology. 2013;227(3):255-62. doi: 10.1159/000354762. Epub 2013 Oct 18.</citation>
    <PMID>24158236</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peppelman M, Wolberink EA, Koopman RJ, van Erp PE, Gerritsen MJ. In vivo Reflectance Confocal Microscopy: A Useful Tool to Select the Location of a Punch Biopsy in a Large, Clinically Indistinctive Lesion. Case Rep Dermatol. 2013 Apr 25;5(1):129-32. doi: 10.1159/000351258. Print 2013 Jan.</citation>
    <PMID>23687492</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Peppelman M, Nguyen KP, Hoogedoorn L, van Erp PE, Gerritsen MJ. Reflectance confocal microscopy: non-invasive distinction between actinic keratosis and squamous cell carcinoma. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol. 2015 Jul;29(7):1302-9. doi: 10.1111/jdv.12806. Epub 2014 Oct 30.</citation>
    <PMID>25357235</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hoogedoorn L, Peppelman M, Blokx WA, van Erp PE, Gerritsen MJ. Prospective differentiation of clinically difficult to distinguish nodular basal cell carcinomas and intradermal nevi by non-invasive Reflectance Confocal Microscopy: a case series study. J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol. 2015 Feb;29(2):330-6. doi: 10.1111/jdv.12548. Epub 2014 May 20.</citation>
    <PMID>24841762</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Longo C, Lallas A, Kyrgidis A, Rabinovitz H, Moscarella E, Ciardo S, Zalaudek I, Oliviero M, Losi A, Gonzalez S, Guitera P, Piana S, Argenziano G, Pellacani G. Classifying distinct basal cell carcinoma subtype by means of dermatoscopy and reflectance confocal microscopy. J Am Acad Dermatol. 2014 Oct;71(4):716-724.e1. doi: 10.1016/j.jaad.2014.04.067. Epub 2014 Jun 11.</citation>
    <PMID>24928707</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 10, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 7, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 20, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 20, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Reflectance confocal microscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Basal cell carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Biopsy</keyword>
  <keyword>Diagnostics</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Basal Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anesthetics, Local</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

