<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02621723</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VUMedicalcenter</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02621723</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Capturing Readmission Internationally to Prevent Readmission by Safer@Home Group</brief_title>
  <acronym>CURIOS@</acronym>
  <official_title>Capturing Readmission Internationally to Prevent Readmission by Safer@Home</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>VU University Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>VU University Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      CURIOS@ is a prospective multi-centre cross-sectional study to investigate readmissions in
      participating units. The data collected is derived from two clinical episodes: the episode
      containing the re-admission and the previous admission (index admission).

      The main aims are:

      Outcomes:

        -  Risk factors to predict preventable readmissions in non-surgical patients

        -  Percentage of subjectively non-preventable and preventable readmissions from patient,
           carer, their nurses and their physician's point of view

        -  Comparison for risk factors on readmissions throughout Europe

        -  Increasing awareness and knowledge for health-care workers on readmissions and its
           preventability
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Data will be derived directly from patients, from the clinical notes of the previous
      admission and records of discharge communication. Also information from treating physicians,
      nurses and immediate caregivers will be collected. The data set will contain no directly
      identifiable variables (data will be registered by using a research code for each patient).

      Data collection will include: Hospital-related data, patient-related data, health-related
      data, time-related data, and physician related data. Also patient feedback is requested.

      After obtaining written informed consent, the researcher will ask the patient 7 questions
      about the (preventability of their) readmission. Also the patient will be asked if one of the
      direct carers can be approached with 2 questions. The carer will most often be a sibling, a
      good friend or someone from the neighborhood. We will approach the carer in person or by
      telephone, and only after explicit permission from the patient. Lastly, we will ask a doctor
      and nurse (responsible for the patient in the first 24 hours of his readmission) similar
      questions.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>6 Months</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of readmissions deemed preventable by patients, their informal carers, nurses and physicians</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Of all the readmissions in the study, we will look at the readmissions which are deemed potentially preventable (YES or NO) by all partners of care chain. In the end this will give us a percentage of readmissions judged as potentially preventable by all partners of care chain.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Causes of preventable readmissions</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>We will ask all partners in the care chain about the causes of the readmissions. These will be categorised:
Disease-related: Natural progress disease, out of control/influence physician or patient - for example: metastasis cancer.
Patient-related: Related to control/influence patient, out of control/influence professionals - for example: a patient who refused extra home care after the index admission.
Human/caregiver-related: Related to the control/influence professionals - for example: poor medication handover after index inclusion.
Organisational: Readmission related to organisational problems - for example: no beds available, transfer from other hospital etc.
Technical: Readmission related to technical defects of materials or equipment - for example: IV-drip home infusion antibiotics broken.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Risk factors for preventable readmissions</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
    <description>For every readmission, we will ask researchers to fill out a dataset with potential risk factors. These are:
General data regarding readmission: i.e. length of stay, time between index admission and readmission.
Patient-related factors: i.e. age, sex, marital status, living situation etc.
Health-related: ie. comorbiditity, frailty score, polypharmacy etc.
Time-related: i.e. Total admissions in previous year
Physician related: i.e. was a discharge letter send?</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Hospital Readmission</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients readmitted for at least one night for a medical specialism after any type of
        admission at any ward in the previous 30 days, with an overnight stay. This could be from
        any ward, for any procedure (elective/non-elective)
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Adult patients aged 18 or above admitted to hospital as unscheduled medical admission
             for a minimum of a single night following a previous admission within 30 days

          -  Index admission can be for any procedure (elective/non-elective)

          -  Index admission at any hospital ward (except psychiatry, pediatrics or gynaecology)
             for a minimum of a single night during the previous 30 days

          -  Readmission should be to a medical ward (Medical ward: Cardiology, geriatrics,
             gastroenterology, hematology, internal medicine, nephrology, neurology, oncology,
             pulmonary medicine, rheumatology.)

          -  If a patient is readmitted more than once within the study period, only the first
             readmission will be included

          -  The port of entry is through an Emergency Department, Acute Medical Unit or any other
             clinical ward (i.e. department of internal medicine).

          -  Patients should all be capable of understanding the study and give written informed
             consent. They should all be mentally competent.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Patients readmitted electively for procedures, surgery or chemotherapy

          -  Patients readmitted for a non-medical specialism (surgery, urology, ent etc..)

          -  Patients admitted or readmitted who are pregnant

          -  Patients admitted or readmitted aged under 18

          -  Patients index or readmission for pediatrics, psychiatry, gynaecology

          -  Patients who stayed less than one night during index and readmission

          -  Patients who have been admitted to another institution in their index admission (To
             facilitate timely case identification and ready access to treating physicians, we will
             only review same-hospital readmissions)

          -  A second readmission for the same patient within the study period
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Prabath Nanayakkara, MD, PhD, FRCP</last_name>
    <phone>031204444444</phone>
    <phone_ext>6791</phone_ext>
    <email>p.nanayakkara@vumc.nl</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Louise van Galen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>031613767381</phone>
    <phone_ext>6185</phone_ext>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital of South West Jutland</name>
      <address>
        <city>Esbjerg</city>
        <zip>5270 Odense N</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Mikkel Brabrand, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <email>mikkel@brabrand.net</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mikkel Brabrand, MD,PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VU University Medical Centre</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <state>Noord-Holland</state>
        <zip>1081 HV</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Prabath W Nanayakkara, MD,PhD,FRCP</last_name>
      <phone>0031204444444</phone>
      <phone_ext>6179</phone_ext>
      <email>p.nanayakkara@vumc.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Louise S van Galen, MD</last_name>
      <phone>0031613767381</phone>
      <phone_ext>6185</phone_ext>
      <email>lo.vangalen@vumc.nl</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Prabath Nanayakkara, MD,PhD,FRCP</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Academic Medical Centre (AMC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Amsterdam</city>
        <zip>1105AZ</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Frits Holleman, MD, PhD</last_name>
      <email>f.holleman@amc.uva.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Frits Holleman</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Albert Schweitzer</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dordrecht</city>
        <zip>3300 AK</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Wilma Jansen</last_name>
      <email>w.jansen@asz.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ralph So, MD</last_name>
      <email>r.so@asz.nl</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ralph So, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Westfriesgasthuis</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hoorn</city>
        <zip>1624 NP</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>VieCuri Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Venlo</city>
        <zip>5912 BL</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Dennis Barten, MD</last_name>
      <email>dbarten@viecuri.nl</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Loes Hooff, MD</last_name>
      <email>loesvhooff@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Dennis Barten, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Loes van Hooff, MD</last_name>
      <role>Sub-Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ysbyty Gwynedd Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bangor</city>
        <zip>LL57 2PW</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chris P Subbe, MD,PhD,FRCP</last_name>
      <email>csubbe@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Chris Subbe, MD,PhD,FRCP</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Hospital of South Manchester</name>
      <address>
        <city>Manchester</city>
        <zip>M13 9WL</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tim Cooksley, MD,MRCP</last_name>
      <email>cooks199@hotmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Tim Cooksley, MD,MRCP</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greysen SR, Stijacic Cenzer I, Auerbach AD, Covinsky KE. Functional impairment and hospital readmission in Medicare seniors. JAMA Intern Med. 2015 Apr;175(4):559-65. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2014.7756.</citation>
    <PMID>25642907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Zanocchi M, Maero B, Martinelli E, Cerrato F, Corsinovi L, Gonella M, Ponte E, Luppino A, Margolicci A, Molaschi M. Early re-hospitalization of elderly people discharged from a geriatric ward. Aging Clin Exp Res. 2006 Feb;18(1):63-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16608138</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Donzé J, Aujesky D, Williams D, Schnipper JL. Potentially avoidable 30-day hospital readmissions in medical patients: derivation and validation of a prediction model. JAMA Intern Med. 2013 Apr 22;173(8):632-8. doi: 10.1001/jamainternmed.2013.3023.</citation>
    <PMID>23529115</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van Walraven C, Wong J, Forster AJ. LACE+ index: extension of a validated index to predict early death or urgent readmission after hospital discharge using administrative data. Open Med. 2012 Jul 19;6(3):e80-90. Print 2012.</citation>
    <PMID>23696773</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dramé M, Lang PO, Novella JL, Narbey D, Mahmoudi R, Lanièce I, Somme D, Gauvain JB, Heitz D, Voisin T, de Wazières B, Gonthier R, Ankri J, Saint-Jean O, Jeandel C, Couturier P, Blanchard F, Jolly D. Six-month outcome of elderly people hospitalized via the emergency department: the SAFES cohort. Rev Epidemiol Sante Publique. 2012 Jun;60(3):189-96. doi: 10.1016/j.respe.2011.11.004. Epub 2012 May 16.</citation>
    <PMID>22608011</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cooksley T, Nanayakkara PW, Nickel CH, Subbe CP, Kellett J, Kidney R, Merten H, Van Galen L, Henriksen DP, Lassen AT, Brabrand M; safer@home consortium. Readmissions of medical patients: an external validation of two existing prediction scores. QJM. 2016 Apr;109(4):245-8. doi: 10.1093/qjmed/hcv130. Epub 2015 Jul 10.</citation>
    <PMID>26163662</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Hansen LO, Williams MV, Singer SJ. Perceptions of hospital safety climate and incidence of readmission. Health Serv Res. 2011 Apr;46(2):596-616. doi: 10.1111/j.1475-6773.2010.01204.x. Epub 2010 Nov 24.</citation>
    <PMID>21105868</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Billings J, Blunt I, Steventon A, Georghiou T, Lewis G, Bardsley M. Development of a predictive model to identify inpatients at risk of re-admission within 30 days of discharge (PARR-30). BMJ Open. 2012 Aug 10;2(4). pii: e001667. doi: 10.1136/bmjopen-2012-001667. Print 2012.</citation>
    <PMID>22885591</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jackson AH, Fireman E, Feigenbaum P, Neuwirth E, Kipnis P, Bellows J. Manual and automated methods for identifying potentially preventable readmissions: a comparison in a large healthcare system. BMC Med Inform Decis Mak. 2014 Apr 5;14:28. doi: 10.1186/1472-6947-14-28.</citation>
    <PMID>24708889</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Davies S, Saynina O, Schultz E, McDonald KM, Baker LC. Implications of metric choice for common applications of readmission metrics. Health Serv Res. 2013 Dec;48(6 Pt 1):1978-95. doi: 10.1111/1475-6773.12075. Epub 2013 Jun 6.</citation>
    <PMID>23742056</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Blunt I, Bardsley M, Grove A, Clarke A. Classifying emergency 30-day readmissions in England using routine hospital data 2004-2010: what is the scope for reduction? Emerg Med J. 2015 Jan;32(1):44-50. doi: 10.1136/emermed-2013-202531. Epub 2014 Mar 25.</citation>
    <PMID>24668396</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bianco A, Molè A, Nobile CG, Di Giuseppe G, Pileggi C, Angelillo IF. Hospital readmission prevalence and analysis of those potentially avoidable in southern Italy. PLoS One. 2012;7(11):e48263. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0048263. Epub 2012 Nov 2.</citation>
    <PMID>23133624</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Cooksley T, Merten H, Kellett J, Brabrand M, Kidney R, Nickel CH, Nanayakkara PW, Subbe CP. PRISMA Analysis of 30 Day Readmissions to a Tertiary Cancer Hospital. Acute Med. 2015;14(2):53-6.</citation>
    <PMID>26305081</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 25, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 1, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 3, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 1, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 1, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 3, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>VU University Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Prabath W.B. Nanayakkara</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD, MD, FRCP</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Preventability</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

