<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02626494</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CoGlu_PUK_ZH_2014_0010</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02626494</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neurobiological Adaptations and Pharmacological Interventions in Cocaine Addiction</brief_title>
  <acronym>CoGlu</acronym>
  <official_title>Neurobiological Adaptations and Pharmacological Interventions in Cocaine Addiction: The Role of Glutamate</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Psychiatric University Hospital, Zurich</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Zurich Center for Integrative Human Physiology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Swiss Federal Institute of Technology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Max-Planck-Institut Tübingen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Psychiatric University Hospital, Zurich</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims at testing for the impact of glutamatergic changes on drug craving in cocaine
      addiction, and to evaluate the effects of n-acetylcysteine (n-AC) on both glutamate
      homeostasis and craving using a randomized, double-blind, placebo controlled cross-over
      design.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Cocaine addiction is a devastating disorder with potentially harmful psychological, physical
      and social consequences. Despite its clinical importance, there is currently no approved
      pharmacological treatment available for cocaine addiction. However, preclinical research has
      recently identified potentially promising targets for pharmacotherapeutic approaches mainly
      based on advances in the understanding of neuroplastic alterations associated with repeated
      cocaine administration in animals.

      Preclinical animal models revealed that chronic administration of cocaine leads to decreased
      basal levels of glutamate within the nucleus accumbens a key region of the neural reward
      circuitry; in turn, the reinstatement of drug seeking results in enhanced glutamatergic
      transmission. However, little is known about similar changes in humans, and about their
      functional role for addictive behavior, mainly due to methodological restrictions. The
      investigators thus aim to examine the changes associated with chronic cocaine use on
      glutamate homeostasis in humans using a newly developed proton magnetic resonance
      spectroscopy (1H-MRS) protocol. This method allows for the quantification of brain
      metabolites such as glutamate in specific regions of the human brain even within small
      subcortical volumes of interest such as the nucleus accumbens that have been hitherto
      difficult to assess.

      Interestingly, the administration of n-AC restored the glutamate homeostasis in rats and
      reduced their drug reinstatement behavior. Therefore, the present study aims at investigating
      if a pharmacological challenge of n-AC influences glutamate homeostasis in humans and whether
      these possible modulations are linked to cocaine craving.

      Power analyses to identify the sample size of this study, were done with a focus on 1H-MRS,
      the most critical procedure in this context within our project. Assuming a mean conservative
      effect size of d=0.80, an α-error probability of 5%, and a conservative power estimation of
      80% and considering a drop-out rate of about 30%, investigators plan to measure 30 cocaine
      dependent patients and 30 healthy controls.

      Imaging data of low quality (e.g. due to movement artifacts) will be excluded. If imaging
      data has to be excluded or if participants do not finish the experiment, the investigators
      will additionally recruit more participants in order to assess the planned sample size.

      Throughout the duration of the entire study, the conductance of pre-defined key processes
      will constantly be monitored by an independent monitor in specified visit intervals to ensure
      that the study is conducted in accordance with the approved protocol, good clinical practice,
      and the applicable regulatory requirement in order to protect the rights and well-being of
      study participants and integrity of data.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Glutamatergic alterations in cocaine users assessed by 1H-MRS as glutamate concentrations in the nucleus accumbens expressed as glutamate ratios in relation to water [glutamate/water]</measure>
    <time_frame>It will be assessed in the placebo condition at either the 1.measurement (approximately 1.5h after ingestion of the last dose), on average 2 days after the initial assessment of the subject or at the 2.measurement (in average 14 days after 1.measurement)</time_frame>
    <description>- Changes in basal glutamatergic neurotransmission in the nucleus accumbens in cocaine addiction will be assessed via 1H-MRS.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of n-acetylcystein on glutamate homeostasis assessed by 1H-MRS as glutamtate concentrations in the nucleus accumbens expressed as glutamate ratios in relation to water [glutamate/water]</measure>
    <time_frame>The impact of n-AC will be assessed by comparing n-AC and placebo condition, with an average time interval of 14 days between measurements.</time_frame>
    <description>The impact of n-AC on glutamatergic neurotransmission in cocaine addiction will be assessed via 1H-MRS.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Impact of n-acetylcystein on craving assessed by visual analog scales</measure>
    <time_frame>The impact of n-AC will be assessed by comparing n-AC and placebo condition with an average time interval of 2 weeks between measurements.</time_frame>
    <description>Craving will be assessed via subjective ratings on visual analog scales
The impact of n-AC will be assessed by comparing craving in cocaine dependent individuals under n-AC and placebo.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Alterations in frontostriatal networks indicated by connectivity coefficients assessed by functional magnetic resonance imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>Alterations in frontostriatal will be assessed by comparing n-AC and placebo condition with an average time interval of 2 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>Alterations in frontostriatal networks will be assessed via magnetic resonance imaging.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">71</enrollment>
  <condition>Cocaine Addiction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Cocaine Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>n-AC and placebo will be given according to a double-blind, placebo-controlled cross-over design. Subjects receive 4 doses of n-AC/placebo over 2 consecutive days (total dose=4800mg; individual dose=1200mg). Subjects will take the first 2 doses of n-AC/placebo 5 days after the screening assessment (one in the morning, one in the evening), and the last 2 dose 1h prior to scanning, with 12 hours dosing intervals in between. 14 days later n-AC/placebo will be administered analogously as described above. Preparation and blinding of n-AC and placebo capsules will be performed by the Kantonsapotheke Zürich according to the guidelines of Good Manufacturing Practice.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Control Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>n-AC and placebo will be given according to a double-blind, placebo-controlled cross-over design. Subjects receive 4 doses of n-AC/placebo over 2 consecutive days (total dose=4800mg; individual dose=1200mg). Subjects will take the first 2 doses of n-AC/placebo 5 days after the screening assessment (one in the morning, one in the evening), and the last 2 dose 1h prior to scanning, with 12 hours dosing intervals in between. 14 days later n-AC/placebo will be administered analogously as described above. Preparation and blinding of n-AC and placebo capsules will be performed by the Kantonsapotheke Zürich according to the guidelines of Good Manufacturing Practice.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>N-Acetylcystein</intervention_name>
    <description>n-AC will be given according to a double-blind, placebo-controlled cross-over design. Subjects receive 3 doses of n-AC over 2 consecutive days (total dose=4800mg; individual doses=2x1200mg, 1x2400mg). Subjects will take 2 first doses (à 1200mg) of n-AC 5 days after the screening assessment (one in the morning, one in the evening), and the last dose (2400mg) 1h prior to scanning, with 12 hours dosing intervals in between. Preparation and blinding of n-AC capsules will be performed by the Kantonsapotheke Zürich according to the guidelines of Good Manufacturing Practice.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cocaine Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>14 days before or after, placebo will be administered analogously as described with n-AC. Placebo will be given according to a double-blind, placebo-controlled cross-over design. Subjects receive 3 doses of placebo over 2 consecutive days (total dose=4800mg; individual doses=2x1200mg, 1x2400mg). Subjects will take 2 first doses (à 1200mg) of placebo 1 day before scanning (one in the morning, one in the evening), and the last dose (2400mg) 1h prior to scanning, with 12 hours dosing intervals in between. Preparation and blinding of placebo capsules will be performed by the Kantonsapotheke Zürich according to the guidelines of Good Manufacturing Practice.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Cocaine Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Healthy Control Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Cocaine use disorder vs. no substance use

          -  Magnetic resonance imaging compatibility

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Regular use of other psychoactive drugs

          -  Comorbidity of other psychiatric disorders

          -  Neurological or somatic disease
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Marcus Herdener, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Center for Addicitve Disorders</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Psychiatric University Hospital, Zurich</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zurich</city>
        <zip>8001</zip>
        <country>Switzerland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Switzerland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 20, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 7, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 10, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 28, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 28, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Psychiatric University Hospital, Zurich</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Dr. med. Marcus Herdener</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Dr. med Marcus Herdener</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Behavior, Addictive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cocaine-Related Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cocaine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

