<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02624336</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>101269-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02624336</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of Synergistic Anti-plaque Activity of Salvadora Persica L. and Green Tea: A Clinical Comparative Study</brief_title>
  <acronym>ESAA</acronym>
  <official_title>Evaluation of Synergistic Anti-plaque Activity of Salvadora Persica L. and Green Tea: A Clinical Comparative Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Malaya</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Malaya</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Accumulation of dental plaque may result in negative effects on the tooth and tooth
      supporting periodontal tissue. In addition, it contributes to the development of caries and
      periodontal diseases. Therefore, an effective dental plaque control is essential for
      maintaining good oral hygiene. Mechanical plaque control has its limitation thus chemical
      plaque control may be used as an adjunct in dental plaque control. Various types of medicinal
      plants can be utilized as stable, safe and biologically active plant-derived galenicals as
      alternative to synthetic mouth wash. Among these plants, Salvadora persica L. (Sp) root
      sticks and green tea (Gt) aqueous extracts were reported to have anti-microbial activity
      against many oral bacteria. The objective of this study was to investigate the efficacy of
      the combination of Gt aqueous extract and Sp aqueous extract as a synergistic anti-bacterial
      and anti-adherence efficacy against primary plaque colonizers.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Dental plaque is the soft deposits that form the biofilm adhering to the tooth surface or
      other hard surfaces inside oral cavity, including removable and fixed restoration. The dental
      plaque is composed of over 500 bacterial species. The colonization of these bacteria follows
      a special pattern starting by adhesion of initial bacterial colonizers to the salivary
      pellicles covering tooth enamel and other hard surfaces in the oral cavity followed by
      secondary colonization of follower bacteria through inter-bacterial adhesion leading to
      dental plaque maturation.

      Periodontal health can be considered to be in a state of balance when the bacterial mass
      presents in the host oral cavity and causes no damage to either the bacteria or the host
      periodontal tissues. Any disruption of this balance results in alterations in both the host
      periodontal and biofilm bacteria and leads ultimately to destruction of the periodontium.
      Accumulation of dental plaque may lead to several harmful effects on the tooth and tooth
      supporting periodontal tissue that contributes to the development of caries and periodontal
      diseases. Therefore, an effective dental plaque control is essential for maintaining good
      oral hygiene.

      Mechanical plaque control, by using toothbrushes and interdental aids, is the mostly adopted
      method. Unfortunately, it is a time consuming process and needs high manual dexterity.
      Moreover, epidemiological studies revealed high prevalence of gingivitis among toothbrush
      users. Hence, chemical plaque control may be used to assist in dental plaque control.

      The anti-plaque agent is that agent that interferes with one of the different phases of
      dental plaque development: interferes with the adhesion of oral bacteria to oral surfaces and
      prevent biofilm formation; interferes with co-aggregation mechanism which thereby prevents
      future growth of micro-colonies; or removes or disrupts existing dental plaque. To date,
      chlorhexidine (CHX) mouthwash is the standard solution used in chemical plaque control, but
      it was found to have several side effects including tooth and some restorations staining,
      unpleasant test, sloughing of oral mucosa and enhancement of supra-gingival calculus
      formation.

      The widely available traditional natural medicinal plants can be utilized as stable, safe and
      biologically active plant-derived galenicals as alternative to synthetic drugs. Among these
      plants, Salvadora persica L. (Sp) root sticks and green tea (Gt), leafs of Camellia sinensis.
      Kuntze, aqueous extracts were reported to have anti-microbial activity against many oral
      bacteria. In our in vitro study, we found that the combination (Co.) of 0.25mg Gt aqueous
      extract and 7.82mg Sp aqueous extract in 1ml exhibited significant synergistic anti-bacterial
      and anti-adherence efficacy against primary plaque colonizers.

      The dental plaque is classified into two categories, supra-gingival plaque and sub-gingival
      plaque, in relation to gingival margin. The supra-gingival dental plaque may be readily
      visualized on teeth after 24 to 48 hours with no oral hygiene measures and it appears white,
      grayish, or yellow in color and has a globular appearance.

      Supra-gingival plaque accumulation on tooth surfaces can be quantified through different
      plaque index systems. In this study, the clinical parameter to record plaque quantity was
      modified Quigely Hein Plaque Index. In this index, a score of 0 to 5 was assigned for each
      facial and lingual (palatal) surface of all teeth except the third molars.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean amount plaque between different DTC1 and placebo comparators i.e. Oradex and distilled water, as anti-plaque agent following 24 hrs plaque regrowth clinical trial by means of modified Quigely Hein Plaque Index [Turesky, 1970].</measure>
    <time_frame>24 hours</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">14</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy Volunteers</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DTC1 mouth wash</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>15ml twice a day, rinse for 30sec refrain from eating or drinking for 30min</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Oradex mouth wash</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>15ml twice a day, rinse for 30sec refrain from eating or drinking for 30min</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Distilled water</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>15ml twice a day, rinse for 30sec refrain from eating or drinking for 30min</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>DTC1</intervention_name>
    <description>15ml DTC1 twice a day, rinse for 30sec refrain from eating or drinking for 30min</description>
    <arm_group_label>DTC1 mouth wash</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Oradex</intervention_name>
    <description>15ml Chlorhexidine gluconate 0.12% (w/v) twice a day, rinse for 30sec refrain from eating or drinking for 30min</description>
    <arm_group_label>Oradex mouth wash</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>CHX</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Distilled water</intervention_name>
    <description>15ml distilled water twice a day, rinse for 30sec refrain from eating or drinking for 30min</description>
    <arm_group_label>Distilled water</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants should be medically healthy.

          -  Participants should have more than 20 teeth.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Participants who have active cavity caries and/or periodontal disease.

          -  Participants who have ongoing orthodontic treatment.

          -  Participants who have been on antibiotics within the past 4 months.

          -  Participants who require prophylactic antibiotic coverage.

          -  Participants who have been on systemic or topical non-steroidal anti-inflammatory
             drugs for the past 4 months.

          -  Participants who are pregnant or intended to and lactating mother.

          -  Participants who have heart valve replacement and have known intolerance or allergy to
             mouth rinses.

          -  Participants who have any systemic disease.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>40 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nor_Adinar Baharuddin, DClinDent</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Malaya</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <reference>
    <citation>Addy M, Moran J, Newcombe R, Warren P. The comparative tea staining potential of phenolic, chlorhexidine and anti-adhesive mouthrinses. J Clin Periodontol. 1995 Dec;22(12):923-8.</citation>
    <PMID>8613560</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Allison DG, Gilbert P. Modification by surface association of antimicrobial susceptibility of bacterial populations. J Ind Microbiol. 1995 Oct;15(4):311-7.</citation>
    <PMID>8605070</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Baehni PC, Takeuchi Y. Anti-plaque agents in the prevention of biofilm-associated oral diseases. Oral Dis. 2003;9 Suppl 1:23-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12974527</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chelli-Chentouf N, Tir Touil Meddah A, Mullié C, Aoues A, Meddah B. In vitro and in vivo antimicrobial activity of Algerian Hoggar Salvadora persica L. extracts against microbial strains from children's oral cavity. J Ethnopharmacol. 2012 Oct 31;144(1):57-66. doi: 10.1016/j.jep.2012.08.025. Epub 2012 Aug 29.</citation>
    <PMID>22963838</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dhar V, Jain A, Van Dyke TE, Kohli A. Prevalence of gingival diseases, malocclusion and fluorosis in school-going children of rural areas in Udaipur district. J Indian Soc Pedod Prev Dent. 2007 Apr-Jun;25(2):103-5.</citation>
    <PMID>17660647</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Farnsworth NR, Akerele O, Bingel AS, Soejarto DD, Guo Z. Medicinal plants in therapy. Bull World Health Organ. 1985;63(6):965-81.</citation>
    <PMID>3879679</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Helldén L, Camosci D, Hock J, Tinanoff N. Clinical study to compare the effect of stannous fluoride and chlorhexidine mouthrinses on plaque formation. J Clin Periodontol. 1981 Feb;8(1):12-6.</citation>
    <PMID>7019266</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ismail AI, Szpunar SM. The prevalence of total tooth loss, dental caries, and periodontal disease among Mexican Americans, Cuban Americans, and Puerto Ricans: findings from HHANES 1982-1984. Am J Public Health. 1990 Dec;80 Suppl:66-70.</citation>
    <PMID>9187585</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Manganiello AD, Socransky SS, Smith C, Propas D, Oram V, Dogon IL. Attempts to increase viable count recovery of human supragingival dental plaque. J Periodontal Res. 1977 Mar;12(2):107-19.</citation>
    <PMID>138728</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Rosan B, Lamont RJ. Dental plaque formation. Microbes Infect. 2000 Nov;2(13):1599-607. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>11113379</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sofrata A, Brito F, Al-Otaibi M, Gustafsson A. Short term clinical effect of active and inactive Salvadora persica miswak on dental plaque and gingivitis. J Ethnopharmacol. 2011 Oct 11;137(3):1130-4. doi: 10.1016/j.jep.2011.07.034. Epub 2011 Jul 20.</citation>
    <PMID>21798329</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sofrata A, Santangelo EM, Azeem M, Borg-Karlson AK, Gustafsson A, Pütsep K. Benzyl isothiocyanate, a major component from the roots of Salvadora persica is highly active against Gram-negative bacteria. PLoS One. 2011;6(8):e23045. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0023045. Epub 2011 Aug 1.</citation>
    <PMID>21829688</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Teles RP, Teles FR. Antimicrobial agents used in the control of periodontal biofilms: effective adjuncts to mechanical plaque control? Braz Oral Res. 2009;23 Suppl 1:39-48. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19838557</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tsai TH, Tsai TH, Chien YC, Lee CW, Tsai PJ. In vitro antimicrobial activities against cariogenic streptococci and their antioxidant capacities: A comparative study of green tea versus different herbs. Food Chem. 2008 Oct 15;110(4):859-64. doi: 10.1016/j.foodchem.2008.02.085. Epub 2008 Mar 4.</citation>
    <PMID>26047271</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Turesky S, Gilmore ND, Glickman I. Reduced plaque formation by the chloromethyl analogue of victamine C. J Periodontol. 1970 Jan;41(1):41-3.</citation>
    <PMID>5264376</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 3, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 7, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 8, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 7, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 7, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 8, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>periodontal disease</keyword>
  <keyword>caries</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

