<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02629653</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CEAC-0613</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02629653</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Body Cooling During Carotid Endarterectomy: No-profit, Open, Mono-centric, Feasibility Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Body Cooling During Carotid Endarterectomy: No-profit, Open, Mono-centric, Feasibility Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>S. Andrea Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>S. Andrea Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Aim of the study is to determine whether endovascular systemic cooling to a target
      temperature of 34-35°C initiated before, and maintained during Carotid EndoArterectomy (CEA),
      is feasible and safe
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is based on the hypothesis that performing CEA during hypothermia substantially
      reduces the risk due to a potential, temporary hypoperfusion, associated with the surgical
      procedure.

      The rationale behind the study is based on the assumption that Carotid EndArterectomy (CEA),
      by removing local causes of downstream altered circulation, improves cerebral hemodynamics
      and provides an effective prevention of stroke and TIA. The intervention itself, however,
      causes immediate risk of stroke or death, and it is also an issue whether the temporary
      reduction of blood flow associated with clamping of the artery, during the surgical
      intervention, may trigger long-lasting brain tissue dysfunction.

      Mild hypothermia (34-35 °C) is probably the most effective approach to protect the brain from
      ischemic insults. Most of the supportive data were obtained in animal models of ischemia.
      Several phase II trials have shown safety and feasibility of cooling subjects with stroke, in
      the hours following onset of symptoms. Early interventions show the highest benefit.

      Eligible patients will initiate cooling 60-90 min before CEA with endovascular cooling (Zoll
      system) to the target 34-35°C (assessed by bladder thermometer). The Zoll IVTM system is an
      endovascular cooling system that consists of a control module (either CoolGard 3000 or
      Thermogard XP), a CoolGard start-up kit, an ICY catheter (either IC-3585 AE or IC-3585 CO or
      IC-3893 AE or IC-3893 CO), a catheter convenience kit for catheter insertion (CO models
      only), thermal probes and cables. All the devise component have CE mark. The Low temperature
      will be maintained during the CEA procedure, followed by gradual, passive, controlled
      rewarming (0.4 °C/h). Type of anaesthesia will be decided according to good clinical
      practice. The cooling procedure will be, therefore, carried out during the anaesthesia
      procedure required by the surgical intervention. There is a chance that the duration of the
      anaesthesia will be longer that required, but all the efforts will be undertaken to keep the
      anaesthesia time as short as if there were no cooling

      Clinical and instrumental evaluations will be carried out before and post intervention. Each
      evaluation will consist of physical examination, neuropsychological evaluation (MoCA test),
      blood tests and brain MRI or TC.

      Safety is evaluated on the basis of severe adverse event
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>Any adverse event at 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Severe adverse events were defined as any life-threatening event including pneumonia (diagnosed on the basis of clinical signs or symptoms), myocardial infarction and parenchymal hemorrhage. Non-severe safety outcomes included incidence of bradycardia (&lt;40 beats per minute), cardiac arrhythmia, hypertension, hypotension and any coagulation disorders.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Carotid Artery Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Hypothermia</condition>
  <condition>Stroke</condition>
  <condition>Carotid Artery Plaque</condition>
  <condition>Carotid Artery Stenosis</condition>
  <condition>Cerebrovascular Accident</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The endovascular cooling system will be Zoll IVTM. This system consists of a control module (either CoolGard 3000 or Thermogard XP), a CoolGard start-up kit, and an ICY catheter (either IC-3585 AE or IC-3585)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>endovascular cooling (Zoll system)</intervention_name>
    <description>The Zoll IVTM is an endovascular cooling system that consists of a control module (either CoolGard 3000 or Thermogard XP), a CoolGard start-up kit, and an ICY catheter (either IC-3585 AE or IC-3585).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single arm</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Subject eligible for CEA, without progression of symptoms, with low (&lt;4) Anesthesia
             Risk Assessment

          2. Age ≥ 18 years;

          3. Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Evidence from a CT or MRI scan or from other pre-inclusion investigations of an
             intracranial haemorrhage, a tumour, encephalitis, or any diagnosis of acute brain
             focal lesion;

          2. Progression or instability of neurological status

          3. Conditions that may be exacerbated by hypothermia, such as haematological dyscrasias,
             oral anticoagulant treatment with INR ≥ 1.7, severe pulmonary disease, severe heart
             failure (defined as a New York Heart Association (NYHA) score of III or IV), history
             of myocardial infarction within the previous 3 months, angina pectoris in the previous
             3 months, severe infection with a C-reactive protein &gt; 50 mg/dl, or a clinical
             diagnosis of sepsis;

          4. Blood oxygen saturation below 94%, allowing a maximum of 2 L/min oxygen delivered
             nasally to achieve this;

          5. Bradycardia (&lt;40 beats/min);

          6. Body weight &gt; 120 kg;

          7. Severe hepatic dysfunction, or severe renal dysfunction;

          8. Pregnancy. Women of childbearing potential are excluded unless a negative test for
             pregnancy has been obtained prior to randomisation;

          9. Other serious illness that may confound treatment assessment or increase the risks of
             cooling;

         10. Social or other conditions that according to the investigator's judgement might be a
             major problem for follow-up.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Francesco Orzi, Prof, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>NESMOS Department, University of Rome &quot;La Sapienza&quot;; St. Andrea Hospital</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NESMOS Department St. Andrea Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rome</city>
        <zip>00189</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Grotta JC. Clinical practice. Carotid stenosis. N Engl J Med. 2013 Sep 19;369(12):1143-50. doi: 10.1056/NEJMcp1214999. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>24047063</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lee JH, Suh BY. Risk factor analysis of new brain lesions associated with carotid endarterectmy. Ann Surg Treat Res. 2014 Jan;86(1):39-44. doi: 10.4174/astr.2014.86.1.39. Epub 2014 Jan 1.</citation>
    <PMID>24761406</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Endarterectomy for asymptomatic carotid artery stenosis. Executive Committee for the Asymptomatic Carotid Atherosclerosis Study. JAMA. 1995 May 10;273(18):1421-8.</citation>
    <PMID>7723155</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Yenari MA, Han HS. Neuroprotective mechanisms of hypothermia in brain ischaemia. Nat Rev Neurosci. 2012 Feb 22;13(4):267-78. doi: 10.1038/nrn3174. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22353781</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Erecinska M, Thoresen M, Silver IA. Effects of hypothermia on energy metabolism in Mammalian central nervous system. J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2003 May;23(5):513-30. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>12771566</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Wu TC, Grotta JC. Hypothermia for acute ischaemic stroke. Lancet Neurol. 2013 Mar;12(3):275-84. doi: 10.1016/S1474-4422(13)70013-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>23415567</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>van der Worp HB, Macleod MR, Kollmar R; European Stroke Research Network for Hypothermia (EuroHYP). Therapeutic hypothermia for acute ischemic stroke: ready to start large randomized trials? J Cereb Blood Flow Metab. 2010 Jun;30(6):1079-93. doi: 10.1038/jcbfm.2010.44. Epub 2010 Mar 31. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20354545</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Kamme F, Campbell K, Wieloch T. Biphasic expression of the fos and jun families of transcription factors following transient forebrain ischaemia in the rat. Effect of hypothermia. Eur J Neurosci. 1995 Oct 1;7(10):2007-16.</citation>
    <PMID>8542058</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 10, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 11, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 14, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 11, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 11, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 14, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>S. Andrea Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Francesco Orzi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Prof, MD</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>carotid endarterectomy</keyword>
  <keyword>stroke</keyword>
  <keyword>hypothermia</keyword>
  <keyword>endovascular cooling</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypothermia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Stroke</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carotid Artery Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carotid Stenosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

