<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02621658</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Bowel Prep Protocol</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02621658</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clear Liquid vs Liberalized Diet in Preparation for Colonoscopy</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clear Liquid vs Liberalized Diet in Preparation for Colonoscopy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>San Antonio Military Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>San Antonio Military Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Colorectal cancer is the third most common cancer diagnosed in both men and women in the
      United States. The death rate from this disease, however, has been decreasing over the last
      20 years. Early detection and removal of pre-malignant polyps is considered to be at the core
      of this change. At the same time, polyp detection is highly dependent on an adequate bowel
      preparation. Froehlich, et al., found that poor bowel preparation is associated with longer
      colonoscopy times, more difficult procedures and a higher rate of incomplete procedures(2).

      Although a Clear Liquid Diet is usually the prescribed diet in most bowel preparation
      regimes, several studies have shown similar results with less restrictive diets.

      Based on the hypothesis that a Full Liquid Diet(FLD) is not inferior to a Clear Liquid
      Diet(CLD), investigators plan to conduct a prospective, randomized trial, in order to compare
      these dietary interventions. The investigators and endoscopists will be blinded to patient's
      diet group.

      Researchers aim to investigate if diet liberalization to a Full Liquid Diet(FLD) is
      associated with similar bowel cleansing as compared with a Clear Liquid Diet(CLD).
      Investigators will compare the performance of these dietary interventions regarding adenoma
      detection rates(ADR), time to cecal intubation(TCI), and colonoscope withdrawal time. In
      addition, the investigators want to assess whether patient's Compliance and Satisfaction is
      similar or superior in the experimental group vs the control group.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to investigate if a Full Liquid Diet is not inferior to a Clear
      Liquid Diet in preparation for Screening Colonoscopy. Based on the data presented above, the
      investigators hypothesize that a Full Liquid Diet will be better tolerated by participants
      and will not adversely affect colonoscopy outcomes in terms of bowel cleansing(BC), adenoma
      detection rate(ADR), time to cecal intubation(TCI).

      The results of this study may help guide dietary interventions in preparation for Colonoscopy
      in the Department of Defense(DOD) Military Treatment Facilities.

      The relationship between adequate colon cleansing and adenoma detection rate(ADR) has been
      already established. Almost 25% of patients, however, have a poor bowel preparation at the
      time of Colonoscopy(1). After reviewing 5832 colonoscopies, Froehlich, et al., found that
      poor bowel preparation is associated with longer colonoscopy times, more difficult procedures
      and a higher rate of incomplete procedures(2).

      Among other causes, bowel cleansing is affected by purgative selection and timing of
      administration, compliance with recommended pre-procedural diet and compliance with purgative
      administration. Recently, it has been found that the classically recommended clear liquid
      diet(CLD) is not indispensable for adequate bowel prep. Stolpman, et. al, found that a
      low-residue diet is non-inferior to clear liquid diet(CLD), in a group of 201 patients(3).
      Similarly, Melicharkova, et al, found that the bowel cleansing efficacy of a low-residue
      breakfast, the day before colonoscopy, was comparable with a clear liquid diet(CLD) in a
      sample of 213 patients administered a low volume purgative in preparation for colonoscopy(4).
      They also found a statistically significant difference in the level of patient's acceptance
      of the low-residue diet.

      A group from South Korea, led by Dr. Jung Yoon, found similar rates of bowel cleansing in
      patient undergoing afternoon colonoscopy, when offered Regular Diet(5). A study, in a small
      study population, presented as an abstract at the American College of Gastroenterology
      Conference in 2011, reported comparable bowel cleansing, polyp detection rate, and
      colonoscopy times in patients allowed a full liquid diet before the procedure(6). Taken
      together, these studies show that a clear liquid diet may not be necessary in order to obtain
      a good bowel cleanse in preparation for colonoscopies performed in the outpatient setting.

      A clear liquid diet is still the recommended diet, however, before this procedure.

      Given the diverse population served at Military Treatments Facilities across the United
      States, and abroad, the investigators aim to investigate if diet liberalization to a Full
      Liquid Diet(FLD) is associated with similar bowel cleansing as compared with a Clear Liquid
      Diet(CLD). In addition, the investigators will compare the performance of these diets
      regarding adenoma detection rates(ADR), time to cecal intubation(TCI), withdrawal time, and
      patient satisfaction.

      This study will be conducted as a prospective, randomized trial. The investigators and
      endoscopists will be blinded to patient's diet group.

      Patients 50 y/o, or older, undergoing screening colonoscopy will be offered participation in
      the study.

      If written, informed consent is obtained, participants will be randomized to (A)Control Group
      or (B) Study Group(in a 1:1 fashion). Study randomization will be performed by using serially
      numbered envelopes containing instructions for CLD or FLD. The control group will be allowed
      to have a Clear Liquid Diet the day before colonoscopy and the Study Group will be allowed to
      have a Full Liquid Diet the day before colonoscopy. These envelopes will be prepared in
      duplicates. One envelope will be provided to the participant and one envelope will be
      maintained, sealed, by the study group.

      Study participants will complete a Bowel Preparation consisting of bisacodyl 10mg per mouth
      x1(at noon, the day before colonoscopy) and 4L Polyethylene Glycol solution(split dose).
      Subjects will drink 2 L of Polyethylene Glycol at 17:00 the day before colonoscopy and the
      other 2 L at 04:00, the morning prior to colonoscopy.

      They will follow one of the diets described above, based on randomization, and will present
      to the BAMC Gastroenterology Clinic for Colonoscopy. Before the procedure, subjects will be
      administered a questionnaire in order to assess their compliance, tolerability and
      satisfaction with the diet. Research team and Endoscopists will also be blinded to these
      questionnaires until the data collection process has finished.

      Colonoscopy will be performed in the usual fashion. Endoscopists will assess the level of
      subject's colon cleansing by means of the Boston Bowel Preparation Scale(7). Time to Cecal
      Intubation and Colonoscope Withdrawal Time will be documented, as is currently done at the
      BAMC Gastroenterology Clinic.

      Adenoma Detection Rates(number of screened patients with at least one adenoma divided by
      total number of patients screened with colonoscopy) will be calculated.

      Investigators will compare Bowel Prep Quality/Colon Cleansing, Time to Cecal Intubation, ADR,
      and Patient's Compliance and Satisfaction with the bowel preparation between the two groups.

      Primarily, the investigators want to assess whether Bowel Prep Quality/Colon Cleansing and
      ADR for the experimental group is non-inferior to Bowel Prep Quality and ADR for the control
      group. In addition, the investigators will asses whether participant's Compliance and
      Satisfaction is similar or superior in the experimental group vs the control group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Bowel Preparation</measure>
    <time_frame>At the time of Colonoscopy</time_frame>
    <description>This will be assessed using the Boston Bowel Preparation Scale</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to Cecal Intubation</measure>
    <time_frame>During Colonoscopy</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Colonoscope Withdrawal time</measure>
    <time_frame>During Colonoscopy</time_frame>
    <description>Time elapsed since the endoscopist starts withdrawing the colonoscope, after reaching the cecum, until the completion of the test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adenoma Detection Rate</measure>
    <time_frame>During Colonoscopy</time_frame>
    <description>Number of patients with at least one adenoma, divided by total number of patients aged 50 years or older screened with colonoscopy</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient compliance</measure>
    <time_frame>Before Colonoscopy</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured using a questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>Before Colonoscopy</time_frame>
    <description>Will be measured using a questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Clear Liquid Diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Clear Liquid Diet the day before colonoscopy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Full Liquid Diet</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Full Liquid Diet the day before colonoscopy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Clear Liquid Diet</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be allowed to consume clear soft drinks like ginger ales, Sprite®, 7-Up®, Gatorade®, Kool Aid®. They can also have strained fruit juices like apple, white grape juice and lemonade, and water, tea and coffee without milk or non-dairy creamer. Patient in this arm will also be allowed to have low-sodium chicken or beef broth , in addition to non-red hard candies, Jell-O®, and popsicles.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Clear Liquid Diet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Full Liquid Diet</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients will be allowed to consume a Full Liquid Diet, including nutritional supplements(Ensure®, Boost®, Glucerna®), strained cereals(like cream of wheat or strained oatmeal) and vegetables, purred fruit without seeds or pulp, milk, plain ice cream or yogurt, sherbet, coffee with cream, and tea.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Full Liquid Diet</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Asymptomatic patients 50 years old or older, undergoing screening colonoscopy and
             willing to participate in the study will be included, after obtaining informed/written
             consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Symptomatic patients, patients with indications for therapeutic colonoscopy, like for
             example, rectal bleeding or with a prior diagnosis requiring evaluation with
             colonoscopy(Prior diagnosis of colon polyps, Iron-deficiency Anemia, Inflammatory
             Bowel Disease, Colorectal Cancer, Chronic diarrhea, Abnormal Imaging) will be excluded
             from participation. Please note that patients with Iron-deficiency Anemia will not be
             excluded from the study, based solely on this diagnosis, if they have an indication,
             otherwise, for Screening Colonoscopy.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>50 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>75 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Luis X Velez-Colon, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>San Antonio Military Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Luis X. Velez-Colon, MD</last_name>
    <phone>210-916-1759</phone>
    <email>luis.x.velezcolon.mil@mail.mil</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Pedro A. Manibusan, DO</last_name>
    <phone>210-916-4367</phone>
    <email>pedro.a.manibusan.mil@mail.mil</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <reference>
    <citation>Harewood GC, Sharma VK, de Garmo P. Impact of colonoscopy preparation quality on detection of suspected colonic neoplasia. Gastrointest Endosc. 2003 Jul;58(1):76-9.</citation>
    <PMID>12838225</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stolpman DR, Solem CA, Eastlick D, Adlis S, Shaw MJ. A randomized controlled trial comparing a low-residue diet versus clear liquids for colonoscopy preparation: impact on tolerance, procedure time, and adenoma detection rate. J Clin Gastroenterol. 2014 Nov-Dec;48(10):851-5. doi: 10.1097/MCG.0000000000000167.</citation>
    <PMID>25296243</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jung YS, Seok HS, Park DI, Song CS, Kim SE, Lee SH, Eun CS, Han DS, Kim YS, Lee CK. A clear liquid diet is not mandatory for polyethylene glycol-based bowel preparation for afternoon colonoscopy in healthy outpatients. Gut Liver. 2013 Nov;7(6):681-7. doi: 10.5009/gnl.2013.7.6.681. Epub 2013 Aug 14.</citation>
    <PMID>24312709</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Froehlich F, Wietlisbach V, Gonvers JJ, Burnand B, Vader JP. Impact of colonic cleansing on quality and diagnostic yield of colonoscopy: the European Panel of Appropriateness of Gastrointestinal Endoscopy European multicenter study. Gastrointest Endosc. 2005 Mar;61(3):378-84.</citation>
    <PMID>15758907</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Melicharkova A, Flemming J, Vanner S, Hookey L. A low-residue breakfast improves patient tolerance without impacting quality of low-volume colon cleansing prior to colonoscopy: a randomized trial. Am J Gastroenterol. 2013 Oct;108(10):1551-5. doi: 10.1038/ajg.2013.21.</citation>
    <PMID>24091500</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Full Liquid Diet vs Clear Liquid Diet for Colonoscopy Preparation: Preliminary Results. Gutkin E, et. al. ACG2011; Abstract P412</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Calderwood AH, Jacobson BC. Comprehensive validation of the Boston Bowel Preparation Scale. Gastrointest Endosc. 2010 Oct;72(4):686-92. doi: 10.1016/j.gie.2010.06.068.</citation>
    <PMID>20883845</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Agresti A, Coull BA, Approximate is better than &quot;exact&quot; for interval estimation of binomial proportions, The American Statistician 52:119-126, 1998.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones B, Jarvis P, Lewis JA, Ebbutt AF. Trials to assess equivalence: the importance of rigorous methods. BMJ. 1996 Jul 6;313(7048):36-9. Erratum in: BMJ 1996 Aug 31;313(7056):550.</citation>
    <PMID>8664772</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 23, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 1, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 3, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 1, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 1, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 3, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>San Antonio Military Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Luis X. Velez-Colon, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Gastroenterology Fellow(PGY5)</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Colorectal Cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Colonoscopy</keyword>
  <keyword>Adenoma Detection Rate</keyword>
  <keyword>Bowel Preparation</keyword>
  <keyword>Time to Cecal Intubation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

