<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02627469</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>KarolinskaII</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02627469</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Oral Hygiene Care and Microflora in Elderly Residents</brief_title>
  <official_title>Effect of Weekly Professional Oral Care, During 12 Months, on the Composition of the Oral Flora and Related Variables in Dependent Elderly Residents</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Karolinska Institutet</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>The Swedish Research Council</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Karolinska Institutet</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Objective: The effect of weekly professional oral care on the composition of the oral flora
      in dentate, dependent elderly residents was followed during a 12-month period.

      Background: Long-term, regular professional oral hygiene care reduces the total number of
      microorganisms and oral disease-related microorganisms. Less is known about the effect on the
      quality/composition of the remaining oral flora.

      Materials and methods: Thirty-three subjects were included in the study group and 35 in the
      control group. Dental status, presence of supragingival-plaque, labial minor gland secretion
      rate, and prescription medicines were recorded. Microbial samples, collected from
      supragingival plaque and the dorsum of the tongue, were analyzed using cultivation technique.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Ethics statement The study was approved by the Ethics Committee at the University of
      Gothenburg, Sweden (Permit Number 039/00).

      Study and control groups After giving an informed and written consent to participate, either
      by the subjects themselves or by a relative or a guardian, 68 subjects were recruited from
      two nursing homes for elderly persons. The nursing homes, belonging to the same institution
      and having the same leadership, are situated in the same area of the city. The study group
      was recruited from one of the nursing homes and consisted of 21 women and 12 men. The control
      group, recruited from the second nursing home, consisted of 23 women and 12 men. To be
      included in the study, the subjects had to have at least 10 natural teeth and no removable
      dentures and be able to follow simple instructions, such as open and close the mouth. The
      subjects were included in the study in the order they gave their informed consent and
      fulfilled the inclusion criteria. Throughout the study period, the subjects in both groups
      were eligible for dental care for dependent individuals, as regulated by law in Sweden,
      including an oral health care assessment free of charge, basic dental care at subsidized
      rates, and nursing home personnel trained in oral health care.

      Intervention The study group received professional oral care, once a week throughout the
      12-month study period, by either of two dental hygienists. The oral care was carried out in
      the residents´ private rooms with the participant sitting in his/her own chair or lying in
      bed. The treatment included brushing of the teeth, at labial and lingual sides, with use of
      an electric toothbrush (Oral-B Professional Care 7000) and a 1100 ppm sodium fluoride
      dentifrice (Zendium Classic, Opus Health Care AB/Zendium). Inter-dental cleaning was carried
      out using inter-dental brushes (TePe: TePe, Malmö, Sweden) and toothpicks (TePe Birch: TePe,
      Malmö, Sweden). Information and training in oral hygiene procedures were given to those in
      the study group capable to understand instructions.

      At the start of the intervention, each subject in the study group, as well as their main
      responsible nursing aid, received an electric toothbrush of the same kind as was used by the
      two dental hygienists (Oral-B Professional Care 7000), and instructions and training on how
      to use the brush. In the control group, the oral health care procedures followed the ordinary
      routines for the department.

      Collection of clinical data and samples for microbial analysis Clinical examinations,
      measurements of labial minor gland salivary secretion rate, and microbial samplings were
      performed between 9 and 12 am (by author KL K) and were carried out in the residents´ private
      rooms. All microbial sampling was performed in duplicate, one week apart. The clinical
      examination was performed at the first of the two duplicate sampling occasions. Plaque
      registration followed by the collection of supragingival plaque for microbial analysis was
      performed at four sites, in that order. The sites selected were interproximally the upper
      right first and second molars, the lower left first and second molars, the upper right second
      incisor and the canine, and the lower left second incisor and the canine. If one or more of
      these teeth were missing, the closest available site was selected. The measurement of the
      labial minor gland salivary secretion rate, followed by microbial sampling from the tongue,
      was performed in that order and at the end of the registration and sampling sessions.

      In both the study and control groups, clinical data, data on prescription medicines, the
      labial minor gland salivary secretion rate, and microbial samples were collected at the
      baseline and at the end of the 12-month study period. In the study group, additional plaque
      registration and sampling for microbial analysis were performed after 3, 6, and 9 months from
      the baseline.

      Clinical examination The clinical examination was carried out, in the light of an adjustable
      headlight, using a dental mirror and a dental probe. The number of natural teeth, clinically
      visible caries lesions and plaque were recorded. Plaque was recorded as no visible plaque
      (score 0), visible but thin plaque (score 1) or visible thick plaque (score 2). A mean of the
      plaque scores recorded at the four interproximal sites selected for registration was
      calculated.

      Prescription medicines Data on prescription medicines was collected from the residents´
      medical records.

      Labial minor gland salivary secretion rate For measurement of the labial minor gland salivary
      secretion rate, performed as described by Eliasson et al., the area of the lower labial
      mucosa was gently dried with a cotton pad. A pre-cut piece of a standard filter paper was
      then placed for 15 s near the midline approximately 3 mm from the outer border of the mucosa.
      The volume of liquid absorbed by the filter paper was measured using a calibrated Periotron®
      (8000, ProFlow™ Inc., Amityville, NY, USA). At each examination, four samples were collected
      from each subject and an individual mean was calculated.

      Microbial sampling and analysis Microbial samples were collected from the supragingival
      plaque and the dorsum of the tongue. An experienced laboratory assistant blinded to which
      group of subjects, study or control group, and to which of the examination occasions the
      samples were collected from, analyzed the samples.

      The supragingival plaque samples were collected using sterile toothpicks (TePe Birch) and
      pooled. The tongue samples were collected using sterile tweezers, cotton pellets and plastic
      spatulas. The spatula, with a circular hole 1.5 cm diameter, was placed on the back part of
      the dorsum. A cotton pellet, immersed in sampling fluid, was swept over the area inside the
      hole. The two samples were each transferred to 3.5 ml of transport medium VMGA III and
      processed within four hours.

      The analyses of the samples were performed as previously described using enriched blood agar
      plates and selective agar plates. The total number of microorganisms growing under anaerobic
      conditions, the total number and proportion of streptococci and the number and proportion of
      Streptococcus sanguinis/oralis and Streptococcus salivarius, both associated with good oral
      health, mutans streptococci, lactobacilli and Actinomyces spp, associated with dental caries,
      F. nucleatum, and P. intermedia/nigrescens, associated with gingival inflammation, P.
      gingivalis and A. actinomycetemcomitans, associated with periodontitis, Candida albicans,
      Staphylococcus aureus, and enteric rods, associated with mucosal and aspiratory infections,
      were calculated. The detection limit was 100 colony-forming units for all species except A.
      actinomycetemcomitans, where the detection limit was 10 colony-forming units. If possible,
      the number of microorganisms was calculated from their number on a plate giving 30 - 300
      colonies. A mean of the results from the duplicate samplings was calculated.

      Statistical methods To normalize the microbial data, the numbers were transformed
      logarithmically. Zero counts were treated as one colony forming unit/ml. Mean and median
      values and standard deviations were calculated. One-way ANOVA was used for the analysis of
      differences between the study and control groups. Two-way ANOVA was used for statistical
      analysis of differences at different time points within the two groups. Results were regarded
      statistically significant at p-values &lt; 0.05. Owing to the multiple influence aspect,
      isolated significances should be interpreted with some caution.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composition of the oral microflora</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Microbial samples were collected from the supragingival plaque and the dorsum of the tongue.
The total number of microorganisms growing under anaerobic conditions, the total number and proportion of streptococci, lactobacilli, Actinomyces spp, F. nucleatum, P. intermedia/nigrescens, P. gingivalis, A. actinomycetemcomitans, Candida albicans, Staphylococcus aureus, and enteric rods, were calculated.
The detection limit was 100 colony-forming units for all species except A. actinomycetemcomitans, where the detection limit was 10 colony-forming units. If possible, the number of microorganisms was calculated from their number on a plate giving 30 - 300 colonies. A mean of the results from the duplicate samplings was calculated.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of Labial minor gland salivary secretion</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>For measurement of the labial minor gland salivary secretion rate, the area of the lower labial mucosa was gently dried with a cotton pad. A pre-cut piece of a standard filter paper was then placed for 15 s near the midline approximately 3 mm from the outer border of the mucosa. The volume of liquid absorbed by the filter paper was measured using a calibrated Periotron® (8000, ProFlow™ Inc., Amityville, NY, USA). At each examination, four samples were collected from each subject and an individual mean was calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Presence of supragingival-plaque</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Plaque was recorded as no visible plaque (score 0), visible but thin plaque (score 1) or visible thick plaque (score 2). A mean of the plaque scores recorded at the four interproximal sites selected for registration was calculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dental status</measure>
    <time_frame>12 month</time_frame>
    <description>A clinical examination was carried out, in the light of an adjustable headlight, using a dental mirror and a dental probe. The number of natural teeth and clinically visible caries lesions were recorded.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Prescription medicines</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Data on prescription medicines was collected from the residents´ medical records.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">68</enrollment>
  <condition>Pneumonia</condition>
  <condition>Aspiration</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Common oral hygiene help administered by nursing staff</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Extended professional oral hygiene care Electric toothbrush (Oral-B Professional Care 7000) 1100 ppm sodium fluoride dentifrice (Zendium Classic, Opus Health Care AB/Zendium)</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Extended professional oral hygiene care</intervention_name>
    <description>Weekly professional oral hygiene performed by dental hygienists</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Electric toothbrush (Oral-B Professional Care 7000)</intervention_name>
    <description>Weekly professional oral hygiene performed by dental hygienists</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>1100 ppm sodium fluoride dentifrice (Zendium Classic)</intervention_name>
    <description>Weekly professional oral hygiene performed by dental hygienists</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria

          -  10 or more natural teeth

          -  no removable dentures

          -  no or mild cognitive impairments

        Exclusion criteria

          -  less than 10 natural teeth

          -  removable dentures

          -  severe cognitive impairments
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Inger Wårdh, Assoc prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Karolinska Institutet</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>February 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 4, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 8, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 11, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 22, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 22, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 23, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Karolinska Institutet</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Inger Wårdh</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>PhD Associate professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Microbiota</keyword>
  <keyword>aged</keyword>
  <keyword>oral health</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Pneumonia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fluorides</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sodium Fluoride</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Listerine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Published data will not be able to connect with an specific individual but each participant is allowed to by request take part of their own data.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

