<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02628730</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BWI-IIS-386</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NHS REC</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02628730</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pulmonary Vein Reconnection Following Ablation Index-guided Ablation: a Success Evaluation</brief_title>
  <acronym>PRAISE</acronym>
  <official_title>Pulmonary Vein Reconnection Following Ablation Index-guided Ablation: a Success Evaluation (PRAISE)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Liverpool Heart and Chest Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Biosense Webster, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Liverpool Heart and Chest Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Atrial fibrillation (AF) is the commonest condition affecting the rhythm of the heart.
      Tablets to try to normalise the heart rhythm rarely work well. As a result, doctors have
      devised a treatment called catheter ablation in which special wires are used to deliver heat
      energy (called ablation lesions) on the inside surface of the heart. Unfortunately, in many
      patients (almost 1 in 2), some of these ablation lesions recover, and this leads to AF
      recurrence. Many of these patients then need a second procedure to deliver further ablation
      at these recovered areas.

      Recent research has shown that monitoring of heat delivery with a factor called Ablation
      Index may be useful in predicting which ablation lesions are less likely to recover.
      Therefore, we aim to carry out AF ablation guided with Ablation Index (AI) and observe
      whether this will be associated with better durability of ablation lesions, and thereby
      better freedom from AF.

      This study will include patients with persistent AF, those whose AF episode(s) last for
      longer than seven days. All patients participating in the study will undergo an initial
      ablation treatment guided by ablation Index . All patients will undergo a repeat procedure
      8-10 weeks after their initial treatment. Any gaps found during the second procedure will be
      closed again by delivery of ablation.

      All participants will be issued with a simple to use handheld heart rhythm monitor, and asked
      to make a 30-second recording of their heart rhythm each day and also whenever they have
      symptoms. The monitor stores these recordings and they will be downloaded at review
      appointments arranged 6 weeks, 3 months, 6 months and 12 months after the initial ablation
      procedure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study is a prospective cohort study in 40 patients with Persistent AF. It will comprise
      two groups:

        1. Active Group (AI guided ablation): An initial pulmonary vein isolation (PVI) procedure
           will be performed guided by AI targets. All patients (regardless of AF recurrence) will
           undergo a repeat EP study at 8-10 weeks to identify and re-ablate site(s) of PV
           reconnection

        2. Historical control group (Contact Force Guided Ablation): will be formed by the 40
           patients enrolled to the repeat study arm of the PRESSURE study (ClinicalTrials.gov
           Identifier: NCT01942408). All 40 patients underwent contact force-guided PVI followed by
           a repeat EP study after 8-10 weeks.

      End-points

      Primary outcome measure:

      The proportion of patients with pulmonary vein (PV) reconnection seen at repeat EP study

      Secondary outcome measures:

        -  The proportion of reconnected PVs seen at repeat electrophysiology (EP) study

        -  The proportion of patients maintaining freedom from atrial tachyarrhythmia for 12 months
           (after an initial 12 week blanking period)

        -  QOL 6 and 12 months after initial ablation, as quantified by the validated atrial
           Fibrillation Effect on QualiTy-of-life (AFEQT) and EQ-5D-5Lquestionnaires.

        -  Rates of major complications occurring within 60 days after a PVI procedure, measured in
           composite numbers and percentage.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients with PV reconnection seen at repeat EP study</measure>
    <time_frame>8-10 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of reconnected PVs seen at repeat EP study</measure>
    <time_frame>8-10 weeks</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The proportion of patients maintaining freedom from atrial fibrillation.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of Life (QOL) using score of AFEQT Questionnaire.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>AFEQT score will be obtained as the sum of units on the questionnaire's scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>QOL using score of EQ-5D-5L Questionnaire.</measure>
    <time_frame>6 and 12 months</time_frame>
    <description>EQ-5D-5L score will be obtained as the sum of units on the questionnaire's scale.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Major complications percent.</measure>
    <time_frame>Occurring within 60 days after a PVI procedure.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">40</enrollment>
  <condition>Atrial Fibrillation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Ablation Index Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>PVI using radiofrequency ablation (RFA) guided by Ablation Index.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Reference Group (Contact Force Group)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>That group will be formed by the 40 patients who underwent mandatory repeat EPS 8-10 weeks following contact force guided PVI in the PRESSURE study (ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: NCT01942408). RFA ablation data from reference group (Contact Force Group) will be compared with those obtained from the Ablation Index Group.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PVI using ThermoCool® SmartTouch® Catheter</intervention_name>
    <description>PVI using RFA, using ThermoCool® SmartTouch® Catheter (Biosense Webster Inc., CA, US), guided by Ablation Index.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Ablation Index Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>RFA ablation data comparison</intervention_name>
    <description>Ablation data from previous ablations, using ThermoCool® SmartTouch® Catheter (Biosense Webster Inc., CA, US), that members of this group had in the past, will be compared with those of the Active Comparator Group.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Reference Group (Contact Force Group)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged over 18 years

          -  Persistent AF (defined, according to the ESC/EHRA Guidelines for the Management of
             Atrial Fibrillation 2010, as AF episode that either lasts longer than 7 days or
             requires termination by cardioversion, either with drugs or by direct current
             cardioversion (DCC) ).

          -  Symptomatic in spite of drug treatment

          -  Due to undergo pulmonary vein isolation by RF ablation

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Inability or unwillingness to receive oral anticoagulation with a Vitamin K antagonist
             (VKA) or non-VKA (NOAC) agent

          -  Previous catheter or surgical ablation procedure for AF

          -  Unwillingness or inability to complete the required follow-up arrangements

          -  Current pattern of paroxysmal AF

          -  Long standing persistent AF (continuous AF longer than 12 months before ablation)

          -  Prior prosthetic mitral valve replacement or severe structural cardiac abnormality

          -  Known infiltrative cardiomyopathy

          -  Known severe left ventricular systolic function (ejection fraction &lt;35%)

          -  Pregnancy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Dhiraj Gupta, MD, DM, FRCP</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Liverpool Heart and Chest Hospital, Liverpool, UK</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ahmed A Hussein, MRCP, MSc</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Liverpool Heart and Chest Hospital, Liverpool, UK</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Moloy Das</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Freeman Hospital, Newcastle, UK</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Antonio D Russo</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Centro Cardiologico Monzino</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Centro Cardiologico Monzino, IRCCS,</name>
      <address>
        <city>Milan</city>
        <zip>20138</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Liverpool Heart &amp; Chest Hospital NHS Foundation Trust</name>
      <address>
        <city>Liverpool</city>
        <zip>L14 3PE</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Freeman Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newcastle Upon Tyne</city>
        <zip>NE7 7DN</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01942408?term=Dhiraj&amp;rank=2</url>
    <description>The Effect of Early Repeat Atrial Fibrillation (AF) Ablation on AF Recurrence (PRESSURE) Study</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Das M, Wynn GJ, Morgan M, Lodge B, Waktare JE, Todd DM, Hall MC, Snowdon RL, Modi S, Gupta D. Recurrence of atrial tachyarrhythmia during the second month of the blanking period is associated with more extensive pulmonary vein reconnection at repeat electrophysiology study. Circ Arrhythm Electrophysiol. 2015 Aug;8(4):846-52. doi: 10.1161/CIRCEP.115.003095. Epub 2015 Jun 24.</citation>
    <PMID>26108982</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 20, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 9, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 11, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 3, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 3, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 5, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Atrial Fibrillation</keyword>
  <keyword>Ablation</keyword>
  <keyword>Pulmonary vein isolation</keyword>
  <keyword>Ablation Index</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Atrial Fibrillation</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

