<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02621268</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>820766</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02621268</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Minimally Invasive Imagery With Indocyanine Green</brief_title>
  <acronym>ICG</acronym>
  <official_title>A Pilot &amp; Feasibility Study of the Imaging Potential of Indocyanine Green in Subjects Undergoing Minimally Invasive Thoracic Surgery Presenting With Thoracic Nodules</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Determine if ICG administered pre-operatively, then imaged intraoperatively using our
      cameras, will aid in the identification of a suspected thoracic nodules, margins, lymph nodes
      and satellite nodules during minimally invasive procedures. The investigators intend on
      enrolling 48 Subjects in this study. The study is focusing on patients presenting with
      suspected thoracic cancers who are considered to be good minimally invasive surgical
      candidates
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      According to the World Health Organization, lung cancer is the most common cause of
      cancer-related death in men and women, and is responsible for 1.3 million deaths worldwide
      annually as of 2004.

      Surgery remains the best option for patients presenting with operable Stage I or II cancers,
      however the five year survival rate for these candidates remains at a dismal 53% for Stage I
      and 32% for Stage II (1). The high rates of recurrence suggest that surgeons are unable to
      completely detect and remove primary tumor nodules in a satisfactory manner as well as
      lingering metastases in sentinel lymph nodes. By ensuring a negative margin through
      near-infrared imagery it would be possible for us to improve the rates of recurrence free
      patients and thus overall survival.

      The use of an ICG probe will allow for the operating field and lung tissue to be observed in
      real-time.

      ICG has been used in the clinical settings since 1957. There is a wealth of data available
      attesting to the safety of this drug injected at its current clinically indicated dosing
      level. ICG has been shown to preferentially uptake in esophageal tumors as opposed to
      surrounding epithelial lumen after one minute of IV exposure (2). Additionally, the same
      group reported being able to better characterize the vascularization of the tumor to further
      clarify the invasiveness of the cancer. ICG usage has been shown to be safe in a similar
      clinical setting by the Gotoh group, who used ICG to detect and characterize bullous and
      emphysematous lesion of the lung in video assisted thoracoscopic surgeries (VATS) with
      Infrared Thoracoscopy that were not previously detectable by white light (3).

      The currently proposed trial is a single center, open-label pilot/observational cohort study.
      Patients with a diagnosis of resectable thoracic nodule/mass who are presumed to be
      resectable via minimally invasive surgery as determined by pre-operative assessment at the
      Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania will be included.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2016</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Ability of imaging system to detect expression of ICG in nodule/mass (i.e. tumor) and discern uptake of dye by tumor</measure>
    <time_frame>36 months</time_frame>
    <description>Detected with imaging probe during minimally invasive procedure</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence rates of all adverse events, treatment-emergent adverse events, and adverse device events from time of ICG administration through participants' first, post-operative appointment with surgeon</measure>
    <time_frame>36 Months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">48</enrollment>
  <condition>Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Indocyanine Green</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dosage calculated by weight of individual, 5mg/kg.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Indocyanine Green</intervention_name>
    <description>Infusion of ICG 24 hours prior to surgery</description>
    <arm_group_label>Indocyanine Green</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ICG</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Adult patients over 18 years of age

          2. Patients presenting with a thoracic nodule presumed to be resectable cancer on
             pre-operative assessment

          3. Good minimally invasive operative candidates as determined by a thoracic oncology
             multidisciplinary team

          4. Subject capable of giving informed consent and participating in the process of
             consent.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnant women as determined by urinary or serum beta human chorionic gonadotropin
             (hCG) within 72 hours of surgery

          2. Subjects with a history of iodide allergies

          3. At-risk patient populations

               1. Homeless patients

               2. Patients with drug or alcohol dependence

               3. Children and neonates

               4. Patients unable to participate in the consent process
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sunil Singhal, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mountain CF, Dresler CM. Regional lymph node classification for lung cancer staging. Chest. 1997 Jun;111(6):1718-23.</citation>
    <PMID>9187199</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Kimura T, Muguruma N, Ito S, Okamura S, Imoto Y, Miyamoto H, Kaji M, Kudo E. Infrared fluorescence endoscopy for the diagnosis of superficial gastric tumors. Gastrointest Endosc. 2007 Jul;66(1):37-43.</citation>
    <PMID>17591472</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gotoh M, Yamamoto Y, Igai H, Chang S, Huang C, Yokomise H. Clinical application of infrared thoracoscopy to detect bullous or emphysematous lesions of the lung. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2007 Dec;134(6):1498-501.</citation>
    <PMID>18023672</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 1, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 1, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 3, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 20, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sunil Singhall</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Director, Thoracic Surgery Research Laboratory</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

