<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02623023</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>PAVE-001</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02623023</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prophylaxis for Anti-VEGF-induced IOP Elevation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Brimonidine/Timolol Fixed Combination Prophylaxis for Intraocular Pressure Elevation Following Intravitreal Injection of Antivascular Endothelial Growth Factor</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>McMaster University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>McMaster University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of our study is to determine the effect of prophylactic treatment with
      brimonidine/timolol fixed combination (Combigan®, Allergan; Dublin, IRL) or placebo therapy
      (Refresh tears®, Allergan; Dublin, IRL) on long-term IOP measurements in patients receiving
      serial intravitreal injection of 0.5 mg ranibizumab (0.05 mL) with six months follow-up.
      Intraocular pressure measurements will be correlated with changes on ancillary testing
      (Humphrey 24-2 visual field testing and optical coherence tomography (OCT) of the optic nerve
      head (ONH). Our study would be the first large, prospective, randomized double-blind
      placebo-controlled trial to examine the relationship between anti-vascular endothelial growth
      factor (VEGF) therapy and sustained ocular hypertension.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The recent introduction of antivascular endothelial growth factor (anti-VEGF) agents has
      quickly progressed to become the standard of care for several ocular diseases. Between 2006
      and 2010, anti-VEGF treatment for neovascular age-related macular degeneration (AMD) was
      initiated in over 620 000 eyes of Medicare beneficiaries in the United States. This paradigm
      shift in retinal therapy stems from evidence that VEGF regulates angiogenesis and vascular
      permeability, processes which characterize the pathophysiology of diabetic retinopathy and
      AMD. Several large multicenter, randomized clinical trials have demonstrated that patients
      with neovascular AMD and clinically significant macular edema (CSME) benefit from frequent
      intravitreal anti-VEGF injections, particularly with ranibizumab . Ranibizumab is a humanized
      monoclonal antibody Fab fragment (IgG1) that inhibits all identified VEGF isoforms, including
      VEGF165, VEGF121 and VEGF110.

      Rigorous study has consistently demonstrated a good relative safety profile for anti-VEGF
      agents. While transient rise in intraocular pressure (IOP) is a known effect immediately
      following intravitreal injection (IVI), sustained IOP elevation was not initially reported in
      patients undergoing anti-VEGF therapy. It was not until post-hoc analysis of the MARINA ,
      ANCHOR AND VIEW trials that a significant long-term effect on IOP from ranibizumab was
      detected. However, there are increasing reports in the literature documenting this
      phenomenon.

      Bakri et al. reported a case series of ocular hypertension (OHT) (IOP ranging 30 - 50 mm Hg)
      after 0.05 mL intravitreal ranibizumab, which persisted and required treatment. Kahook et al.
      published a case series of six patients undergoing anti-VEGF therapy who developed persistent
      OHT, two of whom had a prior diagnosis of glaucoma/glaucoma suspect. In a larger,
      retrospective review of 215 patients being treated with IVI by Good et al., 6% of patients
      required medical or laser treatment for sustained IOP elevation. Subgroup analysis revealed
      that patients with a history of glaucoma had a substantially higher likelihood of
      experiencing sustained IOP elevation, despite a lower median number of IVI than the
      non-glaucoma group. In a retrospective study by Choi et al. , seven of 127 patients (5.5%)
      developed sustained OHT in the study eye, whereas the fellow eye demonstrated stable IOP. Two
      other large retrospective series have reported similar incidence of persistent IOP elevation,
      and review of the literature reveals an incidence of 3.45% to 11.6% in patients with
      neovascular AMD. Post-hoc analysis of a large, multi-center randomized clinical trial for
      treatment of diabetic CSME found the ranibizumab group had a 3-fold increased risk of
      sustained IOP elevation at 3 years compared to the sham-injection group. This study did not
      enroll patients with a history of glaucoma/glaucoma suspect, thus could not define their risk
      ratio. A prospective study of 217 eyes undergoing anti-VEGF IVI found that persistent IOP
      elevation was a frequent outcome, and that the IOP peak was significantly correlated with the
      number of injections. Further, patients with prior diagnosis of glaucoma/glaucoma suspect had
      an incidence of 12.9% of sustained OHT, compared with 3.2% in the non-glaucoma subgroup.

      The pathogenesis of persistent ocular hypertension has not yet been elucidated, but may be
      secondary to chemical damage to the trabecular meshwork from the anti-VEGF agents themselves,
      or mechanically by micro-particle obstruction. Some studies indicate that the number of IVI
      is an independent risk factor for the development of long-term ocular hypertension , and that
      patients with pre-existing glaucoma are particularly vulnerable.

      Transient IOP elevation following anti-VEGF injection has been noted at 30 minutes
      post-injection and rarely requires anterior chamber paracentesis for treatment . Though this
      rise in IOP elevation is expected to return to baseline by 1-hour post-IVI, the long-term
      consequences of this phenomenon are unknown. One proposed mechanism for this transient effect
      on IOP is increased volume of intraocular contents after injection . Gismondi et al found a
      significant relationship between shorter axial length and higher transient IOP following
      intravitreal ranibizumab. One group designed a randomized controlled trial to evaluate the
      effect of preventative treatment for this short-term rise in IOP. Brimonidine/timolol fixed
      combination (Combigan®, Allergan; Dublin, IRL) was administered twice a day on the day prior
      to injection and on the day of treatment, and reduced the rapid increase in post-injection
      IOP in a safe and effective manner. However, this study did not evaluate the incidence of
      persistent OHT.

      As IOP elevation is strongly linked with the development of glaucoma, this potential outcome
      in patients undergoing anti-VEGF therapy warrants attention. The data published on this topic
      to date is primarily comprised of retrospective chart reviews, case series, and post-hoc
      analysis of the MARINA, ANCHOR and Diabetic Retinopathy Clinical Research Network 2010 and
      VIEW trials. Many studies reveal inconsistent methodology in terms of IOP measurement and IVI
      technique. Ultimately, there is no consensus on which factors may predispose patients to the
      development of iatrogenic IOP elevation following anti-VEGF therapy. Further, prophylactic
      treatment for sustained OHT has not been prospectively studied.

      Currently, there are no guidelines for IOP monitoring in patients undergoing anti-VEGF
      therapy. Our study aims to define a treatment algorithm for the monitoring and prophylaxis of
      anti-VEGF-related iatrogenic ocular hypertension. This may also shed some light into the
      possible mechanism of post-injection IOP spike. Further, our research may help identify a
      subgroup of patients vulnerable to long-term sequelae as a result of this phenomenon.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Not yet recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">June 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>long-term intraocular pressure measurements</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>long-term IOP measurements in patients receiving serial IVI of 0.5 mg ranibizumab (0.05 mL) with six months follow-up</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">107</enrollment>
  <condition>Ocular Hypertension</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Combigan group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Combigan will be administered twice a day on the day before the intraocular injection and once in the morning of the injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Refresh tears</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Refresh tears will be administered twice a day on the day before the intraocular injection and once in the morning of the injection</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Combigan</intervention_name>
    <description>brimonidine/timolol fixed combination (Combigan®, Allergan; Dublin, IRL)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Combigan group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>(Combigan®</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Refresh tears</intervention_name>
    <description>This is a placebo group. Refresh tears®, Allergan; Dublin, IRL, is a lubricant eye drop that keeps they eye hydrated</description>
    <arm_group_label>Refresh tears</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age equal to or greater than 18 years

          -  Baseline visual acuity between 20/40 and 20/200 in the eye chart score

          -  Diagnosed with either, CNV secondary to neovascular AMD, CSME secondary to diabetes
             mellitus (DM), or CSME secondary to retinal vein occlusion (RVO)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Baseline IOP ≥30 mmHg

          -  Diagnosed with Neovascular glaucoma

          -  Patients unable to undergo Humphrey 24-2 visual field testing or optical coherence
             tomography

          -  Active ocular inflammatory disease including uveitis

          -  Prior retinal or vitreous surgery including vitrectomy, gas tamponade, silicone oil
             tamponade or scleral buckling

          -  Prior surgical management of glaucoma including trabeculectomy or filtering device

          -  Active hepatitis or clinically significant liver disease

          -  Clinically significant kidney disease

          -  History of penetrating injury or severe ocular trauma

          -  Concurrent enrolment in other clinical trial
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>65 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Prima Moinul, MD</last_name>
    <phone>905-573-7777</phone>
    <phone_ext>38070</phone_ext>
    <email>prima.moinul@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Sarah J Mullen, MD</last_name>
    <phone>(905) 573-7777</phone>
    <phone_ext>38260</phone_ext>
    <email>sarah.mullen@medportal.ca</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 6, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 4, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 7, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 5, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 5, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 9, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Ocular Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brimonidine Tartrate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Brimonidine Tartrate, Timolol Maleate Drug Combination</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Endothelial Growth Factors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

