<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01804517</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IMPACT</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01804517</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Impact of a Nurse for Migraine Management: the IMPACT Project</brief_title>
  <acronym>IMPACT</acronym>
  <official_title>Impact of a Nursing Intervention on the Clinical Evolution of Patients at a University Migraine Clinic</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Notre-Dame Hospital, Montreal, Quebec, Canada</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Allergan</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Notre-Dame Hospital, Montreal, Quebec, Canada</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Headache disorders are prevalent, disabling, under recognized, under diagnosed and under
      treated. Migraine has a prevalence of 10% in men and 25% in women in Canada. The treatment of
      migraine is based on patient education (lifestyle habit modification, trigger avoidance), and
      pharmacological acute treatment and prophylaxis. A multidisciplinary approach allows a
      repartition of tasks between different health professionals.

      In a 2010 meeting, the Canadian Headache Society members supported the concept of Headache
      Centers, and a headache nurse was judged as an essential component of such centers.

      Gaul has reviewed the structured multidisciplinary approach that could be used in a headache
      centre and the existing studies using such structures. Five studies did include a headache
      nurse. No study did observe the impact of a nurse only. Resources in medical care are
      limited. One study did use a program of 96 hours, which does not seem realistic on the
      long-term and for a large pool of patients in a public hospital. Patients are not always able
      to pay for paramedical help such as physiotherapy and psychotherapy. Even if they do, finding
      a specialized therapist for chronic headache is difficult. Defining the role of a nurse and
      demonstrating the impact on patient care is therefore a first step in the concept of a
      headache center. Possible roles of a headache nurse according to Gaul are patient education,
      follow-up of the treatment plan, addressing patient queries, and monitoring of patient
      progress. The headache nurse may also participate in research projects. In a hospital
      Headache Clinic, the nurse may be involved in intra-venous treatments and blood sampling for
      research.

      In summary, evidence to demonstrate the impact of a nurse in a headache clinic is lacking. We
      propose to study this aspect prospectively. A study with positive findings would encourage
      health ministers to fund and support headache nurses for headache centers across Canada for
      headache management. Chronic headache and therefore chronic migraine would be a focus of such
      centers, since most patients seen in specialized centers are chronic.

      HYPOTHESIS: The addition of a headache nurse to the headache team will help the CHUM Migraine
      Clinic to improve treatment outcome, and reduce the burden of headache. This
      multidisciplinary approach will also allow a higher efficiency of the team.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      STUDY DESIGN:

      The goal of this study is to compare two treatment approaches for migraineurs. The first
      approach will be based on the physician only and is limited to fixed appointments (control
      group). The second approach will be based on a team involving a headache nurse (active group)
      who will participate in patient education and follow-up. The goal is to improve patient
      outcome but also physician productivity.

      First 100 patients (control group, phase 1): patients with episodic and chronic migraine will
      be screened, sign consent and be enrolled. They will be seen by the physician only, without
      the nurse's support. This situation will reproduce the actual conditions at the clinic.
      During this phase, the nurse will be involved in the follow-up of known patients (who will
      not be included in the protocol) and data collection. She will develop her headache
      management abilities and help the physicians to develop some educational tools for patients.

      Following 100 patients (active group, phase 2) : patients with episodic and chronic migraine
      will be screened and enroled. They will be seen by the physician and nurse team, with a
      treatment plan tailored to specific needs including regular scheduled visits, follow-up of
      chronification factors and educational sessions. Phone call follow-ups will be planned.
      Patients will have an easier and quicker contact with the team in an emergency situation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>1 Year</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Hit-6 score change</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>HIT-6 score change between inclusion and 8 month.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of moderate and severe headache days</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Variation in the frequency of moderate or severe headache days per month between the first, fourth and eighth month after inclusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of headache days</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the frequency of headache days, all severity included, between the first month and the seventh and eight months following inclusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Chronic headache status</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of patients who were chronic (more than 3 months with &gt;15 headache days per month, retrospective) at entry and were episodic at one year (according to calendars).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medication overuse</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of patients with medication overuse at entry and were not overusing anymore at 8 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acute medication intake</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in the number of days per month with acute medication use between the first month after inclusion and the seventh and eight months following inclusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Efficacy of acute treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>at 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of patients who succeeded in finding a successful and properly used acute treatment at month eight, according to four criteria: efficacy, reliability, absence of recurrence, absence of significant side effects.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Response rate to prophylactics</measure>
    <time_frame>at 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of patients who did complete a successful (&gt;50% response and no significant side-effects) preventive treatment trial at month eight after inclusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Short Form 12 score</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline and 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Change in SF-12 scores between inclusion and third visit. SF-12 is a quality of life questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Visits to the emergency department</measure>
    <time_frame>over 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Number of headache-related emergency department visits per patient during the year following their inclusion.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Severe adverse effects from treatments</measure>
    <time_frame>over 1 year</time_frame>
    <description>Percent of patients with a severe adverse effect from a treatment (necessitating hospitalization, emergency visit or specific treatment).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phone calls returned</measure>
    <time_frame>per 1 month</time_frame>
    <description>Number of phone calls returned per month</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient satisfaction</measure>
    <time_frame>at 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Satisfaction of patients, evaluated by a customized questionnaire.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Phone call return delay</measure>
    <time_frame>for each phone call, mean</time_frame>
    <description>Mean delay for returning the call (number of week days between the date of the call and the date of the return).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Global improvement</measure>
    <time_frame>at 8 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluation of physician of the global improvement of the patient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">200</enrollment>
  <condition>Migraine Without Aura</condition>
  <condition>Migraine With Aura</condition>
  <condition>Chronic Migraine</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physician based approach</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients will be managed as usual at the clinic without the intervention of the nurse.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Physician and nurse</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients will be managed with the help of the nurse for education and follow-up.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients followed at the migraine clinic at the Notre-Dame Hospital in Montreal
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Age 18 or more

          -  Diagnosis of migraine, chronic or episodic, at the first visit. We expect the majority
             of patients to suffer form frequent or chronic migraine.

          -  Consent to participate in the CHUM Migraine Clinic IMPACT project.

          -  For future post-hoc analysis, groups will be stratified according to baseline headache
             frequency (all severity included), assessed retrospectively at the first visit:

               -  &lt;6 headache days per month,

               -  6 to 14 headache days per month

               -  15 or more headache days per month

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Patients whom first headache diagnosis is not migraine (for example post-traumatic
             headache, cluster headache, trigeminal neuralgia, facial pain).

          -  Women with ongoing or planned pregnancy.

          -  Patient with an active psychiatric condition (needing hospitalisation or psychosis).

          -  Patient with mental retardation impairing assessment or follow-up.

          -  Patient with an active medical condition which may lead to frequent hospitalisations
             (eg active cancer, organ graft, hemodialysis etc). This will be determined and
             detailed by the evaluating physician.

          -  Active drug addiction or alcoholism.

          -  Active follow-up at a pain clinic.

          -  Patient speaking a language other than french and incapable to communicate in a
             reliable way.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Leroux, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>FRCPC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hôpital Notre-Dame</name>
      <address>
        <city>Montreal</city>
        <state>Quebec</state>
        <zip>H2L 4M1</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 23, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 2, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 5, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 6, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 6, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 8, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Notre-Dame Hospital, Montreal, Quebec, Canada</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Elizabeth Leroux</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>M.D. Neurologist, FRCPC</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>migraine</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Migraine Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Migraine with Aura</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Migraine without Aura</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

