<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01805024</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SNT-I-015</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>FDA-OPD 5076</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01805024</nct_id>
    <nct_alias>NCT02326831</nct_alias>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Congenital Muscular Dystrophy Ascending Multiple Dose Cohort Study Analyzing Pharmacokinetics at Three Dose Levels In Children and Adolescents With Assessment of Safety and Tolerability of Omigapil (CALLISTO)</brief_title>
  <acronym>CALLISTO</acronym>
  <official_title>Congenital Muscular Dystrophy Ascending Multiple Dose Cohort Study Analyzing Pharmacokinetics at Three Dose Levels In Children and Adolescents With Assessment of Safety and Tolerability of Omigapil (CALLISTO)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Santhera Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Santhera Pharmaceuticals</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of the study is to establish the pharmacokinetic profile of omigapil in
      paediatric and adolescent patients with CMD and to evaluate the safety and tolerability of
      omigapil.

      Funding source - FDA OOPD
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 29, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 5, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Primary objective: to establish the pharmacokinetic profile of omigapil at a range of doses in paediatric and adolescent patients with CMD.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 4 and Week 8</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Secondary objective: to evaluate the safety and tolerability of omigapil at a range of doses in paediatric and adolescent patients.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 4, 8 and 12</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Tertiary objective: to establish the feasibility of conducting disease-relevant clinical assessments in paediatric and adolescent patients with CMD to aid in the design of future studies</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 12 and 16</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">20</enrollment>
  <condition>Congenital Muscular Dystrophy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Omigapil</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Omigapil</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Omigapil</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Ambulatory and non-ambulatory patients from age 5 - 16 years (5 years old or more and
             less than 17 years old) at time of screening with a clinical picture (see below)
             consistent with Ullrich CMD or MDC1A (LAMA2/merosin deficient CMD)

          -  Under regular review at a neuromuscular centre

          -  On adequate double-barrier contraception (if of child-bearing potential)

          -  Stable on any allowed concomitant medications for 1 month prior to run in phase

        For patients with Ullrich CMD - required clinical picture:

          -  Muscle weakness: (inability to walk or, if patient is still ambulatory, inability to
             run and &gt; 5 s for 10 m walk)

          -  FVC 30 - 80% of the predicted value and confirmed at Screening and Baseline visit(s)

        Genetic and Pathology:

        • Molecular diagnosis of collagen VI related myopathy, defined by one dominant or two
        recessive COL6A1, COL6A2 or COL6A3 mutation(s) known to cause the clinical picture,

        OR

        • Histological diagnosis showing (i) absent or significantly decreased expression of
        collagen VI in muscle (overall reduction or basal lamina specific) or (ii) absent or
        significantly abnormal matrix in skin fibroblast culture

        For patients with LAMA2 deficient CMD (MDC1A) - required clinical picture:

          -  Muscle weakness: Inability to walk; if patient is still ambulatory, inability to run
             and &gt; 5 s for 10 m walk.

          -  FVC 30 - 80% of the predicted value and confirmed at Screening and Baseline visit(s)

        Genetics and Pathology:

        • Either: 2 identified pathologic or probable pathologic mutations in LAMA2 gene

        OR:

        • 1 identified pathologic or probable pathologic mutation in LAMA 2 gene with evidence of
        decrease in laminin alpha 2 staining on muscle or skin biopsy

        OR:

        • Evidence of decrease in laminin alpha 2 staining on muscle or skin biopsy with matching
        clinical phenotype and no suspicion of alpha dystroglycanopathy (aDG-RD) (clinically or by
        staining on muscle biopsy)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Use of any investigational drug other than the study medication within 12 weeks of
             study start.

          -  Recurrent hospitalisation for chest infections in previous 2 years (≥2 per year)

          -  Patients with respiratory parameters (eg: low pulmonary function test value i.e. &lt;30%
             or need for brief course of daytime non-invasive ventilation) currently affected by
             short term medications, or acute illness/ conditions (conduct baseline assessments
             when the patient has recovered and no longer taking acute medication)

          -  Any need for surgery (scoliosis, gastrostomy, other) in the preceding 24 weeks or
             foreseen during the course of the study.

          -  Patient has an intercurrent significant medical condition or situation which in the
             opinion of the Investigator or the study Medical Monitor may put the patient at
             significant risk, confound the study results or interfere significantly with the
             patient's participation in the study

          -  Failure to thrive, defined as:

          -  Falling 20 percentiles (20/100) in body weight in the 12 weeks preceding
             Screening/Baseline (based on family report of weight loss and acquiring relevant
             medical records)

          -  In patients below the 3rd percentile, any further drop in body weight percentile in
             the 12 weeks preceding Screening/Baseline (based on family report of weight loss and
             acquiring relevant medical records)

          -  Weight less than 17kg at Baseline

          -  Morbidly obese or grossly overweight (≥86 percentile BMI in children)

          -  History of epilepsy or on antiepileptic medication at Screening/Baseline

          -  Diabetes

          -  On daytime Non Invasive Ventilation (NIV)

          -  Intake of prohibited medication (as listed in Appendix I)

          -  Anticipated need for anesthesia during the course of this study

          -  Patients with renal impairment defined as urinary protein concentration ≥ 0.2 g/L

          -  Patients with moderate to severe hepatic impairment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>16 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NINDS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 4, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 4, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 5, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 2, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 2, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 5, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Muscular Dystrophies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

