<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01805869</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>130033</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13-D-0033</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01805869</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tooth and Tissue Sample Collection During Wisdom Teeth Removal</brief_title>
  <official_title>Diagnosis and Treatment of Patients in Need of Third Molar Removal and Oral Specimen Acquisition</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (NIDCR)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - The third molars (wisdom teeth) normally grow in during late adolescence or early
      adulthood. Many people need or choose to have these teeth removed with oral surgery.
      Normally, the removed teeth and tissue are thrown away as medical waste. However, oral health
      researchers want to collect the teeth and tissue for research. They also want to encourage
      dentists at the National Institutes of Health to improve their skills in oral surgery. This
      study will collect the teeth and tissue of people who need to have oral surgery to remove
      their wisdom teeth.

      Objectives:

        -  To provide continued dental skills training for dentists at the National Institutes of
           Health.

        -  To collect teeth and tissue samples following wisdom tooth removal surgery.

      Eligibility:

      - Individuals between 16 and 50 who need to have their wisdom teeth removed.

      Design:

        -  This study will involve a minimum of three visits. There will be a screening visit, a
           surgery visit, and at least one follow-up visit.

        -  Participants will be screened with a physical exam and medical history. A full dental
           exam with x-rays will be given to evaluate the need for surgery.

        -  At the second visit, participants will have oral surgery to remove their wisdom teeth.
           The teeth and tissue removed during the surgery will be collected for study.

        -  Participants will receive drugs to control the pain after surgery. They will also be
           able to contact a dentist if there are any problems.

        -  Between 7 and 21 days after surgery, participants will have a followup visit to check
           the healing. If they are having no problems, this will be the last visit. If there are
           any postsurgery issues, they will be scheduled for additional visits as needed.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective

      The objective of this protocol is to evaluate and provide treatment for subjects who have a
      clinical indication for the routine extraction of dental third molar wisdom teeth with the
      aim to allow investigators to maintain their expertise in dental clinical care, gain
      additional knowledge about oral health and to utilize surgical waste collected from these
      patients for research studies.

      Study Population

      The protocol will enroll a convenience sample of 1000 subjects ages greater than or equal to
      16-50 in need of clinically indicated, routine extraction of third molars.

      Design

      This is an evaluation, treatment and training protocol. Subjects will receive standard
      evaluation and treatment for clinically indicated, routine extraction of third molars.
      Subjects will report to the NIDCR dental clinic for at least three visits. The first visit
      will be a screening evaluation to determine the clinical need for third molar extraction and
      protocol eligibility. Eligible subjects will return for a second visit for third molar
      extraction. Oral specimens removed during the standard procedure of third molar extraction
      will be distributed for research. A third visit will be scheduled approximately one week
      after surgery for a post-operative clinical evaluation.

      Outcome Measures

      There is no research planned under this protocol. However, data is collected for purposes of
      research and clinical quality assurance. If trends emerge that warrant further exploration,
      outcome measures will be described when IRB approval or determination of exemption is
      requested to carry out the project.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 5, 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>molar extraction</measure>
    <time_frame>2 weeks</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">1000</enrollment>
  <condition>Tooth</condition>
  <condition>Tooth Impaction</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Third Molar Removal</intervention_name>
    <description>Third Molar Removal</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Ages greater than or equal to16-50

          -  Clinical evidence of need (dental decay, bony or soft tissue impaction, orthodontic
             need) for third molar extraction as determined by medical, dental, and radiographic
             evaluation

          -  Willing to allow for the collection of waste tissue (e.g., teeth, alveolar bone,
             excessive gingival tissue) extracted to be used for research

          -  In good general health as defined by the American Society of Anesthesiologists (ASA)
             status I or II

          -  Able to understand and sign an informed consent

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Pregnant or nursing women

          -  Known or suspected allergy or adverse reaction to any of the agents used for local
             anesthesia, suture materials, or conscious sedation medications

          -  Known bleeding disorders or conditions associated with bleeding, including, but not
             limited to, Hemophilia, von Willebrand disease, protein C/S deficiency, antithrombin
             III deficiency, and liver disease

          -  Currently using anticoagulation (blood thinning) medications, including but not
             limited to warfarin (Coumadin), ticlopidine (Ticlid) and clopidogril (Plavix)

          -  Clinical signs of infection (i.e. abscess) at the time of screening&lt;TAB&gt;

          -  An anticipated difficult surgical removal of the third molars as evidenced by
             panoramic radiographs. The following clinical findings would be evidence of probable
             difficult surgical extractions:

               -  Increased depth of tooth impaction in bone

               -  Extreme angulations of the tooth

               -  Close proximity of the tooth to the inferior alveolar nerve canal and/or
                  maxillary sinus

          -  Medical history that would preclude outpatient conscious sedation setting for
             extractions.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janice S Lee, DDS, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Dental and Craniofacial Research (NIDCR)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Sharon Mitchell</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-4372</phone>
    <email>sharon.mitchell@nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Tammy Yokum, M.S.N.</last_name>
      <phone>(301) 827-1138</phone>
      <email>yokumtk@mail.nih.gov</email>
    </contact_backup>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2013-D-0033.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bui CH, Seldin EB, Dodson TB. Types, frequencies, and risk factors for complications after third molar extraction. J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2003 Dec;61(12):1379-89.</citation>
    <PMID>14663801</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sato FR, Asprino L, de Araújo DE, de Moraes M. Short-term outcome of postoperative patient recovery perception after surgical removal of third molars. J Oral Maxillofac Surg. 2009 May;67(5):1083-91. doi: 10.1016/j.joms.2008.09.032.</citation>
    <PMID>19375022</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bouloux GF, Steed MB, Perciaccante VJ. Complications of third molar surgery. Oral Maxillofac Surg Clin North Am. 2007 Feb;19(1):117-28, vii. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18088870</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>April 11, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 5, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 6, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Third Molar</keyword>
  <keyword>Specimen Acquisition</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tooth, Impacted</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

