<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01807546</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Onconova 09-09</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>COMIRB 13-0116</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01807546</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Oral Rigosertib for Squamous Cell Carcinoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Oral Rigosertib in Patients With Relapsed or Metastatic, Platinum-resistant, Human Papillomavirus Positive or Negative Squamous Cell Carcinoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Onconova Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Onconova Therapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary objective of this study is to determine if tumors in patients with papillomavirus
      (HPV) positive or negative squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) that no longer responds to standard
      therapy will decrease in size following treatment with the investigational drug, rigosertib
      sodium (ON 01910.Na). A secondary objective is to determine if treatment with rigosertib
      causes any side effects.

      Rigosertib is an investigational drug, which means that it has not been approved by the U.S.
      Food and Drug Administration (FDA) to treat any diseases. We are studying rigosertib as a new
      anticancer drug. Tests that we have done in the laboratory suggest that rigosertib works by
      blocking cell division in cancer cells and causing them to die.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This will be a multicenter, Phase II study to evaluate the safety and efficacy of oral
      rigosertib in patients with relapsed or metastatic squamous cell carinoma (SCC) who
      previously received platinum-based chemotherapy and/or chemo-radiation therapy.

      Only patients with head and neck squamous cell carinoma (HNSCC), non-small cell lung SCC,
      skin SCC, cervical SCC, penile SCC, anal SCC or esophageal SCC will be enrolled in the study.

      Patients will be administered rigosertib capsules at a dose of 560 mg BID on days 1 to 14 of
      a 21-day cycle. Patients will be enrolled in 2 cohorts based on HPV test results:

        -  Cohort 1 will include up to 40 patients with human papillomavirus (HPV)-positive SCC, of
           which approximately 30 patients will have HNSCC, and approximately 10 patients with SCC
           of another origin (eg, cervix, anal, penile);

        -  Cohort 2 will include up to 40 patients with HPV-negative SCC, of which approximately 30
           patients will have HNSCC, and approximately 10 patients with SCC of another origin (eg,
           lung, skin, esophageal).

      Patients will be evaluated for progression after completing 3 cycles of therapy and every 3
      cycles thereafter. Patients with stable disease (SD) or better, based on revised Response
      Criteria in Solid Tumors (mRECIST) 1.1, will receive repeated cycles of treatment on a 21-day
      cycle schedule until disease progression, development of unacceptable toxicity, or withdrawal
      of consent. Patients with progressive disease (PD) but who, in the opinion of the
      Investigator, appear to be deriving clinical benefit, may continue on study with a planned
      disease reassessment after one further cycle of therapy. Should the patient have SD or PR at
      this reassessment, s/he may continue on study, with subsequent reassessments every 3 cycles.

      Following discontinuation of rigosertib treatment, patients' mortality status will be
      assessed every 3 months.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 9 weeks after start of rigosertib treatment and every 9 weeks thereafter, up to 2 years.</time_frame>
    <description>Outcome is defined as the number of patients with Complete Response (CR) or Partial Response (PR) per revised Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST 1.1). Complete response (CR) is defined as disappearance of all target lesions. Partial Response (PR) is defined as at least a 30% decrease in the sum of diameters of target lesions, taking as reference the baseline sum diameters.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Date of signing ICF to date of death, or date last known to be alive up to 2 years after discontinuation of rigosertib treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>At the time of analysis, the outcome measure will be number of days between the date the patient is enrolled in the study and the date the patient dies or date the patient is last known to be alive, up to 2 years following discontinuation of rigosertib treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression free survival (PFS),</measure>
    <time_frame>9 weeks, 18 weeks, and 27 weeks and every 9 weeks thereafter, up to 2 years after patient enrolled in the study.</time_frame>
    <description>At the time of analysis, the outcome measure will be number of days between the date the patient is enrolled in the study and the date that progressive disease (PD) is documented per revised Response Evaluation Criteria In Solid Tumors (RECIST 1.1).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Concentration of rigosertib in plasma</measure>
    <time_frame>Cycle 1 Day 1, Cycle 1 Day 14 and Cycle 2 Day 14 at 0, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, and 6 hours after the first dose of the day.</time_frame>
    <description>The concentration (expressed as microgram rigosertib per mL plasma and/or nanogram rigosertib per mL plasma) of rigosertib in plasma will be determined by a validated high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) method.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Levels of Biomarkers</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline ( study before drug administration) and Cycle 1, Day 14.</time_frame>
    <description>Genetic and protein profiling will be conducted in blood (collected at Baseline before study drug administration) and in core biopsy or fine needle aspirate tumor samples (collected at Baseline before study drug administration and at Cycle 1 Day 14).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>From signing of Informed Consent Form until 30 days after last dose of study drug.</time_frame>
    <description>All Adverse Events reported by the patient or observed by the Investigator or study site personnel will be recorded. An adverse event is defined as any unfavorable or unintended sign, symptom, or disease that appears or worsens in a patient during the period of observation in a clinical study.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">64</enrollment>
  <condition>Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Anal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Lung Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Cervical Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Esophageal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Skin Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Penile Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>rigosertib</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Oral rigosertib capsules at a dose of 560 mg twice a day for 14 consecutive days of a 21-day cycle (2 weeks on, 1 week off regimen).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rigosertib</intervention_name>
    <description>Oral rigosertib capsules at a dose of 560 mg twice a day for 14 consecutive days of a 21-day cycle (2 weeks on, 1 week off regimen).</description>
    <arm_group_label>rigosertib</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ON 01910.Na</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Histologically confirmed SCC; only patients with HNSCC, non-small cell lung SCC, skin
             SCC, cervical SCC, penile SCC, anal SCC, or esophageal SCC;

          2. For patients with HNSCC only, HPV status must be assessed by in situ hybridization
             (ISH) and/or p16 immunohistochemistry (IHC) according to local standards;

          3. For patients with HNSCC only, HPV status must be assessed by in situ hybridization
             (ISH) and/or p16 immunohistochemistry (IHC) according to local standards. For all
             other patients with SCC originating in tissues other than the head and neck, attempts
             should be made to obtain HPV status;

          4. Incurable, non-resectable, locally-advanced/relapsed and/or distant metastatic disease
             after no more than 3 prior treatment regimens, one of which must be platinum-based
             chemotherapy;

          5. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status ≤2;

          6. Life expectancy of at least 3 months;

          7. Measurable disease according to RECIST version 1.1;

          8. Ability to swallow entire capsules;

          9. Adequate hematologic function;

         10. Adequate hepatic function;

         11. Adequate renal function;

         12. Adequate contraceptive regimens for female and male patients;

         13. Female patients with reproductive potential must have a negative urine or serum
             pregnancy test;

         14. Ability to understand the nature of the study and any hazards of study participation,
             to communicate satisfactorily with the Investigator, and to follow the requirements of
             the entire protocol;

         15. Willingness to adhere to the prohibitions and restrictions specified in this protocol;

         16. The patient must sign an informed consent form (ICF).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Chemotherapy or any potentially myelosuppressive treatment within 3 weeks prior to
             enrollment (6 weeks are required for nitrosoureas or mitomycin C);

          2. Radiotherapy to &gt;25% of the hematopoietic active bone marrow within 4 weeks prior to
             enrollment;

          3. Systemic administration of corticosteroids within the past 4 weeks prior to
             enrollment;

          4. Prior therapy with a phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K), Akt or mammalian target of
             rapamycin (mTOR) inhibitor;

          5. Any other investigational agent or chemotherapy, radiotherapy, or immunotherapy within
             4 weeks of enrollment;

          6. Major surgery within 3 weeks of enrollment or major surgery without full recovery;

          7. Residual clinical signs and symptoms which have not recovered to Common Terminology
             Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4 Grade 1 severity level or below before
             enrollment, except for alopecia, stable residual neuropathy, and residual hand/foot
             syndrome;

          8. Known brain metastases, except for those that have been removed or irradiated and have
             no current clinical impact at the time of enrollment; a computed tomography (CT) scan
             or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the brain should be obtained in patients with
             symptoms suggestive of brain metastases;

          9. Ascites requiring active medical management, including paracentesis;

         10. Serum sodium less than 130 mEq/L or conditions that may predispose patients to
             hyponatremia (eg, previous syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone
             hypersecretion [syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH)],
             chronic diuretic use, etc.);

         11. Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, bleeding, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris,
             and cardiac arrhythmia;

         12. Uncontrolled hypertension, defined as systolic blood pressure ≥160 mmHg and/or
             diastolic blood pressure ≥110 mmHg;

         13. New onset of seizures within 3 months prior to enrollment, or poorly controlled
             seizures;

         14. Psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit the patient's ability to
             tolerate and/or comply with study requirements;

         15. History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to rigosertib;

         16. Female patients who are pregnant or lactating.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Michael Kurman, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Onconova Therapeutics, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California Davis Comprehensive Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sacramento</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>95817</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford Cancer Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Denver VA Medical Center-ECHCS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Denver</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80220</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Veterans Administration New Jersey Health Care System</name>
      <address>
        <city>East Orange</city>
        <state>New Jersey</state>
        <zip>07018</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mount Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10029</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Montefiore Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>The Bronx</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10467</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Ohio State University, James Cancer Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Columbus</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>43210</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennslvania Abramson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mary Crowley Cancer Research Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75201</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Virginia Cancer Specialists, PC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Fairfax</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>22031</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Blue Ridge Cancer Care</name>
      <address>
        <city>Salem</city>
        <state>Virginia</state>
        <zip>24153</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.onconova.com</url>
    <description>Website of Onconova Therapeutics, Inc.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Anderson RT, Keysar SB, Bowles DW, Glogowska MJ, Astling DP, Morton JJ, Le P, Umpierrez A, Eagles-Soukup J, Gan GN, Vogler BW, Sehrt D, Takimoto SM, Aisner DL, Wilhelm F, Frederick BA, Varella-Garcia M, Tan AC, Jimeno A. The dual pathway inhibitor rigosertib is effective in direct patient tumor xenografts of head and neck squamous cell carcinomas. Mol Cancer Ther. 2013 Oct;12(10):1994-2005. doi: 10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-13-0206. Epub 2013 Jul 19.</citation>
    <PMID>23873848</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Garcia-Manero G, Fenaux P. Comprehensive Analysis of Safety: Rigosertib in 557 Patients with Myelodysplastic Syndromes (MDS) and Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML). Blood Dec 2016, 128 (22) 2011; ASH 2016.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 4, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 6, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 8, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <disposition_first_submitted>April 4, 2016</disposition_first_submitted>
  <disposition_first_submitted_qc>April 15, 2016</disposition_first_submitted_qc>
  <disposition_first_posted type="Estimate">May 16, 2016</disposition_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 22, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 22, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 26, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Head and neck cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>Platinum-resistant</keyword>
  <keyword>Squamous cell carcinoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Head and Neck Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Esophageal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Anus Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted, but a results disposition has been submitted           -->
</clinical_study>

