<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01809080</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MH-095109</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01809080</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Intern Health Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigation Into the Interaction Between Genes and Stress in the Etiology of Depression in Interns</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Michigan</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Michigan</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Retrospective studies have established a strong correlation between reports of life stress
      and depression. Investigators have begun to further explore this relationship by examining
      the role of gene x stress interactions in the pathogenesis of depression. In a recent
      landmark study, Caspi and colleagues (2003) reported an interaction between a serotonin
      transporter promoter polymorphism and life stress in the development of depression. This
      finding has been replicated in some but not all follow up studies. Despite the initial
      promise of these results, the ability to draw definitive conclusions is compromised by
      significant study design limitations: 1) retrospective design 2) a focus on acute rather than
      chronic stress 3) substantial variation in the character and intensity of stress between
      subjects. Medical internship is a period filled with predictable and high levels of chronic
      uncontrolled stress. Rates of depression among interns are elevated compared to the general
      population. In this study, we aim to utilize the predictable and consistent stress of
      internship to investigate the relationship between stress, genes and depression with a
      prospective study design that bypasses some of the pitfalls of previous studies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Specific Aims Retrospective studies have established a strong correlation between reports of
      life stress and depression. Investigators have begun to further explore this relationship by
      examining the role of gene x stress interactions in the pathogenesis of depression. In a
      recent landmark study, Caspi and colleagues (2003) reported an interaction between a
      serotonin transporter promoter polymorphism and life stress in the development of depression.
      This finding has been replicated in some but not all follow up studies. Despite the initial
      promise of these results, the ability to draw definitive conclusions is compromised by
      significant study design limitations: 1) retrospective design 2) a focus on acute rather than
      chronic stress 3) substantial variation in the character and intensity of stress between
      subjects. Medical internship is a period filled with predictable and high levels of chronic
      uncontrolled stress. Rates of depression among interns are elevated compared to the general
      population. In this study, we aim to utilize the predictable and consistent stress of
      internship to investigate the relationship between stress, genes and depression with a
      prospective study design that bypasses some of the pitfalls of previous studies.

      Goal 1) Assess the prevalence and development of depression among medical interns

      Although small studies have assessed the point prevalence of depression among medical
      residents, no study has prospectively followed the development of depressive symptoms through
      residency. We will collect baseline psychological profiles of incoming interns prior to the
      commencement of residency duties and subsequently assess for depressive symptoms at 3-month
      intervals throughout internship. This data will allow us to:

        1. Assess the point prevalence of depression among interns in a large sample.

        2. Determine the change in depressive symptoms through the course of the intern year

        3. Evaluate stable psychological factors that associate with the development of depression
           in the face of life stress.

      Goal 2) Evaluate the presence of genotype x stress interaction among this sample

        1. There is conflicting evidence concerning the presence of an interaction between the
           serotonin transporter promoter polymorphism (5-HTTLPR) and life stress in the
           development of depression. We will assess the presence and strength of this interaction
           in the sample of medical interns using a study design that avoids many of the pitfalls
           affecting previous studies.

        2. We will explore novel putative interactions between stress and genetic variants in
           additional genes including BDNF, CRH, COMT, serotonin 1A and serotonin 2A receptor
           variants in the development of depression.

      Goal 3) Evaluate the relationship between serum endothelial and immune factors and the
      development of depressive symptoms under stress.

      The identification biomarkers that predict the onset of depression can facilitate more timely
      and accurate identification of individuals at high risk for the disorder. Unfortunately
      appropriate studies are lacking, largely because it is difficult to know exactly when a
      depressive episode will occur. Medical internship represents a rare situation where we can
      prospectively predict when a cohort of individuals shift will shift from a low stress
      environment to a high stress environment and thus predict when this cohort will experience a
      dramatic increase in depressive symptoms.

      Goal 4) Examine the temporal relationship between hair cortisol levels, stress exposure and
      development of depressive symptoms.A novel technique allows us to assess chronic HPA axis
      activity by measuring cortisol in the growing hair, providing an integrated measure of total
      cortisol secretion over extended periods of time (1-3 months).

      By incorporating this novel method into an established longitudinal study of a chronic
      stressor that dramatically increases rates of depression, we have a unique opportunity to
      determine a) whether cortisol levels prior to stress exposure predict risk of depression in
      response to the stressor (b) whether cortisol rise in response to stress exposure precedes
      and perhaps contributes to development of depressive symptoms or whether cortisol elevations
      in depression develop after symptom onset and perhaps reflect a consequence of depression.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2007</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2027</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Assess the change in rates of depression among medical interns.</measure>
    <time_frame>Months 0, 3, 6, and 12 of Intern Year</time_frame>
    <description>The point prevalence of depression at various points through internship will be determined using subject responses to DSM-IV major depression items at the 0, 3-month, 6-month and 12-month assessments. To investigate whether there is a significant change in depressive symptoms through intern year, the investigators will compare PHQ (baseline) and PHQ (6 month) depression scores through a paired T-test. The effect of baseline psychological traits (neuroticism, resilience, personal history of depression, family history of depression, early family environment, social supports) on the development of depression will also be explored through linear regression analyses with each of the psychological factors as independent variables and PHQ (change) [PHQ (6 month) - PHQ (baseline)] as the dependent variable. The investigators will use linear regression to investigate correlations between training program characteristics (average work hours, specialty) and PHQ (change).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the presence of genotype x stress interaction among this sample.</measure>
    <time_frame>Sample within first 6 months of Intern Year (Because DNA sequence generally does not change with time, the exact timing of sample collection is not critical to the analysis)</time_frame>
    <description>As a baseline analysis, the investigators will investigate association between each variant/haplotype and PHQ (baseline) scores using linear regression. To explore gene x environment interactions, the investigators will assess for association between each variant/haplotype and PHQ change scores (Mean (3,6,9 and 12 month PHQ score) - Baseline (PHQ score)).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate the relationship between serum factors and changes in depressive symptoms under stress.</measure>
    <time_frame>Months 0 and 10 of Intern Year</time_frame>
    <description>For each of the proteins assessed (IL-1beta, IL-6, IL-10, hs-CRP and TNF-alpha), Pearson correlation will be used to assess the relationship between serum and saliva levels. The investigators will assess whether there is a significant change in the serum levels of endothelial and inflammatory markers and endothelial function using a within-subject paired T-test, with baseline values (low stress) paired with internship stress values (high stress). To assess whether the change in endothelial and inflammatory markers correlate with a change in depressive symptoms, the investigators will utilize a linear regression, with the change in marker level used as explanatory variables and the change in depressive symptoms score (PHQ (change) = mean residency depressive symptoms - baseline depressive symptoms) used as the outcome variable</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Examine the temporal relationship between hair cortisol level changes, stress exposure and changes in depressive symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>Months 0, 4, 8, 12 of Intern Year</time_frame>
    <description>Statistical analysis will be conducted using Generalized Estimating Equation (GEE) analysis. To assess whether there is a change in hair cortisol indices with internship stress, the investigators will perform a paired T-test, with pre-internship factor cortisol level paired with post-internship factor cortisol level. To determine the relationship between hair-related factors (hair color, hair treatment, washing frequency), transient mediating factors (work hours, outside stressful life events, recent exercise, sleep and illness), long-term mediating factors (BMI, regular exercise schedule, smoking behavior) and long-term cortisol, the investigators will assess whether the difference in level of these factors between the two assessments shows a significant correlation with the difference in cortisol level. Next, the investigators will identify whether that change in hair cortisol is associated with the change in depressive symptoms while accounting for related variables.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">4380</enrollment>
  <condition>Depression</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Saliva: DNA collection kits are sent via postal mail and participants are asked to provide a
      small sample of saliva.

      Blood samples (up to 50 mL via venopuncture): whole blood and serum will be assessed.

      Hair: The total diameter taken from the scalp's posterior vertex will be about 3 mm, which is
      about half of the diameter of pencil (approximately 100 hair strands with a minimum of 50 mg
      of hair for a 3-cm segment).
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Medical internship is an attractive model to bypass some limitations of previous studies.
        Internship is well chronicled as a time of high stress (Butterfield 1988; Addison et al
        2004). Interns are faced with long work hours, sleep deprivation, loss of autonomy and
        extreme emotional situations (Shanafelt &amp; Habermann 2002). Many physicians recall
        internship as among the most stressful years of their lives (Duffy 2005). The stress of
        internship is often uncontrollable, unpredictable and chronic; features that are
        particularly linked to the development of depression (Kendler et al 2003; Cryan et al
        2004). Several studies have estimated the point prevalence of depression among interns at
        28%-37% (Valko &amp; Clayton 1975; Reuben 1985; Cohen et al 2006), in contrast to a point
        prevalence of 5% in general population (Murphy et al 2000). There is also evidence that
        physicians have underlying personality traits that predispose to depression (McDonough
        1990; Hojat et al 1999).
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects for our study will be drawn from incoming interns in the traditional and
             primary care internal medicine, general surgery, pediatrics, obstetrics/gynecology,
             neurology and psychiatry residency programs at participating University and Community
             residency programs, as well as fourth year medical students at participating medical
             schools.

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Srijan Sen, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Michigan</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Michigan Medical School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ann Arbor</city>
        <state>Michigan</state>
        <zip>48109</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Karg K, Sen S. Gene × environment interaction models in psychiatric genetics. Curr Top Behav Neurosci. 2012;12:441-62. doi: 10.1007/7854_2011_184. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22241248</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Guille C, Sen S. Prescription drug use and self-prescription among training physicians. Arch Intern Med. 2012 Feb 27;172(4):371-2. doi: 10.1001/archinternmed.2011.791.</citation>
    <PMID>22371930</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Guille C, Speller H, Laff R, Epperson CN, Sen S. Utilization and barriers to mental health services among depressed medical interns: a prospective multisite study. J Grad Med Educ. 2010 Jun;2(2):210-4. doi: 10.4300/JGME-D-09-00086.1.</citation>
    <PMID>21975622</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Sen S, Kranzler HR, Krystal JH, Speller H, Chan G, Gelernter J, Guille C. A prospective cohort study investigating factors associated with depression during medical internship. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2010 Jun;67(6):557-65. doi: 10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2010.41. Epub 2010 Apr 5.</citation>
    <PMID>20368500</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Karg K, Burmeister M, Shedden K, Sen S. The serotonin transporter promoter variant (5-HTTLPR), stress, and depression meta-analysis revisited: evidence of genetic moderation. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 2011 May;68(5):444-54. doi: 10.1001/archgenpsychiatry.2010.189. Epub 2011 Jan 3.</citation>
    <PMID>21199959</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 1, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 8, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 12, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 19, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 19, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 21, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Michigan</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Srijan Sen</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor of Psychiatry, Medicial School</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

