<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01805986</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>12115</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>13920</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>12/EM/0452</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>917</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01805986</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Investigation of GM Pathology Using Ultra High Field (7T) MRI Scanner</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigation of Grey Matter Pathology Using Ultra High Field (7T) MRI Scanner</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Nottingham</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Nottingham</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Magnetization transfer imaging is a magnetic resonance technique that has been used over the
      last few years, and known for its ability to detect abnormalities that can be difficult to
      detect by conventional MRI techniques.

      The investigators would like to test if using an 7 Tesla MRI research scanner can help us
      diagnose Multiple Sclerosis more efficiently compared to the current clinical practice, i.e.
      if Multiple Sclerosis lesions in Gray Matter can be more readily identified and associated
      with disease stage on Magnetic Transfer MRI images as opposed to conventional procedures.
      Image analysis will allow the investigators to perform lesion segmentation and sequence
      comparison between different MRI techniques. The investigators will apply computation
      techniques to measure the local cortical thickness. Repeated scans at 6 monthly intervals
      over two years will give an insight into the changes in cortical thickness over time. Based
      on obtained data the investigators will look for the relationship between lesion loads in
      White Matter and Gray Matter, cortical thickness and disease stage.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Purpose for this study:

      This research group has previously investigated the usefulness of a powerful new MRI scanner
      and have found that the 7 Tesla MRI is able to provide detailed structural images of the
      cortex of the brain which can uncover pathology such as cortical demyelinating lesions in MS
      patients. Multiple sclerosis (MS) affects the grey matter as well as the white matter of the
      brain and spinal cord. However as white matter lesions are more easily visible both
      pathologically and on MRI, therefore most MS research has focused on white matter
      demyelination. The investigators would like to assess whether MS lesions in Gray Matter as
      well as White Matter can be more readily identified on Magnetic Transfer Ratio (MTR) images
      as opposed to standard protocols such as DIR, T2* and T1-weighted MPRAGE by comparing the
      results of the manual detection.

      The investigators will correlate lesion loads against cortical thickness and both lesion
      loads and cortical thickness against disease state both globally and on a regional basis. The
      investigators will then compare averaged, normalized profiles from different cortical ribbon
      regions between patients and controls to determine whether a particular layer of the cortical
      strip is more affected. The investigators will also correlate Gray Matter changes with
      distant and neighboring White Matter lesions. In addition, the investigators will also build
      an average lesion map across all subjects, which can be compared against the results
      published in literature. The investigators will use the manual lesion maps to characterize
      the regions of the cortex that deviate from normally appearing Gray Matter.

      How this project will be carried out:

      The investigators will study patients with MS and other neurological disease, and patients
      who are followed already at the neurology. All patients would have had already a brain scan.

      For comparison purposes the investigators will study healthy volunteers, in order to
      demonstrate that any new findings demonstrable with the 7T MRI scan are indeed related to
      pathology.

      Ethical issues:

      Occasionally the investigators discover incidental abnormalities on brain scans of those who
      participate in the study. In such circumstances the investigators will adhere to University
      of Nottingham Incidental Findings Procedure. In the Participant Information Sheet the
      investigators will explain that if the investigators notice any abnormality on MR scans (for
      healthy volunteer) or abnormality on MR scan not expected to be seen under patient's
      neurological diagnosis (for patients) the investigators will refer them to their GP. The
      investigators will send a letter to patient's GP informing that the investigators have
      detected a possible abnormality on the scan. The investigators will show the scans to a
      radiologist based in Academic Radiology at the QMC, who will contact participant's GP if
      further action is required.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Enrolling by invitation</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of Gray Matter lesions detected using different sequences.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of MRI sequencies</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To determine whether Magnetisation Transfer Ratio (MTR) maps are more sensitive for detection of cortical lesions than Double Inversion Recovery (DIR), T2* and phase maps, or Magnetisation Prepared Rapid Acquisition Gradient Echo (MPRAGE) and to better characterise cortical lesions using a combination of sequences.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the relationship between cortical thickness as measured on T1 weighted images and GM and WM lesion load.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Regional variation in the brain</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>To determine the origins of regional changes previously detected via voxel based analysis and histogram analysis, using a multiscale approach, working down from identifying regional variations across the cortex, to identifying whether regional changes are associated with changes in so called Normal Appearing White Matter (NAGM), or whether they are associated with diffuse or focal GM lesions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To detect cortical variations in MT inside and outside GM lesions, in a longitudinal pilot study, reflecting possible cortical remyelination.</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Multiple Sclerosis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>MS patient</arm_group_label>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients studied will be those with known MS. For purposes of comparison as described
        previously, we will also seek to include healthy volunteers.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Patients with MS or other neurological disease which already had at least 1 MRI scan.

          -  Healthy volunteers which had no indication of neurological disease in the past.

          -  Do not have significant cognitive impairment and are able to give consent.

          -  Will not have any contraindication for MR imaging

               -  Are able to lie flat for up to 60 mins.

               -  Age 25 and over.

        Exclusion criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Have any implants in the body.

          -  Have aneurysm clips.

          -  Have pacemaker or artificial heart valve.

          -  Have foreign bodies in their body (e.g. shrapnel).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>25 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nikos Evangelou, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Nottingham</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>May 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 5, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 6, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 16, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 16, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 17, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Multiple Sclerosis, other neurological conditions</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Multiple Sclerosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

