<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01800682</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CR018658</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>TRAM-PAI-1001</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01800682</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Pharmacokinetic Study to Evaluate the Dose-Proportionality of Tramadol (ULTRAM) Extended-Release (ER) in Healthy Participants</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Single-Dose, Open-Label, Randomized, Crossover Dose-Proportionality Study to Evaluate the Effect of Dose on the Pharmacokinetics of 25, 50, and 100 mg ULTRAM ER Under Fasted Conditions in Healthy Adult Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the dose proportionality of the pharmacokinetics
      (explores what the body does to the drug) of tramadol in healthy adult participants.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is an open-label (all people know the identity of the intervention), single-center,
      randomized (study drug assigned by chance), and 3-way crossover (method used to switch
      participants from one study group to another in a clinical trial) study of tramadol
      extended-release (ER). All participants will be randomly assigned to 1 of 6 possible
      treatment sequences of tramadol. The study consists of 3 parts: Screening (within 20 days
      before study commences on Day -1); Open-label treatment (consisting of 3 single-dose
      treatment periods separated with washout period of 4-14 days, and dosing will be under
      fasting conditions on Day 1 in each treatment period); and Follow-up (up to 48-hour blood
      sample collection on Day 3 of Period 3). The duration of study is anticipated to be 6-8 weeks
      per participant. Participants' safety will be monitored throughout the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum concentration (Cmax) of Tramadol</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and at 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 20, 24, 36, and 48 hours post dose of study treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The Cmax is the maximum plasma concentration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to reach maximum concentration (tmax) of Tramadol</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and at 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 20, 24, 36, and 48 hours post dose of study treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The Tmax is time to reach the maximum plasma concentration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time 0 to time of the last quantifiable concentration (AUC[last])</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and at 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 20, 24, 36, and 48 hours post dose of study treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The AUC(last) is the area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time 0 to time of the last quantifiable concentration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time 0 to infinite time (AUC[infinity])</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and at 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 20, 24, 36, and 48 hours post dose of study treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The AUC(infinity) is the area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time 0 to infinite time, calculated as the sum of AUC(last) and C(last)/lambda(z), in which C(last) is the last observed quantifiable concentration.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Elimination half-life period (t1/2) associated with the terminal slope (Lambda z)</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and at 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 20, 24, 36, and 48 hours post dose of study treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Elimination half-life associated with the terminal slope (lambda[z]) of the semi logarithmic drug concentration-time curve, calculated as 0.693/lambda(z).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal slope (Lambda z)</measure>
    <time_frame>Predose and at 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 20, 24, 36, and 48 hours post dose of study treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Terminal slope is defined by first-order rate constant associated with the terminal portion of the curve, determined as the negative slope of the terminal log-linear phase of the drug concentration-time curve.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">30</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tramodol Extended-release (ER), 25 milligram (mg)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tramodol ER, 25 mg tablets will be administered orally once daily on Day 1 of each treatment period (separated with washout period of 4-14 days).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tramodol ER, 50 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tramodol ER, 50 mg tablets will be administered orally once daily on Day 1 of each treatment period (separated with washout period of 4-14 days).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Tramodol ER, 100 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Tramodol ER, 100 mg tablets will be administered orally once daily on Day 1 of each treatment period (separated with washout period of 4-14 days).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tramodol Extended-Release (ER)</intervention_name>
    <description>Tramodol ER, will be administered orally as either 25, 50 or 100 milligram tablet, once daily on Day 1 of each treatment period (separated with washout period of 4-14 days).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Tramodol Extended-release (ER), 25 milligram (mg)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Tramodol ER, 50 mg</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Tramodol ER, 100 mg</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>- Ultram</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Females with negative pregnancy test at Screening and on Day -1 of each treatment
             period

          -  Postmenopausal Females (no spontaneous menses for at least 2 years), surgically
             sterile, abstinent, or, if sexually active, be practicing an effective method of birth
             control

          -  Body mass index (BMI; weight in kilogram [kg] divided by height in square meter [m^2])
             from 18 to 30 kilogram per square meter (kg/m^2), and body weight not less than 50 kg

          -  Blood pressure (after the participant is supine for 5 minutes - average of a minimum
             of 2 readings taken at intervals of at least 1 minute) between 90 and 140 millimeter
             of mercury (mmHg) systolic (top number in blood pressure, pressure during active
             contraction of the heart), and no higher than 90 mmHg diastolic (lower number in blood
             pressure reading pertaining to resting or relaxation phase of heart beat)

          -  Non-Smoker

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of or current clinically significant medical illness including (but not
             limited to) cardiac arrhythmias or other cardiac disease, hematologic disease,
             coagulation disorders (including any abnormal bleeding or blood dyscrasias), lipid
             abnormalities, significant pulmonary disease, including bronchospasmic respiratory
             disease, diabetes mellitus, renal or hepatic insufficiency, thyroid disease,
             neurologic or psychiatric disease, infection, or any other illness that the
             investigator considers should exclude the participant or that could interfere with the
             interpretation of the study results

          -  Clinically significant abnormal values for laboratory tests at Screening

          -  Clinically significant abnormal physical examination, vital signs or electrocardiogram
             at Screening

          -  Use of any prescription or non-prescription medication (including monoamine oxidase
             inhibitors, laxatives, vitamins, and herbal supplements), except for acetaminophen,
             oral contraceptives and hormonal replacement therapy within 30 days before the first
             dose of the study drug is scheduled

          -  History of drug or alcohol abuse within the past 5 years
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC Clinical Trial</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Janssen Research &amp; Development, LLC</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Overland Park</city>
        <state>Kansas</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>February 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 26, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 26, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">February 28, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 26, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 26, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">February 28, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Healthy</keyword>
  <keyword>Tramodol</keyword>
  <keyword>Ultram</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tramadol</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

