<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01801891</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>VASGARD2013</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01801891</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Surface NeuroMuscular Electrical Stimulation in the Treatment of Chronic Venous Leg Ulcers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Surface NeuroMuscular Electrical Stimulation in the Treatment of Chronic Venous Leg Ulcers: A Randomised Controlled Trial of the &quot;VASGARD&quot; Device</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Professor Stewart Walsh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mid Western Regional Hospital, Ireland</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study aims to determine if the use of surface neuromuscular electrical stimulation,
      applied to various motor points on the lower limb to elicit muscle contraction when combined
      with compression bandaging accelerates the rate of venous leg ulcer healing.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      With an increasingly ageing population the incidence of venous ulceration is likely to rise.
      The negative impact of leg ulceration on patients' quality of life and on healthcare costs is
      well recognised. Increased prevalence combined with poor reported healing rates and high
      incidence of ulcer recurrence makes the development of a new treatment which could accelerate
      healing rates beyond that currently achieved using compression bandaging most desirable.
      Surface neuromuscular electrical stimulation in combination with compression bandaging may
      provide such a treatment.

      Surface neuromuscular electrical stimulation (SNMES) is the application of an electrical
      stimulus to motor points in the body using electrodes placed on the surface of the skin to
      elicit a muscular contraction. It has been shown that SNMES of the calf muscles, when used in
      conjunction with compression therapy, provides improved venous flow velocities over
      compression therapy alone. Furthermore, the week-long effect of SNMES and compression therapy
      on healthy participants was found to be well tolerated by all participants and resulted in
      increases in stimulated venous flow and muscle strength. A combined SNMES and compression
      treatment protocol which stimulates peripheral venous blood flow may help to alleviate
      harmful venous pressures in venous leg ulcer patients and provide some degree of
      strengthening of the calf muscles, thus helping to accelerate the healing rates of venous
      ulcers.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Reduction in venous ulcer size</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Reduction in relative ulcer size (area) for each patient over time, standardised to an initial size of 1, will be measured weekly.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Acceptability of surface neuromuscular electrical stimulation</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>Patient and healthcare provider perceptions of the acceptability, efficacy and tolerability of the device will be evaluated through a series of semi-structured interviews</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in skin condition related to the application of Vasgard surface neuromuscular electrical stimulator as a measure of safety and tolerability.</measure>
    <time_frame>12 weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The safety issues associated with using electrical stimulation on this patient group under compression bandaging will be evaluated. The following safety points will be evaluated at each visit.
Appearance of the skin under the electrodes (intact / reddened / broken)
Appearance of skin surrounding the electrodes (intact / reddened /broken)
Appearance of skin under the electrodes leads (intact / reddened / broken</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">25</enrollment>
  <condition>Chronic Venous Disease</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomised to the control group will, in addition to their routine compression bandaging, be given muscle stimulators for home use and instructed to apply 3x 30 minute sessions of comfortable electrical stimulation daily for 12 weeks. The stimulators given to the control group will be set to provide minimal stimulation resulting in no visible muscular contraction.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>VASGARD stimulator</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients randomised to this group, in addition to their routine treatment with compression bandaging, will be given muscle stimulators for home use and instructed to apply 3x 30 minute sessions of comfortable electrical stimulation daily for 12 weeks. The intervention group stimulators will be capable of causing muscular contraction with a maximum force ranging from 30-40% of voluntary contractions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VASGARD stimulator</intervention_name>
    <description>The VASGARD device is a 2 channel muscle stimulator system designed for increasing venous blood flow. Controlled electrical stimuli are delivered to the patient through adhesive gel electrodes placed over the motor points of muscles on the lower leg. This elicits artificial muscular contractions which in turn increases lower limb venous haemodynamics.</description>
    <arm_group_label>VASGARD stimulator</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>SNMES</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Compression bandaging</intervention_name>
    <description>Compression bandaging systems apply graduated external pressure to the lower limb to promote venous return to the heart reducing venous hypertension and thereby facilitate venous ulcer healing.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>VASGARD stimulator</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Graduated compression bandaging</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Primary or recurrent venous leg ulcer.

          -  Ankle-brachial pressure index &gt; 0.8

          -  Ulcer size between 1 and 200 cm2

          -  Patient suitable for full compression bandaging

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of symptomatic heart disease.

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Presence of implants in the lower leg or a pacemaker

          -  History of a neurological disorder

          -  Presence of any contraindications for the use of compression stockings such as severe
             arterial disease i.e. Ankle brachial pressure index (ABPI) &lt;0.8

          -  Presence of cognitive difficulties which may prevent the patient or his/her carer from
             using the stimulator appropriately.

          -  Patients unable to provide informed consent

          -  Patients receiving dialysis

          -  Patients receiving steroids

          -  Patients receiving methotrexate

          -  Ulcer located in the area of electrode placement

          -  Patients in reduced compression bandaging system
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Pierce A Grace, MCh FRCSI</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>HSE</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Department of Electronic Engineering, National University Ireland Galway</name>
      <address>
        <city>Galway</city>
        <zip>000</zip>
        <country>Ireland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MidWestern Regional Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Limerick</city>
        <zip>000</zip>
        <country>Ireland</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Ireland</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>December 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 25, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>February 27, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 1, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 11, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 11, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">December 12, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Mid Western Regional Hospital, Ireland</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Professor Stewart Walsh</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor Stewart Walsh</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Venous ulceration</keyword>
  <keyword>Leg ulcers</keyword>
  <keyword>Venous haemodynamics</keyword>
  <keyword>Surface neuromuscular electrical stimulation</keyword>
  <keyword>SNMES</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leg Ulcer</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Varicose Ulcer</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

