<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02347202</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14-01185</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02347202</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Tools for Distance Delivery of an Evidence-based AD Family Caregiver Intervention</brief_title>
  <official_title>Tools for Distance Delivery of an Evidence-based AD Family Caregiver Intervention</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A 20+ year randomized controlled trial (RCT) demonstrated the many benefits of a counseling
      and support intervention for spouse caregivers, the NYU Caregiver Intervention (NYUCI). The
      NYU Caregiver Intervention (NYUCI) is an evidence-based intervention that provides counseling
      and support for families involved in the care of a relative or friend with Alzheimer's
      Disease and Related Dementias (ADRD). Most notably, the NYUCI substantially reduced
      caregiver's depressive symptoms, improved their physical health, and extended the time
      persons with ADRD remained at home by an average of 1.5 years (Mittelman et al., AG14634,
      formerly MH42216; See http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17101889).

      The intervention is now being widely implemented in-person, but there are barriers that
      prevent many caregivers from receiving its benefits, including geographic distance;
      impediments to older adults leaving their homes; and travel considerations for counselors
      which make it impossible to provide the NYUCI in person.

      The goal of this study is to evaluate the efficacy of an online videoconferencing version of
      the NYUCI. This innovative application has massive implications for social service delivery
      to older adults, because it will make it possible to deliver an in-person intervention, via
      the internet, which is already evidenced based to older adult caregivers who cannot currently
      be served. It will create the online reservation and management technology linking counselors
      with families as well as the evidence of effectiveness of providing such services via secure
      video teleconferencing vehicles. The proposed Telehealth Technology for Distance Counseling
      (TTDC) and related online educational training modules will connect skilled providers to the
      families of persons with dementia without regard to geographic location. Implications for
      rural healthcare delivery are particularly persuasive. To the investigators knowledge, this
      will be the first large-scale TTDC to be developed and rigorously tested with a randomized
      controlled trial. The investigators hypothesize that such a system, coupled with online
      training for providers and families on tele- counseling and distance caregiving, will have
      similar benefits to those achieved with in-person counseling during the original NYUCI RCT.

      This project includes an online reservation and management technology linking counselors with
      families via secure videoconferencing vehicles. The Telehealth Technology for Distance
      Counseling (TTDC), and online technology developed as part of this overall effort, will
      connect skilled providers to the families of persons with dementia without regard to
      geographic location. The related online clinical modules (i.e., interactive, computer-based
      educational materials) developed as a part of this grant effort will prepare counselors to
      provide the intervention, and caregivers to utilize the internet software, to be able to
      participate in counseling.

      The TTDC will include a scheduling system to link counselors to families at their mutual
      convenience and assure delivery in a cost-effective manner. The TTDC has the additional
      potential to transform ADRD care in ethnic and culturally diverse communities by connecting
      highly trained NYUCI counselors with specialized language and cultural skills to families who
      would not have access to these resources locally.

      In this study investigators will have 240 caregivers navigate the online educational module
      and the online reservation system for connecting caregivers with social workers. Half of the
      caregivers will then be paired with social service providers to receive counseling over the
      telephone, and the other half with be paired with social service providers to receive
      counseling via Zoom, a video conferencing program. Recruiting across the United States and
      Toronto, Canada.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2015</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Supportive Care</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in depressive symptoms between groups (One-way analysis of variance, questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Four, eight, and twelve months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>One-way analysis of variance to evaluate differences in depressive symptoms between groups. This data will be collected via a questionnaire.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in reactions to problem behaviors between groups (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Four, eight, and twelve months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>This information will be collected via a questionnaire.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Differences in satisfaction with social support between groups (questionnaire)</measure>
    <time_frame>Four, eight, and twelve months after intervention</time_frame>
    <description>This information will be collected via a questionnaire.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Alzheimer's Disease</condition>
  <condition>Dementia</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Online counseling via Zoom teleconferencing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each participant will be assigned a random number which is linked to group assignment. The numbers will be assigned consecutively to participants as they enroll. All caregivers in the treatment group will receive 6 counseling sessions in 4 months, using teleconferencing. The first session will be an individual session. The caregiver will be asked to select family members to participate in the next 4 sessions. The 4 family sessions will be followed by another individual session with the spouse/partner caregiver. The counselor will send the primary caregiver an email to be forwarded to family members with instructions on how to access the TTDC training on using the teleconferencing technology. All caregivers in the control group will be able to call the counselor for resource information and support.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Telephone support as needed</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>All caregivers in the control group will be able to call the counselor for resource information and support as needed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Online counseling via Zoom teleconferencing</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Online counseling via Zoom teleconferencing</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Telephone support as needed</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Telephone support as needed</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Inclusion criteria for caregivers to become research participants include:

          1. access to an Internet-connected computer with a camera, microphone, and speakers
             either at home, or at another location that affords privacy;

          2. fluent in spoken and written English; and

          3. caregivers who participate must be spouses or partners of people with dementia living
             with them at home when they enter the study. In addition, all caregivers must have at
             least one family member (or close friend) with whom they are in communication about
             the person with dementia, and/or their issues related to being a caregiver, who can
             participate in family counseling sessions; if not, they are excluded from the study.

        Inclusion criteria for counselors to be research participants in both the pilot study and
        the RCT:

          1. Certified or Master's level social worker, a nurse with an RN and at least two years'
             experience working with older adults and their family members evaluated on an
             individual basis by the PIs);

          2. counselors who have received training online or in person in conducting the NYUCI and
             provided the intervention to at least one caregiver in person;

          3. counselors who have completed the online training to conduct the NYUCI via
             videoconferencing;

          4. counselors who have demonstrated the ability to contact caregivers and families via
             videoconferencing by interacting with HealthCare Interactive (HCI) staff in mock
             sessions (HCI is the technology developer for this Phase II effort); and

          5. counselors who have confirmed they have personal liability and malpractice insurance.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Exclusion criteria for caregivers to be participants are:

          1. no access or severely limited access to an Internet-connected computer with a camera;

          2. not fluent in spoken and written English;

          3. not having a family member with whom they are in communication about the person with
             dementia; and

          4. apparent severe mental or physical illness (e.g., self report of clinical depression).

        Exclusion criteria for counselors include:

          1. not a certified or Master's level social worker or nurse with an RN and at least two
             years' experience working with older adults and their family members, or other
             professional with at last two years' experience working with older adults and their
             family members (to be decided by the PIs);

          2. counselors who have not received training online or in person in conducting the NYUCI;

          3. counselors who have not completed the online training to conduct the NYUCI via
             videoconferencing;

          4. counselors who cannot demonstrate ability to contact caregivers and families via
             videoconferencing by interacting with HCI; and

          5. counselors who do not have personal liability and malpractice insurance.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>125 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mary S Mittelman, DrPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NYU School of Medicine</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Tadessech Hailu, MS</last_name>
    <phone>646-754-2291</phone>
    <email>tadessech.hailu@nyumc.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NYU School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10016</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Tadessech Hailu</last_name>
      <phone>646-754-2291</phone>
      <email>tadessech.hailu@nyumc.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Mary S Mittelman, DrPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17101889</url>
    <description>Improving caregiver well-being delays nursing home placement of patients with Alzheimer disease.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 26, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 27, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Counseling</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Alzheimer Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dementia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

