<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02340156</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>SGT53-02-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02340156</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Phase II Study of Combined Temozolomide and SGT-53 for Treatment of Recurrent Glioblastoma</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Study of Combined Temozolomide and Targeted P53 Gene Therapy (SGT-53) for Treatment of Patients With Recurrent Glioblastoma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>SynerGene Therapeutics, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>SynerGene Therapeutics, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This Phase II clinical trial is an open label, single arm, multicenter study of the
      combination of intravenously administered SGT-53 and oral temozolomide in patients with
      confirmed glioblastoma who have proven tumor recurrence or progression. The objective of this
      trial is to assess 6 month progression free survival (PFS), overall survival (OS), anti-tumor
      activity, safety and possibly to evaluate, nanoparticle delivery to tumor site, and the
      induction of apoptosis in the tumor..
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The p53 is a vital human tumor suppressor gene. Loss of p53 suppressor function is present in
      the majority of human cancers. The p53 protein has a diverse range of functions including
      regulation of cell cycle checkpoints, cell death (apoptosis), senescence, DNA repair,
      maintenance of genomic integrity, and control of angiogenesis. Abnormalities of the p53 gene
      may impact the efficacy of standard anticancer treatments such as radiation and chemotherapy.
      P53 mutation and pathway dysfunction are associated with poor clinical outcomes and the
      presence of the p53 mutation correlates with resistance to chemotherapy and radiation. The
      development of somatic gene therapy has created the potential to restore wild type function
      of p53. SGT-53 is a complex of cationic liposome encapsulating a normal human wild type p53
      DNA sequence in a plasmid backbone. This complex has been shown to efficiently and
      specifically deliver the p53 cDNA to the tumor cells and to cross the blood-brain barrier.
      Introduction of the p53 cDNA sequence is expected to restore wtp53 function in the apoptotic
      pathway. P53 restoration has been shown most effective in enhancing cytotoxicity in
      combination with an agent which results in DNA damage or initiates apoptosis. The primary
      mechanism of resistance to current standard chemotherapeutic agent Temozolomide (TMZ) is
      overexpression of O6-methylguanine-DNA-methyl transferase (MGMT), which repairs the
      TMZ-induced DNA lesion by removing the o6-guanine adducts. Thus, a means to down modulate
      MGMT activity would enhance the therapeutic effect of TMZ. A number of reports have indicated
      that increasing wtp53 expression can down-regulate expression of DNA repair genes such as
      MGMT and increases the sensitivity of tumor cells to alkylating agents. This is a Phase II
      clinical trial of the tumor-targeted SGT-53 nanocomplex in combination with chemotherapeutic
      agent, temozolomide which is the standard of care for Glioblastoma Multiforme (GBM) brain
      tumors. We propose to test the combination of SGT-53 and standard temozolomide to determine
      efficacy and safety in patients with confirmed glioblastoma who have proven tumor recurrence
      or progression.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor response</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The 6 month progression-free survival (PFS) will be evaluated using RANO Response Criteria.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events</measure>
    <time_frame>Study drug initiation through 30 days after the last dose of study drug or EOS, whichever is later.</time_frame>
    <description>The safety of the combination of SGT-53 and Temozolomide will be assessed by analysis of adverse experiences, clinical laboratory tests and physical examinations.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 12 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Progression-free survival is defined as the time from the date of enrollment to the date of disease progression, or death (any cause) on or prior to the clinical cutoff date, whichever occurs earlier. Subjects who do not have disease progression or have not died will be censored at the date of the last tumor assessment on or prior to the clinical cutoff.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration until the date of death from any cause, assessed up to 180 months.</time_frame>
    <description>Overall survival is defined as the time from the date of enrollment to the date of death from all causes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Anti-tumor Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>From date of registration until the date of first documented progression or date of death from any cause, whichever came first, assessed up to 12 months.</time_frame>
    <description>The anti-tumor activity of the combination of SGT-53 and Temozolomide will be determined based upon the RANO criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Induction of apoptosis</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>Flow cytometry or histological examination will be used to determine the level of apoptosis induced by SGT-53 in tumors resected 3 days after the first SGT-53 infusion (optional procedure)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nanoparticle tumor delivery</measure>
    <time_frame>3 days</time_frame>
    <description>As an indicator of nanoparticle delivery to the tumors, DNA PCR will be used to determine the presence of SGT-53 delivered exogenous wt p53 in the tumors. This analysis will be performed on any tumors resected 3 days after the first SGT-53 infusion (optional procedure)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">26</enrollment>
  <condition>RECURRENT GLIOBLASTOMA</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>SGT-53 with Temozolomide</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>SGT-53, at 3.6 mg DNA/infusion, will be administered twice weekly in a 28 day cycle starting on Day 1 (cycle 1), Day 29 (cycle 2) and Day 57 (cycle 3). Temozolomide (TMZ) will be administered by mouth daily on days 9-13 of each cycle. Patients who are responding to treatment may receive three additional cycles of SGT-53/TMZ therapy or continue on TMZ alone at investigator's discretion. Surgical resection of recurrent or progressive tumor for tumor analysis is an optional procedure. In these individuals SGT-53, at 3.6 mg DNA/infusion, will be administered twice (on days -1 and -3) in the week prior to surgery. Surgical resection is Day 0. 14-21 days post operatively and having recovered from the effects of surgery, the patients will then start cyclical TMZ with SGT-53 as described above.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Genetic</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SGT-53</intervention_name>
    <description>SGT-53, at 3.6 mg DNA per infusion, will be administered twice per week for 3 weeks (on Day 1, 4, 8, 11, 15 and 18 of each cycle) for 3 cycles. If SGT-53-related toxicity occurs, the dose of SGT-53 will be de-escalated to 2.4 or 1.2 mg DNA/infusion when appropriate.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SGT-53 with Temozolomide</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Temozolomide</intervention_name>
    <description>TMZ will be administered orally on days 9-13 of each cycle. In cycle 1, the dose of TMZ will be 150 mg/m². If the TMZ-related toxicities are tolerated in cycle 1, the dose of TMZ will be escalated to 200 mg/m² for cycle 2 and beyond. If TMZ-related toxicity occurs, the dose if TMZ will be de-escalated to 125 mg/m² (dose level -1), 100 mg/m² (dose level -2) or 75 mg/m² (dose level -3) when appropriate.</description>
    <arm_group_label>SGT-53 with Temozolomide</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Temodar</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed glioblastoma or gliosarcoma in 1st, 2nd or 3rd relapse.

          -  Radiographic demonstration of disease progression following prior therapy

          -  Measurable disease on MRI performed within 14 days prior to registration.

          -  Male or female patients ≥ 18 years of age.

          -  Recurrent disease with an:

               -  interval of ≥ 3 months following radiotherapy + TMZ;

               -  interval of ≥ 14 days between end of surgery and start of protocol therapy for
                  patients who have undergone surgery for recurrent disease.

          -  Patients who tolerated previous administration with TMZ

          -  Recovery from the effects of prior therapy:

               -  4 weeks from cytotoxic agents

               -  6 weeks from nitrosoureas

               -  4 weeks from any investigational agent

               -  1 week from non-cytotoxic agents

               -  12 weeks from radiotherapy

          -  Karnofsky performance status ≥ 60%.

          -  Complete blood count/differential at screening with adequate bone marrow function

          -  If patient is receiving steroids, must be on stable or decreasing steroid dose within
             5 days prior to treatment initiation with SGT-53.

          -  Patients must be willing to forego other cytotoxic and non-cytotoxic drug or radiation
             therapy against the tumor while enrolled in the study.

          -  Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum beta-HCG pregnancy test
             documented within 3 days prior to study initiation.

          -  Women of childbearing potential must agree to use two reliable methods of
             contraception from screening and up to 30 days after discontinuation of study
             treatment

          -  Males not naturally or surgically sterile, who have a female partner of childbearing
             potential, must agree to use two reliable methods of contraception from screening and
             up to 30 days after discontinuation of study treatment

          -  Acceptable liver function

          -  Acceptable blood sugar control

          -  Urinalysis: No clinically significant abnormalities.

          -  PT and PTT ≤ 1.5 X ULN

          -  Have recovered from any previous therapy side effects or toxicities

          -  Organ function characterized by ≤ Grade 1

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Histology other than astrocytoma grade IV

          -  Tumor foci detected below the tentorium or beyond the cranial vault.

          -  Glioblastoma or gliosarcoma disease with leptomeningeal spread.

          -  Patients with a history of any other cancer, unless in complete remission, and off all
             therapy for that disease for a minimum of 5 years

          -  Patients with serum aspartate aminotransferase, alanine aminotransferase &gt; 2.5 X the
             upper limit of normal (ULN) and bilirubin &gt;1.5 ULN

          -  Moderate to severe hepatic impairment.

          -  Positive results from HIV serology testing, if any available.

          -  Supine systolic blood pressure &lt; 100 mmHg or supine diastolic blood pressure &lt; 50 mmHg
             at screening and baseline

          -  Renal insufficiency or serum creatinine &gt;1.5 X ULN at screening.

          -  Females who are pregnant or lactating or plan to become pregnant during the course of
             this study.

          -  Substance or alcohol abuse or dependence, within 12 months prior to screening.

          -  Prior chemotherapy for recurrent GBM with nitrosourea compounds including Gliadel®
             wafers or bevacizumab.

          -  Prior focal radiotherapy within 3 months of screening.

          -  Planned treatment, or treatment with any investigational drug within 4 weeks prior to
             screening.

          -  Severe, active co-morbidity

          -  Patients who are currently taking Coumadin or Coumadin derivatives other than to
             maintain patency of venous access lines.

          -  Requiring renal dialysis

          -  Receiving hematopoietic growth factors

          -  Have significant baseline neuropathies

          -  Had prior exposure to gene vector delivery products within 6 months

          -  Any condition that prevents compliance with the protocol or adherence to therapy.

          -  Active, uncontrolled bacterial, viral, or fungal infections, requiring systemic
             therapy.

          -  Treated with antibiotics for infection within one week prior to study entry.

          -  Fever (&gt; 38.1°C)

          -  Have diastolic blood pressure of &gt; 90 mm Hg resting at baseline despite medication.

          -  Serious nonmalignant disease

          -  Enrollment in a concomitant clinical study

          -  Have a history of hypersensitivity reaction to any of the components of Temozolomide

          -  Have a history of hypersensitivity to dacarbazine (DTIC)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>John deGroot, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kathy Hunter</last_name>
    <phone>713-745-5769</phone>
    <email>kuhunter@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Winnie Wu</last_name>
    <phone>713-794-1286</phone>
    <email>wcwu@mdanderson.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>MD Anderson Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Houston</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>77030</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathy Hunter</last_name>
      <phone>713-745-5769</phone>
      <email>kuhunter@mdanderson.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>China Medical University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taichung</city>
        <zip>40447</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Sophia Lin</last_name>
      <phone>886-937-722118</phone>
      <email>tinghsun3@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Ya-Hui Lin</last_name>
      <phone>886-978-523673</phone>
      <email>yahuilin02@gmail.com</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Der-Yang Cho, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 18, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 15, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 16, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 13, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 13, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">September 14, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glioblastoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Temozolomide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Dacarbazine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

