<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02349568</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EC-55-066-21-1-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02349568</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Cost Effectiveness of Endoscopic Ultrasound ( EUS ) Based Strategy in Diagnosis of Common Bile Duct Stones</brief_title>
  <official_title>The Cost Effectiveness Between EUS-based Strategy Versus Endoscopic Retrograde Cholangiopancreatography ( ERCP )-Based Strategy in Diagnosis of Common Bile Duct Stones in Patients With Intermediate Risk: a Study in Developing Country.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Prince of Songkla University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Prince of Songkla University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Multiple reports in the literature showed the efficacy of EUS comparable to ERCP in the
      diagnosis of common bile duct ( CBD ) stone. The EUS-based strategy has provided the cost
      effectiveness in diagnosis of CBD stone in defined patient risk groups was showed in previous
      studies. The aim of our study was to assess the cost effectiveness of EUS based strategy
      versus ERCP based strategy in diagnosis of CBD stones in patients with intermediate risks for
      CBD stones in a real working situation in a developing country.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background: Multiple reports showed the efficacy of EUS comparable to ERCP in the diagnosis
      of CBD stone. The EUS-based strategy has provided the cost saving in diagnosis of CBD stone
      in patients with intermediate risk in previous studies in western population. There were
      multiple parameters involved the cost effectiveness analysis included cost of ERCP, cost of
      EUS, prevalence of CBD stones, the sensitivity and specificity of EUS and the rate of
      complications related to EUS and ERCP. These parameter may vary from center to center and
      from region to region.

      Aims: To assess the cost effectiveness of EUS based strategy versus ERCP based strategy in
      diagnosis of CBD stones in patients with intermediate risk in a developing country.

      Method : A prospective study in 141 patients with suspected CBD stones based on clinical,
      biochemical and imaging by trans-abdominal ultrasonography or computed abdominal tomography.
      All patients underwent EUS. All patients with high risk for CBD stone underwent ERCP after
      the EUS. For patients with intermediate risk for CBD stone, ERCP's were done at the
      discretion of the attending physicians. For patients with ERCP done, the diagnosis of CBD
      stone was confirmed by ERCP demonstration of CBD stone. In patients with intermediate risk
      without ERCP done, clinical follow up to assess biliary symptoms and liver function test as
      surrogated markers for CBD stone at 3 months interval for one year were done. The false
      negative rate in patients with EUS and ERCP done in this study was used to estimate the false
      negative rate in patients in clinical surrogated group.

      Definition: High risk of CBD stones was defined when CBD stone was detected by US/CT or
      dilated duct with abnormal liver function test ( LFT ). Intermediate risk of CBD stones was
      defined when US/CT showed normal bile duct with abnormal LFT or dilated duct with normal LFT.

      Cost analysis :The cost of making diagnosis of CBD stone excluding all costs of treatment was
      analyzed. The cost of all patients with suspected CBD stones undergoing ERCP was calculated
      and compared with the strategy of EUS follow by ERCP. The cost was evaluated by (1) mean
      costs of EUS and ERCP based on the actual cost in our center which included costs of medical
      staffs, disposable materials, drugs, equipment amortization and maintenance. (2) cost
      associated with complications induced by the procedure.

      Statistical analysis: Test performance of the endoscopic ultrasound in diagnosis of CBD
      stones was analyzed with two by two tables. The sensitivity, specificity, positive and
      negative predictive values were calculated.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The cost of making diagnosis of CBD stone</measure>
    <time_frame>within 12 months after EUS</time_frame>
    <description>The cost of making diagnosis of CBD stone will be measured as the difference in the cost of all patients undergoing ERCP and ERCP follow by EUS intervention. The cost was evaluated by (1) mean costs of EUS and ERCP based on the actual cost in our center which included costs of medical staffs, disposable materials, drugs, equipment amortization and maintenance. (2) costs associated with complications induced by the procedure.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The accuracy of EUS in diagnosis of CBD stone</measure>
    <time_frame>within 12 months after EUS</time_frame>
    <description>This will be measured as proportion of patients who encounter a correctly diagnosis of CBD stone by EUS. Positive EUS finding was confirmed by ERCP. Negative EUS finding was confirmed by ERCP or absence of symptoms for 12 months.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The safety of EUS and ERCP procedure</measure>
    <time_frame>within 1 months</time_frame>
    <description>This will be measured as proportion of patients who encounter a procedural complication (%) during EUS and ERCP that includes pancreatitis, perforation or hemorrhage</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">141</enrollment>
  <condition>Common Bile Duct Calculi</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>High risk group</arm_group_label>
    <description>High risk group was defined when CBD stones was detected by ultrasound ( US ) / computed tomography ( CT ) or dilated duct with abnormal LFT.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intermediate risk group</arm_group_label>
    <description>Intermediate risk group was defined when US/CT showed normal bile duct with abnormal LFT or dilated duct with normal LFT.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>High risk group</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with high risk underwent EUS examination under conscious sedation. EUS was examined from second part of duodenum up to duodenal bulb. All patients even if negative EUS examination of CBD stone were underwent ERCP in the same session. The ERCPs were performed in standard manner. All patients were contacted by phone on day 1, 3 and 30 after the procedure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>High risk group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>EUS examination follow by ERCP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intermediate risk group</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with intermediate risk underwent EUS examination under conscious sedation. EUS was examined from second part of duodenum up to duodenal bulb. ERCPs were done at the discretion of the attending physicians. The ERCPs were performed in standard manner. The patients without ERCP done were contacted at 3 months interval to assess symptoms and LFT for 12 months.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intermediate risk group</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>EUS examination follow by ERCP or clinical follow up</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All patients with suspected CBD stones based on clinical, biochemical and imaging by
        trans-abdominal ultrasonography or computed tomography..
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  history of biliary pain or recent cholangitis

          -  acute pancreatitis

          -  abnormal liver function test

          -  dilatation of CBD and or CBD stone detected by trans-abdominal ultrasound and or
             computed tomography.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  unstable hemodynamics

          -  severe coagulopathy

          -  refusal to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bancha Ovartlarnporn, MD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>NKC Institue of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Faculty of Medicine, Prince of Songkla University, Hatyai, Songkla, Thailand.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NKC Institues of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Prince of Songkla University</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hatyai</city>
        <state>Songkhla</state>
        <zip>90110</zip>
        <country>Thailand</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Thailand</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 16, 2015</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 23, 2015</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 29, 2015</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 23, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 23, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 29, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Prince of Songkla University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Nisa Netinatsunton</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>NKC Institute of Gastroenterology and Hepatology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Calculi</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Gallstones</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

