<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01402024</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>CT/38/011/RS</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01402024</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Study to Evaluate Anti-emetic Effect of Aprepitant Versus Placebo in Children and Adolescent Receiving Chemotherapy</brief_title>
  <acronym>Aprepitant</acronym>
  <official_title>A Study to Evaluate the Anti-emetic Effect of Aprepitant Versus Placebo as an Add-on Therapy in Children and Adolescent Receiving Chemotherapy: A Randomized, Doubly Blinded Controlled Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Dr. Reddy's Laboratories Limited</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Chemotherapy induced nausea and vomiting (CINV) is one of the few mostly observed distressing
      toxicity of cancer treatment. It can occur up to 90% in case of highly emetogenic
      chemotherapy use. CINV causes disturbance in daily living of cancer patient and reduces
      compliance with treatment Even with the standard anti-emetic measures up to 50% patient can
      suffer from this complication. Whereas there is standard anti-emetic guideline exists in case
      of adult patients, there no such guidelines made in pediatric population. The new drug
      Aprepitant has been recommended for use in adults with high efficacy, there no such concrete
      data available in children regarding its use. There are few retrospective reports and limited
      data available regarding use of Aprepitant in children with satisfactory efficacy in reducing
      CINV. As there no randomized large data to suggests its efficacy and its routine use in
      children, we have planned this study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Population:

      Children and adolescents (5-18 years) with weight between 15-65 kg receiving highly
      emetogenic chemotherapy (HEC) -

        -  VAC (vincristine, dactinomycin/Adriamycin, cyclophosphamide)

        -  ABVD (adriamycin, bleomycin, vinblastine, dacarbazine)

        -  Cisplatin/Doxorubicin

      Sampling technique Subjects who met the eligibility criteria will be randomly assigned using
      random allocation number generated by computer into one of the two groups. The unit of
      randomization will be the subject at first cycle of HEC. The same patient will not be
      enrolled for twice

      Procedure for data collection:

        1. The data will be collected from each patient from d1 to d10 of chemotherapy of which
           patient will received chemotherapy in day care, maximum up to d3.

        2. After taking consent patient will be enrolled as per inclusion and exclusion criteria,
           and randomized to one of two groups. All baseline assessment will be done. Patient will
           be explained about the filling of the diary. In first 2 days. The subjects will fill the
           diary under the investigator supervision, and the rest of filling will be in home.
           Reinforcement will be done over phone.

      Procedure of double blinding

        -  Double blinding will be done for the intervention. Four different boxes will be made for
           capsules. Total 3 capsules for 3 days will be made in a blister pack, mentioning the d1,
           d2, d3 (for each capsule). Two different body weight groups will be made: 15-40 kg, and
           41-65 kg.

        -  Group &quot;A&quot; will be the code for Aprepitant group and group &quot;B&quot; will be code for control
           group. Both patient and the investigator will be blinded regarding medicine in the code.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>- Numbers of episodes of nausea and vomiting. - Duration of nausea (in hours). - Severity of nausea as per Edmonton's Symptom Assessment System (ESAS), numerical scale for nausea.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>- Chemotherapy induced additional side effects. - Number of anti-emetic dosage (other than aprepitant) required for treatment of vomiting.</measure>
    <time_frame>5 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">96</enrollment>
  <condition>Chemotherapy Induced Nausea and Vomiting</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Aprepitant</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>It is an double blind randomized placebo controlled trial with age group of 5-18 years and weight between 15-65 kg, who will receive highly emetogenic chemotherapy. Patient who will meet the inclusion criteria will be randomly enrolled in either of the two arm-aprepitant arm and control arm. The patient on aprepitant arm will receive the study drug (aprepitant)along with standard anti-emetic therapy (as per the dosages mentioned in the protocol).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>It is an double blind randomized placebo controlled trial with age group of 5-18 years and weight between 15-65 kg, who will receive highly emetogenic chemotherapy. Patient who will meet the inclusion criteria will be randomly enrolled in either of the two arm-aprepitant arm and control arm. The patient on the control arm will receive the placebo along with standard anti-emetic therapy (as per the dosages mentioned in the protocol).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aprepitant</intervention_name>
    <description>The patient on study group with weight category of 15-40 kg will receive:
D1- Dexamethasone 0.15 mg/kg, ondansetron (0.15 mg/kg, single dose), Aprepitant 80 mg; D2- Dexamethasone 0.15 mg/kg, ondansetron (0.15 mg/kg, single dose), Aprepitant 80 mg; D3- Dexamethasone 0.15 mg/kg, ondansetron (0.15 mg/kg, single dose), Aprepitant 80 mg and
The patient with weight category of 41-65 kg in study group will receive:
D1- Dexamethasone 0.15 mg/kg, ondansetron (0.15 mg/kg, single dose), Aprepitant 125 mg; D2- Dexamethasone 0.15 mg/kg, ondansetron (0.15 mg/kg, single dose), Aprepitant 80 mg; D3- Dexamethasone 0.15 mg/kg, ondansetron (0.15 mg/kg, single dose), Aprepitant 80 mg</description>
    <arm_group_label>Aprepitant</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Empov</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Patient on control group with weight category of 15-40 kg will receive:
D1- Dexamethasone 0.15 mg/kg, ondansetron (0.15 mg/kg, single dose), Aprepitant placebo 80 mg; D2- Dexamethasone 0.15 mg/kg, ondansetron (0.15 mg/kg, single dose), Aprepitant placebo 80 mg; D3- Dexamethasone 0.15 mg/kg, ondansetron (0.15 mg/kg, single dose), Aprepitant placebo 80 mg; and
The patient on control group with weight category of 41-65 kg will receive:
D1- Dexamethasone 0.15 mg/kg, ondansetron (0.15 mg/kg, single dose), Aprepitant placebo 125 mg; D2- Dexamethasone 0.15 mg/kg, ondansetron (0.15 mg/kg, single dose), Aprepitant placebo 80 mg; D3- Dexamethasone 0.15 mg/kg, ondansetron (0.15 mg/kg, single dose), Aprepitant placebo 80 mg (all are injectable except Aprepitant oral capsule).</description>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Empov placebo capsules</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All subjects must have a confirmed diagnosis of malignancy and receiving highly
             emetogenic chemotherapy first time (VAC, ABVD and CDDP/Doxorubicin)

          -  Age group 5-18 years with weight between 15-65 kg

          -  Children/adolescents and their caregiver who can understand Hindi or English and
             willing to participate in the study (with written informed consent)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Significant organ dysfunction

          -  Active infection

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Uncontrolled medical condition other than malignancy

          -  Need for contraindicated concomitant medication

          -  Patients receiving chemotherapy other than VAC, ABVD and CDDP/Doxorubicin

          -  Treatment with another investigational drug within 4 weeks of study start or prior
             Aprepitant use

          -  Had received or will receive RT to abdomen or pelvis in the week prior to treatment

          -  Vomited in the 24 hr prior to treatment

          -  Prior exposure to highly emetogenic chemotherapeutics

          -  Abnormal lab values (ANC&lt;1500/mm3, TLC&lt;3000/mm3, Plt&lt;100,000/mm3, AST/ALT&gt; 2.5 times
             of ULN, bill&gt;1.5 times of ULN, S.cr&gt;1.5 times of ULN, patient on systemic steroids
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sameer Bakhshi, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Dr. BRA IRCH, AIIMS, New Delhi (India)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Dr. BRA IRCH, AIIMS</name>
      <address>
        <city>New Delhi</city>
        <state>Delhi</state>
        <zip>110029</zip>
        <country>India</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>India</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>July 19, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>July 25, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">July 26, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 16, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 16, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 19, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>All India Institute of Medical Sciences, New Delhi</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Sameer Bakhshi</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Additional Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vomiting</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aprepitant</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Fosaprepitant</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Antiemetics</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Emetics</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

