<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01342419</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>22010</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01342419</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Circadian Rhythms of Aqueous Humor Dynamics When Using Brimonidine in Humans With Ocular Hypertension</brief_title>
  <official_title>Circadian Rhythms of Aqueous Humor Dynamics When Using Brimonidine in Humans With Ocular Hypertension</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Nebraska</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Nebraska</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This single-center, investigator-masked, crossover study is designed to investigate the
      circadian rhythms of aqueous humor dynamics in human subjects with ocular hypertension (OHT)
      before and after intervention with a commonly used ocular hypotensive medication,
      brimonidine.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Currently, the only effective treatment to prevent disease progression is lowering of the
      intraocular pressure (IOP).2 Usually, clinical IOP measurements are performed during the day
      with little information collected on nocturnal IOP. A recent surge of interest in nocturnal
      IOPs stems from the hypothesis that significant glaucomatous damage may occur at night.4,5 In
      response, some investigators have advocated particular classes of glaucoma medications based
      on their nocturnal IOP effects.6-8 The most efficacious drug on the market may not be the
      preferred treatment if it is ineffective at night. Therefore, the understanding of nighttime
      IOP and the aqueous humor dynamics that control it has important scientific, clinical, and
      commercial implications.

      Previous research on glaucoma medications has been limited to the effects of ocular
      hypotensive drugs on 24-hour IOP or daytime aqueous humor dynamics. Few studies have
      evaluated nocturnal aqueous humor dynamics. The investigators recently completed studies of
      day and night differences in aqueous humor dynamics in patients treated with drugs from three
      different classes that include a prostaglandin analog, a beta blocker and a carbonic
      anhydrase inhibitor. The current study is designed to elucidate the physiological mechanisms
      driving the efficacy of brimonidine, an alpha 2 adrenergic agonist, throughout the 24-hour
      period, i.e. circadian rhythms in aqueous humor dynamics. Based on what the investigators
      know of 24 hour IOPs this drug is expected to work well at night potentially by enhancing
      uveoscleral outflow. This study will test this hypothesis.

      In studies of new glaucoma medications the preferred study population includes ocular
      hypertensive subjects. These people have high IOP but no optic nerve damage and no glaucoma.
      They may be taking prescribed IOP lowering drugs for this condition or they may not. Those
      taking ocular drugs are asked to stop taking them. Since glaucoma drugs affect aqueous humor
      dynamics in different ways, it is essential that no residual medical effect remains from
      these drugs. A washout period is necessary to remove all topical ocular drug effects. A
      concern for patient safety exists when OHT patients are taken off of glaucoma medications, as
      IOP may rise during the washout period. In order to monitor IOP in these patients, a biweekly
      check of the IOP is made. If pressure rises above the ophthalmologist's preset &quot;target
      pressure&quot; at any point, then the patient is removed from the study and returned to his/her
      previous medical regimen.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Crossover</observational_model>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Actual">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Glaucoma Suspects</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with intraocular pressure between 21 - 35 mmHg
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  History of untreated intraocular pressure (IOO) between 21 and 35 mmHg

          -  19 years of age and older

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnant or nursing

          -  Aphakia or pseudophakia

          -  Best corrected visual acuity worse than 20/60 in either eye

          -  Chronic or recurrent severe ocular inflammatory disease

          -  Ocular infection or inflammation within (3 months of screening visit

          -  History of clinically significant or progressive retinal disease such as retinal
             degeneration, diabetic retinopathy or retinal detachment

          -  Any abnormality preventing reliable tonometry of either eye

          -  History of any severe ocular pathology or serious hypersensitivity to (including
             severe dry eye) that would preclude the administration of a topical Brimonidine or its
             vehicle.

          -  Any eye with a cup-to-disc ratio greater than 0.8

          -  History of intraocular surgery

          -  History of laser surgery

          -  History of severe, unstable, or uncontrolled cardiovascular, hepatic or renal disease

          -  Less than one month (Prior to baseline) stable dosing regimen of any non-glaucoma
             medication that would affect IOP.

          -  Gonioscopy angle &lt;2

          -  Inability to discontinue contact lens wear.

          -  Therapy with any investigational agent within 30 days of screening.

          -  Use of any additional topical or systemic adjunctive ocular hypotensive medications
             during the study.

          -  History of open angle glaucoma (either primary open angle glaucoma or other cause of
             open angle glaucoma) or narrow angle glaucoma.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Carol Toris, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>UNMC Department of Ophthalmology and Visual Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Nebraska Medical Center, Department of Ophthalmology</name>
      <address>
        <city>Omaha</city>
        <state>Nebraska</state>
        <zip>68198</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 25, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 26, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 27, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 13, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 13, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 14, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Nebraska</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Carol B. Toris, BA MS PhD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ocular Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Brimonidine Tartrate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

