<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01348672</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>ORF2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01348672</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Study Phase: Retinal Oxygen Saturation, Blood Flow, Vascular Function and High Resolution Morphometric Imaging in the Living Human Eye</brief_title>
  <official_title>Prospective Study Phase: Retinal Oxygen Saturation, Blood Flow, Vascular Function and High Resolution Morphometric Imaging in the Living Human Eye</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Toronto</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ontario Research Fund</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Toronto</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Canadians fear loss of vision more than any other disability. Vision loss has an enormous
      impact on quality-of-life and is extremely costly from a societal and economic perspective.
      In 2001, more than 600,000 Canadians were estimated to have severe vision loss, accounting
      for 17% of total disability in Canada. One in 9 individuals experience severe vision loss by
      65 years of age; however, this increases to 1 in 4 individuals by 75 years. The financial
      cost of vision loss in Canada is $15.8 billion per year. There is a general perception that
      vision loss is &quot;normal with aging&quot; but 75% of vision loss is estimated to be preventable. The
      major causes of severe vision loss are age-related macular degeneration (ARMD), glaucoma,
      particularly primary open-angle glaucoma (POAG), and diabetic retinopathy (DR). Canada is
      headed for an epidemic of age-related eye disease and, unless something is done to prepare
      for this, severe vision loss will have significant consequences in terms of societal and
      economic costs. Through this proposed Research Program, and in conjunction with the
      investigators international academic and private sector partners, the investigators will
      build and develop unique quantitative imaging technologies to permit non-invasive assessment
      of visual changes, structural changes in the thickness of the retina at the back of the eye
      and also changes in the amount of blood flowing through the blood vessels that feed the
      retina with oxygen. This research will add to the investigators basic knowledge in predicting
      the development of sight-threatening change in patients with the three diseases, and
      facilitate earlier detection of the problem to help us discover earlier treatments for people
      with these conditions. The reliability of each imaging technology will be assessed by
      determining its ability to differentiate between diseased and healthy eyes. Cross-sectional
      analyses at yearly intervals, as well as change over time analyses, will be undertaken.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This research will add to our basic knowledge in predicting the development of
      sight-threatening change in patient with the ARMD, diabetic retinopathy and primary open
      glaucoma, and facilitate earlier detection of the problem to help us discover earlier
      treatments for people with these conditions. The reliability of each imaging technology will
      be assessed by determining its ability to differentiate between diseased and healthy eyes.
      Through this proposed Research Program, and in conjunction with our international academic
      and private sector partners, we will build and develop unique quantitative imaging
      technologies to:

        -  Comprehensively assess the blood supply to, and vascular regulation characteristics of
           the posterior segment of the eye, a diagnostic capability that is currently severely
           limited.

        -  Assess oxygen saturation disturbances in the retina and ON that occur prior to
           clinically detectable changes, diagnostic capability that currently does not exist

        -  Using the retinal blood supply and oxygen saturation parameters, we will derive net
           oxygen delivery to the retina and optic nerve head (ONH), a diagnostic capability that
           does not exist.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>March 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cross-sectional relationship between retinal / ON oxygen saturation, vascular dysregulation and retinal morphometry</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>To investigate the cross-sectional relationship between retinal / ON oxygen saturation, vascular dysregulation and retinal morphometry in groups of patients at risk of progres</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Prospective relationship between retinal/ON oxygen saturation disturbances, vascular dysregulation, retinal morphometry and clinical outcomes</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>To establish the prospective relationship between retinal/ON oxygen saturation disturbances, vascular dysregulation, retinal morphometry and clinical outcomes in patients at risk of progression of ARMD, POAG and DR and age-matched healthy controls</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Topographic distribution of retinal / ON oxygen saturation disturbance, vascular dysfunction and change in morphometric parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>5 years</time_frame>
    <description>To investigate the topographic distribution of retinal / ON oxygen saturation disturbance, vascular dysfunction and change in morphometric parameters in groups of patients at risk of progression of ARMD, POAG and DR</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">381</enrollment>
  <condition>Age Related Macular Degeneration</condition>
  <condition>Glaucoma</condition>
  <condition>Diabetic Retinopathy.</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1. ARMD Study arm</arm_group_label>
    <description>The ARMD study arm (n=150) consists of 3 groups. The groups are organised according to established risk criteria for clinical progression (AREDS, 2003).
Group 1A (n=50); Early stage ARMD with low risk of progression; several small drusen, or a few medium-sized drusen, in one or both eyes. One eye will be randomly selected for the study.
Group 2A (n=50); Intermediate ARMD with high risk of progression to advanced ARMD; many medium-sized drusen, or one or more large drusen, in one or both eyes. More severely affected eyewill be selected for the study.
Group 3A (n=50); In one eye only, either a break-down of light-sensitive cells and supporting tissue in the central retinal area (i.e. geographic atrophy), or abnormal and fragile blood vessels under the retina (i.e. choroidal neovascular membrane formation). The fellow eye is at high risk of progression to advanced ARMD. The fellow eye will be selected for the study.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2. POAG study arm</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patient groups are organised according to established risk criteria for clinical progression (EMGT, 2003).
Group 1P (n=36); Stable, early to moderate, treated patients with POAG. Early to moderate POAG is defined as having an untreated IOP prior to treatment of &gt;21mmHg and a repeatable visual field defect with a Mean Deviation of &lt;12dB and/or documented but stable ONH appearance, consistent with a diagnosis of glaucoma.
Group 2P (n=36); Early to moderate, treated patients with normal tension glaucoma (NTG). Normal Tension Glaucoma is defined using the same criteria as POAG but with an untreated IOP of &lt;21mmHg throughout the day. This group has NTG and is thought to be at increased risk of vascular dysfunction due to loss of ONH perfusion.
Group 3P (n=36); Early to moderate, treated patients with POAG or NTG with recurrent disc hemorrhage (indicative of progression).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>3. DR study arm</arm_group_label>
    <description>DR patient groups are organised according to established risk factors for the clinical progression of DR (increasing from Groups 1 A to 3 A, ETDRS, 1991). We will recruit 41 patients per group (Klein et al, 1984).
Group 1D (n=41); Type 2 diabetic patients with no, or minimal, clinically visible DR. These patients are at low risk of developing sight-threatening DR.
Group 2D (n=41); Type 2 diabetic patients with microaneurysms and / or hard exudates within 2 disc diameters of the fovea and no clinical evidence of retinal thickening. These patients are at increased risk of developing DME.
Group 3D (n=41); Type 2 diabetic patients with the typical features of moderate-to-severe DR i.e. venous beading, intra-retinal microvascular abnormalities (IRMA) and dark blot intra-retinal haemorrhages. These patients are at a much increased risk of developing proliferative DR and/or ischemic maculopathy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        The cohorts will be selected from the clinics of retinal and glaucoma specialists at the
        Toronto Western Hospital and will be identified from their charts. Clinicians will ask
        eligible patients whether they would be interested in participating.

        Also flyers advertising the study will be posted at Toronto Western Hospital and anyone
        interested can contact the principal investigator.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion criteria:

          -  Subjects diagnosed with age related macular degeneration

          -  Subjects diagnosed with glaucoma

          -  Subjects diagnosed with diabetic retinopathy
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>40 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christopher Hudson, OD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Toronto Western Hospital, Toronto Western Research Institute, University of Toronto, University of Waterloo</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Chris Hudson, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>416 603 5694</phone>
    <email>chudson@uwaterloo.ca</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Toronto Western Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Toronto</city>
        <state>Ontario</state>
        <zip>M5T 2S8</zip>
        <country>Canada</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Chris Hudson, Ph.D</last_name>
      <phone>416 603 5694</phone>
      <email>chudson@uwaterloo.ca</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Canada</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bressler NM, Bressler SB, Congdon NG, Ferris FL 3rd, Friedman DS, Klein R, Lindblad AS, Milton RC, Seddon JM; Age-Related Eye Disease Study Research Group. Potential public health impact of Age-Related Eye Disease Study results: AREDS report no. 11. Arch Ophthalmol. 2003 Nov;121(11):1621-4.</citation>
    <PMID>14609922</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klein R, Wang Q, Klein BE, Moss SE, Meuer SM. The relationship of age-related maculopathy, cataract, and glaucoma to visual acuity. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci. 1995 Jan;36(1):182-91.</citation>
    <PMID>7822146</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fundus photographic risk factors for progression of diabetic retinopathy. ETDRS report number 12. Early Treatment Diabetic Retinopathy Study Research Group. Ophthalmology. 1991 May;98(5 Suppl):823-33.</citation>
    <PMID>2062515</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Klein R, Klein BE, Moss SE, Davis MD, DeMets DL. The Wisconsin epidemiologic study of diabetic retinopathy. III. Prevalence and risk of diabetic retinopathy when age at diagnosis is 30 or more years. Arch Ophthalmol. 1984 Apr;102(4):527-32.</citation>
    <PMID>6367725</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Leske MC, Heijl A, Hussein M, Bengtsson B, Hyman L, Komaroff E; Early Manifest Glaucoma Trial Group. Factors for glaucoma progression and the effect of treatment: the early manifest glaucoma trial. Arch Ophthalmol. 2003 Jan;121(1):48-56.</citation>
    <PMID>12523884</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 27, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 4, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 5, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 16, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 16, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 17, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Toronto</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Chris Hudson</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Age related macular degeneration</keyword>
  <keyword>Glaucoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Diabetic retinopathy</keyword>
  <keyword>Retinal oxygen saturation</keyword>
  <keyword>Blood flow</keyword>
  <keyword>Vascular function</keyword>
  <keyword>High resolution imaging</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Macular Degeneration</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Retinal Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetic Retinopathy</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

