<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01846624</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HEMAML0022</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>IRB-31582</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01846624</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Decitabine and Midostaurin in Treating Older Patients With Newly Diagnosed Acute Myeloid Leukemia</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 2 Study of Decitabine in Combination With Midostaurin (PKC412) for Elderly Patients With Newly Diagnosed FLT3-ITD/TKD Positive Acute Myeloid Leukemia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>David Iberri</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Stanford University</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase 2 study evaluates the sequential combination of decitabine then midostaurin for
      the treatment of newly-diagnosed acute myeloid leukemia (AML) in older patients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Treatment with decitabine, a cytidine analog, then midostaurin, a multi-target protein kinase
      inhibitor (PKI), may stop the growth of cancer cells by blocking some of the enzymes needed
      for cell growth.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2024</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete remission (CR) rate</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Median duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">36</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myeloid Leukemia (AML) With Multilineage Dysplasia Following Myelodysplastic Syndrome, in Adults</condition>
  <condition>AML (Adult) With 11q23 (MLL) Abnormalities</condition>
  <condition>AML (Adult) With Del(5q)</condition>
  <condition>AML (Adult) With Inv(16)(p13;q22)</condition>
  <condition>AML (Adult) With t(16;16)(p13;q22)</condition>
  <condition>AML (Adult) With t(8;21)(q22;q22)</condition>
  <condition>Secondary AML (Adult)</condition>
  <condition>Untreated AML (Adult)</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Decitabine, then midostaurin</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>INDUCTION THERAPY Subjects receive decitabine intravenously (IV) over 1 hour on days 1 to 10 and midostaurin orally (PO) twice daily (BID) on days 11 to 28. Treatment repeats every 28 days until documented bone marrow response is achieved or for up to 12 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity. Patients achieving documented bone marrow response by course 6 continue treatment with induction therapy; patients achieving response after course 6 proceed to post-remission therapy.
POST-REMISSION THERAPY Subjects receive decitabine IV over 1 hour on days 1 to 5 and midostaurin PO BID on days 6 to 28. Treatment repeats every 28 days for up to 12 courses (including induction therapy) in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.
After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up for up to 1 year.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Decitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Decitabine, then midostaurin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>5-aza-dCyd</other_name>
    <other_name>5AZA</other_name>
    <other_name>DAC</other_name>
    <other_name>Dacogen</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Midostaurin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given PO</description>
    <arm_group_label>Decitabine, then midostaurin</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>N-benzoyl-staurosporine</other_name>
    <other_name>PKC412</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Newly-diagnosed acute myeloid leukemia (AML) per the World Health Organization [WHO]
             2008 classification [except t(15;17)], including:

               -  De novo AML

               -  Secondary AML

               -  Secondary AML arising from previously-diagnosed myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS)
                  treated with deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) methyltransferase inhibitor (DNMTi) (ie,
                  decitabine or azacitidine)

          -  FLT3-ITD mutation confirmed in bone marrow aspirate

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status ≤ 2

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≤ 2.5 x upper
             limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Serum bilirubin ≤ 2.5 ULN

          -  Serum creatinine ≤ 1.5 mg/dL and/or creatinine clearance ≥ 50 mL/min

          -  Ejection fraction ≥ 50% by echocardiogram

          -  Unwillingness or inability to receive conventional chemotherapy

          -  Ability to understand and the willingness to sign a written informed consent document

          -  Ability to adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol requirements

          -  Life expectancy &gt; 2 months

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Receiving concomitant treatment with other anti-neoplastic agents (EXCEPTION:
             hydroxyurea). Prior treatment with DNMTi therapy (ie, decitabine or azacitidine) for
             MDS is allowed

          -  Received anti-neoplastic treatment within 4 weeks prior to enrollment (EXCEPTION:
             hydroxyurea)

          -  Received any surgical procedure, excluding central venous catheter placement or other
             minor procedures (eg, skin biopsy) within 14 days of study day 1

          -  Received any investigational agent within 4 weeks prior to enrollment

          -  Previous or current history of a myeloproliferative disease

          -  Known active central nervous system (CNS) malignancy

          -  Any other known disease (except carcinoma in-situ), concurrent severe and/or
             uncontrolled medical condition which could compromise participation in the study (eg,
             uncontrolled diabetes; cardiovascular disease including congestive heart failure;
             myocardial infarction within 6 months with poorly controlled hypertension; chronic
             renal disease; active uncontrolled infection)

          -  Active opportunistic infection or treatment for opportunistic infection within 4 weeks
             of first day of study drug dosing

          -  Known confirmed diagnosis of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection or active
             viral hepatitis

          -  Known impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may
             significantly alter the absorption of midostaurin

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to midostaurin and/or decitabine

          -  Impaired cardiac function including any of the following:

               -  Screening electrocardiogram (ECG) with a corrected QT interval (QTc) &gt; 450 msec

               -  Bradycardia defined as heart rate (HR) &lt; 50 beats per minute (bpm)

               -  Right bundle branch block + left anterior hemiblock (bifascicular block)

               -  Patients with myocardial infarction or unstable angina &lt; 3 months prior to
                  starting study drug

               -  Congestive heart failure (CHF) New York (NY) Heart Association class III or IV

          -  Inability to swallow or absorb drug

          -  Other medical or psychiatric illness or organ dysfunction or laboratory abnormality
             which in the opinion of the investigator would compromise the patient's safety or
             interfere with data interpretation

          -  Unwillingness or inability to comply with the protocol

          -  Pregnant

          -  nursing (lactating)

          -  Women of child-bearing potential, defined as all women physiologically capable of
             becoming pregnant, UNLESS they are using highly effective methods of contraception
             during dosing and for 3 months after midostaurin medication; highly effective
             contraception methods as follows:

               -  Total abstinence, when this is in line with the preferred and usual lifestyle of
                  the subject [periodic abstinence (eg, calendar, ovulation, symptothermal,
                  post-ovulation methods) and withdrawal are not acceptable methods of
                  contraception]

               -  Female sterilization (surgical bilateral oophorectomy with or without
                  hysterectomy; or tubal ligation at least six weeks before taking study
                  treatment). In case of oophorectomy alone, reproductive status must be confirmed
                  by follow-up hormone level assessment

               -  Male sterilization, at least 6 months prior to screening (for female subjects on
                  the study, the vasectomized male partner should be the sole partner for that
                  subject)

               -  Combination of any two of the following (a+b or a+c, or b+c):

                    -  Use of oral, injected or implanted hormonal methods of contraception or
                       other forms of hormonal contraception that have comparable efficacy (failure
                       rate &lt; 1%), eg, hormone vaginal ring or transdermal hormone contraception.
                       For oral contraception, women should have been stable on the same pill for a
                       minimum of 3 months before taking study treatment

                    -  Placement of an intrauterine device (IUD) or intrauterine system (IUS)

                    -  Barrier methods of contraception: Condom or Occlusive cap (diaphragm or
                       cervical/vault caps) with spermicidal foam/gel/film/cream/vaginal
                       suppository
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>60 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bruno C. Medeiros</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>David Iberri</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Stanford University, School of Medicine</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stanford</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94305</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Jack Taw</last_name>
      <phone>650-723-2781</phone>
      <email>jtaw@stanford.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Bruno C. de Medeiros</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>David Iberri</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 30, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 30, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 3, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 29, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Stanford University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>David Iberri</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Leukemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leukemia, Myeloid, Acute</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myelodysplastic Syndromes</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Preleukemia</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Decitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Azacitidine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Midostaurin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Staurosporine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

