<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01848886</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-3-2012-116</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>H-3-2012-116</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01848886</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Neurological Complications Comparing Endoscopically vs. Open Harvest of the Radial Artery</brief_title>
  <acronym>NEO</acronym>
  <official_title>Endoscopic Versus Open Radial Artery Harvest and Mammario-radial Versus Aorto-radial Grafting in Patients Undergoing Coronary Artery Bypass Surgery (The 2x2 Factorial Designed Randomised NEO Trial)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG) using the radial artery (RA) has since the nineties
      gone through a revival. The initially reported worse outcome in RA graft patients compared to
      patients grafted with the saphenous vein (SV) has since been corrected. Studies have shown
      better patency when using RA, so the RA is going to be preferred more and more especially in
      younger patients where long time patency is critical. During the last 10 years endoscopic
      techniques to harvest the RA have evolved. Multiple different techniques have been used, but
      now the equipment and technique have been refined and are highly reliable. The investigators
      hypothesize that the endoscopic technique has less complications and a just as good patency
      as open harvest. There are also two possible ways to use the RA as a graft. One way is sewing
      it onto the aorta and another way is sewing it onto the mammarian artery. The investigators
      hypothesize that using it on the mammarian artery is superior as a revascularisation
      technique with just as good a patency as sewing it directly onto the aorta.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objectives

      The present trial will in patients undergoing CABG (1) evaluate the complications in
      endoscopic versus traditionally harvested radial arteries, (2) evaluate graft patency in
      endoscopic harvested radial arteries versus open technique, and (3) evaluate the use of
      mammario-radial grafting versus aorto-radial grafting.

      Design and trial size

      The NEO Trial is a randomised clinical trial with a 2x2 factorial design. We plan to
      randomise 300 participants into four intervention groups: (1) mammario-radial endovascular
      group; (2) aorto-radial endovascular group; (3) mammario-radial open group and (4)
      aorto-radial open group. A subgroup of 100 participants will be selected to undergo a special
      scanning of the vascular perfusion of donor and control hands (MIBI scan). The evaluation of
      graft patency and ischaemia in the arm will be blinded but the assessment of the primary
      outcome of handfunction at three months is non-blinded evaluated by questionnaire.

      Trial interventions

      Trial 1: The experimental procedure in this trial will be endoscopic radial artery harvest
      (ERAH). The control intervention will be open radial artery harvest (ORAH).

      Trial 2: The experimental procedure in this trial will be the technique where the radial
      artery is sewn onto the mammarian artery as a mammario-radial anastomosis
      (composite/Y-graft). The control intervention will be the technique of sewing the radial
      artery directly onto the aorta as an aorto-radial anastomosis (free radial artery).

      Inclusion and exclusion criteria

      All patients referred to our department for sub acute or elective coronary bypass operation
      will be eligible for trial inclusion. Inclusion criteria are: 18 years or older; able and
      willing to give informed consent; multi-vessel disease. Exclusion criteria are: off-pump
      procedure; multi-procedure (i.e. concomitant valve surgery); contrast allergy; geographically
      not available for follow-up; Allen's test with insufficient ulnary artery perfusion; no
      informed consent; acute operation; dialysis; preoperative neurological deficit on the donor
      arm; left ventricle ejection fraction (LVEF) less than 20%; former sternotomy and malignant
      disease.

      Primary and secondary outcomes

      Trial 1: The primary outcome will be evaluation of hand function at three months.

      The secondary outcomes will be: occurrence of neurophysiological defects in the donor arm
      assessed by examination of cutaneous sensibility and measurements of the sensory and motoric
      nervous conduction velocity preoperatively and after three months; change in subjective
      cutaneous sensibility assessed by a clinical examination after three months; complications
      assessed as a composite of haematoma formation, wound dehiscence or infection registered
      before discharge and after three months.

      We will also assess a number of exploratory outcomes (serious adverse events, reoperation for
      bleeding, revascularisation, myocardial infarction, stroke or death, handgrip strength,
      muscular function in the hand, scar evaluation, vascular supply to the hand, graft patency
      and participants subjective evaluation of hand function after 1 year).

      Trial 2: The primary outcome will be the occurrence of cardio- or cerebrovascular events
      during the first year after surgery comparing mammario-radial versus aorto-radial grafts. As
      an exploratory outcome we will also assess graft patency by multi-slice computer tomography
      (MSCT) comparing mammarioradial versus aortoradial grafts one year after surgery.

      Time schedule

      Randomisation will commence after 15th of May 2013. The inclusion period of altogether 300
      participants is expected to last three years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Factorial Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Sum score of hand function questionnaire</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Using Likert-type scale scoring system quality of life is assessed after radial artery harvest. The mean values in the ERAH group will be compared to the mean value in the ORAH group at three months after surgery.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Occurence of cardiac and cerebrovascular events in aortoradial versus mammarioradial grafting</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of one of the following cardiac or cerebrovascular events: all cause mortality, myocardial infarction (MI), target vessel revascularisation (TVR) or stroke at one year postoperatively will be compared.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complications in the donor arm in ERAH versus ORAH</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of complications at three months after surgery. Complications are defined as a composite of haematoma formation, wound dehiscence, or infection will be compared.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical neurological examination in donor arm ERAH versus ORAH</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Clinical examination of subjective cutaneous sensibility will be compared between ERAH versus ORAH groups.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Neurological deficits in ERAH versus ORAH</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Occurence of deficits in following neurological exams will be compared between ERAH and ORAH
Cutaneous sensibility on both forearms and hands by appraisal of dermatomes. All sensibility modalities are examined:
Cutaneous touch sensibility examined by Von Fray hair
Deep pain sensibility examined by algometry.
Sensory nervous conduction velocity examined on both forearms and hands:
N. medianus (dig. II - hdl); orthodromic technique
N. ulnaris (dig. V - hdl); orthodromic technique
N. radialis (antebrachium - tabatiere); antidromic technique
N. cutaneous antebrachium lateralis (elbow - antebrachium); antidromic technique
N. cutaneous antebrachium medialis (elbow - antebrachium); antidromic technique
Motoric nervous conduction velocity examined on both forearms and hands:
N. medianus (hdl - m. abductor policis brevis (APB), elbow - APB)
N. ulnaris (hdl - m. abductor digiti minimi)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Vascular function in the donor arm of the ERAH and ORAH groups compared to non-donor arms.</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>MIBI scan after exercise induced relative ischemia will be compared between donor versus non-donor arms.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Graft patency in ERAH versus ORAH</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>MSCT will be used to evaluate patency.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Graft patency in aortoradial versus mammarioradial grafting</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>MSCT will be used to evaluate patency.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in handgrip strength</measure>
    <time_frame>the day before surgery and 1 year postoperatively.</time_frame>
    <description>Change in handgrip strength will be measured in the conduit donor arm and compared between ERAH versus ORAH.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Change in muscular function in ERAH versus ORAH</measure>
    <time_frame>the day before surgery and 1 year postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Following muscles are rated according to the Oxford Scale for grading muscle strength (see table 7) the day before surgery and at one year postoperatively:
m. abductor pollicis brevis
m. abductor digiti minimi
mm. interosseus palmares
m. flexor digitorum profundus II+V
m. extensor digitorum The change in muscular function will be compared between ERAH versus ORAH.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Serious adverse events in ERAH versus ORAH</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Occurrence of the following serious adverse events at time point one year after surgery: reoperation for bleeding; revascularisation; myocardial infarction; stroke; or death will be compared between ERAH and ORAH.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Scar evaluation in ERAH versus ORAH</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>Using Stony Brooke Scar Evaluation Score the scars will be evaluated and the mean scores compared between ERAH versus ORAH groups.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Neuropathic pain symptoms and signs in ERAH versus ORAH</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months postoperatively</time_frame>
    <description>The Leeds assessment of neuropathic symptoms and signs (LANNS) pain scale will be used after 3 months to compare pain in ERAH versus ORAH groups.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">300</enrollment>
  <condition>Complications Due to Coronary Artery Bypass Graft</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Artery Disease</condition>
  <condition>Myocardial Ischemia</condition>
  <condition>Coronary Disease</condition>
  <condition>Heart Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Cardiovascular Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Arteriosclerosis</condition>
  <condition>Arterial Occlusive Diseases</condition>
  <condition>Vascular Diseases</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Grp 1: ERAH, Mammarioradial (Y-graft)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Endoscopic radial artery harvest Mammarioradial graft (Y-graft) In this group the radial artery is harvested as an endoscopic procedure and positioned on the heart as an composite graft (Y-graft).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Grp 2: ERAH, Aortoradial (Free RA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Endoscopic radial artery harvest Aortooradial (free RA) In this group the radial artery is harvested as an endoscopic procedure and positioned on the heart as an free RA graft.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Grp 3: ORAH, Mammarioradial (Y-graft)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Open radial artery harvest Mammarioradial graft (Y-graft) In this group the radial artery is harvested as an open procedure and positioned on the heart as an composite graft (Y-graft).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Grp 4: ORAH, Aortoradial graft (Free RA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Aortooradial graft (free RA) Open radial artery harvest In this group the radial artery is harvested as an open procedure and positioned on the heart as an free RA graft.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Endoscopic radial artery harvest</intervention_name>
    <description>Radial artery harvest is performed as an endoscopic procedure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Grp 1: ERAH, Mammarioradial (Y-graft)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Grp 2: ERAH, Aortoradial (Free RA)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Open radial artery harvest</intervention_name>
    <description>Radial artery harvest is performed as an open procedure.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Grp 3: ORAH, Mammarioradial (Y-graft)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Grp 4: ORAH, Aortoradial graft (Free RA)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mammarioradial graft (Y-graft)</intervention_name>
    <description>The radial artery is used as an composite graft positioned on the internal mammarian artery.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Grp 1: ERAH, Mammarioradial (Y-graft)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Grp 3: ORAH, Mammarioradial (Y-graft)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aortoradial graft (Free RA)</intervention_name>
    <description>The radial artery is used as an free graft positioned on the aorta.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Grp 2: ERAH, Aortoradial (Free RA)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Grp 4: ORAH, Aortoradial graft (Free RA)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria

          -  Elective/sub acute CABG as an isolated procedure.

          -  Age &gt; 18 years

          -  Multi-vessel disease

          -  Non-dominant arm is eligible for radial artery harvest

          -  Written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Geographically not available for follow up

          -  Modified Allen's test indicating insufficient ulnary artery perfusion

          -  Valve surgery, ablation surgery or any kind of concomitant surgery during same
             admission.

          -  Acute operation (&lt;24 hours from admission)

          -  Dialysis

          -  Preoperative neurological deficit on the donor arm

          -  LVEF &lt; 20% preoperative

          -  Former sternotomy

          -  Contrast allergy

          -  Malignant disease

          -  No written informed consent
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christian L Carranza, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Cardio-Thoracic Surgery, Rigshospitalet, Copenhagen, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Peter Skov Olsen, MD DMSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Cardio-Thoracic Surgery, Rigshospitalet, Copenhagen, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Christian Gluud, MD DMSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Copenhagen Trial Unit, Rigshospitalet, Copenhagen, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Martin Ballegaard, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Clinical Neurophysiology, Rigshospitalet, Copenhagen, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Philip Hasbak, MD PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Clinical Physiology, Nuclear Medicine and PET, Rigshospitalet, Copenhagen, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Andreas Kjær, Prof MD DMSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Clinical Physiology, Nuclear Medicine and PET, Rigshospitalet, Copenhagen, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Klaus F Kofoed, MD DMSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Department of Cardiology and Radiology, Rigshospitalet, Copenhagen, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Mads Werner, MD, DMSc</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Multidisciplinary Pain Centre, Rigshospitalet, Copenhagen, Denmark</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Christian L Carranza, MD</last_name>
    <phone>+4535451488</phone>
    <email>neo-trial@thoraxkir.dk</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Rigshospitalet</name>
      <address>
        <city>Copenhagen</city>
        <zip>2100</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Christian L Carranza, MD</last_name>
      <phone>+4535451488</phone>
      <email>neo-trial@thoraxkir.dk</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Christian L Carranza, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 25, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 5, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 8, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 5, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 5, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 6, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Rigshospitalet, Denmark</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Christian Lildal Carranza</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>MD, Specialist in Cardio-Thoracic Surgery</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ERAH</keyword>
  <keyword>Endoscopic Radial Artery Harvest</keyword>
  <keyword>Y-graft</keyword>
  <keyword>Radial Artery Harvest</keyword>
  <keyword>Total Arterial Revascularisation</keyword>
  <keyword>CABG</keyword>
  <keyword>Radial Artery Conduit</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Cardiovascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Artery Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Coronary Disease</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Heart Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Ischemia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vascular Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arteriosclerosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arterial Occlusive Diseases</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

