<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00485238</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>DSRB A/06/177</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00485238</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ALPI vs Medical Therapy Effects on Optic Nerve Structure &amp; Function</brief_title>
  <acronym>Iridoplasty</acronym>
  <official_title>EFFECTS OF IMMEDIATE ARGON LASER PERIPHERAL IRIDOPLASTY Versus CONVENTIONAL SYSTEMIC MEDICAL THERAPY ON OPTIC NERVE HEAD STRUCTURE AND FUNCTION OF ACUTE PRIMARY ANGLE CLOSURE EYES</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National University Hospital, Singapore</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National University Hospital, Singapore</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The aim is to determine which approach, immediate argon laser peripheral iridoplasty or
      conventional systemic medical treatment efficiently breaks acute angle closure attack without
      consequent visual morbidities. The specific objectives are to see whether sudden intraocular
      pressure(IOP) lowering brought about by laser iridoplasty or medical treatment affects optic
      nerve head structure and function and identify if immediate decompression is associated with
      greater incidence of ocular problems like corneal endothelial compromise, optic disc edema,
      macular edema, decompression retinopathy, cataract formation, progression to chronic angle
      closure.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary Angle Closure Glaucoma (PACG) continues to be a major concern in Asia. It is a major
      cause of visual morbidity in the region1 being the most prevalent type of glaucoma especially
      in Chinese and Mongoloid descent.2,3 During the acute stage of the disease, prompt
      institution of measures to break the attack is necessary. Two recognized approaches are
      utilized in practice in lowering intraocular pressure and preparing for the definitive
      treatment of laser peripheral iridotomy. These are conventional topical and systemic medical
      therapy and immediate peripheral iridoplasty using either argon or diode lasers.

      In the study of Lim, Tan, Chew, Seah et al., laser iridoplasty was noted to have a useful
      role in the management of medically unresponsive acute angle closure, particularly in those
      cases where laser peripheral iridotomy (PI) could not be successfully performed4 . Randomized
      controlled trials of Lam, Lai, Tham et al. comparing immediate laser peripheral iridoplasty
      plus topical medications and topical and systemic medical treatment found no significant
      difference in the eventual mean IOP and requirement for glaucoma medications 5 . However,
      significant difference in efficacy was observed between the two treatment arms within the
      first two hours of treatment with argon laser peripheral iridoplasty and topical medications
      lowering IOP faster than conventional medications6. In all the trials cited, there was no
      mention of sudden IOP lowering effects of either argon laser iridoplasty or conventional
      medications on the optic nerve head and visual field status, as well as its effect on other
      ocular structures like the cornea, lens and retina . In our literature search, two papers
      studied the optic nerve head structure and function in angle closure glaucoma, but not in the
      immediate period of sudden IOP lowering. Ang, Aung, Chua, Yip and Chew made a comparative
      assessment of the visual field loss between symptomatic and asymptomatic PACG, with 50% of
      asymptomatic PACG subjects presenting with end stage visual field loss in contrast to just 7%
      of symptomatic PACG.7 Lai, Tham, Lam et al. compared the retinal nerve fiber layer
      measurements of attack eyes and their fellow eyes after a single unilateral attack of acute
      primary angle closure (APAC) using scanning laser polarimetry six months after the acute
      attack8. Retinal nerve fiber layer damage was documented in eyes where the duration of the
      APAC attack lasted more than 48 hours8. Decompression retinopathy following laser peripheral
      iridoplasty for acute primary angle closure was reported in two cases reported by Lai, Lee,
      Leung and Chung.9 In order to compare the efficiency of laser peripheral iridoplasty and
      medical treatment, as well as to identify any morbidity that may come from sudden
      decompression of the eye, we undertake this randomized controlled trial.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>February 2007</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2008</completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>optic nerve head stereometric analysis HRT3 and Stratus OCT,optic nerve head and RNFL &amp; macula thickness average. AGIS scores of HVF is the measure of functional status.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>amount and rate of IOP-lowering,gonioscopy and ASOCT changes, change in LOCS grading for cataract, corneal decompensation &amp; edema,macular,retinal edema by Stratus OCT.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Glaucoma</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Argon laser Iridoplasty</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intravenous acetazolamide</intervention_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age more than 21 years with ability to give informed consent and cooperate for a slit
             lamp laser procedure

          -  Subjects at their first presentation of acute primary angle closure attack.

          -  Intraocular pressure levels of 40 mm Hg or higher by applanation tonometry or tonopen

          -  Pupillary block as the main mechanism of angle closure

          -  No previous treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age less than 21 years

          -  Angle closure due to non-pupil block mechanism (e.g. plateau iris, pseudoplateau,
             phacomorphic, malignant glaucoma) or other secondary causes (subluxed lens,
             neovascular, uveitic, traumatic, post-operative)

          -  Angle closure patients whose IOP's are not lowered by 20% or more, and are
             unresponsive to maximum medical IOP-lowering agents after one hour of initiating
             treatment and needing other intervention/s to lower IOP(e.g. iridoplasty, surgery).

          -  Corneal opacities or abnormalities obstructing laser application

          -  Use of contact lens

          -  Single-eyed patients
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Paul TK Chew, A/Prof</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National University Hospital, Singapore</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paul TK Chew, A/Prof</last_name>
    <phone>67725317</phone>
    <email>ophchewp@nus.edu.sg</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Maria Cecilia D. Aquino, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>67725317</phone>
    <email>cel_aq@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>5 Lower Kent Ridge Road, Singapore</city>
        <zip>119074</zip>
        <country>Singapore</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Paul TK Chew, A/Prof</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Singapore</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lai JS, Tham CC, Chua JK, Poon AS, Lam DS. Laser peripheral iridoplasty as initial treatment of acute attack of primary angle-closure: a long-term follow-up study. J Glaucoma. 2002 Dec;11(6):484-7.</citation>
    <PMID>12483091</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 11, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 11, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 12, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 13, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 13, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 15, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Paul TK Chew, A/Prof</name_title>
    <organization>National University Hospital, Singapore</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>glaucoma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Glaucoma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acetazolamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

