<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00483730</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AV-007-IM</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00483730</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Actovegin® Versus Placebo in Patients With Diabetic Polyneuropathy (AV-007-IM)</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Multi-centre, Double-blind, Placebo-controlled, Randomised, Parallel Group Clinical Trial to Evaluate Efficacy and Safety of Actovegin® in Diabetic Type 2 Patients With Symptomatic Diabetic Peripheral Polyneuropathy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Nycomed</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Nycomed</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To assess clinical efficacy and safety of Actovegin in type 2 diabetic patients with
      symptomatic diabetic peripheral polyneuropathy after 250 ml i.v. infusions once daily for 20
      days followed by oral treatment 600 mg × 3 daily for 140 days.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2006</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>TSSaverage: Average of the TSS over the treatment period (AUC / exposure time) VPTaverage: Average of the VPT measurement over the treatment period (AUC / exposure time)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approx. 5½ months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>NIS-LLaverage: Average of the NIS-LL over the treatment period (AUC / exposure time)</measure>
    <time_frame>Approx. 5½ months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">569</enrollment>
  <condition>Symptomatic Diabetic Peripheral Polyneuropathy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Deproteinised hemoderivative of calf blood (Actovegin)</intervention_name>
    <description>Symptomatic diabetic peripheral polyneuropathy</description>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        The medical condition / disease to be studied is symptomatic diabetic peripheral
        polyneuropathy.

        All inclusion criteria must be answered &quot;yes&quot; for a patient to participate in the trial.

          1. Has the patient given informed consent according to local requirements before any
             trial related activities? A trial related activity is any procedure that would not
             have been performed during the routine management of the patient.

          2. Is the patient aged ≥ 18 to ≤ 65 years?

          3. Does the patient suffer from type 2 diabetes mellitus?

          4. Has the patient evidence of symptomatic diabetic peripheral polyneuropathy, i.e. TSS ≥
             6 and NIS-LL ≥ 2?

          5. Is the patient's VPT measured to ≤ 30V?

          6. Has the patient adequate circulation to the foot as evidenced by a palpable pulse on
             posterior tibialis artery and dorsal artery of foot?

          7. Is the HbA1C level less than 10%?

          8. Is the patient able to make frequent clinic visits over the trial period?

             For patients receiving tricyclic antidepressants, anticonvulsants, mexiletine or
             neuroleptics as treatment of neuropathic pain:

          9. Has the regimen been stable within the last month?

             For female patients of childbearing potential (childbearing potential is considered
             until menopause has lasted more than 12 months):

         10. Does the patient use an acceptable contraceptive method (hormonal pills, patches,
             implants, injections or intrauterine device)?

         11. Is the pregnancy test negative before the 1st dose of trial medication?

        (Surgically hysterectomised and surgically successfully sterilized females may be included
        on the same conditions as male patients).

        Exclusion Criteria:

        All exclusion criteria must be answered &quot;no&quot; for a patient to participate in the trial.

          1. Does the patient suffer from known allergy towards Actovegin or similar preparations?

          2. Has the patient asymmetrical neuropathy of the trunk or proximal lower limbs?

          3. Does the patient suffer from diabetic foot ulceration or infections?

          4. Does the patient suffer from diabetic amyotrophy?

          5. Does the patient suffer from decompensated cardiac insufficiency, pulmonary oedema,
             oliguria, anuria, generalised oedema?

          6. Does the patient suffer from polyneuropathy due to other underlying causes?

          7. Has the patient been hospitalised due to diabetic polyneuropathy within the last
             month?

          8. Has the patient participated in any other trial with an Investigational Medicinal
             Product (IMP) or device within 30 days before inclusion in this trial?

          9. Has the patient ever used medications that may be etiological factors for neuropathy,
             such as isoniazid, nitrofurantoin, vincristine and phenytoin?

         10. Has the patient used cerebrolysin or α-lipoic acid or received Transcutaneous Electric
             Nerve Stimulation (TENS) or acupuncture within the last month?

         11. Has the patient received opiates as treatment of his / her diabetic polyneuropathy
             within the last month?

         12. Does the patient suffer from any malignancy?

         13. Is the patient nursing?

         14. Does the patient suffer from any mental, psychiatric or other conditions that may
             compromise data collection and understanding of written and verbal information given
             in the trial?

         15. Does the patient suffer from present and / or previous chronic alcohol abuse?

         16. Is there any anamnestic evidence of hypothyroidism?

         17. Is there any anamnestic evidence of vitamin B12 deficiency?

         18. Does the patient suffer from an impaired renal function with high blood urea nitrogen
             (BUN) and / or increased serum creatinine (&gt;120 µmol/L)?
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nycomced Clinical Trial Operations</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Headquaters</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Nycomed</name>
      <address>
        <city>Roskilde</city>
        <zip>4000</zip>
        <country>Denmark</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Denmark</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>June 6, 2007</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>June 6, 2007</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">June 7, 2007</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 7, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Nycomed</name_title>
    <organization>Nycomed</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Polyneuropathies</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Actovegin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

