<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01932983</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>S12-01499</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01932983</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Clinical Application of &quot;Train of Four&quot; Testing in the Intraoperative Monitoring Setting</brief_title>
  <official_title>Clinical Application of Train of Four Testing in the Intraoperative Monitoring Setting</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University School of Medicine</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study examines the clinical application of TOF (train of four test) used by
      anesthesiologists and neurophysiologists during instrumented spine procedures, as well as
      certain associated parameters. 'Train of four' test is a test routinely used during the
      surgery, which is performed by stimulation of peripheral nerve with purpose to determine the
      degree of muscle relaxation by interpretation of muscle response. During spine surgery, it is
      helpful for the surgeon to have a patient's muscles as relaxed as possible with the least
      amount of tone, especially when exposing. Anesthesiologists achieve this level of relaxation
      by giving a neuromuscular blocking agent. If medication given to do this has not fully left
      their system by the time the surgeon needs to start putting in the screws and rods, then the
      intraoperative monitoring can not be adequately performed. If the muscles are too relaxed,
      then free run EMG and screw stimulation, two monitoring methods used, will not be analyzed
      correctly and the surgery may be adversely affected. This study compares the results of the
      'train of four' test performed by neurophysiologists and anesthesiologists. Additionally, it
      looks at the differences, if any, in comparing stimulation of the foot nerve (tibial n.) or
      hand nerve (ulnar n.) Performing the TOF (train of four test) in the lower extremity can be
      relevant for many reasons. Train of four tests can show the presence of four twitches in the
      arms but the legs may not fully recovered from muscle relaxant given by anesthesia. Also,
      train of four test which uses subjective method of interpretation by anesthesiologists may
      present different results compared than objective quantitative method of train of four test
      interpretation. Ultimately, the goal of this study is to show the importance of 'TOF' testing
      in ensuring that any identifiable preventable intraoperative surgical complication is
      appropriately identified.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      TOF test was performed by two routinely used devices, peripheral nerve stimulator and
      intraoperative neurophysiologic monitoring device. TOF monitoring of upper extremity included
      stimulation of ulnar nerve. Negative surface electrode was placed on the wrist in line with
      the smallest digit 1-2cm below skin crease and the positive 2-3cm proximal to the negative
      electrode. Active surface recording electrodes were placed on adductor pollicis muscle. TOF
      monitoring of lower extremity included stimulation of peripheral nerve, posterior tibial
      nerve. Surface stimulating electrodes were placed, negative over inferolateral aspect of
      medial malleolus, and positive electrode 2-3cm proximal to the negative electrode.
      Stimulation current was 20-30 mA for hand and 30-60mA foot TOF by a group of 0.2 millisecond
      pulses, spaced 500 millisecond apart, to deliver four contractions. Surface recording
      electrodes were used for measuring muscle response on foot, active electrode which was
      located on the Flexor hallucis brevis muscle and reference on the big toe. Intraoperative
      monitoring device was used, and software with TOF monitoring programe was installed. EMG
      response was calculated by the peak of amplitude (peak to peak amplitude) presented in
      quantitative value of online measurement. Interpretation was different, visual and
      subjective. Peripheral nerve stimulator was used for subjective TOF test. Output current was
      adjustable from 0 to 70 mA. Repeat stimulation of 4 pulses/0.2 milliseconds repeated every
      500 milliseconds. Surface negative electrodes were placed over the course of ulnar nerve on
      the wrist, in line with the smallest digit, 1-2cm proximal from skin crease, and positive
      electrode 2-3 cm proximal. Response was followed on adductor pollicis muscle. All data were
      kept in electronic medical records and if data are not complete subjects were not included in
      the study. Results were compared between TOF methods on two different body sites, upper and
      lower extremity, by quantitative method and other comparison was made between subjective and
      quantitative method with TOF test located in both methods on the upper extremity.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational [Patient Registry]</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case Control</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <target_duration>1 Day</target_duration>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Muscle contraction - TOF twitch after peripheral nerve stimulation</measure>
    <time_frame>During spine lumbar surgery after pedicle screw placement</time_frame>
    <description>TOF test is performed after pedicle screw placement during lumbar spine surgery, prior neurophysiological pedicle screw position test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">150</enrollment>
  <condition>Neuromuscular Blockade</condition>
  <condition>Muscle Relaxation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TOF test</arm_group_label>
    <description>TOF - train of four test performed on patiens undergoing lumbar spine surgery where introperative neurophysiologic monitoring is applied. Stimulation of peripheral nerve - ulnar nerve resulting with muscle contractions and evaluation of responses by anesthesiologist and neurophysiologists. Stimulation with group of 0.2 millisecond pulses, spaced 500 millisecond apart, at a 2 Hz rate, current 20-60 mA to deliver four muscle contractions. Eligibility criteria included patients for study where subjective visual interpretation and quantitative interpretation of Adductor pollicis muscle responses is followed.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Train of four test</intervention_name>
    <description>TOF test includes stimulation of peripheral nerve of upper extremity, ulnar nerve in this study. Two methods of interpretation are included, visual which uses anesthesiologist TOF device, and quantitative uses intraoperative neurophysiologic monitoring device, both devices are in routine clinical practice use. Different interpretation of muscle contractions are followed, by quantitative method and visual method. Visual evaluates number of twitches and determines the degree of neuromuclular block and percent of blocked acetylcholine receptors. Quantitative method record muscle contraction by using EMG, presents each twitch as amplitude, caluculate peak to peak value, and provide numerical value and difference for each twitch.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TOF test</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects undergoing instrumented orthopedic surgical procedure which requires the use of
        neurophysiologic intraoperative monitoring modalities.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        Subject undergoing spine fusion surgery when intraoperative neurophysiologic monitoring is
        included.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        Subjects with history of previous nerve injury or peripheral neuropathies when
        intraoperative neurophysiologic monitoring was precluded. Possible technical issues during
        surgery prior TOF test such as incorrect electrode placement, lead wire attachment, TOF
        device error or impossibility to correct it in acceptable time when TOF test can not be
        performed.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>85 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Aleksandar Beric, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NYU Langone Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NYU Langone Medical Center, Hospital for Joint Diseases</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://clinicaltrials.gov</url>
    <description>Clinical trial of application of train of four testing in the intraoperative monitoring setting</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Gavrancic B, Lolis A, Beric A. Train-of-four test in intraoperative neurophysiologic monitoring: differences between hand and foot train-of-four. J Clin Neurophysiol. 2014 Dec;31(6):575-9. doi: 10.1097/WNP.0000000000000111.</citation>
    <PMID>25462145</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 26, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 27, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 30, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 26, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 26, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 27, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Neuromuscular blockade</keyword>
  <keyword>TOF test</keyword>
  <keyword>Quantitative TOF method</keyword>
  <keyword>Visual interpretation of TOF</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

