<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01932697</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>MC1273</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2013-01652</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>MC1273</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>P30CA015083</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01932697</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Radiation Therapy and Docetaxel in Treating Patients With HPV-Related Oropharyngeal Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Evaluation of Adjuvant Hyperfractionated Radiation and Docetaxel for HPV Associated Oropharynx Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This phase II trial studies how well radiation therapy and docetaxel work in treating
      patients with human papillomavirus (HPV)-related oropharyngeal cancer. Radiation therapy uses
      high-energy x-rays to kill tumor cells. Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as docetaxel, work
      in different ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells, by stopping
      them from dividing, or by stopping them from spreading. Giving radiation therapy with
      docetaxel my kill more tumor cells.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PRIMARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To assess the cumulative incidence of local/regional failure at 2 years after study
      registration.

      SECONDARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To characterize the rate of acute grade 3 or higher functional mucosal adverse events (up
      to 1 month post-radiation therapy [XRT]) associated with adjuvant docetaxel +
      hyperfractionated radiotherapy (key secondary endpoint).

      II. To assess changes in overall survival, disease-free survival, distant failure rates, and
      quality of life (QOL) associated with adjuvant docetaxel and hyperfractionated radiation.

      III. To characterize other acute adverse events (up to 1 month post-XRT) and late grade 3 or
      higher non-hematologic adverse events (up to 2 years post-XRT) associated with adjuvant
      docetaxel + hyperfractionated radiotherapy.

      TERTIARY OBJECTIVES:

      I. To determine the genetic alterations of oropharynx tumor specimens and the detection rate
      of corresponding cell-free deoxyribonucleic acid (cfDNA) in the pre-surgical, post-surgical,
      and post-radiation blood of oropharynx cancer patients.

      OUTLINE:

      Patients receive docetaxel intravenously (IV) over 1 hour on days 1 and 8 and undergo
      hyperfractionated intensity-modulated radiation therapy (IMRT) twice daily (BID) 5 days a
      week on days 1-12 for a total of 20 fractions.

      After completion of study treatment, patients are followed up at 14 days, 1 month, every 3
      months for 2 years, every 6 months for 1 year and then annually for 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">September 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Cumulative incidence of local/regional failure</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The 2-year cumulative incidence of local/regional failure will be estimated by the competing risk method, where the competing risks are distant failures and deaths from other causes (i.e. deaths from distant failure or non-oropharynx cancer).</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in QOL measured using the Xerostomia- Related Quality of Life Scale (XeQOLS) form, European Quality of Life (EuroQol) 5D (Eq-5D), Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy Head and Neck (FACT H&amp; N) (version 4), and Dermatology Life Quality Index</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 24 months post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>QOL scores will be explored descriptively. In addition, differences between post-baseline and baseline QOL scores will be analyzed using a paired-sample t-test or the nonparametric equivalent to see if the QOL tends to improve over time with treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in swallowing studies</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to up to 12 months post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Swallowing will be scored (yes, no) for aspiration, penetration, velopharyngeal incompetence, epiglottic inversion, tongue base retraction, and pharyngeal swallow response using the metric outlined by Eisbruch et al. The swallowing questions will be explored descriptively to detect patterns and substantial changes over time. In addition, McNemar's test for paired samples will be used to see if the swallowing questions significantly change over time for each post-baseline time point.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival (DFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From registration to the first of either disease recurrence or death, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The distribution of DFS will be estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distant failure rates</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years</time_frame>
    <description>The 2-year cumulative incidence of distant failure will be estimated by the competing risk method, where the competing risks are local/regional failures and deaths from other causes (i.e. deaths from local/regional failure or non-oropharynx cancer).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of acute adverse events graded according to NCI CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 month post-XRT</time_frame>
    <description>The maximum grade for each type of acute adverse event will be recorded for each patient, and frequency tables will be reviewed to determine patterns, especially focusing on grade 3+ adverse events, regardless of attribution to the study treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of acute grade 3 or higher functional mucosal adverse events graded according to the National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 1 month post-hyperfractionated radiation therapy</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of late adverse events graded according to NCI CTCAE version 4.0</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 2 years post-treatment</time_frame>
    <description>The maximum grade for each type of adverse event will be recorded for each patient for up to 2 years post-treatment, and frequency tables will be reviewed to determine patterns, especially focusing on grade 3+ non-hematologic adverse events, regardless of attribution to the study treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>From registration to death due to any cause, assessed up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The distribution of OS will be estimated using the method of Kaplan-Meier.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in transforming growth factor (TGF)-beta1 levels</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline to 1 week post-radiation</time_frame>
    <description>These markers will be correlated with clinical endpoints like acute adverse events, cumulative incidence rates of local/regional failure, overall survival, and disease-free survival.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>E6/E7 messenger ribonucleic acid (mRNA) of HPV16, assessed on a chromogenic RNA in situ hybridization (ISH) assay called RNAscope</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>These markers will be correlated with clinical endpoints like acute adverse events, cumulative incidence rates of local/regional failure, overall survival, and disease-free survival.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">81</enrollment>
  <condition>Human Papillomavirus Infection</condition>
  <condition>Stage I Oropharyngeal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage II Oropharyngeal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage III Oropharyngeal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVA Oropharyngeal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <condition>Stage IVB Oropharyngeal Squamous Cell Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (docetaxel, hyperfractionated IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive docetaxel IV over 1 hour on days 1 and 8 and undergo hyperfractionated IMRT BID 5 days a week on days 1-12 for a total of 20 fractions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Docetaxel</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (docetaxel, hyperfractionated IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Docecad</other_name>
    <other_name>RP56976</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxotere</other_name>
    <other_name>Taxotere Injection Concentrate</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Hyperfractionation</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo hyperfractionated IMRT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (docetaxel, hyperfractionated IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Hyperfractionated Radiation</other_name>
    <other_name>Hyperfractionated Radiation Therapy</other_name>
    <other_name>superfractionated radiation therapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Radiation</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Intensity-Modulated Radiation Therapy</intervention_name>
    <description>Undergo hyperfractionated IMRT</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (docetaxel, hyperfractionated IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>IMRT</other_name>
    <other_name>Intensity Modulated RT</other_name>
    <other_name>Intensity-Modulated Radiotherapy</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laboratory Biomarker Analysis</intervention_name>
    <description>Correlative studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (docetaxel, hyperfractionated IMRT)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Quality-of-Life Assessment</intervention_name>
    <description>Ancillary studies</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treatment (docetaxel, hyperfractionated IMRT)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Quality of Life Assessment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  PRE-REGISTRATION

          -  Provide written informed consent

          -  Submission of research blood draw to be stored until after surgical resection of the
             primary tumor and confirmation of human papilloma virus (HPV) positivity (Mayo Clinic
             Rochester patients only)

          -  Patients with oropharynx carcinoma with a smoking history of ˂ 10 pack-year or
             equivalent 10 year history of tobacco product use and no recent history (within last 5
             years) of tobacco use

          -  REGISTRATION

          -  Histological confirmation of HPV+ squamous cell carcinoma of the oropharynx; HPV
             positivity will be defined as positive staining for p16 on immunohistochemistry (IHC)

          -  Gross total surgical resection with curative intent of the primary tumor and at least
             unilateral neck dissection within 7 weeks of registration

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status (PS) 0 or 1

          -  Smoking history &lt; 10 pack years or equivalent 10 year history of tobacco product use

          -  Absence of distant metastases on standard diagnostic work-up =&lt; 10 weeks prior to
             registration; (chest computed tomography [CT], chest x-ray [CXR], positron emission
             tomography [PET]/CT, etc.)

          -  Must have one of the following risk factors:

               -  Lymph node &gt; 3 cm

               -  2 or more positive lymph nodes

               -  Perineural invasion

               -  Lymphovascular space invasion

               -  T3 or microscopic T4a primary disease

               -  Lymph node extracapsular extension

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1500/mm^3

          -  Platelet count &gt;= 100,000/mm^3

          -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9.0 g/dL

          -  Direct bilirubin within upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Creatinine =&lt; ULN x 1.5

          -  Negative pregnancy test done =&lt; 7 days prior to registration, for women of
             childbearing potential only

          -  Ability to complete questionnaire(s) by themselves or with assistance

          -  Provide informed written consent

          -  Willingness to return to enrolling institution for follow-up (during the active
             monitoring phase of the study)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Any significant tobacco history within the past five years

          -  Any of the following:

               -  Pregnant women

               -  Nursing women

               -  Men or women of childbearing potential who are unwilling to employ adequate
                  contraception

          -  Co-morbid systemic illnesses or other severe concurrent disease which, in the judgment
             of the investigator, would make the patient inappropriate for entry into this study or
             interfere significantly with the proper assessment of safety and toxicity of the
             prescribed regimens

          -  Immunocompromised patients and patients known to be human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)
             positive

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements

          -  Receiving any other investigational agent which would be considered as a treatment for
             the primary neoplasm

          -  Other active malignancy =&lt; 5 years prior to registration; EXCEPTIONS: non-melanotic
             skin cancer or carcinoma-in-situ of the cervix; NOTE: if there is a history or prior
             malignancy, they must not be receiving other specific treatment for their cancer

          -  History of myocardial infarction =&lt; 180 days prior to registration, or congestive
             heart failure requiring use of ongoing maintenance therapy for life-threatening
             ventricular arrhythmias

          -  Prior history of radiation therapy to the affected site

          -  History of connective tissue disorders such as rheumatoid arthritis, lupus, or
             Sjogren's disease

          -  Presence of any of the following risk factors after surgery:

               -  Any positive surgical margin

               -  Adenopathy below the clavicles

          -  Prior systemic chemotherapy for the study cancer; NOTE: prior chemotherapy for a
             different cancer is allowable

          -  History of allergic reaction to docetaxel

          -  Receiving any medications or substances that are strong or moderate inhibitors of
             cytochrome P450, family 3, subfamily A, polypeptide 4 (CYP3A4)

               -  Use of strong or moderate inhibitors is prohibited =&lt; 7 days prior to
                  registration

          -  Receiving any medications or substances that are inducers of CYP3A4

               -  Use of inducers is prohibited =&lt; 12 days prior to registration
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Daniel Ma</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic in Arizona</name>
      <address>
        <city>Scottsdale</city>
        <state>Arizona</state>
        <zip>85259</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>August 27, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>August 27, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">August 30, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 17, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Squamous Cell</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Papillomavirus Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Docetaxel</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

