<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01936012</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>BE.258/EQL/2012</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01936012</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Bioequivalence Study of Two Formulations of 10 mg Lisinopril Tablet Under Fasting Condition</brief_title>
  <official_title>Bioequivalence Study of 10 mg Lisinopril Tablets (Lisinopril 10 mg) Produced by PT Dexa Medica in Comparison With The Innovator Tablets (Zestril速 10 mg, PT Boehringer Ingelheim Indonesia, Indonesia, Under License From Astra Zeneca UK Ltd.)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Dexa Medica Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Dexa Medica Group</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The present study was conducted to find out whether the bioavailability of 10 mg lisinopril
      tablets produced by PT Dexa Medica was equivalent to the tablets produced by the innovator
      (Zestril速 10 mg, PT Boehringer Ingelheim Indonesia, Indonesia, under license from Astra
      Zeneca UK Ltd.)
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This was a randomized, single-blind, two-period, two-sequence, cross-over study under fasting
      condition. The participating subjects were required to have an overnight fast and in the next
      morning were given orally one tablet of the test drug (Lisinopril 10 mg, produced by PT Dexa
      Medica) or one tablet of the reference drug (Zestril速 10 mg, PT Boehringer Ingelheim
      Indonesia, Indonesia, under license from Astra Zeneca UK Ltd.).

      Blood samples were drawn immediately before taking the drug (control), and at 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
      6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 12, 16, 24, 36, and 48 hours after drug administration. Seven days after the
      first drug administration (washout period), the procedure was repeated using the alternate
      drug.

      The pharmacokinetic parameters, including AUCt, AUCinf, Cmax, t max, and t1/2, were
      determined from plasma concentrations of lisinopril, using liquid chromatography with tandem
      mass spectrometry detection (LC-MS/MS) method.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to the last observed quantifiable concentration (AUCt) of lisinopril</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Relative bioavailability (primarily measured by AUCt and AUCinf) between two lisinopril 10 mg tablet formulations (test and reference formulations) was assessed under fasting condition. AUCt was determined from plasma concentration of lisinopril.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time zero to infinity (AUCinf) of lisinopril</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Relative bioavailability (primarily measured by AUCt and AUCinf) between two lisinopril 10 mg tablet formulations (test and reference formulations) was assessed under fasting condition. AUCinf was determined from plasma concentration of lisinopril.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The peak plasma concentration (Cmax) of lisinopril</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Relative bioavailability (secondarily measured by Cmax) between two lisinopril 10 mg tablet formulations (test and reference formulations) was assessed under fasting condition. Cmax was determined from plasma concentration of lisinopril.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time needed to achieve the peak plasma concentration (t max) of lisinopril</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Relative bioavailability (secondarily measured by t max) between two lisinopril 10 mg tablet formulations (test and reference formulations) was assessed under fasting condition. t max was determined from plasma concentration of lisinopril.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The elimination half-life (t1/2) of lisinopril</measure>
    <time_frame>48 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Relative bioavailability (secondarily measured by t1/2) between two lisinopril 10 mg tablet formulations (test and reference formulations) was assessed under fasting condition. t1/2 was determined from plasma concentration of lisinopril.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">34</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lisinopril 10 mg tablets of PT Dexa Medica</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each tablet contains 10.89 mg lisinopril dihydrate that equal to 10 mg lisinopril. A single dose of lisinopril tablet of PT Dexa Medica was given to each of study subjects.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Lisinopril 10 mg tablets of PT Boehringer Ingelheim Indonesia</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Each tablet contains 10.89 mg lisinopril dihydrate that equal to 10 mg lisinopril. A single dose of lisinopril tablet of PT Boehringer Ingelheim Indonesia was given to each of study subjects.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lisinopril 10 mg tablets of PT Dexa Medica</intervention_name>
    <description>Each tablet contains 10.89 mg of lisinopril dihydrate that equal to 10 mg lisinopril. Test product was given as a single dose, under the procedure as described in the Section: Detailed description of the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lisinopril 10 mg tablets of PT Dexa Medica</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Test Product: Lisinopril 10 mg tablets of PT Dexa Medica</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Lisinopril 10 mg tablets of PT Boehringer Ingelheim Indonesia</intervention_name>
    <description>Each tablet contains 10.89 mg of lisinopril dihydrate that equal to 10 mg lisinopril. Reference product was given as a single dose, under the procedure as described in the Section: Detailed description of the study.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Lisinopril 10 mg tablets of PT Boehringer Ingelheim Indonesia</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Reference product: Zestril速 10 mg, produced by PT Boehringer Ingelheim Indonesia, under license from Astra Zeneca UK Ltd..</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy male and female subjects.

          -  Aged 18 - 55 years inclusive.

          -  Non-smokers or moderate smokers (less than 10 cigarettes per day).

          -  Able to participate, communicate well with the investigators and willing to provide
             written informed consent to participate in the study.

          -  Body mass index within 18 to 25 kg/m2.

          -  Vital signs (after 10 minutes rest) were within the following ranges:

               -  systolic blood pressure 110 - 120 mmHg

               -  diastolic blood pressure 70 - 80 mmHg

               -  pulse rate 60 - 90 bpm

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Personal/family history of allergy or hypersensitivity or contraindication to
             lisinopril or allied drugs.

          -  Pregnant or lactating women.

          -  Any major illness or clinically significant ongoing chronic medical illness in the
             past 90 days.

          -  Any clinically significant abnormality of liver function test (ALT, AP, total
             bilirubin &gt;= 1.5 ULN).

          -  Any clinically significant abnormality of renal function test (serum creatinine
             concentration &gt; 1.4 mg/dL).

          -  Positive hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg), anti-HCV, or anti-HIV.

          -  Clinically significant hematology abnormalities.

          -  Clinically significant electrocardiogram (ECG) abnormalities.

          -  Any surgical or medical condition which might significantly alter the absorption,
             distribution, metabolism, or excretion of the study drug.

          -  Past history of anaphylaxis or angioedema.

          -  History of drug or alcohol abuse within 12 months prior to screening.

          -  Participation in any clinical trial within the past 90 days.

          -  History of any bleeding or coagulative disorders.

          -  History of difficulty with donating blood or accessibility of veins in left or right
             arm.

          -  A donation or loss of 500 mL (or more) of blood within 3 months before the study's
             first dosing day.

          -  Intake of any prescription or non-prescription drugs, food supplements, or herbal
             medicines within 14 days of the study's first dosing day.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>PT Equilab International</name>
      <address>
        <city>Jakarta</city>
        <zip>12430</zip>
        <country>Indonesia</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Indonesia</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>September 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 1, 2013</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 1, 2013</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 5, 2013</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>September 1, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>September 1, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">September 5, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Lisinopril</keyword>
  <keyword>Bioequivalence</keyword>
  <keyword>Bioavailability</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetic</keyword>
  <keyword>Angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibitor</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lisinopril</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Angiotensin-Converting Enzyme Inhibitors</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

