<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01098760</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>14898</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>HATT</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01098760</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Hepatocellular Carcinoma - Advanced Stage - Sorafenib Trial in Taiwanese Patients</brief_title>
  <acronym>HATT</acronym>
  <official_title>A Phase IV, Single-arm, Open-label Study of Sorafenib (Nexavar®) in Advanced Hepatocellular Carcinoma (HCC)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Bayer</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Bayer</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-arm, open-label and post-authorization study to evaluate the safety and
      efficacy profile of sorafenib and to evaluate Child-Pugh status progression in subjects with
      advanced HCC treated with sorafenib in Taiwan.

      In a subgroup of patients (hand-foot skin reaction (HFSR) study subgroup), this study also
      aims to test if topical corticosteroids as preventive counter-measure applied to hands and
      feet for the first 3 weeks during sorafenib treatment reduce incidence and severity of HFSR
      compared to a matching, corticosteroid-free cosmetic ointment, measured over the first 3 and
      6 weeks of sorafenib treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to progression</measure>
    <time_frame>30 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>30 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>30 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse event and serious adverse event (SAE) profiles</measure>
    <time_frame>30 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Child-Pugh status progression</measure>
    <time_frame>30 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Plasma Sorafenib exposure (AUC0-12)</measure>
    <time_frame>30 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>For subjects randomized into HFSR study subgroup: overall HFSR incidence in the first 3 weeks of Sorafenib treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>For HFSR study subgroup: a mean HFSR grade determined at the end of the first 3 weeks of sorafenib treatment.</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">151</enrollment>
  <condition>Hepatocellular Carcinoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sorafenib (Nexavar, BAY43-9006) Sorafenib (Nexavar, BAY43-9006) + Nerison Fatty Ointment Sorafenib (Nexavar, BAY43-9006)+Neribas Fatty Ointment</intervention_name>
    <description>Orally taken Sorafenib tablets of 400mg (2x200mg) twice daily (bid) in a continuous schedule. - For patients in Nerisone subgroup: additionally prophylactic use of Nerisone Fatty Ointment (1 g of Nerisone contains 1 mg (0.1%) diflucortolone valerate) cream for hands and feet, twice daily for 3 weeks - For patients in Neribas subgroup: additionally prophylactic use of Neribas Fatty Ointment (non-corticosteroid containing) cream for hands and feet, twice daily for 3 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm 1</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically or cytologically documented HCC (documentation of original biopsy for
             diagnosis is acceptable if tumor tissue is unavailable) or clinical diagnosis by
             American Association for the Study of Liver Disease (AASLD) criteria in cirrhotic
             patients is required. For subjects without cirrhosis, histological or cytological
             confirmation is mandatory.

          -  Unresectable advanced/or metastatic HCC not amenable to local treatment modalities

          -  Patients must have at least one tumor lesion that meets both of the following
             criteria:

               1. The lesion can be accurately measured in at least one dimension according to
                  RECIST amendment (version 1.0)

               2. The lesion has not been previously treated with local therapy (such as surgery,
                  radiation therapy, hepatic arterial therapy, chemoembolization, radiofrequency
                  ablation, percutaneous ethanol injection, or cryoablation).

          -  Patients who have received local therapy such as surgery, radiation therapy, hepatic
             arterial embolization, chemoembolization, radiofrequency ablation, percutaneous
             ethanol injection, or cryoablation are eligible. Previously treated lesions will not
             be selected as target lesions. Local therapy must be completed at least 4 weeks prior
             to the baseline scan.

          -  Cirrhotic status of Child-Pugh Class A. Child-Pugh status should be calculated based
             on clinical findings and laboratory results during the screening period.

          -  Male or female patients &gt;/= 18 years of age

          -  Patients who have a life expectancy of at least 12 weeks

          -  Patients who have an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance score (PS)
             of 0,1 or 2

          -  Resolution of all acute toxic effects of any prior local treatment to National Cancer
             Institute (NCI) Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE), version 4.0
             grade &lt;/= 1

          -  The following laboratory parameters:

               1. Platelet count &gt;/= 60 x 10^9/L

               2. Hemoglobin &gt;/= 8.5 g/dL

               3. Total bilirubin &lt;/= 2.8 mg/dL

               4. Alanine transaminase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) &lt;/= 5 x upper
                  limit of normal

               5. Serum creatinine &lt;/= 1.5 x the upper limit of normal

               6. Prothrombin time-international normalized ratio (INR) &lt;/=2.3 or PT &lt;/= 6 seconds
                  above control.

          -  Patients who are being therapeutically anticoagulated with an agent such as warfarin
             or heparin will be allowed to participate provided that no prior evidence of
             underlying abnormality in these parameters exists. Close monitoring of at least weekly
             evaluations will be performed until INR is stable based on a measurement at pre dose,
             as defined by the local standard of care.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Previous or concurrent cancer that is distinct in primary site or histology from HCC,
             except cervical carcinoma in situ, treated basal cell carcinoma, or superficial
             bladder tumors (Ta, Tis &amp;T1). Any cancer curatively treated &gt; 3 years prior to entry
             is permitted.

          -  Renal failure requiring hemo- or peritoneal dialysis.

          -  History of cardiac disease:

          -  Congestive heart failure &gt; New York Heart Association (NYHA) class 2

          -  Active coronary artery disease (myocardial infarction more than 6 months prior to
             study entry is permitted)

          -  Cardiac arrhythmias requiring anti-arrhythmic therapy other than β-blockers or
             digoxin)

          -  Uncontrolled hypertension, defined as systolic blood pressure &gt; 150 mmHg or diastolic
             blood pressure &gt; 90 mmHg despite optimal medical management.

          -  Active, clinically serious infections (&gt; grade 2 NCI-CTCAE, version 4.0), except
             HBV/HCV infections

          -  Known history of human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection or acquired
             immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS)-related illness or serious acute or chronic illness

          -  Known central nervous system tumors, including metastatic brain disease

          -  Patients with clinically significant gastrointestinal bleeding within 30 days prior to
             study entry

          -  History of organ allograft

          -  Child-Pugh Class B or C

          -  Previous treatment with yttrium-90 spheres

          -  Clinically significant (ie, symptomatic) peripheral vascular disease

          -  Substance abuse or medical, psychological, or social conditions that may interfere
             with the patient's participation in the study or evaluation of the study results

          -  Known or suspected allergy to the investigational agents or any agent given in
             association with this trial

          -  Patients unable to take oral medication, requiring intravenous alimentation, who have
             malabsorption syndrome or any other conditions affecting gastrointestinal absorption,
             or who have active peptic ulcer disease

          -  Any condition that is unstable or which could jeopardize the safety of the patient and
             his/her compliance in the study

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding patients. Women of childbearing potential must have a
             negative urine pregnancy test performed within 7 days prior to the start of study drug
             (assessed locally). Both men and women enrolled in this trial must use adequate
             barrier birth control measures during the course of the trial.

          -  Uncontrolled ascites (defined as not easily controlled with diuretic treatment)

          -  Patients with viral diseases (eg, varicella, herpes zoster); tuberculous or syphilitic
             processes in the areas to be treated; and hypersensitivity to the active substances or
             to any of the excipients will not be included into the HFSR study subgroup.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bayer Study Director</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Bayer</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Chia Yi</city>
        <zip>613</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Hualien county</city>
        <zip>970</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kaohsiung City</city>
        <zip>807</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Kaohsiung City</city>
        <zip>8330</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Taichung City</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei City,</city>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <address>
        <city>Taoyuan</city>
        <zip>33305</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.fda.gov/cder/drug/DrugSafety/DrugIndex.htm</url>
    <description>Click here and search for drug information provided by the FDA.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.fda.gov/medwatch/safety.htm</url>
    <description>Click here and search for information on any recalls, market or product safety alerts by the FDA which might have occurred with this product.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>October 2013</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 1, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 2, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 5, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 30, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 30, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 31, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Sorafenib</keyword>
  <keyword>Hepatocellular Carcinoma (HCC)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Hepatocellular</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Sorafenib</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Niacinamide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

