<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01096641</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FICS 20084002</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01096641</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>An Explorative Study on Physiological and Neurophysiological Determinants of Fatigue in Cancer Survivors</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Explorative Study on Physiological and Neurophysiological Determinants of Fatigue in Cancer Survivors</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Radboud University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Radboud University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Postcancer fatigue is a severe and invalidating problem, impairing quality of life. About 20
      to 40% of the patients remain fatigued, at least one year after successful cancer treatment.
      Fortunately, there is an effective treatment for postcancer fatigue; cognitive behavior
      therapy. However, no cause for postcancer fatigue has been identified yet. The aim of the
      study is to identify factors that (partly) cause postcancer fatigue to improve the
      theoretical understanding of fatigue and to improve the diagnostics of fatigue, predict
      therapy outcome, and facilitate other treatment options.

      In this study, disease-free fatigued cancer patients, who finished treatment for cancer at
      least one year and maximally ten years ago, will be approached for this study. They will be
      compared to non-fatigued patients.

      First, a baseline assessment will take place. Magnetic resonance imaging of the brains will
      be performed to assess brain volume and magnetic resonance spectroscopy will be performed to
      measure the concentrations of specific substances in the brains. Changes in the volume of
      parts of the brains have been observed in (non-cancer) patients with the chronic fatigue
      syndrome (CFS), in comparison with healthy controls. In addition, abnormal concentrations of
      specific substances have been observed in patients with CFS compared to healthy controls. To
      assess muscle fatigue, a two-minute endurance test of the upper arm will be administered at
      maximal voluntary contraction. Next to differences in the brains, CFS patients showed
      (central) muscle fatigue. A maximal exercise test on a bicycle will be performed to assess
      physical fitness. Physical activity in fatigued cancer survivors is decreased, compared to
      healthy controls. It is not known whether physical deconditioning originated during the
      cancer treatment is the reason why these patients are still less active. In addition,
      patients and controls will wear an actometer for two weeks to register baseline daily
      physical activity and for an additional 5 days after the maximal exercise test, to assess the
      effect of exercise on the daily physical activity. Finally, patients and controls will
      complete standardized questionnaires and will perform neurological/psychological tests, like
      a reaction time test and a short time memory task, at baseline.

      The results of the non-fatigued and the fatigued patients will be compared at baseline. For
      the non-fatigued participants, the study will be finished after the baseline measurements.
      The fatigued participants will start with cognitive behavior therapy immediately after the
      baseline measurements or after 6 months, depending on the randomization.

      At the end of the therapy, after six months, or after 6 months of waiting for cognitive
      behavior therapy, a second assessment will take place, comparable to the baseline
      measurements. These results will be compared with the baseline situation to analyze the
      effect of cognitive behavior therapy on the (possible) causes of postcancer fatigue.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Fatigue after curative treatment for cancer is a severe and invalidating problem. 20-40% of
      disease-free cancer patients mention fatigue as a frequent complaint, impairing quality of
      life. In search for (neuro)physiological factors determining fatigue, our centre has recently
      demonstrated the presence of morphological differences in the brains of non-cancer patients
      with the chronic fatigue syndrome (CFS) compared with healthy volunteers. Both in patients
      with CFS and in fatigued patients with neuromuscular diseases we showed that fatigue has a
      central neurophysiological component (so-called central activation failure). Others have
      shown that chronic fatigue is associated with altered brain metabolism. Studies with proton
      MR spectroscopy (1H MRS) have demonstrated a higher choline to creatine ratio in the brains
      of chronically fatigued patients. This suggests increased cell membrane turnover. Also
      reduced levels of N-acetylaspartate-creatine ratio (NAA/Cr) in the right hippocampus have
      been observed in these patients, which suggests a decrease in functional axons. Finally,
      elevated ventricular lactate was observed, which suggests changes in brain glucose
      metabolism. Actigraphy has shown that actual physical activity in fatigued cancer survivors
      is decreased compared to healthy controls. It is not known whether physical deconditioning
      originated during the actual cancer treatment is the reason why these patients are still less
      active. Until now no other (neuro)physiological factors have been identified explaining
      fatigue in cancer survivors. Recently we have shown that Cognitive Behaviour Therapy (CBT)
      especially designed for fatigued cancer patients is an effective treatment.

      Aim: To identify and measure (neuro)physiological factors of fatigue in fatigued cancer
      survivors and to determine the role of these factors in the maintaining of fatigue. The
      identification of (neuro)physiological factors of persistent fatigue can help to improve the
      diagnostics of fatigue, predict therapy outcome and facilitate other treatment options.
      Finally, if (neuro)physiological characteristics of fatigue can be influenced by CBT it will
      enhance our understanding of the mechanism causing fatigue.

      Research questions: 1) What are characteristic (neuro)physiological factors of fatigue in
      disease-free cancer patients? 2) To which degree can these factors be influenced by Cognitive
      Behaviour Therapy?

      Design: In this explorative study fatigued disease-free cancer patients (n=57), who finished
      treatment for cancer at least one year and maximally ten years ago, will be approached for
      this study and asked for informed consent. They will be compared to age and sex matched
      non-fatigued patients (n=21). First, a base-line assessment will take place, which includes
      magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and magnetic resonance spectroscopy (MRS) to assess brain
      morphology and brain metabolites, respectively. To assess peripheral and central fatigue a
      two-minute endurance test will be administered at maximal voluntary (isometric) contraction
      (MVC). During the test changes in EMG and force indicate peripheral fatigue, while central
      fatigue is studied by the twitch interpolation technique. A maximal exercise test will be
      performed to assess physical fitness and deconditioning. At baseline patients will also be
      given an actometer which will register daily activity during two weeks. Further, the
      actometer will register daily activity up to five days after the maximal exercise test.
      Finally, at baseline patients will fill out a standardized questionnaire, including the
      Checklist Individual Strength and a self-observation list to assess fatigue severity. Then,
      the fatigued patients start immediately with Cognitive Behaviour Therapy (CBT). At the end of
      the therapy, after 6 months, a second assessment will take place in this group of patients.
      The assessment consists of the same measurements as at baseline. The results will be compared
      with the baseline situation to analyze the effect of CBT on the (neuro)physiological
      parameters.

      Relevance of this study: Fatigue long after treatment for cancer is a frequently occurring
      problem, which has important consequences for quality of life in these patients.
      Identification of characteristic (neuro)physiological factors of fatigue in disease-free
      cancer patients may not only serve a theoretical understanding of this invalidating
      condition, but may also provide an objective biological marker that could support the
      diagnosis and follow-up of treatment. The identification of (neuro)physiological factors
      which play a role in fatigue after cancer may aid in the early recognition of patients who
      are at risk for developing fatigue and may lead to early intervention and/or different
      treatment strategies.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Active, not recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>April 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Possible (neuro)physiological determinants of postcancer fatigue</measure>
    <time_frame>The measurements will be performed at baseline and comparable measurements will be performed 6 months later (after 6 months cognitive behavior therapy or 6 months waiting list condition)</time_frame>
    <description>MRI to assess brain morphology; MRS to assess brain metabolite concentrations; sEMG and force registration to assess central and peripheral muscle fatigue; maximal exercise test to assess physical condition; actometer measurements and self-observation list to assess daily activity and symptoms; standardized questionnaires to assess fatigue severity and general health; neurological tests to assess information processing and motor speed; screening of blood and urine to find possible explanations for postcancer fatigue.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">57</enrollment>
  <condition>Postcancer Fatigue</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Fatigued patients: Immediate start CBT</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>After the baseline assessment the fatigued patients will be randomized to start immediately with Cognitive Behaviour Therapy, especially designed for fatigued cancer patients. At the end of the therapy, after 6 months, a second assessment will take place.This assessment will include the same measurements as at baseline.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>fatigues patients: delayed CBT (after 6 months)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The fatigued patients on the waiting list will start with CBT after 6 months</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>non-fatiqued controls</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Non-fatigued control group. This group is not included in the randomization.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>immediate CBT</intervention_name>
    <description>After the baseline assessment the fatigued patients will be randomized to start immediately with Cognitive Behaviour Therapy, especially designed for fatigued cancer patients</description>
    <arm_group_label>Fatigued patients: Immediate start CBT</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Delayed CBT</intervention_name>
    <description>After the baseline assessment the fatigued patients will be randomized: this group is to be placed on a waiting list. After 6 months, a second assessment will take place in the group of fatigued patients who received CBT immediately after randomization. This assessment will include the same measurements as at baseline. The fatigued patients on the waiting list will then start with CBT.</description>
    <arm_group_label>fatigues patients: delayed CBT (after 6 months)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Treated for a malignant solid tumour.

          -  Completion of treatment for cancer minimal 1 year ago

          -  Single treatment modality surgery permitted

          -  Current hormonal therapy permitted

          -  Disease-free, as defined by the absence of somatic disease activity parameters.

          -  Age between 19 and 65.

          -  Age at disease onset minimal 18 years

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Brain tumour in the past

          -  Current psychological or psychiatric treatment.

          -  Physical comorbidity which could explain the fatigue.

          -  Contra-indication for MR examinations (e.g. claustrophobia).

          -  Treatment with anti-depressive drugs, anti-epileptic drugs, benzodiazepines.

          -  Insufficient command of the Dutch language to fill out questionnaires.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>19 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>H.W.M. van Laarhoven, Md</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University Medical Centre Nijmegen</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University Medical Centre Nijmegen</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nijmegen</city>
        <zip>6500 HB</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 30, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 30, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 31, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 21, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 21, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 22, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Fatigued disease-free Cancer Patients</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer treatment finished &gt; one year and &lt; ten years ago</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Fatigue</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

