<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01091467</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>08140</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01091467</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Prospective Study of Heart Failure With Preserved Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction</brief_title>
  <acronym>KaRen</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Study of Heart Failure With Preserved Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction: Prevalence, Characterisation and Prognostic Significance of Cardiac Desynchrony</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>French Cardiology Society</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>French Cardiology Society</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to examine electrical and echocardiographic characteristics and
      prognosis of consecutive patients admitted with acute heart failure and diagnosed to have
      heart failure with preserved ejection fraction (HFPEF).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      -  Time 0: Patients will be screened at the time of presentation to the hospital at
           participating centres

        -  Usually patients will be hospitalised for an acute dyspnea in relation with a pulmonary
           congestion. This congestion does not necessarily justify a hospitalization and for part
           of the patients a consultation and a dedicated treatment would be good enough to cure
           the symptoms.

        -  Thus, patients seen in emergency for a congestion and diagnosed or known to have a
           preserved left ventricular ejection fraction (LV EF &gt; 45%) will be proposed to
           participate to the study.

        -  Patients meeting inclusion criteria will be invited back to the clinic in stable
           condition, approximately 4-8 weeks after the initial hospitalization.

        -  Time 4-8 weeks after initial hospitalisation (NOT after discharge): Comprehensive
           history-taking and examinations.

        -  Any information necessary for the study will be collected by the principal investigator
           in each participating center in a dedicated, secure, e-CRF. The access to the e-CRF will
           be restrictive to the only principal investigator of each center. The lonely other
           persons able to take look to the e-CRF are the study monitors.

        -  Time 6, 12, and 18 months: Follow up by phone call or review of charts or other records
           such as death registries. This part of the study will be performed by the CRAs in the
           French Society of Cardiology
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2008</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Death rate</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Analyse survival (all-cause death)</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospitalization for HF</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Hospitalization for Heart Failure</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiovascular death</measure>
    <time_frame>18 months</time_frame>
    <description>Cardiovascular death</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">362</enrollment>
  <condition>Congestive Heart Failure</condition>
  <condition>Left Ventricular Ejection Fraction</condition>
  <condition>Heart Failure With Preserved Ejection Fraction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients with HF</arm_group_label>
    <description>Each patient seen in hospital emergency or for congestive heart failure and with an ejection fraction above 45%</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients presenting to the hospital with congestive heart failure
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient presenting to the hospital with congestive heart failure, defined as:

               1. Clinical signs of heart failure

                  Major criteria

                    -  Paroxysmal nocturnal dyspnea

                    -  Orthopnea

                    -  Jugular venous distension

                    -  Pulmonary crackling rales

                    -  3rd heart sound

                    -  Cardiothoracic ratio &gt; 0.5 on X-ray

                    -  Pulmonary oedema on X-ray

                  Minor Criteria

                    -  peripheral oedema

                    -  nocturnal cough

                    -  dyspnoea at exercise

                    -  hepatomegaly

                    -  pleural effusion

                    -  tachycardia (defined as ≥ 100 beats per minute)

                  Heart failure if: presence of 2 major criteria or 1 major + 2 minor criteria

               2. LVEF ≥ 45% by echocardiography within 72h

               3. BNP &gt; 100 ng/L or NT-proBNP &gt; 300 ng/L

                  Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Evidence of primary hypertrophic or restrictive cardiomyopathy or systemic illness
             known to be associated with infiltrative heart disease

          -  Known cause of right heart failure not related to left ventricular dysfunction

          -  Pericardial constriction

          -  Clinically significant pulmonary disease, as evidenced by requirement of home oxygen.

          -  End-stage renal disease requiring dialysis

          -  Bi-ventricular pacemaker (CRT)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Pontchaillou Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rennes</city>
        <zip>35000</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Karolinska University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Stockholm</city>
        <country>Sweden</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
    <country>Sweden</country>
  </location_countries>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Donal E, Lund LH, Linde C, Edner M, Lafitte S, Persson H, Bauer F, Ohrvik J, Ennezat PV, Hage C, Löfman I, Juilliere Y, Logeart D, Derumeaux G, Gueret P, Daubert JC. Rationale and design of the Karolinska-Rennes (KaRen) prospective study of dyssynchrony in heart failure with preserved ejection fraction. Eur J Heart Fail. 2009 Feb;11(2):198-204. doi: 10.1093/eurjhf/hfn025.</citation>
    <PMID>19168519</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Donal E, Lund L, Linde C, Daubert JC; KaRen investigators. Is cardiac resynchronization therapy an option in heart failure patients with preserved ejection fraction? Justification for the ongoing KaRen project. Arch Cardiovasc Dis. 2010 Jun-Jul;103(6-7):404-10. doi: 10.1016/j.acvd.2010.01.009. Epub 2010 Jun 23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20800804</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Donal E, Lund LH, Oger E, Hage C, Persson H, Reynaud A, Ennezat PV, Bauer F, Sportouch-Dukhan C, Drouet E, Daubert JC, Linde C; KaRen Investigators. Baseline characteristics of patients with heart failure and preserved ejection fraction included in the Karolinska Rennes (KaRen) study. Arch Cardiovasc Dis. 2014 Feb;107(2):112-21. doi: 10.1016/j.acvd.2013.11.002. Epub 2013 Dec 30.</citation>
    <PMID>24388161</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Lund LH, Donal E, Oger E, Hage C, Persson H, Haugen-Löfman I, Ennezat PV, Sportouch-Dukhan C, Drouet E, Daubert JC, Linde C; KaRen Investigators. Association between cardiovascular vs. non-cardiovascular co-morbidities and outcomes in heart failure with preserved ejection fraction. Eur J Heart Fail. 2014 Sep;16(9):992-1001. doi: 10.1002/ejhf.137. Epub 2014 Jul 21.</citation>
    <PMID>25046483</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Donal E, Lund LH, Oger E, Hage C, Persson H, Reynaud A, Ennezat PV, Bauer F, Drouet E, Linde C, Daubert C; KaRen investigators. New echocardiographic predictors of clinical outcome in patients presenting with heart failure and a preserved left ventricular ejection fraction: a subanalysis of the Ka (Karolinska) Ren (Rennes) Study. Eur J Heart Fail. 2015 Jul;17(7):680-8. doi: 10.1002/ejhf.291. Epub 2015 May 29.</citation>
    <PMID>26033771</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Donal E, Lund LH, Oger E, Reynaud A, Schnell F, Persson H, Drouet E, Linde C, Daubert C; KaRen investigators. Value of exercise echocardiography in heart failure with preserved ejection fraction: a substudy from the KaRen study. Eur Heart J Cardiovasc Imaging. 2016 Jan;17(1):106-13. doi: 10.1093/ehjci/jev144. Epub 2015 Jun 16.</citation>
    <PMID>26082167</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hage C, Lund LH, Donal E, Daubert JC, Linde C, Mellbin L. Copeptin in patients with heart failure and preserved ejection fraction: a report from the prospective KaRen-study. Open Heart. 2015 Nov 3;2(1):e000260. doi: 10.1136/openhrt-2015-000260. eCollection 2015.</citation>
    <PMID>26568833</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Savarese G, Donal E, Hage C, Oger E, Persson H, Daubert JC, Linde C, Lund LH; KaRen investigators. Changes in natriuretic peptides after acute hospital presentation for heart failure with preserved ejection fraction: A feasible surrogate trial endpoint? A report from the prospective Karen study. Int J Cardiol. 2017 Jan 1;226:65-70. doi: 10.1016/j.ijcard.2016.10.035. Epub 2016 Oct 17. Erratum in: Int J Cardiol. 2018 Mar 27;:.</citation>
    <PMID>27788392</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Bosseau C, Donal E, Lund LH, Oger E, Hage C, Mulak G, Daubert JC, Linde C; KaRen investigators. The prognostic significance of atrial fibrillation in heart failure with preserved ejection function: insights from KaRen, a prospective and multicenter study. Heart Vessels. 2017 Jun;32(6):735-749. doi: 10.1007/s00380-016-0933-8. Epub 2016 Dec 27.</citation>
    <PMID>28028584</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hage C, Michaëlsson E, Linde C, Donal E, Daubert JC, Gan LM, Lund LH. Inflammatory Biomarkers Predict Heart Failure Severity and Prognosis in Patients With Heart Failure With Preserved Ejection Fraction: A Holistic Proteomic Approach. Circ Cardiovasc Genet. 2017 Feb;10(1). pii: e001633. doi: 10.1161/CIRCGENETICS.116.001633.</citation>
    <PMID>28100627</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Donal E, Lund LH, Oger E, Bosseau C, Reynaud A, Hage C, Drouet E, Daubert JC, Linde C; KaRen Investigators. Importance of combined left atrial size and estimated pulmonary pressure for clinical outcome in patients presenting with heart failure with preserved ejection fraction. Eur Heart J Cardiovasc Imaging. 2017 Jun 1;18(6):629-635. doi: 10.1093/ehjci/jex005.</citation>
    <PMID>28329385</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 8, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 23, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 24, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 21, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 21, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">November 24, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>French Cardiology Society</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Donal Erwan</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Heart Failure</keyword>
  <keyword>Ejection Fraction</keyword>
  <keyword>Echocardiography</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Heart Failure</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

