<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01098422</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>071960</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01098422</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study of Yttrium-90 Radioactive Resin Microspheres to Treat Colorectal Adenocarcinoma Metastatic to the Liver</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase II Study of Yttrium-90 Radioactive Resin Microspheres in the Treatment of Colorectal Adenocarcinoma Metastatic to the Liver After Failure of First-Line Combination Chemotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tony Reid, M.D., Ph.D.</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Sirtex Medical</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Diego</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to determine the effectiveness of radioactive microsphere
      infusion as a treatment for liver metastases from colon or rectal cancer. The investigators
      hypothesis is that the administration of microspheres between first and second line
      chemotherapy will increase progression-free survival time by about 2.5 months and may also
      improve tumor response rates to subsequent second line chemotherapy.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a phase II, single-arm study of Yttrium-90 (Y-90) radioactive resin microspheres in
      the treatment of colorectal adenocarcinoma metastatic to the liver in patients who have had
      progressive disease through first line combination chemotherapy or have otherwise failed
      first line chemotherapy due to toxicity. Expected enrollment at University of California, San
      Diego (UCSD) is approximately 34 subjects.

      The dose of Yttrium-90 radioactive resin microspheres is calculated based on body surface
      area (to estimate normal liver volume), percentage of total liver represented by the targeted
      lobe, and percentage of the lobe that is occupied by tumor, corrected for percentage lung
      shunt. The prescribed dose, calculated by the nuclear medicine physician, will be delivered
      by the interventional radiologist using the standard delivery system with frequent
      fluoroscopic monitoring to assure ante grade blood flow immediately after treatment.
      Additional current standard practice includes obtaining a nuclear medicine scan of the
      patient immediately after each therapeutic Yttrium-90 microspheres administration to prove
      delivery of the agent to the targeted portion of the liver and absence of either
      extra-hepatic Yttrium-90 delivery or free Yttrium-90.

      Blood samples will be obtained one week after the first treatment with microspheres. If the
      patient has bi-lobar disease and the results of lab tests meet protocol specified criteria,
      the dose will be repeated in the initially-untreated lobe. If the lab tests do not meet
      protocol specified criteria (i.e. study inclusion/exclusion criteria), the treatment will be
      deferred for fourteen days and labs repeated. If they are then within parameters, the patient
      will receive the second dose. If they are not within parameters, the patient will proceed to
      chemotherapy.

      Patients will remain off chemotherapy after their final microspheres treatment for a minimum
      of three weeks. Second line treatment options include FDA approved anti-neoplastic agents
      used in colorectal cancer metastatic to the liver with the exception of bevacizumab and
      capecitabine, which has been less rigorously studied with relation to Yttrium-90 radioactive
      microspheres and therefore will not be used. When patients are found to have progressive
      disease while receiving second line chemotherapy, they will then undergo a comprehensive
      clinical, laboratory, and imaging assessment and enter the follow-up phase in which they are
      assessed every five to seven months until death or withdrawal of consent.

      A contrast enhanced ultrasound (CEUS) will be performed pre microsphere treatment (within 14
      days), post microsphere treatment (2 weeks, 4 weeks, 8 weeks and 12 weeks post the
      microsphere treatment). If patients require two treatments with microspheres, they will be
      evaluated 2, 4, 8 and 12 weeks post the second treatment.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Terminated</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    Halted due to slow enrollment
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>January 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival assessed by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors (RECIST) criteria using Computerized Tomography (CT) assessment of tumor(s) at 6 months since the diagnosis date of disease progression on first-line therapy.</measure>
    <time_frame>4 years</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival assessed at 6 months since diagnosis of progression on first-line therapy</measure>
    <time_frame>4 yrs</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor response rate as determined by RECIST criteria using CT or Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) assessment of tumor size every 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>4 yrs</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor response rate as determined by Position Emission Tomography (PET) scan imaging every 3 months</measure>
    <time_frame>4 yrs</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor response rate as determined by Contrast Enhanced Ultrasound scan imaging</measure>
    <time_frame>4 yrs</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to progression, assessed by RECIST criteria using CT or MRI</measure>
    <time_frame>4 yrs</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in abnormal serum tumor marker after administration of microspheres and monthly throughout second line chemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>4 yrs</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of adverse events grade 2 or higher and dose limiting adverse events throughout microspheres treatment, second line chemotherapy and follow-up</measure>
    <time_frame>4 yrs</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Clinical laboratory safety results</measure>
    <time_frame>4 yrs</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>60 day all-cause mortality rate since the start of second line chemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>4 yrs</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">10</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Liver Neoplasms</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Yttrium-90 Radioactive Resin Microspheres</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Yttrium-90 Radioactive Resin Microspheres</intervention_name>
    <description>An injectable formulation of the radioisotope yttrium-90 encapsulated in resin microspheres with potential antineoplastic activity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Yttrium-90 Radioactive Resin Microspheres</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Histologically confirmed colorectal carcinoma. Liver metastasis will be confirmed by
             either PET scan or biopsy.

          -  Ability to understand and willingness to sign written informed consent

          -  Minimum of 18 years of age

          -  Liver dominant metastases measurable by CT or MRI and therefore amenable to serial
             assessment using RECIST criteria

          -  Progressive disease of metastatic colorectal carcinoma on first line combination
             chemotherapy with a 5-fluorouracil/leucovorin with oxaliplatin (FOLFOX) based regimen
             (Folinic Acid, Oxaliplatin and Fluorouracil)or failure of first line chemotherapy due
             to toxicity

          -  Candidate for second line chemotherapy with a fluorouracil, leucovorin, and irinotecan
             (FOLFIRI) regimen. Per standard of care, second line chemotherapy will not include
             Bevacizumab.

          -  Karnofsky Performance Score (KPS) of 70% or greater

          -  Life expectancy of greater than or equal to four months by investigator estimation

          -  Females with negative urine or serum pregnancy test

          -  Effective double barrier contraception for a minimum of two months following the final
             infusion of microspheres

          -  Patients who are not candidates for transarterial chemoembolization (TACE), thermal
             ablation or surgical resection

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Dominant extra-hepatic disease including cerebral metastases or other extra-hepatic
             metastases that are symptomatic

          -  Large volume ascites assessed by cross sectional CT imaging

          -  Any chemotherapy &lt; 4 weeks prior to the first microsphere treatment

          -  Anticipated to need Avastin chemotherapy within eight weeks of day M1

          -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &lt; 1.5 x 109/L

          -  Platelets (PLT) &lt; 60,000/mm3

          -  Hemoglobin (Hgb) &lt; 9.0 gm/dL

          -  Prothrombin time (PT) or Partial Prothrombin time (PTT) &gt; upper limit of normal (ULN)

          -  Serum Creatinine &gt; 2.0 mg/dL

          -  Forced expiratory volume (FEV1) &lt; 1L by baseline pulmonary function tests (ordered if
             investigator judges it to be clinically indicated)

          -  Aspartate aminotransferase (AST) or alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt; 5 times upper
             limits of normal (ULN) or total bilirubin &gt; 2.0 mg/dL

          -  History of incompetent sphincter of oddi (e.g.: sphincterotomy, biliary-enteric
             anastamosis, or percutaneous biliary drain)

          -  Severe hypoalbuminemia (albumin &lt; 2.0 g/dL)

          -  Alkaline phosphatase &gt; 2.5 times ULN

          -  Greater than 20% lung shunting (determined by the MAA - Tc 99 nuclear medicine lung
             shunt scan)

          -  Pre assessment angiogram and MAA scan demonstrating any uncorrectable activity in the
             stomach, bowel or pancreas

          -  Major surgery &lt; 4 weeks prior to the first microsphere treatment

          -  Female who is pregnant or nursing

          -  Men and women of childbearing potential wishing to conceive &lt; 2 months following the
             completion of the microsphere portion of the study.

          -  Any investigational agent administered &lt; 4 weeks prior to microsphere treatment

          -  A known history of hepatitis B or hepatitis C

          -  Known hypersensitivity to any component of microsphere infusion

          -  History of, or current coagulation or bleeding disorder

          -  History of significant hepatic cirrhosis, fibrosis or hemochromatosis

          -  History of malignancy, other than colorectal cancer, within five years of the start of
             study participation, except in situ cervical or skin cancer

          -  Active severe infection or any other concurrent disease or medical conditions that are
             likely to interfere with the study as judged by the investigator

          -  Prior treatment with radioactive microspheres or external beam radiation therapy to
             the liver

          -  Prophylactic anticoagulation and nonsteroidal antiplatelet drugs are only a
             contraindication, if the PT/PTT are above the ULN. Plavix (clopidogrel) will need to
             be stopped 5 days prior to the hepatic-angiogram and the microsphere procedures, then
             started the next day.

          -  History of right to left, bi-directional or transient right to left cardiac shunts,
             worsening or clinically unstable congestive heart failure, acute myocardial infarction
             or acute coronary syndromes serious ventricular arrhythmias or high risk for
             arrhythmias due to prolongation of the QT interval, respiratory failure as manifested
             by signs or symptoms of carbon dioxide retention or hypoxemia or severe emphysema,
             pulmonary emboli or other conditions that causes pulmonary hypertension due to
             compromised pulmonary arterial vasculature
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Tony Reid, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Diego</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>The Rebecca and John Moores UCSD Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Jolla</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92093</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UCSD Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 1, 2010</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>April 1, 2010</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">April 2, 2010</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 4, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 4, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 8, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor-Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Diego</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Tony Reid, M.D., Ph.D.</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Associate Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>liver</keyword>
  <keyword>colorectal</keyword>
  <keyword>metastasis</keyword>
  <keyword>carcinoma</keyword>
  <keyword>Yttrium-90</keyword>
  <keyword>microspheres</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenocarcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liver Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

