<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02084602</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>U.2012.0008</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02084602</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Artesunate/Mefloquine in the Peruvian Amazon</brief_title>
  <acronym>Artesunate</acronym>
  <official_title>Assessment of in Vivo and in Vitro Efficacy of Combined Artesunate/Mefloquine Therapy for Treatment of Uncomplicated Plasmodium Falciparum Infection in the Peruvian Amazon</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Instituto Nacional de Salud. Peru</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Naval Medical Research Unit No 6</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Instituto Nacional de Salud. Peru</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      There is growing evidence of the emergence of P. falciparum resistance to artesunate (a
      derivative of artemisin) in Southeast Asia. The emergence and spread of resistant strains to
      artemisinin would represent an alarming threat to the success of the antimalarial combination
      therapy in the region. The delayed clearance of parasitemia for more than 24 hours has been
      taken as an early sign of resistance, a phenomenon seen at the Thai-Cambodia border.

      The purpose of this research study, is to assess the in vitro and in vivo efficacy of
      combinated artesunate/mefloquine therapy to treatment of uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum
      malaria in the Peruvian Amazon through the analysis of the rate of clearance of parasitemia
      and other important outcomes.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Combination therapy with artemisinin derivatives is the treatment of choice for malaria by P.
      falciparum since 2006, but there is growing evidence of the emergence of P. falciparum
      resistance to artesunate in Southeast Asia. The delayed clearance of parasitemia for more
      than 24 hours has been taken as an early sign of resistance, a phenomenon seen at the
      Thai-Cambodia border. The emergence and spread of resistant strains to artemisinin would
      represent an alarming threat to the success of the antimalarial combination therapy in the
      region.

      This research study, will be conducted in collaboration with the National Institute of Health
      of Peru.

      Objectives:

      Main Objective: To determine the rate of clearance of parasitemia in the first 72 hours after
      administration of artesunate.

      Secondary/exploratory objectives:

        1. to determine the efficacy of the artesunate (AS)/mefloquine (MQ) therapy in participants
           with uncomplicated falciparum malaria in the Peruvian Amazon (sub-study);

        2. to correlate the clinical results from the in vivo study with results of in vitro
           sensitivity and molecular genotyping;

        3. to identify common specific genetic determinants to the resistance of artemisinins in
           parasite populations;

        4. to determine the levels of gametocytes in participants with uncomplicated falciparum
           malaria treated with AS/MQ;

        5. to determine the contribution of host immunity in clinical and parasitological response;

        6. to create a catalog of parasite samples closely correlated with clinical response data
           to perform a longitudinal follow-up of resistance trends;

        7. to determine pharmacokinetic parameters associated with failure of therapy.

      Methodology:

      The study will be conducted in seven health facilities and one hospital in the Department of
      Loreto in the Peruvian Amazon, where 59 volunteers will be enrolled between 5 and 65 years of
      age with confirmed diagnosis of monoinfection by P. falciparum. In addition to the main
      study, we will conduct a sub-study to determine the efficacy of AS/MQ (regime currently used
      in Peru) After signing the informed consent/assent, blood samples will be taken to determine
      parasite density, baseline biochemical tests, genotyping studies, analysis of molecular
      markers and in vitro sensitivity, antibodies against malaria and cytokines. Artesunate will
      be administered according to national guidelines in the first three days, 4 mg/kg/day.
      However, mefloquine administration will be delayed for up to 72 hours to measure the rate of
      clearance of parasitemia with artesunate alone in the first three days. Serial blood samples
      for thick/thin smears will be taken every 4 hours during the first 12 hours and then every 6
      hours until complete the first 72 hours, after the AS administration, during which time the
      study participants will remain in a hospital ward. Monitoring will be undertaken until day 42
      with analysis of thick/thin smears according to WHO guidelines. In case of parasitemia
      recurrence, additional blood samples will be collected for genotyping tests, in vitro
      sensitivity, and analysis of molecular markers of drug resistance and immunology assays. The
      sub-study will be useful to assess the efficacy of the regimen currently in use by the
      Ministry of Health of Peru, in this arm the patients will be given AS 4 mg/kg/day in Days 0,
      1 and 2 and MQ 12.5mg/kg/day in Days 1 and 2. In this arm, the follow up will be done using
      thick smears on Days 1, 2, 3, 7, 14, 21, 28, 35 and 42. Blood samples will be collected on
      Days 0, 42 and the day of recurrence.

      This study will allow the Ministry of Health to know the state of resistance/tolerance to
      artesunate in Peru and take the necessary control measures to ensure that artesunate can be
      used successfully for treatment of falciparum malaria. Importantly, the results of this study
      will be compared to parallelly-designed studies in Kenya (US Army Medical Research Unit
      Kenya-USAMRU K) and Thailand (Army Forces Medical Research Institute of Medical
      Sciences-AFRIMS).

      Relevance: Malaria is one of the main public health problems in Peru, early and efficacious
      treatment in the principal control strategy the appearance of strains that are resistant to
      the regular treatment used in Peru jeopardize the strategies for malaria control in South
      America. This study will allow us to know the current resistance status and to prepare
      corresponding measures.

      Budget: This study will be done as a joined effort between NAMRU-6 and the INS, this will
      cost 201,934.93 Nuevos Soles afforded by Instituto Nacional de Salud and a total cost of
      527,934.93 Nuevos Soles for both participating institutions
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Not yet recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">February 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Parasite clearance time</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 72 hours after administration of artesunate</time_frame>
    <description>Parasite clearance time assessed by microscopy and quantitative PCR</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Parasite reduction rates and ratios</measure>
    <time_frame>24, 48 hours after the first administration of artesunate</time_frame>
    <description>Parasite reduction rates and ratios assessed by microscopy and quantitative PCR</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time for parasite count to fall</measure>
    <time_frame>at least 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Time for parasite count to fall to 50%, 90% and 99% of initial parasite density</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fever clearance time</measure>
    <time_frame>at least 24 hours</time_frame>
    <description>Time taken for temperature to fall below 37˚C and remain there for at least 24 hours</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gametocyte carriage rates</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 14 days since the first administration of artesunate</time_frame>
    <description>Gametocyte carriage rates assessed in person weeks up to 14 days</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">59</enrollment>
  <condition>Malaria, Falciparum</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Artesunate/mefloquine</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Orally administration of artesunate 4mg/Kg by three days Orally administration of mefloquine 15mg/Kg in the fourth day Orally administration of mefloquine 10mg/Kg in the fifth day</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Artesunate</intervention_name>
    <description>Orally administration of artesunate 4mg/Kg by three days</description>
    <arm_group_label>Artesunate/mefloquine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Distribuited by AC Farma</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Mefloquine</intervention_name>
    <description>Orally administration of mefloquine 15mg/Kg in the fourth day Orally administration of mefloquine 10mg/Kg in the fifth day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Artesunate/mefloquine</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Distribuited by AC Farma</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age between 5 and 65 years old inclusive

          -  Monoinfection of P. falciparum confirmed by microscopy

          -  Documented fever (axillary temperature &gt; 37.5°C) and/or history of fever during the
             previous 48 hours in the absence of other obvious causes of fever (such as pneumonia,
             otitis media, etc)

          -  Infection with P. falciparum of 1000 and 100,000 asexual parasites per microliter (μl)
             to be determined by microscopic examination of a thick or thin smear, and positive
             confirmation by polymerase chain reaction (PCR); * Presence of sexual form of P. vivax
             is acceptable; ** PCR confirmation is not an enrollment requirement

          -  Informed consent must be obtained from the participant or both parents/guardian (in
             the case of children), and assent from the child (from 8 to 17 years old)

          -  Willingness of the participant to return to the health facility for regular check-ups
             during the follow-up period of 42 days

          -  Willingness of the participant to transfer to the Hospital de Apoyo Iquitos to start
             treatment

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Severe malaria signs (as defined by the World Health Organization):

               1. Cerebral malaria (irreversible coma)

               2. Severe anemia (hematocrit &lt; 15%, or clinic signs)

               3. Clinic signs of kidney failure (e.g., serum creatinine &gt; 3 mg/dL)

               4. Pulmonary edema

               5. Hypoglycemia (glucose in the blood &lt;40mg/dL or clinic signs)

               6. Shock (PA systolic &lt; 70 mm Hg in adults; &lt; 50 in children)

               7. Spontaneous bleeding/Disseminated intravascular coagulation (CID)

               8. Recurrent generalized convulsions

               9. Acidemia/acidosis (clinic signs)

              10. Macroscopic hemoglobinuria

              11. Jaundice Laboratory tests for measuring some of these conditions may not be
                  available at all study sites. If they are not, we will use clinical criteria of
                  severe malaria at the discretion of the study physician

          -  Background of other chronic or severe diseases (e.g., heart, kidney, liver diseases,
             HIV/AIDS, severe malnutrition), determined clinically by medical history and physical
             examination

          -  Background of hypersensitivity to any of the drugs tested or used as an alternative
             treatment: AS, MQ, quinine or tetracycline/clindamycin

          -  Gestation (based on a serum pregnancy test or medical history) or desire to become
             pregnant during the study period, or not using any family planning method while being
             sexually active (confirmed by urine pregnancy test)

          -  Breastfeeding a child under 6 months old

          -  Have received antimalarial drugs in the previous 7 days

          -  Inability to eat or drink, vomiting (more than twice in the last 24 hours), recent
             history of seizures (one or more in the previous 24 hours), altered level of
             consciousness, inability to sit or stand

          -  Splenectomy background
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>5 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Salomon Durand, Master</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>NAMRU 6</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Edward Smith, MSc (c)</last_name>
    <phone>011 - 511 - 614 - 4141</phone>
    <phone_ext>215</phone_ext>
    <email>edward.simth@med.navy.mil</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>NAMRU 6</name>
      <address>
        <city>Iquitos</city>
        <state>Loreto</state>
        <zip>5116</zip>
        <country>Peru</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Salomon Durand, Master</last_name>
      <phone>011 - 5165 - 617- 6296</phone>
      <phone_ext>2143</phone_ext>
      <email>salomon.durand@gmail.com</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Salomon Durand, Master</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Peru</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Durand S, Sihuincha M, Lachira A, Chaves J, Cabezas C. [A need to monitor P. falciparum resistance to artesunate in Peru]. Rev Peru Med Exp Salud Publica. 2012 Oct-Dec;29(4):579-80. Review. Spanish.</citation>
    <PMID>23338651</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>de Oliveira AM, Chavez J, de Leon GP, Durand S, Arrospide N, Roberts J, Cabezas C, Marquiño W. Efficacy and effectiveness of mefloquine and artesunate combination therapy for uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria in the Peruvian Amazon. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2011 Sep;85(3):573-8. doi: 10.4269/ajtmh.2011.11-0250.</citation>
    <PMID>21896825</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gutman J, Green M, Durand S, Rojas OV, Ganguly B, Quezada WM, Utz GC, Slutsker L, Ruebush TK 2nd, Bacon DJ. Mefloquine pharmacokinetics and mefloquine-artesunate effectiveness in Peruvian patients with uncomplicated Plasmodium falciparum malaria. Malar J. 2009 Apr 9;8:58. doi: 10.1186/1475-2875-8-58.</citation>
    <PMID>19358697</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Alker AP, Lim P, Sem R, Shah NK, Yi P, Bouth DM, Tsuyuoka R, Maguire JD, Fandeur T, Ariey F, Wongsrichanalai C, Meshnick SR. Pfmdr1 and in vivo resistance to artesunate-mefloquine in falciparum malaria on the Cambodian-Thai border. Am J Trop Med Hyg. 2007 Apr;76(4):641-7.</citation>
    <PMID>17426163</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wongsrichanalai C, Meshnick SR. Declining artesunate-mefloquine efficacy against falciparum malaria on the Cambodia-Thailand border. Emerg Infect Dis. 2008 May;14(5):716-9. doi: 10.3201/eid1405.071601.</citation>
    <PMID>18439351</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>March 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 7, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 11, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 12, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 4, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 4, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 6, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>artesunate</keyword>
  <keyword>mefloquine</keyword>
  <keyword>falciparum</keyword>
  <keyword>peruvian amazon</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Malaria, Falciparum</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Artesunate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Artemisinins</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Mefloquine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

