<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02081638</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>140039</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>14-I-0039</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02081638</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Elite Controller and ART-treated HIV+ Statin Versus ASA Treatment Intervention Study</brief_title>
  <official_title>Elite Controller and ART-Treated HIV+ Statin Versus ASA Treatment Intervention Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      - The immune system protects the body from infection. But it can also cause harm. For
      example, the clotting system makes blood clot and protects from bleeding. But blood clots are
      sometimes harmful. People with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection have increased
      inflammation and clotting. This may increase their risk for diseases like stroke or heart
      attack. Researchers want to know how aspirin or HMG-CoA reductase inhibitors (so-called
      statin medications) affect the immune and clotting systems of people with HIV. Aspirin is a
      medicine to decrease clotting. Statins are medications given to lower cholesterol and
      decrease inflammation.

      Objectives:

      - To see how aspirin or statins change immune and clotting systems in people with HIV.

      Eligibility:

      - Adults 18 and older with HIV and a low viral load, not on aspirin or a statin medication.
      They must also have either: (1) never taken anti-HIV medications (ARVs), have a suppressed
      viral load, have stable CD4 counts, and never had an opportunistic infection; or (2) been
      taking ARVs for 5 continuous years and have a suppressed viral load for more than 3 years.

      Design:

        -  Participants will be screened with medical history, physical exam, and blood and lab
           tests.

        -  Participants will repeat screening tests and have an MRI. An MRI is a way to visualize
           blood vessels in the neck and head. Participants will lie on a table that slides in and
           out of a cylinder surrounded by a magnetic field.

        -  Participants will take either study drug once daily for 9 months.

        -  Participants will have a blood procedure twice. Blood will be removed through a needle
           in one arm and circulated through a machine that removes white blood cells. The blood,
           minus white blood cells, is returned through a needle in the other arm.

        -  All participants will be observed for 3 months before and after treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Despite dramatic improvements in mortality with antiretroviral therapy (ART), HIV-infected
      persons remain at risk of developing non-infectious complications, including cardiovascular,
      renal, and neurological disease. A small subset of the HIV-infected population achieve
      durable control of HIV virus in the absence of ART. These individuals, termed elite
      controllers (ECs), remain ART na(SqrRoot) ve, have stable CD4 T cell counts for many years
      and have no history of opportunistic infections. Despite the lack of AIDS complications,
      recent evidence suggests ECs may exhibit heightened immune activation that may contribute to
      a potentially increased risk for non-infectious complications, similar to successfully
      treated progressors.

      In the current 2 group, randomized, open label trial, we intend to study the effects of a
      lipid lowering agent vs aspirin (ASA) on immune activation in HIV-1 infected participants.
      One group will consist of ECs who are HIV-1 infected, maintain HIV-RNA levels of less than
      the LLD of commercially available assays in the absence of ART, have no history of ART or
      opportunistic infections (OIs) and have stable CD4 T cell counts for greater than 3 years.
      The second group will enroll HIV-1 infected Treated Progressors (henceforth referred to as
      ART &lt;50) who have maintained HIV-RNA below the limit of detection in commercially available
      assays (&lt;40, &lt;48, or &lt;50 copies/mL) for greater than 3 years on ART (treatment duration
      greater than 4 years). Up to 2 months after the screening and enrollment visit, each group
      will enter a 3 month observation period (to establish baseline values for biomarkers/cellular
      markers). After 3 months, participants from each group will be randomized to either ASA, 81
      mg PO daily, or atorvastatin (ATV), 40 mg (dose adjusted for subjects on antiretroviral
      regimens with significant interactions, and will be treated for 9 months, followed by 3
      months of a wash out period (see Figure 1). The primary end point will be change of sCD14
      after 9 months of study intervention from Month 3 to Month 12 in each treatment arm, with
      groups combined (EC and ART &lt;50). Secondary objectives will be to compare changes in soluble
      biomarkers (sCD14, IL-6, D-dimer, hsCRP, sTF, sCD163 and other relevad treatment arms (ASA vs
      statin and EC vs ART&lt;50 and with groups combined), to evaluate cardiovascular (CV) disease
      prevalence in EC vs ART&lt;50 and with groups combined), to evaluate cardiovascular (CV) disease
      prevalence in EC vs ART &lt;50 by MR imaging of carotids, to determine MR measurements and
      correlations with biomarkers and cellular activation markers, and to investigate changes in
      plasma viremia as measured by single copy assay over time.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 5, 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">March 2, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">March 1, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary end point will be change of sCD14 from Month 3 to Month 12 in the two groups combined (EC and ART &lt;50).</measure>
    <time_frame>When the last participant has completed all evaluations.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in soluble biomarkers (sCD14, IL-6, D-dimer, hsCRP, sCD163, sTF as well as other relevant markers of inflammation and coagulation) in EC and ART &lt;50 groups treated with ASA or ATV, independently within each group and arm and with grou...</measure>
    <time_frame>When the last participant has completed all evaluations</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in T cell activation (measured by HLA-DR/CD38 co- expression), monocyte immune activation (measured by activated monocyte subsets expressing either CD14++CD16+ and CD14varCD16+ and markers of activation, CCR5 and TF, and migration, CCR2 ...</measure>
    <time_frame>When the last participant has completed all evaluations.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in MR imaging of carotids after 9 months of statin or ASA in each group and both groups combined.</measure>
    <time_frame>When the last participant has completed all evaluations.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">120</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Elite Controller</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>40 HIV positive elite controllers. Twenty will be randomized to aspirin and 20 will be randomized to atorvastatin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Treated Progressors (ART)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>40 HIV positive, treated progressors. Twenty will berandomized to Aspirin and 20 will be randomized toatorvastatin.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Aspirin 81 mg daily</intervention_name>
    <description>81 mg tablet, daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Treated Progressors (ART)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Elite Controller</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Atorvastatin 40 mg daily</intervention_name>
    <description>40 mg tablet, daily. In subjects on certain antiretroviral medications, ATV dosing will be adjusted in accordance with DHHS guidelines .</description>
    <arm_group_label>Elite Controller</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Treated Progressors (ART)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        EC Arm

          1. Age greater than or equal to 18 years.

          2. Documented HIV-1 infection confirmed by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) and
             Western blot tests (will not be repeated if performed previously at NIH).

          3. Categorized as a long term non-progressor EC as defined by viral loads typically less
             than the LLD of commercially available assays and clinical and laboratory criteria (no
             OIs, no ART, stable CD4 T cell counts for more than 3 years). Viral load blips are
             allowed as long as they are less than 500 copies/mL and flanked by viral load
             measurements less than 100copies/mL. Viral load &lt;100c/mL will be acceptable for
             eligibility at screening.

          4. In women of childbearing potential, with no plans for pregnancy for the next 15 months
             and willing to use 2 investigator approved highly reliable methods of birth control
             consistently while on the study or in 3 month follow up.

          5. Willingness to have samples stored for future research.

          6. Not on a statin or ASA for the past 6 months.

        ART &lt;50 Arm

          1. Age greater than or equal to 18 years.

          2. Documented HIV-1 infection confirmed by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) and
             Western blot tests.

          3. In women of childbearing potential, with no plans for pregnancy for the next 15 months
             and willing to use 2 investigator approved highly reliable methods of birth control
             consistently while on the study or in 3 month follow up.

          4. On continuous combination ART &gt;4 years.

          5. HIV RNA &lt;50 copies/mL (or less than 40 or less than 48 copies/mL, depending on the
             lower limit of detection of the assay used; transient periods of low level (&lt;300)
             detectable virus, blips, acceptable if isolated and followed by viral loads less than
             the lower limit of detection) &gt;3 years and current HIV-RNA less than the LLD of the
             commercially available assay used. Subject will be rescreened if HIV is detectable at
             screening visit.

          6. Willingness to have samples stored for future research.

          7. Not on a statin or ASA for the past 6 months.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA

          1. Diagnosis of cardiovascular disease or hypercholesterolemia (LDL cholesterol 190
             mg/dL).

          2. Known hypersensitivity or allergy to ATV or ASA, including a history of myositis or
             rhabdomyolysis with statin or ASA use.

          3. Other contraindication for ASA or statin therapy (active liver disease, peptic ulcer
             disease, etc.).

          4. Women who are lactating, pregnant, or actively trying to become pregnant or
             considering pregnancy over the likely span of the study (including women of
             childbearing potential who are unwilling to use adequate contraception throughout the
             study).

          5. Any chronic inflammatory condition either requiring anti-inflammatory medication
             (systemic corticosteroids, daily NSAID use,immunomodulating medications) which may, in
             the opinion of the investigator, confound the interpretation of soluble inflammatory
             biomarkers. While on study, short term (less than 5 days) NSAID use will be allowed at
             the discretion of the investigator.

          6. Active drug use or alcohol abuse that, in the opinion of the investigator, may
             interfere with the ability of the subject to participate in the study or that may
             unacceptably increase the risk of the study intervention..

          7. Safety laboratory cut offs: coagulation (INR &gt;2 upper limit of normal [ULN], PLT&lt;75K),
             renal function (GFR&lt;60), liver function (ALT or Alkaline phosphatase or direct
             bilirubin &gt;2x ULN), aldolase &lt;1.5 ULN and anemia (Hg &lt;9 mg/dL).

          8. Antiretroviral therapy with tipranivir, or any therapy which combines non-nucleoside
             reverse transcriptase inhibitors with protease inhibitors.

          9. Chronic hepatitis C co-infection. However, if a subject has more than 24 weeks of
             sustained virologic response (SVR), the subject can be considered for eligibility.

         10. If either MR or apheresis is contraindicated, subject may still participate without
             this procedure. In the case of missed apheresis, a 30 mL research blood draw will be
             substituted (see Appendices B and C).

               -  If statin initiation is indicated per current guidelines, subject will be
                  counseled to consult with their PMD. If the subject then chooses to take part in
                  the study, we will provide their PMD with all pertinent lab results during the
                  course of the study, if requested.

        Co-enrollment Guidelines: Co-enrollment in other trials will be restricted, other than
        enrollment on observational studies. Study staff should be notified of co-enrollment as it
        may require the approval of the Investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Irini Sereti, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>April Poole, R.N.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 435-8007</phone>
    <email>pooleal@mail.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Irini Sereti, M.D.</last_name>
    <phone>(301) 496-5533</phone>
    <email>isereti@niaid.nih.gov</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>For more information at the NIH Clinical Center contact Office of Patient Recruitment (OPR)</last_name>
      <phone>800-411-1222</phone>
      <phone_ext>TTY8664111010</phone_ext>
      <email>prpl@cc.nih.gov</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hennipen County Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?A_2014-I-0039.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deeks SG, Phillips AN. HIV infection, antiretroviral treatment, ageing, and non-AIDS related morbidity. BMJ. 2009 Jan 26;338:a3172. doi: 10.1136/bmj.a3172. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>19171560</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krishnan S, Wilson EM, Sheikh V, Rupert A, Mendoza D, Yang J, Lempicki R, Migueles SA, Sereti I. Evidence for innate immune system activation in HIV type 1-infected elite controllers. J Infect Dis. 2014 Mar;209(6):931-9. doi: 10.1093/infdis/jit581. Epub 2013 Nov 1.</citation>
    <PMID>24185941</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Funderburg NT, Mayne E, Sieg SF, Asaad R, Jiang W, Kalinowska M, Luciano AA, Stevens W, Rodriguez B, Brenchley JM, Douek DC, Lederman MM. Increased tissue factor expression on circulating monocytes in chronic HIV infection: relationship to in vivo coagulation and immune activation. Blood. 2010 Jan 14;115(2):161-7. doi: 10.1182/blood-2009-03-210179. Epub 2009 Oct 14.</citation>
    <PMID>19828697</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 14, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 5, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 5, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 7, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 23, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Immune Activation</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Aspirin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Atorvastatin Calcium</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

