<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02085213</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HTA 12/29/01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-003810-42</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>12/29/01</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>13/NE/0339</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02085213</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>GOT-IT Trial: Glyceryl Trinitrate for Retained Placenta</brief_title>
  <acronym>GOT-IT</acronym>
  <official_title>GOT-IT Trial: A Pragmatic Group Sequential Placebo Controlled Randomised Trial to Determine the Effectiveness of Glyceryl Trinitrate for Retained Placenta.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Edinburgh</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Aberdeen</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>NHS Lothian</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Edinburgh</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      A retained placenta (RP) is a complication after a normal birth, which affects nearly 11,000
      women in the UK per year. This is where the placenta is not delivered spontaneously after
      giving birth. It is a major cause of postpartum haemorrhage (major loss of blood) which can
      lead to the death of the mother. The recommended treatment for RP is a surgical procedure -
      manual removal of placenta (MROP). This is a painful and unpleasant intervention for the
      women, involving additional hospital stay, and is an expensive outcome for the NHS. It is
      widely recognised that non-surgical management options for RP are limited and it has been
      recommended that research is needed into new medical treatments for RP. New effective
      treatments for RP would dramatically reduce the number of women requiring MROP with the
      operation being restricted to the small minority of women with particularly stuck placentae.
      The reduction in operative interventions would have cost benefits for the NHS and also for
      women in terms of increased satisfaction, less separation of mother and baby immediately
      after birth, and reduced morbidity.

      This study will try to prove the clinical and cost effectiveness of a known treatment for
      angina, Glyceryl trinitrate (GTN) used to treat RP. The investigators will compare GTN
      against a placebo (dummy treatment) in a randomised controlled blinded trial (GOT-IT).

      The GOT-IT Trial will be conducted in two phases. The first phase will involve an internal
      pilot study where the aim will be to test out and refine trial procedures in a small number
      of hospital sites. The second phase will be the main trial where recruitment will be extended
      to a larger number of hospitals in order to determine clinical and cost effectiveness.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Although a growing body of evidence supports a use for GTN for treatment of RP, much of this
      evidence is based on anecdotal case-reports or clinical &quot;trials&quot; which are non-randomised, do
      not include a placebo arm and are underpowered. Further, in the context of constrained
      maternity resources in a publicly funded health system, it is important to quantify the costs
      associated with the use of GTN (including any subsequent monitoring costs and costs
      associated with complications) in relation to its effectiveness and any subsequent cost
      savings it may deliver over standard practice. There is therefore an urgent need for a
      pragmatic clinical trial of GTN for RP to determine whether GTN is efficacious, safe,
      acceptable and cost-effective as a treatment for RP before a treatment which may (or may not)
      work is embedded within routine clinical practice. Our proposed randomised placebo controlled
      double blind pragmatic UK wide GOT-IT trial RCT (with internal pilot study) will definitively
      determine whether sublingual GTN is (or is not) clinically and cost effective for management
      of RP.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 5, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 26, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Need for Manual Removal of Placenta</measure>
    <time_frame>From time of randomisation up to 15-minutes post administration of study treatment</time_frame>
    <description>Defined as the placenta remaining undelivered 15 minutes post study treatment and/or being required within 15 minutes of treatment due to safety concerns.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Fall in haemoglobin</measure>
    <time_frame>First postnatal day (approximately 24 hours since the birth).</time_frame>
    <description>Fall in haemoglobin of more than 15% between recruitment and the first postnatal day.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time from randomisation to delivery of placenta.</measure>
    <time_frame>From time of randomisation and administration of the study treatment to delivery of placenta (up to approximately 2 hours).</time_frame>
    <description>The time from when the study drug is administered until the placenta is delivered.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Need for earlier than planned MROP on the basis of the clinical condition.</measure>
    <time_frame>From time of randomisation and administration of the study treatment to delivery of placenta (up to approximately 2 hours).</time_frame>
    <description>This will measure how many women required to go to theatre as an emergency before the 15 minute trial has been completed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Systolic and diastolic blood pressure.</measure>
    <time_frame>Study treatment to 15 minutes postadministration.</time_frame>
    <description>Fall in systolic or diastolic blood pressure of more than 15mmHg and/or increase in pulse of more than 20 beats/minute between baseline and 5 and 15 minutes postadministration of active/placebo treatment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Need for blood transfusion</measure>
    <time_frame>From the time of delivery of the placenta to time of discharge from hospital (up to 7 days).</time_frame>
    <description>How many women will be required to have a blood transfusion between time of delivery and hospital discharge.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Need for general anaesthesia</measure>
    <time_frame>From time of randomisation and administration of the study treatment to delivery of placenta (up to approximately 2 hours).</time_frame>
    <description>Will measure how many women required a general anaesthetic from when the study drug was administered until the placenta was delivered.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Maternal Pyrexia</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 72 hours of delivery or discharge from hospital if discharge occurs sooner</time_frame>
    <description>One or more temperature reading of more than 38°C.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sustained uterine relaxation.</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 24 hours of the time of delivery of the placenta.</time_frame>
    <description>Sustained uterine relaxation after removal of placenta requiring uterotonics.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean costs for each treatment allocation group</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks.</time_frame>
    <description>The mean costs will be summarised by treatment allocation group, and the incremental cost (cost saving) associated with the use of GTN will be estimated using an appropriately specified general linear model. The cost data will be presented alongside the primary and secondary outcome data in a cost-consequence balance sheet, indicating which strategy each outcome favours.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1107</enrollment>
  <condition>Placenta, Retained</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Glyceryl Trinitrate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Nitrolingual Pump Spray [Coro-Nitro] A liquid within non-pressurised, red plastic-coated glass bottle fitted with a pump capable of delivering a metered dose containing 400μg of glyceryl trinitrate.
Excipients: The formulation contains fractionated coconut oil, absolute ethanol, medium chain partial glycerides and peppermint oil.
The treatment will be self administered (2 puffs) as a single intervention. No second intervention will be given.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Matched placebo formulation (except for active ingredient of Glyceryl Trinitrate) with matched packaging and labelling.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Glyceryl Trinitrate</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Glyceryl Trinitrate</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>GTN</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Matched Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Matched placebo</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Dummy treatment</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Women with retained placenta.

          -  Women aged 16 or over.

          -  Women with vaginal delivery (including women with a previous caesarean section).

          -  Haemodynamically stable (systolic blood pressure more than 100mg Hg and pulse less
             than 110 beats per min).

          -  &gt; 14 weeks gestation.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Unable to give informed consent.

          -  Suspected placenta accreta/increta/percreta.

          -  Multiple pregnancy.

          -  Women having an instrumental vaginal delivery in theatre

          -  Allergy or hypersensitivity to nitrates or any other constituent of the formulation.

          -  Taken alcohol in the last 24 hours.

          -  Concomitant use with phosphodiesterase inhibitors (such as sildenafil, tadalafil, or
             vardenafil).

          -  Contra-indication due to one of the following: Severe anaemia, constrictive
             pericarditis, extreme bradycardia, incipient glaucoma, Glucose-6-
             phosphatedehydrogenase-deficiency, cerebral haemorrhage and brain trauma, aortic and /
             or mitral stenosis and angina caused by hypertrophic obstructive cardiomyopathy.
             Circulatory collapse, cardiogenic shock and toxic pulmonary oedema.

          -  Currently participating in another CTIMP.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fiona C Denison, Dr</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>The University of Edinburgh</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Royal Infirmary of Edinburgh</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edinburgh</city>
        <state>Midlothian</state>
        <zip>EH16 4TJ</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 4, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 10, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 12, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 16, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 16, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 21, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Retained placenta</keyword>
  <keyword>Manual Removal of Placenta</keyword>
  <keyword>Glyceryl Trinitrate</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Placenta, Retained</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nitroglycerin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

