<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02086279</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>AMHunderGnRH</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02086279</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>AMH Levels Change During Treatment With GnRh Agonist</brief_title>
  <official_title>AMH Levels Change During Treatment With GnRh Agonist: A Prospective Observational Study.</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University Magna Graecia</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University Magna Graecia</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To evaluate the variation of AMH levels in women undergoing treatment with GnRHa, and to
      assess whether this variation correlates with changes in the antral and pre-antral follicle
      ultrasonographic count (AFC).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The anti Mullerian hormone (AMH) is a glycoprotein produced by granulosa cells of antral and
      preantral ovarian follicles.

      Several studies have shown that the AMH levels provide a reliable indication of the size of
      the growing follicles pool (1). AMH is now commonly used as a biomarker for improving the
      ovarian reserve in women of reproductive age because it is related with outcomes of assisted
      reproduction cycles, chances of pregnancy and distance from menopause (2-4).

      For several years GnRH agonists have been used for the purpose of preserving fertility in the
      course of chemotherapy in young women with cancer (5). Their effectiveness, however, isn't
      100% and there is the need to monitor the ovarian reserve in the course of treatment in these
      young women. With the administration of GnRHa, the FSH levels (the most used hormone for
      improve the ovarian reserve, although it is less reliable and less manageable because of its
      intra-cyclic variations) cannot be used to measure the residual ovarian function due to the
      physiological reduction of gonadotropins induced by the treatment. AMH levels, conversely,
      are relatively stable both during the menstrual cycle (6) and during administration of the
      contraceptive pill (7,8), suggesting the gonadotrophin independence of this molecule. AMH
      could therefore be a useful biomarker of ovarian reserve in the course of GnRHa treatment.

      The use of GnRHa for fertility preservation during chemotherapy is controversial because of
      inconclusive outcome data on fertility (9) and because the mechanism by which GnRHa may act
      to preserve fertility is unknown. The major function of GnRHa is to suppress the production
      of pituitary gonadotrophins, acting indirectly on the ovarian follicles, not exposing growing
      follicles to the toxicity of chemotherapy and thus protecting the future ovarian function.

      Determine the effect of GnRHa on AMH serum level is an essential step to determine both the
      effectiveness of the treatment in terms of preservation of fertility and the reliability of
      this marker for ovarian reserve in cancer patients treated with GnRHa. Up to now, the
      published studies have shown extremely contrasting data. Considered that GnRHa is largely
      used in non-oncological patients for preoperative pharmacological preparation in various
      benign gynecological conditions, it is possible to exploit the high number of patients with
      these characteristics for the non-invasive assessment of analogue effect on the AMH levels.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>March 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">November 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>AMH levels change before and after GnRHa</measure>
    <time_frame>At study entry and at 1, 3 and 6 months after the administration of the first vial of GnRH-a</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preantral and antral follicles</measure>
    <time_frame>At study entry and at 1, 3 and 6 months after the administration of the first vial of GnRH-a</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Correlation between AMH levels and preantral and antral follicles count</measure>
    <time_frame>At study entry and at 1,3 and 6 months after the first vial of GnRH</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">67</enrollment>
  <condition>Uterine Fibroids</condition>
  <condition>Endometriosis</condition>
  <condition>Endometriosis of Uterus</condition>
  <condition>Pelvic Pain</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>GnRH analogue</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients with uterine myoma, endometriosis, fibromatous uterus, chronic pelvic pain in list for surgery are usually pharmacologically treated by administration of GnRHa, 11.25 mg at 21° day of the menstrual cycle and repeated after 3 months to reduce pain symptoms, menstrual blood loss, uterine or fibroids vascularization and size, during the months spent on surgery waiting list.
Patients enrolled will be subjected to valuation of ovarian reserve: specifically, serum levels of AMH and antral follicle count (AFC) between 1 and 4 days of the menstrual cycle will be measured at study entry and at 1, 3 and 6 months after the administration of the first vial of GnRH-a</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>GnRH analogue</intervention_name>
    <description>Patients with uterine myoma, endometriosis, fibromatous uterus, chronic pelvic pain in list for laparoscopic surgery or laparotomy are usually pharmacologically treated by administration of GnRHa, 11.25 mg at 21° day of the menstrual cycle and repeated after 3 months. This treatment is part of our preoperative routine in order to reduce pain symptoms, menstrual blood loss, uterine or fibroids vascularization and size, during the months spent on surgery waiting list.
Patients who will satisfy inclusion and exclusion criteria will be enrolled in this study protocol and will be subjected to valuation of ovarian reserve: specifically, serum levels of AMH and antral follicle count (AFC) between first and fourth days of the menstrual cycle will be measured.</description>
    <arm_group_label>GnRH analogue</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Gonadotropin-releasing hormone analogue</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients waiting for surgery for benign conditions such as uterine fibroids and
             endometriosis, undergoing preoperative treatment with two consecutive doses of GnRHa
             at a dose of 11.25 every three months

          -  18 to 45 years aged patients

          -  Regular menstrual intervals between 22 and 35 days

          -  Expressed written consent for the study entry

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients who do not consent to pharmacological preparation with GnRHa

          -  Estrogen-progestin therapy in the 2 months before enrollment

          -  Autoimmune diseases, chronic , metabolic, systemic and endocrine disorders, including
             hyperandrogenism, hyperprolactinemia, diabetes mellitus and thyroid disease.

          -  Hypogonadotropic hypogonadism

          -  Majors clinical conditions
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>45 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fulvio Zullo</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Magna Graecia University of Catanzaro</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Chair of Obstetrics and Gynecology - University division - UMG</name>
      <address>
        <city>Catanzaro</city>
        <state>CZ</state>
        <zip>88100</zip>
        <country>Italy</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Italy</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 9, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 11, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 13, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 22, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 22, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 25, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University Magna Graecia</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Fulvio Zullo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Full Professor Obstetric Gynecology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>AMH levels</keyword>
  <keyword>Ovarian reserve</keyword>
  <keyword>GnRH analogue</keyword>
  <keyword>Ovarian reserve after GnRH analogue</keyword>
  <keyword>Ovarian reserve modification</keyword>
  <keyword>Antral follicle count</keyword>
  <keyword>Antral follicle count after GnRH analogue</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Endometriosis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pelvic Pain</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leiomyoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myofibroma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Adenomyosis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Deslorelin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

