<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02086630</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>11-8455</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R34MH093352</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02086630</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Timely Initiation of HIV Antiretroviral Therapy Among Those Who Delay/Decline</brief_title>
  <acronym>Heart to Heart</acronym>
  <official_title>Intervention to Increase Timely Initiation of HIV Antiretroviral Therapy (ART) Among Those Who Delay or Decline</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>New York University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>St. Luke's-Roosevelt Hospital Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Beth Israel Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>New York University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study addresses racial/ethnic disparities in HIV/AIDS treatment. Many persons living
      with HIV/AIDS (PLHA) in the U.S. (10-19% of PLHA), predominantly African-Americans and
      Latinos, delay taking Highly Active Antiretroviral Therapy (HAART) until late in the course
      of their HIV disease or never initiate HAART when it is medically indicated. However, there
      are no behavioral interventions to increase HAART initiation among PLHA who delay or decline
      HAART (&quot;PLHA-DD&quot;). The overarching aim of the proposed study is to develop a flexible,
      targeted, and sustainable behavioral intervention to increase HAART initiation among PLHA-DD,
      which, if efficacious, will lead to reductions in morbidity, early mortality, and health care
      costs, as well as increased viral load suppression (reducing transmission to others).
      Further, the study complements and primes participants for existing adherence interventions,
      from which PLHA-DD can benefit when they initiate HAART.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This application seeks to reduce racial/ethnic disparities in HIV/AIDS treatment. National
      studies have consistently shown that many persons living with HIV/AIDS (PLHA) in the U.S. (an
      estimated 10-19% of PLHA), predominantly people of color, delay taking Highly Active
      Antiretroviral Therapy (HAART) until late in their HIV disease or never initiate HAART when
      it is medically necessary, even when engaged in care. This population is of critical
      importance because they experience disproportionately higher morbidity and earlier mortality
      compared to their peers on HAART, and higher health care costs. Further, they are less likely
      to achieve virologic suppression, increasing the probability of HIV transmission to others.
      However, we do not yet have a behavioral intervention to increase the timely initiation and
      continued use of HAART for PLHA-DD. This proposal seeks to address a serious gap in existing
      programs by creating a culturally targeted, sustainable, multi-level, and individualized
      video-based behavioral intervention for the population of PLHA who are medically eligible for
      HAART but who have delayed or declined HAART (referred to as &quot;PLHA-DD&quot;). This is not an
      adherence intervention per se, but will serve as a complement to, and primer for, existing
      adherence interventions, from which PLHA-DD can benefit when they initiate HAART. The
      proposed study is innovative in that it seeks to broaden the HAART adherence research
      paradigm to include HAART initiation.

      Barriers to HAART initiation for PLHA-DD are multi-faceted. At the individual level, for
      example, PLHA-DD suffer from negative attitudes toward HAART (particularly medical mistrust
      and fear), a lack of accurate knowledge about HAART and health, and &quot;competing priorities,&quot;
      including mental health problems and substance use. PLHA-DD also experience powerful social
      barriers to HAART including negative peer norms regarding medications and stigma. Further,
      structural barriers such as poor access to necessary resources and supports (e.g.,
      transportation, paperwork) and ancillary services (e.g., mental health care) impede HAART
      initiation.

      We will create a culturally targeted video-based intervention to increase motivation and
      psychosocial and practical preparedness for HAART among PLHA-DD. The study is guided by two
      complementary theoretical models: the Theory of Triadic Influence, a social-cognitive theory
      that integrates individual, social, and structural influences on health behavior and the
      Anti-racist Stance, which acknowledges the salience of barriers linked to racial/ethnic
      minority status in the lives of PLHA-DD (associated with exclusion, stress, discrimination,
      and poor access to institutional structures), without assuming homogeneity among PLHA-DD. The
      intervention will be flexible and individualized: there will be a 12-week intervention period
      during which participants will receive three structured sessions (including one with a
      &quot;support partner&quot; to reduce social barriers, plus patient navigation, an efficacious
      low-threshold and adaptable approach to reduce individual and structural barriers to
      initiating and sustaining HAART. The intensity of navigation will depend on need, increasing
      the intervention's efficiency. The sessions will consist of individualized interactive
      components and targeted high-quality video components, which will enhance ease-of-use,
      fidelity, and future sustainability.

      The aims of this three-year project are to:

        1. Explore health care and social service providers' and PLHA-DD's perspectives on barriers
           to/facilitators of initiation and continuation of HAART for PLHA-DD at the levels of
           individuals, networks, organizations, and other structures;

        2. Develop components of an intervention and examine their acceptability, safety,
           feasibility, and gather preliminary evidence of their efficacy with respect to HAART
           initiation and continuation among PLHA-DD medically eligible for HAART.

      To accomplish these aims, we will conduct a three phase study: (1) an Elicitation Phase to
      explore barriers to HAART among PLHA-DD (n=16) and health care and social service providers
      (N=18); (2) a Development Phase to create intervention components using Intervention Mapping,
      a mechanism for integrating theoretical models, data, and the literature; and (3) an
      Evaluation Phase to test and revise intervention components (N=30-50 PLHA-DD recruited from
      two large urban HIV clinics and assigned to an intervention or control arm using permuted
      blocks random assignment and interviewed at 3 time points).

      We will also explore peer recruitment approaches to reaching PLHA-DD. PLHA recruited through
      peers will be seen at a local field site but will engage in the same procedures as the
      clinic-recruited cohort.

      We will enroll a total of 90-100 PLHA-DD, ideally half from clinics and half through peer
      recruitment.

      The urgent need to address disparities in HAART initiation and continuation and support
      access to HAART for vulnerable populations has been identified by numerous scientific and
      community leaders, health care providers, and public health officials. Although PLHA-DD are a
      modest proportion of the population of PLHA (10-19%), efficacious interventions to reduce
      morbidity, increase longevity, increase viral load suppression, and reduce health care costs
      associated with delayed HAART initiation are sorely lacking for this group, and have very
      high potential public health significance.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">April 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">April 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Initiation of HAART</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Initiation of HAART by self report and Medical Record</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Continuation of HAART once initiated</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Continuation of HAART once initiated</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to ART once initiated</measure>
    <time_frame>9 months</time_frame>
    <description>Adherence to ART once initiated by self report and hair sample</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">95</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV</condition>
  <condition>Antiretroviral Therapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Heart to Heart (HTH) intervention was a flexible and individualized intervention with the following components: 3 intervention sessions with video-components; patient navigation lasting up to 24 weeks; treatment initiation support groups (up to 5); and inclusion of a Support Partner. This is a behavioral intervention. The intervention uses Motivational Interviewing.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>Treatment as usual</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Heart to Heart</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria clinic cohort:

          1. HIV-infected for at least six months by medical chart review

          2. age 18 years or older

          3. African-American or Latino/Hispanic race/ethnicity

          4. CD4 &lt; 500

          5. enrolled as a patient at PKC/CCC (that is, has been seen a provider at least once in
             the clinic in the past year)

          6. medically eligible for HAART by DHHS criteria for at least three months by provider
             report

          7. does not have any condition that in the opinion of the primary care provider would
             interfere with provision of informed consent or make it unsafe to participate in this
             study

          8. has never taken HAART in his/her life OR has taken HAART in the past but on fewer than
             60 days in the past 6 months and not at all in the past 30 days

          9. willing to be randomly assigned to an intervention arm

         10. able to conduct research activities in English

        Inclusion criteria for peer-recruited cohort

          1. HIV-infected for at least six months - with medical confirmation

          2. age 18 years or older

          3. African-American or Latino/Hispanic race/ethnicity

          4. CD4 &lt; 500 by self report or medical chart review if possible

          5. has never taken HAART in his/her life OR has taken HAART in the past but on fewer than
             60 days in the past 6 months and not at all in the past 30 days by self report

          6. willing to be randomly assigned to an intervention arm

          7. able to conduct research activities in English
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York University College of Nursing</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10003</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 11, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 13, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 6, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 6, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 7, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>New York University</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Marya Gwadz</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Senior Research Scientist</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>disparities</keyword>
  <keyword>antiretroviral</keyword>
  <keyword>HIV</keyword>
  <keyword>barriers</keyword>
  <keyword>access</keyword>
  <keyword>delay</keyword>
  <keyword>decline</keyword>
  <keyword>discontinue</keyword>
  <keyword>African American</keyword>
  <keyword>Black</keyword>
  <keyword>Latino</keyword>
  <keyword>Hispanic</keyword>
  <keyword>care continuum</keyword>
  <keyword>Heart to Heart Behavioral intervention</keyword>
  <keyword>Treatment as Usual</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

