<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02087696</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FER-TOC-2013-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2013-004051-20</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02087696</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Uncontrolled Study to Evaluate Efficacy of Tocilizumab in Patients With Moderate or Severe Rheumatoid Arthritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>Uncontrolled Study to Evaluate Efficacy of Tocilizumab in Patients With Moderate or Severe Rheumatoid Arthritis and Candidates With a Biological Monotherapy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Spanish Foundation of Rheumatology</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Roche Farma, S.A</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Spanish Foundation of Rheumatology</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this project is to evaluate the efficacy of Tocilizumab (TCZ) given as
      monotherapy in patients with active rheumatoid arthritis (RA) according to EULAR response at
      24 weeks after treatment initiation.

      The study design is an intervention study, uncontrolled, multicenter, prospective, 32-weeks,
      two cohorts of patients with poor compliance or with any contraindication or intolerance to
      methotrexate.

      One cohort naive to previous biological therapy and the other one treated previously with a
      biological treatment.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Unknown status</overall_status>
  <last_known_status>Recruiting</last_known_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 4</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients achieving good or moderate European League Against Rheumatism (EULAR) response.</measure>
    <time_frame>At 24 weeks of treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy of Tocilizumab monotherapy administered in patients with active rheumatoid arthritis, in terms of percentage of patients achieving good or moderate European League Against Rheumatism (EULAR) response. To be classified as a good response, patients must have a clinically significant change (&gt; 1.2) in DAS28 index as well as achieving low disease activity. Moderate answer assumes DAS28 index decreases between 0.6 and 1,2, long as it reaches low or moderate disease activity (DAS28 ≤ 5.1), or clinically significant (&gt; 1.2) in the DAS28 in patients with a moderate or high activity (DAS28&gt; 3.2) is achieved.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the mean of DAS28 index.</measure>
    <time_frame>Between baseline and week 24.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy of Tocilizumab monotherapy administered in patients with active rheumatoid arthritis, in terms of Disease Activity Score 28 (DAS28) change by the response EULAR criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the mean of Simplex Disease Activity Index (SDAI), Clinical Disease Activity Index (CDAI).</measure>
    <time_frame>At 24 weeks of treatment.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the activity of rheumatoid arthritis by the Simplex Disease Activity Index (SDAI), Clinical Disease Activity Index (CDAI) using the mean change in these index.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients complying American College of Rheumatology (ACR) criteria (ACR20, ACR50 and ACR70).</measure>
    <time_frame>At 24 weeks of treatment</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy by the American College of Rheumatology (ACR) criteria.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the mean of DAS28 index into several subgroups.</measure>
    <time_frame>between baseline and week 24</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the efficacy in patients with active rheumatoid arthritis treated with Tocilizumab monotherapy by the change in DAS28 index between baseline and week 24 in the following subgroups:
Baseline DAS28: greater than 3.2 and less than 5.1 Baseline DAS28: greater than or equal to 5.1 Cohort A: Patients who have never been treated with biological therapy. Cohort B: Patients who have been previously treated with biological therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Percentage of patients with a DAS28 index less than or equal to 3.2</measure>
    <time_frame>At week 24 of treatment.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of non-serious, serious or unexpected adverse events.</measure>
    <time_frame>At the end of study (32 weeks).</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the safety of Tocilizumab monotherapy during the study period.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes in the mean of Health-Related Quality of Life (HRQOL) index into several subgroups.</measure>
    <time_frame>between baseline and week 24.</time_frame>
    <description>To evaluate the Health-Related Quality of Life (HRQOL) of patients with rheumatoid arthritis treated with Tocilizumab monotherapy in the following subgroups:
Baseline DAS28: greater than 3.2 and less than 5.1 Baseline DAS28: greater than or equal to 5.1 Cohort A: Patients who have never been treated with biological therapy. Cohort B: Patients who have been previously treated with biological therapy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">122</enrollment>
  <condition>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Naive biological treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Rheumatoid arthritis patients with intolerance or poor compliance or contraindication to methotrexate and who have not received previous biological treatment.
Tocilizumab dose 8mg/kg administered every 4 weeks for 24 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Previous Biological treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Rheumatoid arthritis patients with intolerance or poor compliance or contraindication to methotrexate and who have not received more than two previous biological treatments.
Tocilizumab dose 8mg/kg administered every 4 weeks for 24 weeks</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Tocilizumab</intervention_name>
    <description>Tocilizumab dose 8mg/kg administered every 4 weeks during 24 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Naive biological treatment</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Previous Biological treatment</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>RoActemra</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with ability and willing to provide written informed consent and comply with
             the requirements of the study protocol.

          -  Patients with active moderate or severe rheumatoid arthritis, according to 1987 ACR
             criteria, diagnosed at least 6 months before inclusion.

          -  18 years old or older

          -  DAS28 index greater than 3.2 at baseline.

          -  If patients are receiving corticosteroid the dose will have to be ≤ 10 mg of
             prednisone (or equivalent) and the patient must have been stable for at least one
             month previous to initiating treatment with Tocilizumab (day 1). Patients may have
             been treated with nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drug (NSAIDs) at stable doses during
             the previous month to inclusion.

          -  Patients receiving outpatient treatment.

          -  Women of childbearing potential and men with childbearing potential partners may only
             participate in the study if they use reliable contraception (eg barrier methods [the
             patient or her partner], oral or patch contraceptives, spermicide and barrier method
             or intrauterine device) during the study period and at least 3 months after receiving
             the last dose of Tocilizumab.

          -  In women of childbearing potential the pregnancy test must be negative at the
             screening visit and at baseline.

          -  Patients on methotrexate monotherapy or combined treatment with a biological agent, or
             patients on biological treatment monotherapy, who show or have ever shown intolerance
             or poor compliance or safety issues with methotrexate.

          -  Patients judge to be candidates to biological monotherapy by the researcher, without
             excluding previous use of other disease-modifying antirheumatic drug (DMARDs)
             different to methotrexate.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients with no peripheral venous access.

          -  Patients with previous failure to more than two biological treatments.

          -  Previous treatment with Tocilizumab at any time before the baseline visit.

          -  Treatment with any other agent on research during the four weeks previous to the
             screening visit (or equivalent period to its five half-lives) Considering the longest
             period.

          -  Previous treatment with cell depletion therapies, including experimental treatments or
             approved agents, as for examples: CAMPATH, antiCD4, antiCD5, antiCD3, antiCD19 and
             antiCD20).

          -  Treatment with intravenous gammaglobulin or plasmapheresis in the 6 months previous to
             the baseline visit.

          -  Intra-articular or parenteral corticosteroids within 4 weeks previous to the baseline
             visit.

          -  Immunization with a live / attenuated vaccine in the previous 4 weeks to the baseline
             visit.

          -  Previous treatment with alkylating agents such as chlorambucil, or full lymphoid
             irradiation.

          -  History of severe allergic or anaphylactic reactions to human, humanized or murine,
             monoclonal antibodies.

          -  Evidence of serious uncontrolled concomitant disease: cardiovascular, nervous system,
             lung (including chronic obstructive pulmonary disease), renal, hepatic, endocrine
             (including uncontrolled diabetes mellitus) or gastrointestinal.

          -  History of diverticulitis, diverticulosis requiring treatment with antibiotics, or
             chronic lower gastrointestinal ulcer disease, Crohn's disease, ulcerative colitis or
             any other lower gastrointestinal symptomatic conditions that could predispose to
             perforations.

          -  Known active Infections, or a history of known recurring infections: Mycobacterial,
             fungal, viral or bacterial type (included, but not limited to, tuberculosis, atypical
             mycobacterial disease, hepatitis B and C, herpes zoster, but excluding nail bed fungal
             infections).

          -  Any major episode of infection that required hospitalization or treatment with
             intravenous antibiotics within 4 weeks previous to the screening visit or oral
             antibiotics within 2 weeks previous to the screening visit.

          -  Active tuberculosis requiring treatment in the past year. Latent tuberculosis
             screening will be perform on all patients according to Spanish Society of
             Rheumatology/Spanish Agency for Medicines and Health Products (SER/AEMPS) guidelines
             of the. Patients treated for tuberculosis without recurrence in the past 3 years will
             not be excluded.

          -  Ongoing liver disease as determined by the principal investigator.

          -  Evidence of active malignancy, malignancies diagnosed in the previous 10 years
             (including solid and hematologic tumors, except basal cell carcinoma and squamous cell
             skin or removed and cured in situ cervix carcinoma), or breast cancer diagnosed in the
             previous 20 years.

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding women.

          -  Patients with reproductive potential who are unwilling to use effective contraception.

          -  History of alcoholism, drug abuse or addiction in the previous year to the screening
             visit.

          -  Neuropathies or other painful conditions that may interfere with pain assessment.

          -  Serum creatinine &gt;1,4 mg/dl (124 mol/l) in women and &gt;1.6 mg/dl (141 mol/l) in men.

          -  Alanine aminotransferase or aspartate aminotransferase &gt; 1.5 times the upper limit of
             normal.

          -  Total bilirubin greater than the upper limit of normal.

          -  Platelet count minor than 100 x 10^9/l (100.000/mm3).

          -  Hemoglobin minor than 85 g/L (&lt;8,5 g/dL, 5,3 mmol/L).

          -  Leukocytes minor than 3,0 x 10^9/L (3000/mm3).

          -  Neutrophils, absolute value minor than 2,0 x 10^9/L (2000/mm3).

          -  Lymphocytes, absolute value minor than 0,5 x 10^9 /L (500/mm3).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Sara Marsal Barril, MD; PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Hospital Vall d'Hebron</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>María Auxiliadora Martín, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <phone>0034915767799</phone>
    <phone_ext>273</phone_ext>
    <email>mauxiliadora.martin@ser.es</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Jesús Tomás Sánchez Costa</last_name>
    <phone>003466656 918</phone>
    <email>jesus.sanchez@ser.es</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Araba (Sede Txagorritxu)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vitoria-Gasteiz</city>
        <state>Alava</state>
        <zip>01009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital del la Agencia Valenciana de Salud Vega Baja</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orihuela</city>
        <state>Alicante</state>
        <zip>03314</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>María Isabel Tevar</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitari de Bellvitge</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hospitalet de Llobregat</city>
        <state>Barcelona</state>
        <zip>08907</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Marques de Valdecilla</name>
      <address>
        <city>Santander</city>
        <state>Cantabria</state>
        <zip>39008</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Can Misses</name>
      <address>
        <city>Ibiza</city>
        <state>Islas Baleares</state>
        <zip>07800</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ana Urruticoechea</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitari Son Espases</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mallorca</city>
        <state>Islas Baleares</state>
        <zip>07120</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario de Canarias</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Cristóbal de La Laguna</city>
        <state>Santa Cruz de Tenerife</state>
        <zip>38320</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sagrario Bustabad</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital de Sagunto</name>
      <address>
        <city>Sagunto</city>
        <state>Valencia</state>
        <zip>46520</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Antonio Gracia</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Galdakao-Usansolo</name>
      <address>
        <city>Galdácano</city>
        <state>Vizcaya</state>
        <zip>48960</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitari Vall d´Hebron</name>
      <address>
        <city>Barcelona</city>
        <zip>08035</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Sara Marsal Barril, MD; PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Puerta del Mar</name>
      <address>
        <city>Cádiz</city>
        <zip>11009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Reina Sofía</name>
      <address>
        <city>Córdoba</city>
        <zip>14004</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Eduardo Collantes</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital San Cecilio</name>
      <address>
        <city>Granada</city>
        <zip>18012</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Enrique Raya</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario de Guadalajara</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guadalajara</city>
        <zip>19002</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Complejo hospitalario Universitario de A Coruña</name>
      <address>
        <city>La Coruña</city>
        <zip>15006</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Francisco Blanco</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Complejo Asistencial Universitario de León</name>
      <address>
        <city>León</city>
        <zip>24080</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Active, not recruiting</status>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario de La Princesa</name>
      <address>
        <city>Madrid</city>
        <zip>28006</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Rosario García de Vicuña</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Civil</name>
      <address>
        <city>Málaga</city>
        <zip>29009</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>María Ángeles Belmonte, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Clínico Universitario de Valencia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46010</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Pilar Trenor</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Universitario Dr. Peset</name>
      <address>
        <city>Valencia</city>
        <zip>46017</zip>
        <country>Spain</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Juan José Alegre</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Spain</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carmona L, Villaverde V, Hernández-García C, Ballina J, Gabriel R, Laffon A; EPISER Study Group. The prevalence of rheumatoid arthritis in the general population of Spain. Rheumatology (Oxford). 2002 Jan;41(1):88-95.</citation>
    <PMID>11792885</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lajas C, Abasolo L, Bellajdel B, Hernández-García C, Carmona L, Vargas E, Lázaro P, Jover JA. Costs and predictors of costs in rheumatoid arthritis: a prevalence-based study. Arthritis Rheum. 2003 Feb 15;49(1):64-70.</citation>
    <PMID>12579595</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carmona L, Ballina J, Gabriel R, Laffon A; EPISER Study Group. The burden of musculoskeletal diseases in the general population of Spain: results from a national survey. Ann Rheum Dis. 2001 Nov;60(11):1040-5.</citation>
    <PMID>11602475</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Smolen JS, Landewé R, Breedveld FC, Dougados M, Emery P, Gaujoux-Viala C, Gorter S, Knevel R, Nam J, Schoels M, Aletaha D, Buch M, Gossec L, Huizinga T, Bijlsma JW, Burmester G, Combe B, Cutolo M, Gabay C, Gomez-Reino J, Kouloumas M, Kvien TK, Martin-Mola E, McInnes I, Pavelka K, van Riel P, Scholte M, Scott DL, Sokka T, Valesini G, van Vollenhoven R, Winthrop KL, Wong J, Zink A, van der Heijde D. EULAR recommendations for the management of rheumatoid arthritis with synthetic and biological disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs. Ann Rheum Dis. 2010 Jun;69(6):964-75. doi: 10.1136/ard.2009.126532. Epub 2010 May 5. Review. Erratum in: Ann Rheum Dis. 2011 Aug;70(8):1519.</citation>
    <PMID>20444750</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Knevel R, Schoels M, Huizinga TW, Aletaha D, Burmester GR, Combe B, Landewé RB, Smolen JS, Sokka T, van der Heijde DM. Current evidence for a strategic approach to the management of rheumatoid arthritis with disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs: a systematic literature review informing the EULAR recommendations for the management of rheumatoid arthritis. Ann Rheum Dis. 2010 Jun;69(6):987-94. doi: 10.1136/ard.2009.126748. Epub 2010 May 6. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>20448280</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Eberhardt K, Fex E. Clinical course and remission rate in patients with early rheumatoid arthritis: relationship to outcome after 5 years. Br J Rheumatol. 1998 Dec;37(12):1324-9.</citation>
    <PMID>9973158</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Goekoop-Ruiterman YP, de Vries-Bouwstra JK, Allaart CF, van Zeben D, Kerstens PJ, Hazes JM, Zwinderman AH, Ronday HK, Han KH, Westedt ML, Gerards AH, van Groenendael JH, Lems WF, van Krugten MV, Breedveld FC, Dijkmans BA. Clinical and radiographic outcomes of four different treatment strategies in patients with early rheumatoid arthritis (the BeSt study): a randomized, controlled trial. Arthritis Rheum. 2005 Nov;52(11):3381-90.</citation>
    <PMID>16258899</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aletaha D, Stamm T, Kapral T, Eberl G, Grisar J, Machold KP, Smolen JS. Survival and effectiveness of leflunomide compared with methotrexate and sulfasalazine in rheumatoid arthritis: a matched observational study. Ann Rheum Dis. 2003 Oct;62(10):944-51.</citation>
    <PMID>12972472</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>De La Mata J, Blanco FJ, Gómez-Reino JJ. Survival analysis of disease modifying antirheumatic drugs in Spanish rheumatoid arthritis patients. Ann Rheum Dis. 1995 Nov;54(11):881-5.</citation>
    <PMID>7492236</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Galindo-Rodriguez G, Aviña-Zubieta JA, Russell AS, Suarez-Almazor ME. Disappointing longterm results with disease modifying antirheumatic drugs. A practice based study. J Rheumatol. 1999 Nov;26(11):2337-43.</citation>
    <PMID>10555887</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Grove ML, Hassell AB, Hay EM, Shadforth MF. Adverse reactions to disease-modifying anti-rheumatic drugs in clinical practice. QJM. 2001 Jun;94(6):309-19.</citation>
    <PMID>11391029</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Fitzpatrick R, Scott DG, Keary I. Cost-minimisation analysis of subcutaneous methotrexate versus biologic therapy for the treatment of patients with rheumatoid arthritis who have had an insufficient response or intolerance to oral methotrexate. Clin Rheumatol. 2013 Nov;32(11):1605-12. doi: 10.1007/s10067-013-2318-z. Epub 2013 Jul 9.</citation>
    <PMID>23835658</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>DiMatteo MR. Variations in patients' adherence to medical recommendations: a quantitative review of 50 years of research. Med Care. 2004 Mar;42(3):200-9.</citation>
    <PMID>15076819</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>van den Bemt BJ, Zwikker HE, van den Ende CH. Medication adherence in patients with rheumatoid arthritis: a critical appraisal of the existing literature. Expert Rev Clin Immunol. 2012 May;8(4):337-51. doi: 10.1586/eci.12.23. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>22607180</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Waimann CA, Marengo MF, de Achaval S, Cox VL, Garcia-Gonzalez A, Reveille JD, Richardson MN, Suarez-Almazor ME. Electronic monitoring of oral therapies in ethnically diverse and economically disadvantaged patients with rheumatoid arthritis: consequences of low adherence. Arthritis Rheum. 2013 Jun;65(6):1421-9. doi: 10.1002/art.37917.</citation>
    <PMID>23728826</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morand EF, McCloud PI, Littlejohn GO. Life table analysis of 879 treatment episodes with slow acting antirheumatic drugs in community rheumatology practice. J Rheumatol. 1992 May;19(5):704-8. Erratum in: J Rheumatol 1992 Dec;19(12):1998.</citation>
    <PMID>1613698</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Askling J, Fored CM, Brandt L, Baecklund E, Bertilsson L, Feltelius N, Cöster L, Geborek P, Jacobsson LT, Lindblad S, Lysholm J, Rantapää-Dahlqvist S, Saxne T, van Vollenhoven RF, Klareskog L. Time-dependent increase in risk of hospitalisation with infection among Swedish RA patients treated with TNF antagonists. Ann Rheum Dis. 2007 Oct;66(10):1339-44. Epub 2007 Jan 29. Erratum in: Ann Rheum Dis. 2007 Nov;66(11):1548.</citation>
    <PMID>17261532</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Heiberg MS, Koldingsnes W, Mikkelsen K, Rødevand E, Kaufmann C, Mowinckel P, Kvien TK. The comparative one-year performance of anti-tumor necrosis factor alpha drugs in patients with rheumatoid arthritis, psoriatic arthritis, and ankylosing spondylitis: results from a longitudinal, observational, multicenter study. Arthritis Rheum. 2008 Feb 15;59(2):234-40. doi: 10.1002/art.23333.</citation>
    <PMID>18240258</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lee SJ, Chang H, Yazici Y, Greenberg JD, Kremer JM, Kavanaugh A. Utilization trends of tumor necrosis factor inhibitors among patients with rheumatoid arthritis in a United States observational cohort study. J Rheumatol. 2009 Aug;36(8):1611-7. doi: 10.3899/jrheum.080889. Epub 2009 Apr 15.</citation>
    <PMID>19369454</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Listing J, Strangfeld A, Rau R, Kekow J, Gromnica-Ihle E, Klopsch T, Demary W, Burmester GR, Zink A. Clinical and functional remission: even though biologics are superior to conventional DMARDs overall success rates remain low--results from RABBIT, the German biologics register. Arthritis Res Ther. 2006;8(3):R66. Epub 2006 Apr 5.</citation>
    <PMID>16600016</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Mariette X, Gottenberg JE, Ravaud P, Combe B. Registries in rheumatoid arthritis and autoimmune diseases: data from the French registries. Rheumatology (Oxford). 2011 Jan;50(1):222-9. doi: 10.1093/rheumatology/keq368.</citation>
    <PMID>21148156</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sarzi-Puttini P, Antivalle M, Marchesoni A, Favalli EG, Gorla R, Filippini M, Caporali R, Bobbio-Pallavicini F, Montecucco C, Atzeni F. Efficacy and safety of anti-TNF agents in the Lombardy rheumatoid arthritis network (LORHEN). Reumatismo. 2008 Oct-Dec;60(4):290-5.</citation>
    <PMID>19132154</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Soliman MM, Ashcroft DM, Watson KD, Lunt M, Symmons DP, Hyrich KL; British Society for Rheumatology Biologics Register. Impact of concomitant use of DMARDs on the persistence with anti-TNF therapies in patients with rheumatoid arthritis: results from the British Society for Rheumatology Biologics Register. Ann Rheum Dis. 2011 Apr;70(4):583-9. doi: 10.1136/ard.2010.139774. Epub 2011 Feb 17.</citation>
    <PMID>21330639</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yazici Y, Shi N, John A. Utilization of biologic agents in rheumatoid arthritis in the United States: analysis of prescribing patterns in 16,752 newly diagnosed patients and patients new to biologic therapy. Bull NYU Hosp Jt Dis. 2008;66(2):77-85.</citation>
    <PMID>18537774</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dougados M, Kissel K, Sheeran T, Tak PP, Conaghan PG, Mola EM, Schett G, Amital H, Navarro-Sarabia F, Hou A, Bernasconi C, Huizinga TW. Adding tocilizumab or switching to tocilizumab monotherapy in methotrexate inadequate responders: 24-week symptomatic and structural results of a 2-year randomised controlled strategy trial in rheumatoid arthritis (ACT-RAY). Ann Rheum Dis. 2013 Jan;72(1):43-50. doi: 10.1136/annrheumdis-2011-201282. Epub 2012 May 5.</citation>
    <PMID>22562983</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Jones G, Sebba A, Gu J, Lowenstein MB, Calvo A, Gomez-Reino JJ, Siri DA, Tomsic M, Alecock E, Woodworth T, Genovese MC. Comparison of tocilizumab monotherapy versus methotrexate monotherapy in patients with moderate to severe rheumatoid arthritis: the AMBITION study. Ann Rheum Dis. 2010 Jan;69(1):88-96. doi: 10.1136/ard.2008.105197.</citation>
    <PMID>19297346</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bykerk VP, Ostör AJ, Alvaro-Gracia J, Pavelka K, Ivorra JA, Graninger W, Bensen W, Nurmohamed MT, Krause A, Bernasconi C, Stancati A, Sibilia J. Tocilizumab in patients with active rheumatoid arthritis and inadequate responses to DMARDs and/or TNF inhibitors: a large, open-label study close to clinical practice. Ann Rheum Dis. 2012 Dec;71(12):1950-4. doi: 10.1136/annrheumdis-2011-201087. Epub 2012 May 21.</citation>
    <PMID>22615456</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Emery P, Keystone E, Tony HP, Cantagrel A, van Vollenhoven R, Sanchez A, Alecock E, Lee J, Kremer J. IL-6 receptor inhibition with tocilizumab improves treatment outcomes in patients with rheumatoid arthritis refractory to anti-tumour necrosis factor biologicals: results from a 24-week multicentre randomised placebo-controlled trial. Ann Rheum Dis. 2008 Nov;67(11):1516-23. doi: 10.1136/ard.2008.092932. Epub 2008 Jul 14. Erratum in: Ann Rheum Dis. 2009 Feb;68(2):296.</citation>
    <PMID>18625622</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Lingjaerde O, Ahlfors UG, Bech P, Dencker SJ, Elgen K. The UKU side effect rating scale. A new comprehensive rating scale for psychotropic drugs and a cross-sectional study of side effects in neuroleptic-treated patients. Acta Psychiatr Scand Suppl. 1987;334:1-100.</citation>
    <PMID>2887090</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morisky DE, Green LW, Levine DM. Concurrent and predictive validity of a self-reported measure of medication adherence. Med Care. 1986 Jan;24(1):67-74.</citation>
    <PMID>3945130</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carmona L, Gómez-Reino JJ, Rodríguez-Valverde V, Montero D, Pascual-Gómez E, Mola EM, Carreño L, Figueroa M; BIOBADASER Group. Effectiveness of recommendations to prevent reactivation of latent tuberculosis infection in patients treated with tumor necrosis factor antagonists. Arthritis Rheum. 2005 Jun;52(6):1766-72.</citation>
    <PMID>15934089</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>March 6, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>March 12, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">March 14, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 21, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 21, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 22, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</keyword>
  <keyword>methotrexate</keyword>
  <keyword>intolerance</keyword>
  <keyword>poor compliance</keyword>
  <keyword>contraindication</keyword>
  <keyword>Tocilizumab</keyword>
  <keyword>monotherapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

