<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03389399</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>17-0846.cc</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03389399</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Pulmonary Physiology and Systemic Inflammatory in EO Pulmonary Events With Brigatinib Use in NSCLC</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pulmonary Physiology and Systemic Inflammatory Signature Investigations in Early Onset Pulmonary Events Associated With Brigatinib Use in Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Colorado, Denver</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Takeda Pharmaceuticals International, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Colorado, Denver</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      To estimate the incidence of Early Onset Pulmonary Events (EOPEs), defined as the proportion
      of participants with a peak reduction in DLCO of 20% or greater after commencing brigatinib
      at 90mg QD.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a single-arm study of patients who plan on starting brigatinib 90 mg QD or brigatinib
      90 mg QD x 7 days to brigatinib 180 mg QD. Participants who enroll on this study protocol
      will either be taking brigatinib in the context of an ongoing clinical trial, or as part of
      standard of care treatment as licensed by FDA.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 22, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 30, 2019</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To estimate the incidence of Early Onset Pulmonary Events (EOPEs)</measure>
    <time_frame>8 days</time_frame>
    <description>EOPEs is defined as the proportion of participants with a peak reduction in Diffusion capacity in the Lung of Carbon monoxide (DLCO) of 20% or greater after commencing brigatinib at 90mg once daily QD.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">43</enrollment>
  <condition>Non-Small Cell Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Brigatinib 90 mg QD or brigatinib 90 mg QD x 7 days</arm_group_label>
    <description>This is a single-arm study of patients who plan on starting brigatinib 90 mg QD or brigatinib 90 mg QD x 7 days to brigatinib 180 mg QD. Study procedures include PFTs, 6minute walk test, Modified Borg dyspnea scale (mBDS), and phlebotomy before participants commence brigatinib and on days 2 and 8 of brigatinib treatment. Participants that develop a peak reduction in DLCO of 20% or more from baseline whose DLCO does not return to their baseline level on day 8 may, at the discretion of the investigator, undergo repeated testing on a subsequent time point (e.g., day 15) for serial observation to ensure resolution of EOPE if that is the suspected cause of DLCO reduction.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        This is a prospective observational study. Brigatinib is not administered by this study.
        Instead, participants will receive brigatinib as part of an ongoing thereapeutic clinical
        trial or will be prescribed brigatinib, which is now an FDA-approved drug. Entry criteria
        for this study will focus on those suitable for this observational study. Any
        brigatinib-related safety procedure or follow-up will also be set forth by the FDA label or
        the relevant clinical trial that is administering brigatinib to the participant in this
        study.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Provision to sign and date the consent form, indicating that he or she has been
             informed of all pertinent aspects of the study, including the potential risks, and is
             willingly participating.

          2. Stated willingness and ability to comply with all scheduled visits and study
             procedures, and be available for the duration of the study.

          3. Be a male or female aged ≥ 18.

          4. Must plan on receiving brigatinib at a starting dose of 90 mg QD, regardless of
             whether they are receiving brigatinib as a part of clinical trial (if they meet
             eligibility criteria for given clinical trial) or outside of clinical trial as part of
             standard of care cancer treatment per the FDA license.

          5. Have histologically or cytologically confirmed locally advanced or metastatic NSCLC
             suitable for treatment with brigatinib per either FDA labels, acceptable off label use
             or within brigatinib clinical trials.

          6. Participants must plan on taking Brigatinib as the only systemic cancer treatment.
             This means that participants cannot be receiving other targeted therapies,
             chemotherapies, or immunotherapies while on brigatinib (Exceptions:
             nonimmunosuppressive supportive cancer therapies such as bone targeting agents [e.g.,
             denosumab], and anti-emetics are allowed).

          7. Must have Hemoglobin (Hb) of ≥10 g/dL.

          8. Recovered from clinically relevant toxicities (in the opinion of the investigator)
             related to prior anticancer therapy to National Cancer Institute (NCI) Common
             Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE, v4.03) grade ≤2.

          9. Have Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status ≤2.

         10. Must have clearly documented information of previously received systemic cancer
             treatments including chemotherapy, immunotherapy, small molecule tyrosine-kinase
             inhibitors (incl. ALK-targeted TKI) and stop date of most recent systemic therapy.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Have baseline oxygen supplementation requirement (i.e., resting O2 sats on room air ≥
             90%).

          2. Have history or presence of pulmonary interstitial disease or drug-related pneumonitis
             on CT imaging of chest performed within 28 days prior to starting brigatinib.

          3. Have malabsorption syndrome or other GI illness that could affect oral absorption of
             the study drug in the opinion of the investigator.

          4. Have had a blood transfusion within past 120 days.

          5. Have received any small molecule inhibitors, including crizotinib, within 7 days of
             the first dose of Brigatinib (e.g., If first scheduled dose of brigatinib is on a
             Monday, May 1st, 2017 then last dose of the prior line of small molecule inhibitor
             must have been given BEFORE Monday, April 24, 2017).

          6. Have received cytotoxic chemotherapy, investigational agents, or cytotoxic doses of
             radiation within 14 days of brigatinib, except SRS or stereotactic body radiosurgery
             to anatomic sites not involving lung tissue.

          7. Have received immunotherapy within 28 days of first dose of brigatinib.

          8. Be on corticosteroid within 48 hours prior to first dose of brigatinib.

          9. Have uncontrolled, or active cardiac, pulmonary or hematologic disease that can affect
             interpretation of DLCO, specifically including, but not restricted to: a. Pulmonary
             interstitial disease or drug-related pneumonitis b. Congestive heart failure (CHF)
             within 6 months prior to first dose c. Pulmonary embolism within last 6 months

         10. Have an ongoing or active infection. The requirement for intravenous (IV) antibiotics
             is considered active infection.

         11. Have a known or suspected hypersensitivity to AP26113 or its excipients.

         12. Have any condition or illness that, in the opinion of the investigator, would
             compromise participant safety or interfere with evaluation of the drug study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Camidge Ross, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Terry Ng, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Colorado, Denver</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Paula Fisk</last_name>
    <phone>720-848-0671</phone>
    <email>PAULA.FISK@UCDENVER.EDU</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Colorado Denver</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aurora</city>
        <state>Colorado</state>
        <zip>80045</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Paula Fisk</last_name>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Camidge Ross, MD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Terry Ng</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 27, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 27, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 3, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>March 23, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>March 23, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">March 27, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Brigatinib</keyword>
  <keyword>Early Onset Pulmonary Events</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Lung Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Non-Small-Cell Lung</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

