<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03384316</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>180032</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>18-C-0032</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03384316</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Multi-Targeted Recombinant Ad5 (CEA/MUC1/Brachyury) Based Immunotherapy Vaccine Regimen in People With Advanced Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Multi-Targeted Recombinant Ad5 (CEA/MUC1/Brachyury) Based Immunotherapy Vaccine Regimen in People With Advanced Cancer</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>Yes</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

      ETBX-011, ETBX-061, and ETBX-051 are cancer vaccines. Their goal is to teach the immune
      system to target and kill cancer cells. The vaccines target 3 proteins found in many types of
      cancer. Researchers think targeting all 3 proteins in unison will have the best results.

      Objective:

      To test the safety of combining ETBX-011, ETBX-061, and ETBX-051 and their effects on the
      immune system.

      Eligibility:

      People ages 18 and older with advanced cancer that has not responded to standard therapies

      Design:

      Participants will be screened with:

      Medical history

      Physical exam

      Blood, urine, and heart tests

      Scan: They will lie in a machine that takes pictures of the body.

      Participants will receive the 3 vaccines through 3 shots under the skin every 3 weeks for 3
      doses, then every 8 weeks for up to 1 year. They will have blood and urine tests at each
      vaccine visit. They will have scans and other measurements of their tumor after 9 weeks and
      then at their vaccine visits every 8 weeks.

      Participants will keep a diary of symptoms at the injection site.

      Participants will have a visit 90 days after their final treatment. This will include a
      physical exam and blood and urine tests. If they have any ongoing side effects, they will be
      followed until these end or are not changing.

      After this visit, they will be called every 3 months for the first year, every 6 months for
      the next 2 years, then every 12 months for another 2 years to see how they are doing.

      Participants will have the option to enroll in a long-term follow-up study.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  The overall goal of the current project is to expand our immunotherapeutic approach for
           the treatment of advanced cancer employing a multi-targeted approach.

        -  Therapeutic cancer vaccines targeting overexpressed proteins offer a potential method to
           activate T cells against tumors.

        -  A novel adenovirus based vaccine targeting three (3) human tumor associated antigens
           (TAA), CEA, MUC1, and brachyury, respectively has demonstrated anti-tumor cytolytic T
           cell responses in pre-clinical animal models of cancer.

      Objectives:

      -To determine the overall safety and recommended phase 2 dose of a combination of three
      immunotherapeutic vaccines (ETBX-011/ETBX-061/ETBX-051), when administered subcutaneously
      (SC) to subjects with advanced solid tumors

      Eligibility:

        -  Subjects age 18 and older with cytologically or histologically confirmed locally
           advanced or metastatic solid tumor malignancy who have completed or had disease
           progression on at least one prior line of disease-appropriate therapy or who are not
           candidates for therapy of proven efficacy for their disease.

        -  Subjects may have measurable or non-measurable but evaluable disease. Subjects with
           surgically resected metastatic disease at high risk of relapse are also eligible.

        -  ECOG performance status less than or equal to 1

        -  Adequate organ and bone marrow function

        -  Subjects with active autoimmune diseases requiring systemic treatment and subjects
           requiring systemic steroids (except for physiologic doses for steroid replacement) are
           not allowed

      Design:

        -  This is a Phase I trial in subjects with advanced cancer. A combination of three
           therapeutic vaccines (ETBX-011, ETBX-51, EBX-61) using the same modified Adenovirus
           vector backbone, separately encoding three well-studied tumor-associated antigens will
           be assessed. The vaccine will be tested at a single dose level, and a dose de-escalation
           design (if required). The dose level of each vaccine tested will be 5x1011 VP. This dose
           has been found in prior phase 1 testing of Ad5 [E1-, E2b-]-CEA(6D) (ETBX-011) to be well
           tolerated (with no dose-limiting toxicities (DLTs) or related Serious adverse events
           (SAEs), and optimal for induction of immune responses. Each of the three vaccines will
           be administered subcutaneously (SC) at separate injection sites (proximal limb,
           preferably the thigh), every 3 weeks for 3 doses, then bi-monthly (every 8 week) boosts
           for up to a year.

        -  Up to six patients will be enrolled at Dose Level 1. If less than or equal to l of 6
           patients experience a DLT, initiation of the dose expansion phase will occur. If greater
           than or equal to 2 of 6 experience DLT at Dose Level 1, then dose de-escalation will
           occur. Up to six patients will be enrolled at the lower dose level Dose Level -1
           (1x10^11 VP). If less than or equal to 1 of 6 patients experience a DLT, then the
           maximum tolerated (MTD) will be declared at this dose, and initiation of the dose
           expansion phase will occur. If greater than or equal to 2 of 6 experience DLT at Dose
           Level -1, then a protocol amendment may be written to evaluate a further dose
           de-escalation.

        -  A dose expansion phase of study will be enrolled after the MTD of the combination
           vaccine has been determined. An additional 4 subjects will be enrolled in the dose
           expansion component of the trial, for a total of 10 subjects at the MTD.

        -  The ETBX-011, ETBX-51 and ETBX-61 vaccines will be administered SC every 3 weeks for 3
           doses, and then bi monthly boosts for up to a year. Evaluations including immunological
           assessments will be carried out at baseline, on days of vaccination, and after the last
           vaccination.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 31, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 1, 2020</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">January 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>Yes</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Sequential Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Safety</measure>
    <time_frame>30 days after treatment</time_frame>
    <description>List of adverse event frequency</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recommended phase 2 dose</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years</time_frame>
    <description>Recommended phase 2 dose</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Objective response rate (ORR)</measure>
    <time_frame>At tumor progression</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients whose tumors shrunk after therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease control rate (DCR)</measure>
    <time_frame>6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of patients with confirmed response or SD lasting for at least 6 months</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of response</measure>
    <time_frame>At progression</time_frame>
    <description>Time from the measurement criteria are met for CR or PR until the first date that recurrent or PD</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Progression-free survival (PFS)</measure>
    <time_frame>At progression</time_frame>
    <description>Median amount of time subject survives without disease progression after treatment</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival (OS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Death</time_frame>
    <description>Median amount of time subject survives after therapy</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">32</enrollment>
  <condition>Neoplasms</condition>
  <condition>Prostate Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Breast Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Colon Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>1-Dose De-Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose De-Escalation</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>2-Dose Expansion</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Dose Expansion</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ETBX-051; adenoviral brachyury vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>immunotherapeutic vaccine administered subcutaneously every 3 weeks for 3 doses, and then every 8 weeks for up to a year</description>
    <arm_group_label>1-Dose De-Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2-Dose Expansion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ETBX-061; adenoviral MUC1 vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>immunotherapeutic vaccine administered subcutaneously every 3 weeks for 3 doses, and then every 8 weeks for up to a year</description>
    <arm_group_label>1-Dose De-Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2-Dose Expansion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ETBX-011; adenoviral CEA vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>immunotherapeutic vaccine administered subcutaneously every 3 weeks for 3 doses, and then every 8 weeks for up to a year</description>
    <arm_group_label>1-Dose De-Escalation</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>2-Dose Expansion</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Age greater than or equal to 18 years (male and female).

          -  Ability to understand and provide signed informed consent that fulfills Institutional
             Review Board (IRB)'s guidelines.

          -  Subjects with cytologically or histologically confirmed locally advanced or metastatic
             solid tumor malignancy.

          -  Subjects must have completed or had disease progression on at least one prior line of
             disease-appropriate therapy or not be candidates for therapy of proven efficacy for
             their disease.

          -  Subjects may have measurable or non-measurable but evaluable. Subjects with surgically
             resected locally advanced or metastatic disease at high risk of relapse are also
             eligible.

          -  Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status less than or equal to 1.

          -  Subjects who have received prior CEA, MUC1, and/or Brachyury-targeted immunotherapy
             (vaccine) are eligible for this trial if this treatment was discontinued at least 4
             weeks prior to enrollment.

          -  Resolution of clinically significant side effects of prior chemotherapy, radiotherapy,
             immunotherapy or surgical procedures to NCI CTCAE Grade less than or equal to 1 or
             grade less than or equal to 2 for neuropathy.

               -  Adequate hematologic function at screening, as follows:

               -  Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;= 1 x 10^9/L

               -  Hemoglobin &gt;= 9 g/dL

               -  Platelets &gt;= 75,000/mcL.

          -  Adequate renal and hepatic function at screening, as follows:

               -  Serum creatinine less than or equal to 1.5 x upper limit of normal (ULN) OR
                  creatinine clearance (CrCl) &gt;= 40 mL/min (if using the Cockcroft-Gault formula
                  below):

                    -  Female CrCl = ((140 - age in years) x weight in kg x 0.85) / (72 x serum
                       creatinine in mg/dL)

                    -  Male CrCl = ((140 - age in years) x weight in kg x 1.00)/ 1.00) / (72 x
                       serum creatinine in mg/dL)

               -  Bilirubin less than or equal to 1.5 x ULN OR in subjects with Gilbert s syndrome,
                  a total bilirubin less than or equal to 3.0 x ULN

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate aminotransferase (AST) less than or equal
             to 2.5 x ULN, unless liver metastases are present, then values must be less than or
             equal to 3 x ULN)

          -  The effects of the combination ETBX-011, ETBX-051, ETBX-061 vaccine regimen on the
             developing human fetus are unknown. For this reason, female subjects of childbearing
             potential defined as any female who has experienced menarche and who has not undergone
             surgical sterilization (hysterectomy or bilateral oophorectomy or tubal ligation) or
             who is not postmenopausal (menopause being defined clinically as 12 months of
             amenorrhea in a woman over 45 in the absence of other biological or physiological
             causes) and male patients who are not surgically sterile (vasectomy etc.), must agree
             to use acceptable contraceptive methods for the duration of the study and for one
             month after the last vaccination. Acceptable forms of contraception include oral
             contraceptives, intrauterine device, condom or vaginal diaphragm plus spermicidal
             (gel/foam/cream/vaginal suppository), or total abstinence.

          -  Ability to attend required study visits and return for adequate follow up, as required
             by this protocol.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          -  Pregnant and nursing women. Because there is an unknown but potential risk for adverse
             events in nursing infants secondary to treatment of the mother with combination
             ETBX-011, ETBX-051, ETBX-061, breastfeeding should be discontinued if the mother is
             treated with combination ETBX-011, ETBX-051, ETBX-061. These potential risks may also
             apply to other agents used in this study.

          -  There should be a minimum of 4 weeks from any prior investigational drug,
             chemotherapy, immunotherapy, with the exception of hormonal therapy for prostate and
             breast cancers, HER2-directed therapy for HER2+ breast or stomach cancer (3+ IHC or
             FISH+), drugs targeting EGFR, ALK or ROS1 in EGFR,ALK, ROS1-mutated lung cancer,
             respectively, or standard maintenance therapies for any solid tumor under the
             condition that subjects are on these therapies for at least two months before start of
             trial treatment.

          -  There should also be a minimum of 4 weeks from any prior radiotherapy except for
             palliative bone directed therapy.

          -  Known active brain or central nervous system metastasis (less than 1 month out from
             definitive radiotherapy or surgery), or seizures requiring anticonvulsant treatment,
             or clinically significant cerebrovascular accident or transient ischemic attack (&lt;3
             months).

          -  Subjects with active autoimmune disease requiring systemic immunosuppressive treatment
             within the past 4 weeks such as but not restricted to inflammatory bowel disease,
             systemic lupus erythematosus, ankylosing spondylitis, scleroderma, or multiple
             sclerosis. A history of autoimmune disease which is not active nor has required recent
             systemic immunosuppressive therapy (&lt; 4 weeks prior to enrollment) is not reason for
             exclusion.

          -  Subjects with serious intercurrent chronic or acute illness, such as cardiac or
             pulmonary disease, hepatic disease, or other illness considered by the Investigator as
             high risk for investigational drug treatment.

          -  Subjects with clinically significant heart disease, such as congestive heart failure
             (class II, III, or IV defined by the New York Heart Association functional
             classification), history of unstable or poorly controlled angina, or history (&lt; 1
             year) of ventricular arrhythmia.

          -  Subjects with a medical or psychological impediment that would impair the ability of
             the subject to receive therapy per protocol or impact ability to comply with the
             protocol or protocol-required visits and procedures.

          -  History of second malignancy within 3 years prior to enrollment except for the
             following: adequately treated non-melanoma skin cancer, cervical carcinoma in situ,
             superficial bladder cancer or other localized malignancy after discussion with the
             medical monitor.

          -  Presence of a known active acute or chronic infection, including human
             immunodeficiency virus (HIV, as determined by enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay
             (ELISA) and confirmed by western blot) and hepatitis B and hepatitis C virus (HBV/HCV,
             as determined by HBsAg and hepatitis C serology).

          -  Subjects on systemic intravenous or oral corticosteroid therapy with the exception of
             physiologic doses of corticosteroids (less than or equal to the equivalent of
             prednisone 10 mg/day) or other immunosuppressives such as azathioprine or cyclosporin
             A are excluded on the basis of potential immune suppression. For these subjects these
             excluded treatments must be discontinued at least 2 weeks prior to enrollment for
             recent short course use (less than or equal to 14 days) or discontinued at least 4
             weeks prior to enrollment for long term use (&gt; 14 days). In addition, the use of
             corticosteroids as premedication for contrast-enhanced studies is allowed prior to
             enrollment and on study.

          -  Subjects with known allergy or hypersensitivity to any component of the
             investigational product will be excluded.

          -  Subjects with acute or chronic skin disorders that will interfere with injection into
             the skin of the extremities or subsequent assessment of potential skin reactions will
             be excluded.

          -  Subjects vaccinated with a live (attenuated) vaccine (e.g., FluMist(R)) or a killed
             (inactivated)/subunit vaccine (e.g., PNEUMOVAX(R), Fluzone(R)) within 28 days or 14
             days, respectively, of the first planned dose of ETBX vaccine.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>100 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Julius Y Strauss, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://clinicalstudies.info.nih.gov/cgi/detail.cgi?B_2018-C-0032.html</url>
    <description>NIH Clinical Center Detailed Web Page</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Balint JP, Gabitzsch ES, Rice A, Latchman Y, Xu Y, Messerschmidt GL, Chaudhry A, Morse MA, Jones FR. Extended evaluation of a phase 1/2 trial on dosing, safety, immunogenicity, and overall survival after immunizations with an advanced-generation Ad5 [E1-, E2b-]-CEA(6D) vaccine in late-stage colorectal cancer. Cancer Immunol Immunother. 2015 Aug;64(8):977-87. doi: 10.1007/s00262-015-1706-4. Epub 2015 May 9.</citation>
    <PMID>25956394</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Morse MA, Chaudhry A, Gabitzsch ES, Hobeika AC, Osada T, Clay TM, Amalfitano A, Burnett BK, Devi GR, Hsu DS, Xu Y, Balcaitis S, Dua R, Nguyen S, Balint JP Jr, Jones FR, Lyerly HK. Novel adenoviral vector induces T-cell responses despite anti-adenoviral neutralizing antibodies in colorectal cancer patients. Cancer Immunol Immunother. 2013 Aug;62(8):1293-301. doi: 10.1007/s00262-013-1400-3. Epub 2013 Apr 30.</citation>
    <PMID>23624851</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gabitzsch ES, Tsang KY, Palena C, David JM, Fantini M, Kwilas A, Rice AE, Latchman Y, Hodge JW, Gulley JL, Madan RA, Heery CR, Balint JP Jr, Jones FR, Schlom J. The generation and analyses of a novel combination of recombinant adenovirus vaccines targeting three tumor antigens as an immunotherapeutic. Oncotarget. 2015 Oct 13;6(31):31344-59. doi: 10.18632/oncotarget.5181.</citation>
    <PMID>26374823</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 3, 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 23, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 26, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 27, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 4, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 4, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 7, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Combination Vaccine</keyword>
  <keyword>Adenoviral</keyword>
  <keyword>ETBX-011</keyword>
  <keyword>ETBX-061</keyword>
  <keyword>ETBX-051</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

