<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03381950</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C12-30</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03381950</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chronic Kidney Disease - Renal Epidemiology and Information Network</brief_title>
  <acronym>CKD-REIN</acronym>
  <official_title>Chronic Kidney Disease - Renal Epidemiology and Information Network: The CKD-REIN Cohort</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Université Paris-Sud</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Agence de La Biomédecine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Arbor Research Collaborative for Health</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Hospital Ambroise Paré Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centre Hospitalier Lyon Sud</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Nancy University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut de Formation et de Recherche sur les Organisations Sanitaires et Sociales</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Biobanque de Picardie</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centre National de Génotypage</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Institut des Maladies Métaboliques et Cardiovasculaires</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Etablissement Français du Sang</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Amiens University Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University Hospital, Bordeaux</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Institut National de la Santé Et de la Recherche Médicale, France</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Preserving kidney function and improving the transition from CKD to End stage renal disease
      (ESRD) is a research and healthcare challenge. The Chronic Kidney Disease-Renal Epidemiology
      and Information Network (CKD-REIN) cohort was established to identify the determinants,
      biomarkers and practice patterns associated with chronic kidney disease outcomes. The study
      includes 3,033 adult patients with moderate to advanced CKD from a representative sample of
      40 nephrology clinics in France with respect to regions and legal status. Patients are
      recruited during a routine visit and followed up for 5 years, before and after starting renal
      replacement therapy. Patient-level clinical, biological, and lifestyle data are collected
      annually, as well as provider-level data on clinical practices, coordinated with the
      International Chronic Kidney Disease Outcomes and Practice Pattern Study (CKDopps). Blood and
      urine samples are stored in a biobank. The overall objective is to develop a research
      platform to address key questions regarding the determinants and biomarkers associated with
      adverse outcomes in CKD and to assess its effective management. It has the following
      hypotheses and specific aims:

        1. to evaluate a large set of social, environmental, bioclinical, and genetic factors, and
           their interactions in relation with CKD outcomes including progression to ESRD,
           mortality, metabolic and vascular complications, and the onset of a number of chronic
           and acute events;

        2. to assess several new biomarkers to predict adverse outcomes of CKD and its
           complications;

        3. to evaluate the associations of provider practices (management of hypertension, anemia,
           nutritional abnormalities, mineral and bone disorder, nutritional status, timing of
           dialysis initiation and transplant wait-listing) with achievement of clinical practice
           guidelines, clinical and patient-reported outcomes (PRO).

        4. to evaluate the associations of health care organization and clinic services (e.g., for
           nutrition, educational programs) with clinical and patient-reported outcomes, and
           achievement of clinical practice guidelines;

        5. to estimate the relative cost-effectiveness of different provider practices and clinic
           services.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      All cohort participants are assessed annually for at least 5 years, until 6 months after the
      start of renal replacement therapy.

      Each year, data are collected from both medical records and patients interview and
      self-administrated questionnaires are asked to report clinical events.

      Interviews and routine biological measurements are repeated annually.

      CKD-REIN is a public-private partnership. It is funded by the Agence Nationale de la
      Recherche through the 2010 'Cohortes-Investissements d'Avenir' programme and by the 2010
      national Programme Hospitalier de Recherche Clinique. CKD-REIN is also supported through
      partnership agreements with Amgen, Baxter, Fresenius Medical Care, GlaxoSmithKline (GSK),
      Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme-Chibret (MSD France), Lilly, Otsuka, and Genzyme a Sanofi company.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2021</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of end-stage renal disease (ESRD)</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Dialysis, transplantation, conservative care management</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mortality</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Specific and all-cause mortality</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of major CKD events including acute kidney injury, cardiovascular and metabolic complications</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of major adverse events including infections, cancer, mineral and bone disease, anemia, nutitional status, hospitalizations</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Prescription drug use</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>For each drug prescription, the trade name, international non-proprietary name, ATC class, unit dose, defined daily dose, pharmaceutical formulation, and administration route are recorded. A linkage with the drug reimbursement files from the health insurance will be also performed.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by the Kidney Disease Quality of Life (KDQOL™) scale. It is a measure of kidney disease-related quality of life that comprises four subscales: Generic core [Physical Component Summary (PCS) and Mental Component Summary (MCS)]; Symptoms/Problems; Burden of Kidney Disease, and Effects of Kidney Disease. Scores of each subscale are calculated, ranged from 0 to 100, with higher scores reflecting better quality of life.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Depression</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by the 10-item Center for Epidemiologic Studies Depression Scale (CESD). It is a screening test for depression and depressive disorder. A total score is reported.The possible range is 0 to 30, with the higher scores indicating more depression symptoms.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cognitive function</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The 30-item minimental status examination (MMSE) is a practical tool for evaluating cognitive status. A total score is reported, ranged from 0 to 30, with the higher scores indicating less cognitive impairment.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Physical Activity</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>The French translation of the Global Physical Activity Questionnaire (Version 2.0) is used to gather information on the time spent in moderate and vigorous physical activity and in sedentary behavior. The GPAQ contains 16 items designed to assess the frequency and duration of physical activity in 3 domains: during work, transportation, and leisure time as well as time spent sitting during a typical week. It distinguishes physical activity duration by min/day and min/week for each physical activity domain, which allows for calculating the energy expenditure scored in metabolic equivalent tasks (METs). According to duration and energy expenditure, physical activity level was classified as low, moderate, and high.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Family relationships</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Assessed by the Family Relationships Index (FRI). the FRI provides a brief measure of family relations by assessing the way people currently perceive and describe their family. The scale consists of 12 items. Each item is coded from 1 to 4. A validation study of this questionnaire is planned.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sleep disorders</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Women's health</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Set of questions regarding the menopause, menstrual cycle and contraception, and past/in progress pregnancies.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost effectiveness of different treatment practices and services</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 5 years</time_frame>
    <description>Several data sources will be used to estimate the cost of different treatment practices and services.
Patient-Level: key resource utilization indicators (e.g., hospitalization, clinic visits, prescription drug use), and procedures for costing these measures.
Clinic-level: The net costs of different treatment practices as well as structural characteristics (such as number of beds of the hospital, number of wards, number of hierarchical levels, for-profit or non for-profit status, teaching or not teaching hospital, spatial organization).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">3033</enrollment>
  <condition>Renal Insufficiency, Chronic</condition>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Serum, plasma and urine samples are collected and stored on all patients at enrollment and
      study end, and in a subsample of 1,200 at 2-year follow-up.
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Patients with CKD Stage 3-5 (eGFR &lt;60 ml/min/1.73m2, not on dialysis or with kidney
        transplant) receiving nephrology care
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  eGFR &lt; 60 ml/min/1.73m2 for at least 1 month

          -  no prior chronic dialysis or transplantation

          -  Written Signed consent form

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Age &lt;18 yrs old,

          -  Pregnant female,

          -  patients who plan to move

          -  Unable to give inform consent,

          -  Decline to participate
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Bénédicte Stengel, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Inserm U1018, UPS-UVSQ, CESP, Renal and Cardiovascular Epidemiology team, Paris, France</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <link>
    <url>https://ckdrein.inserm.fr</url>
    <description>The CKD-REIN Website</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stengel B, Combe C, Jacquelinet C, Briançon S, Fouque D, Laville M, Frimat L, Pascal C, Herpe YE, Deleuze JF, Schanstra J, Pisoni RL, Robinson BM, Massy ZA. The French Chronic Kidney Disease-Renal Epidemiology and Information Network (CKD-REIN) cohort study. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2014 Aug;29(8):1500-7. doi: 10.1093/ndt/gft388. Epub 2013 Sep 24.</citation>
    <PMID>24064325</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Stengel B, Combe C, Jacquelinet C, Briançon S, Fouque D, Laville M, Frimat L, Pascal C, Herpe YÉ, Morel P, Deleuze JF, Schanstra JP, Pisoni RL, Robinson BM, Massy ZA. [The French Chronic Kidney Disease-Renal Epidemiology and Information Network (CKD-REIN) cohort study: To better understand chronic kidney disease]. Nephrol Ther. 2016 Apr;12 Suppl 1:S49-56. doi: 10.1016/j.nephro.2016.01.005. Epub 2016 Mar 11. French.</citation>
    <PMID>26976057</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Affret A, Wagner S, El Fatouhi D, Dow C, Correia E, Niravong M, Clavel-Chapelon F, De Chefdebien J, Fouque D, Stengel B; CKD-REIN study investigators, Boutron-Ruault MC, Fagherazzi G. Validity and reproducibility of a short food frequency questionnaire among patients with chronic kidney disease. BMC Nephrol. 2017 Sep 15;18(1):297. doi: 10.1186/s12882-017-0695-2.</citation>
    <PMID>28915857</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>January 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 11, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 21, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 22, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">January 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>chronic kidney disease</keyword>
  <keyword>prospective cohort study</keyword>
  <keyword>risk profile</keyword>
  <keyword>patient-reported-outcomes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Diseases</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Undecided</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

