<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03382158</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FDAAA</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03382158</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>International PPB Registry for PPB, DICER1 and Associated Conditions</brief_title>
  <official_title>International Pleuropulmonary Blastoma Registry for PPB, DICER1 and Associated Conditions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Children's Hospitals and Clinics of Minnesota</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Washington University School of Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Children's Hospitals and Clinics of Minnesota</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Pleuropulmonary blastoma (PPB) is a rare malignant neoplasm of the lung presenting in early
      childhood. Type I PPB is a purely cystic lesion, Type II is a partially cystic, partially
      solid tumor, Type III is a completely solid tumor. Treatment of children with PPB is at the
      discretion of the treating institution. This study builds off of the 2009 study and will also
      seek to enroll individuals with DICER1-associated conditions, some of whom may present only
      with the DICER1 gene mutation, which will help the Registry understand how these tumors and
      conditions develop, their clinical course and the most effective treatments.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      PPB is a rare cancer of the lung presenting in early childhood, mostly commonly from birth to
      age ~72 months. PPB occurs within the lung or between the lung and the chest wall. There are
      three primary forms of PPB called Types I, II, and III PPB. PPB is related to an underlying
      change/mutation in a gene called DICER1 which impacts gene expression and cell growth. DICER1
      mutations may also lead to the development of other tumors in children and adults.

      The International PPB Registry offers information based on previous data from Registry
      participants and the medical literature and collaborative efforts with international rare
      tumor groups.

      Retrospective central pathology review is required. Therapy decisions remain at the
      discretion of the treating institution.

      Children with Type I PPB require surgery and sometimes chemotherapy. Therapy decisions are
      the responsibility of the treating institution. Surgical guidelines are presented. It is
      unknown whether adjuvant chemotherapy improves cure rates for Type I PPB patients.
      Chemotherapy options include a 22-week regimen: 4 courses of vincristine, actinomycin D and
      cyclophosphamide (VAC) followed by 3 courses of vincristine and actinomycin D (VA).

      Children with Types II and III PPB, require surgery, chemotherapy and sometimes radiation
      therapy. Many children with Types II or III PPB receive a single-arm multi-agent chemotherapy
      neo-adjuvant/adjuvant regimen of IVADo (ifosfamide, vincristine, actinomycin, doxorubicin)
      for 36 weeks. Second and possible 3rd look surgery may be considered for local control.
      Radiation therapy may be considered.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">December 6, 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">December 6, 2026</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">December 6, 2023</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Event-free survival</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <description>The primary endpoint for statistical analysis will be time from start treatment to an event, defined as the occurrence of progression or recurrence of PPB, occurrence of a second malignant neoplasm, or death from any cause that is at least possibly related to the original disease or treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall response to chemotherapy</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will assess overall response to chemotherapy among participants with radiographically measurable tumor following initial surgery or biopsy.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <description>The investigators will assess overall survival and time to death from any cause among participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of life outcomes in individuals diagnosed with PPB.</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <description>Chemotherapy and surgery may have adverse effects on the quality of life outcomes. Multiple factors including treatment, germline DICER1 mutations and familial cancer may impact quality of life for participants.This study will allow the investigators to assess the quality of life outcomes in participants with DICER1-related tumors and will compare outcomes to those with more common childhood cancers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cardiac outcomes in individuals diagnosed with PPB.</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <description>Chemotherapy and surgery may have adverse effects on cardiac outcomes. This study will allow the investigators to assess the cardiac outcomes as measured by ejection fraction and shortening fraction via echocardiogram of participants with DICER1-related tumors, and compare outcomes to those with more common childhood cancers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pulmonary function testing results in individuals diagnosed with PPB</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <description>Chemotherapy and surgery may have adverse effects on pulmonary outcomes. This study will allow the investigators to assess the pulmonary outcome of participants as ascertained by pulmonary function testing (FVC, FEV1/FVC) with DICER1-related tumors, and compare outcomes to those with more common childhood cancers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Incidence of neoplasms in individuals with DICER1-related conditions or germline DICER1 variants. mutation.</measure>
    <time_frame>7 years</time_frame>
    <description>This protocol will include individuals with germline DICER1 mutations and will calculate incidence rates of specific neoplasms in this population</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>4</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">100</enrollment>
  <condition>Pleuropulmonary Blastoma</condition>
  <condition>Sertoli-Leydig Cell Tumor</condition>
  <condition>DICER1 Syndrome</condition>
  <condition>Cystic Nephroma</condition>
  <condition>Wilms Tumor</condition>
  <condition>Pineoblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Renal Sarcoma</condition>
  <condition>Nodular Hyperplasia of Thyroid</condition>
  <condition>Nasal Chondromesenchymal Hamartoma</condition>
  <condition>Ciliary Body Medulloepithelioma</condition>
  <condition>Neuroblastoma</condition>
  <condition>Pituitary Cancer</condition>
  <condition>Embryonal Rhabdomyosarcoma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Type I PPB</arm_group_label>
    <description>Type I PPB is an early manifestation of this malignant disease, cured in some cases by surgery. Surgical guidelines are presented. It is unknown whether adjuvant chemotherapy improves cure rates for individuals with Type I PPB. If the treating physicians select adjuvant chemotherapy treatment, chemotherapy options include a 22-week regimen: 4 courses of vincristine, actinomycin D and cyclophosphamide (VAC) followed by 3 courses of vincristine and actinomycin D (VA). Therapy decisions are the responsibility of the treating institution.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Types II and III PPB</arm_group_label>
    <description>Types II and III PPB are aggressive sarcomas. Surgery and chemotherapy are necessary in all cases. Surgical guidelines are presented. Many children with Types II or III PPB receive a single-arm multi-agent chemotherapy neo-adjuvant/adjuvant regimen of IVADo (ifosfamide, vincristine, actinomycin, doxorubicin) for 36 weeks. Second and possible 3rd look surgery may be considered for local control. Radiation therapy may be considered. Specific therapy decisions are the responsibility of the treating institution.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Type Ir PPB</arm_group_label>
    <description>Type Ir (regressed) PPB is a unique, purely cystic tumor which lacks a primitive cell component. The International PPB Registry for PPB, DICER1 and Associated Conditions will enroll and follow participants with Type Ir PPB, regardless of age.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DICER1 Gene or Cond Assoc with DICER1</arm_group_label>
    <description>PPB and the associated conditions found in PPB families suggest a familial tendency to formation of tumors. The International PPB Registry for PPB, DICER1 and Associated Conditions study will enroll and follow participants who have the DICER1 gene mutations or conditions associated with PPB or DICER1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Tumor tissue, blood, urine, and cerebral spinal fluid (the latter only if a lumbar puncture
      is performed for clinical purposes)
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        1. For those with PPB: PPB primarily affects children so their participation is required.
             The chemotherapy regimens included as guidance have been used in children before, the
             toxicity is acceptable, well known and reported.

          2. For those with DICER1-associated conditions: There's a wide array of conditions
             associated with DICER1, that occur at a variety of ages, from the development of cysts
             in utero, to lung cysts and thyroid disease noted in grandparents.

          3. The Investigators are aware that many individuals with PPB, and with conditions
             associated with DICER1, come from countries outside of the U.S. To not include
             minority groups and non-English speaking groups would severely limit the sample size
             of this study, and may do a disservice to eligible patients and healthcare providers.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Pathology Diagnosis: Individuals with newly-diagnosed PPB Types I, II or III.
             Diagnosis is made by the local pathologist.

             All cases must be submitted for central pathology review. Only centrally-reviewed
             cases confirmed as PPB will be analyzed prospectively.

             Cases in which the initial diagnosis is &quot;suggestive&quot; or &quot;supportive&quot; of PPB, but not
             diagnostic, and in which later resection specimens, including resections following
             chemotherapy, confirm a PPB diagnosis will be included. Patients diagnosed by fine
             needle aspiration biopsy will be included only if a later resection specimen,
             including resection(s) following chemotherapy, is diagnostic of PPB.

          2. Prior Therapy: PPB Type I: All patients are eligible and will be followed in the
             study.

          3. PPB Types II or III: Newly-diagnosed Types II and III PPB patients will be included in
             the Treatment and Biology Registry.

          4. Prior corticosteroid therapy is allowed.

          5. Types II and III PPB patients with PRIOR Type I PPB diagnosis

          6. Individuals with DICER1-related conditions including PPB, Sertoli-Leydig cell tumor,
             gynandroblastoma, cystic nephroma, renal sarcoma and others.

          7. Individuals with the DICER1 gene mutation regardless of whether they have a known
             DICER1-associated condition

          8. Informed consent by patient/ or parent/guardian (also, where appropriate: assent and
             HIPAA consent)

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Kris Ann P Schultz, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Children's Minnesota</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Kris Ann P Schultz, MD</last_name>
    <phone>612-813-7121</phone>
    <email>krisann.schultz@childrensmn.org</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Gretchen M Williams, BS</last_name>
    <phone>612-813-7115</phone>
    <email>gretchen.williams@childrensmn.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Children;s Minnesota</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55404</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Gretchen Williams, BS</last_name>
      <phone>612-813-7115</phone>
      <email>gretchen.williams@childrensmn.org</email>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://PPBregistry.org</url>
    <description>International Pleuropulmonary Blastoma (PPB) Registry web site</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Messinger YH, Stewart DR, Priest JR, Williams GM, Harris AK, Schultz KA, Yang J, Doros L, Rosenberg PS, Hill DA, Dehner LP. Pleuropulmonary blastoma: a report on 350 central pathology-confirmed pleuropulmonary blastoma cases by the International Pleuropulmonary Blastoma Registry. Cancer. 2015 Jan 15;121(2):276-85. doi: 10.1002/cncr.29032. Epub 2014 Sep 10.</citation>
    <PMID>25209242</PMID>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Hill DA, Ivanovich J, Priest JR, Gurnett CA, Dehner LP, Desruisseau D, Jarzembowski JA, Wikenheiser-Brokamp KA, Suarez BK, Whelan AJ, Williams G, Bracamontes D, Messinger Y, Goodfellow PJ. DICER1 mutations in familial pleuropulmonary blastoma. Science. 2009 Aug 21;325(5943):965. doi: 10.1126/science.1174334. Epub 2009 Jun 25.</citation>
    <PMID>19556464</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 11, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 18, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 22, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 22, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>pleuropulmonary blastoma</keyword>
  <keyword>PPB</keyword>
  <keyword>DICER1</keyword>
  <keyword>Sertoli-Leydig cell tumor</keyword>
  <keyword>cystic nephroma</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuroblastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hyperplasia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhabdomyosarcoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Wilms Tumor</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pinealoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pulmonary Blastoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Neuroectodermal Tumors, Primitive</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rhabdomyosarcoma, Embryonal</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hamartoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Leydig Cell Tumor</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Sertoli-Leydig Cell Tumor</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Goiter, Nodular</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Pituitary Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

