<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03384251</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IR.TUMS.SPH.REC.1396.4089</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03384251</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessing an Educational Intervention Program on Knowledge, Attitude and Behaviour Towards Pregnancy Prevention Based on Health Belief Model Amongst Adolescent Girls in Northern Ghana</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessing an Educational Intervention Program on Knowledge, Attitude and Behaviour Towards Pregnancy Prevention Based on Health Belief Model Amongst Adolescent Girls in Northern Ghana: A Clustered Randomized Trial</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tehran University of Medical Sciences</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tehran University of Medical Sciences</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study is designed to assess the impact of an educational intervention program on the
      knowledge, attitude and behaviour towards pregnancy prevention based on Health Belief Model
      amongst adolescent girls in Northern Ghana. It is a randomised clustered controlled trial to
      be conducted on Senior High School students in Northern Ghana The study hypothesises that
      knowledge, attitude and behaviour of adolescents towards pregnancy prevention will differ
      between the groups.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Adolescent pregnancy is a global problem because of its health, social, economic and
      political repercussions on the globe. According to WHO about 16 million girls aged 15 to 19
      and some 1 million girls under 15years give birth every year, mostly in low and middle-income
      countries. Babies born to adolescent mothers face a substantially higher risk of dying than
      those born to women aged 20 to 24. Pregnant adolescents also develop psychological problems
      from social stigma, suffering physical and domestic violence in her attempt to meeting the
      demands of pregnancy and childbearing. Children born to adolescents are at risk of
      malnutrition, low mental and physical development, inappropriate social connection with
      parents and poor education.

      The factors associated with adolescent pregnancies include early marriages, poor social and
      economic support. Curiosity and peer pressure, lack of sexuality education, poor reproductive
      health services and poor attitude of health workers to providing contraceptive services for
      adolescents amongst others.

      Ghana developed a number of policies to improve adolescent development through the provision
      of youth focus friendly health services in the country. However, adolescent pregnancy has not
      declined as expected.

      The Health Belief Model is one of the appropriate health promotion models designed to predict
      preventive health behaviours, and it has enhanced preventive health behaviours in breast
      cancer screening and prevention of risky sexual behaviours in adolescents as well as
      prevention of iron deficiency anaemia. Schools are the best site for providing health
      education and promotion interventions because students spend most of the time in school and
      health promoters have the opportunity of reaching a large number of participants. Students of
      Senior High Schools in Ghana are adolescents and most of them are sexually active and has
      little knowledge about sex education and use of contraceptives. Therefore, providing
      comprehensive sex education to adolescents in schools will increase their knowledge; enhance
      their attitude and behavior towards pregnancy prevention.

      This study, therefore, is intended to assess the impact of an educational intervention
      program on the knowledge, attitude and behavior towards pregnancy prevention based on Health
      Belief Model amongst adolescent girls in Northern Ghana.

      The main objective is to assess the impact of an educational intervention program on
      knowledge, attitude and behavior towards pregnancy prevention based on Health Belief Model
      amongst adolescent girls in Northern Ghana.

      Study design: The study shall be an interventional research using Clustered Randomized
      Controlled Trial to assess the impact of an educational program on the knowledge, attitude
      and behavior of adolescents towards teenage pregnancy using a researcher-structured
      questionnaire based on the Health Belief Model and a validated psychometric &quot;Teen Attitude
      Pregnancy Scale&quot; Intervention: A comprehensive sex education program shall be delivered in
      approximately six (6) sessions comprising of an introductory lesson on susceptibility and
      severity of teenage pregnancy, personal and community values, female reproductive system,
      contraceptives and decision-making. A qualified midwife shall conduct the health education
      program. Teaching and learning materials shall include flip charts, contraceptives, short
      videos, role-play scenarios among others. A practical demonstration, group discussion,
      lectures, role-play and interactive learning methods shall be employed. Attitudinal and
      behavioural intervention strategies shall be adopted for the study based on the Taxonomy of
      Behavior Change Techniques for interventions
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">February 20, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">September 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">July 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>A multi-stage sampling method shall be conducted. A random sampling of six (6) out 12 mixed Senior High Schools in Tamale Metropolis-Northern Ghana would be selected. We shall randomly allocate three (3) schools as the intervention and the other three (3) as control groups respectively. In each school, one class shall be selected at random from each grade in both intervention and control groups.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Knowledge and attitude</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The name of the measuring scale is Teen Pregnancy Prevention Questionnaire. It is designed to measure the knowledge and attitude of adolescents towards pregnancy prevention. It has five constructs( Perceived susceptibility, Perceived severity, Perceived barriers, Perceived Benefits and Self-efficacy) on five Likert scales.
Minimum score and maximum scores for each construct/sub-scale are zero (0) and forty (40) respectively.
A score range of 0-23= inadequate knowledge and poor attitude towards pregnancy prevention, whiles a score range of 24-40 = adequate knowledge and positive attitude towards pregnancy prevention.
A total score shall be computed by summing the sub-scales. the minimum and maximum score for the total score shall be 0 and 200 respectively.
A total score range of 0-119 = inadequate knowledge and poor attitude towards pregnancy prevention A total score range of 120-200 = adequate knowledge and positive attitude towards pregnancy prevention.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Abstinence from sexual intercourse or use of contraceptives</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months and 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The name of the measuring scale is Teen Pregnancy Prevention Questionnaire. It is designed to measure the knowledge and attitude of adolescents towards pregnancy prevention. Incorporated on this scale is a behaviour component, which, has one question on abstinence from sexual intercourse and one question on the use of contraceptives.
Participants self-reporting of abstaining from sexual intercourse or using contraceptives would be scored 10 whiles those self-reporting sexual intercourse and not use contraceptives would be scored 5.
The minimum score is 5 and the maximum score is 10.
A score of 5 = poor behaviour towards pregnancy prevention, whiles a score of 10 = practising positive behaviour towards pregnancy prevention.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">330</enrollment>
  <condition>Adolescent Behavior</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group shall be given a comprehensive sex education in approximately six sessions.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Control group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>No Intervention</arm_group_type>
    <description>This group will not be given any form of education.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>comprehensive sex education</intervention_name>
    <description>A comprehensive sex education program to be delivered in approximately six (6) sessions comprising of an introductory lesson on susceptibility and severity of teenage pregnancy, personal and community values, female reproductive system, contraception and decision-making skills.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Intervention group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Only unmarried adolescent female high school students shall be included in the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Girls who do not want to participate and those who do not fall within the adolescent
             age group as well as married adolescents shall be excluded
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <gender_based>Yes</gender_based>
    <gender_description>Only female adolescents are to participate in this study</gender_description>
    <minimum_age>13 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>19 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ibrahim Yakubu</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tehran University of Medical Sciences</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ibrahim Yakubu</last_name>
    <phone>+233207787877</phone>
    <email>yaib85@gmail.com</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Adadow Yidana, Ph.D</last_name>
    <phone>+233 207436468</phone>
    <email>adadowy@yahoo.com</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Kalpohin Senior High School</name>
      <address>
        <city>Tamale</city>
        <state>Northern Region</state>
        <zip>00233</zip>
        <country>Ghana</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Abraham Akolgo</last_name>
      <phone>00233207296557</phone>
    </contact>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Ghana</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ganchimeg T, Ota E, Morisaki N, Laopaiboon M, Lumbiganon P, Zhang J, Yamdamsuren B, Temmerman M, Say L, Tunçalp Ö, Vogel JP, Souza JP, Mori R; WHO Multicountry Survey on Maternal Newborn Health Research Network. Pregnancy and childbirth outcomes among adolescent mothers: a World Health Organization multicountry study. BJOG. 2014 Mar;121 Suppl 1:40-8. doi: 10.1111/1471-0528.12630.</citation>
    <PMID>24641534</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Aransiola JO, Asa S, Obinjuwa P, Olarewaju O, Ojo OO, Fatusi AO. Teachers' perspectives on sexual and reproductive health interventions for in-school adolescents in Nigeria. Afr J Reprod Health. 2013 Dec;17(4):84-92.</citation>
    <PMID>24558785</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Atuyambe L, Mirembe F, Johansson A, Kirumira EK, Faxelid E. Experiences of pregnant adolescents--voices from Wakiso district, Uganda. Afr Health Sci. 2005 Dec;5(4):304-9.</citation>
    <PMID>16615840</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ahorlu CK, Pfeiffer C, Obrist B. Socio-cultural and economic factors influencing adolescents' resilience against the threat of teenage pregnancy: a cross-sectional survey in Accra, Ghana. Reprod Health. 2015 Dec 23;12:117. doi: 10.1186/s12978-015-0113-9.</citation>
    <PMID>26700638</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Krugu JK, Mevissen FE, Prinsen A, Ruiter RA. Who's that girl? A qualitative analysis of adolescent girls' views on factors associated with teenage pregnancies in Bolgatanga, Ghana. Reprod Health. 2016 Apr 14;13:39. doi: 10.1186/s12978-016-0161-9.</citation>
    <PMID>27080996</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Abdul-Rahman L, Marrone G, Johansson A. Trends in contraceptive use among female adolescents in Ghana. Afr J Reprod Health. 2011 Jun;15(2):45-55.</citation>
    <PMID>22590892</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Adinma JI, Agbai AO, Okeke AO, Okaro JM. Contraception in teenage Nigerian school girls. Adv Contracept. 1999;15(4):283-91.</citation>
    <PMID>11145370</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Somers CL, Johnson SA, Sawilowsky SS. A measure for evaluating the effectiveness of teen pregnancy prevention programs. Psychology in the Schools. 2002;39(3):337-42.</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Yidana A, Ziblim S-D, Azongo TB, Abass YI. Socio-Cultural Determinants of Contraceptives Use Among Adolescents in Northern Ghana. Public Health Research. 2015;5(4):83-9.</citation>
  </reference>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>World Health Organization: Adolescent pregnancy Fact sheet [Internet]. World Health Organization. 2014 [cited September 2014]. Available from: http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs364/en/.</citation>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 16, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 23, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 27, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 27, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 27, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 28, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tehran University of Medical Sciences</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ibrahim Yakubu</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Adolescent pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Teenage pregnancy</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention</keyword>
  <keyword>Ghana</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>The data may be shared on request.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

