<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03388398</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>1R01HD080492-01</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1R01HD080492-01</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03388398</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Population-level Impact of PMTCT Option B+ in Zimbabwe</brief_title>
  <official_title>Evaluation of the Population-level Impact of Prevention of Mother-to-Child HIV Transmission Program Option B+ in Zimbabwe</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, Berkeley</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Centre for Sexual Health and HIV/AIDS Research Zimbabwe (CeSHHAR Zimbabwe)</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Consorcio de Investigación sobre VIH/SIDA/TB (CISIDAT).</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Eunice Kennedy Shriver National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Ministry of Health and Child Welfare, Zimbabwe</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Elizabeth Glaser Pediatric AIDS Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Children's Investment Fund Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, Berkeley</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This study evaluates the impact of Zimbabwe's program for the prevention of mother-to-child
      HIV transmission (PMTCT) on vertical transmission of HIV infection and HIV-free survival
      among infants exposed to HIV. The study will test the hypothesis that the accelerated PMTCT
      program in Zimbabwe will result in fewer new HIV infections in infants and will increase
      infant survival.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The World Health Organization (WHO) recommends that all pregnant women receive antiretroviral
      therapy (ART) during pregnancy and breastfeeding (&quot;Option B&quot;) or ideally throughout their
      lives regardless of clinical stage (&quot;Option B+&quot;). In February 2013, Zimbabwe's Ministry of
      Health and Child Welfare (MoHCW) declared that Zimbabwe would begin implementing Option B+ in
      October of 2013. This impact evaluation utilizes serial population-based, community-level
      surveys to comprehensively assess the prevention of mother-to-child HIV transmission strategy
      (PMTCT) 'Option B+' among mother-infant pairs in Zimbabwe. The investigators will assess the
      population-level impact of Option B+ in Zimbabwe using serial community-based cross-sectional
      serosurveys with data from three time points: 2012 (pre-Option A standard of care), 2014
      (post-Option A / pre-Option B+), and 2017 (post Option B+ implementation) in order to monitor
      population-level trends in MTCT and HIV-free infant survival.

      The investigators will compare outcomes among infants from 2017 to outcomes among
      mother-infant pairs who participated in similar surveys conducted in 2012 and 2014. These
      community-level data, along with in-depth facility survey data, will also allow the
      investigators to examine impact heterogeneity by the extent of integration of PMTCT and ART
      services at the facility. Together with effectiveness data from the serosurveys,
      facility-level resource utilization and cost data will allow assessment of Option B+
      cost-effectiveness. In addition, this study will also include a population-based,
      community-level survey conducted in 2017 to assess retention of mothers in ART services after
      weaning (19-36 months postpartum). These data will allow the investigators to assess
      HIV-infected mothers' retention in care at the time of the survey, when most mothers will
      have stopped breastfeeding
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Enrolling by invitation</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">January 2019</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">May 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Other</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Vertical transmission of HIV infection</measure>
    <time_frame>9-18 months after birth</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of infants born to HIV-infected mothers who were HIV-infected</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>HIV-free survival among infants exposed to HIV</measure>
    <time_frame>9-18 months after birth</time_frame>
    <description>Proportion of infants born to HIV-infected mothers who were alive and HIV-uninfected</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Retention of mothers in antiretroviral therapy services (ART) services after weaning</measure>
    <time_frame>19-36 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>The proportion of HIV-infected mothers who were initiated on ART and who continued ART after weaning</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time between weaning and discontinuation of antiretroviral therapy services (ART) among mothers who did not continue ART after weaning</measure>
    <time_frame>19-36 months postpartum</time_frame>
    <description>Average time between delivery and discontinuation of ART among those mothers who did not continue ART</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heterogeneity of the impact of Option B+ on HIV-free survival among infants 9-18 months of age by the extent of integration of PMTCT and anti-retroviral therapy (ART) services at health facilities</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>HIV-free survival in health facility catchment areas stratified by the extent of integration of PMTCT and ART services at the health facility</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Heterogeneity of the impact of Option B+ on mother-to-child transmission of HIV (MTCT) among infants 9-18 months of age by the extent of integration of PMTCT and anti-retroviral therapy (ART) services at health facilities</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>MTCT in health facility catchment areas stratified by the extent of integration of PMTCT and ART services at the health facility</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-effectiveness of Option B+ compared to the standard of care before Option A</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Facility costing data and HIV-free survival and MTCT in health facility catchment areas in 2012 compared to 2017</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Cost-effectiveness of Option B+ compared to Option A</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Facility costing data and HIV-free survival and MTCT in health facility catchment areas in 2012 compared to 2014</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Variability in health facility accesibility</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Accessibility of health facilities assessed using exit interviews with patients receiving care at health facilities</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Variability in health facility quality of available services</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Quality of available services at health facilities assessed using exit interviews with patients receiving care at health facilities, and clinical vignettes and time and motion studies with healthcare providers at health facilities</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Variability in health facility appropriateness of available services</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline</time_frame>
    <description>Appropriateness of available HIV testing and counseling (HTC), prevention of mother-to-child transmission of HIV (PMTCT) and male circumcision (MC) services assessed using clinical vignettes with healthcare providers at health facilities</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>5</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">30642</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mother-Infant Pairs</arm_group_label>
    <description>Mothers or caregivers (at least 16 years of age) and their infants who are 9 to 18 months of age at the time of their survey.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Mothers or caregivers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Mothers or caregivers (at least 16 years of age) who are 19 to 36 months postpartum at the time of the survey.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Healthcare staff</arm_group_label>
    <description>Healthcare staff (employed staff and volunteers at least 18 years of age) at all participating healthcare facilities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Providers</arm_group_label>
    <description>Health care providers (at least 18 years of age) at select participating healthcare facilities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Patients</arm_group_label>
    <description>Patients (at least 18 years of age) receiving care at select participating healthcare facilities.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      Dried blood spot samples
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        All study participants will be enrolled from 157 health facilities and health facility
        catchment areas in Harare, Mashonaland West, Mashonaland Central, Manicaland, and
        Matabeleland South provinces in Zimbabwe. In Zimbabwe, the catchment area of a health
        facility has a radius of approximately 10 km (allowing for variation due to geography).

        Healthcare staff, providers, and patients will be sampled from health facilities, while
        mother-infant pairs and mothers/caregivers will be sampled from health facility catchment
        areas.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria Mothers-Infant pairs:

          -  Mother or caregiver is 16 years of age or older

          -  Delivered or provides care for an infant (alive or deceased) who is or who would have
             been 9-18 months of age at the time of the survey

          -  Able and willing to provide written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria Mothers-Infant pairs:

          -  Mother or caregiver is younger than 16 years of age

          -  Infant (alive or deceased) is not/would not have been 9-18 months of age at the time
             of the survey

        Inclusion Criteria Mothers/Caregivers:

          -  At least 16 years of age or older

          -  Delivered an infant (alive or deceased) who is or who would have been 19-36 months of
             age at the time of the survey

          -  Able and willing to provide written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria Mothers/Caregivers:

          -  Mother or caregiver is younger than 16 years of age

          -  Infant (alive or deceased) is not/would not have been 19-36 months of age at the time
             of the survey

        Inclusion Criteria Healthcare Staff:

          -  At least 18 years of age or older

          -  Currently providing PMTCT services at one of the 157 selected facilities

          -  Able and willing to provide written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria Healthcare Staff:

          -  Health care staff is younger than 18 years of age

          -  Health care staff is not currently providing PMTCT services at one of the 157 selected
             facilities

        Inclusion Criteria Providers:

          -  At least 18 years of age or older

          -  Currently providing ANC or ART care directly to clients at one of the 20 purposefully
             selected facilities

          -  Splitting time as a provider between one or more of the following HIV services: HIV
             testing and counseling (HTC), prevention of mother-to-child transmission (PMTCT), and
             male circumcision (MC)

          -  Able and willing to provide written informed consent

        Exclusion Criteria Providers:

          -  Provider is younger than 18 years of age

          -  Currently not providing ART care directly to clients at one of the 20 purposefully
             selected facilities

          -  Does not split time as a provider between one or more of the following HIV services:
             HIV testing and counseling (HTC), prevention of mother-to-child HIV transmission
             (PMTCT), and male circumcision (MC)

        Inclusion Criteria Patients:

          -  At least 18 years of age or older

          -  Received HIV testing and counseling (HTC), prevention of mother-to-child HIV
             transmission (PMTCT), or male circumcision (MC) services at one of the 20 purposefully
             selected facilities on the day of the interview

          -  Able and willing to provide verbal consent

        Exclusion Criteria Patients:

          -  Patient is younger than 18 years of age

          -  Did not receive HIV testing and counseling (HTC), prevention of mother-to-child HIV
             transmission (PMTCT), or male circumcision (MC) services at one of the 20 purposefully
             selected facilities on day of interview
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Frances Cowan, MSc, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine, The Centre for Sexual Health and HIV/AIDS Research Zimbabwe</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Nancy Padian, MPH, Ph.D</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, Berkeley</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>May 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 15, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 22, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 3, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 3, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 3, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 4, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mother-to-child transmission of HIV (MTCT)</keyword>
  <keyword>Prevention of mother-to-child HIV transmission (PMTCT)</keyword>
  <keyword>Antiretroviral therapy (ART)</keyword>
  <keyword>Antenatal care (ANC)</keyword>
  <keyword>Pediatric infections</keyword>
  <keyword>Pregnancy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>No</sharing_ipd>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

