<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03388554</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2-103-03-002-2</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03388554</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Effects of tDCS on Auditory Hallucination, Insight, Neurocognitive Function and HRV in Patients With Schizophrenia</brief_title>
  <official_title>To Investigate the Effects of Transcranial Direct Current Stimulation on Auditory Hallucination, Insight, Neurocognitive Function, Heart Rate Variability, Psychosocial Functioning and Quality of Life in Patients With Schizophrenia</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tri-Service General Hospital</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tri-Service General Hospital</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The study aimed to investigate whether transcranial direct current stimulation could modify
      auditory hallucination, insight, neurocognitive function, heart rate variability,
      psychosocial functioning and quality of life in patients with schizophrenia.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Transcranial direct current stimulation (tDCS), a novel, non-invasive and safe
      neuro-modulating technique, has been developed as a new therapeutic option for
      neuropsychiatric disorders. It encompasses the induction of a relatively weak constant
      current flow through the cerebral cortex via scalp electrodes. Dependent on stimulation
      polarity, this results in a modulation of cortical excitability and spontaneous neural
      activity. The technique was established in the 1950s and 1960s primarily in animals. In these
      early studies it was shown that subthreshold DC stimulation increases spontaneous neuronal
      activity if the anode is placed above or within the cortex, while exposure to cathodal
      polarity results in reduced activity. This is caused by a subthreshold membrane
      depolarization by anodal and a hyperpolarization by cathodal stimulation. It was demonstrated
      in humans that the after-effects of tDCS depend on modifications of NMDA receptor-efficacy.
      The after-effects of tDCS are blocked by the NMDA receptor antagonist dextromethorphan, and
      prolonged by the partial NMDA receptor-agonist D-cycloserine. This tDCS polarity-dependent
      alteration of NMDA receptor function seems to be initiated by the respective membrane
      potential shift and probably by the accompanying cortical activity modification,because it is
      prevented by the sodium channel blocker carbamazepine. Intraneuronal calcium concentration
      also contributes, because calcium channel antagonists eliminate the excitability-enhancing
      aftereffects of anodal tDCS. Recently, tDCS has been found to improve psychopathological
      symptoms (auditory hallucination in particular), cognitive deficits and insight of
      schizophrenia and also strengthen cardiac autonomic function in healthy subjects. Further
      replication studies are needed.

      The study aimed to investigate whether transcranial direct current stimulation could modify
      auditory hallucination, insight, neurocognitive function, heart rate variability,
      psychosocial functioning and quality of life in patients with schizophrenia.

      Study design: randomized double-blind, sham-controlled study design.

      Participants: 60 patients having a diagnosis of schizophrenia or schizoaffective with
      refractory auditory verbal hallucinations (defined as the persistence of daily auditory
      verbal hallucinations without remission in spite of antipsychotic medications at an adequate
      dosage for at least 3 months), aged 20-65 years.

      Others: see Arms and Interventions, Eligibility Criteria or Outcome Measures.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">July 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2, 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2, 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Direct current (DC) generated by a DC stimulator (Eldith DC stimulator: www. neuroconn.de/dc-stimulator_plus_en/) was bilaterally delivered through a pair of saline-soaked surface sponge electrodes (35 square centimeter). The anode was placed with the middle of the electrode over a point midway between F3 and FP1 (left dorsolateral prefrontal cortex and left prefrontal cortex). The cathode was located over a point midway between T3 and P3 (left temporo-parietal junction). Stimulation was applied at an intensity of 2 mA for 20 min, twice-daily on 5 consecutive weekdays. The twice daily sessions were separated by at least 3 hours.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
    <masking_description>In sham stimulation, the current was turned on for 30 sec and then ramped down to 0 mA.</masking_description>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline scores of Auditory Hallucination Rating Scale (AHRS) at the timepoint immediately after tDCS, at one month and three months after tDCS.</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months.</time_frame>
    <description>A clinician-administered rating scale to measure the severity of auditory (verbal) hallucination of the patients with schizophrenia spectrum disorder.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline scores of Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) at the timepoint immediately after tDCS, at one month and three months after tDCS.</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months.</time_frame>
    <description>A clinician-administered rating scale to measure the severity of psychopathological symptoms of the patients with schizophrenia spectrum disorder.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline scores at Personal and Social Performance scale (PSP) at the timepoint immediately after tDCS, at one month and three months after tDCS.</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months.</time_frame>
    <description>A clinician-administered rating scale to measure the psychosocial functioning of the patients with schizophrenia spectrum disorder.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline results of Digit span (forward and backward)</measure>
    <time_frame>One month.</time_frame>
    <description>A test to measure the capacity of working memory of the patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline results of Finger tapping test</measure>
    <time_frame>One month.</time_frame>
    <description>A neuropsychological test that examines motor functioning, specifically, motor speed and lateralized coordination.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline results of Continuous Performance (CPT, version 2.0)</measure>
    <time_frame>One month.</time_frame>
    <description>A neuropsychological test that examines the performance of prefrontal-mediated task.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline results of Wisconsin Card Sorting Test (WCST) at the timepoint immediately after tDCS and at one month after tDCS.</measure>
    <time_frame>One month.</time_frame>
    <description>A neuropsychological test of &quot;set-shifting&quot;, i.e. the ability to display flexibility in the face of changing schedules of reinforcement.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline results of Trail Making Test (TMT) at the timepoint immediately after tDCS and at one month after tDCS.</measure>
    <time_frame>One month.</time_frame>
    <description>A neuropsychological test of visual attention and task switching.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline results of Tower of London test at the timepoint immediately after tDCS and at one month after tDCS.</measure>
    <time_frame>One month.</time_frame>
    <description>A neuropsychological test for the assessment of executive functioning specifically to detect deficits in planning, which may occur due to a variety of medical and neuropsychiatric conditions.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline heart rate variability (HRV) at the timepoint immediately after tDCS and at one month after tDCS.</measure>
    <time_frame>One month.</time_frame>
    <description>An index of autonomic functioning.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline scores of the brief version of questionnaire of The World Health Organization Quality of Life (WHOQOL-BREF Taiwan version) at the timepoint immediately after tDCS and at one month after tDCS.</measure>
    <time_frame>One month.</time_frame>
    <description>A self-reported questionnaire to measure quality of life of the patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline scores of self-reported version of the graphic Personal and Social Performance scale (SRG-PSP) at the timepoint immediately after tDCS and at one month after tDCS.</measure>
    <time_frame>One month.</time_frame>
    <description>A self-reported graphic questionnaire to measure psychosocial functioning of the patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline scores of the abbreviated version of the Scale to Assess Unawareness in Mental Disorder in schizophrenia (SUMD) at the timepoint immediately after tDCS, at one month and three months after tDCS.</measure>
    <time_frame>Three months.</time_frame>
    <description>An expert-rating scale based on a patient interview to measure the insight of the patient.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline scores of the Taiwanese version of the Beck Cognitive Insight Scale (BCIS) at the timepoint immediately after tDCS and at one month after tDCS.</measure>
    <time_frame>One month.</time_frame>
    <description>Translated BCIS has two subscales including reflective attitude (R, 9 items, score range 9-36) and certain attitude (C, 6 items, score range 6-24) subscales. The higher score in R subscale indicates higher self-reflectiveness while the higher score in C subscale indicates higher self-certainty. Thus, a composite index (R-C, reflective attitude minus certain attitude, score range 3-30) of the translated BCIS represents the measurement of cogntive insight . The higher score of R-C index indicates higher cognitive insight.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Changes from baseline scores of the Taiwanese version of the Self- Appraisal of Illness Questionnaire (SAIQ) at the timepoint immediately after tDCS and at one month after tDCS.</measure>
    <time_frame>One month.</time_frame>
    <description>This scale is a self-report instrument composed of 17 items on which participants are asked to rate the extent to which they agree with each statement using a four-point Likert scale, ranging from 0, ''do not agree at all'', to 3, ''agree completely'', which varies according to the statement or questions content. SAIQ has three subscales including worry, need for treatment, and presence/outcome of illness subscales. The scores for the three subscales were summed to create a total SAIQ score (range 17-68), which is intended to represent a broad measure of insight. Lower SAIQ total scores indicate less awareness of one's psychiatric illness.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Schizophrenia</condition>
  <condition>Schizoaffective Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Auditory Hallucination, Verbal</condition>
  <condition>Neurocognitive Dysfunction</condition>
  <condition>Autonomic Imbalance</condition>
  <condition>Psychosocial Impairment</condition>
  <condition>Quality of Life</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Direct current (DC) generated by a DC stimulator (Eldith DC stimulator: www. neuroconn.de/dc-stimulator_plus_en/) was bilaterally delivered through a pair of saline-soaked surface sponge electrodes (35 square centimeter). The anode was placed with the middle of the electrode over a point midway between F3 and FP1 (left dorsolateral prefrontal cortex and left prefrontal cortex). The cathode was located over a point midway between T3 and P3 (left temporo-parietal junction). Stimulation was applied at an intensity of 2 mA for 20 min, twice-daily on 5 consecutive weekdays. The twice daily sessions were separated by at least 3 hours. All patients in the active tDCS group were maintained on their antipsychotic medications throughout the study period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Sham tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>In sham stimulation, the current was turned on for 30 sec and then ramped down to 0 mA. All patients in the sham tDCS group were maintained on their antipsychotic medications throughout the study period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>tDCS</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Active tDCS</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Sham tDCS</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - Patients who met DSM-IV-TR criteria for schizophrenia or schizoaffective disorder were
        included in the study. All these patients showed refractory auditory verbal
        hallucinations,which are defined as the persistence of daily auditory verbal hallucinations
        without remission in spite of antipsychotic medications at an adequate dosage for at least
        3 months.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Pregnancy or breastfeeding.

          2. Having epilepsy, severe physical illness, any current psychiatric comorbidity or
             history of substance dependence.

          3. Having contraindications for transcranial electrical/magnetic stimulation.

          4. Having intracranial metal foreign bodies.

          5. Having a history of intracranial neoplasms or surgery, or a history of severe head
             injuries or cerebrovascular diseases.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>20 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hsin-An Chang, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Tri-Service General Hospital, National Defense Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Tri-service general hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Taipei</city>
        <zip>114</zip>
        <country>Taiwan</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Taiwan</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 24, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 24, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">January 3, 2018</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 30, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 1, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Tri-Service General Hospital</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Hsin-An Chang, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Head of Laboratory of Psychophysiology, Department of Psychiatry, Principal Investigator, Attending Psychiatrist, Assistant Professor</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Psychotic Disorders</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Hallucinations</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Cognitive Dysfunction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

