<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT03385512</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>IHS-1608-35689</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT03385512</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>OPEN &amp; ASK: Improving Patient-Centered Communication in Primary Care</brief_title>
  <official_title>Improving Patient-Centered Communication in Primary Care: A Cluster Randomized Controlled Trial of the Comparative Effectiveness of Three Interventions</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of California, San Diego</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Reliant Medical Group</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Palo Alto Medical Foundation</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of California, San Diego</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
    <is_fda_regulated_drug>No</is_fda_regulated_drug>
    <is_fda_regulated_device>No</is_fda_regulated_device>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This large scale multi-center cluster randomized controlled trial (RCT) is designed to assess
      the comparative effectiveness of three interventions in diverse ambulatory care settings and
      patient populations. Findings will help healthcare systems decide which approach to adopt to
      empower patients and enable providers to engage in patient centered communication. The
      specific aims are to:

        1. Engage with patients and healthcare providers who have used the tools in the pilot study
           (ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier NCT02522286) at the Sutter Health Palo Alto Medical
           Foundation (PAMF), as well as new stakeholders at University of California San Diego
           Health System and Meyers Primary Care Institute at University of Massachusetts and
           Reliant Medical Group, to further refine and adapt these patient-centered interventions
           to be integrated into real world primary care clinics.

        2. Conduct a large scale cluster RCT with three arms, to evaluate the comparative
           effectiveness of three interventions: OPEN with in-person SPI training (High Touch),
           OPEN with online SPI training (High Tech), and ASK. Primary outcomes will include
           patient perceptions of how well their PCPs have engaged them in patient centered
           communication. The investigators will also measure patients' confidence in managing
           their health, intention to follow through with care plans, and downstream behaviors in
           following through with care plans, use of services such as phone calls, secure
           messaging, and additional visits.

        3. Identify the strategy that has the most potential for sustained impact and replication
           within and across healthcare systems. The investigators will analyze the fidelity to the
           intervention protocols, including consistency of delivery as intended and the
           time/effort involved in implementing the interventions. The investigators will also
           assess the extent to which the programs become institutionalized.

      The investigators anticipate that this multi-level healthcare system intervention will result
      in significant improvement in: patient satisfaction with how PCP has engaged them in the
      visit, confidence in selfcare; patients' intention to adhere to care plan, and clinical
      indicators. Furthermore, more effective communication would lower health service utilization
      after the visit. The investigators further expect that the intervention will affect
      physicians', medical assistants' and nurses' experience as well as healthcare system leaders'
      intention to implement in routine practice.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">January 23, 2018</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">May 1, 2021</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">August 1, 2020</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <intervention_model_description>Patient and health care team participants and the clinics in which they practice will be randomly assigned to one of three groups for the duration of their participation in the study: 1) OPEN High Tech, 2) OPEN High Touch and 3) ASK. Unit of randomization is clinic. Physicians will be clustered in clinics and patients clustered within physicians.</intervention_model_description>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported experience with care: CollaboRATE</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 7 days of a regularly scheduled appointment (the indexed visit) and 3 months after the indexed visit.</time_frame>
    <description>Responses from CollaboRATE, a validated 3-item, patient-reported measure of shared decision making compared between baseline and intervention patients; immediately after the indexed visit and 3 months after the indexed visit with their PCP for intervention patients; and across interventions for variations. The 3 questions, which will be answered on a scale of o &quot;No effort was made&quot; to 9 &quot;Every effort was made&quot; are:
How much effort was made to help you understand your health issue?
How much effort was made to listen to the things that matter most to you about your health issues? 3. How much effort was made to include what matters most to you in choosing what to do next?</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported experience with care: Doctor Facilitation subscale of the Perceived Involvement in Care Scale</measure>
    <time_frame>Within 7 days of a regularly scheduled appointment (the indexed visit) and 3 months after the indexed visit.</time_frame>
    <description>Responses from this validated 5-item, patient reported measure of their perceptions of how well their physician facilitated their involvement in decision making are compared between baseline and intervention patients; immediately after the indexed visit with their PCP and 3 months after the indexed visit for intervention patients; and across interventions for variations. The 5 questions, which will answered on a scale of 0 &quot;Definitely Disagree&quot; to 9 &quot;Definitely Agree&quot; are:
My doctor asked me whether I agree with his/her decisions
My doctor gave me a complete explanation for my medical symptoms or treatment
My doctor asked me what I believe is causing my medical symptoms
My doctor encouraged me to talk about personal concerns related to my medical symptoms
My doctor encouraged me to give my opinion about my medical treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Action Plan</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be measured within 7 days of the indexed appointment for intervention patients.</time_frame>
    <description>The &quot;Patient Instructions&quot; field of the After Visit Summary that patients receive in paper and/or through their online patient portal after the indexed visit with their provider.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported confidence to adhere to action plan</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be measured within 7 days and again 3 months after the indexed visits for intervention patients.</time_frame>
    <description>Responses from a patient reported measure of their confidence to adhere to their action plan. This will be measured by the question &quot;Overall, how confident are you about your ability to take good care of your health?&quot; using a 5-point Likert scale from 1=not confident at all to 5=Completely confident. This is a question used in the Health Information National Trends Survey (HINTS), a biennial, cross-sectional survey of a nationally-representative sample of American adults, developed and used by the Center for Disease Control and Prevention and National Cancer Institute (https://www.healthypeople.gov/2020/data-source/health-information-national-trends-survey).</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient reported intention to adhere to action plan</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be measured within 7 days and again 3 months after the indexed visits for intervention patients.</time_frame>
    <description>Responses from this patient reported measure of intention to adhere to their action plan. We will examine the psychometric property of these measures and expect that they will enable us to form a factor that measures the construct of intention to adhere to care plans. We call this measure INTENTION.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adherence to action plans</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be measured within 7 days and again 3 months after the indexed visits for intervention patients.</time_frame>
    <description>A patient reported measure that will be adapted from the Medical Outcomes Study (MOS) general adherence survey instrument with help from our study stakeholders.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The Veterans RAND 12-item health survey (VR12)</measure>
    <time_frame>This will be measured within 7 days and again 3 months after the indexed visits for intervention patients.</time_frame>
    <description>A 12-item patient reported health status measure.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Blood pressure</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after indexed visits for intervention patients.</time_frame>
    <description>This will be extracted from the electronic health record and used as a clinical indicator of health outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A1c</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after indexed visits for intervention patients.</time_frame>
    <description>This will be extracted from the electronic health record and used as a clinical indicator of health outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>LDL</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after indexed visits for intervention patients.</time_frame>
    <description>This will be extracted from the electronic health record and used as a clinical indicator of health outcomes.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient-initiated calls</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after indexed visits for intervention patients.</time_frame>
    <description>These will be measured using structured fields in the electronic health record and access log. The investigators will review the charts of the top 5% of telephone callers.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>E-messages</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after indexed visits for intervention patients.</time_frame>
    <description>These will be measured using structured fields in the electronic health record and access log. The investigators will review the charts of the top 5% of e-message senders.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Office visits</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months after indexed visits for intervention patients.</time_frame>
    <description>These will be measured using structured fields in the electronic health record. The investigators will review the charts of the top 5% of office visit generators.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">5565</enrollment>
  <condition>Patient Engagement</condition>
  <condition>Physician's Role</condition>
  <condition>Physician-Patient Relations</condition>
  <condition>Patient Activation</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OPEN High Touch</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this arm will experience the OPEN High Touch intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>OPEN High Tech</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this arm will experience the OPEN High Tech intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>ASK</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants in this arm will experience the ASK intervention.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OPEN High Touch</intervention_name>
    <description>This arm will contain three components: (a) a pre-visit questionnaire delivered through the patient portal of the EHR, asking patients what they most want to discuss with their physician in the upcoming visit; (b) an animated video for patients providing coaching on how to best prepare for their upcoming visits and get the most from the visits; and (c) Standardized Patient Instructor (SPI) providing communication coaching for physicians on how to incorporate what matter most to patients in the visit, with empathy, and clarity.</description>
    <arm_group_label>OPEN High Touch</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>OPEN High Tech</intervention_name>
    <description>The patient components of the intervention will be identical to the patient components of the High Touch arm (i.e., the pre-visit survey and patient coaching video). The difference will be in the PCP training: we will replace the in-person SPI with a mobile app program.</description>
    <arm_group_label>OPEN High Tech</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ASK</intervention_name>
    <description>This arm is intended to activate patients by encouraging them to ask three questions during their primary care visit: (1) What are my options? (2) What are the possible benefits and risks of each option? (3) How likely are the benefits and risks of each option to occur to me? This will involve placing posters with these questions in all exam rooms used by providers in clinics randomized to the ASK arm of the trial.</description>
    <arm_group_label>ASK</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        For patient participants:

          -  Adults 18 years and older,

          -  Have an activated account to the patient portal of the electronic health record

          -  Able to read/write in English or Spanish

          -  Have an appointment with their PCP, who has volunteered to be participate in the
             study, during the data collection period

          -  Willing and able to provide informed consent and complete brief questionnaires online.

        For health care team (primary care providers, nurse and medical assistants) participants:

          -  Employed at one of the participating study clinics

          -  Willing and able to provide informed consent and complete brief questionnaires online.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        For patient participants:

          -  People who don't speak English or Spanish

          -  People who do not have an active My Chart/My Health Online account.

          -  Younger than 18 years old.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ming Tai-Seale, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of California, San Diego</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_contact>
    <last_name>Ming Tai-Seale, PhD, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>858-246-1939</phone>
    <email>mtaiseale@ucsd.edu</email>
  </overall_contact>
  <overall_contact_backup>
    <last_name>Amy Meehan, MPH</last_name>
    <phone>650-853-4758</phone>
    <email>meehana@pamfri.org</email>
  </overall_contact_backup>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Palo Alto Medical Foundation Research Institute</name>
      <address>
        <city>Mountain View</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94040</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Cheryl Stults, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>650-853-2346</phone>
      <email>stultsc@pamfri.org</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Cheryl Stults, PdH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of California San Diego Health System</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Diego</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92093</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Not yet recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Ming Tai-Seale, PhD, MPH</last_name>
      <phone>858-246-1939</phone>
      <email>mtaiseale@ucsd.edu</email>
    </contact>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Ming Tai-Seale, PhD, MPH</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Meyers Primary Care Institute at University of Massachusetts Medical School/Reliant Medical Group</name>
      <address>
        <city>Worcester</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01605</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
    <status>Recruiting</status>
    <contact>
      <last_name>Kathy Mazor, PhD</last_name>
      <phone>508-791-7392</phone>
      <email>Kathy.Mazor@meyersprimary.org</email>
    </contact>
    <contact_backup>
      <last_name>Cassandra Saphirak, MA</last_name>
      <email>Cassandra.Saphirak@meyersprimary.org</email>
    </contact_backup>
    <investigator>
      <last_name>Kathy Mazor, PhD</last_name>
      <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    </investigator>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tai-Seale M, Elwyn G, Wilson CJ, Stults C, Dillon EC, Li M, Chuang J, Meehan A, Frosch DL. Enhancing Shared Decision Making Through Carefully Designed Interventions That Target Patient And Provider Behavior. Health Aff (Millwood). 2016 Apr;35(4):605-12. doi: 10.1377/hlthaff.2015.1398.</citation>
    <PMID>27044959</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Tai-Seale M, Sullivan G, Cheney A, Thomas K, Frosch D. The Language of Engagement: &quot;Aha!&quot; Moments from Engaging Patients and Community Partners in Two Pilot Projects of the Patient-Centered Outcomes Research Institute. Perm J. 2016 spring;20(2):89-92. doi: 10.7812/TPP/15-123. Epub 2016 Feb 22.</citation>
    <PMID>26909777</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dillon EC, Stults CD, Wilson C, Chuang J, Meehan A, Li M, Elwyn G, Frosch DL, Yu E, Tai-Seale M. An evaluation of two interventions to enhance patient-physician communication using the observer OPTION(5) measure of shared decision making. Patient Educ Couns. 2017 Oct;100(10):1910-1917. doi: 10.1016/j.pec.2017.04.020. Epub 2017 May 1.</citation>
    <PMID>28532861</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>February 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 20, 2017</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 20, 2017</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Actual">December 28, 2017</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>February 22, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>February 22, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">February 26, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of California, San Diego</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Ming Tai-Seale</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Professor of Family Medicine and Public Health, and Director of Outcomes Analytics</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Virtual standardized patient coaching</keyword>
  <keyword>Standardized patient instructor coaching</keyword>
  <keyword>Patient centered communication</keyword>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>We will make a complete, cleaned, de-identified copy of the final data set used in conducting the final analyses available within 9 months after the completion of the study. Researchers interested in replicating our methods and study findings will have full access to the study protocol, samples of intervention prototypes, analytic methods and codebook. We will deliver our final protocol, prototypes, toolkit, codebook documents, and instructions regarding how other researchers can access our study documents to PCORI.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

