<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01031433</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999909449</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>09-DA-N449</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01031433</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Assessment of Craving in Nicotine-Dependent Patients With Schizophrenia Using Virtual Reality</brief_title>
  <official_title>Assessment of Craving in Nicotine-Dependent Patients With Schizophrenia Using Virtual Reality</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  The prevalence of cigarette smoking among individuals with schizophrenia is noticeably
           higher than in the general population, and smoking cessation attempts frequently are
           unsuccessful in this population. Little is known about the effects of cigarette/nicotine
           craving in individuals with schizophrenia. Researchers are interested in learning more
           about how craving affects people with schizophrenia and developing new ways to treat
           cravings and improve the effectiveness of smoking cessation therapies and treatments.

        -  In recent years, virtual reality (VR) has been studied to determine whether it can be
           used to induce craving by using life-like cue settings. VR cues involving cigarette use,
           including images of cigarettes and scent cues of tobacco smoke, may be used to elicit
           craving in smokers. Researchers are interested in learning more about how individuals
           with schizophrenia respond to specific VR cues and settings.

      Objectives:

        -  To determine the feasibility of using a contextual real-world paradigm using virtual
           reality involving cigarette smoking in people with schizophrenia.

        -  To examine if virtual reality cues will elicit craving in smokers with schizophrenia.

      Eligibility:

      - Current smokers (five or more cigarettes per day for at least 1 year) between 18 and 45
      years of age who have been diagnosed with schizophrenia/schizoaffective disorder.

      Design:

        -  The study will involve three sessions, with an initial screening visit, a test session,
           and a follow-up session.

        -  Screening visit: Participants will be screened with a medical and psychiatric history,
           and will answer questions about smoking history, current smoking habits and craving
           patterns, and general anxiety levels. This session will also introduce participants to
           the operation and use of the VR equipment. Participants who are comfortable using the VR
           system will return within 2 days for the test session.

        -  Test session: Participants will use the VR equipment to view neutral scenes and scenes
           that are designed to elicit cravings for cigarettes. After viewing each scene,
           participants will answer questions about their overall mood, anxiety levels, and any
           cigarette cravings they may have.

        -  Follow-up session: Participants will return 1 week after the VR session to answer
           questions about mood, anxiety levels, and current smoking habits and craving patterns.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective:

      Nicotine use is high in people with schizophrenia; however, interventions to aid in smoking
      cessation have not been overwhelmingly successful. Craving, particularly situational craving,
      is one reason people relapse. Craving paradigms in people with schizophrenia need to be
      optimized in order to test new treatments on craving measures in this population. Thus, the
      purpose of this study is to determine the feasibility and effects of virtual reality cues on
      craving intensity for smoking in patients with schizophrenia

      Study population:

      We will enroll 25 smokers with a DSM IV diagnosis of schizophrenia with the goal of obtaining
      a total of 16 completers.

      Design:

      This study uses a comparison-controlled, within-subject design. All subjects will undergo a
      baseline assessment and acclimation period and then participate in an experimental condition
      in which four cues will be presented in separate rooms in the VR program. These include two
      smoking cues and two neutral cues in four different rooms. A follow up session for craving
      and symptom assessments will occur one week after the experimental session.

      Outcome Measures:

      During the Cue trials the Cigarette Craving Visual Analogue Scale (CCVAS), a four-item scale,
      and the Tobacco Craving Questionnaire-Short Form (TCQ-SF)will be administered to measure
      cigarette craving during the virtual reality session. At the end of each of the 4 cues
      (neutral, smoking cue with no interaction, smoking cue with interaction, neutral)
      participants will be asked about craving. The CCVAS will be projected into the VR environment
      and participants will respond via hand controller. To assess mood status, the Mood form will
      also be administered at baseline as well as at the end of each of the 4 cues. Before and
      after the experimental session participants will also be rated on the Brief Psychiatric
      Rating Scale (BPRS), Schedule for the Assessment of Negative Symptoms (SANS), side effects,
      and the State-Trait Anxiety Inventory (STAI). The Immersion Questionnaire and Imagery Realism
      Presence Questionnaire (PQ) will be given at the conclusion of the experimental session.
      During the experiment participants will be monitored for physiological reactivity (heart
      rate, blood pressure, and skin conductance response) to cues of smoking as well as neutral
      cues measured. Additionally, subjects will be assessed before and after the experimental
      session
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 28, 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date>July 18, 2012</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>During the Cue trials the Cigarette Craving Visual Analogue Scale (CCVAS) will be administered to measure cigarette craving during the virtual reality session.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">17</enrollment>
  <condition>Nicotine Dependence</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

               1. 18-55 year old males and females

               2. Currently smokes at least 5 cigarettes per day

               3. Current DSM-IV diagnosis of schizophrenia and stable medication regimen

               4. Medically healthy as determined by screening criteria

               5. Urine cotinine level greater than or equal to 100 ng/ml (NicAlert reading greater
                  than or equal to 3)

               6. Agrees to wear a head mounted display (HMD) for up to 45 minutes

               7. Participant able to complete the Evaluation to Sign Consent (ESC) with minimum
                  score of 80 percent on ESC.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

          1. Interest in reducing or quitting tobacco use within the past 3 months

          2. Treatment for tobacco dependence in the past 3 months

          3. Use of nicotine replacement products, bupropion, or varenicline in the past 3 months
             as an aid to quit or reduce smoking.

          4. DSM-IV diagnosis of active alcohol or substance abuse in the past 1 month or
             dependence within the past 6 months

          5. Current use of serotonin reuptake inhibitors or any medication that would interfere
             with the protocol in the opinion of MAI

          6. History of head injury, seizures, or stroke

          7. Pregnant, nursing, or planning to become pregnant during the study

          8. Positive urine toxicology screen for substances other than those used for therapeutic
             purposes: participants who have an initial positive urine toxicology screen for
             substances other than those used for therapeutic purposes will have the opportunity to
             return within two weeks for a second toxicology screen. If at that time the results
             are again positive, the participants will be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stephen J Heishman, Ph.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Maryland at Baltimore/MPRC</name>
      <address>
        <city>Catonsville</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21228</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Andreasen NC. Negative symptoms in schizophrenia. Definition and reliability. Arch Gen Psychiatry. 1982 Jul;39(7):784-8.</citation>
    <PMID>7165477</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bordnick PS, Graap KM, Copp H, Brooks J, Ferrer M, Logue B. Utilizing virtual reality to standardize nicotine craving research: a pilot study. Addict Behav. 2004 Dec;29(9):1889-94.</citation>
    <PMID>15530734</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Carter BL, Tiffany ST. Meta-analysis of cue-reactivity in addiction research. Addiction. 1999 Mar;94(3):327-40.</citation>
    <PMID>10605857</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 18, 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 11, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 11, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 14, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 17, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 17, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 18, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Tobacco Craving</keyword>
  <keyword>Virtual Reality</keyword>
  <keyword>Schizophrenia</keyword>
  <keyword>Smoking</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Schizophrenia</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Tobacco Use Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Nicotine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

