<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01038492</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>Pro00012350</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>155923</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>01344</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01038492</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>p16 Methylation for Smoking Cessation</brief_title>
  <official_title>Testing the Feasibility of Using an Epigenetic Marker, p16, to Promote Smoking Cessation</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Duke University</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Durham VA Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>U.S. Fed</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Cancer and Leukemia Group B</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Duke University</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Smoking cessation is often difficult for smokers to achieve for a variety of reasons
      including: difficulty with nicotine withdrawal, failure to perceive the benefits of smoking
      cessation, and failure to perceive the risks associated with smoking. We argue that the most
      effective biomarkers to affect perceptions of harm, especially for lung cancer, are those
      that signal progression towards disease development Proposed is a pilot study of educating
      smokers about the role of genetics and lung cancer in Durham VA out-patient clinics. The goal
      of this pilot study is to assess the interest in study participation from the VA smoking
      population, as well as to determine the fraction of subjects who will complete the study to
      power a future larger trial. Interested patients will receive a 15 minute educational
      presentation on the function of p16 and its role in development of lung cancer. They will
      then be assessed for airway obstruction by hand-held spirometry followed by review of a
      questionnaire assessing their understanding of the presented information, their concern for
      developing lung cancer, and their desire to quit smoking. All patients will be offered
      smoking cessation assistance at this point. Enrolled patients will then be given 3 sputum
      cups to take home and return with morning sputum samples by mail. Samples will be assessed
      for evidence of p16 methylation and patients will be informed of the results. Follow-up phone
      interviews will be performed at 2 to 4 weeks after patients have received their results by
      mail to assess their understanding of the results, and their desire to stop smoking. A final
      phone interview will occur approximately 3 months after the sputum testing to assess attempts
      to stop smoking as well as the patients continued understanding of their test results. For
      purposes of this pilot, we are interested primarily in the descriptive statistics (e.g.,
      frequencies) associated with the outcome of each objective (e.g., how many expressed
      interest, how many returned the sputum samples).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      In the United States during 2007, ~ 213,380 people were expected to be diagnosed with lung
      cancer, and ~ 160,390 expected to die of the disease. Among those diagnosed with lung cancer,
      79% to 90% are cigarette smokers. Overall, ~21% of adults in the U.S. smoke. The most
      important and cost-effective strategy for the prevention of lung cancer mortality is smoking
      avoidance and cessation. Smoking cessation is often difficult for smokers to achieve for a
      variety of reasons including: difficulty with nicotine withdrawal, failure to perceive the
      benefits of smoking cessation, and failure to perceive the risks associated with smoking. We
      argue that the most effective biomarkers to affect perceptions of harm, especially for lung
      cancer, are those that signal progression towards disease development. Prior to the
      development of lung cancer, there are genetic alterations in the bronchial epithelium. One
      such alteration is the methylation of the promoter region of Rb-p16 (p16) important in
      regulation of the G1-S transition of the cell cycle. Prior studies have shown that presence
      of the promoter methylation of p16 results in a 2-fold increase in risk of developing lung
      cancer in smokers with evidence of airway obstruction.

      Proposed is a pilot study of educating smokers about the role of genetics and lung cancer in
      Durham VA out-patient clinics. The goal of this pilot study is to assess the interest in
      study participation from the VA smoking population, as well as to determine the fraction of
      subjects who will complete the study to power a future larger trial. Interested patients will
      receive a 15 minute educational presentation on the function of p16 and its role in
      development of lung cancer. They will then be assessed for airway obstruction by hand-held
      spirometry followed by review of a questionnaire assessing their understanding of the
      presented information, their concern for developing lung cancer, and their desire to quit
      smoking. All patients will be offered smoking cessation assistance at this point. Enrolled
      patients will then be given 3 sputum cups to take home and return with morning sputum samples
      by mail. Samples will be assessed for evidence of p16 methylation and patients will be
      informed of the results. Follow-up phone interviews will be performed at 2 to 4 weeks after
      patients have received their results by mail to assess their understanding of the results,
      and their desire to stop smoking. A final phone interview will occur approximately 3 months
      after the sputum testing to assess attempts to stop smoking as well as the patients continued
      understanding of their test results. Patients will be compensated a total of $40.00 for
      completing the study. For purposes of this pilot, we are interested primarily in the
      descriptive statistics (e.g., frequencies) associated with the outcome of each objective
      (e.g., how many expressed interest, how many returned the sputum samples).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>April 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">June 2010</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">June 2010</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine patient interest in finding out whether, through the testing of p16 methylation in their sputum, whether they are at increased or average risk for developing cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the percentage of patients who return their sputum for p16 methylation analysis</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the percentage of patients who complete the 1-month phone interview</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the percentage of patients who complete the 3-month interview</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To determine the percentage of patients who have a positive result for p16 methylation in their sputum, indicating they are at higher risk for developing lung cancer</measure>
    <time_frame>3 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">35</enrollment>
  <condition>Tobacco Use Disorder</condition>
  <condition>Smoking Cessation</condition>
  <condition>Lung Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>p16 Methylation in Sputum Testing</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients tested for smoking-related changes in their breathing
shown a presentation on development of lung cancer
complete a questionnaire on items from presentation, desire to have p16 methylation test, views regarding their health and lung cancer, current smoking habits, and demographic detail
given a sputum cup which they are asked to spit into on three consecutive mornings and then return to the lab for processing
a results letter is mailed to them and then followed up with a phone call at one month to discuss the results as well as any changes in their attitudes or smoking habits
patients are called again at three months and asked about any changes in their attitudes or smoking habits</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>p16 Methylation and Lung Cancer Education</intervention_name>
    <description>patients shown a presentation on p16 methylation and the development of lung cancer, asked to complete a questionnaire on items from presentation, desire to have p16 methylation test, views regarding their health and lung cancer, current smoking habits, and demographic details
patients given a sputum cup which they are asked to spit into on three consecutive mornings and then return to the lab for processing
a results letter is mailed to them and then followed up with a phone call at one month to discuss the results as well as any changes in their attitudes or smoking habits
patients are called again at three months and asked about any changes in their attitudes or smoking habits.</description>
    <arm_group_label>p16 Methylation in Sputum Testing</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Lung cancer education</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  current smoker

          -  &gt;30 pack year history

          -  FEV1/FVC&lt;70%

          -  patients in outpatient pulmonary clinics at Durham VAMC and general medicine
             outpatient clinics at Durham VA Hillandale Clinic

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  diagnosis of head, neck, or lung cancer

          -  diagnosis of psychosis or severe cognitive impairment

          -  refusal to sign informed consent

          -  severe speech or hearing impairment
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Scott Shofer, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Durham VA Medical Center/Duke University Medical Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Durham VA Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Durham</city>
        <state>North Carolina</state>
        <zip>27705</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>March 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 23, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 23, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 24, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 26, 2013</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 26, 2013</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 28, 2013</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tobacco Use Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

