<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01035294</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>H-13078</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>1F32AT005048-01A1</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01035294</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Mindfulness-based Intervention for Treatment of Anxiety in ICD (Implantable Cardioverter Defibrillator) Patients</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Mindfulness-based Intervention for Treatment of Anxiety in ICD Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health (NCCIH)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the feasibility and preliminary efficacy of a
      mindfulness-based behavioral intervention combining breathing and other relaxation exercises
      on symptoms of anxiety in patients undergoing the implantation of an implantable cardioverter
      defibrillator. This study will pilot test the feasibility and preliminary efficacy of a
      mindfulness-based intervention intended to improve mindfulness and anxiety levels in ICD
      (Implantable Cardioverter Defibrillators) patients. A randomized controlled study design will
      be used, in which an 8 session phone-delivered mindfulness intervention will be compared to a
      usual care condition among consecutive candidates for ICD procedures. The study will be
      conducted at the Electrophysiology (EPS) Unit at the UMass Memorial Medical Center.
      Assessments will be performed at baseline and at the end of the intervention (9 weeks after
      enrollment).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The Specific Aims of this pilot study are:

      Primary aim:

      To determine the feasibility of a randomized clinical trial of a phone-administered,
      mindfulness-based training program, as measured by recruitment and retention rates, treatment
      adherence and fidelity.

      Secondary aims:

        1. To obtain preliminary estimates of the effect of a phone delivered mindfulness-based
           intervention on mindfulness levels, measured as the difference between baseline and
           post-intervention Five Factors of Mindfulness scores (FFM) in the intervention and in
           the control group at the end of the intervention. Hypothesis: Mindfulness levels will
           improve in the intervention group compared to the control group.

        2. To obtain preliminary estimates of the effect of a phone delivered, mindfulness-based
           intervention on anxiety, measured as the difference between baseline and
           post-intervention Hospital Anxiety and Depression (HAD) anxiety scores in the
           intervention and in the control group at the end of the intervention. Hypothesis:
           Anxiety levels will be reduced in the intervention group, compared to the control group.

        3. To collect preliminary data about the number of arrhythmic episodes/administered shocks
           during the intervention period. Hypothesis: the proportion of patients experiencing
           arrhythmic events/shocks will decrease in the intervention vs. the control group.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2/Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Single (Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Study feasibility</measure>
    <time_frame>post-intervention (9 weeks after enrollment)</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hospital Anxiety and Depression (HAD) anxiety scores</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and post-intervention (9 weeks)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Five Factors of Mindfulness scores (FFM)</measure>
    <time_frame>baseline and post-intervention (9 weeks)</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">46</enrollment>
  <condition>Anxiety Disorder in Conditions Classified Elsewhere</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>mindfulness based intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>usual care (UC)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>mindfulness based intervention (MBI)</intervention_name>
    <description>Eight, phone delivered, individual mindfulness sessions. Each training session will last 30 minutes (20 minutes for intervention + an additional 10 minutes for questions, answers, and for scheduling the next intervention. Patients will also receive instructions to practice at home every day, at least once a day, for at least 15 minutes. An audio CD containing guided mindfulness exercises will be given to the patient at the beginning of the study, to guide them during their home practice. The CD consists of sequences of different mindfulness techniques, consistent with the techniques learned during each session with the instructor. Each patient will record the minutes of mindfulness practice in a diary to be kept daily.</description>
    <arm_group_label>mindfulness based intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>usual care</intervention_name>
    <description>The UC group will be offered the standard care planned by the hospital, which includes the routine care provided by the electrophysiology team and other health care professionals that the patient may see over the course of the ICD experience. All patients receive a number of printed education materials and participate to support meetings for ICD patients four times a year. Being part of the standard care offered at UMass Memorial Medical Center, these meetings are offered to all patients regardless of their assignment (thus including patients assigned to the MBI arm).</description>
    <arm_group_label>usual care (UC)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Age ≥ 21

          2. ICD procedure

          3. Ability to understand and speak English

          4. Access to a telephone

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Inability or unwillingness to give informed consent

          2. Signs of cognitive impairment (Blessed Orientation-Memory-Concentration (BOMS)scores
             &gt;10)

          3. New York Heart Association (NYHA) functional class&gt;III, angina Canadian Cardiovascular
             Society(CCS) III and IV or clinically unstable

          4. Awaiting coronary by-pass or heart transplantation

          5. Co-morbid life threatening condition

          6. Ongoing severe depression or psychosis
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>21 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elena Salmoirago-Blotcher, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UMass Memorial Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Worcester</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>01655</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 20, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 17, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 18, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>January 25, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>January 25, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">January 30, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>University of Massachusetts, Worcester</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Elena Salmoirago-Blotcher</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Principal Investigator</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Anxiety Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

