<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01037361</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>100015</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10-N-0015</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01037361</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Cerebral Activity Related to Primary Motor Stereotypies in Children: An EEG Study.</brief_title>
  <official_title>Cerebral Activity Related to Primary Motor Stereotypies in Children: An EEG Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Motor stereotypies are a movement disorder characterized by involuntary, repetitive, and
           rhythmic movements. These movements have a predictable pattern and seem purposeful, but
           they serve no obvious function, tend to be prolonged, and can be suppressed. Common
           examples of motor stereotypies include hand waving, head nodding, and body rocking.

        -  Researchers are interested in learning more about motor stereotypies. Many children with
           autism and other developmental disorders tend to exhibit these behaviors, but normal
           healthy children and even some adults have demonstrated motor stereotypies under certain
           conditions (including boredom and stress). More research is needed to determine the
           internal causes of and potential successful treatments for these behaviors.

      Objectives:

      - To use electroencephalography (EEG) to study cerebral activity related to stereotypies in
      children.

      Eligibility:

      - Children between 7 and 18 years of age who demonstrate stereotypy movements on a consistent
      basis (at least 10 times a day for at least 4 months).

      Design:

        -  The study will require two visits to the National Institutes of Health Clinical Center.

        -  First visit: Outpatient screening visit to determine the child s eligibility for the
           study, including questionnaires for parents/guardians and a medical assessment of the
           stereotypies.

        -  Second visit: Participating children will spend 1 day in a room at the NIH Clinical
           Center Pediatric Day Hospital. During the visit, participants will wear a portable EEG
           unit to measure brain activity. For the first hour of the visit, researchers will
           perform movement tests to study the brain activity related to normal movements. For the
           rest of the day, participants may play games, watch television or movies, read, or nap,
           while continuing to wear the EEG to monitor brain activity related to the stereotypic
           movements.

        -  Participants will receive a small amount of compensation for their time and
           participation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective

      Motor stereotypy is a common movement disorder observed in children and adolescents but whose
      pathophysiology is unknown. Therefore, our overall objective is to study cerebral activity
      related to stereotypies. First, we want to define whether motor stereotypies are preceded by
      a cortical potential, as it is observed before voluntary movements. We hypothesize that no
      pre-movement potentials will precede the stereotypies. However, if a pre-movement potential
      is observed, our secondary objective is to compare this potential to cortical potentials that
      precede voluntary movements. We also aim to study cortical potentials preceding voluntary
      movements in healthy children and to compare them with the potentials observed in children
      with stereotypies.

      Study population

      12 children presenting with primary motor stereotypies and 12 healthy children.

      Design

      Using 19 scalp electrodes, we will record the patients electroencephalographic (EEG) activity
      for up to 8 hours during one day. The electromyographic (EMG) activity of the muscles
      involved in the stereotypies will be recorded with surface EMG electrodes. Healthy children
      will undergo an EEG for 2 hours. During this EEG recording, they will be asked to perform
      arms movements.

      Outcome measures

      Primary outcomes: latency and amplitude of both evoked and induced activity (cortical
      potentials) related to motor stereotypies will be measured.

      Secondary outcomes: latency and amplitude of evoked and induced activity related to voluntary
      movements will be measured.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2, 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date>June 29, 2012</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Latency and amplitude of evoked (ERPs) and induced (ERD) activity related to motor stereotypies.</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Measures of latency and amplitude of evoked and induced activity related to voluntary movements.</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">17</enrollment>
  <condition>Movement Disorder</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  Population

             12 children presenting with primary motor stereotypies will be recruited as well as 12
             healthy children.

        INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients:

        Children will be eligible to participate if they meet the following criteria:

          -  Are 7 through 18 years old;

          -  Are identified as having complex-motor stereotypies with predominant movements
             consisting of repetitive arm flapping, hand waving, or finger wiggling movements (only
             children presenting with these movements will be included);

          -  Predominant stereotypic movements must have started before six years of age;

          -  Predominant stereotypic movements must have been present for at least four months and
             occur at least 10 times a day;

          -  Dr Harvey Singer must have witnessed movements either in person or via videotape.

          -  The use of medication that does not affect the central nervous system will be allowed
             during the study.

          -  Subjects with the diagnosis of ADHD, obsessive-compulsive disorder, conduct disorder,
             or learning disability can be included.

        Healthy volunteers:

        Children will be eligible to participate if they meet the following criteria:

          -  Are 7 through 18 years old;

          -  Are able to give informed assent.

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        Patients:

        Subjects will be excluded from this study if there is:

          -  Diagnosis of autism, autistic spectrum disorder, Asperger syndrome, Pervasive
             Developmental Disorder NOS, or mental retardation (IQ &lt; 70);

          -  Concurrent significant medical, neurological, or psychiatric condition;

        Use of tranquilizers, psychotropic drugs or medications which could modulate the cortical
        activity, or if subjects have taken these medications during the month prior to their
        screening visit. As a consequence, children under stimulant medications for ADHD will be
        excluded from the study.

        Healthy volunteers:

          -  Abnormal neurological exam, current or past history of neurological disease or
             psychiatric disease. Patients with neurological diseases of the central nervous system
             that impair the motor system or cognitive function will be excluded;

          -  Use of tranquilizers, psychotropic drugs or medications which could modulate the
             cortical activity, or if subjects have taken these medications during the month prior
             to their screening visit.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>7 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>18 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Beth A Belluscio, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center, 9000 Rockville Pike</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20892</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bodfish JW, Symons FJ, Parker DE, Lewis MH. Varieties of repetitive behavior in autism: comparisons to mental retardation. J Autism Dev Disord. 2000 Jun;30(3):237-43.</citation>
    <PMID>11055459</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Castellanos FX, Ritchie GF, Marsh WL, Rapoport JL. DSM-IV stereotypic movement disorder: persistence of stereotypies of infancy in intellectually normal adolescents and adults. J Clin Psychiatry. 1996 Mar;57(3):116-22.</citation>
    <PMID>8617696</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Deecke L. Electrophysiological correlates of movement initiation. Rev Neurol (Paris). 1990;146(10):612-9. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>2263824</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 29, 2012</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 19, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 19, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 23, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 19, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 19, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 22, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Children and Adolescents</keyword>
  <keyword>Motor Control</keyword>
  <keyword>Movement-Related Potential</keyword>
  <keyword>Stereotypic Movement Disorder</keyword>
  <keyword>Electroencephalogram (EEG)</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Movement Disorders</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

