<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01031108</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>114089</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01031108</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Clinical Trial to Assess the Safety of Oral SRT2104 and Its Effects on Vascular Dysfunction in Otherwise Healthy Cigarette Smokers and Subjects With Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase I, Randomized, Placebo-Controlled, Crossover Clinical Trial to Assess the Safety of Oral SRT2104 and Its Effects on Vascular Dysfunction in Otherwise Healthy Cigarette Smokers and Subjects With Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Sirtris, a GSK Company</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The primary purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and tolerability of SRT2104 (2.0
      g administered once daily for 28 days) and to examine the effects of SRT2104 (2.0 g
      administered once daily for 28 days) on reversing vasomotor and fibrinolytic dysfunction in
      both type 2 diabetes mellitus patients and otherwise healthy cigarette smokers in a fed
      state.

      This study will investigate the effects of SRT2104 on the reduction of platelet activation
      markers (platelet-monocyte aggregates), and to evaluate the effects of SRT2104 on platelet
      and monocyte surface markers (P-selectin, CD11b), inflammatory markers (high sensitivity CRP,
      IL-6, SAA, TNF-α and sCD40L), and markers of oxidative stress (urinary and plasma
      F2-isoprostanes and nitrotyrosine).

      Further goals of this study is to characterize the pharmacokinetic profile of SRT2104 after a
      single dose and multiple administrations in both type 2 diabetes mellitus patients and
      otherwise healthy cigarette smokers in a fed state, and to explore the effects of SRT2104 on
      potential biomarkers of activity for glucose control (HbA1c, glycated albumin and
      fructosamine) and/or Sirt1 activation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Single-center, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, crossover, safety, activity, and
      pharmacokinetic (PK) study of 2.0 g of SRT2104 administered orally once daily for 28
      consecutive days to two different populations: type 2 diabetic (T2D) subjects on an existing,
      stable, hypoglycemic regimen and otherwise healthy cigarette smokers (≥ 10cigarettes/day for
      at least 1 year). Approximately 24 subjects with T2D and 24 otherwise healthy cigarette
      smokers, aged 18-60 years, who fulfill the inclusion/exclusion criteria, will be enrolled in
      this study to ensure at least 20 evaluable subjects per population are enrolled. Subjects
      will be evenly stratified and randomized to receive SRT2104 2.0 g/day or placebo once daily
      for 28 days. After 28 days, subjects will cross over to receive the other test article for
      another 28 days of dosing, bringing the total dosing period to 56 days.

      Subjects will sign the informed consent form at the screening visit (to occur within 21 days
      of first dose of test article), and will undergo screening assessments to verify eligibility
      for the study. If eligible and willing to participate, subjects will return to the clinic on
      Days -1 and 1 for safety assessments, hematology and biochemistry measurements, platelet
      monocyte aggregation (PMA) assessment, forearm venous occlusion plethysmography, pulse wave
      analysis (PWA), pulse wave velocity (PWV) and PK sampling. The first dose of test article
      will occur on Day 1 after eligibility has been confirmed. After each 28 day dosing period,
      subjects will return on Day 28 and Day 56 for safety assessments, hematology and biochemistry
      measurements, forearm plethysmography, PWA, PWV, and PK sampling. Subjects will return to the
      clinic on Days 2, 15, 29, 43, and 57 for safety assessments and additional PK sampling.
      Subjects will be asked to complete a study drug diary on a daily basis for compliance and
      adverse event (AE) monitoring (diabetic subjects will be required to monitor and record their
      fasting blood glucose in the diary also). An End of Study visit will occur 14 days following
      the final dose of SRT2104 or placebo on Day 70. A followup safety call will be made to each
      subject 30 days following their final dose of SRT2104 or placebo (Day 86).
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 28, 2010</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 12, 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">October 12, 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Crossover Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Basic Science</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate the safety and tolerability of SRT2104 (2.0 g administered once daily for 28 days) in both type 2 diabetes mellitus patients and otherwise healthy cigarette smokers in a fed state.</measure>
    <time_frame>AEs and clinically significant abnormal laboratory values will be recorded based upon investigator observation and subject reporting through a subject diary. Safety will be monitored by AEs, VS, physical exam, labs and ECGs during the study.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To examine the effects of SRT2104 (2.0 g administered once daily for 28 days) on reversing vasomotor and fibrinolytic dysfunction in both type 2 diabetes mellitus patients and otherwise healthy smokers in a fed state.</measure>
    <time_frame>Forearm venous occlusion plethysmography will be performed on Days -1, 28, and 56 to assess vasomotor and fibrinolytic function. Pulse wave analysis and pulse wave velocity will be measured to assess arterial stiffness on Days -1, 28, and 56.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To investigate the effects of SRT2104 on the reduction of platelet activation markers (platelet-monocyte aggregates).</measure>
    <time_frame>Serum/plasma/urine research sample(s) will be collected on Days 1, 28, and 56 and will be used to measure platelet activation (platelet-monocyte aggregates).</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To evaluate SRT2104 effects on platelet and monocyte surface markers (P-selectin, CD11b), inflammatory markers (high sensitivity CRP, IL-6, SAA, TNF-α and sCD40L), and markers of oxidative stress (urinary and plasma F2-isoprostanes and nitrotyrosine).</measure>
    <time_frame>Serum/plasma/urine research sample(s) will be collected on Days 1, 28, and 56 to evaluate platelet and monocyte surface markers, inflammatory markers, and markers of oxidative stress.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To characterize the pharmacokinetic profile of SRT2104 after a single dose and multiple administrations in both type 2 diabetes mellitus patients and otherwise healthy smokers in a fed state.</measure>
    <time_frame>Plasma samples will be collected on Days 1, 28, and 56 at 0h, 15min, 30min, 1, 2, 3, 4, 8, and 12hrs post-dose. Samples will also be collected 24 and 27 hrs post-dose on Days 2, 29, and 57. Also, pre-dose samples will be collected on Days 15 and 43.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To explore the effects of SRT2104 on potential biomarkers of activity for glucose control (HbA1c, glycated albumin and fructosamine) and/or Sirt1 activation.</measure>
    <time_frame>Serum/plasma/urine research sample(s) will be collected on Days 1, 28, and 56 and will be used to measure potential biomarkers of activity for glucose control.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">38</enrollment>
  <condition>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Type 2 Diabetic Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Type 2 Diabetic Treatment Group will be randomized to receive test material (2.0g SRT2104 or placebo) in the form of 8 capsules per day for 28 days. After 28 days of dosing, subjects will cross over to receive placebo or 2.0g SRT2104 for an additional 28 days. Dosing of SRT2104 or placebo will take place at approximately the same time every morning, approximately 15 minutes following consumption of a standardized morning meal (220 cc of Ensure Plus®). Subjects must wait at least 1-2 hours after dosing before consuming additional calories. Water is permitted ad libitum.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Otherwise Healthy Cigarette Smoking Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The Otherwise Healthy Cigarette Smoking Treatment Group will be randomized to receive test material (2.0g SRT2104 or placebo) in the form of 8 capsules per day for 28 days. After 28 days of dosing, subjects will cross over to receive placebo or 2.0g SRT2104 for an additional 28 days. Dosing of SRT2104 or placebo will take place at approximately the same time every morning, approximately 15 minutes following consumption of a standardized morning meal (220 cc of Ensure Plus®). Subjects must wait at least 1-2 hours after dosing before consuming additional calories. Water is permitted ad libitum.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>For the placebo product, SRT2104 drug substance will be replaced by microcrystalline cellulose (Avicel® PH 105) to match the SRT2104 investigational product.
Eight placebo capsules are stored in a dosing bottle and provided to all participating subjects for oral ingestion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Otherwise Healthy Cigarette Smoking Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Type 2 Diabetic Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>SRT2104</intervention_name>
    <description>SRT2104 investigational product is a size 00 Swedish Orange opaque hard gelatin capsule containing 0.25 g of SRT2104, a new chemical entity which is supplied as a micronized, yellowish/amber powder. Eight SRT2104 capsules are stored in a dosing bottle and provided to all participating subjects for oral ingestion.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Otherwise Healthy Cigarette Smoking Group</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Type 2 Diabetic Group</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        - Ambulatory male and female subjects (of any race) either with type 2 diabetes or
        otherwise healthy cigarette smokers (≥ 10 cigarettes/day for at least 1 year) within the
        age range of 18-70 years (inclusive) at the time of Screening.

          -  If a subject is diabetic, HbA1c at Screening is &lt; 9.0%

          -  If a subject is diabetic, fasting plasma glucose (FPG) ≤ 13.875 mmol/L (≤ 250 mg/dL).

          -  If a subject is diabetic, an official diagnosis of type 2 diabetes must be documented
             for at least 6 months prior to first dose of test article.

          -  If a subject is diabetic, subject must be on an existing, stable, hypoglycemic therapy
             or a stable dietary regimen to control their disease for at least 3 months prior to
             Screening.

        Note: If a subject is a diabetic and a smoker, then they are not eligible for the trial. A
        minimum 5 year non-smoking history is required for all type 2 diabetic subjects to be
        enrolled into the study.

          -  Female subjects of child-bearing potential, willing to use reliable contraception (see
             Section 5.10) for the duration of the study, through to the 30 day safety follow up
             visit (a female of child-bearing potential is defined as any female, regardless of her
             age with functioning ovaries and no documented impairment of oviductal or uterine
             function that would cause sterility. Females with oligomenorrhea or who are
             perimenopausal, and young females who have begun to menstruate are considered to be of
             child-bearing potential)

          -  All male subjects must agree with their partners to use double-barrier birth control
             or abstinence while participating in the study and for 12 weeks following the last
             dose of study drug.

          -  Willingness to provide written informed consent to participate in the study.

          -  Subject may be on concomitant treatments for other conditions, provided the medical
             condition necessitating the treatment and therapy is stable for at least 3 months
             prior to screening and the treatment is not counterindicated by the study protocol.

          -  Subject is not currently on a therapeutic regimen of ACE inhibitors, anti-coagulants,
             anti-platelets, or any other medications or treatments which may influence coagulation
             (with the exception of 81 mg or less of aspirin/acetylsalicylic acid daily).

          -  Body Mass Index (BMI) of 18.5-38 kg/m^2 (inclusive).

          -  Resting supine blood pressure (BP) &lt;160/90 mmHg.

          -  Absence of significant disease (other than type 2 diabetes) or clinically significant
             abnormal laboratory values on the laboratory evaluations, medical history, or physical
             examination during screening; normal end organ function at the discretion of the
             principal investigator.

          -  Negative test result at screening for HIV 1 and 2.

          -  Negative test result at screening for hepatitis B &amp; C virus.

          -  Have a normal 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG) or one with changes considered to be
             clinically insignificant on medical review. QTcB must be &lt; 450 msec for males and
             females. QTcB must be &lt;480 msec in subjects with Bundle Branch Block.

          -  Comprehension of the nature and purpose of the study and compliance with the
             requirements of the entire protocol.

          -  Able to communicate in person and by telephone in a manner that allows all protocol
             procedures to be carried out safety and reliably in the opinion of the investigative
             site staff.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  If diabetic, any major illness in the past 3 months or any significant ongoing chronic
             medical illness not related to diabetes which in the opinion of the principal
             investigator or medical monitor could risk subject safety or interpretation of the
             results.

          -  If an otherwise healthy cigarette smoker, any major illness or injury in the past 3
             months or any significant ongoing chronic medical illness (including diabetes) which
             in the opinion of the principal investigator or medical monitor could risk subject
             safety or interpretation of the results.

          -  Renal or liver impairment, defined as alkaline phosphatase and/or bilirubin ≥ 1.5 x
             ULN (an isolated bilirubin &gt;1.5 x ULN is acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and
             direct bilirubin is &lt;35%), serum creatinine level of ≥ 123.76 µmol/L (≥ 1.4 mg/dL ) in
             females and ≥ 132.60 µmol/L (≥ 1.5 mg/dL ) in males, and &gt; 2 × ULN for liver
             transaminases (ALT and AST), respectively.

          -  History of or current gastrointestinal diseases or surgeries influencing drug
             absorption, except for appendectomy.

          -  History, within 3 years, of drug abuse (including benzodiazepines, opioids,
             amphetamine, cocaine, and THC).

          -  History of alcoholism (more than 2 years), moderate drinkers (more than three drinks
             per day) or having consumed alcohol within 48 hours prior to first dose of test
             article (one drink is equal to one unit of alcohol [one glass wine, half pint beer,
             one measure of spirit]).

          -  Participation in any clinical trial within the past 3 months prior to the first dose
             of test article in the current study.

          -  History of difficulty in donating blood or accessibility of veins in left or right
             arm.

          -  Donation of blood or loss of blood (greater than 500 mL) within 3 months prior to
             receiving the first dose of test material.

          -  Use of any dietary or herbal supplements within 2 weeks prior the first dose of study
             drug, with the exception of an Investigator approved vitamin.

          -  History of sensitivity to any of the study medications, or components thereof or a
             history of drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of the investigator or medical
             monitor, contraindicates their participation.

          -  Active neoplastic disease or history of neoplastic disease within 5 years of study
             entry (except for basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin or carcinoma in
             situ).

          -  A positive pre-study drug screen.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Edinburgh</city>
        <zip>EH16 4SB</zip>
        <country>United Kingdom</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United Kingdom</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</url>
    <description>Researchers can use this site to request access to anonymised patient level data and/or supporting documents from clinical studies to conduct further research.</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.gsk-clinicalstudyregister.com/study/114089?search=study&amp;search_terms=114089#rs</url>
    <description>Results for study 114089 can be found on the GSK Clinical Study Register.</description>
  </link>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 10, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 10, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 14, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 19, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 19, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 20, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 2</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <patient_data>
    <sharing_ipd>Yes</sharing_ipd>
    <ipd_description>Patient-level data for this study will be made available through www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com following the timelines and process described on this site.</ipd_description>
  </patient_data>
  <study_docs>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>114089</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Study Protocol</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>114089</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Individual Participant Data Set</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>114089</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Statistical Analysis Plan</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>114089</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Dataset Specification</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>114089</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Clinical Study Report</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>114089</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Annotated Case Report Form</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
    <study_doc>
      <doc_id>114089</doc_id>
      <doc_type>Informed Consent Form</doc_type>
      <doc_url>https://www.clinicalstudydatarequest.com</doc_url>
      <doc_comment>For additional information about this study please refer to the GSK Clinical Study Register</doc_comment>
    </study_doc>
  </study_docs>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

