<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01031121</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>999909451</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>09-DA-N451</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01031121</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Breath Carbon Monoxide and Cotinine as Biomarkers to Distinguish Smokers From Nonsmokers</brief_title>
  <official_title>Breath Carbon Monoxide and Cotinine as Biomarkers to Distinguish Smokers From Nonsmokers</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute on Drug Abuse (NIDA)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institutes of Health Clinical Center (CC)</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background:

        -  Self-report and biochemical verification are used to determine smoking status in
           treatment trials and clinical research. Each method has merits and limitations that make
           it appropriate for particular situations. Participants who feel social pressure to
           report tobacco abstinence may provide unreliable self-reporting results. Biochemical
           verification using breath carbon monoxide (CO) is a more reliable indicator, but several
           biological and environmental factors (including exposure to secondhand smoke) can affect
           the sensitivity and specificity of breath CO measurement.

        -  An ideal biomarker of smoking status is cotinine, the major metabolite of nicotine.
           Cotinine levels found in blood, urine, and saliva can be used to distinguish between
           smokers and nonsmokers, as well as between light and heavy smokers. Researchers are
           interested in using cotinine assessments to develop suitable breath CO cutoff levels to
           categorize different types of smokers and nonsmokers for use in future research.

      Objectives:

      - To determine a breath carbon monoxide (CO) cutoff level that optimally discriminates
      between heavy and light smokers and nonsmokers who are and who are not exposed to
      environmental tobacco smoke.

      Eligibility:

        -  Individuals between 18 and 64 years of age who fall into one of the following groups:

        -  current smokers reporting more than 10 cigarettes per day for at least 6 months

        -  current smokers reporting 10 or fewer cigarettes per day for at least 6 months

        -  nonsmokers reporting regular environmental exposure to tobacco smoke

        -  nonsmokers reporting limited or no exposure to tobacco smoke

      Design:

        -  The study will involve a single outpatient session.

        -  Participants will provide breath CO, urine, and saliva samples, and will complete
           several smoking-related questionnaires on smoking history, current craving levels, and
           perceived level of nicotine dependence.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Objective:

      To determine a breath carbon monoxide (CO) cutoff level that optimally discriminates between
      heavy and light smokers and nonsmokers who are and who are not exposed to environmental
      tobacco smoke. Breath CO will be compared against cotinine concentration, which is the gold
      standard in verifying smoking status.

      Study population:

      The study will include four groups: 1) 60 smokers reporting &gt; 10 cigarettes per day, 2) 60
      smokers reporting less than or equal to 10 cigarettes per day, 3) 60 nonsmokers reporting
      regular environmental exposure to tobacco smoke, and 4) 60 nonsmokers reporting limited or no
      environmental exposure to tobacco smoke (total of 120 smokers and 120 nonsmokers).

      Design:

      Parallel groups design.

      Outcome Measures:

      1) breath CO; 2) semiquantitative salivary cotinine; 3) quantitative salivary nicotine,
      cotinine, and 3-hydroxycotinine; 4) semiquantitative urinary cotinine; 5) quantitative
      urinary nicotine, cotinine, norcotinine, and 3-hydroxycotinine; and 6) self-reported smoking
      variables.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 8, 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date>October 22, 2010</completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Other</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">240</enrollment>
  <condition>Nicotine Dependence</condition>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        -  INCLUSION CRITERIA:

        For Smokers:

          1. males and females 18-64 years old

          2. smoking 1-10 cigarettes or &gt; 10 cigarettes per day for the past 6 months

        For Nonsmokers:

        1. males and females 18-64 years old

        EXCLUSION CRITERIA:

        For Smokers:

          1. current interest in reducing or quitting smoking

          2. treatment for nicotine dependence in the past 3 months

          3. use of nicotine replacement products, bupropion, or varenicline in the past 3 months

          4. current use of tobacco products other than cigarettes

          5. marijuana use greater than 5 times in past 14 days or use during 24 hours before
             session

          6. chronic pulmonary disease

          7. study investigator or subordinate staff

        For Nonsmokers:

          1. use of any tobacco or nicotine products in the past 3 months

          2. marijuana use greater than 5 times in past 14 days or use during 24 hours before
             session

          3. chronic pulmonary disease

          4. study investigator or subordinate staff
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>64 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>National Institute on Drug Abuse, Biomedical Research Center (BRC)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21224</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Benowitz NL. Biomarkers of environmental tobacco smoke exposure. Environ Health Perspect. 1999 May;107 Suppl 2:349-55. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>10350520</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bernert JT, Harmon TL, Sosnoff CS, McGuffey JE. Use of continine immunoassay test strips for preclassifying urine samples from smokers and nonsmokers prior to analysis by LC-MS-MS. J Anal Toxicol. 2005 Nov-Dec;29(8):814-8.</citation>
    <PMID>16374940</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Chatkin J, Fritscher L, de Abreu C, Cavalet-Blanco D, Chatkin G, Wagner M, Fritscher C. Exhaled carbon monoxide as a marker for evaluating smoking abstinence in a Brazilian population sample. Prim Care Respir J. 2007 Feb;16(1):36-40.</citation>
    <PMID>17297525</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>October 22, 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 11, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 11, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 14, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 30, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">July 2, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <keyword>Cigarette Smoking</keyword>
  <keyword>Biomarkers</keyword>
  <keyword>Nicotine</keyword>
  <keyword>Cotinine</keyword>
  <keyword>Metabolites</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Tobacco Use Disorder</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carbon Monoxide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

