<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01031420</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>FER-GU-026</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>NCI-2010-01910</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01031420</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Dose Dense MVAC for Muscle Invasive Bladder Cancer</brief_title>
  <official_title>Phase II Trial of Neoadjuvant Dose Dense MVAC in Muscle Invasive Bladder Cancer and High Risk Urothelial Carcinoma of the Upper Urinary Tract</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Fox Chase Cancer Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Fox Chase Cancer Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Standard treatment for early stage bladder cancer is chemotherapy with methotrexate (M),
      vinblastine (V), adriamycin (A), and cisplatin (C) followed by surgical removal of any
      remaining cancer and the bladder with the intent of cure. The MV chemotherapy is usually
      given every 14 days with the AC given along each 28 days. This study looks at giving the same
      drugs at the same doses closer together, all drugs every 14 days, with the support of growth
      factor medication to promote growth of the white blood cells and platelets and allow
      chemotherapy to be finished sooner and surgery to be done sooner.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Primary Objective To assess the rate of complete response (pT0) at cystectomy or ureterectomy
      following preoperative dose dense MVAC (DD-MVAC) in patients with muscle invasive urothelial
      carcinoma of the bladder or high grade upper tract urothelial carcinoma.

      Secondary Objectives To assess the toxicity profile of DD-MVAC when given in the neoadjuvant
      setting: To define the number of patients who complete all three cycles of treatment without
      dose reduction, and to compare incidence of toxicity to the historical standard described by
      Grossman et al. To assess the 5 year overall and relapse free survival in patients who
      receive neoadjuvant DD-MVAC. To compare complete response rates between the following
      subgroups of study patients: Among bladder patients: Clinical N0 versus N1 (Appendix B) Among
      bladder patients: T2 stage without high risk features versus T2 with high risk features plus
      those with &gt; T2 stage.

      Three 14 day cycles of:

      Methotrexate 30 mg/m2 IV push or infusion over 2-3 minutes. Day 1

      Vinblastine 3 mg/m2 Slow IV push or infusion over Day 1

      Doxorubicin 30 mg/m2 Slow IV push or infusion over 15 minutes Day 1

      Cisplatin 70 mg/m2 IV infusion over 4 hours Note: May divide dose over two sequential days
      (35 mg/m2/d x 2 days) if creatinine clearance 50-59 mL/min Day 1* (or divided over Day 1 and
      Day 2)

      Pegfilgrastim 6 mg SQ 24-48 hours after completion of chemotherapy.

      Followed in 4-8 weeks by radical cystectomy/ureterectomy.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2009</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the rate of complete response at cystectomy or ureterectomy following preoperative dose dense MVAC in patients with muscle invasive urothelial carcinoma of the bladder or high risk upper tract urothelial carcinoma.</measure>
    <time_frame>Following completion of the 3rd/final cycle of chemotherapy (about week 9) by CT imaging and at time of surgery for pathologic response.</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>To assess the toxicity profile of dose dense MVAC given in the neoadjuvant setting.</measure>
    <time_frame>Ongoing throughout treatment at each MD visit every 14 days.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">54</enrollment>
  <condition>Muscle Invasive Bladder Cancer</condition>
  <condition>High Risk Urothelial Carcinoma of the Upper Urinary Tracts</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>dose dense MVAC</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>standard doses of MVAC given every 14 days x 3.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>single arm dose dense MVAC</intervention_name>
    <description>standard doses of methotrexate, vinblastine, adriamycin, and cisplatin given every 14 days.</description>
    <arm_group_label>dose dense MVAC</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>methotrexate sodium</other_name>
    <other_name>MTX</other_name>
    <other_name>Mexate</other_name>
    <other_name>Mexate-AQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Foex</other_name>
    <other_name>Folex</other_name>
    <other_name>Abitrexate</other_name>
    <other_name>Rheumatrex</other_name>
    <other_name>amethopterin</other_name>
    <other_name>Velban</other_name>
    <other_name>Velsar</other_name>
    <other_name>AlkabanAQ</other_name>
    <other_name>Velbe</other_name>
    <other_name>vinblastine sulfate</other_name>
    <other_name>vincaleukoblastine</other_name>
    <other_name>VLB</other_name>
    <other_name>doxorubicin</other_name>
    <other_name>doxorubicin hydrochloride liposomal Doxil,</other_name>
    <other_name>Rubex</other_name>
    <other_name>Adria</other_name>
    <other_name>cis-platinum, cisdiammineddichloroplatinum,</other_name>
    <other_name>CDDP</other_name>
    <other_name>Platinol</other_name>
    <other_name>platinum</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  histologically confirmed urothelial carcinoma of bladder, ureter, or renal pelvis.
             T2-T4 and muscle invasion must be established by TURBT. Upper tract must be high
             grade. N0-N1 are eligible.

          -  candidate for radical cystectomy, nephroureterectomy, or segmental ureterectomy with
             goal of cure.

             -&gt;/= 18 years old

          -  ECOG performance status 0-1.

          -  Adequate marrow and organ function.

          -  May enter on therapeutic anticoagulation if it can be safely held during perioperative
             period.

          -  No women of childbearing potential, pregnant or breastfeeding.

          -  LVEF &gt;/= 50 %

          -  Patients with history of other non-urothelial malignancies may enroll if: 1)no
             evidence of distant disease w/in last year. 2)No anticancer treatment for &gt;/= 1 year
             other than adjuvant treatment or treatment for secondary prevention. 3) Less than 360
             mg/m2 lifetime dose of adriamycin.

          -  ability to understand and willingness to sign written informed consent and HIPAA.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Intravesicular therapy w/in 4 weeks of study entry or those who have not recovered
             from adverse effects of such agents administered more than 4 weeks earlier.

          -  Patients may not be receiving any investigational agents within 4 weeks of study
             entry.

          -  History of allergic reactions attributed to compounds of similar chemical or biologic
             composition to Methotrexate, Vinblastine, Adriamycin or Cisplatin or other agents used
             in the study.

          -  Uncontrolled intercurrent illness including, but not limited to, ongoing or active
             infection, symptomatic congestive heart failure, unstable angina pectoris, cardiac
             arrhythmia, or psychiatric illness/social situations that would limit compliance with
             study requirements.

          -  Pregnant women are excluded from this study due to the potential for teratogenic or
             abortifacient effects of cytotoxic chemotherapy.

          -  Known HIV-positive patients on combination antiretroviral therapy are ineligible
             because of the potential for pharmacokinetic interactions with cytotoxic chemotherapy.
             In addition, these patients are at increased risk of lethal infections when treated
             with marrow-suppressive therapy.

             -. Patients who have undergone prior pelvic radiation are excluded due to risk of life
             threatening myelosuppression.

          -  Patients who have received any previous systemic chemotherapy or radiation therapy for
             urothelial carcinoma or cytotoxic chemotherapy for another malignancy within 1 year of
             study entry are ineligible.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Elizabeth Plimack, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Fox Chase Cancer Center</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Thomas Jefferson University Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19107</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Fox Chase Cancer Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19111</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=24821881</url>
    <description>Pubmed.gov</description>
  </link>
  <results_reference>
    <citation>Plimack ER, Hoffman-Censits JH, Viterbo R, Trabulsi EJ, Ross EA, Greenberg RE, Chen DY, Lallas CD, Wong YN, Lin J, Kutikov A, Dotan E, Brennan TA, Palma N, Dulaimi E, Mehrazin R, Boorjian SA, Kelly WK, Uzzo RG, Hudes GR. Accelerated methotrexate, vinblastine, doxorubicin, and cisplatin is safe, effective, and efficient neoadjuvant treatment for muscle-invasive bladder cancer: results of a multicenter phase II study with molecular correlates of response and toxicity. J Clin Oncol. 2014 Jun 20;32(18):1895-901. doi: 10.1200/JCO.2013.53.2465. Epub 2014 May 12.</citation>
    <PMID>24821881</PMID>
  </results_reference>
  <verification_date>November 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>December 3, 2009</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>December 11, 2009</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">December 14, 2009</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 3, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 3, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 4, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>bladder</keyword>
  <keyword>cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>invasive</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Urinary Bladder Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Carcinoma, Transitional Cell</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Liposomal doxorubicin</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Vinblastine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

