<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02138708</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>P120910</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02138708</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluation of the Pulmonary Vascular Reactivity Test in Patients With Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension and a Cardiac Shunt</brief_title>
  <acronym>ReVAch</acronym>
  <official_title>Pharmacological Test of Pulmonary Endothelium-dependent Vascular Reactivity to Acetylcholine in Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension With Congenital Cardiac Shunt Child and Adult</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Assistance Publique - Hôpitaux de Paris</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to assess the predictive performance of the pulmonary vascular
      reactivity to acetylcholine, in the presence pulmonary arterial hypertension (estimated 1
      year after the closure of the shunt).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Pulmonary arterial hypertension (PAH) is an important cause of mortality and morbidity in
      patients with congenital heart disease with a shunt.

      These congenital cardiac shunts are responsible for PAH, which evolves towards higher
      pulmonary vascular resistance if they are not closed early.

      Patients with significant pulmonary flow and low pulmonary vascular resistance fully benefit
      from surgical shunt closure with complete disappearance of pulmonary hypertension after
      closure. In contrast, patients with low pulmonary flow and high pulmonary vascular resistance
      will have no benefit because they keep a deleterious pulmonary hypertension after closure of
      the shunt.

      In certain situations, especially late discovery of heart disease, the issue of operability
      of these patients is crucial because closing the shunt inappropriately worsens the
      spontaneous prognosis. Currently, in case of doubt on the operability, there are several
      clinical and hemodynamic criteria used empirically, but their predictive value is uncertain.

      It is therefore necessary to stratify patients into operable and inoperable groups to improve
      their overall outcome after surgery.

      In this research project we propose to assess the predictive performance of the pulmonary
      vascular reactivity to acetylcholine test on the presence of elevated PAH 1 year after the
      closure of the shunt. This reactivity test will be evaluated on a population of patients for
      whom the decision of the surgical closure of the shunt has been adjudicated on the basis of
      explorations and usual tests (and therefore blind to the knowledge of the result of the
      reactivity test). The test in this study is designed with repeated injections and increasing
      doses with a continuous flow of acetylcholine in the left lower lobe of the pulmonary artery.
      The last injection consisted with adenosine with inhaled O2/NO (potentiating effect) for
      maximum vasodilatation. The parameter of interest is the Doppler flow velocity in the
      pulmonary artery endothelium-dependent vasodilation by acetylcholine relative to the speed at
      maximum vasodilatation (adenosine + in nitric oxide (NO) inhalation)
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Suspended</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2016</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">April 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Predictive performance of the reactivity test to the occurence of pulmonary arterial hypertension one year after the closure of the shunt.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year +/- 2 months</time_frame>
    <description>Evaluated in patient with &quot;shunt closed&quot; by :
the area under the ROC curve.
the parameter of interest is the Doppler flow velocity in m / s in endothelium-dependent vasodilation by acetylcholine relative to the speed in m / s at maximum vasodilatation (adenosine + in nitric oxide (NO) inhalation)
presence or absence of PAH one year after closure of the shunt will be evaluated by a conventional cardiac catheterization</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>occurrence of pulmonary hypertension.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year +/- 2 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nature and frequency of adverse events</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year +/- 2 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Characteristic of the distribution of test of reactivity in the population &quot;shunt unclosed&quot;</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year +/- 2 months</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Pulmonary Arterial Hypertension With Congenital Cardiac Shunt</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Shunt closed</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>patients with heart disease and shunt who, following hemodynamic exploration, will be selected for closure of their shunt</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Pharmacological test of pulmonary endothelial</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Shunt closed</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Before any shunt closure operation, the patients will have a the endothelium-dependant reactivity test.</other_name>
    <other_name>This includes for the same patient :</other_name>
    <other_name>- Implementation of Doppler probe in the lower left lobe guided in one probe 5 catheter guide right coronary 5 Fr</other_name>
    <other_name>- then control infusion G5%</other_name>
    <other_name>- then, 3 successive acetylcholine infusions to locally obtain successive concentrations of 10-10, 10-8, 10-6 mol /L</other_name>
    <other_name>- and infusion of adenosine 50μg/Kg/min with NO inhald/FiO2 100%</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient child or adult, (regardless of age and weight) , which presents with heart
             disease with a shunt,

          -  Patient who requires, during current care, a hemodynamic exploration by
             catheterization to assess pulmonary vascular resistance (due to doubt on the
             operability of the patient on the usual clinical and echo cardiographic data) .

          -  Informed consent signed by the patient or at least one holder of parental authority,
             and the investigator

          -  Patient affiliated or benefiting from a social security scheme

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patient with a specific treatment for PAH (the prostacyclin derivatives, antagonists
             of endothelium receptors and inhibitors of phosphodiesterase 5).

          -  Patient participating in another research with exclusion period

          -  Known allergy to acetylcholine or adenosine

          -  Contraindication to the use of KRENOSIN (adenosine)

          -  atrioventricular block second or third degree, with the exception of patients with
             cardiac pacemaker.

          -  dysfunction sinoatrial (the headset disease) except patients with a pacemaker

          -  chronic obstructive pulmonary disease with bronchospasm (eg bronchial asthma)

          -  long QT Syndrome

          -  severe arterial hypotension

          -  known adenosine hypersensitivity

          -  Pregnant or patient of childbearing potential not using an effective contraception
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 2, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 14, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 15, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 20, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 20, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 21, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Pulmonary arterial hypertension,</keyword>
  <keyword>congenital heart disease,</keyword>
  <keyword>heart shunt,</keyword>
  <keyword>acetylcholine</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacological test of pulmonary vascular reactivity (acetylcholine) in</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Hypertension</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Familial Primary Pulmonary Hypertension</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Acetylcholine</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

