<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02134587</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>E015/10</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02134587</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Educational Intervention in Pharmacovigilance for Hospital Health Professionals</brief_title>
  <acronym>EIPhv</acronym>
  <official_title>Implementation of a Hospital Pharmacovigilance Service and Comparison of Algorithms for Adverse Drug Reaction Causality Assessment</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Universidade Estadual Paulista Júlio de Mesquita Filho</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Universidade Estadual Paulista Júlio de Mesquita Filho</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Spontaneous reports by health professionals generate the signals in pharmacovigilance.
      However, the passive method has limitations and the most important of them are the
      underreporting and the poor quality of data, hindering the causality assessment of adverse
      drug events (ADE). Therefore, the present study aimed to validate an educational intervention
      (EI) in pharmacovigilance for hospital health professionals, in order to analyze the impact
      on the knowledge, skill and attitude in ADE reporting.

      Investigators proposed a multifaceted EI which will be developed in four meetings with one
      hour each. The following activities will be carried out: application of a questionnaire to
      assess the knowledge, skill and attitude before and after EI; lecture; practical class and
      education material distribution. The answers of questionnaire are going to be analyzed using
      content analysis technique. The definitions of World Health Organization and the minimum and
      desired criteria to fill the ADE form, according to the Pan American Health Organization, are
      going to be considered gold-standard answers. The statistical test of Wilcoxon-Mann Whitney
      test for paired samples will be applied, in order to assess the impact of educational
      intervention on behavior of health professionals (ADE reporting).

      With the present study, the following hypotheses will be tested:

      H0= There is no difference between the numbers of ADE reported (behavior/attitudes) before
      and after the educational intervention.

      H1= The numbers of ADE reported before and after the educational intervention are different.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      A quasi-experimental study with health professionals who acted in a general and public
      hospital of medium complexity with 104 beds will be performed.

      Investigators proposed an educational intervention, with the development of lecture and
      practical class, application of questionnaire before and after EI and the distribution of
      educational material. Activities will be developed in four meetings of one hour each one.

      In the first meeting, questionnaire will be applied, in order to assess knowledge, skills and
      attitudes in pharmacovigilance prior to EI. The instrument was elaborated based on previous
      studies. Second meeting will be comprise a lecture regarding the theoretical framework and
      importance of pharmacovigilance, and distribution of educational material, whose content
      includes the same issues of presentation. In the third meeting, a practical class will be
      performed to promote a discussion of a fictitious case of adverse drug reaction (ADR), in
      order to elucidate the correct fill of ADE form. In the fourth meeting, will be repeated the
      application of questionnaire, in order to assess the impact of EI. With the aim to verify
      change behavior of health professionals regarding pharmacovigilance activities, the number of
      ADE reports made prior and after intervention will be compared.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>February 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Absolute Number of ADE Reporting (Change Behavior of Health Professionals)</measure>
    <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
    <description>Investigators are going to verify the numbers of adverse drug events reported by health professionals which was made 12 months before educational intervention. A follow up across 12 months post-educational intervention also will be performed, in order to identify the number of adverse drug events reported by health professionals. Prevalence of ADE in both periods will be estimated and compared, in order to asses the impact of the intervention on change behavior of health professionals.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Knowledge (Awareness) Regarding Pharmacovigilance</measure>
    <time_frame>Two days</time_frame>
    <description>Knowledge assessment will be performed by content analysis of answers obtained from questionnaire, being assigned scores from zero to ten. Definitions related to pharmacovigilance of World Health Organization will be considered gold-standard answers. Scores below five will be classified as unsatisfactory, among five and 7.5 were considered regular and above 7.6 satisfactory on the knowledge acquisition.The questionnaire will be applied in the first (prior to educational intervention) and fourth (post-educational intervention period) meetings. Data will be compared, in order to assess the impact of educational intervention on knowledge of health professionals.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Quality of ADE Reports</measure>
    <time_frame>Two days</time_frame>
    <description>Skills evaluation will be carried out according to the perception of the voluntary regarding the relevance´s degree of the information to be filled in ADE form. Therefore, in the first (prior to educational intervention) and fourth (post-educational intervention period) meetings, subjects will be asked to highlight the fields of ADE form, according to unnecessary, necessary or essential information to be reported. Minimal and desirable criteria to be filled in ADE form preconized by Pan-American Health Organization will be considered gold-standard answers. Scores from zero to ten will be assigned, according to gold-standard answers. Data will be compared, in order to estimate the impact of educational intervention on skills to fill ADE form.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">203</enrollment>
  <condition>Adverse Drug Reaction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Subjects post educational intervention</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>Multifaceted educational intervention in pharmacovigilance</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Other</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Multifaceted educational intervention</intervention_name>
    <description>Application of questionnaire of knowledge, attitudes and skills in pharmacovigilance.
Lecture regarding the theoretical framework and importance of pharmacovigilance, and distribution of educational material
Distribution of educational material
Practical class to explain the correct fill of adverse drug events form
Reapplication of questionnaire of knowledge, attitudes and skills in pharmacovigilance.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Subjects post educational intervention</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

        All health professionals (physicians, pharmacists, nurses, auxiliaries of nurses and
        pharmacists, as well as the multidisciplinary team - social assistants, physiotherapists,
        audiologists, nutritionists, psychologists, occupational therapists and administrative
        officers), with employment link at the hospital under study who agree to participate by
        signing an informed consent form are going to be enrolled.

        Exclusion Criteria:

        The exclusion criteria meet professionals who will be on sick leave, vacation, those who
        will not to be registered to carry out the intervention and those who will refuse to answer
        the questionnaire, despite to having shown interest in participating in the lecture and
        practical class.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Patricia C Mastroianni, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>School of Pharmaceutical Sciences of Unesp</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Fabiana R Varallo, Master</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>School of Pharmaceutical Sciences of Unesp</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital Estadual Américo Brasiliense</name>
      <address>
        <city>Américo Brasiliense</city>
        <state>São Paulo</state>
        <zip>14820-000</zip>
        <country>Brazil</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Brazil</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Figueiras A, Tato F, Fontaiñas J, Gestal-Otero JJ. Influence of physicians' attitudes on reporting adverse drug events: a case-control study. Med Care. 1999 Aug;37(8):809-14.</citation>
    <PMID>10448723</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herdeiro MT, Figueiras A, Polónia J, Gestal-Otero JJ. Physicians' attitudes and adverse drug reaction reporting : a case-control study in Portugal. Drug Saf. 2005;28(9):825-33.</citation>
    <PMID>16119975</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herdeiro MT, Figueiras A, Polónia J, Gestal-Otero JJ. Influence of pharmacists' attitudes on adverse drug reaction reporting : a case-control study in Portugal. Drug Saf. 2006;29(4):331-40.</citation>
    <PMID>16569082</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gerritsen R, Faddegon H, Dijkers F, van Grootheest K, van Puijenbroek E. Effectiveness of pharmacovigilance training of general practitioners: a retrospective cohort study in the Netherlands comparing two methods. Drug Saf. 2011 Sep 1;34(9):755-62. doi: 10.2165/11592800-000000000-00000.</citation>
    <PMID>21830837</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pedrós C, Vallano A, Cereza G, Mendoza-Aran G, Agustí A, Aguilera C, Danés I, Vidal X, Arnau JM. An intervention to improve spontaneous adverse drug reaction reporting by hospital physicians: a time series analysis in Spain. Drug Saf. 2009;32(1):77-83. doi: 10.2165/00002018-200932010-00007.</citation>
    <PMID>19132807</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Figueiras A, Herdeiro MT, Polónia J, Gestal-Otero JJ. An educational intervention to improve physician reporting of adverse drug reactions: a cluster-randomized controlled trial. JAMA. 2006 Sep 6;296(9):1086-93.</citation>
    <PMID>16954488</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herdeiro MT, Ribeiro-Vaz I, Ferreira M, Polónia J, Falcão A, Figueiras A. Workshop- and telephone-based interventions to improve adverse drug reaction reporting: a cluster-randomized trial in Portugal. Drug Saf. 2012 Aug 1;35(8):655-65. doi: 10.2165/11599750-000000000-00000.</citation>
    <PMID>22788235</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Herdeiro MT, Polónia J, Gestal-Otero JJ, Figueiras A. Improving the reporting of adverse drug reactions: a cluster-randomized trial among pharmacists in Portugal. Drug Saf. 2008;31(4):335-44.</citation>
    <PMID>18366244</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Ribeiro-Vaz I, Herdeiro MT, Polónia J, Figueiras A. Strategies to increase the sensitivity of pharmacovigilance in Portugal. Rev Saude Publica. 2011 Feb;45(1):129-35. Epub 2010 Nov 12. English, Portuguese.</citation>
    <PMID>21085884</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Biagi C, Montanaro N, Buccellato E, Roberto G, Vaccheri A, Motola D. Underreporting in pharmacovigilance: an intervention for Italian GPs (Emilia-Romagna region). Eur J Clin Pharmacol. 2013 Feb;69(2):237-44. doi: 10.1007/s00228-012-1321-7. Epub 2012 Jun 17.</citation>
    <PMID>22706618</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 5, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 9, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <results_first_submitted>March 29, 2015</results_first_submitted>
  <results_first_submitted_qc>July 26, 2015</results_first_submitted_qc>
  <results_first_posted type="Estimate">August 20, 2015</results_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 26, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 26, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 20, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Universidade Estadual Paulista Júlio de Mesquita Filho</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Fabiana Rossi Varallo</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Clinical pharmacist and PhD student</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Health knowledge, attitudes, practices.</keyword>
  <keyword>Adverse drug reaction reporting systems.</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacovigilance. Product Surveillance, Postmarketing.</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug-related side effects and adverse reactions.</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Drug-Related Side Effects and Adverse Reactions</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Subjects Post Educational Intervention</title>
          <description>Multifaceted educational intervention in pharmacovigilance
Multifaceted educational intervention: 1- Application of questionnaire of knowledge, attitudes and skills in pharmacovigilance.
2- Lecture regarding the theoretical framework and importance of pharmacovigilance, and distribution of educational material 3- Distribution of educational material 4- Practical class to explain the correct fill of adverse drug events form 5- Reapplication of questionnaire of knowledge, attitudes and skills in pharmacovigilance.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="203"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="173"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="30"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Did not completed all meetings</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="30"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Subjects Post Educational Intervention</title>
          <description>Multifaceted educational intervention in pharmacovigilance
Multifaceted educational intervention: 1- Application of questionnaire of knowledge, attitudes and skills in pharmacovigilance.
2- Lecture regarding the theoretical framework and importance of pharmacovigilance, and distribution of educational material 3- Distribution of educational material 4- Practical class to explain the correct fill of adverse drug events form 5- Reapplication of questionnaire of knowledge, attitudes and skills in pharmacovigilance.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <analyzed_list>
        <analyzed>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <scope>Overall</scope>
          <count_list>
            <count group_id="B1" value="173"/>
          </count_list>
        </analyzed>
      </analyzed_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="30.6" spread="6.5"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Female</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="150"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
            <class>
              <title>Male</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="23"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Region of Enrollment</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <title>Brazil</title>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="B1" value="173"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Absolute Number of ADE Reporting (Change Behavior of Health Professionals)</title>
        <description>Investigators are going to verify the numbers of adverse drug events reported by health professionals which was made 12 months before educational intervention. A follow up across 12 months post-educational intervention also will be performed, in order to identify the number of adverse drug events reported by health professionals. Prevalence of ADE in both periods will be estimated and compared, in order to asses the impact of the intervention on change behavior of health professionals.</description>
        <time_frame>12 months</time_frame>
        <population>Before educational intervention, health professionals reported only three adverse drug events, related to therapeutic failure. However, after the study, the number of reports rise 70-fold, since subjects reported 165 medication errors, 26 adverse drug reactions, 18 quality deviations, 5 therapeutic failure and one off-label use.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Subjects Post Educational Intervention</title>
            <description>Multifaceted educational intervention in pharmacovigilance
Multifaceted educational intervention: 1- Application of questionnaire of knowledge, attitudes and skills in pharmacovigilance.
2- Lecture regarding the theoretical framework and importance of pharmacovigilance, and distribution of educational material 3- Distribution of educational material 4- Practical class to explain the correct fill of adverse drug events form 5- Reapplication of questionnaire of knowledge, attitudes and skills in pharmacovigilance.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Subjects Prior to Educational Intervention</title>
            <description>Number of health professionals who had the potential to report adverse drug reaction, before the educational intervention</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Absolute Number of ADE Reporting (Change Behavior of Health Professionals)</title>
          <description>Investigators are going to verify the numbers of adverse drug events reported by health professionals which was made 12 months before educational intervention. A follow up across 12 months post-educational intervention also will be performed, in order to identify the number of adverse drug events reported by health professionals. Prevalence of ADE in both periods will be estimated and compared, in order to asses the impact of the intervention on change behavior of health professionals.</description>
          <population>Before educational intervention, health professionals reported only three adverse drug events, related to therapeutic failure. However, after the study, the number of reports rise 70-fold, since subjects reported 165 medication errors, 26 adverse drug reactions, 18 quality deviations, 5 therapeutic failure and one off-label use.</population>
          <units>absolute number of adverse drug events</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="173"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="173"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="215"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="3"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Knowledge (Awareness) Regarding Pharmacovigilance</title>
        <description>Knowledge assessment will be performed by content analysis of answers obtained from questionnaire, being assigned scores from zero to ten. Definitions related to pharmacovigilance of World Health Organization will be considered gold-standard answers. Scores below five will be classified as unsatisfactory, among five and 7.5 were considered regular and above 7.6 satisfactory on the knowledge acquisition.The questionnaire will be applied in the first (prior to educational intervention) and fourth (post-educational intervention period) meetings. Data will be compared, in order to assess the impact of educational intervention on knowledge of health professionals.</description>
        <time_frame>Two days</time_frame>
        <population>The subjects were assessed regarding pharmacovigilance´s knowledge prior to educational interventions and after as well, in order to evaluate the effectiveness of the study in aware health professionals to report adverse drug events.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Subjects Post Educational Intervention</title>
            <description>Knowledge of health professionals after multifaceted educational intervention in pharmacovigilance
Multifaceted educational intervention: 1- Application of questionnaire of knowledge, attitudes and skills in pharmacovigilance.
2- Lecture regarding the theoretical framework and importance of pharmacovigilance, and distribution of educational material 3- Distribution of educational material 4- Practical class to explain the correct fill of adverse drug events form 5- Reapplication of questionnaire of knowledge, attitudes and skills in pharmacovigilance.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Subjects Prior to Educational Intervention</title>
            <description>Knowledge of health professionals before the educational intervention regarding pharmacovigilance</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Knowledge (Awareness) Regarding Pharmacovigilance</title>
          <description>Knowledge assessment will be performed by content analysis of answers obtained from questionnaire, being assigned scores from zero to ten. Definitions related to pharmacovigilance of World Health Organization will be considered gold-standard answers. Scores below five will be classified as unsatisfactory, among five and 7.5 were considered regular and above 7.6 satisfactory on the knowledge acquisition.The questionnaire will be applied in the first (prior to educational intervention) and fourth (post-educational intervention period) meetings. Data will be compared, in order to assess the impact of educational intervention on knowledge of health professionals.</description>
          <population>The subjects were assessed regarding pharmacovigilance´s knowledge prior to educational interventions and after as well, in order to evaluate the effectiveness of the study in aware health professionals to report adverse drug events.</population>
          <units>percentage of right answers</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="173"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="173"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="5.2" lower_limit="0.9" upper_limit="9.3"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="2.3" lower_limit="0.0" upper_limit="6.6"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>0.00001</p_value>
            <method>Wilcoxon (Mann-Whitney)</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Quality of ADE Reports</title>
        <description>Skills evaluation will be carried out according to the perception of the voluntary regarding the relevance´s degree of the information to be filled in ADE form. Therefore, in the first (prior to educational intervention) and fourth (post-educational intervention period) meetings, subjects will be asked to highlight the fields of ADE form, according to unnecessary, necessary or essential information to be reported. Minimal and desirable criteria to be filled in ADE form preconized by Pan-American Health Organization will be considered gold-standard answers. Scores from zero to ten will be assigned, according to gold-standard answers. Data will be compared, in order to estimate the impact of educational intervention on skills to fill ADE form.</description>
        <time_frame>Two days</time_frame>
        <population>The subjects were assessed regarding pharmacovigilance´s skills prior to educational interventions and after as well, in order to evaluate the effectiveness of the study in contribute on the improvement of the quality of information inserted on the form.</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Subjects Post Educational Intervention</title>
            <description>Skills of health professionals in fill correctly the adverse drug events form after multifaceted educational intervention in pharmacovigilance
Multifaceted educational intervention: 1- Application of questionnaire of knowledge, attitudes and skills in pharmacovigilance.
2- Lecture regarding the theoretical framework and importance of pharmacovigilance, and distribution of educational material 3- Distribution of educational material 4- Practical class to explain the correct fill of adverse drug events form 5- Reapplication of questionnaire of knowledge, attitudes and skills in pharmacovigilance.</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Subjects Prior to Educational Intervention</title>
            <description>Skills of health professionals in fill correctly the adverse drug events form before educational intervention</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Quality of ADE Reports</title>
          <description>Skills evaluation will be carried out according to the perception of the voluntary regarding the relevance´s degree of the information to be filled in ADE form. Therefore, in the first (prior to educational intervention) and fourth (post-educational intervention period) meetings, subjects will be asked to highlight the fields of ADE form, according to unnecessary, necessary or essential information to be reported. Minimal and desirable criteria to be filled in ADE form preconized by Pan-American Health Organization will be considered gold-standard answers. Scores from zero to ten will be assigned, according to gold-standard answers. Data will be compared, in order to estimate the impact of educational intervention on skills to fill ADE form.</description>
          <population>The subjects were assessed regarding pharmacovigilance´s skills prior to educational interventions and after as well, in order to evaluate the effectiveness of the study in contribute on the improvement of the quality of information inserted on the form.</population>
          <units>percent of correctly filled forms</units>
          <param>Median</param>
          <dispersion>Full Range</dispersion>
          <analyzed_list>
            <analyzed>
              <units>Participants</units>
              <scope>Measure</scope>
              <count_list>
                <count group_id="O1" value="173"/>
                <count group_id="O2" value="173"/>
              </count_list>
            </analyzed>
          </analyzed_list>
          <class_list>
            <class>
              <category_list>
                <category>
                  <measurement_list>
                    <measurement group_id="O1" value="5.2" lower_limit="0.0" upper_limit="9.2"/>
                    <measurement group_id="O2" value="3.9" lower_limit="0.0" upper_limit="8.0"/>
                  </measurement_list>
                </category>
              </category_list>
            </class>
          </class_list>
        </measure>
        <analysis_list>
          <analysis>
            <group_id_list>
              <group_id>O1</group_id>
            </group_id_list>
            <non_inferiority_type>Superiority or Other</non_inferiority_type>
            <p_value>&lt;0.0001</p_value>
            <method>Wilcoxon (Mann-Whitney)</method>
          </analysis>
        </analysis_list>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <time_frame>The number of adverse drug events reported by health professionals was followed up after one year of educational intervention.</time_frame>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Subjects Post Educational Intervention</title>
          <description>Multifaceted educational intervention in pharmacovigilance
Multifaceted educational intervention: 1- Application of questionnaire of knowledge, attitudes and skills in pharmacovigilance.
2- Lecture regarding the theoretical framework and importance of pharmacovigilance, and distribution of educational material 3- Distribution of educational material 4- Practical class to explain the correct fill of adverse drug events form 5- Reapplication of questionnaire of knowledge, attitudes and skills in pharmacovigilance.</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="0"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>0</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="0"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>All Principal Investigators ARE employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Fabiana Rossi Varallo</name_or_title>
      <organization>School of Pharmaceutical Scientes of Universidade Estadual Paulista Júlio de Mesquita Filho, Araraquara, SP (Brazil)</organization>
      <phone>5516997629496</phone>
      <email>varallo.f.r@gmail.com</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>

