<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02139813</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>2014.851</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02139813</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Omega Loop Versus Roux-en-Y Gastric Bypass</brief_title>
  <acronym>YOMEGA</acronym>
  <official_title>Prospective Multicentric Randomized Trial of Efficiency and Safety of Laparoscopic Omega Loop Bypass Versus Roux-en-Y Gastric Bypass</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Hospices Civils de Lyon</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Hospices Civils de Lyon</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Several prospective trials and metaanalysis have demonstrated the superiority of bariatric
      surgery on the medical treatment of obesity. The Roux-en-Y Gastric ByPass (RYGBP) procedure
      has been practiced for more than 30 years, and is the procedure of choice for morbidly obese
      with metabolic disorders in most of the reference centers. Nevertheless, the RYGBP is a
      technically demanding procedure with a learning curve of more than 75 cases. The complication
      rate is around 10% in expert centers.

      More recently another procedure has been described which seems as efficient on weight loss
      and co-morbidities as the RYGBP, with the advantage of being less technically difficult and
      less morbid, especially for multi-complicated obese and/or the super obese. It consists of a
      unique gastro-jejunal anastomosis between a long gastric pouch and a jejunal Omega loop.
      However, this procedure could be at risk of biliary reflux and anastomotic ulcers with
      dysplastic changes of the gastric and esophageal mucosa. As a result, the Omega loop bypass
      (OLB) has only been developed by a few teams and remains a controversial subject,
      particularly as only one monocentric randomized trial has compared it to the RYGBP, which is
      remains the gold standard. The first litterature results show similar or even better weight
      loss efficiency than RYGBP with a better feasibility. The early complication rate seems
      lower, but there are still insufficient data on long term morbidity and biliary reflux
      consequences.

      By performing a randomized and prospective comparison of OLB to RYGBP, the aim of the
      investigators study is to analyze the weight loss efficiency, the morbidity and mortality,
      the feasibility, and the quality of life of both techniques, in order to validate the Omega
      loop bypass as a procedure of choice in bariatric surgery

      Hypothesis :

      The OLB, while being as efficient as RYGBP on weight loss and metabolic complications, could
      be less morbid.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2018</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 2018</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight loss assessment according to Excess BMI Loss percentage (EBL%)</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Weight loss assessment according to Excess BMI Loss percentage (EBL%), calculated using the following formula:
((BMI 2 years after surgery - initial BMI) / (initial BMI - 22.5)) X 100</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Weight loss according to absolute weight loss (aWL in kg), Excess Weight Loss percentage (EWL%), EBL%</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 12, 18 and 24 months after surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Waist size reduction according to absolute waist size (in cm)</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 3, 6, 12, 18 and 24 months after surgery</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Medical and surgical complication rates</measure>
    <time_frame>1, 12 and 24 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Medical and surgical complication rates (anastomotic leaks, biliary reflux, bowel obstruction, anastomotic ulcers, anastomotic stenosis, internal hernia, chronic gastritis, esophagitis, iron deficiency anemia …)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Type and severity of complications</measure>
    <time_frame>During the month following surgery (for early complications) and from one month to 24 months postoperatively (for late complications)</time_frame>
    <description>Type and severity of early and late complications for each procedure, according to the Dindo-Clavien classification</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Operative time</measure>
    <time_frame>Recorded on the day of surgery (Day 0)</time_frame>
    <description>Operative time (expressed in minutes)</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Mean length of stay</measure>
    <time_frame>Average period of 5 days from surgery (Day of surgery = D0) until the end of hospitalization, recorded on Visit 4 (Month1 +/- 10 days)</time_frame>
    <description>Mean length of stay based on the number of days of hospitalization from surgery (Day of surgery = D0) until the end of hospitalization</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Patient's quality of life</measure>
    <time_frame>The day before surgery (D-1) and 6, 12 and 24 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Patient's quality of life score according to the IWQOL questionnaire and the BAROS questionnaire adapted to bariatric surgery</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Metabolic and lipid profile</measure>
    <time_frame>During the period of inclusion (D-60 to D-2) and at 6, 12 and 24 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Metabolic profile of glucose homeostasis and the lipid profile according to antidiabetic and anitilipidemic treatments, HbA1c level, fasting glycemia, HDL, LDL and TG.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Dumping syndrome and hypoglycemia symptoms</measure>
    <time_frame>At 1, 3,6,12,18 and 24 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Dumping syndrome and hypoglycemia symptoms will be assessed using the Sigstad questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Gastroesophageal reflux</measure>
    <time_frame>The day before surgery (Day-1) and 6, 12, and 24 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Gastroesophageal reflux assessed by items 5 and 27 of the GIQLI questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Modifications of the gastric and esophageal mucosa</measure>
    <time_frame>2 years after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Histological modifications of the gastric and esophageal mucosa, based on upper GI endoscopy with biopsies</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Frequency of diarrhea</measure>
    <time_frame>The day before surgery (day-1) and 6, 12, and 24 months after surgery</time_frame>
    <description>Frequency of diarrhea based on items 7, 30, 31 and 36 of the GIQLI questionnaire</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Nutritional status</measure>
    <time_frame>During the period of inclusion (D-60 to D-2) and 6, 12, and 24 months after surgery (The 24-hour steatorrhea will be quantified at 6 months).</time_frame>
    <description>Nutritional status, assessed by PTH, vitamin B1, B9, B12, and D levels before and 12 and 24 months after surgery and assessed by hemoglobin, albumin, prealbumin, ferritin, saturation coefficient, before and 6, 12 and 24 months after surgery .</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">256</enrollment>
  <condition>Obesity</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Laparoscopic Omega Loop Bypass</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Laparoscopic Mini-gastric bypass</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Laparoscopic Roux-en-Y Gastric ByPass</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Procedure of reference in bariatric surgery</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Laparoscopic Mini-gastric bypass</intervention_name>
    <description>The laparoscopic Omega Loop Bypass will consist of:
a long gastric tube, stapled approximately 1.5 cm from the left of the lesser curvature of the antrum to the angle of His
a narrow gastric tube will be calibrated to be approximately 1.5 cm wide
an Omega loop of 200 cm
a unique gastro-jejunal anatomosis of 200cm from the ligament of Treitz, using a linear stapler</description>
    <arm_group_label>Laparoscopic Omega Loop Bypass</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Procedure of reference in bariatric surgery</intervention_name>
    <description>The laparoscopic Roux-en-Y Gastric Bypass will consist of:
a small gastric pouch (about 30cc)
an antecolic alimentary limb
a gastro-jejunal anastomosis using a linear stapler
a 150cm long alimentary limb
a 50cm biliary limb
a latero-lateral jejuno-jejunal anastomosis
closure of the mesenteric defects</description>
    <arm_group_label>Laparoscopic Roux-en-Y Gastric ByPass</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Aged between 18 and 65 years old

          -  Morbid obesity with BMI ≥ 40 kg/m2 or BMI ≥ 35 kg/m2 associated with one or more
             co-morbidities (type 2 diabetes, arterial hypertension, sleep apnea, dyslipidemia,
             arthritis)

          -  Patient who has benefited from an upper GI endoscopy with biopsies

          -  Patient who has benefited from a pluridisciplinary evaluation, with a favorable
             opinion for a gastric bypass

          -  Patient who understands and accepts the need for a long term follow-up

          -  Patient who agrees to be included in the study and who signs the informed consent form

          -  Patient affiliated to a healthcare insurance plan

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  History of esophagitis on upper GI endoscopy (Los Angeles classification)

          -  Severe gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD), resistant to medical treatment

          -  Presence of dysplastic modifications of the gastric mucosa or a history of gastric
             cancer, on upper gastrointestinal endoscopy.

          -  Presence of Helicobacter Pylori resistant to medical treatment

          -  Presence of an unhealed gastro-duodenal ulcer or an ulcer diagnosed less than 2 months
             previously

          -  History of previous bariatric surgery (gastric band, sleeve gastrectomy, vertical
             banded gastroplasty)

          -  Presence of a severe and evolutive life threatening pathology, unrelated to obesity

          -  Presence of chronic diarrhea (≥ 3 loose or liquid stools per day, over a period of
             more than 4 weeks)

          -  Pregnancy or desire to be pregnant during the study

          -  Binge eating disorders or other eating disorders according to DSM V criteria

          -  Mentally unbalanced patients, under supervision or guardianship

          -  Patient who does not understand French/is unable to give consent

          -  Patient not affiliated to a French or European healthcare insurance

          -  Patient who has already been included in a trial which has a conflict of interests
             with the present study
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Maud ROBERT, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Service de Chirurgie Digestive - Hôpital Edouard Herriot - Hospices Civils de Lyon - France</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Clinique Universitaire de Chirurgie Digestive et de l'Urgence - CHU de Grenoble</name>
      <address>
        <city>Grenoble</city>
        <zip>38043</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cabinet de chirurgie générale, digestive et de l'obésité - Hôpital Privé Drôme et Ardèche</name>
      <address>
        <city>Guilherand-Granges</city>
        <zip>07500</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service de Chirurgie Générale et Endocrinienne - Hôpital Claude Huriez - CHU de Lille</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lille</city>
        <zip>59037</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service de Chirurgie Digestive - Hôpital Edouard Herriot - Hospices Civils de Lyon</name>
      <address>
        <city>Lyon</city>
        <zip>69437</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service de Chirurgie Digestive et Hépato-Bilio-Pancréatique et Transplantation Hépatique - Hôpital de la Pitié Salpêtrière</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75013</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service de Chirurgie Digestive, Générale et Cancérologique - Hôpital Européen Georges Pompidou - APHP</name>
      <address>
        <city>Paris</city>
        <zip>75908</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service de Chirurgie Générale - Hôpital Privé de la Loire</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Etienne</city>
        <zip>42100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service de Chirurgie Digestive et Hépato-Biliaire-Centre Hospitalier Privé Saint Grégoire</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint Grégoire</city>
        <zip>35768</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Service de Chirurgie Générale, Digestive et Viscérale - Centre Hospitalier Intercommunal de Poissy / Saint Gerrmain en Laye</name>
      <address>
        <city>Saint-germain-en-laye</city>
        <zip>78100</zip>
        <country>France</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>France</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>April 2018</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 12, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 13, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 15, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>April 24, 2018</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">April 25, 2018</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Obesity -</keyword>
  <keyword>Bariatric surgery</keyword>
  <keyword>Gastric bypass</keyword>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

