<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02131675</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GCO 12-1425</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02131675</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Detection of C-peptide in Youth With Longstanding Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus</brief_title>
  <official_title>Observational Study of C-peptide Levels in Youth With Longstanding Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus as Detected by an Ultrasensitive Assay</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Background Type 1 diabetes is characterized by pancreatic beta-cell destruction and an
      inability to synthesize insulin. Connecting peptide (C-peptide) is formed from the same
      precursor as insulin and is produced in equimolar amounts as insulin. There are several
      clinical trials currently being performed to explore the possibility of beta-cell
      preservation or regeneration. Most children are not eligible for these trials because it is
      often presumed that C-peptide levels will decrease and become undetectable after years of
      having type 1 diabetes. Several studies in the adult population have demonstrated that
      C-peptide may remain measureable in patients who have had diabetes for up to 50 years after
      diagnosis. Recently, it was demonstrated that 10% of adult patients who have had type 1
      diabetes for 31-40 years have measureable levels of serum C-peptide if measured with an
      ultrasensitive assay. The levels were lower in patients who had diabetes for a longer time.
      This pattern was also demonstrated in the Diabetes Control and Complications Trial (DCCT) and
      NHANES trial. No studies have been performed exclusively in pediatric patients Hypothesis The
      investigators hypothesize that C-peptide should be detectable in the sera of pediatric
      patients who have had type 1 diabetes for greater than 1 year and as far out as &gt; 20 years
      after diagnosis. The investigators also hypothesize that since their patient population has
      had diabetes for less time as compared to adults, the levels of C-peptide should be higher
      than reported for adults and that a greater proportion of patients in the pediatric
      population will have detectable C-peptide levels as compared to adults.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      1) Objectives:

        1. To determine if C-peptide is detectable in the sera of children that have had type 1
           diabetes for more than 1 year using an ultrasensitive assay.

        2. To correlate C-peptide levels with duration since diagnosis, current age, antibody
           titers at diagnosis, hemoglobin A1c, total daily insulin dosage.

        3. To determine responsiveness of residual C-peptide to mixed-meal testing.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>October 2012</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">December 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>C-peptide level</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Hemoglobin A1c</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Hemoglobin A1c at diabetes diagnosis and at most recent medical visit will be correlated with C-peptide level</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total daily dose of insulin</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Total daily dose of insulin per kilogram will be correlated with C-peptide level</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Age at diabetes diagnosis</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Age at diabetes diagnosis will be correlated with C-peptide level</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Duration of diabetes</measure>
    <time_frame>Day 1</time_frame>
    <description>Duration of diabetes will be correlated with C-peptide level</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>1</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">50</enrollment>
  <condition>Type 1 Diabetes Mellitus</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Boost shake</arm_group_label>
    <description>children that have had type 1 diabetes for more than 1 year</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Dietary Supplement</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Boost shake</intervention_name>
    <description>Blood draw after mixed-meal consumption</description>
    <arm_group_label>Boost shake</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>mixed-meal</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples Without DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      serum
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Subjects will be recruited from the population of patients seen in the Division of
        Pediatric Endocrinology and Diabetes. These patients must have type 1 diabetes and must
        have been diagnosed more than 1 year prior to their recruitment. Potential subjects will be
        identified by reaching out to the physicians in the division and asking that they inform
        the investigators of patients that they see with type 1 diabetes. Those patients will have
        their information reviewed by the investigators using EPIC, the electronic medical record
        at The Mount Sinai Hospital.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Non-Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Male or female

          -  1-25 years of age

          -  Have had type 1 diabetes for more than 1 year.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Does not meet inclusion criteria

          -  Foster children

          -  Patients without primary caregiver

          -  Pregnant
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>1 Year</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>21 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Robert Rapaport, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Evan Graber, DO</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>11103</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Sperling MA, Weinzimer SA, Tamborlane WV. Diabetes Mellitus. In: Sperling MA ed. Pediatric Endocrinology. 3rd ed. Philadelphia, PA: Saunders Elsevier; 2008:385</citation>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wherrett DK, Bundy B, Becker DJ, DiMeglio LA, Gitelman SE, Goland R, Gottlieb PA, Greenbaum CJ, Herold KC, Marks JB, Monzavi R, Moran A, Orban T, Palmer JP, Raskin P, Rodriguez H, Schatz D, Wilson DM, Krischer JP, Skyler JS; Type 1 Diabetes TrialNet GAD Study Group. Antigen-based therapy with glutamic acid decarboxylase (GAD) vaccine in patients with recent-onset type 1 diabetes: a randomised double-blind trial. Lancet. 2011 Jul 23;378(9788):319-27. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60895-7. Epub 2011 Jun 27.</citation>
    <PMID>21714999</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Orban T, Bundy B, Becker DJ, DiMeglio LA, Gitelman SE, Goland R, Gottlieb PA, Greenbaum CJ, Marks JB, Monzavi R, Moran A, Raskin P, Rodriguez H, Russell WE, Schatz D, Wherrett D, Wilson DM, Krischer JP, Skyler JS; Type 1 Diabetes TrialNet Abatacept Study Group. Co-stimulation modulation with abatacept in patients with recent-onset type 1 diabetes: a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial. Lancet. 2011 Jul 30;378(9789):412-9. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60886-6. Epub 2011 Jun 28.</citation>
    <PMID>21719096</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pescovitz MD, Greenbaum CJ, Krause-Steinrauf H, Becker DJ, Gitelman SE, Goland R, Gottlieb PA, Marks JB, McGee PF, Moran AM, Raskin P, Rodriguez H, Schatz DA, Wherrett D, Wilson DM, Lachin JM, Skyler JS; Type 1 Diabetes TrialNet Anti-CD20 Study Group. Rituximab, B-lymphocyte depletion, and preservation of beta-cell function. N Engl J Med. 2009 Nov 26;361(22):2143-52. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa0904452.</citation>
    <PMID>19940299</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Gottlieb PA, Quinlan S, Krause-Steinrauf H, Greenbaum CJ, Wilson DM, Rodriguez H, Schatz DA, Moran AM, Lachin JM, Skyler JS; Type 1 Diabetes TrialNet MMF/DZB Study Group. Failure to preserve beta-cell function with mycophenolate mofetil and daclizumab combined therapy in patients with new- onset type 1 diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2010 Apr;33(4):826-32. doi: 10.2337/dc09-1349. Epub 2010 Jan 12.</citation>
    <PMID>20067954</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Wang L, Lovejoy NF, Faustman DL. Persistence of prolonged C-peptide production in type 1 diabetes as measured with an ultrasensitive C-peptide assay. Diabetes Care. 2012 Mar;35(3):465-70. doi: 10.2337/dc11-1236.</citation>
    <PMID>22355018</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Keenan HA, Sun JK, Levine J, Doria A, Aiello LP, Eisenbarth G, Bonner-Weir S, King GL. Residual insulin production and pancreatic ß-cell turnover after 50 years of diabetes: Joslin Medalist Study. Diabetes. 2010 Nov;59(11):2846-53. doi: 10.2337/db10-0676. Epub 2010 Aug 10.</citation>
    <PMID>20699420</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Effects of age, duration and treatment of insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus on residual beta-cell function: observations during eligibility testing for the Diabetes Control and Complications Trial (DCCT). The DCCT Research Group. J Clin Endocrinol Metab. 1987 Jul;65(1):30-6.</citation>
    <PMID>2884229</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Greenbaum CJ, Anderson AM, Dolan LM, Mayer-Davis EJ, Dabelea D, Imperatore G, Marcovina S, Pihoker C; SEARCH Study Group. Preservation of beta-cell function in autoantibody-positive youth with diabetes. Diabetes Care. 2009 Oct;32(10):1839-44. doi: 10.2337/dc08-2326. Epub 2009 Jul 8.</citation>
    <PMID>19587365</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>May 2014</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>April 8, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 2, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 6, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 2, 2014</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 2, 2014</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">May 6, 2014</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>C-peptide</keyword>
  <keyword>type 1 diabetes</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Diabetes Mellitus, Type 1</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

