<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02135094</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>TP-02</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>201306603</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02135094</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Low Intensity Ultrasound Therapy for Upper Back Pain Relief</brief_title>
  <official_title>Short Term Effects of Long Duration Low Intensity Continuous Ultrasound for Trapezius Muscle Pain</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>ZetrOZ, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>ZetrOZ, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to measure the effectiveness of a wearable therapeutic
      ultrasound device for relief of pain associated with the trapezius muscle of the upper back
      over a 4-week period. The trapezius muscle is a wide, flat, superficial muscle that covers
      most of the upper back and the posterior of the neck.The hypothesis is that the ultrasound
      device will lower the reported daily pain level of subjects suffering from trapezius muscle
      pain in their upper back.

      Subjects who participate in the study will self-administer the ultrasound device beginning at
      the onset of trapezius muscle pain, which is defined as a score of 3.0 or higher on a scale
      of 1-10. Subjects will be required to visit the clinical site at enrollment and weeks 2 and 4
      for a total of 3 visits. Subjects will report their daily pain levels in a diary.

      The wearable ultrasound device, Sam®, has been cleared by the FDA for pain relief, relief of
      joint contracture, relief of muscle spasm, and increased circulation.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The study will have approximately 60 subjects randomly assigned into a user group (active
      ultrasound device) of 40 participants or a control group (inactive ultrasound device) of 20
      participants with an equal number of males and females in each group. The research
      coordinator will be blinded to the assignment of devices to each group.

      The daily pain scores reported by patients who receive active devices will be compared to
      those who receive placebo devices.

      Background:

      Approximately 50 to 80 million people in the United States suffer from some form of chronic
      pain. Back pain is the most common neurological disorder in the United States after headaches
      and costs consumers nearly $50 billion annually. Pharmaceuticals currently dominate the
      treatment options despite a myriad of public health problems including cost, untoward side
      effects, and addiction to widely available opioid analgesics. Non-pharmaceutical treatments,
      such as the one under test, provide a safer and potentially lower cost alternative to
      traditional analgesic use.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in pain on the visual analog scale (VAS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 2, Week 4</time_frame>
    <description>Patients apply the ultrasound device when trapezius muscle pain exceeds a score of 3 or higher by VAS. Device maybe be worn safely for 4 h per day for 7 days a week. Patients record VAS score on days when the device is applied - before treatment, during treatment, and after treatment.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Comparison of pain level using Global Rating of Change (GROC) scale.</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 2, Week 4</time_frame>
    <description>GROC score will be recorded daily after treatment. Scores will be compared for baseline, Week 2, and Week 4</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change in trigger point depth</measure>
    <time_frame>Baseline, Week 2, Week 4</time_frame>
    <description>The certified examiner will measure depth at each trigger point location with a pressure algometer. The examiner will identify 2 trigger points on the subject's left and right upper trapezius muscle and place the algometer at the location. The examiner will apply small amounts of pressure to the algometer to measure the tightness of the muscle.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">60</enrollment>
  <condition>Muscle Spasm</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Active ultrasound therapy device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive treatment from the Sam Ultrasonic Diathermy Device for 4 hours on days when their trapezius muscle pain score is at least a 3 on a scale of 0-10 (VAS). The active device emits continuous ultrasound at 3 megahertz (MHz) frequency and 0.132 watts/cm2 intensity</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo ultrasound therapy device</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients apply the Sam Ultrasonic Diathermy Device for 4 hours on days when their trapezius muscle pain score is at least a 3 on a scale of 0-10 (VAS). The placebo device appears and operates identically to the active device except that it does not emit ultrasound.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sam Ultrasonic Diathermy Device (Active Device)</intervention_name>
    <description>low intensity continuous therapeutic ultrasound at 3 megahertz (MHz) frequency and 0.132 Watts/cm2 for treatment duration of 4 hours per day</description>
    <arm_group_label>Active ultrasound therapy device</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ZetrOZ ultrasound device</other_name>
    <other_name>wearable ultrasound device</other_name>
    <other_name>long duration ultrasound</other_name>
    <other_name>LITUS device</other_name>
    <other_name>long duration low intensity device</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Sam Ultrasonic Diathermy Device (Placebo Device)</intervention_name>
    <description>The placebo device appears and operates identically to the active device except that it does not emit ultrasound.</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo ultrasound therapy device</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>ZetrOZ ultrasound device</other_name>
    <other_name>wearable ultrasound device</other_name>
    <other_name>long duration ultrasound</other_name>
    <other_name>LITUS device</other_name>
    <other_name>long duration low intensity device</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Between the ages of 18 and 65 years.

          -  Has acute trapezius muscle pain that has been assessed by a health care practitioner.

          -  Has a VAS pain severity score of 3.0 or higher in the trapezius muscle 3-4 times over
             the past week prior to enrolling in the trial.

          -  Subjects must be willing and able to self-administer treatment daily within their
             place of residence or during normal daily activity, excluding bathing, showering, or
             other water activities which may result in submersion of the device under test.

          -  Not taken any prescription pain medications or muscle relaxers in the 5 days prior to
             the study and agree not to take any during the study and to maintain any dosage of
             NSAIDs (nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drug) or non-prescription pain medications
             constant during the study

          -  Has access to a mobile phone or camera and the help of another individual to take a
             picture of the upper back area immediately after use of the device

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Subjects with known neuropathy will be excluded from the study

          -  Women who are pregnant may not participate.

          -  Prisoners

          -  Smokers

          -  Subjects with Type I or Type II Diabetes

          -  Subjects who have had surgery in the target area within the last 6 months will be
             excluded from the study.

          -  Subjects who are non-ambulatory (i.e. who cannot walk) will be excluded from the
             study.

          -  Subjects who refuse to agree to not increase current use or initiate new use of pain
             medication during the course of the trial unless medically necessary to ensure patient
             safety.

          -  Subjects who refuse to agree to not use any cream, gel, or topical solution during the
             administration of treatment other than the approved ultrasound gel provided to the
             subject at the initiation of the study.

          -  Subjects who refuse to discontinue massage therapy or spinal manipulation during the
             duration of this study.

          -  Subjects who have had massage therapy within 1 day of beginning the protocol

          -  Subjects who refuse to discontinue all other interventional treatment modalities (i.e.
             transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation (TENS), ultrasound)

          -  Subjects who had a local corticosteroid or PRP (platelet-rich plasma) injection within
             the past 3 months.

          -  Subjects who have a clinically significant or unstable medical or psychological
             conditions that would compromise participation in the study.

          -  Subjects who have participated in another clinical trial for an investigational drug
             and/or agent within 30 days prior to screening.

          -  Subjects involved in any injury-related litigation in the target area.

          -  Subjects with abnormal neurological history, lumbar radicular symptoms, spinal
             stenosis, foot drop, herniated nucleus pulposus (gel-like substance within a spinal
             disc), or other structural defects.

          -  Subjects with back pain related to major trauma in the last 6 months

          -  Subjects with open sores or wounds in the treatment area that would prevent use of the
             device
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>65 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>George K. Lewis, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>ZetrOZ, Inc.</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>ZetrOZ, Inc.</name>
      <address>
        <city>Trumbull</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06611</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>January 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 2, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 7, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 9, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 17, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 17, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 18, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>trapezius</keyword>
  <keyword>upper back</keyword>
  <keyword>muscle pain</keyword>
  <keyword>pain relief</keyword>
  <keyword>ultrasound</keyword>
  <keyword>double blind</keyword>
  <keyword>Sam</keyword>
  <keyword>ZetrOZ</keyword>
  <keyword>muscle</keyword>
  <keyword>LITUS</keyword>
  <keyword>low intensity therapeutic ultrasound</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Spasm</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>May 9, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

