<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02139202</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>819466</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>CMS561871</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02139202</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Heartstrong Pilot Program</brief_title>
  <official_title>HeartStrong Pilot Program - Automated Hovering to Improve Medication Adherence Among Myocardial Infarction Patients</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a 6-month pilot study intended to test the effect of financial incentives on
      improving medication adherence in AMI patients; to test the effect on adherence of removing
      financial incentives; and to test the effect on the enrollment rate of modifying recruitment
      procedures.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This pilot study is part of a larger study. Our plan for testing the implementation of a new
      model for care delivery builds on infrastructure that we have developed and tested with NIH
      Support (RC2 AG036592-01, Asch and Volpp, Multiple PIs). We aim to improve medication
      adherence in patients following hospital admission for acute myocardial infarction (AMI).
      Poor adherence to cardioprotective medications leads to worse medical treatment outcomes,
      higher hospitalization and mortality rates, and increased health care costs among CAD
      patients.20,21(references listed in full grant submission) Hence, medication adherence among
      such patients is an important modifiable factor that affects the triple aim of improved
      health care quality, improved health, and lower cost.

      In this Pilot, we want to test an alternate approach to recruiting this patient population in
      hopes of increasing the enrollment rates to greater than that in the main trial. Our
      hypothesis is that if enrollment barriers are too high, the participants enrolling in the
      study already possess a predisposition to medication adherence based on their interest in
      research participation. By increasing the percentage of patients who enroll, we believe we
      will enable the research results to be more generalizable including more of the patient
      population, who may experience medication adherence problems as indicated in lack of
      willingness to participate in research. By increasing the percentage of patients who enroll,
      we are attempting to include more patients who may receive benefit of improved adherence
      offered in this program. In this pilot study we plan to recruit patients from UPHS Health
      System. Patients who decide to enroll will be placed into an abbreviated, 6-month version of
      our HeartStrong research program offered in the main intervention. The modification in
      recruitment procedures we are testing is the inclusion of the GlowCap electronic pill bottles
      in the recruitment mailings that we send to prospective participants, thus lowering the
      enrollment barrier by giving patients direct contact with the electronic pill bottles. We
      will examine the enrollment rate using this method in comparison to the methods used in the
      main intervention.

      We believe including the GlowCaps in the recruitment packet will provide a couple of
      benefits. First, participants will have the opportunity to see the pill bottles and have a
      better understanding of the study intervention from the beginning of the recruitment process.
      Second, our study team will be able to conduct the recruitment, verbal consent and GlowCap
      set up in the space of a single phone call. While this will make the phone call longer, the
      logistics of getting patients on the phone at multiple time points is challenging, so the
      opportunity to encapsulate these efforts in one call are beneficial for both the engagement
      advisors and the patients.

      We are also testing the effect upon adherence rates that removing financial incentives has on
      patient's medication adherence levels. Participants who choose to enroll in this research
      program will receive a compound set of approaches including: (1) provision of up to 4
      Vitality GlowCaps, a remote monitoring and medication bottle reminder device, for aspirin,
      beta blockers, statins and, if they received a stent for plavix or similar anti-platelet
      agents; (2) assignment of an engagement advisor from the study team; (3) enlisting a family
      member or friend (patient choice) as a support person for medication adherence; (4)
      engagement incentives that will use lotteries where winning will be dependent on medication
      adherence; and (5) self-service/customization of the Way to Health platform communication
      methods. Participants in this program will be offered all of these components; however, they
      are still able to participate even if they opt not to use any of the list above. At the
      3-month point, participants will be told the incentive portion has completed and they are to
      continue using their electronic pill bottles for 3 more months and they will receive all
      other components of the study.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>May 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">October 2016</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2015</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>N/A</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Health Services Research</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Recruitment Uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Primary outcomes will be recruitment uptake of patients discharged with recent AMI from the UPHS.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Enrollment Uptake</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 3 months</time_frame>
    <description>Primary outcomes will be the enrollment rate of targeted patients in this study.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Success of Process</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Secondary outcomes will be success of process outcomes as reported by the study team and reported by the recruited patients.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Removing Incentives</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>The effect of removing financial incentives on the medication adherence rate of participants.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Effects of Recruitment Methods on the Operational Processes</measure>
    <time_frame>up to 6 months</time_frame>
    <description>Additional outcomes will be success of process outcomes as reported by the study team and reported by the recruited patients.</description>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">17</enrollment>
  <condition>Acute Myocardial Infarction</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Full Program</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Other</arm_group_type>
    <description>The intervention will (1) use the GlowCaps, a remote monitoring and reminder pill bottle; (2) be assigned an engagement advisor from the study team; (3) be asked to provide the study team with names and contact information of up to 3 family members or friends as support partners for medication adherence. The study team will contact these people in order listed until 1 agrees to serve in this role; (4) will select a 2-digit lucky number to be used as part of the sweepstakes-based engagement incentives in which eligibility to win will be conditional on medication adherence for the first three months; and (5) will determine their preferences for Way to Health platform communication methods during the study.
The group receiving the program intervention will also have their claims data analyzed for the 1 months post-enrollment.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Social Influence</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Full Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Electronic Pill Bottles</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Full Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Behavioral</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Financial Incentives</intervention_name>
    <arm_group_label>Full Program</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients admitted to the University of Pennsylvania Health System who are discharged
             (or scheduled to be discharged) to their homes with a principal or secondary diagnosis
             code of International Classification of Diseases, 9th Revision, Clinical Modification
             (ICD-9-CM) 410 (except when the fifth digit was 2) and a length of stay of 1 to 180
             days will be considered eligible for the study. Patients must be between 18 and 80
             years old and have been discharged to home, 3) Patients are only eligible to enroll in
             the study for up to 60 days after their hospital discharge for a heart attack.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Patients will be excluded if they are less than 18 years old, will not or cannot give
             consent, or have a markedly shortened life expectancy (diagnosis of metastatic cancer,
             end-stage renal disease on dialysis, or dementia). Patients who have a known allergy
             or history of side effects to any of the 4 targeted classes of medications will be
             enrolled but provided GlowCaps only for the remaining medications.

        Patients with insurance coverage of one of the main study partners. (Horizon, Independence
        Blue Cross, Aetna, Keystone Mercy, and HealthFirst) (Please note, patients who are
        prescribed the anti-platelet Effient® (prasugrel) will not be given a GlowCap to use for
        this medication due to specific guidance about pill maintenance. The package insert for
        Effient® (prasugrel) (http://pi.lilly.com/us/effientppi.pdf) indicates the medication
        should remain in the original bottle, it should be kept at room temperature between 59°F to
        86°F (15°C to 30°C) and the container should be closed tightly with the gray cylinder
        inside and be protected from moisture. This does not necessarily exclude these patients
        from participation in the study, they will still be eligible as long as they have been
        prescribed at least 2 of the remaining 3 medications being observed in this study. Also,
        those who are taking an anti-platelet other than Effient® (prasugrel) (ie, Plavix) will be
        given a GlowCap to use to take that medication.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>80 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Shivan Mehta, MD, MBA</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>May 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 13, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 14, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 15, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>May 1, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>May 1, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">May 3, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Acute</keyword>
  <keyword>Myocardial</keyword>
  <keyword>Infarction</keyword>
  <keyword>AMI</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Infarction</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Myocardial Infarction</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

