<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02135718</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201344</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02135718</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>ELLIPTA™ vs. MDI Inhaler Preference Study, in Adult Subjects With Asthma</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Preference Study of Inhaler Attributes Between Two Inhalers; ELLIPTA and MDI, in Adult Subjects With Asthma</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      This is a multicenter, stratified, and randomized, open-label, placebo study in subjects with
      asthma to compare inhalers, ELLIPTA a new dry powder inhaler (DPI) and metered dose inhalers
      (MDI). This study is conducted to evaluate subject's preference of several inhaler-specific
      attributes individually between an existing MDI and the ELLIPTA a dry powder inhaler.
      Subjects who have not used the ELLIPTA inhaler in the past 6 months and their asthma must be
      controlled on their current therapy were enrolled. Subjects meeting the eligibility criteria
      will be stratified according to their current inhaler use (stable for the past 3 months): 1.)
      Currently using a DPI as an inhaled asthma controller therapy OR 2.) Currently using an MDI
      as an inhaled asthma controller therapy (No fluticasone MDI use in the last 3 months) OR 3.)
      Currently using no inhaled asthma controller therapy (this includes patients using a LTM
      and/or SABA only). Once stratified, eligible subjects were randomized (1:1) to one of two
      sequences for using the inhaler: ELLIPTA inhaler once daily in Period 1 followed by MDI twice
      daily in Period 2 or MDI twice daily in Period 1 followed by ELLIPTA inhaler once daily in
      Period 2 for for 5-9 days each. In addition, subjects will be randomly assigned (1:1
      allocation) to receive one of two sets of questions: Version 1 presents response options in
      the order of ELLIPTA inhaler, MDI, No preference; Version 2 presents response options in the
      order of MDI, ELLIPTA inhaler, No preference. At the end of the second trial period, subjects
      answered questions which assessed their preference of inhaler attributes. ELLIPTA is a
      registered trademark of the GSK group of companies.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>June 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">July 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">July 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <time_perspective>Prospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with the indicated inhaler preference based on the number of steps needed to use the inhaler</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 18</time_frame>
    <description>The number of participants who expressed the indicated device preference (i.e., preference for ELLIPTA inhaler, preference for MDI inhaler, and no preference) based on the number of steps needed to use the inhaler was summarized by prior inhaler use, by study inhaler use sequence, by preference question version and overall.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with the indicated inhaler preference based on how easy it is to tell how many doses you have left</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 18</time_frame>
    <description>The number of participants who expressed the indicated device preference (i.e., preference for ELLIPTA inhaler, preference for MDI inhaler, and no preference) based on how easy it is to tell how many doses you have left was summarized by prior inhaler use, by study inhaler use sequence, by preference question version and overall.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of participants with the indicated inhaler preference based on the comfort of the mouthpiece</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to Day 18</time_frame>
    <description>The number of participants who expressed the indicated device preference (i.e., preference for ELLIPTA inhaler, preference for MDI inhaler, and no preference) based on the comfort of the mouthpiece was summarized by prior inhaler use, by study inhaler use sequence, by preference question version and overall.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>2</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">288</enrollment>
  <condition>Asthma</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects will use the ELLIPTA inhaler once daily for 5 to 9 days during the first period followed by the MDI inhaler twice daily for 5 to 9 days during the second period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
    <description>Subjects will use the MDI inhaler twice daily for 5 to 9 days during the first period followed by the ELLIPTA inhaler once daily for 5 to 9 days during the second period.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>ELLIPTA inhaler</intervention_name>
    <description>ELLIPTA inhaler, placebo DPIwith 30 doses (2 strips with 30 blisters per strip containing lactose in strip first strip and Lactose blended with magnesium stearate in second strip)</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Device</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Inhalation Aerosol (MDI)</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo inhaler MDI will be supplied containing aerosol propellant</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Diagnosed and treated asthma patients aged 18 years or older
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Informed consent: Subject must give their signed and dated written informed consent to
             participate; Subject understands and is willing, able, and likely to comply with study
             procedures and restrictions; Subject must be able to read, comprehend, and record
             information in English.

          -  Age: &gt;=18 years of age at Visit 1

          -  Gender: Male or non-pregnant female subjects. Female subjects must not be pregnant at
             the time of Visit 1 based on the investigator's evaluation during medical history and
             physician examination.

          -  Asthma Diagnosis: Asthma as defined by the National Institutes of Health

          -  Reversibility of Disease: Demonstrated historical reversibility of &gt;=12% and &gt;=200
             milliliter (mL) reversibility of forced expiratory volume in one second (FEV1) within
             10-40 minutes following 2-4 inhalations of albuterol/salbutamol inhalation aerosol (or
             equivalent nebulized treatment with albuterol/salbutamol solution) within 24 months of
             Visit 1.

          -  Ability to use Inhalers: Subjects must demonstrate the ability to correctly use the
             ELLIPTA and MDI inhalers.

          -  Current asthma therapy: Subjects must be using one of the following three stable
             asthma therapies for at least 3 months prior to screening: a. Currently using a DPI as
             an inhaled asthma controller therapy; OR b. Currently using an MDI as an inhaled
             asthma controller therapy (No fluticasone MDI use in the last 3 months); OR c.
             Currently using no inhaled asthma controller therapy (this includes patients using a
             leukotriene modifiers (LTM) and/or short-acting beta2-agonists (SABA) as rescue only).
             All subjects will be allowed the concomitant use of their currently prescribed asthma
             treatment(s) throughout the study, including rescue albuterol MDI (SABA) as needed.

        Exclusion Criteria

          -  Pregnant: Women who are pregnant or lactating.

          -  MDI daily controller therapy: Subjects using Fluticatsone propionate (fluticasone HFA)
             MDI during the last 3 months.

          -  ELLIPTA USE: Subjects who used any ELLIPTA inhaler (e.g., participated in a clinical
             study of fluticasone furoate (FF) or FF/vilanterol (VI) or any component of them, or
             placebo) within 6 months (i.e., 180 days) prior to Visit 1.

          -  Asthma Control: Subjects who in the investigator's judgment have poorly controlled or
             have unstable asthma.

          -  Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (COPD): Subjects with a current primary
             diagnosis of COPD.

          -  History of Life-threatening asthma: Defined for this protocol as an asthma episode
             that required intubation and/or was associated with hypercapnea, respiratory arrest or
             hypoxic seizures.

          -  Asthma Exacerbation: Any asthma exacerbation requiring oral corticosteroids within 1
             month of Visit 1. A subject must not have had any hospitalization for asthma within 3
             months prior to Visit 1.

          -  Concurrent Diseases/Abnormalities: Historical or current evidence of clinically
             significant uncontrolled disease including, but not limited to: cardiovascular
             disease, hepatic disease, renal disease, hematological disease, neurological disease,
             or pulmonary disease (including, but not confined to chronic bronchitis, emphysema,
             bronchiectasis with the need of treatment, cystic fibrosis, bronchopulmonary
             dysplasia, and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease). Significant is defined as any
             disease that, in the opinion of the investigator, would put the safety of the subject
             at risk through participation, or which would affect the efficacy or safety analysis
             if the disease/condition exacerbated during the study.

          -  Oropharyngeal Examination: A subject will not be eligible for the study if he/she has
             clinical visual evidence of oral candidiasis at Visit 1.

          -  Investigational Medications: A subject must not have used any investigational drug
             within 30 days prior to Visit 1.

          -  Drug Allergy: Known or suspected sensitivity to the constituents of the placebo dry
             powder inhaler or MDI (i.e. lactose or magnesium stearate).

          -  Milk Protein Allergy: History of severe milk protein allergy.

          -  Tobacco Use. Current smoker or a smoking history of 10 pack years or more (e.g. 20
             cigarettes/day for 10 years)

          -  Affiliation with Investigator's Site: A subject will not be eligible for this study if
             he/she is an immediate family member of the participating Investigator,
             sub-Investigator, study coordinator, or employee of the participating Investigator.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Huntington Beach</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92647</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Newport Beach</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92663</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Vista</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92083</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Aventura</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33180</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Baltimore</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>21236</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Bethesda</city>
        <state>Maryland</state>
        <zip>20814</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>North Dartmouth</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02747</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Minneapolis</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55402</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Plymouth</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55441</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Canton</city>
        <state>Ohio</state>
        <zip>44718</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Medford</city>
        <state>Oregon</state>
        <zip>97504</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Orangeburg</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29118</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Spartanburg</city>
        <state>South Carolina</state>
        <zip>29303</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Austin</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78750</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78229</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>June 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>May 8, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 8, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 12, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 6, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 6, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 8, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ELLIPTA</keyword>
  <keyword>Asthma</keyword>
  <keyword>Inhaler preference</keyword>
  <keyword>Fluticasone furoate</keyword>
  <keyword>ELLIPTA inhaler</keyword>
  <keyword>Dry Powder Inhaler</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Asthma</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

