<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02134314</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>C1INH (Berinert) for DGF</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>IND15806</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02134314</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>C1INH Inhibitor Preoperative and Post Kidney Transplant to Prevent DGF &amp; IRI</brief_title>
  <acronym>C1INHDGF</acronym>
  <official_title>Assessing Safety and Efficacy of Preoperative and Post-Transplant C1 Inhibitor (Berinert速) vs. Placebo in Recipients of a Renal Allograft From Deceased High Risk Donors and Its Impact on DGF and IRI</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The use of C1INH (Berinert) in patients receiving deceased donor kidney transplants with high
      risk for delayed graft function (DGF) may show significant improvement in outcomes post
      transplant compared with patients that do not receive C1INH treatment. Complement activation
      has been detected in animal models and human kidneys with ischemic reperfusion injury (IRI)
      and inflammatory cell infiltrates. By blocking complement activation the investigators hope
      to improve kidney graft function post transplant in these recipients.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Early graft function has a long-term effect on graft survival. Poor early graft function and
      DGF contributes to decreased short- and long-term patient and graft survival, increased
      incidence of acute rejection, prolonged hospitalization, and higher costs of transplantation.
      Although multiple factors contribute to the impaired graft function, ischemia-reperfusion
      injury (IRI) is the underlying pathophysiology leading to poor early graft function and DGF.
      A &gt;35% incidence of DGF has remained constant over time despite significant improvements in
      immunosuppressive strategies and patient management. This may be due to increased use of
      kidneys from &quot;extended-criteria&quot; and/or non-heart-beating donors, where even greater rates
      (&gt;60%) of DGF have been reported.

      More than 96,680 people are currently waiting for a kidney transplant in the United States
      (UNOS.org 3/22/13). Of the 15,092 kidney transplants performed in the US in 2011, ~11,000
      (62%) were from deceased donors. Of these, approximately 17% were from expanded-criteria
      donors. The USRDS reports that more than 50% of patients on the waiting list are willing to
      accept a kidney from an expanded-criteria donor (ECD) or DCD donor.

      From the investigators previous studies with C1INH (Berinert速) for prevention of antibody
      mediated rejection (ABMR), the investigators noted that no patients developed ABMR during
      treatment with C1INH, the investigators also noted a near significant reduction in delayed
      graft function (DGF) due to ischemia/reperfusion injury(IRI)(ClinicalTrials.gov(NCT01134510),
      FDA IND: 14363). These findings suggest an important role for complement in the mediation of
      IRI and that inhibition of early complement activation using C1INH in patients receiving at
      risk kidneys for IRI should reduce this costly and often devastating complication of kidney
      transplantation. In addition, numerous other studies in animal models have shown dramatic
      improvements in IRI models with the use of C1INH. Complement activation is detectable in
      animal and in human kidneys models after IRI and experimental data suggests that use of C1INH
      prior to induction of IRI significantly reduces IRI as well as inflammatory cell infiltrates.
      Based on this, the investigators hypothesize that the use of C1INH in patients receiving
      deceased donor (DD) kidney transplants with high risk for DGF will show significant
      reductions in DGF and improved outcomes post-transplant compared with patients receiving DD
      transplants who do not receive C1INH treatment. Here, the investigators propose to
      investigate the application of pre-operative and post-transplant doses of C1INH (Berinert速)
      vs. placebo in adult subjects receiving a DD renal allograft considered at high-risk for IRI
      and DGF. The investigators hypothesize that C1INH treated patients will demonstrate improved
      function of the kidney allograft compared to placebo, with equivalence in safety. The primary
      objectives of this study are: Using a double blinded, placebo controlled format, the
      investigators will:

      1. Evaluate and compare the safety of C1INH (50 U/kg, round to the nearest 500unit)
      administered pre-transplant and 24 hrs post-transplant in recipients of kidney allografts
      from high risk for IRI deceased donors. The secondary objectives are to:

        1. On the basis of safety and efficacy, determine appropriate Berinert速 study dose for
           Phase III investigation, and

        2. Determine appropriate endpoint choice for Phase III investigation.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2014</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 13, 2017</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">March 13, 2017</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1/Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Triple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients enrolled with serum creatinine &gt;3mg/dL on postoperative day 5.</measure>
    <time_frame>First 7 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients enrolled who require at least one session of dialysis in the first 7 days post transplant.</measure>
    <time_frame>First 7 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with serum creatinine reduction ratio of &lt; 30% from 24 to 48 hours post-transplant.</measure>
    <time_frame>First 2 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of dialysis sessions per patient in the first 7 days post transplant.</measure>
    <time_frame>First 7 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Serum Creatinine</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Creatinine Clearance</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>24h urine output</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of Dialysis use and duration per patient</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of patients with delayed graft function (DGF) (categorized by DGF scale)</measure>
    <time_frame>First 7 days</time_frame>
    <description>DGF Scale:
Grade 1 - immediate urine production and no need for dialysis with creatinine reduction ratio (CRR) between time 0 of transplantation and day 7 post-transplantation &gt;70%
Grade 2 - creatinine reduction ratio (CRR) between time 0 of transplantation and day 7 post-transplantation of &gt;70% with need for dialysis
Grade 3 - creatinine reduction ratio (CRR) between time 0 of transplantation and day 7 post-transplantation &lt;70% with no need for dialysis
Grade 4 - creatinine reduction ratio (CRR) between time 0 of transplantation and day 7 post-transplantation of &lt;70% with need for dialysis.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Overall incidence of adverse events and serious adverse events and relationship of AE and SAEs to the study treatment</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluation of blood chemistry, hematology, and coagulation parameters</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Patient and graft survival</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <other_outcome>
    <measure>Rate of acute cellular rejection (ACR)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 90 days</time_frame>
  </other_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">70</enrollment>
  <condition>End Stage Renal Disease</condition>
  <condition>Kidney Failure</condition>
  <condition>Delayed Graft Function</condition>
  <condition>Ischemic Reperfusion Injury</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>C1-Inhibitor (Berinert) (Human) (C1INH)</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>35 patients will receive C1 esterase inhibitor in addition to standard of care immunosuppressive therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Placebo Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>35 patients will receive placebo in addition to standard of care immunosuppressive therapy.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>C1 Esterase Inhibitor</intervention_name>
    <description>C1 Esterase Inhibitor 50 units/kg IVPB administered on day of transplant, and another dose 24 hours post op. Total: 2 doses</description>
    <arm_group_label>C1-Inhibitor (Berinert) (Human) (C1INH)</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Berinert (C1INH)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo</intervention_name>
    <description>Placebo medication identical to study drug (C1 esterase inhibitor) volume will be administered on day of transplant, and another dose 24 hours post op. Total: 2 doses</description>
    <arm_group_label>Normal Saline</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Normal Saline (0.9%NaCl)</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  18-70yrs; recipient of ECD/DCD/ECD&amp;DCD with risk index 3-8 for DGF based on specific
             criteria

          -  recipient who are ABO compatible with donor allograft

          -  pretransplant with meningococcal vaccination

          -  understand and sign a written consent prior to any study specific procedure.

        Risk index (minimum 3- maximum 8):

        DGF scale: Donor Age (&lt;40yr = 0, 41-49yr = 1, 50-54yr = 2, 55-59yr = 3, &gt;60yr=6), Cold
        Ischemia Time (0-12= 0, 13-18=1, 19-24=2, 24-30=3, 31-36=4, &gt;37=6; Recipient Race (nonblack
        = 0, black =1); Donor death due to CVA (donor age &lt;50yrs = 0, donor age &gt;50yrs = 3).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  patients with known prothrombotic disorder (e.g. factor V leiden)

          -  history of thrombosis or hypercoagulable state excluding access clotting

          -  history of administration of C1INH containing products or recombinant C1INH within 15
             days prior to study entry

          -  patients with known contraindication to treatment with C1INH

          -  patients with abnormal coagulation function (INR &gt;2, PTT&gt; 50, PLT&lt;80,000)

          -  who are not on anti-coagulation

          -  patients with known active presence of malignancies

          -  PCR positive for hep B/hep C/or HIV

          -  preemptive kidney transplantation recipient

          -  recipients of multi-organ transplants (kidney and any other organ)

          -  recipients of kidney allograft from DD who: CIT &lt;18h, terminal serum creatinine &lt;/=
             1mg/dl, recipient of kidney allograft that was on pump preservation for any period
             prior to transplantation, recipient of kidney allograft from a living donor, female
             subject who are pregnant or lactating.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Stanley C Jordan, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center, Los Angeles, CA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ashley Vo, PharmD</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center, Los Angeles, CA</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</name>
      <address>
        <city>Los Angeles</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>90048</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>http://cedars-sinai.edu/Patients/Quality-Measures/Clinical-Areas/Transplantation/Kidney-Transplantation.aspx</url>
    <description>Cedars Sinai Medical Center Kidney Transplantation</description>
  </link>
  <link>
    <url>http://www.berinert.com/</url>
    <description>Information of C1INH (Berinert)</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Dalle Lucca JJ, Li Y, Simovic M, Pusateri AE, Falabella M, Dubick MA, Tsokos GC. Effects of C1 inhibitor on tissue damage in a porcine model of controlled hemorrhage. Shock. 2012 Jul;38(1):82-91. doi: 10.1097/SHK.0b013e31825a3522.</citation>
    <PMID>22683724</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Pascual J, Zamora J, Pirsch JD. A systematic review of kidney transplantation from expanded criteria donors. Am J Kidney Dis. 2008 Sep;52(3):553-86. doi: 10.1053/j.ajkd.2008.06.005. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18725015</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Castellano G, Melchiorre R, Loverre A, Ditonno P, Montinaro V, Rossini M, Divella C, Battaglia M, Lucarelli G, Annunziata G, Palazzo S, Selvaggi FP, Staffieri F, Crovace A, Daha MR, Mannesse M, van Wetering S, Paolo Schena F, Grandaliano G. Therapeutic targeting of classical and lectin pathways of complement protects from ischemia-reperfusion-induced renal damage. Am J Pathol. 2010 Apr;176(4):1648-59. doi: 10.2353/ajpath.2010.090276. Epub 2010 Feb 11.</citation>
    <PMID>20150432</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Giral-Classe M, Hourmant M, Cantarovich D, Dantal J, Blancho G, Daguin P, Ancelet D, Soulillou JP. Delayed graft function of more than six days strongly decreases long-term survival of transplanted kidneys. Kidney Int. 1998 Sep;54(3):972-8.</citation>
    <PMID>9734625</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>February 19, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>May 8, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">May 9, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 18, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 18, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 20, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Principal Investigator</responsible_party_type>
    <investigator_affiliation>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</investigator_affiliation>
    <investigator_full_name>Stanley Jordan, MD</investigator_full_name>
    <investigator_title>Medical Director, Kidney Transplant Program; Director of Transplant Immunology and Nephrology</investigator_title>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>ESRD</keyword>
  <keyword>CKD</keyword>
  <keyword>Kidney Transplant</keyword>
  <keyword>ECD</keyword>
  <keyword>delayed graft function</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Kidney Failure, Chronic</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Renal Insufficiency</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Reperfusion Injury</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Delayed Graft Function</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Complement C1s</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Complement C1 Inhibitor Protein</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Complement C1 Inactivator Proteins</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <pending_results>
    <submitted>March 13, 2018</submitted>
    <returned>April 13, 2018</returned>
    <submitted>May 8, 2018</submitted>
  </pending_results>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

