<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00760864</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>01-03-TL-715-005</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>2004-002157-30</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>U1111-1114-2984</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00760864</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Safety and Efficacy of TAK-715 in Subjects With Rheumatoid Arthritis</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo-Controlled, Dose-Ranging Study to Evaluate the Safety and Efficacy of Oral TAK-715 in the Treatment of the Signs and Symptoms of Rheumatoid Arthritis</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Takeda</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Takeda</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the safety and efficacy of TAK-715, twice daily
      (BID), in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis signs and symptoms in patients with a partial
      response to methotrexate.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Rheumatoid arthritis affects approximately 1% of the adult population, and is a chronic,
      progressive disease characterized by synovial inflammation. The resulting inflammation leads
      to destruction of the synovium and surrounding joint tissues, which can result in cartilage
      destruction, bone erosion and resultant loss of joint function. It is an autoimmune disorder
      of unknown etiology and typically affects the joints of the hand, wrist, knee, and foot,
      usually in a bilateral pattern. Symptoms experienced early in the disease process include
      pain, swelling, and tenderness of affected joints. As the disease progresses, many patients
      experience joint stiffness, weakness, fatigue, anorexia, and weight loss, and ultimately
      tissue damage and joint destruction. The severity of symptoms varies widely, ranging from
      annoyance to debilitation. Rheumatoid arthritis is a disease that primarily afflicts adults,
      with women being affected more often than men. Because rheumatoid arthritis is both chronic
      and destructive, it requires early diagnosis and aggressive treatment to minimize the
      morbidity associated with its progression, which can lead to deterioration in physical
      function and psychological and social well-being. The objectives of rheumatoid arthritis
      therapy are to reduce inflammation and to decrease the progression of articular damage.
      Disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs are used to accomplish these objectives.

      During the past several years, rheumatologists have become increasingly aggressive in
      initiating treatment with disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs early in the course of
      rheumatoid arthritis in an attempt to prevent joint destruction. The gold standard of therapy
      has been methotrexate, which has been shown to be efficacious and safe, and appears to remain
      effective, even after many years of treatment. However, not all patients respond to
      methotrexate, and even patients who do respond most frequently have only a partial response
      (reduced signs and symptoms, but still active disease). As a result, many patients are
      treated with 2 or more disease-modifying antirheumatic drugs at the same time.

      More recently, biologics (biotechnology drugs) have been introduced in the armamentarium
      against rheumatoid arthritis, based on an improved understanding of the role of the
      proinflammatory mediators, TNF-alpha, interleukin-1, and interleukin-6 in rheumatoid
      arthritis. Etanercept (Enbrel®), a soluble TNF-alpha type II receptor-human immunoglobulin
      fusion protein administered subcutaneously twice a week, infliximab (Remicade®), a chimeric
      human mouse monoclonal antibody against TNF-alpha, administered intravenously every 4 to 8
      weeks along with weekly methotrexate, and adalimumab (Humira®), a human-derived recombinant
      immunoglobulin monoclonal antibody, administered subcutaneously every other week, are
      currently available for treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. They have demonstrated rapid and
      substantial improvement in rheumatoid arthritis, presumably by preventing the actions of
      TNF-alpha in the joint, thereby reducing the inflammatory and destructive consequences of
      TNF-alpha. Etanercept and infliximab have been granted Food and Drug Administration (FDA)
      approved indications for reducing signs and symptoms, inhibiting the progression of
      structural damage and improving physical function of patients with moderately to severely
      active rheumatoid arthritis. Adalimumab has been granted FDA approved indications for
      reducing signs and symptoms and inhibiting the progression of structural damage, and Anakinra
      (Kineret®), an interleukin-1 receptor antagonist administered subcutaneously daily, received
      FDA approval for reducing signs and symptoms.

      TAK-715 is a p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase inhibitor that has shown in nonclinical
      studies to decrease proinflammatory cytokine production, specifically tumor necrosis factor-α
      (TNF-α), interleukin (IL)-1, and IL-6. These cytokines are thought to be pivotal mediators of
      inflammation and the resultant joint destruction in rheumatoid arthritis. TAK-715 has also
      been shown to inhibit the production of cyclooxygenase-2-mediated prostanoids and nitric
      oxide as well as oppose the differentiation of osteoclasts, each of which contributes to the
      joint damage associated with rheumatoid arthritis.

      Individuals who participate in this study will provide written informed consent and will be
      required to commit to a screening visit and up to approximately 5 additional visits at the
      study center. Study participation is anticipated to be up to 6 months. Multiple procedures
      will occur at each visit which may include fasting, blood collection, urine collection,
      physical examinations and electrocardiograms. Participants will be required to provide
      detailed medical histories related to rheumatoid arthritis and complete multiple
      questionnaires.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2004</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2005</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2005</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Quadruple (Participant, Care Provider, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite ACR 20% improvement response rate from baseline with 3 of the following: pain assessment; disease activity; physical function; C-reactive protein and erythrocyte sedimentation rate.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite ACR 50% improvement response rate from baseline with 3 of the following: swollen-tender joint counts; pain assessment; disease activity; physical function; C-reactive protein and erythrocyte sedimentation rate.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Composite ACR 70% improvement response rate from baseline with 3 of the following: swollen-tender joint counts; pain assessment; disease activity; physical function; C-reactive protein and erythrocyte sedimentation rate.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6.</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in swollen and tender joint counts.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in patient's assessment of pain.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in patient's global assessment of disease activity.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in physician's assessment of disease activity.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in patient's self assessment of physical function using the Health Assessment Questionnaire.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in C-reactive protein.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Change from baseline in erythrocyte sedimentation rate.</measure>
    <time_frame>Week 6</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to American College of Rheumatology 20% improvement response.</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 2, 4, and 6</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to American College of Rheumatology 50% improvement response.</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 2, 4, and 6</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Time to American College of Rheumatology 70% improvement response.</measure>
    <time_frame>Weeks 2, 4, and 6</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>4</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">432</enrollment>
  <condition>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TAK-715 25 mg BID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TAK-715 50 mg BID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TAK-715 100 mg BID</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Methotrexate</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TAK-715 and methotrexate</intervention_name>
    <description>TAK-715 25 mg, tablets, orally, twice daily and methotrexate stable dose for up to 6 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TAK-715 25 mg BID</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TAK-715 and methotrexate</intervention_name>
    <description>TAK-715 50 mg, tablets, orally, twice daily and methotrexate stable dose for up to 6 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TAK-715 50 mg BID</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>TAK-715 and methotrexate</intervention_name>
    <description>TAK-715 100 mg, tablets, orally, twice daily and methotrexate stable dose for up to 6 weeks.</description>
    <arm_group_label>TAK-715 100 mg BID</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Methotrexate</intervention_name>
    <description>TAK-715 placebo-matching, tablets, orally, twice daily and methotrexate stable dose for up to 6 weeks</description>
    <arm_group_label>Methotrexate</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Had a diagnosis of rheumatoid arthritis using American College of Rheumatology
             criteria of at least 6 months duration.

          -  A female subject of childbearing potential who is sexually active must agree to use
             adequate contraception, and must be neither pregnant nor lactating from Screening
             throughout the duration of the study.

          -  Had a physical examination at Screening that revealed no clinically significant
             abnormalities (other than rheumatoid arthritis) in the investigator's opinion.

          -  Had clinical laboratory test results at Screening that were normal or, if abnormal,
             were not clinically significant in the investigator's opinion.

          -  Had a 12-lead electrocardiogram at Screening that was normal or, if abnormal, was not
             clinically significant in the investigator's opinion.

          -  Had a chest x-ray within 6 months prior to or during the Pretreatment Period that, in
             the investigator's opinion, showed no signs of active tuberculosis and was free of
             clinically significant findings.

          -  Had a negative purified protein derivative skin test for tuberculosis (less than or
             equal to 5 mm in duration) during the Screening Period.

          -  Had been receiving oral or parenteral methotrexate for at least 6 months prior to
             Baseline and must have been on a stable dose (12.5 to 25 mg per week, inclusive) of
             methotrexate for at least 4 weeks prior to Baseline. The subject must have been on a
             dose of folic acid at greater than or equal to 1 mg/day.

          -  Had at least 6 swollen and 9 tender joints using the 66/68 joint count scale at
             Screening and Baseline.

          -  At Screening, the subject must have had a C-reactive protein of at least 1.2 mg/dL or
             an erythrocyte sedimentation rate of at least 28 mm/hr.

          -  For individuals who were taking a systemic corticosteroid, the maintenance dose of
             prednisone, or its equivalent, could not exceed 10 mg/day and must have been stable
             for at least 4 weeks prior to Baseline and must have remained at that stable dose
             throughout the study.

          -  For individuals who were taking a nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug for the
             treatment of rheumatoid arthritis, the maintenance dose of the nonsteroidal
             anti-inflammatory drug must have been stable for at least 4 weeks prior to Baseline
             and must have remained at that stable dose throughout the study.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Had been diagnosed with any type of arthritis at age 16 or younger.

          -  Had a history of a clinically significant illness, medical condition, or laboratory
             abnormality within 3 months prior to Baseline that, in the investigator's opinion,
             would preclude the subject's participation in the study.

          -  Had a known history of human immunodeficiency virus infection.

          -  Had a known history of hepatitis B or C.

          -  Had uncontrolled hypertension.

          -  Had moderate or severe liver disease at Screening, as defined by at least 1 of the
             following conditions:

               -  Aspartate transaminase or alanine transaminase greater than 1.2 times the upper
                  limit of normal.

               -  Total bilirubin greater than 1.2 times upper limit of normal (excluding subjects
                  diagnosed with Gilbert's disease).

               -  Alkaline phosphatase greater than 1.5 times upper limit of normal.

          -  Had elevated serum creatinine level for age and gender at Screening.

          -  Had hemoglobin less than 9.0 g/dL, white blood cell count of less than 3000/mm3, or a
             platelet count less than 100,000/mm3 at Screening.

          -  Had an American College of Rheumatology revised rheumatoid arthritis functional status
             of IV at Screening.

          -  Had taken, is required to take or intends to continue taking any disallowed
             medication, any prescription medication, herbal treatment or over-the counter
             medication that may interfere with evaluation of the study medication, including:

               -  A disease-modifying antirheumatic drug or a biologic agent other than
                  methotrexate in the 8 weeks prior to Baseline, including:

                    -  Plaquenil.

                    -  Sulfasalazine.

                    -  Tetracycline.

                    -  infliximab (Remicade®).

                    -  leflunomide (Arava®).

                    -  etanercept (Enbrel®).

                    -  anakinra (Kineret®).

               -  Had failed therapy due to lack of efficacy with any anti- tumor necrosis factor
                  agent.

               -  Had failed due to lack of efficacy with more than 2 disease-modifying
                  antirheumatic drugs (other than methotrexate).

               -  Had received any intra-articular, intramuscular, or intravenous corticosteroids
                  within 4 weeks prior to Baseline.

               -  The subject had any previous use of cyclophosphamide, chlorambucil, or other
                  alkylating agent.

          -  Was at high risk of an opportunistic infection because of a compromised immune system,
             in the investigator's opinion, with the exception of subjects receiving chronic
             steroid treatment.

          -  Had a history of or a current inflammatory condition with signs and symptoms that
             could have confounded the diagnosis of rheumatoid arthritis (eg, connective tissue
             disease, systemic lupus erythematosus, psoriasis, psoriatic arthritis,
             spondyloarthropathy).

          -  Had been diagnosed as having a secondary, non-inflammatory type of arthritis (eg,
             osteoarthritis or fibromyalgia) that, in the investigator's opinion, was symptomatic
             enough to interfere with the evaluation of the efficacy of the study drug on the
             subject's primary diagnosis of rheumatoid arthritis.

          -  Had a history of drug abuse or alcohol abuse within the past 2 years.

          -  The subject had a body mass index greater than 35 at Screening.

          -  Had a history of cancer, other than basal cell carcinoma, that had not been in
             remission for at least 5 years prior to the first dose of study drug.

          -  Had a known hypersensitivity to TAK-715 or its constituents.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>VP Biological Sciences</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>Takeda</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>June 2010</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>September 24, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>September 24, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">September 26, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 9, 2010</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 9, 2010</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">June 11, 2010</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Sr. VP, Clinical Science</name_title>
    <organization>Takeda Global Research &amp; Development Center, Inc.</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Rheumatoid Arthritis</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug Therapy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Arthritis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Arthritis, Rheumatoid</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Methotrexate</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

