<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00766155</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>EORTC-40054-22062</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>EU-20880</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>PETACC-6</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>ROCHE-EORTC-40054</secondary_id>
    <secondary_id>2006-006532-21</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00766155</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Chemotherapy and Radiation Therapy Before Surgery Followed by Capecitabine With or Without Oxaliplatin in Treating Patients With Locally Advanced Rectal Cancer</brief_title>
  <acronym>PETACC-6</acronym>
  <official_title>Preoperative Chemoradiotherapy and Postoperative Chemotherapy With Capecitabine and Oxaplatin vs.Capecitabine Alone in Locally Advanced Rectal Cancer (PETACC-6)</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer - EORTC</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer - EORTC</source>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      RATIONALE: Drugs used in chemotherapy, such as capecitabine and oxaliplatin, work in
      different ways to stop the growth of tumor cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping
      them from dividing. Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays to kill tumor cells. Giving
      radiation therapy that uses a 3-dimensional image of the tumor to help focus thin beams of
      radiation directly on the tumor may kill more tumor cells and have fewer side effects. Giving
      chemotherapy together with radiation therapy before surgery may make the tumor smaller and
      reduce the amount of normal tissue that needs to be removed. Giving chemotherapy after
      surgery may kill any tumor cells that remain after surgery. It is not yet known whether
      capecitabine is more effective with or without oxaliplatin in treating patients with rectal
      cancer.

      PURPOSE: This randomized phase III trial is studying giving chemotherapy together with
      radiation therapy before surgery followed by capecitabine with or without oxaliplatin to see
      how well it works in treating patients with locally advanced rectal cancer.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      OBJECTIVES:

      Primary

        -  Investigate whether the addition of oxaliplatin to neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy and
           adjuvant chemotherapy comprising capecitabine improves disease-free survival in patients
           with locally advanced rectal cancer.

      Secondary

        -  Compare the overall survival of patients with locally advanced rectal cancer treated
           with neoadjuvant chemoradiotherapy and adjuvant chemotherapy comprising capecitabine
           with versus without oxaliplatin.

        -  Determine the loco-regional failure and distant failure of patients treated with these
           regimens.

        -  Determine the pathological down-staging (ypT0-2N0) of patients treated with these
           regimens.

        -  Determine the pathological complete remission (yp T0N0) rate of patients treated with
           these regimens.

        -  Determine the tumor progression grade and histopathological R0 resection of patients
           treated with these regimens.

        -  Determine the sphincter preservation rate of patients treated with these regimens.

        -  Determine the perioperative complication rate of these regimens in these patients.

        -  Determine the toxicity of these regimens in these patients.

      OUTLINE: This is a multicenter study. Patients are stratified according to treating center,
      clinical T category (T1-3 vs T4), clinical nodal status (Nx vs NO vs N1-2), distance from the
      tumor to the anal verge (≤ 5 cm vs &gt; 5 cm) and method of locoregional staging (EUS+MRI vs
      EUS+CTscan vs MRI alone). Patients are randomized to 1 of 2 treatment arms.

        -  Arm I (control):

             -  Neoadjuvant therapy: Patients receive oral capecitabine twice daily on days 1-35.
                Patients also undergo concurrent 3-dimensional conformal radiotherapy 5 days a week
                on days 1-33 followed by surgery. Patients may receive additional chemoradiotherapy
                on days 36-38.

             -  Adjuvant therapy: Beginning 4-8 weeks after surgery, patients receive oral
                capecitabine twice daily on days 1-15. Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for 6
                courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.

        -  Arm II (investigational):

             -  Neoadjuvant therapy: Patients receive oral capecitabine twice daily and undergo
                concurrent 3-dimensional conformal radiotherapy 5 days a week on days 1-33.
                Patients also receive oxaliplatin IV over 1 hour on days 1, 8, 15, 22, and 29 prior
                to radiotherapy followed by surgery. Patients may receive additional
                chemoradiotherapy on days 36-38.

             -  Adjuvant therapy: Beginning 4-8 weeks after surgery, patients receive oxaliplatin
                IV over 2 hours on day 1 and oral capecitabine twice daily on days 1-15. Treatment
                repeats every 3 weeks for 6 courses in the absence of disease progression or
                unacceptable toxicity.

      After completion of study therapy, patients are followed every 3 months for 3 years, and then
      every 6 months for 2 years.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>August 2008</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <primary_purpose>Treatment</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Disease-free survival</measure>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Overall survival within at least the first 5 years after treatment</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Loco-regional failure, defined as local or regional recurrence, inoperable disease, or R1 or R2 resection</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Distant failure (i.e., distant metastasis)</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathological down-stage (ypT0, 2N0) rate</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Pathological complete remission (ypT0N0) rate</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Tumor regression grade</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Histopathological R0 resection rate</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Sphincter preservation rate</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Preoperative complication rate</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Toxicity according to CTCAE v.3.0 weekly during treatment, at 4-8 weeks after surgery, at therapy completion, and every 6 months for 5 years after therapy completion</measure>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1094</enrollment>
  <condition>Colorectal Cancer</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive oral capecitabine twice daily and undergo concurrent 3-dimensional conformal radiotherapy 5 days a week on days 1-33. Patients may receive additional chemoradiotherapy on days 36-38. Patients then undergo surgery. Beginning 4-8 weeks after surgery, patients receive capecitabine twice daily on day 1-15. Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for up to 6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Patients receive oral capecitabine twice daily and undergo concurrent 3-dimensional conformal radiotherapy 5 days a week on days 1-33. Patients also receive oxaliplatin IV over 1 hour on days 1, 8, 15, 22, and 29 prior to radiotherapy followed by surgery. Patients may receive additional chemoradiotherapy on days 36-38. Beginning 4-8 weeks later, patients receive oxaliplatin IV over 2 hours on day 1, and oral capecitabine twice daily on days 1-15. Treatment repeats every 3 weeks for up to 6 courses in the absence of disease progression or unacceptable toxicity.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>capecitabine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given orally</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm I</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>oxaliplatin</intervention_name>
    <description>Given IV</description>
    <arm_group_label>Arm II</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        DISEASE CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  Histologically confirmed adenocarcinoma of the rectum

               -  Tumor ≤ 12 cm from the anal verge

               -  Stage T3-4 or any node-positive disease

          -  No evidence of metastatic disease (confirmed by negative CT scan of the chest and
             abdomen)

          -  Resectable disease or expected to become resectable after preoperative chemoradiation

          -  May only be randomized once in this trial

        PATIENT CHARACTERISTICS:

          -  WHO/ECOG performance status 0-2

          -  Hemoglobin ≥ 10.0 g/dL (transfusion allowed to achieve or maintain levels)

          -  ANC ≥ 1,500/mm^3

          -  Platelet count ≥ 100,000/mm^3

          -  ALT and AST ≤ 2.5 times upper level of normal (ULN)

          -  Alkaline phosphatase ≤ 2.5 times ULN

          -  Total bilirubin ≤ 1.5 times ULN

          -  Creatinine clearance &gt; 50 mL/min

          -  Creatinine ≤ 1.5 times ULN

          -  Able to swallow tablets

          -  No prior or concurrent malignancies within the past 5 years except for adequately
             treated cone-biopsied carcinoma in situ of the cervix or basal cell carcinoma of the
             skin

          -  No clinically significant (i.e., active) cardiac disease, including any of the
             following:

               -  Congestive heart failure

               -  Symptomatic coronary artery disease

               -  Cardiac arrhythmia

          -  No myocardial infarction within the past 12 months

          -  No known significant impairment of intestinal resorption (e.g., chronic diarrhea,
             inflammatory bowel disease)

          -  No pre-existing conditions that would preclude chemoradiotherapy or radiotherapy
             (i.e., fistulas, severe ulcerative colitis [particularly patients currently taking
             sulfasalazine], Crohn's disease, or prior adhesions)

          -  No peripheral neuropathy ≥ grade 2 by CTCAE v3.0

          -  No serious uncontrolled intercurrent infections or other serious uncontrolled
             concomitant disease

          -  No history of uncontrolled seizures, central nervous system disorders or psychiatric
             disability that, in the opinion of the principal investigator, is clinically
             significant and would preclude giving informed consent or interfere with compliance
             with oral drug administration

          -  No psychological, familial, sociological, or geographical condition potentially
             hampering compliance with the study protocol and follow-up schedule

          -  Not pregnant or nursing

          -  Fertile patients must use effective contraception

        PRIOR CONCURRENT THERAPY:

          -  No prior cytotoxic chemotherapy or radiation therapy for rectal cancer

          -  No prior radiation therapy to the pelvis

          -  No prior or concurrent investigational drug, agent, or procedure

          -  More than 4 weeks since prior participation in the active or follow-up period of
             another investigational protocol

          -  No known allergy or any other adverse reaction to any of the study drugs or to any
             related compound

          -  No known dihydropyrimidine dehydrogenase deficiency

          -  No organ allograft requiring immunosuppressive therapy

          -  No concurrent sorivudine or chemically related analogues (e.g., brivudine)
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>120 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Hans-Joachim Schmoll, MD, PhD</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>Martin-Luther-Universität Halle-Wittenberg</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Karin Haustermans</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>U.Z. Gasthuisberg, Leuven</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <removed_countries>
    <country>Germany</country>
  </removed_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 2, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 2, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 3, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 11, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 11, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 12, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>stage II rectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>stage III rectal cancer</keyword>
  <keyword>adenocarcinoma of the rectum</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Colorectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Rectal Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Capecitabine</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Oxaliplatin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

