<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00766701</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>GT1</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00766701</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Spectroscopic Evaluation of Cervical Neoplasia</brief_title>
  <official_title>Pivotal Study for Assessment of Cervical Neoplasia Using Fluorescence and Reflectance Spectroscopy</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Guided Therapeutics</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>National Cancer Institute (NCI)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Guided Therapeutics</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The overall objective of this study is to evaluate whether fluorescence and reflectance
      spectroscopy can improve the ability to detect the presence of premalignant lesions on the
      cervix.

      The specific aims of the study are:

        -  To compare information obtained from fluorescence and reflectance spectroscopic
           measurements of the cervix with standard methods for detecting cervical pre-cancers.

        -  To validate previously developed algorithms for discriminating between normal and
           pre-cancerous tissue based on spectroscopic measurements.

        -  To evaluate the safety of spectroscopic measurement of cervical tissue.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      If you agree to take part in this study, spectroscopic measurements on your cervix will be
      made for research purposes, prior to your routine colposcopy examination.

      MEASUREMENT PROCEDURE:

      The doctor will first place a vaginal speculum and then perform the LightTouch Ã Â® procedure
      (that looks at tissue from the cervix using light). The doctor will use a fresh single use
      contact tube (a tube attached to the LightTouch device that helps hold it in place) and apply
      it gently to your cervix. This will transmit light much like a flashlight. The light will
      either reflect or bounce immediately off your cervix or it will enter the skin for less than
      a second, and then return back to the LightTouch device. Each reading will take about 5-7
      minutes, and up to two readings may be taken. You may also be asked to repeat the
      experimental test the same day, for example 2 to 3 hours after the first test, as part of
      another experimental procedure to study whether the device gives the same result twice in a
      row on the same woman (a repeatability study). If you agree to a second (LightTouch)
      procedure you will again have placement of the contact tube applied gently to your cervix and
      another test will be taken. This could take another 5 to 7 minutes of your time.

      Whether you agree to do one of the experimental tests or both of the tests, following the
      LightTouch experimental procedure(s), you will have a Pap smear of the endocervix (the doctor
      will use a small plastic brush remove cells from the endocervix canal). We will also test for
      human papilloma virus (HPV). HPV is a virus that is sexually transmitted is associated with
      abnormal Pap smears. The doctor will use two separate vials for these tests, one to take your
      Pap smear and the other to take more cells for an HPV test. Once the doctor takes your Pap
      smear and HPV test. The doctor will do the colposcopy exam using a colposcope to look at the
      cervix more closely to check for abnormal areas. The doctor will also apply acetic acid and
      Lugols if required. The doctor may also perform biopsy (remove one or more tissue samples
      you're your cervix) for later examination by a pathologist. If considered necessary, an ECC
      (Endocervical Curettage scraping of cells from the inside of the endocervix) will be
      performed if an abnormal area is seen.

      A video image (camera) will be used to capture locations of abnormal areas and compare with
      the readings from the spectroscopic image. Your overall study participation time will be
      approximately 30 minutes. If you are asked to participate in second test and agree, it will
      take place directly after the first test. The spectroscopy portion in which measurements are
      taken takes 5 to 7 minutes to complete. If you have the second study procedure this will take
      an additional 15-30 minutes making your overall participation time up to 60 minutes (one
      hour). You may be asked to re-test one time during the same visit if the information
      collected is bad because of movement or if the device did not work.

      The results of the LightTouch test will be compared with the results of your colposcopy and
      biopsy. The results of the LightTouch test test will not be used to plan your treatment. If
      your biopsy results show any abnormal changes, your doctor will discuss treatment options
      with you.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>January 2003</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">September 2008</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">September 2008</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Cohort</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Retrospective</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Determine the efficacy of the CNDS, within the context of current ASCCP guidelines, to more effectively triage women with ASC/LSIL results, women with positive HPV results and women being followed for previous cervical dysplasia.</measure>
    <time_frame>December 2008</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>A second objective is to prospectively demonstrate equivalence between two versions of the CNDS used in the pivotal trial.</measure>
    <time_frame>Q1 2009</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1599</enrollment>
  <condition>Cervical Neoplasia</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Procedure</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Procedure: Spectroscopy and Digital Imaging</intervention_name>
    <description>Procedure: Spectroscopy and Digital Imaging</description>
    <other_name>Spectroscopy</other_name>
    <other_name>Digital Imaging</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <biospec_retention>Samples With DNA</biospec_retention>
  <biospec_descr>
    <textblock>
      histology slides
    </textblock>
  </biospec_descr>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        Double-blind, Prospective, Safety-efficacy study
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Age 16 or above

          -  Able to read or understand and give informed consent

          -  Scheduled for colposcopy

          -  Pap test within 120 days

          -  Willing to undergo a Pap test and HPV test on day of study

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Pregnancy

          -  Menstruating on the day of colposcopy and CNDS test

          -  Radiation therapy to her genitourinary system within 1 year

          -  Prior hysterectomy

          -  Congenital anatomical cervical variant (e.g., double cervix)

          -  Friable cervix at the time of the study (i.e., a cervix that bleeds easily upon
             minimal contact or trauma)

          -  Post-coital or other significant bleeding at the time of the exam

          -  Excessive cervical mucous or discharge that cannot be removed and is significant
             enough, in the opinion of the investigator, to interfere with a Pap test or
             colposcopy, resulting from inflammatory, bacterial or other sources

          -  History of any photosensitizing disease or other disease affected by Ultra-violet
             radiation, (e.g., pophyria, Lupus Erythematosus).

          -  Undergoing phototherapy

          -  Recent use of photosensitizing agents, such as fluoroquinolones or retinoids).

          -  Patients who are pregnant are not eligible for this study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Female</gender>
    <minimum_age>16 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Lisa Flowers, MD</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Emory University/Grady Hospital System</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Arkansas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Little Rock</city>
        <state>Arkansas</state>
        <zip>72205</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Orange Coast/Saddleback</name>
      <address>
        <city>Laguna Beach</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>92653</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Saint Francis Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Hartford</city>
        <state>Connecticut</state>
        <zip>06112</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Miami</name>
      <address>
        <city>Miami</city>
        <state>Florida</state>
        <zip>33136</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Grady Memorial Hospital</name>
      <address>
        <city>Atlanta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30303</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Medical College of Georgia</name>
      <address>
        <city>Augusta</city>
        <state>Georgia</state>
        <zip>30912</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Texas</name>
      <address>
        <city>Dallas</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>75390</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>October 2008</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>October 3, 2008</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>October 3, 2008</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">October 6, 2008</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>October 3, 2008</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>October 3, 2008</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">October 6, 2008</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Dr. Lisa Flowers M.D.</name_title>
    <organization>Emory University</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Neoplasms</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

