<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01475695</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>115243</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01475695</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>GSK2251052 Mass Balance in Healthy Adult Subjects</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open Label, Non-Randomized, Single Dose, Mass Balance Study to Investigate the Recovery, Excretion, and Pharmacokinetics of 14C-GSK2251052 Administered as a Single Intravenous Dose to Healthy Adult Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Approximately 6 healthy male subjects will be administered a single 1500 mg intravenous dose
      of 14C-GSK2251052 under fasted conditions. Blood, urine and fecal samples will be collected
      for a minimum of 14 days following study drug administration. Safety and tolerability will be
      monitored throughout the study. A follow-up visit will occur 7-14 days after study drug
      administration.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date type="Actual">April 21, 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">May 19, 2011</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 19, 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Other</primary_purpose>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Evaluate pharmacokinetic parameters for GSK2251052 and radiolabeled compound following intravenous dose</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the concentration-time curve from time zero (pre-dose) extrapolated to infinite time</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Area under the concentration-time curve from time zero (pre-dose) to last time of quantifiable concentration within a subject across all treatments</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Maximum observed concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Time of occurrence of maximum observed concentration</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Terminal phase half-life</measure>
    <time_frame>Up tp 14 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Systemic clearance of parent drug</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Volume of distribution</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Percent recovery of total radiocarbon in urine and feces</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Urine, fecal recovery and total recovery of radioactivity (as a percentage of total radioactive dose in each interval and cumulative)</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Adverse events, vital signs, electrocardiogram and clinical laboratory assessments.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Collection of samples for characterization and quantification, or estimation, of GSK2251052-related metabolites in plasma, urine and fecal homogenates to be conducted under a separate protocol.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 14 days</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">6</enrollment>
  <condition>Community-acquired Infection</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Single cohort</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>14C GSK2251052</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>14C GSK2251052</intervention_name>
    <description>1500 mg iv dose GSK2251052</description>
    <arm_group_label>Single cohort</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Healthy as determined by a responsible and experienced physician, based on a medical
             evaluation including medical history, physical examination, laboratory tests and ECG.
             A subject with a clinical abnormality or laboratory parameters outside the reference
             range for the population being studied may be included only if the Investigator and
             the GSK Medical Monitor agree that the finding is unlikely to introduce additional
             risk factors and will not interfere with the study procedures.

          -  Male between 30 and 55 years of age inclusive, at the time of signing the informed
             consent.

          -  Male subjects must agree to use one of the contraception methods listed in Section
             8.1. This criterion must be followed from the time of the first dose of study
             medication through at least 90 days following the dose of GSK2251052.

          -  Body weight equal to or greater than 50 kg and BMI within the range 18.5-30.0 kg/m2
             (inclusive).

          -  Capable of giving written informed consent, which includes compliance with the
             requirements and restrictions listed in the consent form.

          -  QTcB less than 450 msec or QTc less than 480 msec in subjects with Bundle Branch
             Block.

          -  Available to complete the study and return for follow-up visits if necessary.

          -  A history of regular bowel movements (averaging one or more bowel movements per day).

          -  AST, ALT, alkaline phosphatase and bilirubin equal to or less than 1.5xULN (isolated
             bilirubin greater than 1.5xULN is acceptable if bilirubin is fractionated and direct
             bilirubin less than 35%).

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Female subjects.

          -  A positive pre-study Hepatitis B surface antigen or positive Hepatitis C antibody
             result within 3 months of screening.

          -  Current or chronic history of liver disease, or known hepatic or biliary abnormalities
             (with the exception of Gilbert's syndrome or asymptomatic gallstones).

          -  A positive pre-study drug/alcohol screen. A minimum list of drugs that will be
             screened for include amphetamines, barbiturates, cocaine, opiates, cannabinoids and
             benzodiazepines.

          -  A positive test for HIV antibody.

          -  History of regular alcohol consumption within 6 months of the study defined as: an
             average weekly intake of greater than 21 units for males or greater than14 units for
             females. One unit is equivalent to 8 g of alcohol: a half-pint (approximately 240 ml)
             of beer, 1 glass (125 ml) of wine or 1 (25 ml) measure of spirits.

          -  The subject has participated in a clinical trial and has received an investigational
             product within the following time period prior to the first dosing day in the current
             study: 30 days, 5 half-lives or twice the duration of the biological effect of the
             investigational product (whichever is longer).

          -  Exposure to more than four new chemical entities within 12 months prior to the first
             dosing day.

          -  Use of prescription or non-prescription drugs, including vitamins, herbal and dietary
             supplements (including St John's Wort) within 7 days (or 14 days if the drug is a
             potential enzyme inducer) or 5 half-lives (whichever is longer) prior to the first
             dose of study medication, unless in the opinion of the Investigator and GSK Medical
             Monitor the medication will not interfere with the study procedures or compromise
             subject safety.

          -  History of sensitivity to any of the study medications, or components thereof or a
             history of drug or other allergy that, in the opinion of the investigator or GSK
             Medical Monitor, contraindicates their participation.

          -  Where participation in the study would result in donation of blood or blood products
             in excess of 500 mL within a 56 day period

          -  Unwillingness or inability to follow the procedures outlined in the protocol.

          -  Subject is mentally or legally incapacitated.

          -  History of sensitivity to heparin or heparin-induced thrombocytopenia.

          -  Urinary cotinine levels indicative of smoking or history or regular use of tobacco- or
             nicotine-containing products within 6 months prior to screening.

          -  Consumption of red wine, seville oranges, grapefruit or grapefruit juice [and/or
             pummelos, exotic citrus fruits, grapefruit hybrids or fruit juices] from 7 days prior
             to the first dose of study medication.

          -  Subjects who have received a total body radiation dose of greater than 5.0 mSv (upper
             limit of WHO category II) or exposure to significant radiation (e.g. serial x-ray or
             CT scans, barium meal etc) in the 12 months prior to this study.

          -  Any condition that could interfere with the accurate assessment and recovery of
             radioactivity [14C].

          -  Participation in a clinical trial involving administration of 14C-labelled compound(s)
             within the last 12 months.

          -  Subjects with a pre-existing condition interfering with normal gastrointestinal
             anatomy or motility, hepatic and/or renal function, that could interfere with the
             absorption, metabolism, and/or excretion of the study drugs. Subjects with a history
             of cholecystectomy should be excluded.

          -  The subject's systolic blood pressure is outside the range of 90-140 mmHg, or
             diastolic blood pressure is outside the range of 45-90 mmHg or heart rate is outside
             the range of 45-100 bpm. A single repeat is allowed to determine eligibility.

          -  Exclusion criteria for screening ECG per protocol.(a single repeat is allowed for
             eligibility determination).
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Male</gender>
    <minimum_age>30 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>55 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>GSK Investigational Site</name>
      <address>
        <city>Zuidlaren</city>
        <zip>9471 GP</zip>
        <country>Netherlands</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>Netherlands</country>
  </location_countries>
  <link>
    <url>https://www.gsk-clinicalstudyregister.com/study/115243?search=study&amp;search_terms=115243#rs</url>
    <description>Results for study 115243 can be found on the GSK Clinical Study Register.</description>
  </link>
  <reference>
    <citation>Bowers GD, Tenero D, Patel P, Huynh P, Sigafoos J, O'Mara K, Young GC, Dumont E, Cunningham E, Kurtinecz M, Stump P, Conde JJ, Chism JP, Reese MJ, Yueh YL, Tomayko JF. Disposition and metabolism of GSK2251052 in humans: a novel boron-containing antibiotic. Drug Metab Dispos. 2013 May;41(5):1070-81. doi: 10.1124/dmd.112.050153. Epub 2013 Feb 25.</citation>
    <PMID>23439661</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>June 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 17, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 17, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 21, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>June 27, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>June 27, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">June 28, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Mass balance</keyword>
  <keyword>intravenous</keyword>
  <keyword>GSK2251052</keyword>
  <keyword>Healthy volunteer</keyword>
  <keyword>Antimicrobial</keyword>
  <keyword>Radiolabel</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Community-Acquired Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

