<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01479296</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>HVTN 085</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>10796</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01479296</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Evaluating the Immune Response to a rAd5 HIV Vaccine Administered in Three Different Ways in Healthy, HIV-Uninfected Adults</brief_title>
  <official_title>A Phase 1b Randomized Double-Blind Clinical Trial to Examine Whether Polytopic Administration of VRC rAd5 Gag-pol/Env A/B/C Vaccine Enhances HIV-Specific Cellular Immune Responses in Humans</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</agency>
      <agency_class>NIH</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases (NIAID)</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the immune response to the Vaccine Research Center
      (VRC) rAd5 HIV vaccine when the vaccine components are administered in three different ways,
      in healthy, HIV-uninfected adults.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The VRC rAd5 HIV vaccine contains four different components. In this study, researchers will
      examine how the immune system responds to the vaccine when the four components are
      administered in three different ways:

        1. The vaccine dose containing all four components is given as a single injection in one
           arm, and placebo injections are given in the other arm and both legs.

        2. The vaccine dose containing all four components is divided into fourths, and one-fourth
           of the full dose is given in each arm and leg.

        3. The four vaccine components are separated, and a different component is given in each
           arm and leg.

      This study will enroll healthy, HIV-uninfected adults. Participants will be randomly assigned
      to one of three groups. Group 1 will receive the entire dose of vaccine in their right arm
      and placebo vaccine in the other arm and both legs. Group 2 will receive all four different
      components of the vaccine, given separately as a different component per each arm and leg.
      Group 3 will receive the entire vaccine dose divided into fourths, with one fourth of the
      full dose given in each arm and leg.

      At a baseline study visit, participants will undergo a physical examination and a medical and
      medication history review. Female participants will also take a pregnancy test. Participants
      will complete questionnaires and receive counseling on HIV risk reduction and pregnancy
      prevention. All participants will then receive vaccine given as four injections—one each in
      their right arm, left arm, right thigh, and left thigh (except for Group 1, placebo
      injections are given in left arm and both legs). After receiving the vaccine, participants
      will remain in the clinic for at least 30 minutes for observation and monitoring of side
      effects. For 7 days after the vaccination, participants will record any side effects in a
      symptom log; for the first 3 days after the vaccination, study staff will call participants
      to ensure they are completing the symptom log. Follow-up visits will occur at Months 1, 4,
      and 7. These visits will include the baseline study procedures and a blood collection.
      Participants will be contacted by study researchers once a year for 5 years for follow-up
      health monitoring. Blood collected during study visits will be saved for future testing.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Active, not recruiting</overall_status>
  <start_date>December 2011</start_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">May 2013</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Prevention</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Participant, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Number of recognized epitopes as measured by enzyme-linked immunospot (ELISpot)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at 4 weeks following vaccination</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Total magnitude of gene-specific CD4 and CD8 T-cell responses as measured by intracellular cytokine staining (ICS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at 4 weeks following vaccination</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total vaccine-specific CD4 and CD8 T-cell responses as measured by ICS</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at 4 weeks following vaccination</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Total vaccine-specific CD4 and CD8 T-cell responses as measured by ICS</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at 28 weeks following vaccination</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Polyfunctional CD4 and CD8 T-cell responses across one and multiple antigenic components of VRC rAd5 HIV vaccine as measured by ICS</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at 28 weeks following vaccination</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Antibody binding to HIV epitopes by multiplex binding antibody assay and/or peptide array</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at 28 weeks following vaccination</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Local and systemic reactogenicity signs and symptoms, laboratory measures of safety, adverse events (AEs), and serious adverse events (SAEs) reported on an expedited basis to the Division of AIDS (DAIDS)</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at 28 weeks following vaccination</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>T-cell receptor beta chain sequence diversity of epitope-specific CD4 and CD8 T cells</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at 28 weeks following vaccination</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Human leukocyte antigen (HLA) type, epitope-specific T-cell responses as measured by ELISpot, ICS, tetramer, and/or other assays</measure>
    <time_frame>Measured at 28 weeks following vaccination</time_frame>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>3</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Anticipated">90</enrollment>
  <condition>HIV Infections</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1: rAd5 Plus Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the VRC rAd5 gag-pol/env A/B/C vaccine injection in their right arm (1×10^10 PU), and placebo vaccine injections in their left arm, right thigh, and left thigh.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2: Separated Vaccine Components</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the rAd5 gag-pol vaccine injection in their right arm (0.5×10^10 PU), the rAd5 env A vaccine injection in their left arm (0.17×10^10 PU), the rAd5 env B vaccine injection in their right thigh (0.17×10^10 PU), and the rAd5 env C vaccine injection in their left thigh (0.17×10^10 PU).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3: Divided Dose rAd5</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
    <description>Participants will receive the VRC rAd5 gag-pol/env A/B/C vaccine injection divided into fourths, with one fourth of the total dose given in each of 4 sites: right arm, left arm, right thigh, and left thigh (each at 0.25×10^10 PU).</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>VRC rAd5 vaccine (rAd5 gag-pol/env A/B/C)</intervention_name>
    <description>Given intramuscularly</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1: rAd5 Plus Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Group 3: Divided Dose rAd5</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>VRC-HIVADV014-00-VP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rAd5 env A</intervention_name>
    <description>Given intramuscularly</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2: Separated Vaccine Components</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>VRC-HIVADV038-00-VP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rAd5 env B</intervention_name>
    <description>Given intramuscularly</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2: Separated Vaccine Components</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>VRC-HIVADV052-00-VP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rAd5 env C</intervention_name>
    <description>Given intramuscularly</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2: Separated Vaccine Components</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>VRC-HIVADV053-00-VP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>rAd5 gag-pol</intervention_name>
    <description>Given intramuscularly</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 2: Separated Vaccine Components</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>VRC-HIVADV054-00-VP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Biological</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Placebo Vaccine</intervention_name>
    <description>Given intramuscularly</description>
    <arm_group_label>Group 1: rAd5 Plus Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>VRC-DILUENT013-DIL-VP</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Access to a participating HIV Vaccine Trials Network (HVTN) clinical research site
             (CRS) and willing to be followed for the planned duration of the study

          -  Able and willing to provide informed consent

          -  Demonstrates understanding of this study and that in a previous trial there was an
             association of increased acquisition of HIV with receipt of that study vaccine;
             completes a questionnaire prior to vaccination with verbal demonstration of
             understanding of all questionnaire items answered incorrectly

          -  Willing to receive HIV test results

          -  Willing to discuss HIV infection risks, amenable to HIV risk reduction counseling, and
             committed to maintaining behavior consistent with low risk of exposure to HIV through
             the last required study visit

          -  Willing to be contacted annually after completion of scheduled clinic visits for a
             total of 5 years following initial study injection

          -  Agrees not to enroll in another study of an investigational research agent prior to
             completion of last required study visit (excludes annual contacts for safety
             surveillance)

          -  In good general health as shown by medical history, physical exam, and screening
             laboratory tests

          -  Assessed by the clinic staff as being at &quot;low risk&quot; of HIV infection on the basis of
             sexual behaviors. More information on this criterion can be found in the protocol.

          -  Body weight greater than or equal to 110 lb (greater than or equal to 50 kg)

          -  Hemoglobin greater than or equal to 12.5 g/dL for participants who were born female;
             greater than or equal to 13.5 g/dL for participants who were born male

          -  White blood cell count between 3300 to 12,000 cells/mm^3

          -  Total lymphocyte count greater than or equal to 800 cells/mm^3

          -  Remaining differential either within institutional normal range or with site physician
             approval

          -  Platelets between 125,000 to 550,000/mm^3

          -  Alanine aminotransferase (ALT) less than 1.25 times the institutional upper limit of
             normal

          -  Ad5 neutralizing antibody titer less than 1:18

          -  Negative HIV-1 and -2 blood test: U.S. participants must have a negative Food and Drug
             Administration (FDA)-approved enzyme immunoassay (EIA). Non-U.S. sites may use locally
             available assays that have been approved by HVTN Laboratory Operations.

          -  Negative hepatitis B surface antigen (HBsAg)

          -  Negative anti-hepatitis C virus antibodies (anti-HCV) or negative HCV polymerase chain
             reaction (PCR) if the anti-HCV is positive

          -  Participants who were born female: negative serum or urine beta human chorionic
             gonadotropin pregnancy test performed prior to vaccination on the day of vaccination

          -  Participants who were born female must agree to consistently use effective
             contraception from at least 21 days prior to enrollment through the last required
             study visit for sexual activity that could lead to pregnancy; or not be of
             reproductive potential, such as having reached menopause (no menses for 1 year) or
             having undergone hysterectomy, bilateral oophorectomy, or tubal ligation; or be
             sexually abstinent. More information on this criterion can be found in the protocol.

          -  Participants who were born female must also agree not to seek pregnancy through
             alternative methods, such as artificial insemination or in vitro fertilization until
             after the last required study visit

          -  Participants who were born male must be fully circumcised (as documented at screening
             examination)

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Excessive daily alcohol use, frequent binge drinking, chronic marijuana abuse, or any
             other use of illicit drugs within the 12 months prior to study entry

          -  History of newly acquired syphilis, gonorrhea, nongonococcal urethritis, herpes
             simplex virus type 2 (HSV2), chlamydia, pelvic inflammatory disease (PID),
             trichomonas, mucopurulent cervicitis, epididymitis, proctitis, lymphogranuloma
             venereum, chancroid, or hepatitis B within the 12 months prior to study entry

          -  Untreated or incompletely treated syphilis infection

          -  HIV vaccine(s) received in a prior HIV vaccine trial. For potential participants who
             have received control/placebo in an HIV vaccine trial, the HVTN 085 Protocol Safety
             Review Team (PSRT) will determine eligibility on a case-by-case basis.

          -  Non-HIV experimental vaccine(s) received within the 5 years prior to study entry in a
             previous vaccine trial. Exceptions may be made for vaccines that have subsequently
             undergone licensure by the FDA. For potential participants who have received
             control/placebo in an experimental vaccine trial, the HVTN 085 PSRT will determine
             eligibility on a case-by-case basis. For potential participants who have received an
             experimental vaccine(s) more than 5 years ago, eligibility for enrollment will be
             determined by the PSRT on a case-by-case basis.

          -  Immunosuppressive medications received within 168 days before first vaccination. (Not
             excluded: 1) corticosteroid nasal spray for allergic rhinitis; 2) topical
             corticosteroids for mild, uncomplicated dermatitis; or 3) oral/parenteral
             corticosteroids given for nonchronic conditions not expected to recur [length of
             therapy 10 days or less with completion at least 30 days prior to study entry].)

          -  Blood products received within 120 days before the first vaccination

          -  Immunoglobulin received within 60 days before the first vaccination

          -  Live attenuated vaccines other than influenza vaccine received within 30 days before
             the first vaccination or scheduled within 14 days after injection (e.g., measles,
             mumps, and rubella [MMR]; oral polio vaccine [OPV]; varicella; yellow fever)

          -  Influenza vaccine or any vaccines that are not live attenuated vaccines and were
             received within 14 days prior to the first vaccination (e.g., tetanus, pneumococcal,
             hepatitis A or B)

          -  Allergy treatment with antigen injections within 30 days before the first vaccination
             or that are scheduled within 14 days after the first vaccination

          -  Investigational research agents received within 30 days before the first vaccination

          -  Intent to participate in another study of an investigational research agent during the
             planned duration of the study

          -  Current anti-tuberculosis prophylaxis or therapy

          -  Clinically significant medical condition, physical examination findings, clinically
             significant abnormal laboratory results, or past medical history with clinically
             significant implications for current health. More information on this criterion can be
             found in the protocol.

          -  Any medical, psychiatric, occupational, or other condition that, in the judgment of
             the investigator, would interfere with, or serve as a contraindication to, study
             adherence, assessment of safety or reactogenicity, or a participant's ability to give
             informed consent

          -  Serious adverse reactions to vaccines, including anaphylaxis and related symptoms such
             as hives, respiratory difficulty, angioedema, and/or abdominal pain. (Not excluded: a
             participant who had a nonanaphylactic adverse reaction to pertussis vaccine as a
             child.)

          -  Autoimmune disease

          -  Immunodeficiency

          -  Asthma other than mild, well-controlled asthma. More information on this criterion can
             be found in the protocol.

          -  Diabetes mellitus type 1 or type 2, including cases controlled with diet alone. (Not
             excluded: history of isolated gestational diabetes.)

          -  Thyroidectomy or thyroid disease requiring medication during the 12 months before
             study entry

          -  History of hereditary angioedema, acquired angioedema, or idiopathic angioedema

          -  Hypertension: If a person has been found to have elevated blood pressure or
             hypertension during screening or previously, exclude for blood pressure that is not
             well controlled. If a person has NOT been found to have elevated blood pressure or
             hypertension during screening or previously, exclude for systolic blood pressure
             greater than or equal to 150 mm Hg at study entry or diastolic blood pressure greater
             than or equal to 100 mm Hg at study entry. More information on this criterion can be
             found in the protocol.

          -  Body mass index (BMI) greater than or equal to 40; or BMI greater than or equal to 35
             with two or more of the following factors: age greater than or equal to 45 years old,
             systolic blood pressure greater than 140 mm Hg, diastolic blood pressure greater than
             90 mm Hg, current smoker, or known hyperlipidemia

          -  Bleeding disorder diagnosed by a doctor (e.g., factor deficiency, coagulopathy,
             platelet disorder requiring special precautions)

          -  Cancer (Not excluded: a participant with a surgical excision and subsequent
             observation period that in the investigator's estimation has a reasonable assurance of
             sustained cure or is unlikely to recur during the period of the study.)

          -  Seizure disorder (Not excluded: a participant with a history of seizures who has not
             required medications or had a seizure in the 3 years prior to study entry.)

          -  Asplenia: any condition resulting in the absence of a functional spleen

          -  Psychiatric condition that precludes compliance with the study. Specifically excluded
             are people with psychoses within the 3 years prior to study entry, ongoing risk of
             suicide, or history of suicide attempt or gesture within the 3 years prior to study
             entry.

          -  Pregnant or breastfeeding

          -  Has been fully circumcised within 90 days prior to the first vaccination or displays
             evidence that surgical site is not fully healed
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Ian Frank</last_name>
    <role>Study Chair</role>
    <affiliation>University of Pennsylvania</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Bridge HIV CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Francisco</city>
        <state>California</state>
        <zip>94143</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>UIC Project WISH CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Chicago</city>
        <state>Illinois</state>
        <zip>60612</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Brigham and Women's Hospital Vaccine CRS (BWH VCRS)</name>
      <address>
        <city>Boston</city>
        <state>Massachusetts</state>
        <zip>02115-6110</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Columbia P&amp;S CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10032-3732</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>New York Blood Center CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>New York</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>10065</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>University of Rochester Vaccines to Prevent HIV Infection CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>New York</state>
        <zip>14642</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Penn Prevention CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Vanderbilt Vaccine (VV) CRS</name>
      <address>
        <city>Nashville</city>
        <state>Tennessee</state>
        <zip>37232-2582</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <reference>
    <citation>Appay V, Douek DC, Price DA. CD8+ T cell efficacy in vaccination and disease. Nat Med. 2008 Jun;14(6):623-8. doi: 10.1038/nm.f.1774. Review.</citation>
    <PMID>18535580</PMID>
  </reference>
  <reference>
    <citation>Vezys V, Yates A, Casey KA, Lanier G, Ahmed R, Antia R, Masopust D. Memory CD8 T-cell compartment grows in size with immunological experience. Nature. 2009 Jan 8;457(7226):196-9. doi: 10.1038/nature07486. Epub 2008 Nov 12.</citation>
    <PMID>19005468</PMID>
  </reference>
  <verification_date>December 2017</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 22, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 22, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 24, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>December 14, 2017</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>December 14, 2017</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Actual">December 18, 2017</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>HIV Infections</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Vaccines</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

