<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01471418</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>813671</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01471418</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>The Use of PET/CT to Evaluate Synovitis in the Temporomandibular Joint (TMJ)</brief_title>
  <official_title>Investigation of the Use of Positron Emission Tomography With 18F-FDG PET/CT for the Diagnosis of Synovitis in the Temporomandibular Joint</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>University of Pennsylvania</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>University of Pennsylvania</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Temporomandibular joint disorders (TMD) are a common musculoskeletal problem with an
      estimated 40-75 percent of the population reporting at least one sign. Up to fifteen percent
      of the patients who seek care for one of these conditions, will go on to develop chronic
      pain. The two most common TMD conditions include myofascial pain disorder and internal
      derangement of the Temporomandibular Joint (TMJ). These two conditions have similar clinical
      presentations, making an accurate diagnosis difficult. Currently, there is no accurate exam
      or test to differentiate between these two conditions.

      Internal derangement of the TMJ is a condition with disk displacement, pain, and dysfunction,
      which may progress to localized osteoarthritis. Fortunately, this condition is self-limiting
      for the majority of the patients afflicted, with a small minority progressing to advanced
      joint destruction, disability and chronic pain.18 Currently there are no prognostic
      indicators to identify these individuals. There are three hypothesis of degenerative TMJ
      disease, they include: direct mechanical trauma, hypoxia reperfusion injuries, and neurogenic
      inflammation. All involve parafunctional habits such as clenching or grinding by the patient
      and a low-grade inflammatory response/synovitis. 18-fluorodeoxyglucose (18-FDG), a
      radioisotope used with positron emission tomography (PET) and paired with a CT scan (PET/CT),
      may have a role in imaging inflammation in arthritis as recently demonstrated in several
      pilot studies involving osteoarthritis of the knee and shoulder. 18-FDG accumulates in areas
      of increased metabolism, particularly activated leukocytes, as measured by increased
      standardized uptake value.2 PET/CT offers the unique advantage of showing active disease
      before anatomic damage is evident. Our hypothesis is that there is an increased uptake of
      18-FDG on PET/CT in synovitis of the TMJ.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      This is a prospective, double-blinded, pilot study to evaluate the ability of PET/CT with FDG
      to detect synovitis of the temporomandibular joint. Patients presenting to the Department of
      Oral and Maxillofacial Surgery at the Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania with
      symptomatic internal derangement of the temporomandibular joint requiring arthroscopy will be
      compared to control subjects. Key inclusion criteria include any individual found to have a
      primary diagnosis of internal derangement of the temporomandibular joint requiring
      arthroscopy as determined by the treating physician. All patients will have failed a trial
      period of &quot;conservative treatment therapy&quot; including occlusal splint therapy, NSAIDs, or
      muscle relaxants for a period no less than eight weeks. Exclusion criteria will include
      patients not medically stable to undergo arthroscopy under general anesthesia, patients with
      overlying infection of the skin, patients with conditions other than internal derangement
      causing temporomandibular pain or dysfunction.

      Once a patient has been identified as eligible for the study, the treating physician will
      contact a member of the study team. Each participating patient will undergo a standardized
      exam, the research diagnostic criteria for TMD (RDC/TMD). A member of the research team, from
      the department of oral medicine, will administer this exam. This standardized exam has been
      previously validated in the literature, and each member of the research team will undergo
      training and calibration prior to administering the RDC/TMD. This exam will be performed on
      the day of the arthroscopy. In addition, each patient will be given a Wilkes score, based on
      the Wilkes classification of internal derangement.36 The patient will then undergo
      arthroscopy of the temporomandibular joint as per the treating physician. TMJ arthroscopy
      includes: a small incision in front of the ear, introduction of an arthroscope and irrigation
      needle into the joint space, irrigation of fluid, and at the discretion of the treating
      physician may include the lysis of adhesion and the introduction of medication into the
      joint. At the time of the procedure, the synovitis score will be determined based on an
      eleven point synovitis scale as described by Murakami, with zero being absence of synovial
      inflammation. This scoring is bone by observation, and is typically include in the
      arthroscopy procedure for diagnosis. The patient will also be given a binomial score of
      presence or absence of synovitis. A representative photograph will be obtained of the
      patient's joint during arthroscopy, as is routinely done during this procedures.

      Prior to the procedure, the patients will have undergone a PET/CT scan to evaluate the TMJ.
      This radiographic exam will be limited to the head and neck region in order to minimize
      radiation exposure. The radiologists reading the study will be blinded to the results of the
      clinical exam and condition. The results of the PET/CT study will be given as a binomial
      score of positive or negative and given a continuous score based on uptake relative to the
      unaffected joint.

      Control subjects will undergo the RDC/TMD standardized exam prior to the radiographic study,
      and only have the PET/CT performed, with no subsequent intervention. These patients will be
      aged matched to the treatment subjects. This information will then be utilized to determine
      the utility of PET/CT in the detection of synovitis of the temporomandibular joint.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Withdrawn</overall_status>
  <why_stopped>
    29-Apr-14 UPENN IRB granted approval to close study due to lack of funding
  </why_stopped>
  <start_date>December 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Anticipated">October 2012</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 2</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <allocation>Non-Randomized</allocation>
    <intervention_model>Parallel Assignment</intervention_model>
    <primary_purpose>Diagnostic</primary_purpose>
    <masking>Double (Care Provider, Investigator)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The primary outcome variable will be the presence or absence of 18F-FDG uptake on positron emission tomography combined with computed tomography (CT) of the temporomandibular joint.</measure>
    <time_frame>1 year</time_frame>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>1</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">0</enrollment>
  <condition>Temporomandibular Joint</condition>
  <condition>Conservative Treatment Therapy</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Disease population</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Experimental</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>PET/CT with 18-FDG</intervention_name>
    <description>FDG uptake</description>
    <arm_group_label>Disease population</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  Key inclusion criteria include any individual found to have a primary diagnosis of
             internal derangement of the temporomandibular joint requiring arthroscopy as
             determined by the treating physician.

          -  All patients will have failed a trial period of &quot;conservative treatment therapy&quot;
             including occlusal splint therapy, NSAIDs, or muscle relaxants for a period no less
             than eight weeks, as per standard of care.

          -  All patients will be between the ages of 18 and 70.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          -  Exclusion criteria will include patients not medically stable to undergo arthroscopy
             under general anesthesia, patients with overlying infection of the skin, uncontrolled
             diabetes, patients with bilateral TMJ internal derangement, pregnancy, and patients
             with conditions other than internal derangement causing temporomandibular pain or
             dysfunction.

          -  Patients less than 18 or greater than 70 years of age will also be excluded.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>70 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Hospital of the University of Pennsylvania</name>
      <address>
        <city>Philadelphia</city>
        <state>Pennsylvania</state>
        <zip>19104</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2015</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 10, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 14, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 16, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>July 6, 2015</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>July 6, 2015</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">July 8, 2015</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>TMJ</keyword>
  <keyword>orofacial pain</keyword>
  <keyword>synovitis</keyword>
  <keyword>arthroscopy</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Synovitis</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

