<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT01475279</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>T89-04-US</org_study_id>
    <nct_id>NCT01475279</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>A Study to Evaluate the Effect of T89(Dantonic®)on Steady-State Pharmacodynamics of Warfarin</brief_title>
  <official_title>An Open-Label, Multiple-Dose, Single-Center, Sequential, Inpatient Study to Determine the Effect of T89 on Steady-State Pharmacodynamics of Warfarin in Healthy Subjects</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Tasly Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Tasly Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      The purpose of this study is to evaluate the potential effect of Dantonic on the steady-state
      pharmacodynamics and pharmacokinetic of warfarin in healthy subjects and safety of the
      co-administration of Dantonic and warfarin.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      Due to a large proportion of patients that could benefit from Dantonic treatment is likely to
      take warfarin concomitantly. And there is no systematic experience of warfarin drug-drug
      interaction between Dantonic and warfarin on humans. It is highly relevant to investigate the
      potential interaction of theses two drugs.

      Primary endpoint:

      •The change in INR with T89 (Day 25) compared with that without T89 (Day 18)

      Secondary endpoints:

        -  The change in PK variables for R-warfarin and S-warfarin on Day 17 compared with those
           on Day 24

        -  Safety assessments across all time points
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>July 2011</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2012</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">November 2011</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 1</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <intervention_model>Single Group Assignment</intervention_model>
    <masking>None (Open Label)</masking>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in INR with T89 (Day 25) compared with that without T89 (Day 18)</measure>
    <time_frame>outcome measure will be assessed in two weeks and data will be presented up to eight weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The mean INR change with T89 (Day 25) and without T89 (Day 18) will be assessed by standard t test.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>The change in PK variables for R-warfarin and S-warfarin on Day 17 compared with those on Day 24</measure>
    <time_frame>outcome measure will be assessed in two weeks and data will be presented up to eight weeks</time_frame>
    <description>The S- and R-warfarin concentration time profiles will be listed and displayed graphically. And 90% CI of the geometric mean ratio for Cmax and AUClast of both R- and S-warfarin will be caculated.</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <enrollment type="Actual">24</enrollment>
  <condition>Healthy</condition>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Warfarin; Dantonic</intervention_name>
    <description>Individual warfarin dose during the study; 225mg Dantonic b.i.d for one week</description>
    <other_name>coumadin</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          1. Nonsmoking male or female with 18-50 years of age and a body mass index (BMI) from
             19.0 to 30.0 kg/m2;

          2. Healthy adult with no active medical problems or significant chronic diseases as
             determined by the study doctor based on medical history, physical examination and
             laboratory evaluations;

          3. Taking no medications 2 weeks before Day 0 and during the study, including drugs of
             abuse, prescription and non prescription medications (including natural health
             products, Vitamins, and herbals) and did not receive vaccinations;

          4. Agree to avoid eating Seville oranges, grapefruits (including grapefruit juice),
             broccoli, brussels sprouts, charcoal-grilled meats, alcoholic beverages, and caffeine-
             and theobromine-containing beverages and foods from the time of screening visit and
             the duration of the study;

          5. Agree to maintain adequate birth control, independent from hormonal contraceptive use,
             from the time of the screening visit and during the study, at the discretion of the
             investigator;

          6. Agree to abstain from alcoholic beverages, caffeinated beverages and orange juice from
             6pm the night before a study day until completion of that study day;

          7. A negative fecal occult blood test (FOBT) ;

          8. Agree to avoid participation in contact sports and/or other activities with
             significant risk of trauma injury for 7 days after each study day;

          9. Subject understands and is willing, able and likely to comply with all study
             procedures and restrictions;

         10. Subject is able to give voluntary oral and written informed consent, at the discretion
             of the investigator.

        Exclusion Criteria:

          1. Subjects with an elevated INR (INR&gt; 1.2) at screening visit;

          2. No gastrointestinal bleeding history within 12 months prior to screening visit;

          3. No history of endoscopically proven peptic ulcer disease;

          4. Known hypersensitivity to warfarin;

          5. Prosthetic heart valves, mitral stenosis, or other conditions such as recent (&lt;3
             months) pulmonary embolism requiring anticoagulant therapy;

          6. History or presence of renal and hepatic insufficiency;

          7. History of hyperthyroidism;

          8. History of any bleeding disorder or hypercoagulation state;

          9. Surgical or medical condition liable to interfere with the absorption, metabolism or
             excretion of warfarin;

         10. Regular intake of other medication affecting the process of coagulation or platelet
             aggregation (during the 2 weeks prior to screening and/or during the run-in and
             treatment periods);

         11. Significant change in diet likely to interfere with the effects of warfarin in the 2
             weeks prior to screening and/or during the run-in and treatment periods, at the
             discretion of the investigator;

         12. History of conditions associated with hemorrhagic risk, surgery or head injury within
             6 months prior to screening visit;

         13. Hematological abnormalities (thrombocytopenia, clinically significant low granulocyte
             count, anemia, hypofibrinogenaemia, hemophilia, purpura, hemopathy with prolongation
             of bleeding time);

         14. Blood loss/donation &gt;400 mL within 12 weeks prior to the screening visit and/or during
             the run-in and treatment periods;

         15. Known to have serum hepatitis or who are carrier of the hepatitis B surface antigen
             (HBsAg), or hepatitis C antibody, or have a positive result to the test for HIV
             antigens and/or antibodies;

         16. Pregnancy or lactation;

         17. Participation in any other clinical trial or receipt of an investigational drug within
             60 days prior to the time of the screening visit, or previous participation in this
             study;

         18. Those subjects unable, in the opinion of the investigator, to comply fully with the
             trial requirements;

         19. Subjects with a recent history (within 24 months prior to the screening visit) of
             alcoholism or known drug dependence, at the discretion of the investigator;

         20. Subjects with positive urine cotinine, urine drug screen and/or alcohol breath test;

         21. In the opinion of the investigator, patients with medical history or other factors
             which may interfere with enrollment or the study.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>18 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>50 Years</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>Accepts Healthy Volunteers</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Healthcare Discoveries, LLC d/b/a ICON Development Solutions</name>
      <address>
        <city>San Antonio</city>
        <state>Texas</state>
        <zip>78209</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>November 2011</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>November 14, 2011</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>November 18, 2011</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">November 21, 2011</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>November 7, 2012</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>November 7, 2012</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">November 8, 2012</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Warfarin</keyword>
  <keyword>Dantonic</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacodynamics</keyword>
  <keyword>Pharmacokinetics</keyword>
  <keyword>Interaction</keyword>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Warfarin</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

