<clinical_study>
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on May 29, 2018</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT02039960</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>201235</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>PRJ2215</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT02039960</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>PRJ2215: Assessment of Buproprion Misuse/Abuse 2004-2011</brief_title>
  <official_title>PRJ2215: Assessment of Buproprion Misuse/Abuse 2004-2011</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>GlaxoSmithKline</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
  </sponsors>
  <source>GlaxoSmithKline</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <has_dmc>No</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      Bupropion hydrochloride was first approved on 30 December 1985 in United States for
      depression and is currently approved in 80 countries. Bupropion has also subsequently been
      approved for smoking cessation and for seasonal affective disorder.

      Cumulative exposure to bupropion is estimated at approximately 97.3 million patient exposures
      up to 31 December 2012.

      Bupropion hydrochloride is a weak catecholamine reuptake inhibitor predominantly affecting
      serotonin, norepinephrine and dopamine. Its mechanism of action and its structural
      similarities to diethylpropion, amphetamines, and cocaine, bupropion resembles stimulants in
      many respects, leading to concerns about potential abuse of the product.

      Abuse potential had been part of the Benefit Risk Management Plan for bupropion up until 2003
      and at that point, had no longer been regarded as a potential risk that required
      additional/further evaluation outside standard pharmacovigilance monitoring. The current
      European Risk Management Plan also states that standard pharmacovigilance monitoring applies
      to abuse potential. Monitoring has shown a recent increase in the number of spontaneous
      reports from the Adverse Event reporting System (AERS) of drug abuse.

      The bupropion team agreed that although the numbers of abuse reports was small relative to
      the total number of reports for bupropion in OCEANS, there was sufficient information in AERS
      to warrant investigation of the potential effect on public health.

      To investigate the degree of misuse and abuse of bupropion (including non-oral routes of
      administration) in the United States, the Drug Abuse Warning Network will be used to examine
      the study period 2004-2011.
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      There are two primary objectives to the study, which are as follows: 1) to examine the number
      of bupropion reports over time within the DAWN database and to describe the number of all
      DAWN reports for prescription drugs and 2) to examine the number of reports for bupropion,
      stratified by demographics, route of administration, and disposition of the patient.

      If sample size permits, an evaluation of the disposition of the patients exposed to only
      bupropion at the time of Emergency Department (ED) visit will be conducted.

      DAWN is a public health surveillance system that reports on drug-related visits to hospital
      Emergency Departments (ED). DAWN is used to monitor trends in drug misuse and abuse, identify
      the emergence of new substances and drug combinations, assess health hazards associated with
      drug use and abuse, and estimate the impact of drug use, misuse, and abuse on the United
      States' health care system.

      DAWN's target sample frame consists of all non-Federal, short-stay, general medical and
      surgical hospitals in the United States that have one or more EDs open 24 hours a day. DAWN
      employs a multistage sampling design for the selection of EDs for analysis. Stratified simple
      random sampling with oversampling in selected metropolitan areas is used to select the
      hospitals.

      A DAWN case is any ED visit involving recent drug use. DAWN cases are identified through the
      review of ED medical records in participating hospitals. DAWN captures both ED visits that
      are directly caused by drugs and those in which drugs are a contributing factor but not the
      direct cause of the ED visit. These criteria encompass all types of drug-related events,
      including accidental ingestion and adverse reaction, as well as drug misuse or abuse.

      DAWN collects data on all types of drugs—illegal drugs, prescription and over-the-counter
      medications, dietary supplements, and both pharmaceutical and nonpharmaceutical inhalants.
      DAWN notes whether alcohol is involved in addition to drug(s) for patients of all ages.
      Because alcohol is considered an illicit drug for minors, alcohol abuse without the
      involvement of other drugs is considered a drug-related ED visit for patients under the age
      of 21. DAWN does not report current medications (i.e., medications and pharmaceuticals taken
      regularly by the patient as prescribed or indicated) that are deemed by the ED medical staff
      to be unrelated to the ED visit.

      The study population includes patients of all ages presenting to emergency departments for
      drug-related causes. The DAWN visit eligibility criteria are intended to be broad and
      inclusive and to have few exceptions. They take into account the fact that documentation in
      medical records varies in clarity and completeness across hospitals and among clinicians
      within hospitals. The criteria are designed to minimize the potential for DAWN Reporter
      judgments that could cause data to vary systematically and unexpectedly across different data
      collectors and hospitals. In addition, the criteria allow for the capture of a diverse set of
      drug-related visits that can be aggregated or disaggregated to serve a variety of analytical
      purposes and the interests of multiple audiences.

      There are few variables within the DAWN dataset. For this analysis, variables of interest can
      be grouped into the following categories: year of visit, age, sex, race, reason for
      presentation to the emergency department, case type, drug, route of administration,
      toxicology confirmed, and result of treatment in ED.

      The Drug Abuse Warning Network datasets from 2004-2011 will be used for the proposed
      analyses.

      All eligible DAWN cases will be included in this analysis.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>November 2013</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">January 2014</primary_completion_date>
  <study_type>Observational</study_type>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <study_design_info>
    <observational_model>Case-Only</observational_model>
    <time_perspective>Cross-Sectional</time_perspective>
  </study_design_info>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>The number of bupropion abuse case reports from the DAWN data.</measure>
    <time_frame>Up to 8 years</time_frame>
    <description>Abuse case reports of interest include unlicensed route of administration, specifically, inhalation of bupropion.</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <number_of_groups>3</number_of_groups>
  <enrollment type="Actual">1</enrollment>
  <condition>Depressive Disorder, Major</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>DAWN cases including all prescription drugs</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group will consist of all DAWN cases where prescription drugs are mentioned.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>All bupropion cases (including use of other drugs)</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group will consist of all DAWN cases where bupropion is mentioned and is a subset of Group 1.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Burpropion Only Cases</arm_group_label>
    <description>This group will consist of all DAWN cases where burpropion is specifically the only drug mentioned within the case report, and is a subset of Group 2.</description>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>Bupropion</intervention_name>
    <description>Bupropion is a weak catecholamine reuptake inhibitor predominantly affecting serotonin, norepinephrine and dopamine and is approved for depression, smoking cessation and seasonal affective disorder.</description>
    <arm_group_label>DAWN cases including all prescription drugs</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>Burpropion Only Cases</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_label>All bupropion cases (including use of other drugs)</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <study_pop>
      <textblock>
        A DAWN case is any ED visit involving recent drug use. DAWN cases are identified through
        the review of ED medical records in participating hospitals. DAWN captures both ED visits
        that are directly caused by drugs and those in which drugs are a contributing factor but
        not the direct cause of the ED visit. These criteria encompass all types of drug-related
        events, including accidental ingestion and adverse reaction, as well as drug misuse or
        abuse.

        DAWN collects data on all types of drugs—illegal drugs, prescription and over-the-counter
        medications, dietary supplements, and both pharmaceutical and nonpharmaceutical inhalants.
        DAWN notes whether alcohol is involved in addition to drug(s) for patients of all ages.
        Because alcohol is considered an illicit drug for minors, alcohol abuse without the
        involvement of other drugs is considered a drug-related ED visit for patients under the age
        of 21. DAWN does not report current medications that are deemed to be unrelated to the ED
        visit.
      </textblock>
    </study_pop>
    <sampling_method>Probability Sample</sampling_method>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Inclusion Criteria:

          -  All DAWN case reports mentioning use of bupropion will be included in this analysis.

        Exclusion Criteria:
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>All</gender>
    <minimum_age>N/A</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>GSK Clinical Trials</last_name>
    <role>Study Director</role>
    <affiliation>GlaxoSmithKline</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <verification_date>August 2016</verification_date>
  <!-- For several months we've had both old and new date name tags                             -->
  <!-- Now, the old date names have been dropped.                                               -->
  <!-- The new date name replacements are:                                                      -->
  <!--     OLD (gone)                                        NEW (in use)                       -->
  <!--   lastchanged_date                         becomes   last_update_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_date                       becomes   study_first_submitted               -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_date               becomes   results_first_submitted             -->
  <!--   firstreceived_results_disposition_date   becomes   disposition_first_submitted         -->
  <study_first_submitted>January 9, 2014</study_first_submitted>
  <study_first_submitted_qc>January 16, 2014</study_first_submitted_qc>
  <study_first_posted type="Estimate">January 20, 2014</study_first_posted>
  <last_update_submitted>August 3, 2016</last_update_submitted>
  <last_update_submitted_qc>August 3, 2016</last_update_submitted_qc>
  <last_update_posted type="Estimate">August 5, 2016</last_update_posted>
  <responsible_party>
    <responsible_party_type>Sponsor</responsible_party_type>
  </responsible_party>
  <keyword>Epidemiology</keyword>
  <keyword>Drug Abuse Warning Network (DAWN)</keyword>
  <keyword>bupropion</keyword>
  <keyword>abuse</keyword>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depression</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Depressive Disorder, Major</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm            -->
    <mesh_term>Bupropion</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>
  <!-- Results have not yet been posted for this study                                          -->
</clinical_study>

